<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34765478</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2224-4344</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Translational pediatrics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Transl Pediatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Study of the changes in immune indexes, pathogenic characteristics and related risk factors in children with viral diarrhea.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2544</StartPage><EndPage>2551</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2544-2551</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.21037/tp-21-433</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Infectious diarrhea is a serious hazard to children under 5 years old. The causative microorganisms are mostly viruses and bacteria, with different treatment required for each. Currently, early clinical differential diagnosis is difficult with the available testing methods. Therefore, new and more sensitive indicators of viral infection reflect the early stage of infection are needed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We collected blood samples and fresh fecal samples from 100 children diagnosed with viral diarrhea who were treated in the outpatient clinic at Changzhou Tumor Hospital Affiliated to Soochow University from January 2018 to December 2020. The levels of interleukin-2 (IL-2), IL-6, tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), and C-reactive protein (CRP) in serum, the erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) and enterovirus were measured and compared with those in a matched healthy control group. Patients' demographic and risk factor data were collected by interviewing parents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The mean levels of IL-2, IL-6, TNF-α, ESR, and CRP in the viral diarrhea group were higher than those in the healthy control group. Except for IL-6, the differences in inflammatory factors between groups were statistically significant (P&lt;0.05). Human rotavirus (HRV) infection was the highest. Children's hand-washing habits, weekly disinfection of toys, and vaccination were protective factors for viral diarrhea, and indoor flies were an important risk factor (P&lt;0.05).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The serum levels of markers were significantly increased in the children with viral diarrhea. HRV was the main pathogen, and mixed infections existed. Infection control requires hand washing, regular disinfection of toys, vaccination and preventing indoor flies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>2021 Translational Pediatrics. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Di-Ying</ForeName><Initials>DY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Changzhou Tumor Hospital Affiliated to Soochow University, Changzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhan</LastName><ForeName>Feng</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Changzhou Tumor Hospital Affiliated to Soochow University, Changzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Hui-Ling</ForeName><Initials>HL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Changzhou Tumor Hospital Affiliated to Soochow University, Changzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>China</Country><MedlineTA>Transl Pediatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101649179</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2224-4336</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inflammatory factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenic bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral diarrhea</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of Interest: All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form (available at https://dx.doi.org/10.21037/tp-21-433). The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34765478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8578756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21037/tp-21-433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">tp-10-10-2544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Gong Z, Zeng M, Zhu Qg, et al. Molecular epidemiology of group A rotavirus diarrhea in children in Shanghai; 30:288-92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng M, Zhang Y, Zhu Q, et al. Clinical and molecular epidemiology of rotavirus in children with community-acquired and hospital-acquired diarrhea in Shanghai, China. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2010;29:177-80. 10.1097/INF.0b013e3181ba99d4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0b013e3181ba99d4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19915511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Oza S, Hogan D, et al. Global, regional, and national causes of child mortality in 2000-13, with projections to inform post-2015 priorities: an updated systematic analysis. Lancet 2015;385:430-40. 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61698-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61698-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25280870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lesanu G, Becheanu CA, Vlad RM, et al. Clinical characteristics of rotavirus diarrhea in hospitalized Romanian infants. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2013;32:89-91. 10.1097/INF.0b013e3182706152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0b013e3182706152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22929174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu M, Deng Y, Zhang X, et al. Etiology of acute diarrhea due to enteropathogenic bacteria in Beijing, China. J Infect 2012;65:214-22. 10.1016/j.jinf.2012.04.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2012.04.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22546618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li A, Zhang C, Pang P, et al. Changes of creatine phosphokinase and high sensitivity C-reactive protein in children with group A rotavirus. Chinese Journal of nosocomial infection, 2010; 20:50-2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Decaluwe H, Harrison LM, Mariscalco MM, et al. Procalcitonin in children with Escherichia coli O157:H7 associated hemolytic uremic syndrome. Pediatr Res 2006;59:579-83. 10.1203/01.pdr.0000203100.45658.d5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1203/01.pdr.0000203100.45658.d5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16549533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korczowski B, Szybist W. Serum procalcitonin and C-reactive protein in children with diarrhoea of various aetiologies. Acta Paediatr 2004;93:169-73. 10.1111/j.1651-2227.2004.tb00700.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1651-2227.2004.tb00700.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15046268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narváez CF, Franco MA, Angel J, et al. Rotavirus differentially infects and polyclonally stimulates human B cells depending on their differentiation state and tissue of origin. J Virol 2010;84:4543-55. 10.1128/JVI.02550-09</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.02550-09</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2863723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20164228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodin P, Jojic V, Gao T, et al. Variation in the human immune system is largely driven by non-heritable influences. Cell 2015;160:37-47. 10.1016/j.cell.2014.12.020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.12.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4302727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25594173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strömbeck A, Lundell AC, Nordström I, et al. Earlier infantile immune maturation is related to higher DTP vaccine responses in children. Clin Transl Immunology 2016;5:e65. 10.1038/cti.2016.7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/cti.2016.7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4815027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27217956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parashar UD, Burton A, Lanata C, et al. Global mortality associated with rotavirus disease among children in 2004. J Infect Dis 2009;200 Suppl 1:S9-s15. 10.1086/605025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/605025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19817620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parashar UD, Hummelman EG, Bresee JS, et al. Global illness and deaths caused by rotavirus disease in children. Emerg Infect Dis 2003;9:565-72. 10.3201/eid0905.020562</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid0905.020562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2972763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12737740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boni-Cisse C, Meite S, Mlan AB, et al. Genotypic characterization of rotavirus in children under 5 years circulating in Côte D'Ivoire from 2010 to 2013. Virol J 2018;15:78. 10.1186/s12985-018-0973-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-018-0973-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5922014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29699581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li YT, Xu H, Ye JZ, et al. Efficacy of Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG in treatment of acute pediatric diarrhea: A systematic review with meta-analysis. World J Gastroenterol 2019;25:4999-5016. 10.3748/wjg.v25.i33.4999</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3748/wjg.v25.i33.4999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6737314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31543689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong AY, Jeong HS, Jo MY, et al. Molecular epidemiology and genetic diversity of human astrovirus in South Korea from 2002 to 2007. Clin Microbiol Infect 2011;17:404-8. 10.1111/j.1469-0691.2010.03263.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2010.03263.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20491833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen TA, Yagyu F, Okame M, et al. Diversity of viruses associated with acute gastroenteritis in children hospitalized with diarrhea in Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam. J Med Virol 2007;79:582-90. 10.1002/jmv.20857</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.20857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17385670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebire NJ, Malone M, Shah N, et al. Pathology of astrovirus associated diarrhoea in a paediatric bone marrow transplant recipient. J Clin Pathol 2004;57:1001-3. 10.1136/jcp.2004.017178</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jcp.2004.017178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1770412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15333670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren B, Zhao R, Wang N, et al. Study on etiology and epidemic characteristics of viral diarrhea in hospitalized infants under 5 years old in Taiyuan City in 2012. Journal of practical medical technology, 2013; 20:1269-71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang F, Jin M, Li D, et al. Molecular epidemiology of viral diarrhea in children at ages of less than 5 years in Lanzhou City, Gansu Province, China in 2017. Chinese Journal of Biologicals 2019;32:1102-7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maffey L, Vega CG, Parreño V, et al. Controlling Rotavirus-associated diarrhea: Could single-domain antibody fragments make the difference? Rev Argent Microbiol 2015;47:368-79. 10.1016/j.ram.2015.09.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ram.2015.09.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26654700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Ryan GM, Ashkenazi-Hoffnung L, O'Ryan-Soriano MA, et al. Management of acute infectious diarrhea for children living in resource-limited settings. Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther 2014;12:621-32. 10.1586/14787210.2014.901168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1586/14787210.2014.901168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24661314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wehkamp J, Götz M, Herrlinger K, et al. Inflammatory Bowel Disease. Dtsch Arztebl Int 2016;113:72-82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4782273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26900160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holtman GA, Lisman-van Leeuwen Y, Reitsma JB, et al. Noninvasive Tests for Inflammatory Bowel Disease: A Meta-analysis. Pediatrics 2016;137. 10.1542/peds.2015-2126</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2015-2126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26681783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lapić I, Padoan A, Bozzato D, et al. Erythrocyte Sedimentation Rate and C-Reactive Protein in Acute Inflammation. Am J Clin Pathol 2020;153:14-29. 10.1093/ajcp/aqz142</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ajcp/aqz142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31598629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mou X, Qu W, Liu J. Epidemiological characteristics of rotavirus in Yantai city from 2017 to 2019. Preventive medicine forum 2021; 27:336-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y, Zhao Q, Ni Z, et al. Investigation on risk factors of viral diarrhea in infants under 5 years old in Yuxi City. China primary health care 2019; 33:65-7.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>