<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">34936258</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2590-7379</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>41</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biomedica</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Identification of enteric viruses from raw water using fluoro-immuno-magnetic separation coupled to RT-PCR.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>745</StartPage><EndPage>755</EndPage><MedlinePgn>745-755</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7705/biomedica.6032</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION">Enteric viruses have been associated with the production of a variety of diseases transmitted by the fecal-oral route and carried through contaminated food and water. Given their structure and composition, they are highly resistant to environmental conditions and most of the chemical agents used in the purification processes. Therefore, the systematic monitoring of raw water is necessary to ensure its quality especially when it is used for producing drinking water for human consumption.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE">We identified the presence of rotavirus and hepatitis A virus by means of the fluoro-immuno-magnetic separation technique (FIMS) in raw water taken from four purification plants and their water supplies in the department of Norte de Santander.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS">The viruses were captured and separated from the water samples using magnetic microparticles functionalized with monoclonal anti-Hepatitis A and anti-Rotavirus antibodies. Confocal microscopy was used to monitor the viral concentration process and transmission electron microscopy for the morphological visualization of the separated viruses. The reverse transcriptase-coupled polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) was applied to confirm the presence of pathogens.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">The two enteric viruses were identified in the majority of the analyzed water samples including water supply sources.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">We determined that the FIMS technique together with RT-PCR is highly effective for the detection of viral pathogens in complex matrices such as raw water.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Villamizar</LastName><ForeName>Raquel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departamento de Medicina, Facultad de Salud, Universidad de Pamplona, Pamplona, Colombia. raqvillamizar@unipamplona.edu.co.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peláez-Carvajal</LastName><ForeName>Dioselina</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Grupo de Virología, Dirección de Redes en Salud Pública, Instituto Nacional de Salud, Bogotá D.C., Colombia. biomedica@ins.gov.co.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Acero</LastName><ForeName>Luis Felipe</ForeName><Initials>LF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Grupo de Virología, Dirección de Redes en Salud Pública, Instituto Nacional de Salud, Bogotá D.C., Colombia. biomedica@ins.gov.co.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><Language>spa</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Identificación de virus entéricos en aguas crudas usando separación inmunomagnética acoplada a RT-PCR.</VernacularTitle><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Colombia</Country><MedlineTA>Biomedica</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8205605</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0120-4157</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030041" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hepatitis A virus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020133" MajorTopicYN="N">Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012401" MajorTopicYN="Y">Rotavirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014871" MajorTopicYN="N">Water Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>Introducción. Los virus entéricos se asocian con una serie de enfermedades transmitidas por vía fecal-oral en alimentos o agua contaminada. Dada su estructura y composición, son muy resistentes a las condiciones ambientales y a la mayoría de los agentes químicos empleados en los procesos de potabilización, por lo cual es necesario un monitoreo sistemático del agua cruda para asegurar su calidad, máxime cuando se emplea como materia prima en la producción de agua potable para consumo humano. Objetivo. Determinar la presencia de rotavirus y del virus de la hepatitis A mediante la técnica de separación fluoro-inmuno-magnética en agua cruda procedente de cuatro plantas de potabilización y sus fuentes hídricas en el departamento de Norte de Santander. Materiales y métodos. Los virus fueron capturados y separados a partir de las muestras de agua, empleando micropartículas magnéticas funcionalizadas con anticuerpos monoclonales anti-hepatitis A y anti-rotavirus. Se empleó microscopía confocal para hacer el seguimiento del proceso de concentración viral y, microscopía electrónica de transmisión, para la visualización morfológica de los virus separados. La reacción en cadena de la polimerasa acoplada a transcriptasa inversa (RT-PCR) se utilizó para confirmar la presencia de los patógenos. Resultados. Los dos virus entéricos se detectaron en la mayoría de las muestras de agua analizadas, incluidas las de sus fuentes hídricas. Conclusión. La técnica de separación fluoro-inmuno-magnética acoplada a RT-PCR fue altamente efectiva en la detección de patógenos virales en matrices complejas como el agua cruda.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCCIÓN.">Los virus entéricos se asocian con una serie de enfermedades transmitidas por vía fecal-oral en alimentos o agua contaminada. Dada su estructura y composición, son muy resistentes a las condiciones ambientales y a la mayoría de los agentes químicos empleados en los procesos de potabilización, por lo cual es necesario un monitoreo sistemático del agua cruda para asegurar su calidad, máxime cuando se emplea como materia prima en la producción de agua potable para consumo humano.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJETIVO.">Determinar la presencia de rotavirus y del virus de la hepatitis A mediante la técnica de separación ﬂuoro-inmuno-magnética en agua cruda procedente de cuatro plantas de potabilización y sus fuentes hídricas en el departamento de Norte de Santander.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALES Y MÉTODOS.">Los virus fueron capturados y separados a partir de las muestras de agua, empleando micropartículas magnéticas funcionalizadas con anticuerpos monoclonales anti-hepatitis A y anti-rotavirus. Se empleó microscopía confocal para hacer el seguimiento del proceso de concentración viral y, microscopía electrónica de transmisión, para la visualización morfológica de los virus separados. La reacción en cadena de la polimerasa acoplada a transcriptasa inversa (RT-PCR) se utilizó para confrmar la presencia de los patógenos.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTADOS.">Los dos virus entéricos se detectaron en la mayoría de las muestras de agua analizadas, incluidas las de sus fuentes hídricas.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIÓN.">La técnica de separación ﬂuoro-inmuno-magnética acoplada a RT-PCR fue altamente efectiva en la detección de patógenos virales en matrices complejas como el agua cruda.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rotavirus infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hepatitis A</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">raw water</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">water purification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">magnetic segregation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Conﬂicts of interest:</b> The authors declare no conﬂicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34936258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8767791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7705/biomedica.6032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Organización Mundial de la Salud, Fondo de las Naciones Unidas para la Infancia (UNICEF)  Progresos en materia de agua potable, saneamiento e higiene: informe de actualización de 2017 y línea de base de los ods.  [march 15, 2019].   available from:  https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/260291/9789243512891-spa.pdf?sequence=1
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministerio de Agricultura  Decreto 1594 de 1984. “En cuanto a usos del agua y residuos líquidos”.  [April 8, 2019].  Available from:  www.ideam.gov.co&gt;documents&gt;Dec 1594 1984.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purparia G, Macalusoa G, Di Bellaa S, Gucciardia F, Miraa F, Di Marco P, et al. Molecular characterization of human enteric viruses in food, water samples, and surface swabs in Sicily. Int J Infect Dis. 2019;80:66–72. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2018.12.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2018.12.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30639406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  . Guidelines for Drinking-water Quality. Fourth edition. Geneva; 2011.  [April 20, 2019].  Available from:  whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2011/9789241548151 eng.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falman JC, Fagnant-Sperati CS, Kossik AL, Boyle DS, Meschke JS. Evaluation of secondary concentration methods for poliovirus detection in wastewater. Food Environ Virol. 2019;11:20– 31. doi: 10.1007/s12560-018-09364-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-018-09364-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6394643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30612304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cormier J, Gutiérrez M, Goodridge L, Janes M. Concentration of enteric virus indicator from seawater using granular activated carbon. J Virol Methods. 2014;196:212–218. doi: 10.1016/i.iviromet.2013.11.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/i.iviromet.2013.11.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24269798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandler JC, Schaeffer JW, Davidson M, Magzamen SL, Pérez-Méndez A, Reynolds SJ, et al. A method for the improved detection of aerosolized influenza viruses and the malespecific (F+) RNA coliphage MS2. J Virol Methods. 2017;246:38–41. doi: 10.1016/i.jviromet.20T7.04.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/i.jviromet.20T7.04.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7113747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28450173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coughlin BA, Kniel KE. Protocol recovery and detection of enteric viruses from non- traditional irrigation water sources. Methods Protoc. 2019;2:55–63. doi: 10.3390/mps2030055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/mps2030055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6789464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31262023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haramoto E, Kitaiima M, Hata A, Torrey JR, Masago Y, Sano D, et al. A review on recent progress in the detection methods and prevalence of human enteric viruses in water. Water Res. 2018;135:168–186. doi: 10.1016/i.watres.2018.02.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/i.watres.2018.02.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ha JH, Choi C, HA SD. Evaluation of immunomagnetic separation method for the recovery of hepatitis A virus and GI.1 and GII.4 Norovirus strains seeded on oyster and mussel. Food Environ Virol. 2014;6:290–296. doi: 10.1007/s12560-014-9156-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-014-9156-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24952877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villamizar R, Osma JF, Ortiz OO. New technique for direct fluoroinmunomagnetic detection of rotavirus in water samples. J Water Health. 2017;15:932–941. doi: 10.2166/wh.2017028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wh.2017028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29215357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peláez D, Guzmán B, Rodríguez J, Acero F, Nava G. Presencia de virus entéricos en muestras de agua para el consumo humano en Colombia: desafíos de los sistemas de abastecimiento. Biomédica. 2016;36:169–178. doi: 10.7705/biomedica.v36i0.2987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7705/biomedica.v36i0.2987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elmahdy EM, Fongaro G, Schissi CD, Petrucio MM, Barardi CRM. Enteric viruses in surface water and sediment samples from the catchment area of Peri Lagoon, Santa Catarina State, Brazil. J Water Health. 2016;14:142–154. doi: 10.2166/wh.2015.295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wh.2015.295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26837838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Environmental Protection Agency  Drinking water contaminant candidate List 4- Draft. EPA- HQ-OW-2012-0217.  [August 20, 2017].  Available from:  http://federalregister.gov/a/2015-02210
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Alzate C, Valencia CR, Taphorn R, González I. Physicochemical and biological characterization of the Roble River, Upper Cauca, western Colombia. Rev Mus Argent Cienc Nat. 2010;12:5–16. doi: 10.22179/REVMACN.12.247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22179/REVMACN.12.247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowlands J. Human hepatitis A virus is united with a host of relations. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2015;112:15010–15011. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1520121112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1520121112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4679024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26582796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathew D, Gautum R. Rotavirus. Clin Lab Med. 2015;35:363–391. doi: 10.1016/j.cll.2015.02.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cll.2015.02.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26004648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Departamento Administrativo Nacional de Estadística (DANE)  Censo general 2005.  [June 24, 2019].  Available from:  https://www.dane.gov.co/index.php/estadisticas-por-tema/demografia-y-poblacjon/censo-generaJ-2Q05-1
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministerio de Desarrollo Económico  Dirección de Agua Potable y Saneamiento Básico Reglamento Técnico del Sector de Agua Potable y Saneamiento Básico. RAS 2000. Título B. 2019 Apr 08;  https://www.minvivienda.gov.co/sites/default/files/documentos/titulob-030714.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forero-Céspedes A, Reinoso-Flórez G. Water quality assessment of the Opia River (Tolima-Colombia), using macroinvertebrates and physicochemical parameters. Caldasia. 2013;35:371–387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valverde-Solis A, Moreno-Tamayo E, Ortiz-Palacios NY. Análisis de la calidad de varios cuerpos de aguas superficiales en Bahía Solano utilizando índices de contaminación. Rev Cient Inst Biod Des. 2015;34:14–21. doi: 10.18636/riutch.v34i1.553.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18636/riutch.v34i1.553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lodder WJ, van den Ber L, Rutjes SA, de Roda Husman AM. Presence of enteric viruses in source waters for drinking water production in the Netherlands. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2010;76(72):17–17. doi: 10.1128/AEM.00245-10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00245-10</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2935033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20622124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koh I, Josephson L. Magnetic nanoparticle sensors. Sensors. 2009;9:8130–8145. doi: 10.3390/s91008130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s91008130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3292100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22408498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Williams S, Zborowski M, Chalmers J. Binding affinities/avidities of antibodyantigen interactions: Quantification and scale-up implications. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2006;95:5–5. doi: 10.1002/bit.21024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bit.21024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16937410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center for Diseases Control and Prevention (CDC)  Effect of chlorination on inactivating selected pathogen.  [June 28, 2021].  Available from:  https://www.cdc.gov/ safewatei7effectiveness-on-pathogens.html
.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>