<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34976988</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2296-4185</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>9</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in bioengineering and biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Bioeng Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle><i>Salix</i> spp. Bark Hot Water Extracts Show Antiviral, Antibacterial, and Antioxidant Activities-The Bioactive Properties of 16 Clones.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>797939</StartPage><MedlinePgn>797939</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">797939</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fbioe.2021.797939</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Earlier studies have shown that the bark of <i>Salix</i> L. species (Salicaceae family) is rich in extractives, such as diverse bioactive phenolic compounds. However, we lack knowledge on the bioactive properties of the bark of willow species and clones adapted to the harsh climate conditions of the cool temperate zone. Therefore, the present study aimed to obtain information on the functional profiles of northern willow clones for the use of value-added bioactive solutions. Of the 16 willow clones studied here, 12 were examples of widely distributed native Finnish willow species, including dark-leaved willow (<i>S. myrsinifolia</i> Salisb.) and tea-leaved willow (<i>S. phylicifolia</i> L.) (3 + 4 clones, respectively) and their natural and artificial hybrids (3 + 2 clones, respectively). The four remaining clones were commercial willow varieties from the Swedish willow breeding program. Hot water extraction of bark under mild conditions was carried out. Bioactivity assays were used to screen antiviral, antibacterial, antifungal, yeasticidal, and antioxidant activities, as well as the total phenolic content of the extracts. Additionally, we introduce a fast and less labor-intensive steam-debarking method for <i>Salix</i> spp. feedstocks. Clonal variation was observed in the antioxidant properties of the bark extracts of the 16 <i>Salix</i> spp. clones. High antiviral activity against a non-enveloped enterovirus, coxsackievirus A9, was found, with no marked differences in efficacy between the native clones. All the clones also showed antibacterial activity against <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> and <i>Escherichia coli</i>, whereas no antifungal (<i>Aspergillus brasiliensis</i>) or yeasticidal (<i>Candida albicans</i>) efficacy was detected. When grouping the clone extract results into <i>Salix myrsinifolia</i>, <i>Salix phylicifolia</i>, native hybrid, artificial hybrid, and commercial clones, there was a significant difference in the activities between <i>S. phylicifolia</i> clone extracts and commercial clone extracts in the favor of <i>S. phylicifolia</i> in the antibacterial and antioxidant tests. In some antioxidant tests, <i>S. phylicifolia</i> clone extracts were also significantly more active than artificial clone extracts. Additionally, <i>S. myrsinifolia</i> clone extracts showed significantly higher activities in some antioxidant tests than commercial clone extracts and artificial clone extracts. Nevertheless, the bark extracts of native Finnish willow clones showed high bioactivity. The obtained knowledge paves the way towards developing high value-added biochemicals and other functional solutions based on willow biorefinery approaches.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2021 Tienaho, Reshamwala, Sarjala, Kilpeläinen, Liimatainen, Dou, Viherä-Aarnio, Linnakoski, Marjomäki and Jyske.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tienaho</LastName><ForeName>Jenni</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Production Systems, Natural Resources Institute Finland (Luke), Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reshamwala</LastName><ForeName>Dhanik</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological and Environmental Science, Nanoscience Center, University of Jyväskylä, Jyväskylä, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarjala</LastName><ForeName>Tytti</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Production Systems, Natural Resources Institute Finland (Luke), Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kilpeläinen</LastName><ForeName>Petri</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Production Systems, Natural Resources Institute Finland (Luke), Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liimatainen</LastName><ForeName>Jaana</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Production Systems, Natural Resources Institute Finland (Luke), Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dou</LastName><ForeName>Jinze</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bioproducts and Biosystems, School of Chemical Engineering, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Viherä-Aarnio</LastName><ForeName>Anneli</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Production Systems, Natural Resources Institute Finland (Luke), Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Linnakoski</LastName><ForeName>Riikka</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Natural Resources, Natural Resources Institute Finland (Luke), Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marjomäki</LastName><ForeName>Varpu</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological and Environmental Science, Nanoscience Center, University of Jyväskylä, Jyväskylä, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jyske</LastName><ForeName>Tuula</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Production Systems, Natural Resources Institute Finland (Luke), Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Bioeng Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101632513</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-4185</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Salix spp.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antioxidant</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bark</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">debarking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">water-extracts</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34976988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8716786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fbioe.2021.797939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">797939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ainsworth E. A., Gillespie K. M. (2007). Estimation of Total Phenolic Content and Other Oxidation Substrates in Plant Tissues Using Folin-Ciocalteu Reagent. Nat. Protoc. 2, 875–877. 10.1038/nprot.2007.102</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17446889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antoniadou K., Herz C., Le N. P. K., Mittermeier-Kleßinger V. K., Förster N., Zander M., et al. (2021). Identification of Salicylates in Willow Bark (Salix Cortex) for Targeting Peripheral Inflammation. Ijms 22, 11138. 10.3390/ijms222011138</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms222011138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8540557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34681798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arif T., Bhosale J. D., Kumar N., Mandal T. K., Bendre R. S., Lavekar G. S., et al. (2009). Natural Products - Antifungal Agents Derived from Plants. J. Asian Nat. Prod. Res. 11, 621–638. 10.1080/10286020902942350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10286020902942350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20183299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benzie I. F. F., Strain J. J. (1996). The Ferric Reducing Ability of Plasma (FRAP) as a Measure of "Antioxidant Power": The FRAP Assay. Anal. Biochem. 239, 70–76. 10.1006/abio.1996.0292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1006/abio.1996.0292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8660627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bobleter O. (1994). Hydrothermal Degradation of Polymers Derived from Plants. Prog. Polym. Sci. 19, 797–841. 10.1016/0079-6700(94)90033-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0079-6700(94)90033-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boeckler G. A., Gershenzon J., Unsicker S. B. (2011). Phenolic Glycosides of the Salicaceae and Their Role as Anti-herbivore Defenses. Phytochemistry 72, 1497–1509. 10.1016/j.phytochem.2011.01.038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2011.01.038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21376356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bounaama A., Enayat S., Ceyhan M. S., Moulahoum H., Djerdjouri B., Banerjee S. (2016). Ethanolic Extract of Bark fromSalix aegyptiacaAmeliorates 1,2-Dimethylhydrazine-Induced Colon Carcinogenesis in Mice by Reducing Oxidative Stress. Nutr. Cancer 68, 495–506. 10.1080/01635581.2016.1152379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01635581.2016.1152379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27093594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brebu M., Vasile C. (2010). Thermal Degradation of Lignin—A Review. Cellul. Chem. Technol. 44, 353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brereton N. J. B., Berthod N., Lafleur B., Pedneault K., Pitre F. E., Labrecque M. (2017). Extractable Phenolic Yield Variation in Five Cultivars of Mature Short Rotation Coppice Willow from Four Plantations in Quebec. Ind. Crops Prod. 97, 525–535. 10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.12.049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.12.049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown G. D., Denning D. W., Levitz S. M. (2012). Tackling Human Fungal Infections. Science 336, 647. 10.1126/science.1222236</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1222236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22582229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christenhusz M. J. M., Fay M. F., Chase M. W. (2017). Plants of the World. KewChina: Kew Publishing Royal Botanic GardensThe University of Chicago Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chrubasik S., Eisenberg E., Balan E., Weinberger T., Luzzati R., Conradt C. (2000). Treatment of Low Back Pain Exacerbations with Willow Bark Extract: a Randomized Double-Blind Study. Am. J. Med. 109, 9–14. 10.1016/S0002-9343(00)00442-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0002-9343(00)00442-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10936472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DIN EN 1275 (2006). Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics - Quantitative Suspension Test for the Evaluation of Basic Fungicidal or Basic Yeasticidal Activity of Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics - Test Method and Requirements. (phase 1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djomo S. N., Kasmioui O. E., Ceulemans R. (2011). Energy and Greenhouse Gas Balance of Bioenergy Production from poplar and Willow: a Review. Glob. Change Biol. Bioenergy 3, 181–197. 10.1111/j.1757-1707.2010.01073.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1757-1707.2010.01073.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dou J., Galvis L., Holopainen-Mantila U., Reza M., Tamminen T., Vuorinen T. (2016). Morphology and Overall Chemical Characterization of Willow (Salix sp.) Inner Bark and Wood: Toward Controlled Deconstruction of Willow Biomass. ACS Sustainable Chem. Eng. 4, 3871–3876. 10.1021/acssuschemeng.6b00641</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.6b00641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dou J., Heinonen J., Vuorinen T., Xu C., Sainio T. (2021). Chromatographic Recovery and Purification of Natural Phytochemicals from Underappreciated Willow Bark Water Extracts. Separation Purif. Technology 261, 118247. 10.1016/j.seppur.2020.118247</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.seppur.2020.118247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dou J., Paltakari J., Johansson L.-S., Vuorinen T. (2019). Novel Insight into the Separation and Composite Utilization of Sclerenchyma Fiber Bundles of Willow Bark. ACS Sustainable Chem. Eng. 7, 2964–2970. 10.1021/acssuschemeng.8b04001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.8b04001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dou J., Xu W., Koivisto J. J., Mobley J. K., Padmakshan D., Kögler M., et al. (2018). Characteristics of Hot Water Extracts from the Bark of Cultivated Willow (Salix sp.). ACS Sustainable Chem. Eng. 6, 5566–5573. 10.1021/acssuschemeng.8b00498</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.8b00498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durak A., Gawlik-Dziki U. (2014). The Study of Interactions between Active Compounds of Coffee and Willow (Salixsp.) Bark Water Extract. Biomed. Res. Int. 2014, 1–11. 10.1155/2014/386953</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2014/386953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4071790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25013777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Shemy H. A., Aboul-Enein A. M., Aboul-Enein K. M., Fujita K. (2007). Willow Leaves' Extracts Contain Anti-tumor Agents Effective against Three Cell Types. PLoS One 2 (1), e178. 10.1371/journal.pone.0000178</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1779808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17264881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Förster N., Ulrichs C., Zander M., Kätzel R., Mewis I. (2008). Influence of the Season on the Salicylate and Phenolic Glycoside Contents in the Bark of Salix Daphnoides, Salix Pentandra, and Salix Purpurea . J. Appl. Bot. Food Qual. 82, 99–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraga-Corral M., Otero P., Echave J., Garcia-Oliveira P., Carpena M., Jarboui A., et al. (2021). By-Products of Agri-Food Industry as Tannin-Rich Sources: A Review of Tannins' Biological Activities and Their Potential for Valorization. Foods 10, 137. 10.3390/foods10010137</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10010137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7827785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33440730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glynn C., Rönnberg-Wästljung A.-C., Julkunen-Tiitto R., Weih M. (2004). Willow Genotype, but Not Drought Treatment, Affects Foliar Phenolic Concentrations and Leaf-Beetle Resistance. Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata 113, 1–14. 10.1111/j.0013-8703.2004.00199.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.0013-8703.2004.00199.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grienke U., Schmidtke M., von Grafenstein S., Kirchmair J., Liedl K. R., Rollinger J. M. (2012). Influenza Neuraminidase: a Druggable Target for Natural Products. Nat. Prod. Rep. 29, 11–36. 10.1039/C1NP00053E</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C1NP00053E</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22025274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu J., Guo M., Zheng L., Yin X., Zhou L., Fan D., et al. (2021). Protective Effects of Lignin-Carbohydrate Complexes from Wheat Stalk against Bisphenol a Neurotoxicity in Zebrafish via Oxidative Stress. Antioxidants 10, 1640. 10.3390/antiox10101640</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox10101640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8533324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34679774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hallgren P., Ikonen A., Hjalten J., Roininen H. (2003). Inheritance Patterns of Phenolics in F1, F2, and Back-Cross Hybrids of willows: Implications for Herbivore Responses to Hybrid Plants. J. Chem. Ecol. 29, 1143–1158. 10.1023/A:1023829506473</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1023829506473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12857027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hazra B., Biswas S., Mandal N. (2008). Antioxidant and Free Radical Scavenging Activity of Spondias Pinnata . BMC Complement. Altern. Med. 8, 63. 10.1186/1472-6882-8-63</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-8-63</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2636748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19068130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heiska S., Tikkanen O.-P., Rousi M., Julkunen-Tiitto R. (2007). Bark Salicylates and Condensed Tannins Reduce Vole Browsing Amongst Cultivated Dark-Leaved willows (Salix Myrsinifolia). Chemoecology 17, 245–253. 10.1007/s00049-007-0385-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00049-007-0385-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobisch M. A., Phiri J., Dou J., Gane P., Vuorinen T., Bauer W., et al. (2020). Willow Bark for Sustainable Energy Storage Systems. Materials 13, 1016. 10.3390/ma13041016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma13041016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7078613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32102362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou J., Guo Z., Liu H., Yin T. (2017). Gender Effects on Salix Suchowensis Growth and wood Properties as Revealed by a Full-Sib Pedigree. Can. J. Plant Sci. 97, 594–600. 10.1139/cjps-2016-0153</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/cjps-2016-0153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang D., Ou B., Hampsch-Woodill M., Flanagan J. A., Prior R. L. (2002). High-throughput Assay of Oxygen Radical Absorbance Capacity (ORAC) Using a Multichannel Liquid Handling System Coupled with a Microplate Fluorescence Reader in 96-well Format. J. Agric. Food Chem. 50, 4437–4444. 10.1021/jf0201529</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf0201529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12137457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Väre H., Saarinen J., Kurtto A., Hämet-Ahti L. (Editors) (2021). Suomen Puu- Ja Pensaskasvio [Woody Flora of Finland]. third ed. (Helsinki: Publications of the Finnish Dendrological Society; ), 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hytönen J., Saarsalmi A. (2009). Long-term Biomass Production and Nutrient Uptake of Birch, Alder and Willow Plantations on Cut-Away Peatland. Biomass and Bioenergy 33, 1197–1211. 10.1016/j.biombioe.2009.05.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biombioe.2009.05.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikonen A., Tahvanainen J., Roininen H. (2002). Phenolic Secondary Compounds as Determinants of the Host Plant Preferences of the Leaf Beetle Agelastica Alni . Chemoecology 12, 125–131. 10.1007/s00012-002-8337-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00012-002-8337-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Z.-Y., Woollard A. C. S., Wolff S. P. (1990). Hydrogen Peroxide Production during Experimental Protein Glycation. FEBS Lett. 268, 69–71. 10.1016/0014-5793(90)80974-N</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(90)80974-N</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2384174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julkunen-Tiitto R. (1986). A Chemotaxonomic Survey of Phenolics in Leaves of Northern Salicaceae Species. Phytochemistry 25, 663–667. 10.1016/0031-9422(86)88020-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0031-9422(86)88020-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julkunen-Tiitto R. (1985). Chemotaxonomical Screening of Phenolic Glycosides in Northern Willow Twigs by Capillary Gas Chromatography. J. Chromatogr. A 324, 129–139. 10.1016/S0021-9673(01)81312-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0021-9673(01)81312-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julkunen-Tiitto R., Sorsa S. (2001). Testing the Effect of Drying Methods on Willow Flavonoids, Tannins and Salicylates. J. Chem. Ecol. 27, 779–789. 10.1023/A:1010358120482</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1010358120482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11446300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julkunen-Tiitto R., Virjamo V. (2017). “Biosynthesis and Roles of Salicaceae Salicylates,” in Plant Specialized Metabolism: Genomics, Biochemistry, and Biological Functions. Editors Arimura G., Maffei M. (Boca Raton: CRC Press; ), 65–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kammerer B., Kahlich R., Biegert C., Gleiter C. H., Heide L. (2005). HPLC-MS/MS Analysis of Willow Bark Extracts Contained in Pharmaceutical Preparations. Phytochem. Anal. 16, 470–478. 10.1002/pca.873</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pca.873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16315493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khayyal M., El-Ghazaly M., Abdallah D., Okpanyi S., Kelber O., Weiser D. (2005). Mechanisms Involved in the Anti-inflammatory Effect of a Standardized Willow Bark Extract. Arzneimittelforschung 55, 677–687. 10.1055/s-0031-1296917</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0031-1296917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16366042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilpeläinen P., Leppänen K., Spetz P., Kitunen V., Ilvesniemi H., Pranovich A., et al. (2012). BIOREFINERY. Pressurised Hot Water Extraction of Acetylated Xylan from Birch Sawdust. Pulp Pap. Res. J. 27, 680–688. 10.3183/npprj-2012-27-04-p680-688</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3183/npprj-2012-27-04-p680-688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilpeläinen P. O., Hautala S. S., Byman O. O., Tanner L. J., Korpinen R. I., Lillandt M. K.-J., et al. (2014). Pressurized Hot Water Flow-Through Extraction System Scale up from the Laboratory to the Pilot Scale. Green. Chem. 16, 3186–3194. 10.1039/C4GC00274A</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C4GC00274A</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krzyżaniak M., Stolarski M. J., Szczukowski S., Tworkowski J. (2016). Life Cycle Assessment of New Willow Cultivars Grown as Feedstock for Integrated Biorefineries. Bioenerg. Res. 9, 224–238. 10.1007/s12155-015-9681-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12155-015-9681-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavola A., Maukonen M., Julkunen-Tiitto R. (2018). Variability in the Composition of Phenolic Compounds in winter-dormant Salix Pyrolifolia in Relation to Plant Part and Age. Phytochemistry 153, 102–110. 10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.05.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.05.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29906656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu A.-L., Wang H.-D., Lee S. M., Wang Y.-T., Du G.-H. (2008). Structure-activity Relationship of Flavonoids as Influenza Virus Neuraminidase Inhibitors and Their In Vitro Anti-viral Activities. Bioorg. Med. Chem. 16, 7141–7147. 10.1016/j.bmc.2008.06.049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bmc.2008.06.049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18640042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malterud K. E., Bremnes T. E., Faegri A., Moe T., Dugstad E. K. S., Anthonsen T., et al. (1985). Flavonoids from the wood of Salix Caprea as Inhibitors of wood-destroying Fungi. J. Nat. Prod. 48, 559–563. 10.1021/np50040a007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/np50040a007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marjomäki V., Turkki P., Huttunen M. (2015). Infectious Entry Pathway of Enterovirus B Species. Viruses 7, 6387–6399. 10.3390/v7122945</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v7122945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4690868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26690201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monte Junior E. S. d., Santos M. E. L. d., Ribeiro I. B., Luz G. d. O., Baba E. R., Hirsch B. S., et al. (2020). Rare and Fatal Gastrointestinal Mucormycosis (Zygomycosis) in a COVID-19 Patient: a Case Report. Clin. Endosc. 53, 746–749. 10.5946/ce.2020.180</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5946/ce.2020.180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7719411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33207116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mostafa I., Abbas H. A., Ashour M. L., Yasri A., El-Shazly A. M., Wink M., et al. (2020). Polyphenols from Salix Tetrasperma Impair Virulence and Inhibit Quorum Sensing of Pseudomonas aeruginosa . Molecules 25, 1341. 10.3390/molecules25061341</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules25061341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7146421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32187997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nahrstedt A., Schmidt M., Jäggi R., Metz J., Khayyal M. T. (2007). Willow Bark Extract: the Contribution of Polyphenols to the Overall Effect. Wien. Med. Wochenschr. 157, 348–351. 10.1007/s10354-007-0437-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10354-007-0437-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17704985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nassar M. M., MacKay G. D. M. (1984). Mechanism of thermal Decomposition of Lignin. Wood Fiber Sci. 16, 441–453.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nissinen K., Virjamo V., Mehtätalo L., Lavola A., Valtonen A., Nybakken L., et al. (2018). A Seven-Year Study of Phenolic Concentrations of the Dioecious Salix Myrsinifolia . J. Chem. Ecol. 44, 416–430. 10.1007/s10886-018-0942-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10886-018-0942-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29552701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noleto-Dias C., Harflett C., Beale M. H., Ward J. L. (2020). Sulfated Flavanones and Dihydroflavonols from Willow. Phytochemistry Lett. 35, 88–93. 10.1016/j.phytol.2019.11.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phytol.2019.11.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6988443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32025274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noleto-Dias C., Ward J. L., Bellisai A., Lomax C., Beale M. H. (2018). Salicin-7-sulfate: A New Salicinoid from Willow and Implications for Herbal Medicine. Fitoterapia 127, 166–172. 10.1016/j.fitote.2018.02.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2018.02.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5999357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29447984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noleto-Dias C., Wu Y., Bellisai A., Macalpine W., Beale M., Ward J. (2019). Phenylalkanoid Glycosides (Non-salicinoids) from Wood Chips of Salix Triandra × Dasyclados Hybrid Willow. Molecules 24, 1152. 10.3390/molecules24061152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules24061152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6470679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30909533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohta T., Yamasaki S., Egashira Y., Sanada H. (1994). Antioxidative Activity of Corn Bran Hemicellulose Fragments. J. Agric. Food Chem. 42, 653–656. 10.1021/jf00039a010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf00039a010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parajuli R., Knudsen M. T., Dalgaard T. (2015). Multi-criteria Assessment of Yellow, green, and Woody Biomasses: Pre-screening of Potential Biomasses as Feedstocks for Biorefineries. Biofuels, Bioprod. Bioref. 9, 545–566. 10.1002/bbb.1567</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bbb.1567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paunonen R., Julkunen-Tiitto R., Tegelberg R., Rousi M., Heiska S. (2009). Salicylate and Biomass Yield, and Leaf Phenolics of Dark-Leaved Willow (Salix Myrsinifolia Salisb.) Clones under Different Cultivation Methods after the Second Cultivation Cycle. Ind. Crops Prod. 29, 261–268. 10.1016/j.indcrop.2008.05.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2008.05.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phiri J., Dou J., Vuorinen T., Gane P. A. C., Maloney T. C. (2019). Highly Porous Willow Wood-Derived Activated Carbon for High-Performance Supercapacitor Electrodes. ACS Omega 4, 18108–18117. 10.1021/acsomega.9b01977</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsomega.9b01977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6843703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31720513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piątczak E., Dybowska M., Płuciennik E., Kośla K., Kolniak-Ostek J., Kalinowska-Lis U. (2020). Identification and Accumulation of Phenolic Compounds in the Leaves and Bark of Salix alba (L.) and Their Biological Potential. Biomolecules 10, 1391. 10.3390/biom10101391</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biom10101391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7600001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33003576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poolman J. T., Anderson A. S. (2018). Escherichia coliandStaphylococcus Aureus: Leading Bacterial Pathogens of Healthcare Associated Infections and Bacteremia in Older-Age Populations. Expert Rev. Vaccin. 17, 607–618. 10.1080/14760584.2018.1488590</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14760584.2018.1488590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29902092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prior R. L., Hoang H., Gu L., Wu X., Bacchiocca M., Howard L., et al. (2003). Assays for Hydrophilic and Lipophilic Antioxidant Capacity (Oxygen Radical Absorbance Capacity (ORACFL)) of Plasma and Other Biological and Food Samples. J. Agric. Food Chem. 51, 3273–3279. 10.1021/jf0262256</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf0262256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12744654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quosdorf S., Schuetz A., Kolodziej H. (2017). Different Inhibitory Potencies of Oseltamivir Carboxylate, Zanamivir, and Several Tannins on Bacterial and Viral Neuraminidases as Assessed in a Cell-free Fluorescence-Based Enzyme Inhibition Assay. Molecules 22, 1989. 10.3390/molecules22111989</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules22111989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6150325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29149072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos P. A. B., Moreirinha C., Silva S., Costa E. M., Veiga M., Coscueta E., et al. (2019). The Health-Promoting Potential of Salix Spp. Bark Polar Extracts: Key Insights on Phenolic Composition and In Vitro Bioactivity and Biocompatibility. Antioxidants 8, 609. 10.3390/antiox8120609</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox8120609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6943414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31801290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasa K., Viherä-Aarnio A., Rytkönen P., Hyväluoma J., Kaseva J., Suhonen H., et al. (2021). Quantitative Analysis of Feedstock Structural Properties Can Help to Produce Willow Biochar with Homogenous Pore System. Ind. Crops Prod. 166, 113475. 10.1016/j.indcrop.2021.113475</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2021.113475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasi S., Kilpeläinen P., Rasa K., Korpinen R., Raitanen J.-E., Vainio M., et al. (2019). Cascade Processing of Softwood Bark with Hot Water Extraction, Pyrolysis and Anaerobic Digestion. Bioresour. Technology 292, 121893. 10.1016/j.biortech.2019.121893</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.121893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31430669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruokolainen V., Domanska A., Laajala M., Pelliccia M., Butcher S. J., Marjomäki V. (2019). Extracellular Albumin and Endosomal Ions Prime Enterovirus Particles for Uncoating that Can Be Prevented by Fatty Acid Saturation. J. Virol. 93, e00599–19. 10.1128/JVI.00599-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.00599-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6694817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31189702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruuhola T., Julkunen-Tiitto R. (2003). Trade-off between Synthesis of Salicylates and Growth of Micropropagated Salix Pentandra . J. Chem. Ecol. 29, 1565–1588. 10.1023/A:1024266612585</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1024266612585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12921436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rytter R.-M., Rytter L., Högbom L. (2015). Carbon Sequestration in Willow (Salix spp.) Plantations on Former Arable Land Estimated by Repeated Field Sampling and C Budget Calculation. Biomass and Bioenergy 83, 483–492. 10.1016/j.biombioe.2015.10.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biombioe.2015.10.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saracila M., Tabuc C., Panaite T. D., Papuc C. P., Olteanu M., Criste R. D. (2018). Effect of the Dietary Willow Bark Extract (Salix Alba) on the Caecal Microbial Population of Broilers (14-28 Days) Reared at 32˚C. Life Agriculture” Conf. Proc. 1 (1), 155–161. 10.2478/alife-2018-0023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2478/alife-2018-0023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saska M. M., Kuzovkina Y. A. (2010). Phenological Stages of Willow (Salix). Ann. Appl. Biol. 156, 431–437. 10.1111/j.1744-7348.2010.00400.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7348.2010.00400.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shara M., Stohs S. J. (2015). Efficacy and Safety of White Willow Bark (Salix alba ) Extracts. Phytother. Res. 29, 1112–1116. 10.1002/ptr.5377</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.5377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25997859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh D. P., Moore C. A., Gilliland A., Carr J. P. (2004). Activation of Multiple Antiviral Defence Mechanisms by Salicylic Acid. Mol. Plant Pathol. 5, 57–63. 10.1111/j.1364-3703.2004.00203.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2004.00203.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20565582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singleton V. L., Orthofer R., Lamuela-Raventós R. M. (1999). [14] Analysis of Total Phenols and Other Oxidation Substrates and Antioxidants by Means of Folin-Ciocalteu Reagent. Meth. Enzymol. 299, 152–178. 10.1016/S0076-6879(99)99017-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0076-6879(99)99017-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singleton V. L., Rossi J. A., Jr. (1965). Colorimetry of Total Phenolics with Phosphomolybdic-Phosphotungstic Acid Reagents. Am. J. Enol. Vitic. 16, 144–158. 10.2307/3006717</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/3006717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spanakis E. K., Aperis G., Mylonakis E. (2006). Reviews of Anti‐infective Agents: New Agents for the Treatment of Fungal Infections: Clinical Efficacy and Gaps in Coverage. Clin. Infect. Dis. 43, 1060–1068. 10.1086/507891</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/507891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16983621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinbach D., Kruse A., Sauer J. (2017). Pretreatment Technologies of Lignocellulosic Biomass in Water in View of Furfural and 5-hydroxymethylfurfural Production- A Review. Biomass Conv. Bioref. 7, 247–274. 10.1007/s13399-017-0243-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13399-017-0243-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahvanainen J., Helle E., Julkunen-Tiitto R., Lavola A. (1985a). Phenolic Compounds of Willow Bark as Deterrents against Feeding by Mountain Hare. Oecologia 65, 319–323. 10.1007/bf00378905</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/bf00378905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28310435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahvanainen J., Julkunen-Tiitto R., Kettunen J., Lavola A. (1985b). Phenolic Glycosides Govern the Food Selection Pattern of Willow Feeding Leaf Beetles. Oecologia 67, 52–56. 10.1007/bf00378451</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/bf00378451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28309845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tawfeek N., Mahmoud M. F., Hamdan D. I., Sobeh M., Farrag N., Wink M., et al. (2021). Phytochemistry, Pharmacology and Medicinal Uses of Plants of the Genus Salix: An Updated Review. Front. Pharmacol. 12, 50. 10.3389/fphar.2021.593856</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2021.593856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7908037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33643045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tienaho J., Karonen M., Muilu-Mäkelä R., Kaseva J., De Pedro N., Vicente F., et al. (2020). Bioactive Properties of the Aqueous Extracts of Endophytic Fungi Associated with Scots Pine (Pinus Sylvestris) Roots. Planta Med. 86, 1009–1024. 10.1055/a-1185-4437</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/a-1185-4437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32521558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tienaho J., Sarjala T., Franzén R., Karp M. (2015). Method with High-Throughput Screening Potential for Antioxidative Substances Using Escherichia coli Biosensor katG′:lux. J. Microbiol. Methods 118, 78–80. 10.1016/j.mimet.2015.08.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2015.08.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26327540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tienaho J., Silvan N., Muilu-Mäkelä R., Kilpeläinen P., Poikulainen E., Sarjala T. (2021). Ultraviolet Absorbance of Sphagnum Magellanicum, S. Fallax and S. Fuscum Extracts with Seasonal and Species-specific Variation. Photochem. Photobiol. Sci. 20, 379–389. 10.1007/s43630-021-00026-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43630-021-00026-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33721276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Tienaho J. (2020). Utilizing Nordic Forest Plant and Fungi Extracts: Bioactivity Assessment with Bacterial Whole-Cell Biosensors. Academic dissertation. . https://trepo.tuni.fi/handle/10024/120296.
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyśkiewicz K., Konkol M., Kowalski R., Rój E., Warmiński K., Krzyżaniak M., et al. (2019). Characterization of Bioactive Compounds in the Biomass of Black Locust, poplar and Willow. Trees 33, 1235–1263. 10.1007/s00468-019-01837-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00468-019-01837-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Välimaa A.-L., Raitanen J.-E., Tienaho J., Sarjala T., Nakayama E., Korpinen R., et al. (2020). Enhancement of Norway spruce Bark Side-Streams: Modification of Bioactive and Protective Properties of Stilbenoid-Rich Extracts by UVA-Irradiation. Ind. Crops Prod. 145, 112150. 10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verwijst T., Lundkvist A., Edelfeldt S., Albertsso J. (2013). “Development of Sustainable Willow Short Rotation Forestry in Northern Europe,” in Biomass Now–Sustainable Growth and Use. Editor Matovic M. D. (London: IntechOpen; ), 479–502. 10.5772/55072</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5772/55072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vesterlund S., Paltta J., Lauková A., Karp M., Ouwehand A. C. (2004). Rapid Screening Method for the Detection of Antimicrobial Substances. J. Microbiol. Methods 57, 23–31. 10.101/j.mimet.2003.11.01410.1016/j.mimet.2003.11.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.101/j.mimet.2003.11.01410.1016/j.mimet.2003.11.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15003685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilhelmova-Ilieva N., S. Galabov A., Mileva M. (2019). “Tannins as Antiviral Agents,” in Tannins-Structural Properties, Biological Properties and Current Knowledge. Editor Aires A. (London: IntechOpen Limited; ). 10.5772/intechopen.86490</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5772/intechopen.86490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vlachojannis J. E., Cameron M., Chrubasik S. (2009). A Systematic Review on the Effectiveness of Willow Bark for Musculoskeletal Pain. Phytother. Res. 23, 897–900. 10.1002/ptr.2747</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.2747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19140170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
VMR, Verified Market Research (2020). Global Antimicrobial Packaging Market
. https://www.verifiedmarketresearch.com/product/antimicrobial-packaging-market/(accessed May 19, 2021). </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volk T. A., Verwijst T., Tharakan P. J., Abrahamson L. P., White E. H. (2004). Growing Fuel: a Sustainability Assessment of Willow Biomass Crops. Front. Ecol. Environ. 2, 411–418. 10.1890/1540-9295(2004)002[0411:gfasao]2.0.co;2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1890/1540-9295(2004)002[0411:gfasao]2.0.co;2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R., Zheng L., Xu Q., Xu L., Wang D., Li J., et al. (2021). Unveiling the Structural Properties of Water-Soluble Lignin from Gramineous Biomass by Autohydrolysis and its Functionality as a Bioactivator (Anti-inflammatory and Antioxidative). Int. J. Biol. Macromolecules 191, 1087–1095. 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.09.124</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.09.124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34600953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward J. L., Wu Y., Harflett C., Onafuye H., Corol D., Lomax C., et al. (2020). Miyabeacin: A New Cyclodimer Presents a Potential Role for Willow in Cancer Therapy. Sci. Rep. 10, 6477. 10.1038/s41598-020-63349-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-63349-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7160102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32296088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood J. N. (2015). From Plant Extract to Molecular Panacea: a Commentary on Stone (1763) 'An Account of the success of the Bark of the Willow in the Cure of the Agues'. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B 370, 20140317. 10.1098/rstb.2014.0317</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rstb.2014.0317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4360122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25750237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F., Jia X., Yin L., Cheng Y., Miao Y., Zhang X. (2019). The Effect of Hemicellulose and Lignin on Properties of Polysaccharides in Lentinus Edodes and Their Antioxidant Evaluation. Molecules 24, 1834. 10.3390/molecules24091834</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules24091834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6539561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31086063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y., Dobermann D., Beale M. H., Ward J. L. (2016). Acutifoliside, a Novel Benzoic Acid Glycoside from Salix Acutifolia . Nat. Product. Res. 30, 1731–1739. 10.1080/14786419.2015.1137571</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14786419.2015.1137571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26820172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan B., Chen Z. S., Hu Y., Yong Q. (2021). Insight in the Recent Application of Polyphenols from Biomass. Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol. 9. 10.3389/fbioe.2021.753898</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fbioe.2021.753898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8473751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34589477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng L., Lu G., Pei W., Yan W., Li Y., Zhang L., et al. (2021). Understanding the Relationship between the Structural Properties of Lignin and Their Biological Activities. Int. J. Biol. Macromolecules 190, 291–300. 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.08.168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.08.168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34461157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>