<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35119491</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-1076</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>181</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>May</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European journal of pediatrics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur J Pediatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Neurodevelopmental outcomes of newborns and infants with parechovirus and enterovirus central nervous infection: a 5-year longitudinal study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2005</StartPage><EndPage>2016</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2005-2016</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00431-022-04402-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">Though parechovirus (PeV) and enterovirus (EV) are common causes of central nervous system (CNS) infection in childhood, little is known about their long-term neurologic/neurodevelopmental complications. We investigated, longitudinally over a 5-year period, motor neurodevelopment in term-born newborns and infants with RT-qPCR-confirmed PeV- or EV-CNS infection. Motor neurodevelopment was assessed with standardized tests: Alberta Infant Motor Scale (AIMS), Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development version-3 (Bayley-3-NL), and Movement Assessment Battery for Children version-2 (M-ABC-2-NL) at 6, 12, 24, and 60 months post-infection. Results of children with PeV-CNS infection were compared with those of peers with EV-CNS infection and with Dutch norm references. In the multivariate analyses adjustments were made for age at onset, gender, maternal education, and time from CNS infection Sixty of 172 eligible children aged ≤ 3 months were included. Children with PeV-CNS infection had consistently lower, non-significant mean gross motor function (GMF) Z-scores, compared with peers with EV-CNS infection and population norm-referenced GMF. Their GMF improved between 6 and 24 months and decreased at 5 years. Their fine motor function (FMF) scores fell within the population norm reference.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These results suggest that the impact of PeV-A3-CNS infection on gross motor neurodevelopment in young children might manifest later in life. They highlight the importance of longitudinal neurodevelopmental assessments of children with PeV-A3-CNS infection up to school age.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="WHAT IS KNOWN" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">• Human parechovirus (PeV) is a major cause of central nervous system infection (CNS infection) in newborns and infants. • There is interest in the neurological and neurodevelopmental outcome of newborns and infants with PeV-A3-CNS infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="WHAT IS NEW" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">• This prospective study compares the motor neurodevelopment of term-born newborns and infants with PeV-A3-CNS infection with those with EV-CNS infection and with norm references. • The results support the importance of follow-up of newborns and infants with PeV-A3-CNS infection to detect subtle neurodevelopmental delay and start early interventions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2022. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Hinsbergh</LastName><ForeName>Ted</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1655-6815</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Elisabeth-Tweesteden Hospital, Hilvarenbeekseweg 60, Tilburg, 5022 LC, The Netherlands. t.vanhinsbergh@etz.nl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elbers</LastName><ForeName>Roy-G</ForeName><Initials>RG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amsterdam UMC, Department of Clinical Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, Medical Faculty (AMC), University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bouman</LastName><ForeName>Zita</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Psychology, Canisius Wilhelmina Hospital, Nijmegen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Furth</LastName><ForeName>Marceline</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatric Infectious Diseases and Immunology, Amsterdam UMC, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, AI&amp;II, De Boelelaan 1117, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Obihara</LastName><ForeName>Charlie</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Elisabeth-Tweesteden Hospital, Hilvarenbeekseweg 60, Tilburg, 5022 LC, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Eur J Pediatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7603873</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0340-6199</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D020904">Glia Maturation Factor</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002494" MajorTopicYN="Y">Central Nervous System Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020904" MajorTopicYN="N">Glia Maturation Factor</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008137" MajorTopicYN="N">Longitudinal Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030061" MajorTopicYN="Y">Parechovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010850" MajorTopicYN="Y">Picornaviridae Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011446" MajorTopicYN="N">Prospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Central nervous system infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neurodevelopmental outcomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parechovirus</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35119491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-022-04402-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00431-022-04402-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Harvala H, Simmonds P et al (2019) Strategies to improve detection and management of human parechovirus infection in young infants. Lancet Infect Dis 19:e51–e58</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30288-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Braccio S, Ribeiro S et al (2019) Enterovirus and parechovirus meningitis in infants younger than 90 days old in the UK and Republic of Ireland: a British Paediatric Surveillance Unit study. Arch Dis Child 104:552–557</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2018-315643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrerizo M, Díaz-Cerio M, Muñoz-Almagro C et al (2017) Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus and parechovirus infections according to patient age over a 4-year period in Spain. J Med Virol 89:435–442</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.24658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Crom SCM, Obihara CC, de Moor RA et al (2013) Prospective comparison of the detection rates of human enterovirus and parechovirus RT-qPCR and viral culture in different pediatric specimens. J Clin Virol 58:449–454</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2013.07.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verboon-Maciolek MA, Groenendaal F, Hahn CD et al (2008) Human parechovirus causes encephalitis with white mater injury in neonates. Ann Neurol 64:266–273</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ana.21445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson TM, Vuillermin P, Hodge J et al (2017) An outbreak of severe infections among Australian infants caused by a novel recombinant strain of human parechovirus type 3. Sci Rep 7:44423. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep44423</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep44423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28290509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5349594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H et al (2020) Recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol 165:793–797</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-019-04520-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Hinsbergh TMT, Elbers RG, Ket JCF et al (2020) Neurological and neurodevelopmental outcomes after human parechovirus CNS infection in neonates and young children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Child Adolesc Health 4:592–605</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30181-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Hinsbergh TMT, de Crom SCM, Lindeboom R et al (2019) Human parechovirus meningitis and gross-motor neurodevelopment in young children. Eur J Pediatr 178:473–481</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-019-03319-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapiainen T, Prevots R, Izurieta HS et al (2007) Aseptic meningitis: case definition and guidelines for collection, analysis and presentation of immunization safety data. Vaccine 25:5793–5802</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2007.04.058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Hinsbergh TMT, Elbers RG, van Furth AM et al (2019) Longitudinal association between human parechovirus central nervous system infection and gross-motor neurodevelopment in young children. Pediatr Infect Dis J 38:110–114</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000002052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Central Bureau for Statistics (2020) Statistics Netherlands [Internet]. Available at: https://www.cbs.nl/nl-nl/onze-diensten/methoden/classificaties/onderwijs-en-beroepen/standaard-onderwijsindeling--soi--/standaard-onderwijsindeling-2016 ; Edition 2018/’19, Page 10,11. Accessed 17 May 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piper MC, Darrah J (1994) Motor assessment of the developing infant. WB Saunders, Philadelphia</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayley N (2006) Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development - 3th ed. San Antonio: NCS Pearson</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henderson SE, Sugden DA (2010) Movement ABC-2 Movement Assessment Battery for Children - 2th ed. Nederlandse Bewerking: BCM Smits-Engelsman. Amsterdam, the Netherlands: Pearson Assessment and Information B.V</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darrah J, Bartlett D, Maguire TO et al (2014) Have infant gross motor abilities changed in 20 years? A re-evaluation of the Alberta Infant Motor Scale normative values. Dev Med Child Neurol 56:877–881</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dmcn.12452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Baar AL, Steenis LJ, Verhoeven M et al (2014) Bayley-III-NL; technische handleiding. Amsterdam, the Netherlands: Pearson Assessment and Information B.V</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albuquerque PL, Guerra MQF, Lima MC et al (2018) Concurrent validity of the Alberta Infant Motor Scale to detect delayed gross motor development in preterm infants: a comparative study with the Bayley III. Dev Neurorehabil 21:408–414</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28537470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinheiro JBD, DebRoy S, Sarkar D et al (2020) nlme: Linear and Nonlinear Mixed Effects Models. R package version 3.1–131. [Internet]. Available at https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=nlme . Published 2017. Accessed 17 May 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blank R, Barnett AL, Cairney J et al (2019) International clinical practice recommendations on the definition, diagnosis, assessment, intervention, and psychosocial aspects of developmental coordination disorder. Dev Med Child Neurol 61:242–285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dmcn.14132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye A, Yan S, Huang K et al (2019) Maternal intelligence quotient and motor development in early childhood: the mediating role of mother’s education. J Paediatr Child Health 55:87–94</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jpc.14123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karelehto E, Wildenbeest JG, Benschop KSM et al (2018) Human parechovirus 1, 3 and 4 neutralizing antibodies in Dutch mothers and infants and their role in protection against disease. Pediatr Infect Dis J 37:1304–1308</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000001986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin GL, McGinley JP, Drysdale SB et al (2018) Epidemiology and immune pathogenesis of viral sepsis. Front Immunol 9:2147. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2018.02147</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.02147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30319615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6170629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rice D, Barone S (2000) Critical periods of vulnerability for the developing nervous system: evidence from humans and animal models. Environ Health Perspect 108:511–533</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10852851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">1637807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismail FY, Fatemi A, Johnston MV (2017) Cerebral plasticity: windows of opportunity in the developing brain. Eur J Paediatr Neurol 21:23–48</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejpn.2016.07.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton PN, Walker K, McMullan B et al (2020) Early life parechovirus infection neurodevelopmental outcomes at 3 years: a cohort study. J Pediatr 219:111–117</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2019.12.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Izumita R, Aizawa Y, Watanabe K, Saitoh A (2019) Persistence of high neutralizing antibody titers after neonatal and early infantile infection with parechovirus-A3. Pediatr Infect Dis J 38(7):e159–e161</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000002245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darrah J, Senthilselvan A, Magill-Evans J (2009) Trajectories of serial motor scores of typically developing children: implications for clinical decision making. Infant Behav Dev 32:72–78</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novak I, Morgan C, Adde L et al (2017) Early, accurate diagnosis and early intervention in cerebral palsy: advances in diagnosis and treatment. JAMA Pediatr 171:897–907</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2017.1689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flatters I, Mushtaq F, Hill LJ et al (2014) The relationship between a child’s postural stability and manual dexterity. Exp Brain Res 232:2907–2917</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00221-014-3947-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffiths A, Toovey R, Morgan PE, Spittle AJ (2018) Psychometric properties of gross motor assessment tools for children: a systematic review. BMJ Open 8:e021734. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2018-021734</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-021734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30368446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6224743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilbride H, Jackson MA, Selvarangan R (2021) Childhood outcomes following parechovirus infections in a US young infant cohort. Pediatr Infect Dis J 40:295–299</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000002988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>