<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">35784975</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Secondary to Enterovirus-Human-Rhinovirus Infection in an Adult.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e26475</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e26475</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e26475</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.26475</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus-human-rhinovirus (EV-HRV) are small RNA viruses that are airborne and can spread by direct contact or fomites and usually cause the common cold, asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbation. EV-HRV-associated acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is common in children but is a rare cause of ARDS in adults. ARDS is defined according to the Berlin criteria and can be mild, moderate or severe depending on the PaO <sub><sup>2</sup></sub> to FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio. We report a case of a 70-year-old female with cardiac comorbidities, emphysema, second-hand smoking of 25 years, on methotrexate for rheumatoid arthritis presenting with ARDS secondary to EV-HRV infection. Despite initial treatment with appropriate antibiotics, steroids, low tidal volume mechanical ventilation, rescue maneuvers such as ventilation in prone positioning, paralyses, and inhaled nitric oxide, she passed away. EV-HRV causes upper respiratory tract infections but causes cytokine releases such as IL-1, IL-6, and IL-8 in the lower respiratory tract and in the blood which can cause ARDS. Very few cases of EV-HRV ARDS in immunocompetent adults are reported in the literature. Female sex is also associated with EV-HRV ARDS. No antiviral therapy exists for patients critically ill with EV-HRV; however, one case of successful treatment with high-dose intravenous vitamin C (HIVC) is reported in the literature. EV-HRV is one of the most common viruses identified in patients admitted with viral pneumonia in the intensive care unit. It should not be forgotten as a cause of ARDS.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2022, Hamid et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hamid</LastName><ForeName>Khizar</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, University of South Dakota Sanford School of Medicine, Sioux Falls, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, University of South Dakota Sanford School of Medicine, Sioux Falls, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Devasahayam</LastName><ForeName>Joe</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pulmonary Critical Care, Avera McKennan Hospital and University Health Center, Sioux Falls, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute respiratory distress syndrome (ards)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">community aquired pneumonia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid 19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medical intensive care unit (micu)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral infection</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35784975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9247263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.26475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Atomic structure of a rhinovirus C, a virus species linked to severe childhood asthma. Liu Y, Hill MG, Klose T, et al. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2016;113:8997–9002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4987780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27511920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhinovirus-induced rapidly progressing acute respiratory distress syndrome in an immunocompetent host. Ngu S, Pervaiz S, Avula A, Chalhoub M. Cureus. 2019;11:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6443533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30989006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A novel druggable interprotomer pocket in the capsid of rhino- and enteroviruses. Abdelnabi R, Geraets JA, Ma Y, et al. PLoS Biol. 2019;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6559632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31185007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enterovirus-human rhinovirus: a rare cause of acute respiratory distress syndrome. Soni P, Rai A, Aggarwal N, Kamholz S, Yoon T, Kupfer Y. J Investig Med High Impact Case Rep. 2017;5:2324709617728526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5588805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28904980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viral pneumonia and acute respiratory distress syndrome. Shah RD, Wunderink RG. Clin Chest Med. 2017;38:113–125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7131505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28159154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute respiratory distress syndrome: the Berlin Definition. Ranieri VM, Rubenfeld GD, Thompson BT, et al. JAMA. 2012;307:2526–2533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22797452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical characteristics and outcomes of severe rhinovirus-associated pneumonia identified by bronchoscopic bronchoalveolar lavage in adults: comparison with severe influenza virus-associated pneumonia. Choi SH, Huh JW, Hong SB, et al. J Clin Virol. 2015;62:41–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7106464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25542469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adverse effects of low dose methotrexate therapy in rheumatoid arthritis. McKendry RJ, Dale P. https://europepmc.org/article/med/8308769. J Rheumatol. 1993;20:1850–1856.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8308769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low-tidal-volume ventilation in the acute respiratory distress syndrome. Malhotra A. N Engl J Med. 2007;357:1113–1120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2287190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17855672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Treatment of ARDS with prone positioning. Scholten EL, Beitler JR, Prisk GK, Malhotra A. Chest. 2017;151:215–224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6026253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27400909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inhaled nitric oxide for acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) in children and adults. Gebistorf F, Karam O, Wetterslev J, Afshari A. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6464789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27347773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inhaled nitric oxide in adult patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome. Monsalve-Naharro JÁ, Domingo-Chiva E, García Castillo S, Cuesta-Montero P, Jiménez-Vizuete JM. Farm Hosp. 2017;41:292–312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28236803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dexamethasone in hospitalized patients with COVID-19. Horby P, Lim WS, Emberson JR, et al. N Engl J Med. 2021;384:693–704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7383595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32678530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>dexamethasone in ARDS network. Dexamethasone treatment for the acute respiratory distress syndrome: a multicentre, randomised controlled trial. Villar J, Ferrando C, Martínez D, et al. Lancet Respir Med. 2020;8:267–266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32043986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Intravenous vitamin C as adjunctive therapy for enterovirus/rhinovirus induced acute respiratory distress syndrome. Fowler Iii AA, Kim C, Lepler L, et al. World J Crit Care Med. 2017;6:85–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5295174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28224112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Intravenous high-dose vitamin C for the treatment of severe COVID-19: study protocol for a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Liu F, Zhu Y, Zhang J, Li Y, Peng Z. BMJ Open. 2020;10:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7348463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32641343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>