<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">35832753</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Fulminant Coxsackievirus Myocarditis in an Immunocompetent Adult: A Case Report and Literature Analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e25787</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e25787</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e25787</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.25787</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Myocarditis is an inflammatory condition that impacts cardiac myocytes and is caused mostly by viruses. It can manifest as chest pain, dyspnea, palpitations, fatigue, syncope, shortness of breath, and in severe cases frank cardiogenic shock. It accounts for around 10 percent of all sudden cardiac deaths in young adults, who are described as being in their early thirties. Inflammatory cardiomyopathy resulting from acute myocarditis may also appear as new-onset heart failure (HF), delaying the diagnosis and treatment of these patients. It is crucial to recognize the sensitivity of symptom onset, especially in young individuals; mildly elevated troponin levels that are inconsistent with the severity of left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) impairment and associated left ventricular dilatation strongly suggest inflammatory cardiomyopathy rather than acute myocarditis. The current treatment for myocarditis is primarily supportive, with an emphasis on the management of heart failure and arrhythmias in accordance with clinical practice guidelines. In this case report, we describe a male in his early forties who presented with abrupt onset exertional shortness of breath and chest discomfort. His cardiac catheterization did not show evidence of coronary artery disease; however, an echocardiogram revealed new-onset heart failure with reduced ejection fraction, the diagnosis of coxsackievirus myocarditis was made based on his clinical presentation, and a positive coxsackievirus immunoassay.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2022, Jain et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jain</LastName><ForeName>Ashish</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Conemaugh Memorial Medical Center, Johnstown, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rane</LastName><ForeName>Rahul P</ForeName><Initials>RP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Conemaugh Memorial Medical Center, Johnstown, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mumtaz</LastName><ForeName>Maha</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Conemaugh Memorial Medical Center, Johnstown, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Butt</LastName><ForeName>Asfand Y</ForeName><Initials>AY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Conemaugh Memorial Medical Center, Johnstown, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdelsalam</LastName><ForeName>Mahmoud</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Conemaugh Memorial Medical Center, Johnstown, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Waseem</LastName><ForeName>Saba</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Conemaugh Memorial Medical Center, Johnstown, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coxsackie virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fulminant cardiomyopathy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fulminant myocarditis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nonischemic cardiomyopathy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35832753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9272903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.25787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Myocarditis: current trends in diagnosis and treatment. Magnani JW, Dec GW. Circulation. 2006;113:876–890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16476862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The coxsackievirus and adenovirus receptor. Freimuth P, Philipson L, Carson SD. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol. 2008;323:67–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18357766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myocarditis and inflammatory cardiomyopathy: current evidence and future directions. Tschöpe C, Ammirati E, Bozkurt B, et al. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2021;18:169–193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7548534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33046850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CCR5del32 genotype in human enteroviral cardiomyopathy leads to spontaneous virus clearance and improved outcome compared to wildtype CCR5. Lassner D, Siegismund CS, Kühl U, Rohde M, Stroux A, Escher F, Schultheiss HP. J Transl Med. 2018;16:249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6123922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30180856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical presentation and outcome in a contemporary cohort of patients with acute myocarditis: multicenter Lombardy registry. Ammirati E, Cipriani M, Moro C, et al. Circulation. 2018;138:1088–1099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29764898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardiac MR with late gadolinium enhancement in acute myocarditis with preserved systolic function: ITAMY study. Aquaro GD, Perfetti M, Camastra G, et al. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2017;70:1977–1987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29025554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute and fulminant myocarditis: a pragmatic clinical approach to diagnosis and treatment. Ammirati E, Veronese G, Cipriani M, et al. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2018;20:114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30259175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnosis of myocarditis: death of Dallas criteria. Baughman KL. Circulation. 2006;113:593–595.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16449736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viral myocarditis--diagnosis, treatment options, and current controversies. Pollack A, Kontorovich AR, Fuster V, Dec GW. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2015;12:670–680.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26194549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meta-analysis on the immunohistological detection of inflammatory cardiomyopathy in endomyocardial biopsies. Katzmann JL, Schlattmann P, Rigopoulos AG, et al. Heart Fail Rev. 2020;25:277–294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31396762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Report of the 1995 World Health Organization/International Society and Federation of Cardiology Task Force on the Definition and Classification of cardiomyopathies. Richardson P, McKenna W, Bristow M, et al. Circulation. 1996;93:841–842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8598070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The role of endomyocardial biopsy in the management of cardiovascular disease: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association, the American College of Cardiology, and the European Society of Cardiology. Endorsed by the Heart Failure Society of America and the Heart Failure Association of the European Society of Cardiology. Cooper LT, Baughman KL, Feldman AM, et al. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2007;50:1914–1931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17980265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Current state of knowledge on aetiology, diagnosis, management, and therapy of myocarditis: a position statement of the European Society of Cardiology Working Group on Myocardial and Pericardial Diseases. Caforio AL, Pankuweit S, Arbustini E, et al. Eur Heart J. 2013;34:2636-48, 2648a-2648d.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23824828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>High risk of sustained ventricular arrhythmia recurrence after acute myocarditis. Rosier L, Zouaghi A, Barré V, et al. J Clin Med. 2020;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7141537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32244983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>