<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35972696</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-0991</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>79</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Single Mutation in the Cryptic AUG (cAUG) Affects In Vitro Translation and Replication Efficiencies and In Vivo Virulence of Coxsackievirus B3 (CVB3).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>288</StartPage><MedlinePgn>288</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00284-022-02986-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The 5'UTR of the genomic RNA of CVB3, unusually long and rich on highly structured secondary structure, contains a conserved cis acting RNA element named the cryptic AUG (cAUG), where the cellular 48S complex is formed. In this study, we investigate the role of this cAUG in CVB3 translation, replication, and virulence. Mutant viral sub-genomic replicon RNA was constructed by site-directed mutagenesis. We characterize in vitro translation and replication efficiencies and in vivo virulence of a cAUG mutant in comparison with wild-type strain. UV-cross-linking assay and Real-Time PCR were used, respectively, to detect binding host proteins and to quantify viral production. Secondary structures of domain containing the cAUG site were studied and compared. The results suggest that introduced mutation in the CVB3 5'UTR affects in vitro and ex vivo viral translation which cannot be rescued by compensatory mutations. A reduced interaction of the La and PCBP2 translation initiation factors with cAUG residue of mutant was revealed. Decreasing production of viral mutant RNA was also demonstrated. Furthermore, secondary structure prediction reveals changes in the ribosome binding sites of the cAUG moiety of mutant sense strand RNA and no alterations in the structure of wild type, suggesting that cAUG mutation specifically affects the secondary structure of the sense RNA strand. Taken together, AUG integrity influences the efficiency of ribosome recruitment through IRES element and the capacity of replication.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2022. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ben Youssef</LastName><ForeName>Ahlem</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Unit UR17ES30 "Virology &amp; Antiviral Strategies", Institute of Biotechnology, University of Monastir, Tahar HADDED Street, 5000, Monastir, Tunisia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gharbi</LastName><ForeName>Jawhar</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, College of Science, King Faisal University, P.O. Box 380, Al-Ahsa, 31982, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>George</LastName><ForeName>Biju</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, 560012, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Das</LastName><ForeName>Saumitra</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, 560012, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ben M'hadheb</LastName><ForeName>Manel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0145-7240</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Unit UR17ES30 "Virology &amp; Antiviral Strategies", Institute of Biotechnology, University of Monastir, Tahar HADDED Street, 5000, Monastir, Tunisia. benmhadhebmanel@yahoo.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>[Grant Nb. INT/P-09/2013]</GrantID><Agency>indian international cooperation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>GRANT280</GrantID><Agency>Deanship of Scientific Research, King Faisal University</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7808448</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0343-8651</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D020121">5' Untranslated Regions</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C501903">PCBP2 protein, human</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012367">RNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016601">RNA-Binding Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020121" MajorTopicYN="N">5' Untranslated Regions</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006367" MajorTopicYN="N">HeLa Cells</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009154" MajorTopicYN="N">Mutation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009690" MajorTopicYN="N">Nucleic Acid Conformation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014176" MajorTopicYN="N">Protein Biosynthesis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012367" MajorTopicYN="Y">RNA, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016601" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA-Binding Proteins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014774" MajorTopicYN="N">Virulence</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014779" MajorTopicYN="N">Virus Replication</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35972696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00284-022-02986-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00284-022-02986-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Muehlenbachs A, Bhatnagar J, Zaki SR (2015) Tissue tropism, pathology and pathogenesis of enterovirus infection. J Pathol 235(2):217–228</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25211036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao L, Fu Z (2018) Roles of host immunity in viral myocarditis and dilated cardiomyopathy. J Immunol Res 2018:1–12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutkiewicz MS, Ojdowska A, Smolska A, Dymarek-Babs B, Jasinska T, Ciesiolka J (2012) Molecular mechnisms of genome expression of coxsackievirus B3 that belongs to enteroviruses. Biotechnologia 93(4):414–423</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikonov OS, Chernykh ES, Garber MB, Nikonova EY (2017) Enteroviruses: classification, diseases they cause, and approaches to development of antiviral drugs. Biochem Mosc 82(13):1615–1631</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson SM, Tsueng G, Sin J et al (2014) Coxsackievirus B exits the host cell in shed microvesicles displaying autophagosomal markers. PLoS Patho 10(4):145–155</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellen CUT, Wimmer E (2014) Enterovirus genetics. Human enterovirus infections. Wiley, Hoboken, pp 25–72</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racaniello VR (2006) Picornaviridae: the virus and their replication. In: Knipe HP, Howley DM (eds) Field’s Virology, 5th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins a Wolter Kulwer Business, Philadelphia, pp 795–838</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M’hadheb-Gharbi MB, El Hiar R, Paulous S, Jaïdane H, Aouni M, Kean KM, Gharbi J (2008) Role of GNRA motif mutations within stem-loop V of internal ribosome entry segment in Coxsackievirus B3 molecular attenuation. J Mol Microbiol Biotechnol 14(4):147–156</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17693702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>M’hadheb-Gharbi MB, KeanK M, Gharbi J (2009) Molecular analysis of the role of IRES stem-loop V in replicative capacities and translation efficiencies of Coxsackievirus B3 mutants. Mol Bio Rep 36(2):255–262</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M’hadheb-Gharbi MB, Paulous S, Aouni M, Kean KM, Gharbi J (2007) The substitution U<sup>475</sup> → C with Sabin3-like mutation within the IRES attenuate Coxsackievirus B3 cardiovirulence. Mol Biotechnol 36(1):52–60</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17827538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>M’hadheb-Gharbi MB, Gharbi J, Paulous S et al (2006) Effects of the Sabin-like mutations in domain V of the internal ribosome entry segment on translational efficiency of the Coxsackievirus B3. Mol Gen Genom 276(4):402–412</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee C, Maull E, Chapman N, Tracy S, Gauntt C (1997) Genomic regions of coxsackievirus B3 associated with cardiovirulence. J Med Virol 52(3):341–347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9210047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunn JJ, Bradrick SS, Chapman NM, Tracy SM, Romero JR (2003) The stem loop II within the 5′ non translated region of clinical Coxsackievirus B3 genomes determines cardiovirulence phenotype in a murine model. J Infect Dis 187(10):1552–1561</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12721935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman NM, Tu Z, Tracy S, Gauntt CJ (1994) An infectious cDNA copy of the genome of a non cardiovirulent Coxsackievirus B3 strain: its complete sequence analysis and comparison to the genomes of cardiovirulent Coxsackieviruses. Arch Virol 135(1–2):115–130</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8198437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tu Z, Chapman MN, Hufnagel G et al (1995) The cardiovirulent phenotype of Coxsackievirus B3 is determined at a single site in the genomic 5′ nontranslated region. J Virol 69:4607–4618</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7609025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">189260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunn JJ, Chapman MN, Tracy S, Romero RJ (2000) Genomic determinants of cardiovirulence in coxsackievirus B3 clinical isolates: localization to the 5′ nontranslated region. J Virol 74(10):4787–4794</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10775617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">112001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souii A, M’hadheb-Gharbi M, Sargueil B, Brossard A, Chamond N, Aouni M, Gharbi J (2013) Ribosomal initiation complex assembly within the wild-strain of Coxsackievirus B3 and live-attenuated Sabin3-like IRESes during the initiation of translation. Int J Mol Sci 14(3):4400–4418</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23439549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3634407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma B, Ponnuswamy A, Gnanasundram SV, Das S (2011) Cryptic AUG is important for 48S ribosomal assembly during internal initiation of translation of coxsackievirus B3 RNA. J Gen Virol 92:1–10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lulla V, Dinan AM, Hosmillo M et al (2019) An upstream protein-coding region in enteroviruses modulates virus infection in gut epithelial cells. Nat Microbiol 4(2):280–292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30478287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lòpez de Quinto S, Martìnez-Salas E (2000) Interaction of the eIF4G initiation factor with the aphthovirus IRES is essential for internal initiation of translation in vivo. RNA 6:1380–1392</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11073214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">1370009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lòpez de Quinto S, Saiz M, de la Morena D, Sobrino F, Martinez-Salas E (2002) IRES-driven translation is stimulated separately by the FMDV 3′-NCR and poly (A) sequences. Nucleic Acids Res 30(20):4398–4405</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12384586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">137133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chomczynski P, Sacchi N (1987) Single-step method of RNA isolation by acid guanidium thiocyanate-phenol-choroform extraction. Anal Biochem 162(1):156–159</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2440339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brenda L-U, Yazmin F, Magdalena S-P-O, Marcelo L-L (2022) RNA-binding proteins as regulators of internal initiation of viral mRNA translation. Viruses 19(2):188–194</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Semler BL (2004) Poliovirus proves IRES-istible in vivo. J Clin Invest 113(12):1678–1681</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15199401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">420512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willian S, Tracy S, Chapman N et al (2000) Mutations in a conserved enteroviral RNA oligonucleotide sequence affect positive strand viral RNA synthesis. Arch Virol 145(10):2061–2086</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11087092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradrick SS, Dobrikova EY, Kaiser C, Shveygert M, Gromeier M (2007) Poly(A)-binding protein is differentially required for translation mediated by viral internal ribosome entry sites. RNA 103(9):1582–1593</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernandez G (2008) Was the initiation of translation in early eukaryotes IRES driven? Trends Biochem Sci 33(2):58–64</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18242094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozano G, Martinez-Salas E (2015) Structural insights into viral IRES-dependent translation mechanisms. Curr Opin Virol 12:113–120</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26004307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang D, Wilson JE, Anderson DR et al (1997) In vitro mutational and inhibitory analysis of the cis-acting translational elements within the5′ untranslated region of coxsackievirus B3: potential targets for antiviral action of antisense oligomers. J Virol 228(1):63–73</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Carthy CM, Cheung P et al (1999) Structural and functional analysis of the 5′-untranslated region of coxsackievirus B3 RNA: in vivo translational and infectivity studies of full-length mutants. J Virol 265(2):206–217</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samantha L, Flynn ME, Katherine R, Manuel A (2021) RNA binding proteins as pioneer determinants of infection: protective, proviral, or both? Viruses 13(11):2172–2179</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trevor RS, Irina SA, Tatyana VP, Christopher UTH (2014) The mechanism of translation initiation on Type 1 picornavirus IRESs. EMBO J 33(1):76–92</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ming-Chih L, Han-Hsiang C, Peng X, Robert YLW (2020) Translation control of enterovirus A71 gene expression. Biomed Sci 27(1):22–29</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharyya S, Das S (2005) Mapping of secondary structure of the spacer region within the 5′-untranslated region of the coxsackievirus B3 RNA: possible role of an apical GAGA loop in binding La protein and influencing internal initiation of translation. Vir Res 108(1–2):89–100</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray PS, Das S (2002) La autoantigen is required for the interna lribosome entry site-mediated translation of coxsackievirus B3 RNA. Nuc Ac Res 30(20):4500–4508</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma B, Bhattacharyya S, Das S (2010) Polypyrimidine tract binding protein interacts with coxsackievirus B3 RNA and influences its translation. J Gen Virol 91(5):1245–1255</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20071487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zell R, Ihle Y, Seitz S, Guondel U, Wutzler P, Goorlach MM (2008) Poly(rC)-binding protein 2 interacts with the oligo(rC) tract of coxsackievirus B3. Bio Chem Biophys Res Commun 366(4):917–921</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>