<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36154273</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2165-0497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbiology spectrum</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microbiol Spectr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multiplex PCR Detection of Respiratory Tract Infections in SARS-CoV-2-Negative Patients Admitted to the Emergency Department: an International Multicenter Study during the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0236822</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0236822</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e02368-22</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/spectrum.02368-22</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Respiratory tract infection (RTI) is a common cause of visits to the hospital emergency department. During the ongoing coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), nonpharmaceutical intervention has influenced the rates of circulating respiratory viruses. In this study, we sought to detect RTI etiological agents other than SARS-CoV-2 in emergency department patients from 13 countries in Europe, the Middle East, and Africa from December 2020 to March 2021. We sought to measure the impact of patient characteristics and national-level behavioral restrictions on the positivity rate for RTI agents. Using the BioFire Respiratory Panel 2.0 Plus, 1,334 nasopharyngeal swabs from patients with RTI symptoms who were negative for SARS-CoV-2 were tested. The rate of positivity for viral or bacterial targets was 36.3%. Regarding viral targets, human rhinovirus or enterovirus was the most prevalent (56.5%), followed by human coronaviruses (11.0%) and adenoviruses (9.9%). Interestingly, age stratification showed that the positivity rate was significantly higher in the children's group than in the adults' group (68.8% versus 28.2%). In particular, human rhinovirus or enterovirus, the respiratory syncytial virus, and other viruses, such as the human metapneumovirus, were more frequently detected in children than in adults. A logistic regression model was also used to determine an association between the rate of positivity for viral agents with each country's behavioral restrictions or with patients' age and sex. Despite the impact of behavioral restrictions, various RTI pathogens were actively circulating, particularly in children, across the 13 countries. <b>IMPORTANCE</b> As SARS-CoV-2 has dominated the diagnostic strategies for RTIs during the current COVID-19 pandemic situation, our data provide evidence that a variety of RTI pathogens may be circulating in each of the 13 countries included in the study. It is now plausible that the COVID-19 pandemic will one day move forward to endemicity. Our study illustrates the potential utility of detecting respiratory pathogens other than SARS-CoV-2 in patients who are admitted to the emergency department for RTI symptoms. Knowing if a symptomatic patient is solely infected by an RTI pathogen or coinfected with SARS-CoV-2 may drive timely and appropriate clinical decision-making, especially in the emergency department setting.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Duclos</LastName><ForeName>Maelys</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>bioMérieux, Marcy l'Étoile, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Hommel</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>bioMérieux, Marcy l'Étoile, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Allantaz</LastName><ForeName>Florence</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>bioMérieux, Marcy l'Étoile, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Powell</LastName><ForeName>Michaela</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>bioMérieux Inc., Salt Lake City, Utah, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Posteraro</LastName><ForeName>Brunella</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1663-7546</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Chirurgiche, Fondazione Policlinico Universitario A. Gemelli IRCCS, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Sanguinetti</LastName><ForeName>Maurizio</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9780-7059</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dipartimento di Scienze di Laboratorio e Infettivologiche, Fondazione Policlinico Universitario A. Gemelli IRCCS, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016448">Multicenter Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Microbiol Spectr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101634614</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2165-0497</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060885" MajorTopicYN="N">Multiplex Polymerase Chain Reaction</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004636" MajorTopicYN="N">Emergency Service, Hospital</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">emergency department</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiplex PCR assay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory tract infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral infection</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare a conflict of interest. M.D., B.H., F.A., and M.P. are employees of bioMérieux; the other authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36154273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9603986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.02368-22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>GBD 2016 Lower Respiratory Infections Collaborators. 2018. Estimates of the global, regional, and national morbidity, mortality, and aetiologies of lower respiratory infections in 195 countries, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. Lancet Infect Dis 18:1191–1210. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30310-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30310-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6202443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30243584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas M, Bomar PA. 2022. Upper respiratory tract infection. StatPearls Publishing, Treasure Island, FL. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30422556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30422556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafei K, Lichenstein R. 2006. Airway infectious disease emergencies. Pediatr Clin North Am 53:215–242. doi:10.1016/j.pcl.2005.10.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pcl.2005.10.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16574523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu B, Guo H, Zhou P, Shi ZL. 2021. Characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19. Nat Rev Microbiol 19:141–154. doi:10.1038/s41579-020-00459-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-00459-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7537588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33024307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosch AA, Biesbroek G, Trzcinski K, Sanders EA, Bogaert D. 2013. Viral and bacterial interactions in the upper respiratory tract. PLoS Pathog 9:e1003057. doi:10.1371/journal.ppat.1003057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3542149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23326226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hodinka RL. 2016. Respiratory RNA viruses. Microbiol Spectr 4. doi:10.1128/microbiolspec.DMIH2-0028-2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.DMIH2-0028-2016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27726802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matienzo N, Youssef MM, Comito D, Lane B, Ligon C, Morita H, Winchester A, Decker ME, Dayan P, Shopsin B, Shaman J. 2021. Respiratory viruses in pediatric emergency department patients and their family members. Influenza Other Respir Viruses 15:91–98. doi:10.1111/irv.12789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/irv.12789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7767945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33210476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamrani Hanchi A, Guennouni M, Rachidi M, Benhoumich T, Bennani H, Bourrous M, Maoulainine FMR, Younous S, Bouskraoui M, Soraa N. 2021. Epidemiology of respiratory pathogens in children with severe acute respiratory infection and impact of the multiplex PCR film array respiratory panel: a 2-year study. Int J Microbiol 2021:2274261. doi:10.1155/2021/2276261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2021/2276261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8741400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35003265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lumley SF, Richens N, Lees E, Cregan J, Kalimeris E, Oakley S, Morgan M, Segal S, Dawson M, Walker AS, Eyre DW, Crook DW, Beer S, Novak A, Stoesser NE, Matthews PC. 2022. Changes in paediatric respiratory infections at a UK teaching hospital 2016–2021; impact of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. J Infect 84:40–47. doi:10.1016/j.jinf.2021.10.022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2021.10.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8591975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34757137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomez GB, Mahe C, Chaves SS. 2021. Uncertain effects of the pandemic on respiratory viruses. Science 372:1043–1044. doi:10.1126/science.abh3986.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abh3986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34083477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawrocki J, Olin K, Holdrege MC, Hartsell J, Meyers L, Cox C, Powell M, Cook CV, Jones J, Robbins T, Hemmert A, Ginocchio CC. 2021. The effects of social distancing policies on non-SARS-CoV-2 respiratory pathogens. Open Forum Infect Dis 8:ofab133. doi:10.1093/ofid/ofab133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofab133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7989184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34322558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sreenath K, Batra P, Vinayaraj EV, Bhatia R, SaiKiran K, Singh V, Singh S, Verma N, Singh UB, Mohan A, Bhatnagar S, Trikha A, Guleria R, Chaudhry R. 2021. Coinfections with other respiratory pathogens among patients with COVID-19. Microbiol Spectr 9:e0016321. doi:10.1128/Spectrum.00163-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/Spectrum.00163-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8552727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34287033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Lu R, Shen J, Xie Z, Liu G, Tan W. 2019. Comparison of viral and epidemiological profiles of hospitalized children with severe acute respiratory infection in Beijing and Shanghai, China. BMC Infect Dis 19:729. doi:10.1186/s12879-019-4385-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-4385-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6701130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31429710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Tao Y, Tang M, Du B, Xia Y, Mo X, Cao Q. 2018. Rapid detection of respiratory organisms with the FilmArray respiratory panel in a large children's hospital in China. BMC Infect Dis 18:510. doi:10.1186/s12879-018-3429-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-018-3429-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6180626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30305033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen S, Lv F, Chen X, Zhu L, Li H, Lin L, Zhang H. 2019. Application of a nucleic acid-based multiplex kit to identify viral and atypical bacterial aetiology of lower respiratory tract infection in hospitalized children. J Med Microbiol 68:1211–1218. doi:10.1099/jmm.0.001006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.001006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31225788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinonen S, Rodriguez-Fernandez R, Diaz A, Oliva Rodriguez-Pastor S, Ramilo O, Mejias A. 2019. Infant immune response to respiratory viral infections. Immunol Allergy Clin North Am 39:361–376. doi:10.1016/j.iac.2019.03.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.iac.2019.03.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6625527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31284926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wishaupt JO, van der Ploeg T, de Groot R, Versteegh FG, Hartwig NG. 2017. Single- and multiple viral respiratory infections in children: disease and management cannot be related to a specific pathogen. BMC Infect Dis 17:62. doi:10.1186/s12879-016-2118-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-016-2118-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5225597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28077074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehder KJ, Wilson EA, Zimmerman KO, Cunningham CK, Turner DA. 2015. Detection of multiple respiratory viruses associated with mortality and severity of illness in children. Pediatr Crit Care Med 16:e201–e206. doi:10.1097/PCC.0000000000000492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PCC.0000000000000492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4560664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26121097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asner SA, Rose W, Petrich A, Richardson S, Tran DJ. 2015. Is virus coinfection a predictor of severity in children with viral respiratory infections? Clin Microbiol Infect 21:264.e1–264.e6. doi:10.1016/j.cmi.2014.08.024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2014.08.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7128494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25596778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi T, McLean K, Campbell H, Nair H. 2015. Aetiological role of common respiratory viruses in acute lower respiratory infections in children under five years: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Glob Health 5:e010408. doi:10.7189/jogh.05.010408.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7189/jogh.05.010408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4593292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26445672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohns Vasconcelos M, Loens K, Sigfrid L, Iosifidis E, Epalza C, Donà D, Matheeussen V, Papachristou S, Roilides E, Gijon M, Rojo P, Minotti C, Da Dalt L, Islam S, Jarvis J, Syggelou A, Tsolia M, Nyirenda Nyang’wa M, Keers S, Renk H, Gemmel A-L, D’Amore C, Ciofi degli Atti M, Rodríguez-Tenreiro Sánchez C, Martinón-Torres F, Burokienė S, Goetghebuer T, Spoulou V, Riordan A, Calvo C, Gkentzi D, Hufnagel M, Openshaw PJ, de Jong MD, Koopmans M, Goossens H, Ieven M, Fraaij PLA, Giaquinto C, Bielicki JA, Horby P, Sharland M. 2021. Aetiology of acute respiratory infection in preschool children requiring hospitalisation in Europe: results from the PED-MERMAIDS multicentre case-control study. BMJ Open Resp Res 8:e000887. doi:10.1136/bmjresp-2021-000887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2021-000887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8323363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34326154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh EE, Hall CB. 2015. Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), p 1948–1960. In Bennett JE, Dolin R, Blaser MJ (ed), Mandell, Douglas, and Bennett's Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases, 3rd ed. WB Saunders, Philadelphia, PA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massey BW, Jayathilake K, Meltzer HY. 2020. Respiratory microbial co-infection with SARS-CoV-2. Front Microbiol 11:2079. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2020.02079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.02079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7477285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32983056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrarca L, Nenna R, Frassanito A, Pierangeli A, Di Mattia G, Scagnolari C, Midulla F. 2020. Human bocavirus in children hospitalized for acute respiratory tract infection in Rome. World J Pediatr 16:293–298. doi:10.1007/s12519-019-00324-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12519-019-00324-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7091143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31776891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control. 2021. Seasonal influenza. Annual epidemiological report for 2020–2021. https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/seasonal-influenza-annual-epidemiological-report-2020-2021. Accessed 23 June 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization. 2022. Epidemic diseases: flu. https://ais.paho.org/phip/viz/ed_flu.asp. Accessed 23 June 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hale T, Angrist N, Goldszmidt R, Kira B, Petherick A, Phillips T, Webster S, Cameron-Blake E, Hallas L, Majumdar S, Tatlow H. 2021. A global panel database of pandemic policies (Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker). Nat Hum Behav 5:529–538. doi:10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33686204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tempia S, Walaza S, Bhiman JN, McMorrow ML, Moyes J, Mkhencele T, Meiring S, Quan V, Bishop K, McAnerney JM, von Gottberg A, Wolter N, Du Plessis M, Treurnicht FK, Hellferscee O, Dawood H, Naby F, Variava E, Siwele C, Baute N, Nel J, Reubenson G, Zar HJ, Cohen C. 2021. Decline of influenza and respiratory syncytial virus detection in facility-based surveillance during the COVID-19 pandemic, South Africa, January to October 2020. Euro Surveill 26:2001600. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2021.26.29.2001600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2021.26.29.2001600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8299743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34296675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arsene S, Couty C, Faddeenkov I, Go N, Granjeon-Noriot S, Smit D, Kahoul R, Illigens B, Boissel JP, Chevalier A, Lehr L, Pasquali C, Kulesza A. 2022. Modeling the disruption of respiratory disease clinical trials by non-pharmaceutical COVID-19 interventions. Nat Commun 13:1980. doi:10.1038/s41467-022-29534-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-29534-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9008035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35418135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metsalu T, Vilo J. 2015. ClustVis: a web tool for visualizing clustering of multivariate data using principal component analysis and heatmap. Nucleic Acids Res 43:W566–W570. doi:10.1093/nar/gkv46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv46</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4489295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25969447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>