<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36371612</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-1654</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>33</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Reviews in medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Combating coxsackievirus B infections.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2406</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2406</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/rmv.2406</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Coxsackieviruses B (CVB) are small, non-enveloped, single-stranded RNA viruses belonging to the Enterovirus genus of the Picornaviridae family. They are common worldwide and cause a wide variety of human diseases ranging from those having relatively mild symptoms to severe acute and chronic pathologies such as cardiomyopathy and type 1 diabetes. The development of safe and effective strategies to combat these viruses remains a challenge. The present review outlines current approaches to control CVB infections and associated diseases. Various drugs targeting viral or host proteins involved in viral replication as well as vaccines have been developed and shown potential to prevent or combat CVB infections in vitro and in vivo in animal models. Repurposed drugs and alternative strategies targeting miRNAs or based on plant extracts and probiotics and their derivatives have also shown antiviral effects against CVB. In addition, clinical trials with vaccines and drugs are underway and offer hope for the prevention or treatment of CVB-induced diseases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2022 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alhazmi</LastName><ForeName>Abdulaziz</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Université de Lille et CHU de Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microbiology and Parasitology Department, Faculty of Medicine, Jazan University, Jazan, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nekoua</LastName><ForeName>Magloire Pandoua</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2981-0803</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Université de Lille et CHU de Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mercier</LastName><ForeName>Ambroise</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7926-6167</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Université de Lille et CHU de Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vergez</LastName><ForeName>Ines</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Université de Lille et CHU de Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sane</LastName><ForeName>Famara</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Université de Lille et CHU de Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alidjinou</LastName><ForeName>Enagnon Kazali</ForeName><Initials>EK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Université de Lille et CHU de Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hober</LastName><ForeName>Didier</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4301-2074</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Université de Lille et CHU de Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9112448</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1052-9276</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003384" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coxsackievirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003922" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36371612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.2406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H, et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol. 2020;165(3):793-797. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-019-04520-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gold RG. Post-viral pericarditis. Eur Heart J. 1988;9(Suppl G):175-179. https://doi.org/10.1093/eurheartj/9.suppl_g.175</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong AH, Lau CS, Cheng PK, Ng AY, Lim WW. Coxsackievirus B3-associated aseptic meningitis: an emerging infection in Hong Kong. J Med Virol. 2011;83(3):483-489. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.21998</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marier R, Rodriguez W, Chloupek RJ, et al. Coxsackievirus B5 infection and aseptic meningitis in neonates and children. Am J Dis Child. 1975;129(3):321-325. https://doi.org/10.1001/archpedi.1975.02120400031007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papa A, Dumaidi K, Franzidou F, Antoniadis A. Genetic variation of coxsackie virus B5 strains associated with aseptic meningitis in Greece. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2006;12(7):688-691. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-0691.2006.01476.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhazmi A, Lazrek M, Alidjinou EK, Descombes G, Engelmann I, Hober D. Paediatric enterovirus meningitis without cerebrospinal fluid pleocytosis. J Infect. 2019;79(6):612-625. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2019.11.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson CC, Rich SS. Genetics of type 1 diabetes. Curr Opin Genet Dev. 2018;50:7-16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gde.2018.01.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jerram ST, Leslie RD. The genetic architecture of type 1 diabetes. Genes. 2017;8(8):209. https://doi.org/10.3390/genes8080209</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhazmi A, Sane F, Lazrek M, et al. Enteroviruses and type 1 diabetes mellitus: an overlooked relationship in some regions. Microorganisms. 2020;8(10):1458. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms8101458</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeung WC, Rawlinson WD, Craig ME. Enterovirus infection and type 1 diabetes mellitus: systematic review and meta-analysis of observational molecular studies. BMJ. 2011;342(feb03 1):d35. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.d35</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, Ye F, Chen Y, et al. Association between enterovirus infection and type 1 diabetes risk: a meta-analysis of 38 case-control studies. Front Endocrinol. 2021;12:706964. https://doi.org/10.3389/fendo.2021.706964</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilonen J, Lempainen J, Veijola R. The heterogeneous pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes mellitus. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2019;15(11):635-650. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574-019-0254-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isaacs SR, Foskett DB, Maxwell AJ, et al. Viruses and type 1 diabetes: from enteroviruses to the virome. Microorganisms. 2021;9(7):1519. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms9071519</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hober D, Sane F. Enteroviral pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes. Discov Med. 2010;10(51):151-160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman NM, Kim KS. Persistent coxsackievirus infection: enterovirus persistence in chronic myocarditis and dilated cardiomyopathy. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol. 2008;323:275-292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman NM, Kim KS, Drescher KM, Oka K, Tracy S. 5' terminal deletions in the genome of a coxsackievirus B2 strain occurred naturally in human heart. Virology. 2008;375(2):480-491. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2008.02.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tam PE, Messner RP. Molecular mechanisms of coxsackievirus persistence in chronic inflammatory myopathy: viral RNA persists through formation of a double-stranded complex without associated genomic mutations or evolution. J Virol. 1999;73(12):10113-10121. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.73.12.10113-10121.1999</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chehadeh W, Kerr-Conte J, Pattou F, et al. Persistent infection of human pancreatic islets by coxsackievirus B is associated with alpha interferon synthesis in beta cells. J Virol. 2000;74(21):10153-10164. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.74.21.10153-10164.2000</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Sané F, Engelmann I, Geenen V, Hober D. Enterovirus persistence as a mechanism in the pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes. Discov Med. 2014;18(100):273-282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sane F, Caloone D, Gmyr V, et al. Coxsackievirus B4 can infect human pancreas ductal cells and persist in ductal-like cell cultures which results in inhibition of Pdx1 expression and disturbed formation of islet-like cell aggregates. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2013;70(21):4169-4180. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-013-1383-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertin A, Sane F, Gmyr V, et al. Coxsackievirus-B4 infection of human primary pancreatic ductal cell cultures results in impairment of differentiation into insulin-producing cells. Viruses. 2019;11(7):597. https://doi.org/10.3390/v11070597</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van der Linden L, Wolthers KC, van Kuppeveld FJ. Replication and inhibitors of enteroviruses and parechoviruses. Viruses. 2015;7(8):4529-4562. https://doi.org/10.3390/v7082832</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerba CP, Gramos DM, Nwachuku N. Comparative inactivation of enteroviruses and adenovirus 2 by UV light. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2002;68(10):5167-5169. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.68.10.5167-5169.2002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meister S, Verbyla ME, Klinger M, Kohn T. Variability in disinfection resistance between currently circulating enterovirus B serotypes and strains. Environ Sci Technol. 2018;52(6):3696-3705. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.8b00851</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Firquet S, Beaujard S, Lobert PE, et al. Viruses contained in droplets applied on warmed surface are rapidly inactivated. Microbes Environ. 2014;29(4):408-412. https://doi.org/10.1264/jsme2.me14108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kibbee R, Örmeci B. Peracetic acid (PAA) and low-pressure ultraviolet (LP-UV) inactivation of Coxsackievirus B3 (CVB3) in municipal wastewater individually and concurrently. Water Res. 2020;183:116048. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2020.116048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Firquet S, Beaujard S, Lobert PE, et al. Survival of enveloped and non-enveloped viruses on inanimate surfaces. Microbes Environ. 2015;30(2):140-144. https://doi.org/10.1264/jsme2.me14145</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torii S, Miura F, Itamochi M, Haga K, Katayama K, Katayama H. Impact of the heterogeneity in free chlorine, UV. Environ Sci Technol. 2021;55(5):3156-3164. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.0c07796</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engelbrecht RS, Weber MJ, Salter BL, Schmidt CA. Comparative inactivation of viruses by chlorine. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1980;40(2):249-256. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.40.2.249-256.1980</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cromeans TL, Kahler AM, Hill VR. Inactivation of adenoviruses, enteroviruses, and murine norovirus in water by free chlorine and monochloramine. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2010;76(4):1028-1033. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.01342-09</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali MA. Ultraviolet, chlorine and ozone disinfection of some enteroviruses in drinking water and treated effluents. J Egypt Publ Health Assoc. 1997;72(3-4):411-423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jensen H, Thomas K, Sharp DG. Inactivation of coxsackieviruses B3 and B5 in water by chlorine. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1980;40(3):633-640. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.40.3.633-640.1980</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Payment P, Tremblay M, Trudel M. Relative resistance to chlorine of poliovirus and coxsackievirus isolates from environmental sources and drinking water. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1985;49(4):981-983. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.49.4.981-983.1985</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Black S, Thurston JA, Gerba CP. Determination of Ct values for chlorine of resistant enteroviruses. J Environ Sci Health A Tox Hazard Subst Environ Eng. 2009;44(4):336-339. https://doi.org/10.1080/10934520802659653</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolf C, von Gunten U, Kohn T. Kinetics of inactivation of waterborne enteric viruses by ozone. Environ Sci Technol. 2018;52(4):2170-2177. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b05111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang XC, Qiu FG, Xue XP, Lu X. Application of a virological tracer method for the assessment of pathogen removal by physicochemical treatment and chemical disinfection. Water Sci Technol. 2005;52(8):205-512. https://doi.org/10.2166/wst.2005.0265</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thevenin T, Lobert PE, Hober D. Inactivation of coxsackievirus B4, feline calicivirus and herpes simplex virus type 1: unexpected virucidal effect of a disinfectant on a non-enveloped virus applied onto a surface. Intervirology. 2013;56(4):224-230. https://doi.org/10.1159/000350556</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drulak M, Wallbank AM, Lebtag I, Werboski L, Poffenroth L. The relative effectiveness of commonly used disinfectants in inactivation of coxsackievirus B5. J Hyg. 1978;81(3):389-397. https://doi.org/10.1017/s0022172400025274</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thraenhart O, Kuwert E. [Virucidal efficacy of a chemical instrument surface disinfectant ("Gigasept") against coxsackie virus type B3. II. Investigation in the instrumental surface test (author's transl)]. Zentralbl Bakteriol Orig B. 1977;164(1-2):22-44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaiser L, Crump CE, Hayden FG. In vitro activity of pleconaril and AG7088 against selected serotypes and clinical isolates of human rhinoviruses. Antivir Res. 2000;47(3):215-220. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0166-3542(00)00106-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pevear DC, Tull TM, Seipel ME, Groarke JM. Activity of pleconaril against enteroviruses. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1999;43(9):2109-2115. https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.43.9.2109</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers JM, Diana GD, McKinlay MA. Pleconaril. A broad spectrum antipicornaviral agent. Adv Exp Med Biol. 1999;458:69-76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Florea NR, Maglio D, Nicolau DP. Pleconaril, a novel antipicornaviral agent. Pharmacotherapy. 2003;23(3):339-348. https://doi.org/10.1592/phco.23.3.339.32099</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero JR. Pleconaril: a novel antipicornaviral drug. Expet Opin Invest Drugs. 2001;10(2):369-379. https://doi.org/10.1517/13543784.10.2.369</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidtke M, Wutzler P, Zieger R, Riabova OB, Makarov VA. New pleconaril and [(biphenyloxy)propyl]isoxazole derivatives with substitutions in the central ring exhibit antiviral activity against pleconaril-resistant coxsackievirus B3. Antivir Res. 2009;81(1):56-63. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2008.09.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honkimaa A, Sioofy-Khojine AB, Oikarinen S, Bertin A, Hober D, Hyöty H. Eradication of persistent coxsackievirus B infection from a pancreatic cell line with clinically used antiviral drugs. J Clin Virol. 2020;128:104334. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2020.104334</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thibaut HJ, De Palma AM, Neyts J. Combating enterovirus replication: state-of-the-art on antiviral research. Biochem Pharmacol. 2012;83(2):185-192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2011.08.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotbart HA, Webster AD. Treatment of potentially life-threatening enterovirus infections with pleconaril. Clin Infect Dis. 2001;32(2):228-235. https://doi.org/10.1086/318452</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senior K. FDA panel rejects common cold treatment. Lancet Infect Dis. 2002;2(5):264. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1473-3099(02)00277-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Cloud G, Bradley J, et al. Double blind placebo-controlled trial of pleconaril in infants with enterovirus meningitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2003;22(4):335-341. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.inf.0000059765.92623.70</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wildenbeest JG, van den Broek PJ, Benschop KS, et al. Pleconaril revisited: clinical course of chronic enteroviral meningoencephalitis after treatment correlates with in vitro susceptibility. Antivir Ther. 2012;17(3):459-466. https://doi.org/10.3851/imp1936</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sioofy-Khojine AB, Honkimaa A, Hyöty H. A preclinical assessment to repurpose drugs to target type 1 diabetes-associated type B coxsackieviruses. Diabet Med. 2020;37(11):1849-1853. https://doi.org/10.1111/dme.14175</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egorova A, Kazakova E, Jahn B, Ekins S, Makarov V, Schmidtke M. Novel pleconaril derivatives: influence of substituents in the isoxazole and phenyl rings on the antiviral activity against enteroviruses. Eur J Med Chem. 2020;188:112007. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2019.112007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egorova A, Ekins S, Schmidtke M, Makarov V. Back to the future: advances in development of broad-spectrum capsid-binding inhibitors of enteroviruses. Eur J Med Chem. 2019;178:606-622. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2019.06.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crotty S, Maag D, Arnold JJ, et al. The broad-spectrum antiviral ribonucleoside ribavirin is an RNA virus mutagen. Nat Med. 2000;6(12):1375-1379. https://doi.org/10.1038/82191</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaucourt S, Vignuzzi M. Ribavirin: a drug active against many viruses with multiple effects on virus replication and propagation. Molecular basis of ribavirin resistance. Curr Opin Virol. 2014;8:10-15. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coviro.2014.04.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heim A, Grumbach I, Pring-Akerblom P, et al. Inhibition of coxsackievirus B3 carrier state infection of cultured human myocardial fibroblasts by ribavirin and human natural interferon-alpha. Antivir Res. 1997;34(3):101-111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Diabetes Virus Detection and Intervention Trial (DiViDIntervention). Accessed August 12, 2022. https://www.clinicaltrialsregister.eu/ctr-search/search?query=2015-003350-41</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hulsebosch BM, Mounce BC. Polyamine analog diethylnorspermidine restricts coxsackievirus B3 and is overcome by 2A protease mutation in vitro. Viruses. 2021;13(2):310. https://doi.org/10.3390/v13020310</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulferts R, de Boer SM, van der Linden L, et al. Screening of a library of FDA-approved drugs identifies several enterovirus replication inhibitors that target viral protein 2C. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2016;60(5):2627-2638. https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.02182-15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks MJ, Sasadeusz JJ, Tannock GA. Antiviral chemotherapeutic agents against respiratory viruses: where are we now and what's in the pipeline? Curr Opin Pulm Med. 2004;10(3):197-203. https://doi.org/10.1097/00063198-200405000-00009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arbidol. Drugs R 1999;2(3):171-172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong Q, Yang Z, Liu Y, et al. Antiviral activity of Arbidol against Coxsackie virus B5 in vitro and in vivo. Arch Virol. 2009;154(4):601-607. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-009-0346-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye W, Yao M, Dong Y, et al. Remdesivir (GS-5734) impedes enterovirus replication through viral RNA synthesis inhibition. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:1105. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2020.621197</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furuta Y, Komeno T, Nakamura T. Favipiravir (T-705), a broad spectrum inhibitor of viral RNA polymerase. Proc Jpn Acad Ser B Phys Biol Sci. 2017;93(7):449-463. https://doi.org/10.2183/pjab.93.027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanke K, Krenn BM, Melchers WJG, Seipelt J, van Kuppeveld FJM. PDTC inhibits picornavirus polyprotein processing and RNA replication by transporting zinc ions into cells. J Gen Virol. 2007;88(Pt 4):1206-1217. https://doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.82634-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Si X, McManus BM, Zhang J, et al. Pyrrolidine dithiocarbamate reduces coxsackievirus B3 replication through inhibition of the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway. J Virol. 2005;79(13):8014-8023. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.79.13.8014-8023.2005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andries K, Dewindt B, Snoeks J, et al. In vitro activity of pirodavir (R 77975), a substituted phenoxy-pyridazinamine with broad-spectrum antipicornaviral activity. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1992;36(1):100-107. https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.36.1.100</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacroix C, Laconi S, Angius F, et al. In vitro characterisation of a pleconaril/pirodavir-like compound with potent activity against rhinoviruses. Virol J. 2015;14(1):106. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12985-015-0330-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makarov VA, Braun H, Richter M, et al. Pyrazolopyrimidines: potent inhibitors targeting the capsid of rhino- and enteroviruses. ChemMedChem. 2015;10(10):1629-1634. https://doi.org/10.1002/cmdc.201500304</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manganaro R, Zonsics B, Bauer L, et al. Synthesis and antiviral effect of novel fluoxetine analogues as enterovirus 2C inhibitors. Antivir Res. 2020;178:104781. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104781</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuo J, Quinn KK, Kye S, Cooper P, Damoiseaux R, Krogstad P. Fluoxetine is a potent inhibitor of coxsackievirus replication. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2012;56(9):4838-4844. https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.00983-12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer L, Manganaro R, Zonsics B, et al. Fluoxetine inhibits enterovirus replication by targeting the viral 2C protein in a stereospecific manner. ACS Infect Dis. 2019;5(9):1609-1623. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsinfecdis.9b00179</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Engelmann I, Bossu J, et al. Persistence of Coxsackievirus B4 in pancreatic ductal-like cells results in cellular and viral changes. Virulence. 2017;8(7):1229-1244. https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2017.1284735</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Sané F, Bertin A, Caloone D, Hober D. Persistent infection of human pancreatic cells with Coxsackievirus B4 is cured by fluoxetine. Antivir Res. 2015;116:51-54. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2015.01.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Bertin A, Sane F, Caloone D, Engelmann I, Hober D. Emergence of fluoxetine-resistant variants during treatment of human pancreatic cell cultures persistently infected with coxsackievirus B4. Viruses. 2019;11(6):486. https://doi.org/10.3390/v11060486</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benkahla MA, Alidjinou EK, Sane F, Desailloud R, Hober D. Fluoxetine can inhibit coxsackievirus-B4 E2 in vitro and in vivo. Antivir Res. 2018;159:130-133. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.10.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gofshteyn J, Cárdenas AM, Bearden D. Treatment of chronic enterovirus encephalitis with fluoxetine in a patient with X-linked agammaglobulinemia. Pediatr Neurol. 2016;64:94-98. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2016.06.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Q, Yuan S, Zhang C, et al. Discovery of itraconazole with broad-spectrum in vitro antienterovirus activity that targets nonstructural protein 3A. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2015;59(5):2654-2665. https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.05108-14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang Q, Li S, Du L, et al. Emetine protects mice from enterovirus infection by inhibiting viral translation. Antivir Res. 2020;173:104650. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2019.104650</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gielen V, Johnston SL, Edwards MR. Azithromycin induces anti-viral responses in bronchial epithelial cells. Eur Respir J. 2010;36(3):646-654. https://doi.org/10.1183/09031936.00095809</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schögler A, Kopf BS, Edwards MR, et al. Novel antiviral properties of azithromycin in cystic fibrosis airway epithelial cells. Eur Respir J. 2015;45(2):428-439. https://doi.org/10.1183/09031936.00102014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng S, Meng X, Huang Q, et al. Spiramycin and azithromycin, safe for administration to children, exert antiviral activity against enterovirus A71 in vitro and in vivo. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2019;53(4):362-369. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2018.12.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werner B, Dittmann S, Funke C, et al. Effect of lovastatin on coxsackievirus B3 infection in human endothelial cells. Inflamm Res. 2014;63(4):267-276. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00011-013-0695-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams P, Kandiah E, Effantin G, Steven AC, Ehrenfeld E. Poliovirus 2C protein forms homo-oligomeric structures required for ATPase activity. J Biol Chem. 2009;284(33):22012-22021. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.m109.031807</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeghipour S, Bek EJ, McMinn PC. Selection and characterisation of guanidine-resistant mutants of human enterovirus 71. Virus Res. 2012;169(1):72-79. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virusres.2012.07.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sane F, Alidjinou EK, Kacet N, et al. Human milk can neutralize Coxsackievirus B4 in vitro. J Med Virol. 2013;85(5):880-887. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.23518</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seganti L, Di Biase AM, Marchetti M, Pietrantoni A, Tinari A, Superti F. Antiviral activity of lactoferrin towards naked viruses. Biometals. 2004;17(3):295-299. https://doi.org/10.1023/b:biom.0000027708.27142.bc</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denani CB, Real-Hohn A, de Carvalho CAM, Gomes AMO, Gonçalves RB. Lactoferrin affects rhinovirus B-14 entry into H1-HeLa cells. Arch Virol. 2021;166(4):1203-1211. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-021-04993-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim MJ, Lee DK, Park JE, Park IH, Seo JG, Ha NJ. Antiviral activity of. Biotechnol Biotechnol Equip. 2014;28(4):681-688. https://doi.org/10.1080/13102818.2014.945237</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Kfoury KA, Romond MB, Scuotto A, et al. Bifidobacteria-derived lipoproteins inhibit infection with coxsackievirus B4 in vitro. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2017;50(2):177-185. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2017.03.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arena MP, Elmastour F, Sane F, et al. Inhibition of coxsackievirus B4 by Lactobacillus plantarum. Microbiol Res. 2018;210:59-64. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micres.2018.03.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh SF, Rezaee R, Mehmandoust M, Badibostan H, Karimi G. Assessment of in vitro bioactivities of Pis v 1 (2S albumin) and Pis v 2.0101 (11S globulin) proteins derived from pistachio (Pistacia vera L.). Food Measure. 2020;14(2):1054-1063. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11694-019-00355-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Wei F, Chen LJ, et al. In vitro and in vivo studies of the inhibitory effects of emodin isolated from Polygonum cuspidatum on Coxsakievirus B₄. Molecules. 2013;18(10):11842-11858. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules181011842</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badia-Boungou F, Sane F, Alidjinou EK, et al. Aqueous extracts of Syzygium brazzavillense can inhibit the infection with coxsackievirus B4 in vitro. J Med Virol. 2019;91(7):1210-1216. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.25436</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galochkina AV, Zarubaev VV, Kiselev OI, Babkin VA, Ostroukhova LA. Antiviral activity of the dihydroquercetin during the coxsackievirus B4 replication in vitro. Vopr Virusol. 2016;61(1):27-31. https://doi.org/10.18821/0507-4088-2016-61-1-27-31</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galochkina AV, Anikin VB, Babkin VA, Ostrouhova LA, Zarubaev VV. Virus-inhibiting activity of dihydroquercetin, a flavonoid from Larix sibirica, against coxsackievirus B4 in a model of viral pancreatitis. Arch Virol. 2016;161(4):929-938. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-016-2749-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Si X, Wang Y, Wong J, Zhang J, McManus BM, Luo H. Dysregulation of the ubiquitin-proteasome system by curcumin suppresses coxsackievirus B3 replication. J Virol. 2007;81(7):3142-3150. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.02028-06</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y, Ge W, Cai H, Zhang H. Curcumin protects mice from coxsackievirus B3-induced myocarditis by inhibiting the phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase/Akt/nuclear factor-κB pathway. J Cardiovasc Pharmacol Ther. 2013;18(6):560-569. https://doi.org/10.1177/1074248413503044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krenn BM, Gaudernak E, Holzer B, Lanke K, Van Kuppeveld FJ, Seipelt J. Antiviral activity of the zinc ionophores pyrithione and hinokitiol against picornavirus infections. J Virol. 2009;83(1):58-64. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.01543-08</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reshamwala D, Shroff S, Sheik Amamuddy O, et al. Polyphenols Epigallocatechin gallate and resveratrol, and polyphenol-functionalized nanoparticles prevent enterovirus infection through clustering and stabilization of the viruses. Pharmaceutics. 2021;13(8):1182. https://doi.org/10.3390/pharmaceutics13081182</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song X, Liu Z, Wang H, et al. QiHong prevents death in coxsackievirus B3 induced murine myocarditis through inhibition of virus attachment and penetration. Exp Biol Med. 2007;232(11):1441-1448. https://doi.org/10.3181/0704-rm-110</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fengqin L, Yulin W, Xiaoxin Z, et al. The heart-protective mechanism of Qishaowuwei formula on murine viral myocarditis induced by CVB3. J Ethnopharmacol. 2010;127(2):221-228. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2009.11.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yen MH, Lee JJ, Yeh CF, et al. Yakammaoto inhibited human coxsackievirus B4 (CVB4)-induced airway and renal tubular injuries by preventing viral attachment, internalization, and replication. J Ethnopharmacol. 2014;151(3):1056-1063. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2013.11.049</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Wang Y, Ren Z, et al. Protective effects of 20(s)-protopanaxtriol on viral myocarditis infected by coxsackievirus B3. Pathobiology. 2012;79(6):285-289. https://doi.org/10.1159/000331229</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu H, Zhang Y, Ye G, Li Z, Zhou P, Huang C. In vivo and in vitro antiviral activities of calycosin-7-O-beta-D-glucopyranoside against coxsackie virus B3. Biol Pharm Bull. 2009;32(1):68-73. https://doi.org/10.1248/bpb.32.68</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song JH, Ahn JH, Kim SR, et al. Manassantin B shows antiviral activity against coxsackievirus B3 infection by activation of the STING/TBK-1/IRF3 signalling pathway. Sci Rep. 2019;9(1):9413. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-45868-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu NY, Ilnytska O, Belov G, et al. Viral reorganization of the secretory pathway generates distinct organelles for RNA replication. Cell. 2010;141(5):799-811. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2010.03.050</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Schaar HM, van der Linden L, Lanke KH, et al. Coxsackievirus mutants that can bypass host factor PI4KIIIβ and the need for high levels of PI4P lipids for replication. Cell Res. 2012;22(11):1576-1592. https://doi.org/10.1038/cr.2012.129</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laajala M, Reshamwala D, Marjomäki V. Therapeutic targets for enterovirus infections. Expert Opin Ther Targets. 2020;24(8):745-757. https://doi.org/10.1080/14728222.2020.1784141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao X, Lei X, Zhang Z, et al. Enterovirus 3A facilitates viral replication by promoting phosphatidylinositol 4-kinase IIIβ-ACBD3 interaction. J Virol. 2017;91(19):e00791-e00817. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.00791-17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison DN, Gazina EV, Purcell DF, Anderson DA, Petrou S. Amiloride derivatives inhibit coxsackievirus B3 RNA replication. J Virol. 2008;82(3):1465-1473. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.01374-07</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strating JR, van der Linden L, Albulescu L, et al. Itraconazole inhibits enterovirus replication by targeting the oxysterol-binding protein. Cell Rep. 2015;10(4):600-615. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2014.12.054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer L, Ferla S, Head SA, et al. Structure-activity relationship study of itraconazole, a broad-range inhibitor of picornavirus replication that targets oxysterol-binding protein (OSBP). Antivir Res. 2018;156:55-63. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.05.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Linden L, van der Schaar HM, Lanke KH, Neyts J, van Kuppeveld FJ. Differential effects of the putative GBF1 inhibitors Golgicide A and AG1478 on enterovirus replication. J Virol. 2010;84(15):7535-7542. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.02684-09</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geller R, Vignuzzi M, Andino R, Frydman J. Evolutionary constraints on chaperone-mediated folding provide an antiviral approach refractory to development of drug resistance. Genes Dev. 2007;21(2):195-205. https://doi.org/10.1101/gad.1505307</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engelmann I, Alidjinou EK, Bertin A, Sane F, Hober D. miRNAs in enterovirus infection. Crit Rev Microbiol. 2018;44(6):701-714. https://doi.org/10.1080/1040841x.2018.1499608</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye X, Liu Z, Hemida MG, Yang D. Targeted delivery of mutant tolerant anti-coxsackievirus artificial microRNAs using folate conjugated bacteriophage Phi29 pRNA. PLoS One. 2011;6(6):e21215. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0021215</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinkert S, Westermann D, Wang X, et al. Prevention of cardiac dysfunction in acute coxsackievirus B3 cardiomyopathy by inducible expression of a soluble coxsackievirus-adenovirus receptor. Circulation. 2009;120(23):2358-2366. https://doi.org/10.1161/circulationaha.108.845339</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stein EA, Pinkert S, Becher PM, et al. Combination of RNA interference and virus receptor trap exerts additive antiviral activity in coxsackievirus B3-induced myocarditis in mice. J Infect Dis. 2015;211(4):613-622. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiu504</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinkert S, Klingel K, Lindig V, et al. Virus-host coevolution in a persistently coxsackievirus B3-infected cardiomyocyte cell line. J Virol. 2011;85(24):13409-13419. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.00621-11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodfellow IG, Evans DJ, Blom AM, et al. Inhibition of coxsackie B virus infection by soluble forms of its receptors: binding affinities, altered particle formation, and competition with cellular receptors. J Virol. 2005;79(18):12016-12024. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.79.18.12016-12024.2005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinkert S, Dieringer B, Diedrich S, Zeichhardt H, Kurreck J, Fechner H. Soluble coxsackie- and adenovirus receptor (sCAR-Fc); a highly efficient compound against laboratory and clinical strains of coxsackie-B-virus. Antivir Res. 2016;136:1-8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2016.10.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baicus A. History of polio vaccination. World J Virol. 2012;1(4):108-114. https://doi.org/10.5501/wjv.v1.i4.108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norrby E, Prusiner SB. Polio and Nobel prizes: looking back 50 years. Ann Neurol. 2007;61(5):385-395. https://doi.org/10.1002/ana.21153</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katz SL. From culture to vaccine--Salk and Sabin. N Engl J Med. 2004;351(15):1485-1487. https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmp048217</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Innis BL, Snitbhan R, Kunasol P, et al. Protection against hepatitis A by an inactivated vaccine. JAMA. 1994;271(17):1328-1334. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.1994.03510410040030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tambyah PA, Oon J, Asli R, et al. An inactivated enterovirus 71 vaccine is safe and immunogenic in healthy adults: a phase I, double blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, study of two dosages. Vaccine. 2019;37(31):4344-4353. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.06.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Zeng G, Chu K, et al. Five-year immunity persistence following immunization with inactivated enterovirus 71 type (EV71) vaccine in healthy children: a further observation. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2018;14(6):1517-1523. https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2018.1442997</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei M, Meng F, Wang S, et al. 2-Year efficacy, immunogenicity, and safety of vigoo enterovirus 71 vaccine in healthy Chinese children: a randomized open-label study. J Infect Dis. 2017;215(1):56-63. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiw502</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Mo Z, Liang Z, et al. Immunity and clinical efficacy of an inactivated enterovirus 71 vaccine in healthy Chinese children: a report of further observations. BMC Med. 2015;13(1):226. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-015-0448-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R, Liu L, Mo Z, et al. An inactivated enterovirus 71 vaccine in healthy children. N Engl J Med. 2014;370(9):829-837. https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmoa1303224</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone VM, Hankaniemi MM, Svedin E, et al. A Coxsackievirus B vaccine protects against virus-induced diabetes in an experimental mouse model of type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2018;61(2):476-481. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00125-017-4492-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hankaniemi MM, Laitinen OH, Stone VM, et al. Optimized production and purification of Coxsackievirus B1 vaccine and its preclinical evaluation in a mouse model. Vaccine. 2017;35(30):3718-3725. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.05.057</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hankaniemi MM, Stone VM, Sioofy-Khojine AB, et al. A comparative study of the effect of UV and formalin inactivation on the stability and immunogenicity of a Coxsackievirus B1 vaccine. Vaccine. 2019;37(40):5962-5971. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.08.037</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone VM, Hankaniemi MM, Laitinen OH, et al. A hexavalent Coxsackievirus B vaccine is highly immunogenic and has a strong protective capacity in mice and nonhuman primates. Sci Adv. 2020;6(19):eaaz2433. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aaz2433</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng X, Hu X, Salazar MA. On reducing the risk of vaccine-associated paralytic poliomyelitis in the global transition from oral to inactivated poliovirus vaccine. Lancet. 2018;392(10147):610-612. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140-6736(18)30483-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platt LR, Estívariz CF, Sutter RW. Vaccine-associated paralytic poliomyelitis: a review of the epidemiology and estimation of the global burden. J Infect Dis. 2014;210(Suppl 1):S380-S389. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiu184</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohsen MO, Zha L, Cabral-Miranda G, Bachmann MF. Major findings and recent advances in virus-like particle (VLP)-based vaccines. Semin Immunol. 2017;34:123-132. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smim.2017.08.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassine IH, Gharbi J, Hamrita B, Almalki MA, Rodríguez JF, Ben M'hadheb M. Characterization of Coxsackievirus B4 virus-like particles VLP produced by the recombinant baculovirus-insect cell system expressing the major capsid protein. Mol Biol Rep. 2020;47(4):2835-2843. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11033-020-05333-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hankaniemi MM, Baikoghli MA, Stone VM, et al. Structural insight into CVB3-VLP non-adjuvanted vaccine. Microorganisms. 2020;8(9):1287. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms8091287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hankaniemi MM, Stone VM, Andrejeff T, et al. Formalin treatment increases the stability and immunogenicity of coxsackievirus B1 VLP vaccine. Antivir Res. 2019;171:104595. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2019.104595</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jang SK, Kräusslich HG, Nicklin MJ, Duke GM, Palmenberg AC, Wimmer E. A segment of the 5' nontranslated region of encephalomyocarditis virus RNA directs internal entry of ribosomes during in vitro translation. J Virol. 1988;62(8):2636-2643. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.62.8.2636-2643.1988</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown DM, Kauder SE, Cornell CT, Jang GM, Racaniello VR, Semler BL. Cell-dependent role for the poliovirus 3' noncoding region in positive-strand RNA synthesis. J Virol. 2004;78(3):1344-1351. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.78.3.1344-1351.2004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossmann MG. The canyon hypothesis. Hiding the host cell receptor attachment site on a viral surface from immune surveillance. J Biol Chem. 1989;264(25):14587-14590. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0021-9258(18)63732-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanagawa B, Spiller OB, Choy J, et al. Coxsackievirus B3-associated myocardial pathology and viral load reduced by recombinant soluble human decay-accelerating factor in mice. Lab Invest. 2003;83(1):75-85. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.lab.0000049349.56211.09</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carson SD, Tracy S, Kaczmarek ZG, Alhazmi A, Chapman NM. Three capsid amino acids notably influence coxsackie B3 virus stability. J Gen Virol. 2016;97(1):60-68. https://doi.org/10.1099/jgv.0.000319</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung SK, Kim JY, Kim IB, Park SI, Paek KH, Nam JH. Internalization and trafficking mechanisms of coxsackievirus B3 in HeLa cells. Virology. 2005;333(1):31-40. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2004.12.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triantafilou K, Triantafilou M. Lipid-raft-dependent Coxsackievirus B4 internalization and rapid targeting to the Golgi. Virology. 2004;326(1):6-19. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2004.04.051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain KM, Leong KL, Ng MM, Chu JJ. The essential role of clathrin-mediated endocytosis in the infectious entry of human enterovirus 71. J Biol Chem. 2011;286(1):309-321. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.m110.168468</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson RJ, Standart N. Do the poly(A) tail and 3' untranslated region control mRNA translation? Cell. 1990;62(1):15-24. https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(90)90235-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joachims M, Van Breugel PC, Lloyd RE. Cleavage of poly(A)-binding protein by enterovirus proteases concurrent with inhibition of translation in vitro. J Virol. 1999;73(1):718-727. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.73.1.718-727.1999</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarun SZ, Sachs AB. Association of the yeast poly(A) tail binding protein with translation initiation factor eIF-4G. EMBO J. 1996;15(24):7168-7177. https://doi.org/10.1002/j.1460-2075.1996.tb01108.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lloyd RE, Jense HG, Ehrenfeld E. Restriction of translation of capped mRNA in vitro as a model for poliovirus-induced inhibition of host cell protein synthesis: relationship to p220 cleavage. J Virol. 1987;61(8):2480-2488. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.61.8.2480-2488.1987</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hogle JM, Chow M, Filman DJ. Three-dimensional structure of poliovirus at 2.9 A resolution. Science. 1985;229(4720):1358-1365. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.2994218</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cathcart AL, Semler BL. Differential restriction patterns of mRNA decay factor AUF1 during picornavirus infections. J Gen Virol. 2014;95(Pt 7):1488-1492. https://doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.064501-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rozovics JM, Chase AJ, Cathcart AL, et al. Picornavirus modification of a host mRNA decay protein. mBio. 2012;3(6):e00431-e00412. https://doi.org/10.1128/mbio.00431-12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blair WS, Parsley TB, Bogerd HP, Towner JS, Semler BL, Cullen BR. Utilization of a mammalian cell-based RNA binding assay to characterize the RNA binding properties of picornavirus 3C proteinases. RNA. 1998;4(2):215-225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zell R, Sidigi K, Bucci E, Stelzner A, Görlach M. Determinants of the recognition of enteroviral cloverleaf RNA by coxsackievirus B3 proteinase 3C. RNA. 2002;8(2):188-201. https://doi.org/10.1017/s1355838202012785</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baltimore D, Girard M, Darnell JE. Aspects of the synthesis of poliovirus RNA and the formation of virus particles. Virology. 1966;29(2):179-189. https://doi.org/10.1016/0042-6822(66)90024-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell YC, Semler BL, Ehrenfeld E. Requirements for RNA replication of a poliovirus replicon by coxsackievirus B3 RNA polymerase. J Virol. 1999;73(11):9413-9421. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.73.11.9413-9421.1999</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parsley TB, Towner JS, Blyn LB, Ehrenfeld E, Semler BL. Poly (rC) binding protein 2 forms a ternary complex with the 5'-terminal sequences of poliovirus RNA and the viral 3CD proteinase. RNA. 1997;3(10):1124-1134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chase AJ, Daijogo S, Semler BL. Inhibition of poliovirus-induced cleavage of cellular protein PCBP2 reduces the levels of viral RNA replication. J Virol. 2014;88(6):3192-3201. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.02503-13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamarnik AV, Andino R. Two functional complexes formed by KH domain containing proteins with the 5' noncoding region of poliovirus RNA. RNA. 1997;3(8):882-892.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhbari P, Richardson SJ, Morgan NG. Type 1 diabetes: interferons and the aftermath of pancreatic beta-cell enteroviral infection. Microorganisms. 2020;8(9):1419. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms8091419</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staring J, von Castelmur E, Blomen VA, et al. PLA2G16 represents a switch between entry and clearance of Picornaviridae. Nature. 2017;541(7637):412-416. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature21032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma HC, Liu Y, Wang C, et al. An interaction between glutathione and the capsid is required for the morphogenesis of C-cluster enteroviruses. PLoS Pathog. 2014;10(4):e1004052. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1004052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mounce BC, Olsen ME, Vignuzzi M, Connor JH. Polyamines and their role in virus infection. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev. 2017;81(4):000299-e117. https://doi.org/10.1128/mmbr.00029-17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyoo H, van der Schaar HM, Dorobantu CM, Rabouw HH, Strating JRPM, van Kuppeveld FJM. ACBD3 is an essential pan-enterovirus host factor that mediates the interaction between viral 3A protein and cellular protein PI4KB. mBio. 2019;10(1):027422-e2818. https://doi.org/10.1128/mbio.02742-18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albulescu L, Bigay J, Biswas B, et al. Uncovering oxysterol-binding protein (OSBP) as a target of the anti-enteroviral compound TTP-8307. Antivir Res. 2017;140:37-44. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2017.01.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruokolainen V, Domanska A, Laajala M, Pelliccia M, Butcher SJ, Marjomäki V. Extracellular albumin and endosomal ions prime enterovirus particles for uncoating that can Be prevented by fatty acid saturation. J Virol. 2019;93(17):005999-e619. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.00599-19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekoua MP, Alidjinou EK, Hober D. Persistent coxsackievirus B infection and pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes mellitus. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2022;18(8):503-516. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574-022-00688-1</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>