<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">36406612</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2052-336X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>20</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of environmental health science &amp; engineering</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Environ Health Sci Eng</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Quantitative microbial risk assessment of enteroviruses in raw-eatable vegetables irrigated by wastewater: examining different scenarios of washing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>629</StartPage><EndPage>640</EndPage><MedlinePgn>629-640</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40201-022-00789-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Due to the increasing water crisis, the reuse of wastewater deserves attention as a method to reduce the pressure of the water crisis, especially in developing countries. The application of health risk assessment models is a way to estimate disease burdens associated with crop irrigation by wastewater effluents. In this study, a quantitative microbial risk assessment (QMRA) with probabilistic Monte-Carlo simulation was used to estimate the annual risk of enteroviruses (EVs) infection and disease burden for consumers of effluent-irrigated raw vegetables in Tehran, the capital of Iran. Wastewater effluent samples were collected over two seasons: summer and winter. EVs were analyzed in three stages, concentration and separation, cell culture, and real-time PCR (RT-PCR). A questionnaire was used to determine the dominant patterns of vegetable washing by consumers. There were 4 vegetable washing steps: wiping away mud (A), rinsing (B), using detergents (C), using disinfectants (D). 5 patterns of washing were examined in the laboratory and the concentration of enteroviruses was measured in every pattern. pattern 1: just wiping away mud (A), pattern 2: wiping away mud and rinsing (AB), pattern 3: wiping away mud by using detergents and rinsing (ABCB), pattern 4: wiping away mud by using disinfectants and rinsing (ABDB), and pattern 5: wiping away mud by using detergents and disinfectants and rinsing (ABCBDB). For washing pattern 1, pattern 2, and pattern 3, the estimated annual infection risk of EVs was estimated to be 5.6 × 10<sup>-1</sup>, 3.6 × 10<sup>-1</sup>, 1.7 × 10<sup>-1</sup> (risk/per.day), and burden of disease was calculated as 3 × 10<sup>-2</sup>, 2 × 10<sup>-2</sup>, and 9 × 10<sup>-3</sup> (burden/year), respectively. The results showed that if vegetables are washed according to method 5, the microbial risk will be minimized and the excess prevalence of viral infections will be eliminated.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Tehran University of Medical Sciences 2022.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hashemi</LastName><ForeName>Seyed Yaser</ForeName><Initials>SY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1948-9910</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411705.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0166 0922</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shahmahmoodi</LastName><ForeName>Shohreh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411705.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0166 0922</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hadi</LastName><ForeName>Mahdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Water Quality Research (CWQR), Institute for Environmental Research (IER), Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411705.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0166 0922</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nodehi</LastName><ForeName>Ramin Nabizadeh</ForeName><Initials>RN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411705.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0166 0922</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alimohammadi</LastName><ForeName>Mahmood</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411705.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0166 0922</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nejati</LastName><ForeName>Ahmad</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411705.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0166 0922</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mesdaghinia</LastName><ForeName>Alireza</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411705.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0166 0922</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Environ Health Sci Eng</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101613643</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">QMRA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Real-time PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vegetables</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater effluents</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36406612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9672215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40201-022-00789-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>L. Chacón, K. Barrantes, C. Santamaría-Ulloa, M. Solano, L. Reyes, L. Taylor, et al., "A somatic coliphage threshold approach to improve the management of activated sludge wastewater treatment plant effluents in resource-limited regions," Applied and Environmental Microbiology, vol. 86, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32591380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Fito and S. W. Van Hulle, "Wastewater reclamation and reuse potentials in agriculture: towards environmental sustainability," Environment, Development and Sustainability, pp. 1–24, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revitt DM, Lundy L, Fatta-Kassinos D. Development of a qualitative approach to assessing risks associated with the use of treated wastewater in agricultural irrigation. Journal of Hazardous Materials. 2021;406:124286. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33342600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baghapour MA, Nasseri S, Djahed B. Evaluation of Shiraz wastewater treatment plant effluent quality for agricultural irrigation by Canadian Water Quality Index (CWQI) Iranian journal of environmental health science &amp; engineering. 2013;10:1–9. doi: 10.1186/1735-2746-10-27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1735-2746-10-27</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3627627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23566673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lotfi K, Bonakdari H, Ebtehaj I, Delatolla R, Zinatizadeh AA, Gharabaghi B. A novel stochastic wastewater quality modeling based on fuzzy techniques. J Environ Health Sci Eng. 2020;18:1099–1120. doi: 10.1007/s40201-020-00530-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40201-020-00530-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7721937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33312627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sayo Sussy Kiratu, Nyamato John M, G. S, Heavy metal concentrations in soil and vegetables irrigated with sewage effluent: A case study of Embu sewage treatment plant, Kenya. Scientific African. 2020;8:e00337. doi: 10.1016/j.sciaf.2020.e00337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sciaf.2020.e00337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Y. Hashemi, M. Yegane Badi, H. Pasalari, A. Azari, H. Arfaeinia, and A. Kiani, "Degradation of Ceftriaxone from aquatic solution using a heterogeneous and reusable O3/UV/Fe3O4@ TiO2 systems: operational factors, kinetics and mineralisation," International Journal of Environmental Analytical Chemistry, pp. 1–17, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marleni NNN, Saleh L, Andriani N, Ermawati R, Firdaus NA. Selection of Municipal Wastewater Reuse Technology for Agricultural Water by Using Multi Criteria Analysis (MCA): The Case of Walcheren Wastewater Treatment Plant, The Netherlands. Journal of Wetlands Environmental Management. 2020;8:63–76. doi: 10.20527/jwem.v8i1.207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20527/jwem.v8i1.207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benito M, Menacho C, Chueca P, Ormad MP, Goñi P. Seeking the reuse of effluents and sludge from conventional wastewater treatment plants: Analysis of the presence of intestinal protozoa and nematode eggs. Journal of environmental management. 2020;261:110268. doi: 10.1016/j.jenvman.2020.110268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2020.110268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32148324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shamsollahi HR, Ghoochani M, Sadeghi K, Jaafari J, Masinaei M, Sillanpää M, et al. Evaluation of the physical and chemical characteristics of water on the removal efficiency of rotavirus in drinking water treatment plants and change in induced health risk. Process Saf Environ Prot. 2019;130:6–13. doi: 10.1016/j.psep.2019.07.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psep.2019.07.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandukar S, Sherchan SP, Haramoto E. Applicability of crAssphage, pepper mild mottle virus, and tobacco mosaic virus as indicators of reduction of enteric viruses during wastewater treatment. Sci Rep. 2020;10:1–8. doi: 10.1038/s41598-020-60547-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-60547-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7046655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32107444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mesdaghinia A, Younesian M, Nasseri S, Nodehi RN, Hadi M. A bibliometric and trend analysis on the water-related risk assessment studies for Cryptosporidium pathogen. Iran J Parasitol. 2015;10:338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4662734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26622289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrinca A, Donia D, Pierangeli A, Gabrieli R, Degener A, Bonanni E, et al. Presence and environmental circulation of enteric viruses in three different wastewater treatment plants. J Appl Microbiol. 2009;106:1608–1617. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2672.2008.04128.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2008.04128.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19226391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okitsu S, Khamrin P, Takanashi S, Thongprachum A, Hoque SA, Takeuchi H, et al. Molecular detection of enteric viruses in the stool samples of children without diarrhea in Bangladesh. Infection, Genetics and Evolution. 2020;77:104055. doi: 10.1016/j.meegid.2019.104055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2019.104055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31629889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nodehi RN, Aslani H, Alomohammadi M, Nemati R, Naddafi K, Ghany M. Performance comparison of Fenton and Fenton modified with copper in raw wastewater disinfection for reuse in agriculture. Iranian Journal of Health and Environment. 2012;5:189–200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alimohammadi M, Naderi M. Effectiveness of Ozone Gas on Airborne Virus Inactivation in Enclosed Spaces: A Review Study. Ozone: Science &amp; Engineering. 2021;43:21–31. doi: 10.1080/01919512.2020.1822149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01919512.2020.1822149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebomah KE, Okoh AI. An African perspective on the prevalence, fate and effects of carbapenem resistance genes in hospital effluents and wastewater treatment plant (WWTP) final effluents: A critical review. Heliyon. 2020;6:e03899. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e03899.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e03899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7215200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32420480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasalari H, Ataei-Pirkooh A, Aminikhah M, Jafari AJ, Farzadkia M. Assessment of airborne enteric viruses emitted from wastewater treatment plant: atmospheric dispersion model, quantitative microbial risk assessment, disease burden. Environ Pollut. 2019;253:464–473. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2019.07.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.07.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31325891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moazeni M, Nikaeen M, Hadi M, Moghim S, Mouhebat L, Hatamzadeh M, et al. Estimation of health risks caused by exposure to enteroviruses from agricultural application of wastewater effluents. Water Res. 2017;125:104–113. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2017.08.028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2017.08.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28841422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Hamilton KA, Lobos A, Hughes B, Staley C, Sadowsky MJ, et al. Quantitative microbial risk assessment of microbial source tracking markers in recreational water contaminated with fresh untreated and secondary treated sewage. Environ Int. 2018;117:243–249. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2018.05.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.05.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29772486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schijven J, Teunis P, Suylen T, Ketelaars H, Hornstra L, Rutjes S. QMRA of adenovirus in drinking water at a drinking water treatment plant using UV and chlorine dioxide disinfection. Water Res. 2019;158:34–45. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2019.03.090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2019.03.090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31015141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahmahmoodi S, Zahraei SM, Gouya MM, Mousavi T, Hosseini M, OstovarEsfandabadi M, et al. Relative frequency and type identification of non-polio enteroviruses isolated from acute flaccid paralysis cases in Iran, 1995–2000. Journal of School of Public Health and Institute of Public Health Research. 2012;10:53–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apha A. WEF (2005) Standard methods for the examination of water and wastewater. American Water Works Association, and Water Environment Federation: American Public Health Association; 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO, "Guidelines for environmental surveillance of poliovirus circulation," World Health Organization, 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan J, Sun CJ, Chen F, Zhou C, Li YQ, Liu YP, et al. Capillary Electrophoresis-Based Detection for Foodborne Enteroviruses in Vegetable Samples. Chromatographia. 2015;78:1191–1199. doi: 10.1007/s10337-015-2931-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10337-015-2931-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mok HF, Hamilton AJ. Exposure factors for wastewater-irrigated Asian vegetables and a probabilistic rotavirus disease burden model for their consumption. Risk Anal. 2014;34:602–613. doi: 10.1111/risa.12178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/risa.12178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3984355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24576153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y. "Enteroviruses Dose Response Models. Quantitative Microbial Risk Assessment Wiki," Center for Advancing Microbial Risk Assessment, Michigan State University. 2013. http://qmrawiki.msu.edu/index.php. Accessed 25 Jan 2015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pouillot R, Delignette-Muller ML. Evaluating variability and uncertainty separately in microbial quantitative risk assessment using two R packages. Int J Food Microbiol. 2010;142:330–340. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2010.07.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2010.07.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20674055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mok H-F, Barker SF, Hamilton AJ. A probabilistic quantitative microbial risk assessment model of norovirus disease burden from wastewater irrigation of vegetables in Shepparton, Australia. Water Res. 2014;54:347–362. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2014.01.060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2014.01.060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24594660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Havelaar and J. Melse, "Quantifying public health risk in the WHO Guidelines for drinking-water quality: A burden of disease approach," 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symonds E, Verbyla M, Lukasik J, Kafle R, Breitbart M, Mihelcic J. A case study of enteric virus removal and insights into the associated risk of water reuse for two wastewater treatment pond systems in Bolivia. Water Res. 2014;65:257–270. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2014.07.032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2014.07.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25129566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall JN, Moore S, Harper SB, Lynch JW. Global variability in fruit and vegetable consumption. American journal of preventive medicine. 2009;36:402–409e5. doi: 10.1016/j.amepre.2009.01.029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2009.01.029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19362694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng CAN, He J, MacGregor GA. Fruit and vegetable consumption and stroke: meta-analysis of cohort studies. The Lancet. 2006;367:320–326. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68069-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68069-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16443039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO, WHO guidelines for the safe use of wasterwater excreta and greywater vol. 1: World Health Organization, 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanders EC, Yuan Y, Pitchford A. Fecal coliform and E. coli concentrations in effluent-dominated streams of the Upper Santa Cruz watershed. Water. 2013;5:243–261. doi: 10.3390/w5010243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w5010243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aali R, Nikaeen M, Khanahmad H, Hassanzadeh A. Monitoring and comparison of antibiotic resistant bacteria and their resistance genes in municipal and hospital wastewaters. Int J Prev Med. 2014;5:887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4124567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25105001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An Y-J, Kampbell DH, Breidenbach GP. Escherichia coli and total coliforms in water and sediments at lake marinas. Environ Pollut. 2002;120:771–778. doi: 10.1016/S0269-7491(02)00173-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0269-7491(02)00173-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12442800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Harbi AH. Faecal coliforms in pond water, sediments and hybrid tilapia Oreochromis niloticus× Oreochromis aureus in Saudi Arabia. Aquac Res. 2003;34:517–524. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-2109.2003.00832.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2109.2003.00832.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieczorek M, Ciąćka A, Witek A, Kuryk Ł, Żuk-Wasek A. Environmental surveillance of non-polio enteroviruses in Poland, 2011. Food and environmental virology. 2015;7:224–231. doi: 10.1007/s12560-015-9195-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-015-9195-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25862480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kargar M, Sadeghipour S, Nategh R. Environmental surveillance of non-polio enteroviruses in Iran. Virology Journal. 2009;6:1–5. doi: 10.1186/1743-422X-6-149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-6-149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2761390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19781063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>