<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">36421377</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2079-7737</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biology (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Re-Enlightenment of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes under the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1662</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/biology11111662</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Fulminant type 1 diabetes (FT1D) is a subtype of type 1 diabetes (T1D) that is characterized by the rapid progression to diabetic ketoacidosis against the background of rapid and almost complete pancreatic islet destruction. The HbA1c level at FT1D onset remains normal or slightly elevated despite marked hyperglycemia, reflecting the rapid clinical course of the disease, and is an important marker for diagnosis. FT1D often appears following flu-like symptoms, and there are many reports of its onset being linked to viral infections. In addition, disease-susceptibility genes have been identified in FT1D, suggesting the involvement of host factors in disease development. In most cases, islet-related autoantibodies are not detected, and histology of pancreatic tissue reveals macrophage and T cell infiltration of the islets in the early stages of FT1D, suggesting that islet destruction occurs via an immune response different from that occurring in autoimmune type 1 diabetes. From 2019, coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by the novel severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) spread worldwide and became a serious problem. Reports on the association between SARS-CoV-2 and T1D are mixed, with some suggesting an increase in T1D incidence due to the COVID-19 pandemic. When discussing the association between COVID-19 and T1D, it is also necessary to focus on FT1D. However, it is not easy to diagnose this subtype without understanding the concept. Therefore, authors hereby review the concept and the latest findings of FT1D, hoping that the association between COVID-19 and T1D will be adequately evaluated in the future.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sano</LastName><ForeName>Hiroyuki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8581-4809</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine (I), Osaka Medical and Pharmaceutical University, Takatsuki 569-8686, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Imagawa</LastName><ForeName>Akihisa</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine (I), Osaka Medical and Pharmaceutical University, Takatsuki 569-8686, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Biology (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101587988</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2079-7737</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acquired immunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">autoimmune type 1 diabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coronavirus disease 2019</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fulminant type 1 diabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">innate immunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36421377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9687436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biology11111662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">biology11111662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Miyagawa J., Matsuzawa Y., for the Osaka IDDM Study Group A Novel Subtype of Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Characterized by a Rapid Onset and an Absence of Diabetes-Related Antibodies. N. Engl. J. Med. 2000;342:301–307. doi: 10.1056/NEJM200002033420501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJM200002033420501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10655528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shibasaki S., Imagawa A., Tauriainen S., Iino M., Oikarinen M., Abiru H., Tamaki K., Seino H., Nishi K., Takase I., et al. Expression of Toll-Like Receptors in the Pancreas of Recent-Onset Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Endocr. J. 2010;57:211–219. doi: 10.1507/endocrj.K09E-291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1507/endocrj.K09E-291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20009359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Uchigata Y., Kanatsuka A., Kawasaki E., Kobayashi T., Shimada A., Shimizu I., Toyoda T., Maruyama T., et al. Fulminant type 1 Diabetes: A Nationwide Survey in Japan. Diabetes Care. 2003;26:2345–2352. doi: 10.2337/diacare.26.8.2345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diacare.26.8.2345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12882860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho Y.M., Kim J.T., Ko K.S., Koo B.K., Yang S.W., Park M.H., Lee H.K., Park K.S. Fulminant type 1 diabetes in Korea: High prevalence among patients with adult-onset type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2007;50:2276–2279. doi: 10.1007/s00125-007-0812-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-007-0812-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17724575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L., Mao J., Lu Z., Yan X., Ye Y., Jiang F. Clinical analysis of fulminant type 1 diabetes in China and comparison with a nationwide survey in Japan. Ann. Endocrinol. 2013;74:36–39. doi: 10.1016/j.ando.2012.11.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ando.2012.11.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23357571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murao S., Makino H., Kaino Y., Konoue E., Ohashi J., Kida K., Fujii Y., Shimizu I., Kawasaki E., Fujiyama M., et al. Differences in the contribution of HLA-DR and -DQ haplotypes to susceptibility to adult-onset and childhood-onset type 1 diabetes in Japanese patients. Diabetes. 2004;53:2684–2690. doi: 10.2337/diabetes.53.10.2684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diabetes.53.10.2684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15448101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shibasaki S., Imagawa A., Hanafusa T. Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus: A New Class of Type 1 Diabetes. Adv. Exp. Med. Biol. 2012;771:20–23. doi: 10.1007/978-1-4614-5441-0_3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4614-5441-0_3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23393667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imagawa A., Hanafusa T. Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus. Endocr. J. 2006;53:577–584. doi: 10.1507/endocrj.KR-72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1507/endocrj.KR-72</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16873987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekine N., Motokura T., Oki T., Umeda Y., Sasaki N., Hayashi M., Sato H., Fujita T., Kaneko T., Asano Y., et al. Rapid Loss of Insulin Secretion in a Patient with Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus and Carbamazepine Hypersensitivity Syndrome. JAMA. 2001;285:1153–1154. doi: 10.1001/jama.285.9.1153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.285.9.1153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11231743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirota H., Tsutsumi C., Kimata H., Watanabe D., Imbe H., Takamoto S., Shibasaki S., Sano H., Onishi M., Furukawa K., et al. A Case of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Patient Accompanied by Hyperinsulinemic Hypoglycemia Prior to Clinical Diagnosis of Diabetes. J. Jpn. Diabetes Soc. 2016;59:210–217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Awata T., Ikegami H., Uchigata Y., Osawa H., Kawasaki E., Kawabata Y., Kobayashi T., Shimada A., et al. Report of the Committee of the Japan Diabetes Society on the Research of Fulminant and Acute-Onset Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus: New Diagnostic Criteria of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus. J. Diabetes Investig. 2012;3:536–539. doi: 10.1111/jdi.12024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.12024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4015434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24843620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albandar H.J., Fuqua J., Albandar J.M., Safi S., Merrill S.A., Ma P.C. Immune-Related Adverse Events (IrAE) in Cancer Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors (ICI) and Survival Outcomes Correlation: To Rechallenge or Not? Cancers. 2021;13:989. doi: 10.3390/cancers13050989.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cancers13050989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7956829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33673446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Endo T., Takizawa S., Tanaka S., Takahashi M., Fujii H., Kamisawa T., Kobayashi T. Amylase alpha-2A Autoantibodies: Novel Marker of Autoimmune Pancreatitis and Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes. 2009;58:732–737. doi: 10.2337/db08-0493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db08-0493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2646073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19001184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takizawa S., Endo T., Wanjia X., Tanaka S., Takahashi M., Kobayashi T. HSP 10 Is a New Autoantigen in Both Autoimmune Pancreatitis and Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 2009;386:192–196. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2009.06.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2009.06.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19520060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haseda F., Imagawa A., Nishikawa H., Mitsui S., Tsutsumi C., Fujisawa R., Sano H., Murase-Mishiba Y., Terasaki J., Sakaguchi S., et al. Antibody to CMRF35-Like Molecule 2, CD300e A Novel Biomarker Detected in Patients with Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes. PLoS ONE. 2016;11:e0160576. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0160576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0160576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4981355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27513516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oram R.A., Jones A.G., Besser R.E.J., Knight B.A., Shields B.M., Brown R.J., Hattersley A.T., McDonald T.J. Erratum to: The Majority of Patients with Long-Duration Type 1 Diabetes Are Insulin Microsecretors and have Functioning Beta Cells. Diabetologia. 2014;57:262. doi: 10.1007/s00125-013-3103-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-013-3103-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3855529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24121625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infante M., Ricordi C. Editorial—Moving Forward on the Pathway of Targeted Immunotherapies for Type 1 Diabetes: The Importance of Disease Heterogeneity. Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci. 2019;23:8702–8704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31646605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murase Y., Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Iwahashi H., Uchigata Y., Kanatsuka A., Kawasaki E., Kobayashi T., Shimada A., Shimizu I., et al. Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes as a High Risk Group for Diabetic Microangiopathy—A Nationwide 5-Year-Study in Japan. Diabetologia. 2007;50:531–537. doi: 10.1007/s00125-006-0575-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-006-0575-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17235525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takaike H., Uchigata Y., Nakagami T., Iwamoto Y. Incidence and Development of Diabetic Microangiopathy of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes—Comparison with Non-Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes. Intern. Med. 2010;49:1079–1083. doi: 10.2169/internalmedicine.49.3294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.49.3294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20558921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beik P., Ciesielska M., Kucza M., Kurczewska A., Kuźmińska J., Maćkowiak B., Niechciał E. Prevention of Type 1 Diabetes: Past Experiences and Future Opportunities. J. Clin. Med. 2020;9:2805. doi: 10.3390/jcm9092805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm9092805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7563637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32872668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bougnères P.F., Landais P., Boisson C., Carel J.C., Frament N., Boitard C., Chaussain J.L., Bach J.F. Limited Duration of Remission of Insulin Dependency in Children with Recent Overt Type I Diabetes Treated with Low-Dose Cyclosporin. Diabetes. 1990;39:1264–1272. doi: 10.2337/diab.39.10.1264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diab.39.10.1264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2210078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keymeulen B., Vandemeulebroucke E., Ziegler A.G., Mathieu C., Kaufman L., Hale G., Gorus F., Goldman M., Walter M., Candon S., et al. Insulin Needs after CD3-Antibody Therapy in New-Onset Type 1 Diabetes. N. Engl. J. Med. 2005;352:2598–2608. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa043980.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa043980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15972866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keymeulen B., Walter M., Mathieu C., Kaufman L., Gorus F., Hilbrands R., Vandemeulebroucke E., Van De Velde U., Crenier L., De Block C., et al. Four-year metabolic outcome of a randomised controlled CD3-antibody trial in recent-onset type 1 diabetic patients depends on their age and baseline residual beta cell mass. Diabetologia. 2010;53:614–623. doi: 10.1007/s00125-009-1644-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-009-1644-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20225393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherry N., Hagopian W., Ludvigsson J., Jain S.M., Wahlen J., Ferry R.J., Bode B., Aronoff S., Holland C., Carlin D., et al. Teplizumab for Treatment of Type 1 Diabetes (Protégé study): 1-year Results from a Randomised, Placebo-controlled Trial. Lancet. 2011;378:487–497. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60931-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60931-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3191495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21719095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orban T., Bundy B., Becker D.J., DiMeglio L.A., Gitelman S.E., Goland R., Gottlieb P.A., Greenbaum C.J., Marks J.B., Monzavi R., et al. Co-stimulation Modulation with Abatacept in Patients with Recent-onset Type 1 Diabetes: A randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2011;378:412–419. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60886-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60886-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3462593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21719096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pescovitz M.D., Greenbaum C.J., Krause-Steinrauf H., Becker D.J., Gitelman S.E., Goland R., Gottlieb P.A., Marks J.B., McGee P.F., Moran A.M., et al. Rituximab, B-Lymphocyte Depletion, and Preservation of Beta-Cell Function. N. Engl. J. Med. 2009;361:2143–2152. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0904452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0904452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6410357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19940299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ludvigsson J., Faresjö M., Hjorth M., Axelsson S., Chéramy M., Pihl M., Vaarala O., Forsander G., Ivarsson S., Johansson C., et al. GAD Treatment and Insulin Secretion in Recent-Onset Type 1 Diabetes. N. Engl. J. Med. 2008;359:1909–1920. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0804328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0804328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18843118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herold K.C., Bundy B.N., Long S.A., Bluestone J.A., DiMeglio L.A., Dufort M.J., Gitelman S.E., Gottlieb P.A., Krischer J.P., Linsley P.S., et al. An Anti-CD3 Antibody, Teplizumab, in Relatives at Risk for Type 1 Diabetes. N. Engl. J. Med. 2019;381:603–613. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1902226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1902226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6776880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31180194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone V.M., Hankaniemi M.M., Svedin E., Sioofy-Khojine A., Oikarinen S., Hyöty H., Laitinen O.H., Hytönen V.P., Flodström-Tullberg M. A Coxsackievirus B Vaccine Protects against Virus-Induced Diabetes in an Experimental Mouse Model of Type 1 Diabetes. Diabetologia. 2018;61:476–481. doi: 10.1007/s00125-017-4492-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-017-4492-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6448957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29151123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Uchigata Y., Kanatsuka A., Kawasaki E., Kobayashi T., Shimada A., Shimizu I., Maruyama T., Makino H. Different Contribution of Class II HLA in Fulminant and Typical Autoimmune Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus. Diabetologia. 2005;48:294–300. doi: 10.1007/s00125-004-1626-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-004-1626-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15688210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsutsumi C., Imagawa A., Ikegami H., Makino H., Kobayashi T., Hanafusa T., Japan Diabetes Society Committee on Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Research Class II HLA Genotype in Fulminant type 1 Diabetes: A Nationwide Survey with Reference to Glutamic Acid Decarboxylase Antibodies. J. Diabetes Investig. 2012;3:62–69. doi: 10.1111/j.2040-1124.2011.00139.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.2040-1124.2011.00139.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4014934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24843547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawabata Y., Nishida N., Awata T., Kawasaki E., Imagawa A., Shimada A., Osawa H., Tanaka S., Takahashi K., Nagata M., et al. Genome-Wide Association Study Confirming a Strong Effect of HLA and Identifying Variants in CSAD/lnc-ITGB7-1 on Chromosome 12q13.13 Associated with Susceptibility to Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes. 2019;68:665–675. doi: 10.2337/db18-0314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db18-0314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30552108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arany E., Strutt B., Romanus P., Remacle C., Reusens B., Hill D.J. Taurine Supplement in Early Life Altered Islet Morphology, Decreased Insulitis and Delayed the Onset of Diabetes in Non-Obese Diabetic Mice. Diabetologia. 2004;47:1831–1837. doi: 10.1007/s00125-004-1535-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-004-1535-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15502919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berlin C., Berg E.L., Briskin M.J., Andrew D.P., Kilshaw P.J., Holzmann B., Weissman I.L., Hamann A., Butcher E.C. Alpha 4 Beta 7 Integrin Mediates Lymphocyte Binding to the Mucosal Vascular Addressin MAdCAM-1. Cell. 1993;74:185–195. doi: 10.1016/0092-8674(93)90305-A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(93)90305-A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7687523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanafusa T., Imagawa A., Iwahashi H., Uchigata Y., Kanatsuka A., Kawasaki E., Kobayashi T., Shimada A., Shimizu I., Maruyama T., et al. Report of the Japan Diabetes Society’s Committee on Research on Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus: Analysis of Antiviral Antibodies at Disease Onset. J. Jpn. Diab. Soc. 2008;51:531–536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanafusa T., Imagawa A. Fulminant type 1 Diabetes: A Novel Clinical Entity Requiring Special Attention by All Medical Practitioners. Nat. Clin. Pract. Endocrinol. Metab. 2007;3:36–45. doi: 10.1038/ncpendmet0351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ncpendmet0351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17179928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imagawa A., Hanafusa T. Fulminant type 1 Diabetes--an Important Subtype in East Asia. Diabetes Metab. Res. Rev. 2011;27:959–964. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.1236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/dmrr.1236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22069293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goto A., Takahashi Y., Kishimoto M., Nakajima Y., Nakanishi K., Kajio H., Noda M. A Case of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Associated with Significant Elevation of Mumps Titers. Endocr. J. 2008;55:561–564. doi: 10.1507/endocrj.K07E-126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1507/endocrj.K07E-126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18520103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akatsuka H., Yano Y., Gabazza E.C., Morser J., Sasaki R., Suzuki T., Fujiwara R., Katsuki A., Takei Y., Sumida Y. A Case of Fulminant type 1 Diabetes with Coxsackie B4 Virus Infection Diagnosed by Elevated Serum Levels of Neutralizing Antibody. Diabetes Res. Clin. Pract. 2009;84:e50–e52. doi: 10.1016/j.diabres.2009.03.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2009.03.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19362384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sano H., Terasaki J., Tsutsumi C., Imagawa A., Hanafusa T. A Case of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus After Influenza B Infection. Diabetes Res. Clin. Pract. 2008;79:e8–e9. doi: 10.1016/j.diabres.2007.10.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2007.10.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18177974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawasaki S., Kuroiwa S., Mikami T., Shibata H., Misawa H., Tamura Y., Yamamoto S., Terauchi Y. A Case of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Which was Estimated to Triggered by Enterovirus Infection after 25 Years of the Vogt-Koyanagi-Harada (VKH) Disease Onset. J. Jpn. Diab. Soc. 2016;59:768–774.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohta M., Miura J., Ohsato A., Maruyama S., Ishii A., Iizuka J., Tanabe K., Iwamoto Y. A Case of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Undergoing Immunosuppression Therapy after Kidney Transplantation with Cytomegalovirus Antigenemia Elevation. J. Jpn. Diab. Soc. 2009;52:919–925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohara N., Kaneko M., Nishibori T., Sato K., Furukawa T., Koike T., Sone H., Kaneko K., Kamoi K. Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Associated with Coxsackie Virus Type A2 Infection: A Case Report and Literature Review. Intern. Med. 2016;55:643–646. doi: 10.2169/internalmedicine.55.5292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.55.5292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26984083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirtipal N., Bharadwaj S., Kang S.G. From SARS to SARS-CoV-2, Insights on Structure, Pathogenicity and Immunity Aspects of Pandemic Human Coronaviruses. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2020;85:104502. doi: 10.1016/j.meegid.2020.104502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2020.104502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7425554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32798769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourgonje A.R., Abdulle A.E., Timens W., Hillebrands J.-L., Navis G.J., Gordijn S.J., Bolling M.C., Dijkstra G., Voors A.A., Osterhaus A.D., et al. Angiotensin-converting Enzyme 2 (ACE2), SARS-CoV-2 and the Pathophysiology of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) J. Pathol. 2020;251:228–248. doi: 10.1002/path.5471.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/path.5471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7276767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32418199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Makino H., Miyagawa J.I., Juto P. High Titres of IgA Antibodies to Enterovirus in Fulminant type-1 Diabetes. Diabetologia. 2005;48:290–293. doi: 10.1007/s00125-004-1624-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-004-1624-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15654603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pak C.Y., Eun H.M., Mcarthur R.G., Yoon J.W. Association of Cytomegalovirus Infection with Autoimmune Type 1 Diabe-Tes. Lancet. 1988;2:1–4. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(88)92941-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(88)92941-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2898620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honeyman M.C., Stone N.L., Harrison L.C. T-Cell Epitopes in Type 1 Diabetes Autoantigen Tyrosine Phosphatase IA-2: Potential for Mimicry with Rotavirus and Other Environmental Agents. Mol. Med. 1998;4:231–239. doi: 10.1007/BF03401920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF03401920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2230363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9606176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filippi C.M., von Herrath M.G. Viral Trigger for Type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes. 2008;57:2863–2871. doi: 10.2337/db07-1023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db07-1023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2570378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18971433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen M., Tauriainen S., Honkanen T., Oikarinen S., Vuori K., Kaukinen K., Rantala I., Maki M., Hyoty H. Detection of Enteroviruses in the Intestine of Type 1 Diabetic Patients. Clin. Exp. Immunol. 2008;151:71–75. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2249.2007.03529.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2249.2007.03529.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2276929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17991291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krogvold L., Edwin B., Buanes T., Frisk G., Skog O., Anagandula M., Korsgren O., Undlien D., Eike M.C., Richardson S.J. Detection of a Low-grade Enteroviral Infection in the Islets of Langerhans of Living Patients Newly Diagnosed with Type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes. 2015;64:1682–1687. doi: 10.2337/db14-1370.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db14-1370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25422108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geravandi S., Richardson S., Pugliese A., Maedler K. Localization of Enteroviral RNA within the Pancreas in Donors with T1D and T1D-Associated Autoantibodies. Cell Rep. Med. 2021;2:100371. doi: 10.1016/j.xcrm.2021.100371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.xcrm.2021.100371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8385321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34467248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Insel R.A., Dunne J.L., Atkinson M.A., Chiang J.L., Dabelea D., Gottlieb P.A., Greenbaum C.J., Herold K.C., Krischer J.P., Lernmark Å., et al. Staging Presymptomatic Type 1 Diabetes: A Scientific Statement of JDRF, the Endocrine Society, and the American Diabetes Association. Diabetes Care. 2015;38:1964–1974. doi: 10.2337/dc15-1419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc15-1419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5321245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26404926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson S.J., Morgan N.G. Enteroviral Infections in the Pathogenesis of Type 1 Diabetes: New Insights for Therapeutic Intervention. Curr. Opin. Pharmacol. 2018;43:11. doi: 10.1016/j.coph.2018.07.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2018.07.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6294842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30064099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elshebani A., Olsson A., Westman J., Tuvemo T., Korsgren O., Frisk G. Effects on Isolated Human Pancreatic Islet Cells after Infection with Strains of Enterovirus Isolated at Clinical Presentation of Type 1 Diabetes. Virus Res. 2007;124:193–203. doi: 10.1016/j.virusres.2006.11.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2006.11.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17169456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiohara T., Kano Y., Hirahara K., Aoyama Y. Prediction and Management of Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS) Expert Opin. Drug Metab. Toxicol. 2017;13:701–704. doi: 10.1080/17425255.2017.1297422.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/17425255.2017.1297422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28633581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiohara T., Mizukawa Y. Drug-Induced Hypersensitivity Syndrome (DiHS)/Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS): An Update in 2019. Allergol. Int. 2019;68:301–308. doi: 10.1016/j.alit.2019.03.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.alit.2019.03.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31000444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kano Y., Inaoka M., Shiohara T. Association between Anticonvulsant Hypersensitivity Syndrome and Human Herpesvirus 6 Reactivation and Hypogammaglobulinemia. Arch. Dermatol. 2004;140:183–188. doi: 10.1001/archderm.140.2.183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archderm.140.2.183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14967790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugita K., Tohyama M., Watanabe H., Otsuka A., Nakajima S., Iijima M., Hashimoto K., Tokura Y., Miyachi Y., Kabashima K. Fluctuation of Blood and Skin Plasmacytoid Dendritic Cells in Drug-Induced Hypersensitivity Syndrome. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 2010;126:408–410. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2010.06.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2010.06.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20624646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kano Y., Hiraharas K., Sakuma K., Shiohara T. Several Herpesviruses Can Reactivate in a Severe Drug-Induced Multiorgan Reaction in the Same Sequential Order as in Graft-Versus-Host Disease. Br. J. Dermatol. 2006;155:301–306. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2133.2006.07238.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2133.2006.07238.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16882166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoneda S., Imagawa A., Fukui K., Uno S., Kozawa J., Sakai M., Yumioka T., Iwahashi H., Shimomura I. A Histological Study of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Related to Human Cytomegalovirus Reactivation. J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab. 2017;102:2394–2400. doi: 10.1210/jc.2016-4029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/jc.2016-4029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28398495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onuma H., Tohyama M., Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Kobayashi T., Kano Y., Ohashi J., Hashimoto K., Osawa H., Makino H., et al. High Frequency of HLA B62 in Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes with the Drug-Induced Hypersensitivity Syndrome. J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab. 2012;97:E2277–E2281. doi: 10.1210/jc.2012-2054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/jc.2012-2054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23071161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller J.A., Groß R., Conzelmann C., Krüger J., Merle U., Steinhart J., Weil T., Koepke L., Bozzo C.P., Read C., et al. SARS-CoV-2 Infects and Replicates in Cells of the Human Endocrine and Exocrine Pancreas. Nature Metab. 2021;3:149–165. doi: 10.1038/s42255-021-00347-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s42255-021-00347-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33536639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirakawa J. Pancreatic β-cell fate in subjects with COVID-19. J. Diabetes Investig. 2021;12:2126–2128. doi: 10.1111/jdi.13671.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.13671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8668054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34529355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L., Han Y., Nilsson-Payant B.E., Gupta V., Wang P., Duan X., Tang X., Zhu J., Zhao Z., Jaffré F., et al. A Human Pluripotent Stem Cell-Based Platform to Study SARS-CoV-2 Tropism and Model Virus Infection in Human Cells and Organoids. Cell Stem Cell. 2020;27:125–136. doi: 10.1016/j.stem.2020.06.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2020.06.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7303620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32579880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geravandi S., Mahmoudi-aznaveh A., Azizi Z., Maedler K., Ardestani A. SARS-CoV-2 and Pancreas: A Potential Pathological Interaction? Trends Endocrinol. Metab. 2021;32:842–845. doi: 10.1016/j.tem.2021.07.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tem.2021.07.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8302839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34373155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C.-T., Lidsky P.V., Xiao Y., Lee I.T., Cheng R., Nakayama T., Jiang S., Demeter J., Bevacqua R.J., Chang C.A., et al. SARS-CoV-2 Infects Human Pancreatic β Cells and Elicits β Cell Impairment. Cell Metab. 2021;33:1565–1576. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2021.05.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2021.05.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8130512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34081912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang X., Uhl S., Zhang T., Xue D., Li B., Vandana J.J., Acklin J.A., Bonnycastle L.L., Narisu N., Erdos M.R., et al. SARS-CoV-2 infection induces beta cell transdifferentiation. Cell Metab. 2021;33:1577–1591.e7. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2021.05.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2021.05.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8133495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34081913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rathmann W., Kuss O., Kostev K. Incidence of Newly Diagnosed Diabetes after COVID-19. Diabetologia. 2022;65:949–954. doi: 10.1007/s00125-022-05670-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-022-05670-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8923743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35292829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuchay M.S., Reddy P.K., Gagneja S., Mathew A., Mishra S.K. Short Term Follow-up of Patients Presenting with Acute Onset Diabetes and Diabetic Ketoacidosis during an Episode of COVID-19. Diabetes Metab. Syndr. 2020;14:2039–2041. doi: 10.1016/j.dsx.2020.10.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.10.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7577220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33113470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J.-K., Lin S.-S., Ji X.-J., Guo L.-M. Binding of SARS Coronavirus to Its Receptor Damages Islets and Causes Acute Diabetes. Acta Diabetol. 2010;47:193–199. doi: 10.1007/s00592-009-0109-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00592-009-0109-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7088164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19333547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy P.K., Kuchay M.S., Mehta Y., Mishra S.K. Diabetic Ketoacidosis Precipitated by COVID-19: A Report of Two Cases and Review of Literature. Diabetes Metab. Syndr. 2020;14:1459–1462. doi: 10.1016/j.dsx.2020.07.050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.07.050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7395228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32771918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paengsai N., Jourdain G., Salvadori N., Tantraworasin A., Mary J.Y., Cressey T.R., Chaiwarith R., Bowonwatanuwong C., Bhakeecheep S., Kosachunhanun N. Recommended First-Line Antiretroviral Therapy Regimens and Risk of Diabetes Mellitus in HIV-Infected Adults in Resource-Limited Settings. Open Forum Infect. Dis. 2019;6:ofz298. doi: 10.1093/ofid/ofz298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofz298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6778321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31660327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng F., Gao D., Ma X., Guo Y., Wang R., Jiang W., Gong S. Corticosteroids in diabetes patients infected with COVID-19. Ir. J. Med. Sci. 2021;190:29–31. doi: 10.1007/s11845-020-02287-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11845-020-02287-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7315113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32588377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montefusco L., Ben Nasr M., D’Addio F., Loretelli C., Rossi A., Pastore I., Daniele G., Abdelsalam A., Maestroni A., Dell’Acqua M., et al. Acute and Long-Term Disruption of Glycometabolic Control after SARS-CoV-2 Infection. Nat. Metab. 2021;3:774–785. doi: 10.1038/s42255-021-00407-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s42255-021-00407-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9931026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34035524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sefik E., Qu R., Junqueira C., Kaffe E., Mirza H., Zhao J., Brewer J.R., Han A., Steach H.R., Israelow B., et al. Inflammasome activation in infected macrophages drives COVID-19 pathology. Nature. 2022;606:585–593. doi: 10.1038/s41586-022-04802-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04802-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9288243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35483404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unsworth R., Wallace S., Oliver N.S., Yeung S., Kshirsagar A., Naidu H., Kwong R.M.W., Kumar P., Logan K.M. New-Onset Type 1 Diabetes in Children during COVID-19: Multicenter Regional Findings in the U.K. Diabetes Care. 2020;43:e170–e171. doi: 10.2337/dc20-1551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc20-1551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32816997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tittel S.R., Rosenbauer J., Kamrath C., Ziegler J., Reschke F., Hammersen J., Mönkemöller K., Pappa A., Kapellen T., Holl R.W., et al. Did the COVID-19 Lockdown Affect the Incidence of Pediatric Type 1 Diabetes in Germany? Diabetes Care. 2020;43:e172–e173. doi: 10.2337/dc20-1633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc20-1633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7576433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32826282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qeadan F., Tingey B., Egbert J., Pezzolesi M.G., Burge M.R., Peterson K.A., Honda T. The associations between COVID-19 diagnosis, type 1 diabetes, and the risk of diabetic ketoacidosis: A nationwide cohort from the US using the Cerner Real-World Data. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0266809. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0266809.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0266809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9017888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35439266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGlacken-Byrne S.M., Drew S.E.V., Turner K., Peters C., Amin R. The SARS-CoV-2 Pandemic Is Associated with Increased Severity of Presentation of Childhood Onset Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus: A Multi-Centre Study of the First COVID-19 Wave. Diabet. Med. 2021;38:e14640. doi: 10.1111/dme.14640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dme.14640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8420510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34245598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldman S., Pinhas-Hamiel O., Weinberg A., Auerbach A., German A., Haim A., Zung A., Brener A., Strich D., Azoulay E., et al. Alarming Increase in Ketoacidosis in Children and Adolescents with Newly Diagnosed Type 1 Diabetes during the First Wave of the COVID-19 Pandemic in Israel. Pediatr. Diabetes. 2022;23:10–18. doi: 10.1111/pedi.13296.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/pedi.13296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34865288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beliard K., Ebekozien O., Demeterco-Berggren C., Alonso G.T., Gallagher M.P., Clements M., Rapaport R. Increased DKA at presentation among newly diagnosed type 1 diabetes patients with or without COVID-19: Data from a multi-site surveillance registry. J. Diabetes. 2021;13:270–272. doi: 10.1111/1753-0407.13141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1753-0407.13141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33283979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazzeroni P., Bernardi L., Pecora F., Motta M., Bianchi L., Ruozi M.B., Giacometti A., Venezia S., Iovane D.I. Diabetic Ke-Toacidosis at Type 1 Diabetes Onset: Indirect Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic. Acta Biomed. 2020;91:e2020193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7927550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33525255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dżygało K., Nowaczyk J., Szwilling A., Kowalska A. Increased Frequency of Severe Diabetic Ketoacidosis at Type 1 Diabetes Onset among Children during COVID-19 Pandemic Lockdown: An Observational Cohort Study. Pediatr. Endocrinol. Diabetes Metab. 2020;26:167–175. doi: 10.5114/pedm.2020.101003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/pedm.2020.101003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33554490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alaqeel A., Aljuraibah F., Alsuhaibani M., Huneif M., Alsaheel A., Dubayee M.A., Alsaedi A., Bakkar A., Alnahari A., Taha A., et al. The Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic Lockdown on the Incidence of New-Onset Type 1 Diabetes and Ketoacidosis among Saudi Children. Front. Endocrinol. 2021;12:669302. doi: 10.3389/fendo.2021.669302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fendo.2021.669302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8049603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33868185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salmi H., Heinonen S., Hästbacka J., Lääperi M., Rautiainen P., Miettinen P.J., Vapalahti O., Hepojoki J., Knip M. New-Onset Type 1 Diabetes in Finnish Children during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Arch. Dis. Child. 2022;107:180–185. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2020-321220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2020-321220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34045208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M., Wang H., Tian L., Pang Z., Yang Q., Huang T., Fan J., Song L., Tong Y., Fan H. COVID-19 vaccine development: Milestones, lessons and prospects. Signal Transduct. Target. Ther. 2022;7:146. doi: 10.1038/s41392-022-00996-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-00996-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9062866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35504917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang X., He B., Liu Z., Zhou Z., Li X. Fulminant type 1 diabetes after COVID-19 vaccination. Diabetes Metab. 2022;48:101324. doi: 10.1016/j.diabet.2022.101324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diabet.2022.101324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8786596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35091092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohuchi K., Amagai R., Tamabuchi E., Kambayashi Y., Fujimura T. Fulminant type 1 diabetes mellitus triggered by coronavirus disease 2019 vaccination in an advanced melanoma patient given adjuvant nivolumab therapy. J. Dermatol. 2022;49:e167–e168. doi: 10.1111/1346-8138.16304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1346-8138.16304</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35014070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasaki K., Morioka T., Okada N., Natsuki Y., Kakutani Y., Ochi A., Yamazaki Y., Shoji T., Ohmura T., Emoto M. New-onset fulminant type 1 diabetes after severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 vaccination: A case report. J. Diabetes Investig. 2022;13:1286–1289. doi: 10.1111/jdi.13771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.13771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9114923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35167186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toussirot É., Bereau M. Vaccination and Induction of Autoimmune Diseases. Inflamm. Allergy Drug Targets. 2015;14:94–98. doi: 10.2174/1871528114666160105113046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1871528114666160105113046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26728772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y., Xu Z., Wang P., Li X.M., Shuai Z.W., Ye D.Q., Pan H.F. New-onset autoimmune phenomena post-COVID-19 vaccination. Immunology. 2022;165:386–401. doi: 10.1111/imm.13443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/imm.13443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34957554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Churilov L.P., Normatov M.G., Utekhin V.J. Molecular Mimicry between SARS-CoV-2 and Human Endocrinocytes: A Prerequisite of Post-COVID-19 Endocrine Autoimmunity? Pathophysiology. 2022;29:486–494. doi: 10.3390/pathophysiology29030039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathophysiology29030039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9504401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36136066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baek H.S., Yoon J.W. Direct involvement of macrophages in destruction of beta-cells leading to development of diabetes in virus-infected mice. Diabetes. 1991;40:1586–1597. doi: 10.2337/diab.40.12.1586.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diab.40.12.1586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1661690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimada A., Maruyama T. Encephalomyocarditis-virus-induced Diabetes Model Resembles “Fulminant” Type 1 Diabetes in Humans. Diabetologia. 2004;47:1854–1855. doi: 10.1007/s00125-004-1538-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-004-1538-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15502917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon J.W., McClintock P.R., Onodera T., Notkins A.L. Virus-induced diabetes mellitus. XVIII. Inhibition by a Nondiabetogenic Variant of Encephalomyocarditis Virus. J. Exp. Med. 1980;152:878–892. doi: 10.1084/jem.152.4.878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1084/jem.152.4.878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2185964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6252275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sano H., Terasaki J., Mishiba Y., Imagawa A., Hanafusa T. Exendin-4, a Glucagon-Like Peptide-1 Receptor Agonist, Suppresses Pancreatic β-Cell Destruction Induced by Encephalomyocarditis Virus. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 2011;404:756–761. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2010.12.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2010.12.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21144822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon J.-W., Onodera T., Notkins A.L. Virus-Induced Diabetes Mellitus: VIII. Passage of Encephalomyocarditis Virus and Severity of Diabetes in Susceptible and Resistant Strains of Mice. J. Gen. Virol. 1977;37:225–232. doi: 10.1099/0022-1317-37-2-225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/0022-1317-37-2-225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">200705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Izumi K., Mine K., Inoue Y., Teshima M., Ogawa S., Kai Y., Kurafuji T., Hirakawa K., Miyakawa D., Ikeda H., et al. Reduced Tyk2 Gene Expression in β-Cells Due to Natural Mutation Determines Susceptibility to Virus-Induced Diabetes. Nat. Commun. 2015;6:6748. doi: 10.1038/ncomms7748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ncomms7748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4396380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25849081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kounoue E., Nagafuchi S., Nakamura M., Nakano S., Koga T., Nakayama M., Mituyama M., Niho Y., Takaki R. Encephalomyocarditis (EMC) Virus-Induced Diabetes Mellitus Prevented by Corynebacterium parvum in Mice. Experientia. 1987;43:430–431. doi: 10.1007/BF01940440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF01940440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3032672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baek H.S., Yoon Y.W. Role of Macrophages in the Pathogenesis of Encephalomyocarditis Virus-induced Diabetes in Mice. J. Virol. 1990;64:5708–5715. doi: 10.1128/jvi.64.12.5708-5715.1990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jvi.64.12.5708-5715.1990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC248710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2173763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu I., Makino H., Osawa H., Kounoue E., Imagawa A., Hanafusa T., Kawasaki E., Fujii Y. Association of Fulminant type 1 Diabetes with Pregnancy. Diabetes Res. Clin. Pract. 2003;62:33–38. doi: 10.1016/S0168-8227(03)00147-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0168-8227(03)00147-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14581155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu I., Makino H., Imagawa A., Iwahashi H., Uchigata Y., Kanatsuka A., Kawasaki E., Kobayashi T., Shimada A., Maruyama T., et al. Clinical and Immunogenetic Characteristics of Fulminant type 1 Diabetes Associated with Pregnancy. J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab. 2006;91:471–476. doi: 10.1210/jc.2005-1943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/jc.2005-1943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16278271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baden M.Y., Imagawa A., Abiru N., Awata T., Ikegami H., Uchigata Y., Oikawa Y., Osawa H., Kajio H., Kawasaki E., et al. Characteristics and Clinical Course of Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Related to Anti-Programmed Cell death-1 Therapy. Diabetol. Int. 2019;10:58–66. doi: 10.1007/s13340-018-0362-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13340-018-0362-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6357237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30800564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barroso-Sousa R., Barry W.T., Garrido-Castro A.C., Hodi F.S., Min L., Krop I.E., Tolaney S.M. Incidence of endocrine dysfunction following the use of different immune checkpoint inhibitor regimens: A systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Oncol. 2018;4:173–182. doi: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2017.3064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2017.3064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5838579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28973656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stamatouli A.M., Quandt Z., Perdigoto A.L., Clark P.L., Kluger H., Weiss S.A., Gettinger S., Sznol M., Young A., Rushakoff R., et al. Collateral Damage: Insulin-Dependent Diabetes Induced with Checkpoint Inhibitors. Diabetes. 2018;67:1471–1480. doi: 10.2337/dbi18-0002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dbi18-0002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6054443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29937434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotwal A., Haddox C., Block M., Kudva Y.C. Immune checkpoint inhibitors: An emerging cause of insulin-dependent diabetes. BMJ Open Diabetes Res. Care. 2019;7:e000591. doi: 10.1136/bmjdrc-2018-000591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjdrc-2018-000591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6398813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30899528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo Preiato V., Salvagni S., Ricci C., Ardizzoni A., Pagotto U., Pelusi C. Diabetes mellitus induced by immune checkpoint inhibitors: Type 1 diabetes variant or new clinical entity? Review of the literature. Rev. Endocr. Metab. Disord. 2021;22:337–349. doi: 10.1007/s11154-020-09618-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11154-020-09618-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33409866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyriacou A., Melson E., Chen W., Kempegowda P. Is Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor-Associated Diabetes the Same as Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus? Clin. Med. 2020;20:417–423. doi: 10.7861/clinmed.2020-0054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7861/clinmed.2020-0054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7385772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32675150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clotman K., Janssens K., Specenier P., Weets I., De Block C.E.M. Programmed Cell Death-1 Inhibitor-induced Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus. J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab. 2018;103:3144–3154. doi: 10.1210/jc.2018-00728.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/jc.2018-00728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29955867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okamoto M., Okamoto M., Gotoh K., Masaki T., Ozeki Y., Ando H., Anai M., Sato A., Yoshida Y., Ueda S., et al. Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus with Anti-programmed Cell Death-1 therapy. J. Diabetes Investig. 2016;7:915–918. doi: 10.1111/jdi.12531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.12531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5089956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27181090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neu A., Hofer S.E., Karges B., Oeverink R., Rosenbauer J., Holl R.W. Ketoacidosis at Diabetes Onset Is Still Frequent in Children and Adolescents. A Multicenter Analysis of 14,664 Patients from 106 Institutions. Diabetes Care. 2009;32:1647–1648. doi: 10.2337/dc09-0553.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc09-0553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2732146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19549730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grönberg A., Espes D., Carlsson P.-O. Better HbA1c during the First Years after Diagnosis of Type 1 Diabetes Is Associated with Residual C Peptide 10 Years Later. BMJ Open Diabetes Res. Care. 2020;8:e000819. doi: 10.1136/bmjdrc-2019-000819.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjdrc-2019-000819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7206906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32107263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pihoker C., Gilliam L.K., Hampe C.S., Lernmark A. Autoantibodies in diabetes. Diabetes. 2005;54((Suppl. S2)):S52–S61. doi: 10.2337/diabetes.54.suppl_2.S52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diabetes.54.suppl_2.S52</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16306341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchand L., Thivolet A., Dalle S., Chikh K., Reffet S., Vouillarmet J., Fabien N., Cugnet-Anceau C., Thivolet C. Diabetes Mellitus Induced by PD-1 and PD-L1 Inhibitors: Description of Pancreatic Endocrine and Exocrine Phenotype. Acta Diabetol. 2019;56:441–448. doi: 10.1007/s00592-018-1234-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00592-018-1234-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30284618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav D. Nonspecific Hyperamylasemia and Hyperlipasemia in Diabetic Ketoacidosis: Incidence and Correlation with Biochemical Abnormalities. Am. J. Gastroenterol. 2000;95:3123–3128. doi: 10.1111/j.1572-0241.2000.03279.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1572-0241.2000.03279.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11095328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell-Thompson M., Rodriguez-Calvo T., Battaglia M. Abnormalities of the Exocrine Pancreas in Type 1 Diabetes. Curr. Diabetes Rep. 2015;15:79. doi: 10.1007/s11892-015-0653-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11892-015-0653-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5072278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26318606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Yoshida T., Nakaki F., Hiai H., Okazaki T., Honjo T. Establishment of NOD-Pdcd1−/− Mice as an Efficient Animal Model of Type I Diabetes. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2005;102:11823–11828. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0505497102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0505497102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1188011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16087865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari M.J., Salama A.D., Chitnis T., Smith R.N., Yagita H., Akiba H., Yamazaki T., Azuma M., Iwai H., Khoury S.J., et al. The programmed death-1 (PD-1) pathway regulates autoimmune diabetes in nonobese diabetic (NOD) mice. J. Exp. Med. 2003;198:63–69. doi: 10.1084/jem.20022125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1084/jem.20022125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2196083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12847137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang S.C., Latchman Y.E., Buhlmann J.E., Tomczak M.F., Horwitz B.H., Freeman G.J., Sharpe A.H. Regulation of PD-1, PD-L1, and PD-L2 Expression during Normal and Autoimmune Responses. Eur. J. Immunol. 2003;33:2706–2716. doi: 10.1002/eji.200324228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/eji.200324228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14515254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni R., Ihara K., Miyako K., Kuromaru R., Inuo M., Kohno H., Hara T. PD-1 Gene Haplotype is Associated with the Development of Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus in Japanese Children. Hum. Genet. 2007;121:223–232. doi: 10.1007/s00439-006-0309-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00439-006-0309-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17203303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu Y., Xiao L., Gu W., Chen S., Feng Y., Wang J., Wang Z., Cai Y., Chen H., Xu X., et al. Rs2227982 and rs2227981 in PDCD1 Gene are Functional SNPs Associated with T1D Risk in East Asian. Acta Diabetol. 2018;55:813–819. doi: 10.1007/s00592-018-1152-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00592-018-1152-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29774466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nielsen C., Hansen D., Husby S., Jacobsen B.B., Lillevang S.T. Association of a Putative Regulatory Polymorphism in the PD-1 Gene with Susceptibility to Type 1 Diabetes. Tissue Antigens. 2003;62:492–497. doi: 10.1046/j.1399-0039.2003.00136.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1399-0039.2003.00136.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14617032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka S., Kobayashi T., Momotsu T. A Novel Subtype of Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus. N. Engl. J. Med. 2000;342:1835–1837.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10866555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aida K., Nishida Y., Tanaka S., Maruyama T., Shimada A., Awata T., Suzuki M., Shimura H., Takizawa S., Ichijo M., et al. RIG-I− and MDA5-Initiated Innate Immunity Linked with Adaptive Immunity Accelerates Beta-Cell Death in Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes. 2011;60:884–889. doi: 10.2337/db10-0795.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db10-0795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3046849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21289206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishida Y., Aida K., Kihara M., Kobayashi T. Antibody-validated Proteins in Inflamed Islets of Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes Profiled by Laser-capture Microdissection Followed by Mass Spectrometry. PLoS ONE. 2014;9:e107664. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0107664.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4199548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25329145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCartney S.A., Vermi W., Lonardi S., Rossini C., Otero K., Calderon B., Gilfillan S., Diamond M.S., Unanue E.R., Colonna M. RNA Sensor-Induced Type I IFN Prevents Diabetes Caused by a β Cell-Tropic Virus in Mice. J. Clin. Investig. 2011;121:1497–1507. doi: 10.1172/JCI44005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1172/JCI44005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3069767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21403398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakata S., Imagawa A., Miyata Y., Yoshikawa A., Kozawa J., Okita K., Funahashi T., Nakamura S., Matsubara K., Iwahashi H., et al. Low Gene Expression Levels of Activating Receptors of Natural Killer Cells (NKG2E and CD94) in Patients with Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Immunol. Lett. 2013;156:149–155. doi: 10.1016/j.imlet.2013.10.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.imlet.2013.10.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24177169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z., Zheng C., Tan Y.Y., Li Y.J., Yang L., Huang G., Lin J., Zhou Z.G. Gene Expression Changes in Patients with Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Chin. Med. J. 2011;124:3613–3617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22340212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roep B.O., Kleijwegt F.S., van Halteren A.G.S., Bonato V., Boggi U., Vendrame F., Marchetti P., Dotta F. Islet Inflammation and CXCL10 in Recent-Onset Type 1 Diabetes. Clin. Exp. Immunol. 2010;159:338–343. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2249.2009.04087.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2249.2009.04087.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2819499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20059481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berg A.-K., Korsgren O., Frisk G. Induction of the Chemokine Interferon-γ-Inducible Protein-10 in Human Pancreatic Islets during Enterovirus Infection. Diabetologia. 2006;49:2697–2703. doi: 10.1007/s00125-006-0429-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-006-0429-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16969644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagawa Y., Shimada A., Oikawa Y., Irie J.-I., Shigihara T., Tsumura K., Narumi S., Saruta T. Two Cases of “Fulminant” Type 1 Diabetes Suggesting Involvement of Autoimmunity. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 2003;1005:359–361. doi: 10.1196/annals.1288.059.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1196/annals.1288.059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14679092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka S., Nishida Y., Aida K., Maruyama T., Shimada A., Suzuki M., Shimura H., Takizawa S., Takahashi M., Akiyama D., et al. Enterovirus Infection, CXC Chemokine Ligand 10 (CXCL10), and CXCR3 Circuit. Diabetes. 2009;58:2285–2291. doi: 10.2337/db09-0091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db09-0091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2750208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19641142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawasaki E., Nakamura K., Kuriya G., Satoh T., Kobayashi M., Kuwahara H., Abiru N., Yamasaki H., Matsuura N., Miura J., et al. Zinc Transporter 8 Autoantibodies in Fulminant, Acute-Onset, and Slow-Onset Patients with Type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes Metab. Res. Rev. 2011;27:895–898. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.1269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/dmrr.1269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22069281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimada A., Oikawa Y., Shigihara T., Senda T., Kodama K. A Case of Fulminant type 1 Diabetes with Strong Evidence of Autoimmunity. Diabetes Care. 2002;25:1482–1483. doi: 10.2337/diacare.25.8.1482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diacare.25.8.1482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12145259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotani R., Nagata M., Imagawa A., Moriyama H., Yasuda H., Miyagawa J., Hanafusa T., Yokono K. T Lymphocyte Response against Pancreatic Beta Cell Antigens in Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Diabetologia. 2004;47:1285–1291. doi: 10.1007/s00125-004-1441-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-004-1441-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15243701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tada A., Shimada A., Yamada T., Oikawa Y., Yamada Y., Okubo Y., Irie J., Bluestone J.A., Itoh H. A Mimic of Viral Double-Stranded RNA Triggers Fulminant Type 1 Diabetes-Like Syndrome in Regulatory T Cell-Deficient Autoimmune Diabetic Mouse. J. Immunol. 2011;187:4947–4953. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1000837.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1000837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21967896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haseda F., Imagawa A., Murase-Mishiba Y., Terasaki J., Hanafusa T. CD4 + CD45RA − FoxP3 High Activated Regulatory T Cells Are Functionally Impaired and Related to Residual Insulin-Secreting Capacity in Patients with Type 1 Diabetes. Clin. Exp. Immunol. 2013;173:207–216. doi: 10.1111/cei.12116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cei.12116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3722921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23607886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haseda F., Imagawa A., Murase-Mishiba Y., Sano H., Hirano-Kuwata S., Ueda H., Terasaki J., Hanafusa T. Low CTLA-4 Expression in CD4+ Helper T-Cells in Patients with Fulminant type 1 Diabetes. Immunol. Lett. 2011;139:80–86. doi: 10.1016/j.imlet.2011.05.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.imlet.2011.05.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21620894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>