<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36597906</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Feb</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Local immune dysregulation and subsequent inflammatory response contribute to pulmonary edema caused by Enterovirus infection in mice.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e28454</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e28454</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.28454</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Pulmonary edema that comes on suddenly is the leading cause of mortality in hand-foot-and-mouth disease (HFMD) patients; however, its pathogenesis is still largely unclear. A range of research suggest immunopathogenesis during the occurrence of pulmonary edema in severe HFMD patients. Herein, to investigate the potential mechanism of immune dysregulation in the development of pulmonary edema upon Enterovirus (EV) infection, we established mouse infection models for Enteroviruses (EVs) including Coxsackievirus (CV) A6, Enterovirus A71 (EVA71), and CVA2 exhibiting a high incidence of pulmonary edema. We found that EVs infection induced an immune system disorder by reducing the numbers of pulmonary and circulatory T cells, B cells, macrophages, and monocytes and increasing the numbers of lung neutrophils, myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs), and activated T cells. In addition, the concentrations of C-X-C motif chemokine ligand 1 (CXCL-1), tumor necrosis factor-alpha, monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, and interleukin 6 were increased in EV-infected lungs. Moreover, we found that EVs replication in mice lungs lead to apoptosis of lung cells and degradation of tight junction proteins. In conclusion, EVs infection likely triggered a complexed immune defense mechanism and caused dysregulation of innate immune cells (MDSCs, neutrophils, monocytes, and macrophages) and adaptive cellular immunity (B cells, T cells). This dysregulation increased the release of cytokines and other inflammatory factors from activated immune-related cells and caused lung barrier damage and pulmonary edema.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Tiantian</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4895-4316</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Dong</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dai</LastName><ForeName>Xinchen</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Suzhou Institute of Systems Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meng</LastName><ForeName>Caiyun</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Suzhou Institute of Systems Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Suzhou Institute of Systems Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Cheng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3141-8568</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Wangquan</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Peiyu</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Shuaiyin</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6129-0310</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Haiyan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1797-304X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Yuefei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Weiguo</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Suzhou Institute of Systems Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duan</LastName><ForeName>Guangcai</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academy of Medical Science, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011654" MajorTopicYN="Y">Pulmonary Edema</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008168" MajorTopicYN="N">Lung</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hand-foot-and-mouth disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunophenotyping characteristics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neutrophils</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pulmonary edema</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36597906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Principi N. Hand, foot and mouth disease: current knowledge on clinical manifestations, epidemiology, aetiology and prevention. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2018;37(3):391-398.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu YF, Jia LP, Yu FY, et al. Molecular epidemiology of coxsackievirus A16 circulating in children in Beijing, China from 2010 to 2019. World J Pediatr. 2021;17(5):508-516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang SW, Cheng D, Wang JR. Enterovirus A71: virulence, antigenicity, and genetic evolution over the years. J Biomed Sci. 2019;26(1):81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yip CCY, Lau SKP, Woo PCY, et al. Recombinant coxsackievirus A2 and deaths of children, Hong Kong, 2012. Emerging Infect Dis. 2013;19(8):1285-1288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Chang Z, Wu P, et al. Emerging enteroviruses causing hand, foot and mouth disease, China, 2010-2016. Emerging Infect Dis. 2018;24(10):1902-1906.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez-López N, Muñoz-Almagro C, Launes C, et al. Surveillance for enteroviruses associated with hand, foot, and mouth disease, and other mucocutaneous symptoms in Spain, 2006-2020. Viruses. 2021;13(5):781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang H, Zhang Z, Rao Q, et al. The epidemiological characteristics of enterovirus infection before and after the use of enterovirus 71 inactivated vaccine in Kunming, China. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2021;10(1):619-628.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, Cohen R, Bisseux M, et al. A large-scale outbreak of hand, foot and mouth disease, France, as at 28 September 2021. Euro Surveill. 2021;26(43):2100978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ju Y, Tan Z, Huang H, et al. Clinical and epidemiological characteristics of coxsackievirus A6- and enterovirus 71-associated clinical stage 2 and 3 severe hand, foot, and mouth disease in guangxi, Southern China, 2017. J Infect. 2020;80(1):121-142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen M, Zuo X, Tan Y, et al. Six amino acids of VP1 switch along with pandemic of CV-A6-associated HFMD in guangxi, Southern China, 2010-2017. J Infect. 2019;78(4):323-337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamau E, Nguyen D, Celma C, et al. Seroprevalence and virologic surveillance of enterovirus 71 and coxsackievirus A6, United Kingdom, 2006-2017. Emerging Infect Dis. 2021;27(9):2261-2268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, Li Y, Zhang C, et al. Clinical features and phylogenetic analysis of severe hand-foot-and-mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6. Infect Genet Evol. 2020;77:104054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He YQ, Chen L, Xu WB, et al. Emergence, circulation, and spatiotemporal phylogenetic analysis of coxsackievirus a6- and coxsackievirus a10-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease infections from 2008 to 2012 in shenzhen, China. J Clin Microbiol. 2013;51(11):3560-3566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Nicholls JM, Liu F, et al. Pulmonary and central nervous system pathology in fatal cases of hand foot and mouth disease caused by enterovirus A71 infection. Pathology. 2016;48(3):267-274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y, Zhang C, Zhang R, et al. Pulmonary edema following central nervous system lesions induced by a non-mouse-adapted EV71 strain in neonatal BALB/c mice. Virol J. 2017;14(1):243.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang SW, Lee YP, Hung YT, et al. Exogenous interleukin-6, interleukin-13, and interferon-gamma provoke pulmonary abnormality with mild edema in enterovirus 71-infected mice. Respir Res. 2011;12(1):147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long L, Xu L, Xiao Z, et al. Neurological complications and risk factors of cardiopulmonary failure of EV-A71-related hand, foot and mouth disease. Sci Rep. 2016;6:23444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teoh HL, Mohammad SS, Britton PN, et al. Clinical characteristics and functional motor outcomes of enterovirus 71 neurological disease in children. JAMA Neurology. 2016;73(3):300-307.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong KT, Munisamy B, Ong KC, et al. The distribution of inflammation and virus in human enterovirus 71 encephalomyelitis suggests possible viral spread by neural pathways. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol. 2008;67(2):162-169.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Junttila E, Ala-Kokko T, Ohtonen P, et al. Neurogenic pulmonary edema in patients with nontraumatic intracerebral hemorrhage: predictors and association with outcome. Anesth Analg. 2013;116(4):855-861.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan LG, Parashar UD, Lye MS, et al. Deaths of children during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in sarawak, Malaysia: clinical and pathological characteristics of the disease. Clin Infect Dis. 2000;31(3):678-683.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SM, Lei HY, Huang KJ, et al. Pathogenesis of enterovirus 71 brainstem encephalitis in pediatric patients: roles of cytokines and cellular immune activation in patients with pulmonary edema. J Infect Dis. 2003;188(4):564-570.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan Z, Zhao R, Shen Y, et al. Low-frequency, exhausted immune status of CD56(dim) NK cells and disordered inflammatory cytokine secretion of CD56(bright) NK cells associated with progression of severe HFMD, especially in EV71-infected patients. Int Immunopharmacol. 2021;101:108369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y, Zhang C, Wang H, et al. Mast cells contribute to enterovirus 71 infection-induced pulmonary edema in neonatal mice. Lab Invest. 2018;98(8):1039-1051.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang N, Yang X, Sun J, et al. Neutrophil extracellular traps induced by VP1 contribute to pulmonary edema during EV71 infection. Cell Death Discov. 2019;5:111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan G, Yang H, Shi L, et al. Serum inflammatory cytokine levels correlate with hand-foot-mouth disease severity: a nested serial case-control study. PLoS One. 2014;9(11):e112676.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y, Li D, Sun T, et al. Pathological features of enterovirus 71-Associated brain and lung damage in mice based on quantitative proteomic analysis. Front Microbiol. 2021;12:663019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D, Sun T, Tao L, et al. A mouse-adapted CVA6 strain exhibits neurotropism and triggers systemic manifestations in a novel murine model. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2022;11(1):2248-2263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji W, Qin L, Tao L, et al. Neonatal murine model of coxsackievirus A2 infection for the evaluation of antiviral therapeutics and vaccination. Front Microbiol. 2021;12:658093.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed LJ, Muench H. A simple method of estimating fifty per cent endpoints12. Am J Epidemiol. 1938;27(3):493-497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrade ACSP, Campolina-Silva GH, Queiroz-Junior CM, et al. A biosafety level 2 mouse model for studying Betacoronavirus-Induced acute lung damage and systemic manifestations. J Virol. 2021;95(22):e0127621.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji W, Hu Q, Zhang M, et al. The disruption of the endothelial barrier contributes to acute lung injury induced by coxsackievirus A2 infection in mice. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(18):9895.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang ZY, Chen XQ, Sun D, Wei D. Mortality in children with severe hand, foot and mouth disease in guangxi, China. Indian Pediatr. 2018;55(2):137-139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prochetto E, Borgna E, Jiménez-Cortegana C, Sánchez-Margalet V, Cabrera G. Myeloid-derived suppressor cells and vaccination against pathogens. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2022;12:1003781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dang D, Zhang C, Zhang R, et al. Involvement of inducible nitric oxide synthase and mitochondrial dysfunction in the pathogenesis of enterovirus 71 infection. Oncotarget. 2017;8(46):81014-81026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Roller J, Slotta JE, et al. Distinct patterns of leukocyte recruitment in the pulmonary microvasculature in response to local and systemic inflammation. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol. 2013;304(4):L298-L305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Li Q, Li J, et al. Elevated levels of circulating histones indicate disease activity in patients with hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD). Scand J Infect Dis. 2014;46(12):818-824.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kellner M, Noonepalle S, Lu Q, et al. ROS signaling in the pathogenesis of acute lung injury (ALI) and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Adv Exp Med Biol. 2017;967:105-137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szturmowicz M, Demkow U. Neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs) in severe SARS-CoV-2 lung disease. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(16):8854.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gudbjörnsson B, Hällgren R, Nettelbladt O, et al. Phenotypic and functional activation of alveolar macrophages, T lymphocytes and NK cells in patients with systemic sclerosis and primary sjögren's syndrome. Ann Rheum Dis. 1994;53(9):574-579.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagtap S. Evaluation of CD4+ T-cells and CD8+ T-cells in triple-negative invasive breast cancer. Indian J Pathol Microbiol. 2018;61(4):477-478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang LY, Hsiung CA, Lu CY, et al. Status of cellular rather than humoral immunity is correlated with clinical outcome of enterovirus 71. Pediatr Res. 2006;60(4):466-471.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ke Y, Liu WN, Her Z, et al. Enterovirus A71 infection activates human immune responses and induces pathological changes in humanized mice. J Virol. 2019;93(3):e01066-18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Ma J, Xiu J, et al. Deferoxamine compensates for decreases in B cell counts and reduces mortality in enterovirus 71-infected mice. Mar Drugs. 2014;12(7):4086-4095.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>