<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36905116</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dynamic changes in polioviruses identified by environmental surveillance in Guangzhou, 2009-2021.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e28668</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e28668</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.28668</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Polio cases can be missed by acute flaccid paralysis (AFP) case surveillance alone, emphasizing the importance of environmental surveillance (ES). In this study, to investigate the serotype distribution and epidemiological trends of poliovirus (PV), we characterized PV isolated from domestic sewage in Guangzhou City, Guangdong Province, China from 2009 to 2021. A total of 624 sewage samples were collected from the Liede Sewage Treatment Plant, and the positive rates of PV and non-polio enteroviruses were 66.67% (416/624) and 78.37% (489/624), respectively. After sewage sample treatment, each sewage sample was inoculated in six replicate tubes of three cell lines, and 3370 viruses were isolated during the 13-year surveillance period. Among these, 1086 isolates were identified as PV, including type 1 PV (21.36%), type 2 PV (29.19%), and type 3 PV (49.48%). Based on VP1 sequences, 1057 strains were identified as Sabin-like, 21 strains were high-mutant vaccines, and eight strains were vaccine-derived poliovirus (VDPV). The numbers and serotypes of PV isolates in sewage were influenced by the vaccine switch strategy. After type 2 OPV was removed from the trivalent oral PV (OPV) vaccine and a bivalent OPV (bOPV) was adopted in May 2016, the last type 2 PV strain was isolated from sewage, with no detection thereafter. Type 3 PV isolates increased significantly and became the dominant serotype. Before and after the second vaccine switch in January 2020, that is, from the first dose of IPV and second-fourth doses of bOPV to the first two doses of IPV and third-fourth doses of bOPV, there was also a statistical difference in PV positivity rates in sewage samples. Seven type 2 VDPVs and one type 3 VDPV were identified in sewage samples in 2009-2021, and phylogenetic analysis indicated that all VDPVs isolated from ES in Guangdong are newly discovered VDPVs, different from VDPV previously discovered in China, and were classified as ambiguous VDPV. It is noteworthy that no VDPV cases were reported in AFP case surveillance in the same period. In conclusion, continued PV ES in Guangzhou since April 2008 has been a useful supplement to AFP case surveillance, providing an important basis for evaluating the effectiveness of vaccine immunization strategies. ES improves early detection, prevention, and control; accordingly, this strategy can curb the circulation of VDPVs and provide a strong laboratory basis for maintaining a polio-free status.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Meizhong</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5313-9792</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2692-5437</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO WPRO Regional Polio Reference Laboratory and Ministry of Health Key Laboratory for Medical Virology, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Shufen</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Shuangli</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO WPRO Regional Polio Reference Laboratory and Ministry of Health Key Laboratory for Medical Virology, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Caixia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Xue</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Hanri</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fang</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ke</LastName><ForeName>Bixia</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Hui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoshida</LastName><ForeName>Hiromu</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology II, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Wenbo</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO WPRO Regional Polio Reference Laboratory and Ministry of Health Key Laboratory for Medical Virology, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ke</LastName><ForeName>Changwen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deng</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoling</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Huanying</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012722">Sewage</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000509">alpha-Fetoproteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011055">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012722" MajorTopicYN="N">Sewage</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000509" MajorTopicYN="N">alpha-Fetoproteins</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011055" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">environmental surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine switch strategy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine-derived poliovirus</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36905116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Johnson Muluh T, Hamisu AW, Craig K, et al. Contribution of environmental surveillance toward interruption of poliovirus transmission in Nigeria, 2012-2015. J Infect Dis. 2016;213(suppl 3):S131-S135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyer O. Polio: WHO declares type 3 poliovirus eradicated after 31 year campaign. BMJ. 2019;367:l6201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mbaeyi C, Baig S, Khan Z, et al. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication-Pakistan, January 2020-July 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:1359-1364.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadigh KS, Akbar IE, Wadood MZ, et al. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication-Afghanistan, January 2020-November 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:85-89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macklin GR, Goel AK, Mach O, et al. Epidemiology of type 2 vaccine-derived poliovirus outbreaks between 2016 and 2020. Vaccine. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan D, Wang D, Zhang Y, et al. Implication of a high risk for type 2 vaccine-derived poliovirus emergence and transmission after the switch from trivalent to bivalent oral poliovirus vaccine. J Infect Dis. 2021;223:113-118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramirez Gonzalez A, Farrell M, Menning L, et al. Implementing the synchronized global switch from trivalent to bivalent oral polio vaccines-lessons learned from the global perspective. J Infect Dis. 2017;216:S183-S192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Zhu S, Yan D, et al. Type I vaccine-derived polioviruses in China from 1995 to 2019. Biosaf Health. 2019;1:155-158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pons-Salort M, Burns CC, Lyons H, et al. Preventing vaccine-derived poliovirus emergence during the polio endgame. PLoS Pathog. 2016;12:e1005728.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burns CC, Diop OM, Sutter RW, Kew OM. Vaccine-derived polioviruses. J Infect Dis. 2014;210(suppl 1):S283-S293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw AG, Majumdar M, Troman C, et al. Rapid and sensitive direct detection and identification of poliovirus from stool and environmental surveillance samples by use of nanopore sequencing. J Clin Microbiol. 2020;58:e00920-20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamisu AW, Blake IM, Sume G, et al. Characterizing environmental surveillance sites in Nigeria and their sensitivity to detect poliovirus and other enteroviruses. J Infect Dis. 2022;225(8):1377-1386.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hovi T, Shulman LM, van der Avoort H, Deshpande J, Roivainen M, De Gourville EM. Role of environmental poliovirus surveillance in global polio eradication and beyond. Epidemiol Infect. 2012;140:1-13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao Z, Zhang Y, Liu Y, et al. Isolation and characterization of a type 2 vaccine-derived poliovirus from environmental surveillance in China, 2012. PLoS One. 2013;8:e83975.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Tao Z, Li Y, et al. Environmental surveillance of human enteroviruses in Shandong Province, China, 2008-2012: serotypes, temporal fluctuation and molecular epidemiology. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2014;80(15):4683-4691.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu W, Zhang Y. Isolation and characterization of Vaccine-Derived polioviruses, relevance for the Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Methods Mol Biol. 2016;1387:213-226.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H, Harrington C, Gerloff N, et al. Validation of a redesigned pan-poliovirus assay and real-time PCR platforms for the global poliovirus laboratory network. PLoS One. 2021;16:e0255795.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA. Sensitive, seminested PCR amplification of VP1 sequences for direct identification of all enterovirus serotypes from original clinical specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44:2698-2704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Yan D, Zhu S, et al. Type 2 vaccine-derived poliovirus from patients with acute flaccid paralysis in China: current immunization strategy effectively prevented its sustained transmission. J Infect Dis. 2010;202:1780-1788.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swindell SR, Plasterer TN. SEQMAN: Contig assembly. In: Swindell SR, ed. Sequence Data Analysis Guidebook. Vol 70. Springer; 1997:75-89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Stecher G, Li M, Knyaz C, Tamura K. MEGA X: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis across computing platforms. Mol Biol Evol. 2018;35:1547-1549.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darriba D, Taboada GL, Doallo R, Posada D. jModelTest 2: more models, new heuristics and parallel computing. Nature Methods. 2012;9:772.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stamatakis A. RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies. Bioinformatics. 2014;30:1312-1313.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou NA, Fagnant-Sperati CS, Komen E, et al. Feasibility of the bag-mediated filtration system for environmental surveillance of poliovirus in Kenya. Food Environ Virol. 2020;12:35-47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivanova OE, Yarmolskaya MS, Eremeeva TP, et al. Environmental surveillance for poliovirus and other enteroviruses: long-term experience in Moscow, Russian Federation, 2004-2017. Viruses. 2019;11:424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delogu R, Battistone A, Buttinelli G, et al. Poliovirus and other enteroviruses from environmental surveillance in Italy, 2009-2015. Food Environ Virol. 2018;10:333-342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakamura T, Hamasaki M, Yoshitomi H, et al. Environmental surveillance of poliovirus in sewage water around the introduction period for inactivated polio vaccine in Japan. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2015;81:1859-1864.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asghar H, Diop OM, Weldegebriel G, et al. Environmental surveillance for polioviruses in the Global Polio Eradication Initiative. J Infect Dis. 2014;210(suppl 1):S294-S303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Reilly KM, Verity R, Durry E, et al. Population sensitivity of acute flaccid paralysis and environmental surveillance for serotype 1 poliovirus in Pakistan: an observational study. BMC Infect Dis. 2018;18:176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odoom JK, Obodai E, Boateng G, et al. Detection of vaccine-derived poliovirus circulation by environmental surveillance in the absence of clinical cases. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2021;17:2117-2124.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Guidelines for Environmental Surveillance of Poliovirus Circulation. WHO; 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroiss SJ, Ahmadzai M, Ahmed J, et al. Assessing the sensitivity of the polio environmental surveillance system. PLoS One. 2018;13:e0208336.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan Q, Zhu Q, Zheng H, et al. Epidemiological serosurvey of poliovirus in Guangdong, China: a cross-sectional study. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2018;14(11):2644-2648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitamura K, Shimizu H. The molecular evolution of type 2 vaccine-derived polioviruses in individuals with primary immunodeficiency diseases. Viruses. 2021;13(7):1407.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valesano AL, Taniuchi M, Fitzsimmons WJ, et al. The early evolution of oral poliovirus vaccine is shaped by strong positive selection and tight transmission bottlenecks. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29(1):32-43.e4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jorba J, Diop OM, Iber J, et al. Update on vaccine-derived polioviruses-worldwide, January 2016-June 2017. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017;66:1185-1191.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>