<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">36939356</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2165-0497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbiology spectrum</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microbiol Spectr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of Eleven RNA Extraction Methods for Poliovirus Direct Molecular Detection in Stool Samples.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0425222</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0425222</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e04252-22</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/spectrum.04252-22</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Direct detection by PCR of poliovirus RNA in stool samples provides a rapid diagnostic and surveillance tool that can replace virus isolation by cell culture in global polio surveillance. The sensitivity of direct detection methods is likely to depend on the choice of RNA extraction method and sample volume. We report a comparative analysis of 11 nucleic acid extraction methods (7 manual and 4 semiautomated) for poliovirus molecular detection using stool samples (<i>n</i> = 59) that had been previously identified as poliovirus positive by cell culture. To assess the effect of RNA recovery methods, extracted RNA using each of the 11 methods was tested with a poliovirus-specific reverse transcription-quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR), a pan-poliovirus RT-PCR (near-whole-genome amplification), a pan-enterovirus RT-PCR (entire capsid region), and a nested VP1 PCR that is the basis of a direct detection method based on nanopore sequencing. We also assessed extracted RNA integrity and quantity. The overall effect of extraction method on poliovirus PCR amplification assays tested in this study was found to be statistically significant (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001), thus indicating that the choice of RNA extraction method is an important component that needs to be carefully considered for any diagnostic based on nucleic acid amplification. Performance of the methods was generally consistent across the different assays used. Of the 11 extraction methods tested, the MagMAX viral RNA isolation kit used manually or automatically was found to be the preferable method for poliovirus molecular direct detection considering performance, cost, and processing time. <b>IMPORTANCE</b> Poliovirus, the causative agent of poliomyelitis, is a target of global eradication led by the World Health Organization since 1988. Direct molecular detection and genomic sequencing without virus propagation in cell culture is arguably a critical tool in the final stages of polio eradication. Efficient recovery of good-quality viral RNA from stool samples is a prerequisite for direct detection by nucleic acid amplification. We tested 11 nucleic acid extraction methods to identify those facilitating sensitive, fast, simple, and cost-effective extraction, with flexibility for manual and automated protocols considered. Several different PCR assays were used to compare the recovered viral RNA to test suitability for poliovirus direct molecular detection. Our findings highlight the importance of choosing a suitable RNA extraction protocol and provide useful information to diagnostic laboratories and researchers facing the choice of RNA extraction method for direct molecular virus detection from stool.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Akello</LastName><ForeName>Joyce Odeke</ForeName><Initials>JO</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0483-426X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Bujaki</LastName><ForeName>Erika</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vaccines, National Institute for Biological Standards and Control (NIBSC), MHRA, Potters Bar, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaw</LastName><ForeName>Alexander G</ForeName><Initials>AG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3166-872X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khurshid</LastName><ForeName>Adnan</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, National Institute for Health, Islamabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arshad</LastName><ForeName>Yasir</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, National Institute for Health, Islamabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Troman</LastName><ForeName>Catherine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Majumdar</LastName><ForeName>Manasi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vaccines, National Institute for Biological Standards and Control (NIBSC), MHRA, Potters Bar, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Toole</LastName><ForeName>Áine</ForeName><Initials>Á</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Evolutionary Biology, University of Edinburgh, Ashworth Laboratories, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rambaut</LastName><ForeName>Andrew</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Evolutionary Biology, University of Edinburgh, Ashworth Laboratories, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alam</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Masroor</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, National Institute for Health, Islamabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martin</LastName><ForeName>Javier</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5326-7081</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vaccines, National Institute for Biological Standards and Control (NIBSC), MHRA, Potters Bar, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grassly</LastName><ForeName>Nicholas C</ForeName><Initials>NC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>MR/R015600/1</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Microbiol Spectr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101634614</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2165-0497</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PCR amplification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RNA extraction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecular detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliovirus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36939356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10100708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.04252-22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hull HF, Ward NA, Hull BP, Milstien JB, Hull HF, de Quadros C. 1994. Paralytic poliomyelitis: seasoned strategies, disappearing disease. Lancet 343:1331–1337. doi:10.1016/s0140-6736(94)92472-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(94)92472-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7910329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. 2003. Guidelines for environmental surveillance of poliovirus circulation. https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/WHO_V-B_03.03_eng.pdf. Accessed 19 August 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood DJ, Hull B. 1999. L20B cells simplify culture of polioviruses from clinical samples. J Med Virol 58:188–192. doi:10.1002/(SICI)1096-9071(199906)58:2&lt;188::AID-JMV15&gt;3.0.CO;2-H.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9071(199906)58:2&lt;188::AID-JMV15&gt;3.0.CO;2-H</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10335869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. 2015. WHO Global Action Plan to minimize poliovirus facility-associated risk after type-specific eradication of wild polioviruses and sequential cessation of oral polio vaccine use. https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/208872. Accessed 1 July 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H, Harrington C, Gerloff N, Mandelbaum M, Jeffries-Miles S, Apostol LNG, Valencia MAD, Shaukat S, Angez M, Sharma DK, Nalavade UP, Pawar SD, Simbu EP, Andriamamonjy S, Razafindratsimandresy R, Vega E. 2021. Validation of a redesigned pan-poliovirus assay and real-time PCR platforms for the global poliovirus laboratory network. PLoS One 16:e0255795. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0255795.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0255795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8345876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34358268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw AG, Majumdar M, Troman C, O’Toole Á, Benny B, Abraham D, Praharaj I, Kang G, Sharif S, Alam MM, Shaukat S, Angez M, Khurshid A, Mahmood N, Arshad Y, Rehman L, Mujtaba G, Akthar R, Salman M, Klapsa D, Hajarha Y, Asghar H, Bandyopadhyay A, Rambaut A, Martin J, Grassly N. 2020. Rapid and sensitive direct detection and identification of poliovirus from stool and environmental surveillance samples by use of Nanopore sequencing. J Clin Microbiol 58:e00920-20. doi:10.1128/JCM.00920-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00920-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7448630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32611795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerloff N, Mandelbaum M, Pang H, Collins N, Brown B, Sun H, Harrington C, Hecker J, Agha C, Burns CC, Vega E. 2021. Direct detection of polioviruses using a recombinant poliovirus receptor. PLoS One 16:e0259099. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0259099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0259099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8562806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34727100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita M, Kilpatrick DR, Nakamura T, Burns CC, Bukbuk D, Oderinde SB, Oberste MS, Kew OM, Pallansch MA, Shimizu H. 2015. Development of an efficient entire-capsid-coding-region amplification method for direct detection of poliovirus from stool extracts. J Clin Microbiol 53:73–78. doi:10.1128/JCM.02384-14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.02384-14</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4290957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25339406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilpatrick DR, Yang C, Ching K, Vincent A, Iber J, Campagnoli R, Mandelbaum M, De L, Yang S, Nix A, Kew OM. 2009. Rapid group-, serotype-, and vaccine strain-specific identification of poliovirus isolates by real-time reverse transcription-PCR using degenerate primers and probes containing deoxyinosine residues. J Clin Microbiol 47:1939–1941. doi:10.1128/JCM.00702-09.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00702-09</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2691077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19386844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laassri M, Dipiazza A, Bidzhieva B, Zagorodnyaya T, Chumakov K. 2013. Quantitative one-step RT-PCR assay for rapid and sensitive identification and titration of polioviruses in clinical specimens. J Virol Methods 189:7–14. doi:10.1016/j.jviromet.2012.12.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2012.12.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23305817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monteiro L, Bonnemaison D, Vekris A, Petry KG, Bonnet J, Vidal R, Cabrita J, Mégraud F. 1997. Complex polysaccharides as PCR inhibitors in feces: Helicobacter pylori model. J Clin Microbiol 35:995–998. doi:10.1128/jcm.35.4.995-998.1997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.35.4.995-998.1997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC229720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9157172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan SC, Yiap BC. 2009. DNA, RNA, and protein extraction: the past and the present. J Biomed Biotechnol 2009:574398. doi:10.1155/2009/574398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2009/574398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2789530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20011662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shulman LM, Hindiyeh M, Muhsen K, Cohen D, Mendelson E, Sofer D. 2012. Evaluation of four different systems for extraction of RNA from stool suspensions using MS-2 coliphage as an exogenous control for RT-PCR inhibition. PLoS One 7:e39455. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0039455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0039455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3397973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22815706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iker BC, Bright KR, Pepper IL, Gerba CP, Kitajima M. 2013. Evaluation of commercial kits for the extraction and purification of viral nucleic acids from environmental and fecal samples. J Virol Methods 191:24–30. doi:10.1016/j.jviromet.2013.03.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2013.03.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23578704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrich A, Mahony J, Chong S, Broukhanski G, Gharabaghi F, Johnson G, Louie L, Luinstra K, Willey B, Akhaven P, Chui L, Jamieson F, Louie M, Mazzulli T, Tellier R, Smieja M, Cai W, Chernesky M, Richardson SE. Ontario Laboratory Working Group for the Rapid Diagnosis of Emerging Infections. 2006. Multicenter comparison of nucleic acid extraction methods for detection of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus RNA in stool specimens. J Clin Microbiol 44:2681–2688. doi:10.1128/JCM.02460-05.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.02460-05</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1594626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16891478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schroeder A, Mueller O, Stocker S, Salowsky R, Leiber M, Gassmann M, Lightfoot S, Menzel W, Granzow M, Ragg T. 2006. The RIN: an RNA integrity number for assigning integrity values to RNA measurements. BMC Molecular Biol 7:3. doi:10.1186/1471-2199-7-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2199-7-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1413964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16448564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kvastad L, Carlberg K, Larsson L, Villacampa EG, Stuckey A, Stenbeck L, Mollbrink A, Zamboni M, Magnusson JP, Basmaci E, Shamikh A, Prochazka G, Schaupp A, Borg Å, Fugger L, Nistér M, Lundeberg J. 2021. The spatial RNA integrity number assay for in situ evaluation of transcriptome quality. Commun Biol 4:57. doi:10.1038/s42003-020-01573-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s42003-020-01573-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7794352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33420318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul R, Ostermann E, Wei Q. 2020. Advances in point-of-care nucleic acid extraction technologies for rapid diagnosis of human and plant diseases. Biosens Bioelectron 169:112592. doi:10.1016/j.bios.2020.112592.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2020.112592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7476893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32942143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Old MO, Martinez CV, Kwock D, Garcia J, Martin G, Chan C, Maldonado YA. 2003. Direct extraction of Sabin poliovirus genomes from human fecal samples using a guanidine thiocyanate extraction method. J Virol Methods 110:193–200. doi:10.1016/s0166-0934(03)00133-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0166-0934(03)00133-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12798248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boom R, Sol CJ, Salimans MM, Jansen CL, Wertheim-van Dillen PM, van der Noordaa J. 1990. Rapid and simple method for purification of nucleic acids. J Clin Microbiol 28:495–503. doi:10.1128/jcm.28.3.495-503.1990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.28.3.495-503.1990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC269651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1691208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrington C, Sun H, Jeffries-Miles S, Gerloff N, Mandelbaum M, Pang H, Collins N, Burns CC, Vega E. 2021. Culture-independent detection of poliovirus in stool samples by direct RNA extraction. Microbiol Spectr 9:e00668-21. doi:10.1128/Spectrum.00668-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/Spectrum.00668-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8579935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34756088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. 2004. Polio laboratory manual. https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/68762. Accessed 1 July 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilpatrick DR, Iber JC, Chen Q, Ching K, Yang S, De L, Mandelbaum MD, Emery B, Campagnoli R, Burns CC, Kew O. 2011. Poliovirus serotype-specific VP1 sequencing primers. J Virol Methods 174:128–130. doi:10.1016/j.jviromet.2011.03.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2011.03.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21440569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hilz H, Wiegers U, Adamietz P. 1975. Stimulation of proteinase K action by denaturing agents: application to the isolation of nucleic acids and the degradation of ‘masked’ proteins. Eur J Biochem 56:103–108. doi:10.1111/j.1432-1033.1975.tb02211.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1975.tb02211.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1236799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGookin R. 1985. RNA extraction by the proteinase k method. Methods Mol Biol 2:109–112. doi:10.1385/0-89603-064-4:109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1385/0-89603-064-4:109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21374178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerloff N, Sun H, Mandelbaum M, Maher C, Nix WA, Zaidi S, Shaukat S, Seakamela L, Nalavade UP, Sharma DK, Oberste MS, Vega E. 2018. Diagnostic assay development for poliovirus eradication. J Clin Microbiol 56:e01624-17. doi:10.1128/JCM.01624-17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.01624-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5786708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29212703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stern A, Yeh MT, Zinger T, Smith M, Wright C, Ling G, Nielsen R, Macadam A, Andino R. 2017. The evolutionary pathway to virulence of an RNA virus. Cell 169:35–46. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2017.03.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.03.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5787669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28340348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>