<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34707960</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enteroviral Meningoencephalitis as a Complication of Rituximab Therapy for Rheumatoid Arthritis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e18189</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e18189</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e18189</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.18189</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviral meningoencephalitis is a rare complication of rituximab therapy that has been described in the treatment of hematologic malignancies. We report the first case of enteroviral meningoencephalitis in a patient receiving rituximab for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. A 37-year-old female treated with rituximab for severe rheumatoid arthritis presented with fever, headache, confusion, and tremor. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain was unrevealing. Cerebrospinal fluid showed a lymphocytic pleocytosis and multiplex polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was positive for enterovirus. She was treated with intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) for five days and had significant improvement in symptoms. Rituximab is an anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody that induces B-cell depletion and possible hypogammaglobulinemia, putting patients at increased risk for viral infections. We present this case to highlight that patients on rituximab, regardless of the indication for use, are susceptible to severe complications of otherwise typically self-limited viral infections. Furthermore, we describe the potential use of IVIG in treating these patients.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2021, Cook et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cook</LastName><ForeName>Samuel G</ForeName><Initials>SG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Wright State University Boonshoft School of Medicine, Dayton, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ford</LastName><ForeName>Aven W</ForeName><Initials>AW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Wright Patterson Medical Center, Wright Patterson AFB, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lindholm</LastName><ForeName>David A</ForeName><Initials>DA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Wright Patterson Medical Center, Wright Patterson AFB, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Scott</LastName><ForeName>Joshua</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Wright Patterson Medical Center, Wright Patterson AFB, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ivig</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meningoencephalitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rheumatoid arthritis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rituximab</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34707960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8533663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.18189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Multiple-year experience in the diagnosis of viral central nervous system infections with a panel of polymerase chain reaction assays for detection of 11 viruses. Huang C, Morse D, Slater B, et al. Clin Infect Dis. 2004;39:630–635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15356774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enterovirus meningitis in adults. Rotbart HA, Brennan PJ, Fife KH, Romero JR, Griffin JA, McKinlay MA, Hayden FG. Clin Infect Dis. 1998;27:896–898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9798053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enteroviral T-cell encephalitis related to immunosuppressive therapy including rituximab. Garzo-Caldas N, Ruiz-Sainz E, Vila-Bedmar S, et al. Neurology. 2017;89:408–409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5574672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28645913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biogen and Genentech, Inc Inc. South San Francisco, CA: Genentech, Inc.; 2021. Rituxan [Package Insert]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enteroviral meningoencephalitis as complication of rituximab therapy in a patient treated for diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. Servais S, Caers J, Warling O, Frusch N, Baron F, De Prijck B, Beguin Y. Br J Haematol. 2010;150:379–381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20408837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The host immune response in respiratory virus infection: balancing virus clearance and immunopathology. Newton AH, Cardani A, Braciale TJ. Semin Immunopathol. 2016;38:471–482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4896975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26965109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enteroviral infections in adults treated with rituximab: a new case of chronic meningitis and myofasciitis and literature review. (Article in French) Maillet F, Pineton De Chambrun M, Monzani Q, et al. Rev Med Interne. 2020;41:200–205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31980187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chronic enteroviral meningoencephalitis in a patient on rituximab for the treatment of psoriatic arthritis: a case report and brief literature review. Tellez R, Lastinger AM, Hogg JP. IDCases. 2019;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6522838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31193253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brainstem encephalitis caused by Coxsackie A16 virus in a rituximab-immunosuppressed patient. Cameron Smail R, O'Neill JH, Andresen D. BMJ Case Rep. 2019;12:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6720567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31451462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatal underhanded chronic enterovirus infection associated with anti-CD20 monotherapy for central nervous system demyelinating disease. Luciani L, Ninove L, Zandotti C, et al. Mult Scler. 2021;27:320–323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32584194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viral encephalitis associated with rituximab maintenance therapy: two cases and a review of literature. Noij DP, den Heijer T, van Zaanen HC. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32043478/ Neth J Med. 2020;78:37–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32043478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enteroviral encephalitis in a patient with a marginal zone lymphomatreated with rituximab. Schilthuizen C, Berenschot HW, Levin MD. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20508271/ Neth J Med. 2010;68:221–223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20508271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Successful treatment of echovirus meningoencephalitis and myositis-fasciitis with intravenous immune globulin therapy in a patient with X-linked agammaglobulinemia. Mease PJ, Ochs HD, Wedgwood RJ. N Engl J Med. 1981;304:1278–1281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6783908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chronic enteroviral meningoencephalitis in agammaglobulinemic patients. McKinney RE Jr, Katz SL, Wilfert CM. Rev Infect Dis. 1987;9:334–356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3296100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antibodies against enteroviruses in intravenous Ig preparations: great variation in titres and poor correlation with the incidence of circulating serotypes. Galama JM, Vogels MT, Jansen GH, Gielen M, Heessen FW. J Med Virol. 1997;53:273–276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9365895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>