<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">34724290</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2672</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>132</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of applied microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Appl Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Natural inactivation of MS2, poliovirus type 1 and Cryptosporidium parvum in an anaerobic and reduced aquifer.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2464</StartPage><EndPage>2474</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2464-2474</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jam.15349</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The study of microbial inactivation rates in aquifer systems has most often been determined in aerobic and oxidized systems. This study examined the inactivation (i.e. loss of infectivity) of MS2, poliovirus type 1 (PV1) and Cryptosporidium parvum in an anaerobic and reduced groundwater system that has been identified as storage zones for aquifer storage and recovery (ASR) facilities.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS AND RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Anaerobic and reduced (ORP &lt; <sup>-</sup> 250 mV) groundwater from an artesian well was diverted to an above-ground, flow-through mesocosm that contained diffusion chambers filled with MS2, PV1 or Cryptosporidium parvum. The respective infectivity assays were performed on microorganisms recovered from the diffusion chambers during 30- to 58-day experiments. The net reduction in infectivity was 5.73 log<sub>10</sub> over 30 days for MS2, 5.00 log<sub>10</sub> over 58 days for PV1 and 4.07 log<sub>10</sub> over 37 days for C. parvum. The best fit inactivation model for PV1 was the log-linear model and the Weibull model for MS2 and C. parvum, with respective inactivation rates (95% confidence interval) of 0.19 (0.17-0.21) log<sub>10</sub>  day<sup>-1</sup> , 0.31 (0.19-0.89) log<sub>10</sub>  day<sup>-1</sup> and 0.20 (0.14-0.37) log<sub>10</sub>  day<sup>-1</sup> .</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The groundwater geochemical conditions in this aquifer enhanced the inactivation of MS2, PV1, and C. parvum at rates approximately 2.0-5.3-fold, 1.2-17.0-fold, and 4.5-5.6-fold greater, respectively, than those from published studies that used diffusion chambers in aerobic-to-anoxic groundwater systems, with positive redox potentials.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SIGNIFICANCE AND IMPACT OF THE STUDY" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Geochemical conditions like those in the aquifer zone in this study can naturally and significantly reduce concentrations of microbial indicators and pathogens of human health concern in injected surface water. Appropriate storage times for injected surface water could complement above-ground engineered processes for microorganism removal and inactivation (e.g. filtration, disinfection) by naturally increasing overall microorganism log-inactivation rates of ASR facilities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021 Society for Applied Microbiology. This article has been contributed to by US Government employees and their work is in the public domain in the USA.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lisle</LastName><ForeName>John T</ForeName><Initials>JT</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5447-2092</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>St. Petersburg Coastal and Marine Science Center, U.S. Geological Survey, St. Petersburg, Florida, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lukasik</LastName><ForeName>George</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>BCS Laboratories, Inc., Gainesville, Florida, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>South Florida Water Management District</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>U.S. Geological Survey</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Appl Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9706280</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1364-5072</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000693" MajorTopicYN="N">Anaerobiosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003457" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cryptosporidiosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003458" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cryptosporidium</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016785" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cryptosporidium parvum</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060587" MajorTopicYN="Y">Groundwater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018508" MajorTopicYN="Y">Water Purification</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inactivation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">protozoa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">water</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34724290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.15349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Bae, J. &amp; Schwab, K. (2008) Evaluation of murine norovirus, feline calicivirus, poliovirus, and MS2 as surrogates for human norovirus in a model of viral persistence in surface water and groundwater. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 74, 477-484.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bazhanov, N., Escaffre, O., Freiberg, A., Garofalo, R. &amp; Casola, A. (2017) Broad-range antiviral activity of hydrogen sulfide against highly pathogenic RNA viruses. Scientific Reports, 7, 41029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bigelow, W. &amp; Esty, J. (1920) The thermal death point in relation to time of typical thermophilic organisms. Journal of Infectious Diseases, 27, 602-617.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charles, K.J., Shore, J., Sellwood, J., Laverick, M., Hart, A. &amp; Pedley, S. (2009) Assessment of the stability of human viruses and coliphage in groundwater by PCR and infectivity methods. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 106, 1827-1837.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dillon, P., Stuyfzand, P., Grischek, T., Lluria, M., Pyne, D., Jain, R. et al. (2019) Sixty years of global progress in managed aquifer recharge. Hydrogeology Journal, 27, 1-30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Florida Department of Environmental Protection (FDEP). (2013a) Drinking water standards, monitoring, and reporting. Florida Administrative Code Rule Chapter 62-550, Rules 102-828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Florida Department of Environmental Protection (FDEP). (2013b) Underground injection control. Florida Administrative Code Rules Chapter 62-528, Rules 100-900.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fout, S., Brinkman, N., Cashdollar, J., Griffin, S., Mcminn, B., Rhodes, E. et al. (2014) Method 1615 Measurement of Enterovirus and Norovirus Occurrence in Water by Culture and RT-qPCR. EPA/600/R-10/181, p. 116. Washington, DC: U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, L., Wei, Z., Hu, K., Hu, L., Li, Y., Chen, X. et al. (2018) Hydrogen sulfide inhibits the growth of Escherichia coli through oxidative damage. Journal of Microbiology, 56, 238-245.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geeraerd, A., Valdramidis, V. &amp; Van Impe, J. (2005) GInaFiT, a freeware tool to assess non-log-linear microbial survivor curves. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 102, 95-105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golder and Associates. (2007) Lake Okeechobee aquifer storage and recovery (ASR) regional project site characterization report: Construction of single-zone monitor well MW0010 and groundwater sampling site 2 (Kissimmee River site), Okeechobee County, Florida. Jacksonville, FL: Golder and Associates.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon, C. &amp; Toze, S. (2003) Influence of groundwater characteristics on the survival of enteric viruses. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 95, 536-544.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ives, R., Kamarainen, A., John, D. &amp; Rose, J. (2007) Use of cell culture to assess Cryptosporidium parvum survival rates in natural groundwaters and surface waters. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 73, 5968-5970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>John, D. &amp; Rose, J. (2005) Review of factors affecting microbial survival in groundwater. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 39, 7345-7356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson, A., Giovanni, G. &amp; Rochelle, P. (2012) Comparison of assays for sensitive and reproducible detection of cell culture-infectious Cryptosporidium parvum and Cryptosporidium hominis in drinking water. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 78, 156-162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisle, J. (2016) Natural inactivation of Escherichia coli in anaerobic and reduced groundwater. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 120, 1739-1750.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mafart, P., Couvert, O., Gaillard, S. &amp; Leguerinel, I. (2002) On calculating sterility in thermal preservation methods: application of the Weibull frequency distribution model. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 72, 107-113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maliva, R., Manahan, W. &amp; Missimer, T. (2021) Climate change and water supply: governance and adaptation planning in Florida. Water Policy, 23, 521-536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McFeters, G., Bissonnette, G., Jezeski, J., Thomson, C. &amp; Stuart, D. (1974) Comparative survival of indicator bacteria and enteric pathogens in well water. Applied Microbiology, 27, 823-829.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McFeters, G. &amp; Stuart, D. (1972) Survival of coliform bacteria in natural waters: field and laboratory studies with membrane-filter chambers. Applied Microbiology, 24, 805-811.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McFeters, G. &amp; Terzieva, S. (1991) Survival of Escherichia coli and Yersinia enterocolitica in stream water: comparison and field and laboratory exposure. Microbial Ecology, 22, 65-74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mesquita, M. &amp; Emelko, M. (2012) Bacteriophages as surrogates for the fate and transport of pathogens in source water and in drinking water treatment processes. In: Kurtboke, I. (Ed.) Bacteriophages (Chp. 4). London, UK: IntechOpen Limited, pp. 256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller, J. (1997) Hydrogeology of Florida. In Randazzo, A. &amp; Jones, D. (Eds.) The geology of Florida. Gainesville, FL: University Press of Florida, pp. 69-88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirecki, J. (2013). Comprehensive Everglades Restoration Plan aquifer storage and recovery pilot project: Final technical data report for the Kissimmee River and Hillsboro ASR systems. Jacksonville, FL: South Florida Water Management District, West Palm Beach, FL &amp; U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, pp. 370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirecki, J., Bennett, M. &amp; López-Baláez, M. (2013) Arsenic control during aquifer storage recovery cycle tests in the Floridan Aquifer. Groundwater, 51, 539-549.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell, J. &amp; Akram, S. (2017) Pathogen specific persistence modeling data. In Rose, J. &amp; Jimenez-Cisneros, B. (Eds.) Global water pathogen project. Lansing, MI: Michigan State University, pp 1-24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogorzaly, L., Bertrand, I., Paris, M., Maul, A. &amp; Gantzer, C. (2010) Occurrence, survival, and persistence of human adenoviruses and F-Specific RNA phages in raw groundwater. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 76, 8019-8025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page, D., Dillon, P., Toze, S. &amp; Sidhu, J. (2010) Characterising aquifer treatment for pathogens in managed aquifer recharge. Water Science &amp; Technology, 62, 2009-2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page, D., Miotlinski, K., Toze, S. &amp; Barron, O. (2014) Human health risks of untreated groundwater third pipe supplies for non-potable domestic applications. Urban Water Journal, 11, 461-466.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page, D., Vanderzalm, J., Barry, K., Torkzaban, S., Gonzalez, D. &amp; Dillon, P. (2015) E. coli and turbidity attenuation during urban stormwater recycling via aquifer storage and recovery in a brackish limestone aquifer. Ecological Engineering, 84, 427-434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plummer, N. &amp; Sprinkle, C. (2001) Radiocarbon dating of dissolved inorganic carbon in groundwater from confined parts of the Upper Floridan aquifer, Florida, USA. Hydrogeology Journal, 9, 127-150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pyne, D. (2005) Aquifer storage recovery: a guide to groundwater recharge through wells. Gainesville, FL: ASR Systems.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reese, R. &amp; Richardson, E. (2007) Synthesis of the hydrogeological framework of the Floridan Aquifer system and delineation of a major Avon Park permeable zone in central and southern Florida. Report 2007-5270. Reston, VA: USGS Scientific Investigations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regnery, J., Gerba, C., Dickenson, E. &amp; Drewes, J. (2017) The importance of key attenuation factors for microbial and chemical contaminants during managed aquifer recharge: a review. Critical Reviews in Environmental Science and Technology, 47, 1409-1452.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schijven, J. &amp; Hassanizadeh, S. (2002) Virus removal by soil passage at field scale and ground-water protection of sandy aquifers. Water Science and Technology, 46, 123-129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schijven, J., Hoogenboezem, W., Hassanizadeh, M. &amp; Peters, J. (1999) Modeling removal of bacteriophages MS2 and PRD1 by dune recharge at Castricum, Netherlands. Water Resources Research, 35, 1101-1111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott, T. (1988) The lithostratigraphy of the hawthorn group (miocene) of Florida. Tallahassee, FL: Florida Geological Survey Bulletin 59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidhu, J. &amp; Toze, S. (2012) Assessment of pathogen survival potential during managed aquifer recharge with diffusion chambers. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 113, 693-700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidhu, J., Toze, S., Hodgers, L., Barry, K., Page, D., Li, Y. et al. (2015) Pathogen decay during managed aquifer recharge at four sites with different geochemical characteristics and recharge water sources. Journal of Environmental Quality, 44, 1402-1412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidhu, J., Toze, S., Hodgers, L., Shackelton, M., Barry, K., Page, D. et al. (2010) Pathogen inactivation during passage of stormwater through a constructed reedbed and aquifer transfer, storage and recovery. Water Science and Technology, 62, 1190-1197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toze, S. (2004) Pathogen survival in groundwater during artificial recharge. In Steenvoorden, J. &amp; Endreny, T. (Eds.) Wastewater re-use and groundwater quality. Wallingford, UK: International Association of Hydrological Sciences, pp 70-84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toze, S., Bekele, E., Page, D., Sidhu, J. &amp; Shackleton, M. (2010) Use of static quantitative microbial risk assessment to determine pathogen risks in an unconfined carbonate aquifer used for managed aquifer recharge. Water Research, 44, 1038-1049.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA). (2001) Method 1602: Male-specific (F+) and Somatic Coliphage in Water by Single Layer (SAL) Procedure. Washington, DC: U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA). (2006) Ground water rule. Federal Register, 71, 65574-65660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waldron, M. &amp; Horvath, L. (2010) Construction of proximal monitor well #18 (MW-18), Kissimmee River ASR Pilot Site, Okeechobee County, Florida. Fort Myers, FL: Entrix Inc.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Y. &amp; Griffiths, M. (2013) Comparative persistence of subgroups of F-specific RNA phages in river water. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 79, 4564-4567.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yates, M., Gerba, C. &amp; Kelley, L. (1985) Virus persistence in groundwater. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 49, 778-781.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>