<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34853761</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Case Series on Enteroviral Meningitis in Pakistan.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e19048</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e19048</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e19048</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.19048</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses (EVs) are the most common cause of viral meningitis with a peak incidence between late summer and fall. The onset of symptoms is characteristically abrupt and typically includes headache, fever, nausea or vomiting, malaise, photophobia, and meningismus. In addition, diarrhea, upper respiratory symptoms, and a rash may also be present. The clinical presentation and epidemiologic features help in the diagnosis and it is confirmed by the detection of RNA in the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR). We present the clinical description, diagnosis, and management of five consecutive cases of viral meningitis secondary to enterovirus that presented to the emergency department at a tertiary care center in Karachi, Pakistan, over a span of five weeks during the monsoon season. These cases or outbreaks have not been reported previously in Pakistan and, hence, this case series is the first of its kind. All of our patients were young males, with ages between 18-35 years, did not have any prior co-morbidities, and resided in different localities of Karachi, Pakistan. The presenting complaints were severe headache in all five patients (100%), fever in all five patients (100%), and diarrhea in two out of five patients (40%). On examination, neck stiffness was present in all patients (100%). After the required workup and detection of RNA in the CSF by PCR, diagnosis of enteroviral meningitis was confirmed. The patients were given symptomatic treatment and discharged home with no neurologic complications. Aseptic meningitis occurring during the summer or fall is most likely to be caused by non-polio EVs (eg. coxsackievirus, echovirus, etc.). It is self-limiting and only requires supportive treatment. However, clinically it cannot be differentiated from other central nervous system infections and significant morbidity has been reported, including hospitalization and impairment of routine activities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2021, Jafri et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jafri</LastName><ForeName>Lubna</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurology, Aga Khan University Hospital, Karachi, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farooq Khan</LastName><ForeName>Ayisha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurology, Aga Khan University Hospital, Karachi, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arshad</LastName><ForeName>Tooba</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurology, Aga Khan University Hospital, Karachi, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanwar</LastName><ForeName>Dureshahwar</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurology, Aga Khan University Hospital, Karachi, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">case series</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">headache</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meningitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral meningitis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34853761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8608667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.19048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Viral meningitis. Logan SA, MacMahon E. BMJ. 2008;336:36–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2174764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18174598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enteroviruses: classification, diseases they cause, and approaches to development of antiviral drugs. Nikonov OS, Chernykh ES, Garber MB, Nikonova EY. Biochemistry (Mosc) 2017;82:1615–1631.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7087576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29523062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multiple-year experience in the diagnosis of viral central nervous system infections with a panel of polymerase chain reaction assays for detection of 11 viruses. Huang C, Morse D, Slater B, et al. Clin Infect Dis. 2004;39:630–635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15356774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viral meningitis: current issues in diagnosis and treatment. McGill F, Griffiths MJ, Solomon T. Curr Opin Infect Dis. 2017;30:248–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28118219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Outcome of treated paediatric clinical meningitis, with and without cerebro spinal fluid (CSF) analysis at a tertiary care hospital of Karachi. Aziz S, Ameer M. Acad J Ped Neonatol. 2019;8:555793.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enterovirus-associated encephalitis in the California encephalitis project, 1998-2005. Fowlkes AL, Honarmand S, Glaser C, et al. J Infect Dis. 2008;198:1685–1691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18959496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A clinical, epidemiologic and laboratory investigation of aseptic meningitis during the four-year period, 1955-1958. II. The clinical disease and its sequelae. Lepow ML, Coyne N, Thompson LB, Carver DH, Robbins FC. N Engl J Med. 1962;266:1188–1193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14464188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Value of repeat lumbar puncture in the differential diagnosis of meningitis. Feigin RD, Shackelford PG. N Engl J Med. 1973;289:571–574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4723106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapid detection of enterovirus RNA in cerebrospinal fluid specimens with a novel single-tube real-time reverse transcription-PCR assay. Verstrepen WA, Kuhn S, Kockx MM, Van De Vyvere ME, Mertens AH. J Clin Microbiol. 2001;39:4093–4096.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC88492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11682535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An outbreak of echovirus meningitis in children. Sathish N, Scott JX, Shaji RV, et al.  http://www.indianpediatrics.net/apr2004/apr-384-388.htm. Indian pediatrics. 2004;41:384–388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15123868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology profile of viral meningitis infections among patients in Qatar (2015-2018) Mathew S, Al Khatib HA, Al Ansari K, et al. Front Med (Lausanne) 2021;8:663694.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8241925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34222280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC: Viral meningitis.  [
Jun;
2021 
];https://www.cdc.gov/meningitis/viral.html 2021 12:2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enteroviral infections in primary immunodeficiency (PID): a survey of morbidity and mortality. Halliday E, Winkelstein J, Webster AD. J Infect. 2003;46:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12504601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enteroviral meningitis: natural history and outcome of pleconaril therapy. Desmond RA, Accortt NA, Talley L, Villano SA, Soong SJ, Whitley RJ. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2006;50:2409–2414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1489762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16801419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>