<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">34862630</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>94</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Epidemiological characteristics and cerebrospinal fluid cytokine profiles of enterovirus encephalitis in children in Hangzhou, China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2645</StartPage><EndPage>2652</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2645-2652</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.27504</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses (EVs) are common causes of viral encephalitis in children. To better understand the epidemiological and pathological characteristics of EV encephalitis, we enrolled suspected encephalitis patients younger than 15 years old in Hangzhou, China, from October 2016 to September 2019 for cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) collection and analyses. A total of 7735 CSF samples were collected, among which 330 (4.27%) were positive for the EV genome. The positivity rate was significantly higher in boys than girls (χ<sup>2</sup>  =  5.68, p =  0.02). The monthly case numbers peaked from June to August (80.30%). Among the different age groups, the 0-2 months age group showed the highest number of cases (28.48% of all cases). The 6-7 years (10.82%) and 9-10 years (9.29%) age groups showed the highest EV-positivity rates among suspected encephalitis cases. Sixty-two EV-positive and 53 control CSF samples were collected for Bio-Plex Pro human cytokine assays that simultaneously tested 48 cytokines. Principle component analyses showed significant separation between EV-positive and control samples, but insignificant separation between children and newborns. The levels of 28 cytokines and chemokines were significantly elevated in the EV-positive group including many proinflammatory and a few anti-inflammatory cytokines, as well as chemokines belonging to the CC and CXC subfamilies. Only one cytokine, stem cell growth factor-β, showed a decrease in the EV-positive group. Thus, this study revealed age, sex, and seasonal preferences for EV encephalitis incidences in children and identified many cytokines dysregulated during EV encephalitis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jialu</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Zeyu</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0218-2277</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Diagnosis and Treatment of Infectious Diseases, National Clinical Research Center for Infectious Diseases, Collaborative Innovation Center for Diagnosis and Treatment of Infectious Disease, The First Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7501-5707</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Lifang</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1321-2339</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Feng</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4907-7212</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pan</LastName><ForeName>Dongli</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0421-6242</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Microbiology and Parasitology, and Department of Infectious Diseases of Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016207">Cytokines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002555" MajorTopicYN="N">Cerebrospinal Fluid</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016207" MajorTopicYN="N">Cytokines</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004660" MajorTopicYN="Y">Encephalitis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018792" MajorTopicYN="Y">Encephalitis, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chemokines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cytokines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">encephalitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34862630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Chen BS, Lee HC, Lee KM, Gong YN, Shih SR. Enterovirus and encephalitis. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ai J, Xie Z, Liu G, et al. Etiology and prognosis of acute viral encephalitis and meningitis in Chinese children: a multicentre prospective study. BMC Infect Dis. 2017;17:494.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasbun R, Rosenthal N, Balada-Llasat JM, et al. Epidemiology of meningitis and encephalitis in the United States, 2011-2014. Clin Infect Dis. 2017;65:359-363.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Fischer M, Dominguez SR, Tyler KL, Abzug MJ. Encephalitis in US Children. Infect Dis Clin North Am. 2018;32:145-162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boucher A, Herrmann JL, Morand P, et al. Epidemiology of infectious encephalitis causes in 2016. Med Mal Infect. 2017;47:221-235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang LY, Huang LM, Gau SS, et al. Neurodevelopment and cognition in children after enterovirus 71 infection. N Engl J Med. 2007;356:1226-1234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudolph H, Schroten H, Tenenbaum T. Enterovirus infections of the central nervous system in children: an update. The. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2016;35:567-569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang LY, Lin HY, Gau SS, et al. Enterovirus A71 neurologic complications and long-term sequelae. J Biomed Sci. 2019;26:57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kothur K, Wienholt L, Mohammad SS, et al. Utility of CSF cytokine/chemokines as markers of active intrathecal inflammation: comparison of demyelinating, Anti-NMDAR and enteroviral encephalitis. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0161656.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing W, Liao Q, Viboud C, et al. Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2008-12: an epidemiological study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14:308-318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Zhang X, Chen X, et al. Epidemiology of childhood enterovirus infections in Hangzhou, China. Virol J. 2015;12:58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Jiang J, Zhang Y, Li W. Cytokine characteristic of cerebrospinal fluid from children with enteroviral meningitis compared to bacterial meningitis. J Clin Lab Anal. 2020;34:e23198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granerod J, Cunningham R, Zuckerman M, et al. Causality in acute encephalitis: defining aetiologies. Epidemiol Infect. 2010;138:783-800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesan A, Tunkel AR, Bloch KC, et al. Case definitions, diagnostic algorithms, and priorities in encephalitis: consensus statement of the international encephalitis consortium. Clin Infect Dis. 2013;57:1114-1128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rittichier KR, Bryan PA, Bassett KE, et al. Diagnosis and outcomes of enterovirus infections in young infants. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:546-550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu T, Fan XP, Wang WY, Yuan TM. Enterovirus infections are associated with white matter damage in neonates. J Paediatr Child Health. 2014;50:817-822.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fowlkes AL, Honarmand S, Glaser C, et al. Enterovirus-associated encephalitis in the California encephalitis project, 1998-2005. The. J Infect Dis. 2008;198:1685-1691.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Spence-Davizon E, Osborne C, et al. Clinical characteristics of enterovirus A71 neurological disease during an outbreak in children in Colorado, USA, in 2018: an observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:230-239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Miao Z, Yan J, et al. Sero-molecular epidemiology of enterovirus-associated encephalitis in Zhejiang Province, China, from 2014 to 2017. Int J Infect Dis. 2019;79:58-64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thoelen I, Lemey P, Van Der Donck I, Beuselinck K, Lindberg AM, Van Ranst M. Molecular typing and epidemiology of enteroviruses identified from an outbreak of aseptic meningitis in Belgium during the summer of 2000. J Med Virol. 2003;70:420-429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baek K, Yeo S, Lee B, et al. Epidemics of enterovirus infection in Chungnam Korea, 2008 and 2009. Virol J. 2011;8:297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Z, Li W, Xu J, et al. Proteomic analysis of cerebrospinal fluid in children with acute enterovirus-associated meningoencephalitis identifies dysregulated host processes and potential biomarkers. J Proteome Res. 2020;19:3487-3498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichinger A, Hagen A, Meyer-Buhn M, Huebner J. Clinical benefits of introducing real-time multiplex PCR for cerebrospinal fluid as routine diagnostic at a tertiary care pediatric center. Infection. 2019;47:51-58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan S, Jiang SC, Zhang ZW, Fu YF, Hu J, Li ZL. Quantification of cytokine storms during virus infections. Front Immunol. 2021;12:659419.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith JA, Das A, Ray SK, Banik NL. Role of pro-inflammatory cytokines released from microglia in neurodegenerative diseases. Brain Res Bull. 2012;87:10-20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm U, Klamp T, Groot M, Howard JC. Cellular responses to interferon-gamma. Annu Rev Immunol. 1997;15:749-795.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trinchieri G. Interleukin-12 and the regulation of innate resistance and adaptive immunity. Nat Rev Immunol. 2003;3:133-146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu M, Mizoguchi I, Morishima N, Chiba Y, Mizuguchi J, Yoshimoto T. Regulation of antitumor immune responses by the IL-12 family cytokines, IL-12, IL-23, and IL-27. Clin Dev Immunol. 2010;2010:2010-2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J, Zhu H, Murphy TL, Ouyang W, Murphy KM. IL-18-stimulated GADD45 beta required in cytokine-induced, but not TCR-induced, IFN-gamma production. Nature Immunol. 2001;2:157-164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li F, Wang Y, Yu L, et al. Viral infection of the central nervous system and neuroinflammation precede blood-brain barrier disruption during japanese encephalitis virus infection. J Virol. 2015;89:5602-5614.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asensio VC, Campbell IL. Chemokine gene expression in the brains of mice with lymphocytic choriomeningitis. J Virol. 1997;71:7832-7840.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farber JM. Mig and IP-10: CXC chemokines that target lymphocytes. J Leukoc Biol. 1997;61:246-257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salazar-Mather TP, Hamilton TA, Biron CA. A chemokine-to-cytokine-to-chemokine cascade critical in antiviral defense. J Clin Invest. 2000;105:985-993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu MT, Armstrong D, Hamilton TA, Lane TE. Expression of Mig (monokine induced by interferon-gamma) is important in T lymphocyte recruitment and host defense following viral infection of the central nervous system. Journal of immunology (Baltimore, Md: 1950). 2001;166:1790-1795.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorner BG, Scheffold A, Rolph MS, et al. MIP-1alpha, MIP-1beta, RANTES, and ATAC/lymphotactin function together with IFN-gamma as type 1 cytokines. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2002;99:6181-6186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Li S, Cai C, Xu Y, Jiang Y, Chen Z. Cerebrospinal fluid chemokine patterns in children with enterovirus 71-related encephalitis. Sci Rep. 2018;8:1658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koper OM, Kamińska J, Grygorczuk S, Zajkowska J, Kemona H. CXCL9 concentrations in cerebrospinal fluid and serum of patients with tick-borne encephalitis. Archives of medical science. 14. AMS; 2018:313-320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zajkowska J, Moniuszko-Malinowska A, Pancewicz SA, et al. Evaluation of CXCL10, CXCL11, CXCL12 and CXCL13 chemokines in serum and cerebrospinal fluid in patients with tick borne encephalitis (TBE). Adv Med Sci. 2011;56:311-317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boshtam M, Asgary S, Kouhpayeh S, Shariati L, Khanahmad H. Aptamers against pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokines: a review. Inflammation. 2017;40:340-349.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas SM, Kar S, Singh R, et al. Immunomodulatory cytokines determine the outcome of Japanese encephalitis virus infection in mice. J Med Virol. 2010;82:304-310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marques CP, Hu S, Sheng W, Cheeran MC, Cox D, Lokensgard JR. Interleukin-10 attenuates production of HSV-induced inflammatory mediators by human microglia. GLIA. 2004;47:358-366.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tun MM, Aoki K, Senba M, et al. Protective role of TNF-α, IL-10 and IL-2 in mice infected with the Oshima strain of Tick-borne encephalitis virus. Sci Rep. 2014;4:5344.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oakley OR, Garvy BA, Humphreys S, Qureshi MH, Pomeroy C. Increased weight loss with reduced viral replication in interleukin-10 knock-out mice infected with murine cytomegalovirus. Clin Exp Immunol. 2008;151:155-164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffiths MJ, Ooi MH, Wong SC, et al. In enterovirus 71 encephalitis with cardio-respiratory compromise, elevated interleukin 1β, interleukin 1 receptor antagonist, and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor levels are markers of poor prognosis. J Infect Dis. 2012;206:881-892.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stein A, Panjwani A, Sison C, et al. Pilot study: elevated circulating levels of the proinflammatory cytokine macrophage migration inhibitory factor in patients with chronic spinal cord injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2013;94:1498-1507.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>