<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">34913637</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2448-5667</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>59</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Med Inst Mex Seguro Soc</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>[Historical, clinical and epidemiological aspects of poliomyelitis in Mexico (1946-1960)].</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>585</StartPage><EndPage>590</EndPage><MedlinePgn>585-590</MedlinePgn></Pagination><Abstract><AbstractText>Poliomyelitis emerged in Europe as an epidemic disease at the end of the 19th century. During the thirties of the twentieth century it reached great intensity in the United States and Canada, but it was after the Second World War when the disease became a serious world public health problem, which punished several countries of the world, including Mexico. Poliomyelitis is a very contagious viral disease that invades the central nervous system (destroys motor neurons) that frightened the Mexican population in the first half of the twentieth century, not so much by high mortality and morbidity figures but by its paralytic sequels, like the disability, and by the fact that it affected one of the most vulnerable population groups: children. The disease mainly affected children under five years of age, being rare in the first months of life of the newborn due to the protective effect of immunity that the mother transfers to the son through breast milk; After eight months, at the end of the feed, the infant could be infected by poliovirus by invading the spinal cord and producing paralysis, most commonly of the legs or trunk. Likewise, it caused a paralysis in the respiratory muscles (diaphragm) of children, who had to help them to breathe since, if not, they were suffocated, so they were introduced in machines commonly known as steel lungs or lungs of Emerson type (machine that allows a person to breathe when he lost control of his respiratory muscles, such as the diaphragm, invented in 1928 by the American engineer Philip Drinker).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021 Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gómez-De Lara</LastName><ForeName>José Luis</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1547-1214</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universidad de Guadalajara, Centro Universitario de Ciencias Sociales y Humanidades. Zapopan, Jalisco, México.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rodríguez-Paz</LastName><ForeName>Carlos Agustín</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1802-0715</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Hospital General de Zona 50 del IMSS, Servicio de Cirugía. San Luis Potosí, San Luis Potosí, México.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>spa</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Historical, clinical and epidemiological aspects of poliomyelitis in Mexico (1946-1960).</VernacularTitle><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Mexico</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Med Inst Mex Seguro Soc</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101243727</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0443-5117</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002490" MajorTopicYN="N">Central Nervous System</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008800" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Mexico</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010243" MajorTopicYN="N">Paralysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014481" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United States</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>La poliomielitis emergió en Europa como enfermedad epidémica a finales del siglo XIX. Durante los años treinta del siglo XX alcanzó gran intensidad en los Estados Unidos y Canadá, pero fue tras la Segunda Guerra Mundial cuando la enfermedad se convirtió en un grave problema de salud pública mundial que castigó terriblemente a varios países del mundo, incluyendo a México. La poliomielitis es una enfermedad viral muy contagiosa que invade el sistema nervioso central (destruye las neuronas motoras) que atemorizó a la población mexicana en la primera mitad del siglo XX, no tanto por las altas cifras de mortalidad y morbilidad sino por sus secuelas paralíticas, como la invalidez, y por el hecho de que afectó a uno de los grupos poblacionales más vulnerables: los niños. La enfermedad afectaba principalmente a los niños menores de cinco años, siendo poco frecuente en los primeros meses de vida del recién nacido debido al efecto protector de la inmunidad que le transfiere la madre al hijo a través de la leche materna; después de ocho meses, al término de la alimentación, el infante podía ser infectado por el poliovirus invadiendo la medula espinal y produciendo la parálisis, más comúnmente de las piernas o tronco. Asimismo, ocasionaba una parálisis en los músculos respiratorios (diafragma) de los niños, a quienes había que auxiliarlos a respirar ya que, si no, se asfixiaban, por lo que se les introducía en unas máquinas conocidas comúnmente como pulmones de acero o pulmotores de tipo Emerson (máquina que permite a una persona respirar cuando esta perdió el control de sus músculos respiratorios, como el diafragma, inventada en 1928 por el ingeniero estadounidense Philip Drinker).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021 Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">History of epidemics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mexico</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poliomyelitis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34913637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>