<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35096227</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1937-8688</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>40</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pan African medical journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pan Afr Med J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Real-time monitoring of a circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus outbreak immunization campaign using digital health technologies in South Sudan.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>200</StartPage><MedlinePgn>200</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">200</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.11604/pamj.2021.40.200.31525</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">the use of digital health technologies and geographical information systems (GIS) in the conduct of immunization campaigns had proven to be a success story, and is gaining acceptance towards improving supervision, accountability, and real-time access to quality information. The demand for real-time information by policymakers and stakeholders in the polio eradication programme is increasing towards ensuring a world free from all polioviruses. This study aims to develop a tool that monitor and evaluate the circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus (cVDPV) campaign processes in real-time using open data kits (ODK) to collect data, analyze and visualize using an interactive dashboard in Power BI, towards improving timeliness and completeness of data reporting and providing real-time quality information to stakeholders.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">electronic checklists were developed using open data kits (ODK) and uploaded onto android-based smartphones for data collection during a round of cVDPV outbreak response immunization. Supervisors were deployed to the field and the checklists were utilized at both stages of the campaign activities. A Power BI data visualization tool was used for reporting, analysis, and monitoring the activities of the campaign.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">an interactive dashboard was developed, providing real-time information that supports stakeholders during the campaign processes with improved timeliness and completeness of data reporting. The usage of the tool during the campaign enhanced close supervision, and increased transparency in data availability and accessibility by all partners.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">the study had shown that real-time information has significantly improved the smooth conduct of the immunization campaign processes through identifying gaps, and challenges in the field and can be utilized in similar resource settings including complex and humanitarian. It has demonstrated the capability of mobile phones using ODK for data collection and linked to a Power BI dashboard for enhanced supervision and transparency, and we encourage further studies to assess the effects of the tools on the campaign results.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: Isah Mohammed Bello et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bello</LastName><ForeName>Isah Mohammed</ForeName><Initials>IM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO), Inter-Country Support Team Office for East and Southern Africa, Harare, Zimbabwe.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sylvester</LastName><ForeName>Maleghemi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO) Country Office, Juba, South Sudan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferede</LastName><ForeName>Melesachew</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO) Country Office, Juba, South Sudan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akpan</LastName><ForeName>Godwin Ubong</ForeName><Initials>GU</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO), Regional Office for Africa, Cite de Djoue, Brazzaville, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ayesheshem</LastName><ForeName>Ademe Tegegne</ForeName><Initials>AT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO) Country Office, Juba, South Sudan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mwanza</LastName><ForeName>Michael Nzioki</ForeName><Initials>MN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO), Regional Office for Africa, Cite de Djoue, Brazzaville, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okiror</LastName><ForeName>Samuel</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO), Regional Office for Africa, Cite de Djoue, Brazzaville, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anyuon</LastName><ForeName>Atem</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ministry of Health, Juba, South Sudan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oluseun</LastName><ForeName>Olu Olushayo</ForeName><Initials>OO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization (WHO) Country Office, Juba, South Sudan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>001</GrantID><Acronym>WHO_</Acronym><Agency>World Health Organization</Agency><Country>International</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Uganda</Country><MedlineTA>Pan Afr Med J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101517926</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014612">Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="ErratumIn"><RefSource>Pan Afr Med J. 2022 Feb 07;41:105. doi: 10.11604/pamj.2022.41.105.33607</RefSource><PMID Version="1">35222786</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007114" MajorTopicYN="N">Immunization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000068037" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">South Sudan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014612" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vaccines</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Geographic information system</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Power BI</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cVDPV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">circulating vaccine derived poliovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">open data kits</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35096227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8760295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11604/pamj.2021.40.200.31525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PAMJ-40-200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for Africa. Polio. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative World Health Organization. Circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative Vaccine-derived polioviruses - GPEI. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Global Polio Eradication Initiative Strategy for the response to type 2 circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus 2020-2021. 2020:1–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Food and Drug Association (FDA) What is digital health? 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nations U. The impact of digital technologies. 2020. Accessed on 6th September 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarke A, Blidi N, Dahn B, Agbo C, Tuopileyi R, Rude MJ, et al. Strengthening acute flaccid paralysis surveillance post Ebola virus disease outbreak 2015-2017: the Liberia experience. Pan African Medical Journal. 2019;33(Suppl 2):2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6675926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31402963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shuaib FMB, Musa PF, Gashu ST, Onoka C, Ahmed SA, Bagana M, et al. AVADAR (auto-visual AFP detection and reporting): demonstration of a novel SMS-based smartphone application to improve acute flaccid paralysis (AFP) surveillance in Nigeria. BMC Public Health. 2018;18(Suppl 4):1305.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6291924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30541508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ticha JM, Akpan GU, Paige LM, Senouci K, Stein A, Briand P, et al. Outcomes of the deployment of the auto-visual acute flaccid paralysis detection and reporting (AVADAR) system for strengthening polio surveillance in africa from 2017 to 2018: evaluation study. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2020;6(4):e18950.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7744265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33263550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Using SMS technologies to enhance polio surveillance. 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jusril H, Ariawan I, Damayanti R, Lazuardi L, Musa M, Wulandari SM, et al. Digital health for real-time monitoring of a national immunisation campaign in Indonesia: a large-scale effectiveness evaluation. BMJ Open. 2020;10(12):e038282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7733193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33303436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazi AM, Murtaza A, Khoja S, Zaidi AK, Ali SA. Monitoring polio supplementary immunization activities using an automated short text messaging system in Karachi, Pakistan. Bull World Health Organ. 2014 Mar 1;92(3):220–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3949591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24700982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Polio Network The use of digital technologies and approaches for real-time monitoring of supplementary immunization activities. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw R, Bosworth H. Short message service (SMS) text messaging as an intervention medium for weight loss: a literature review. Health Informatics J. 2012;18(4):235–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3675895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23257055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Touray K, Mkanda P, Tegegn SG, Nsubuga P, Erbeto TB, Banda R, et al. Tracking vaccination teams during polio campaigns in Northern Nigeria by use of geographic information system technology: 2013-2015. J Infect Dis. 2016 May 1;213(Suppl 3) Suppl 3:S67–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4818548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26609004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barau I, Zubairu M, Mwanza MN, Seaman VY. Improving polio vaccination coverage in Nigeria through the use of geographic information system technology. J Infect Dis. 2014 Nov 1;210(Suppl 1):S102–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balfour N, Wainaina Kinyanjui J, Mutai C. Mobile phone-based hygiene and sanitation promotion in Somalia. 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazi AM, Jafri LA. The use of mobile phones in polio eradication. Bull World Health Organ. 2016 Feb 1;94(2):153–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4750438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26908965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakakhan J, Al-Tamimi W, Butt MO ul I, Musani A, Abbass M. Use of real-time data transmission method for polio vaccination campaign monitoring in Iraq. 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzales IC. Philippines: 2020. Implementation of lot quality assurance sampling using mobile data collection tools to assess vaccination coverage after synchronized polio vaccination in the province of Camiguin.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haskew J, Kenyi V, William J, Alum R, Puri A, Mostafa Y, et al. Use of mobile information technology during planning, implementation and evaluation of a polio campaign in South Sudan. PLoS One. 2015;10(8):e0135362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4529202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26252383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ACAPS South Sudan complex crisis. Accessed on 6th September 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food Security Information Network Global Network Against Crises, 2020 global report on food crises. FaoOrg. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liebling H, Barrett H, Artz L. South Sudanese refugee survivors of sexual and gender-based violence and torture: health and justice service responses in Northern Uganda. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020 Mar 5;17(5):1685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7084827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA) South Sudan Humanitarian Needs Overview 2020 (November 2019) ReliefWeb. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartung C, Anokwa Y, Brunette W, Lerer A, Tseng C, Borriello G. ACM International Conference Proceeding Series. 2010. Open data kit: tools to build information services for developing regions.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomlinson M, Solomon W, Singh Y, Doherty T, Chopra M, Ijumba P, et al. The use of mobile phones as a data collection tool: a report from a household survey in South Africa. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2009 Dec 23;9:51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2811102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20030813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maduka O, Akpan G, Maleghemi S. Using android and open data kit technology in data management for research in resource-limited settings in the niger delta region of nigeria: cross-sectional household survey. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2017 Nov 30;5(11):e171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5786425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29191798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allmendinger RW, Siron CR, Scott CP. Structural data collection with mobile devices: accuracy, redundancy, and best practices. Journal of Structural Geology. 2017;102:98–112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesan M, Prashant S, Jhunjhunwala A. A review on challenges in implementing mobile phone based data collection in developing countries. Journal of Health Informatics in Developing Countries. 2012;6(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grantz KH, Meredith HR, Cummings DAT, Metcalf CJE, Grenfell BT, Giles JR, et al. The use of mobile phone data to inform analysis of COVID-19 pandemic epidemiology. Nat Commun. 2020 Sep 30;11(1):4961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7528106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32999287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MNM, UJM, AMN, IM, BK, DM . 2012. The benefits of using mobile phones in monitoring health interventions: the perspective from the neglected tropical diseases control in Tanzania. Accessed on 25th February 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Källander K, Tibenderana JK, Akpogheneta OJ, Strachan DL, Hill Z, ten Asbroek AH, et al. Mobile health (mHealth) approaches and lessons for increased performance and retention of community health workers in low-and middle-income countries: a review. J Med Internet Res. 2013 Jan 25;15(1):e17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3636306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23353680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murali-Ganesh R, Tan Z, Harvey A, Ballurkar K, Navani V, Pooviah N. From smartphone to electronic health record (EHR): an innovative implementation of patient-reported outcomes and patient-generated health data in routine cancer care. Asia-Pacific Journal of Clinical Oncology. 2018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown AE, Okayasu H, Nzioki MM, Wadood MZ, Chabot-Couture G, Quddus A, et al. Lot quality assurance sampling to monitor supplemental immunization activity quality: an essential tool for improving performance in polio endemic countries. J Infect Dis. 2014 Nov 1;210(Suppl 1):S333–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mbabazi WB, Tabu CW, Chemirmir C, Kisia J, Ali N, Corkum MG, et al. Innovations in communication technologies for measles supplemental immunization activities: lessons from Kenya measles vaccination campaign, November 2012. Health Policy Plan. 2015 Jun;30(5):638–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4421834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24920218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>