<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35149996</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>94</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Isolation and characterization of a novel clade of coxsackievirus B2 associated with hand, foot, and mouth disease in Southwest China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2598</StartPage><EndPage>2606</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2598-2606</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.27657</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Coxsackievirus B2 (CVB2) is an enterovirus B (EV-B) species and can cause aseptic meningitis, myocarditis and hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD). We characterized a novel CVB2 (YN31V3) associated with HFMD in Yunnan, Southwest China, in 2019. Although YN31V3 and other Mainland China epidemic strains mainly belonged to genotype C, YN31V3 formed an independent branch. The genome sequence of the strain YN31V3 from this study showed a 12.91% nucleotide difference to its closest strain RW41-2/YN/CHN/2012. Recombination analyses showed that the newly isolated YN31V3 was probably a recombinant, which was closely related to CVB2 strains in the genomic P1 region and other EV-B strains in the P2 and P3 regions, respectively. YN31V3 strain had a temperature-sensitive phenotype. The challenge of suckling BALB/c mice with YN31V3 could cause symptoms of disease and severe pathological lesions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2022 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Ming</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Danhan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Changzeng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fei</LastName><ForeName>Chengrui</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Hao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Zhaoqing</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Shaohui</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8992-1177</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Genetics, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Kunming, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016679" MajorTopicYN="N">Genome, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="N">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">complete genome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coxsackievirus B2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phylogenetic analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">temperature sensitivity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">virus recombination</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35149996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Jmii H, Fisson S, Aouni M, Jaidane H. Type B coxsackieviruses and central nervous system disorders: critical review of reported associations. Rev Med Virol. 2021;31(4):e2191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colli ML, Paula FM, Marselli L, et al. Coxsackievirus B tailors the unfolded protein response to favour viral amplification in pancreatic β cells. J Innate Immun. 2019;11(4):375-390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang HW, Chen YS, Chen JY, et al. Phylodynamic reconstruction of the spatiotemporal transmission and demographic history of coxsackievirus B2. BMC Bioinformatics. 2015;16:302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins KA, Abdou MH, Hadi MA. Coxsackie B2 virus infection causing multiorgan failure and cardiogenic shock in a 42-year-old man. Tex Heart Inst J. 2019;46(1):32-35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer T, Grumbach IM, Kreuzer H, Morguet AJ. Giant cell myocarditis due to coxsackie B2 virus infection. Cardiology. 1997;88(3):296-299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander JP Jr., Chapman LE, Pallansch MA, Stephenson WT, Török TJ, Anderson LJ. Coxsackievirus B2 infection and aseptic meningitis: a focal outbreak among members of a high school football team. J Infect Dis. 1993;167(5):1201-1205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sousa IP Jr, Machado RS, Burlandy FM, Silva E. Detection and characterization of a coxsackievirus B2 strain associated with acute meningoencephalitis, Brazil, 2018. Rev Soc Bras Med Trop. 2020;54:e20190499.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji H, Fan H, Lu P, et al. Surveillance for severe hand, foot, and mouth disease from 2009 to 2015 in Jiangsu province: epidemiology, etiology, and disease burden. BMC Infect Dis. 2019;19(1):79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Zhang H, Zhao Y, Guo C, Yang Z, Ma S. Molecular characterization of a new human coxsackievirus B2 associated with severe hand-foot-mouth disease in Yunnan Province of China in 2012. Arch Virol. 2017;162(1):307-311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blomqvist S, Bruu A-L, Stenvik M, Hovi T. Characterization of a recombinant type 3/type 2 poliovirus isolated from a healthy vaccinee and containing a chimeric capsid protein VP1. J Gen Virol. 2003;84(3):573-580.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Zhu S, Yan D, et al. Natural type 3/type 2 intertypic vaccine-related poliovirus recombinants with the first crossover sites within the VP1 capsid coding region. PLoS One. 2010;5(12):e15300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Zhao Y, Liu H, et al. Molecular characterization of two novel echovirus 18 recombinants associated with hand-foot-mouth disease. Sci Rep. 2017;7:8448.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martcheva M, Bolker BM, Holt RD. Vaccine-induced pathogen strain replacement: what are the mechanisms? J R Soc Interface. 2008;5(18):3-13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ang PY, Chong CWH, Alonso S. Viral determinants that drive enterovirus-A71 fitness and virulence. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2021;10(1):713-724.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midgley SE, Nielsen AG, Trebbien R, Poulsen MW, Andersen PH, Fischer TK. Co-circulation of multiple subtypes of enterovirus A71 (EV-A71) genotype C, including novel recombinants characterised by use of whole genome sequencing (WGS), Denmark 2016. Euro Surveill. 2017;22(26):30565.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu X, Wan Z, Li Y, Hu Y, Jin X, Zhang C. National epidemiology and evolutionary history of four hand, foot and mouth disease-related enteroviruses in China from 2008 to 2016. Virol Sin. 2020;35(1):21-33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang H, Zhang Z, Rao Q, et al. The epidemiological characteristics of enterovirus infection before and after the use of enterovirus 71 inactivated vaccine in Kunming, China. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2021;10(1):619-628.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng X-D, Tong Y, Wei Z-N, et al. Epidemical and etiological study on hand, foot and mouth disease following EV-A71 vaccination in Xiangyang, China. Sci Rep. 2020;10:20909.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Zhang H, Zhao Y, et al. Characterization of four vaccine-related polioviruses including two intertypic type 3/type 2 recombinants associated with aseptic encephalitis. Virol J. 2016;13(1):1-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Zhu Y, Pan Y, Liu Z, Guo C, Ma S. Complete genome sequence analysis of two human coxsackievirus A9 strains isolated in Yunnan, China, in 2009. Virus Genes. 2015;50(3):358-364.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y, Wang B, Huang H, Zhao Z. Enterovirus 71 induces anti-viral stress granule-like structures in RD cells. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2016;476(4):212-217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H-B, Yu L, Zhang J, et al. A 5-year molecular epidemiology survey of human enterovirus 71 before vaccine application in Yunnan Province, China. J Med Virol. 2020;92(8):1085-1092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan YF, Sam IC, AbuBakar S. Phylogenetic designation of enterovirus 71 genotypes and subgenotypes using complete genome sequences. Infect Genet Evol. 2010;10(3):404-412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao Z, Wang H, Xu A, et al. Isolation of a recombinant type 3/type 2 poliovirus with a chimeric capsid VP1 from sewage in Shandong, China. Virus Res. 2010;150(1-2):56-60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savolainen-Kopra C, Samoilovich E, Kahelin H, Hiekka AK, Hovi T, Roivainen M. Comparison of poliovirus recombinants: accumulation of point mutations provides further advantages. J Gen Virol. 2009;90(8):1859-1868.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagiwara A, Yoneyama T, Hashimoto I. Isolation of a temperature-sensitive strain of enterovirus 71 with reduced neurovirulence for monkeys. J Gen Virol. 1983;64(2):499-502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasri D, Bouslama L, Pillet S, Bourlet T, Aouni M, Pozzetto B. Basic rationale, current methods and future directions for molecular typing of human enterovirus. Expert Rev Mol Diagn. 2007;7(4):419-434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pu X, Qian Y, Yu Y, Shen H. Echovirus plays a major role in natural recombination in the coxsackievirus B group. Arch Virol. 2019;164(3):853-860.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukashev AN, Lashkevich VA, Ivanova OE, Koroleva GA, Hinkkanen AE, Ilonen J. Recombination in circulating Human enterovirus B: independent evolution of structural and non-structural genome regions. J Gen Virol. 2005;86(12):3281-3290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Peñaranda S, Pallansch MA. RNA recombination plays a major role in genomic change during circulation of coxsackie B viruses. J Virol. 2004;78(6):2948-2955.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trovão NS, Shepherd FK, Herzberg K, et al. Evolution of rotavirus C in humans and several domestic animal species. Zoonoses Public Health. 2019;66(5):546-557.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Liu H, Zhao Y, et al. Identification of a new recombinant strain of echovirus 33 from children with hand, foot, and mouth disease complicated by meningitis in Yunnan, China. Virol J. 2019;16(1):1-7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martino TA, Petric M, Weingartl H, et al. The coxsackie-adenovirus receptor (CAR) is used by reference strains and clinical isolates representing all six serotypes of coxsackievirus group B and by swine vesicular disease virus. Virology. 2000;271(1):99-108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergelson JM, Cunningham JA, Droguett G, et al. Isolation of a common receptor for Coxsackie B viruses and adenoviruses 2 and 5. Science. 1997;275(5304):1320-1323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomko RP, Xu R, Philipson L. HCAR and MCAR: the human and mouse cellular receptors for subgroup C adenoviruses and group B coxsackieviruses. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 1997;94(7):3352-3356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergelson JM, Mohanty JG, Crowell RL, St John NF, Lublin DM, Finberg RW. Coxsackievirus B3 adapted to growth in RD cells binds to decay-accelerating factor (CD55). J Virol. 1995;69(3):1903-1906.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polacek C, Ekström J-O, Lundgren A, Lindberg AM. Cytolytic replication of coxsackievirus B2 in CAR-deficient rhabdomyosarcoma cells. Virus Res. 2005;113(2):107-115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minor PD, Dunn G, Evans DM, et al. The temperature sensitivity of the Sabin type 3 vaccine strain of poliovirus: molecular and structural effects of a mutation in the capsid protein VP3. J Gen Virol. 1989;70(5):1117-1123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong J, Kang B, Yeo S, Jee Y, Park JH. Pathogenesis of coxsackievirus B2 in mice: characterization of clinical isolates of the coxsackievirus B2 from patients with myocarditis and aseptic meningitis in Korea. J Vet Sci. 2017;18(4):457-464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biebricher CK, Eigen M. What is a quasispecies? Curr Top Microbiol Immunol. 2006;299:1-31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KS, Tracy S, Tapprich W, et al. 5ʹ-Terminal deletions occur in coxsackievirus B3 during replication in murine hearts and cardiac myocyte cultures and correlate with encapsidation of negative-strand viral RNA. J Virol. 2005;79(11):7024-7041.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>