<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35365341</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-2518</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>41 Suppl 1</Volume><Issue>Suppl 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Apr</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Vaccine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vaccine</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Review of use of inactivated poliovirus vaccine in campaigns to control type 2 circulating vaccine derived poliovirus (cVDPV) outbreaks.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>A113</StartPage><EndPage>A121</EndPage><MedlinePgn>A113-A121</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.03.027</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0264-410X(22)00304-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Delivering inactivated poliovirus vaccine (IPV) with oral poliovirus vaccine (OPV) in campaigns has been explored to accelerate the control of type 2 circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus (cVDPV) outbreaks. A review of scientific literature suggests that among populations with high prevalence of OPV failure, a booster with IPV after at least two doses of OPV may close remaining humoral and mucosal immunity gaps more effectively than an additional dose of trivalent OPV. However, IPV alone demonstrates minimal advantage on humoral immunity compared with monovalent and bivalent OPV, and cannot provide the intestinal immunity that prevents infection and spread to those individuals not previously exposed to live poliovirus of the same serotype (i.e. type 2 for children born after the switch from trivalent to bivalent OPV in April 2016). A review of operational data from polio campaigns shows that addition of IPV increases the cost and logistic complexity of campaigns. As a result, campaigns in response to an outbreak often target small areas. Large campaigns require a delay to ensure logistics are in place for IPV delivery, and may need implementation in phases that last several weeks. Challenges to delivery of injectable vaccines through house-to-house visits also increases the risk of missing the children who are more likely to benefit from IPV: those with difficult access to routine immunization and other health services. Based upon this information, the Strategic Advisory Group of Experts in immunization (SAGE) recommended in October 2020 the following strategies: provision of a second dose of IPV in routine immunization to reduce the risk and number of paralytic cases in countries at risk of importation or new emergences; and use of type 2 OPV in high-quality campaigns to interrupt transmission and avoid seeding new type 2 cVDPV outbreaks.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2022. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Estivariz</LastName><ForeName>Concepcion F</ForeName><Initials>CF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1600 Clifton Road, Atlanta, GA 30329, USA. Electronic address: cge3@cdc.gov.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kovacs</LastName><ForeName>Stephanie D</ForeName><Initials>SD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1600 Clifton Road, Atlanta, GA 30329, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mach</LastName><ForeName>Ondrej</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Polio Eradication Department, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>001</GrantID><Acronym>WHO_</Acronym><Agency>World Health Organization</Agency><Country>International</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CC999999</GrantID><Acronym>ImCDC</Acronym><Agency>Intramural CDC HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Vaccine</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8406899</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0264-410X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011054">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011055">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011054" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011055" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Campaigns</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Inactivated poliovirus vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Oral poliovirus vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Outbreak response</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35365341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1913181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10389290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.03.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0264-410X(22)00304-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Global circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus cases, 2000–2018. Available at http://polioeradication.org/polio-today/polio-now/this-week/circulating-vaccine-derived-poliovirus. Accessed 16 December 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirreff G, Wadood MZ, Vaz RG, Sutter RW, Grassly NC. Estimated effect of inactivated poliovirus vaccine campaigns, Nigeria and Pakistan, January 2014-April 2016. Emerg Infect Dis 2017;23:258–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5324799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27861118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Meeting of the Strategic Advisory Group of Experts on Immunization, 31 March - 1 April 2020: conclusions and recommendations. Wkly Epidemiol Rec. 2020;95:241–56</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Meeting of the Strategic Advisory Group of Experts on immunization, October 2020 - conclusions and recommendations. Wkly Epidemiol Rec. 2020;92:301–20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fine PE, Carneiro IA. Transmissibility and persistence of oral polio vaccine viruses: implications for the global poliomyelitis eradication initiative. Am J Epidemiol 1999;150:1001–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10568615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogra PL, Fishaut M, Gallagher MR. Viral vaccination via the mucosal routes. Rev Infect Dis 1980;2:352–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6997965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutter RW, Pallansch MA, Sawyer LA, Cochi SL, Hadler SC. Defining surrogate serologic tests with respect to predicting protective vaccine efficacy: poliovirus vaccination. Ann N Y Acad Sci 1995;754:289–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7625665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gelfand HM, Potash L, LeBlanc DR, Fox JP. Revised preliminary report on the Louisiana observations of the natural spread within families of living vaccine strains of poliovirus. In: First International Conference on live poliovirus vaccines. p. 203–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghendon Y, Sanakoyeva II. Comparison of the resistance of the intestinal tract ot poliomyelitis virus (Sabin’s strains) in persons after naturally and experimentally acquired immunity. Acta Virol 1961;5:265–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onorato IM, Modlin JF, McBean AM, Thoms ML, Losonsky GA, Bernier RH. Mucosal immunity induced by enhanced-potency inactivated and oral polio vaccines. J Infect Dis 1991;163:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1845806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutter RW, Patriarca PA. Inactivated and live, attenuated poliovirus vaccines: mucosal immunity. In: Kurstak E, editor. Measles and poliomyelitis. Austria: Springer-Verlag; 1993. p. 279–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hird TR, Grassly NC. Systematic review of mucosal immunity induced by oral and inactivated poliovirus vaccines against virus shedding following oral poliovirus challenge. PLoS Pathog, 8. p. e1002599.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3330118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22532797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafari H, Deshpande JM, Sutter RW, Bahl S, Verma H, Ahmad M, et al. Polio eradication. efficacy of inactivated poliovirus vaccine in India. Science 2014;345:922–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10389671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25146288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John J, Giri S, Karthikeyan AS, Iturriza-Gomara M, Muliyil J, Abraham A, et al. Effect of a single inactivated poliovirus vaccine dose on intestinal immunity against poliovirus in children previously given oral vaccine: an open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2014;384:1505–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25018120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benyesh-Melnick M, Melnick JL, Rawls WE, Wimberly I, Oro JB, Ben-Porath E, et al. Studies of the immunogenicity, communicability and genetic stability of oral poliovaccine administered during the winter. Am J Epidemiol 1967;86:112–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4378110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heymann DL, Murphy K, Brigaud M, Aymard M, Tembon A, Maben GK. Oral poliovirus vaccine in tropical Africa: greater impact on incidence of paralytic disease than expected from coverage surveys and seroconversion rates. Bull World Health Organ 1987;65:495–501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2491033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3500802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platt LR, Estivariz CF, Sutter RW. Vaccine-associated paralytic poliomyelitis: a review of the epidemiology and estimation of the global burden. J Infect Dis 2014;210(Suppl 1):S380–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10424844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burns CC, Diop OM, Sutter RW, Kew OM. Vaccine-derived polioviruses. J Infect Dis 2014;210(Suppl 1):S283–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macklin GR, O’Reilly KM, Grassly NC, Edmunds WJ, Mach O, Santhana Gopala Krishnan R, et al. Evolving epidemiology of poliovirus serotype 2 following withdrawal of the serotype 2 oral poliovirus vaccine. Science 2020;368:401–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10805349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32193361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estívariz CF, Pallansch MA, Anand A, Wassilak SGF, Sutter RW, Wenger JD, et al. Poliovirus vaccination options for achieving eradication and securing the endgame. Curr Opin Virol 2013;3:309–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10395005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23759252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patriarca PA, Wright PF, John TJ. Factors affecting the immunogenicity of oral poliovirus vaccine in developing countries: review. Rev Infect Dis 1991;13:926–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1660184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem AF, Mach O, Quadri F, Khan A, Bhatti Z, Rehman Nu, et al. Immunogenicity of poliovirus vaccines in chronically malnourished infants: a randomized controlled trial in Pakistan. Vaccine 2015;33:2757–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4447616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25917673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patriarca PA, Linkins RW, Sutter RW. Poliovirus vaccine formulations. In: Kurstak E, editor. Measles and Poliomyelitis. Wiena: Springer-Verlag; 1993. p. 267–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birmingham ME, Aylward RB, Cochi SL, Hull HF. National immunization days: state of the art. J Infect Dis 1997;175(Suppl 1):S183–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9203714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>el-Sayed N, el-Gamal Y, Abbassy AA, Seoud I, Salama M, Kandeel A, et al. Monovalent type 1 oral poliovirus vaccine in newborns. N Engl J Med. 2008;359:1655–65</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18923170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estívariz CF, Anand A, Gary HE Jr, Rahman M, Islam J, Bari TI, et al. Immunogenicity of three doses of bivalent, trivalent, or type 1 monovalent oral poliovirus vaccines with a 2 week interval between doses in Bangladesh: an open-label, non-inferiority, randomised, controlled trial. Lancet Infect Dis 2015;5:898–904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10406135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26093980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John TJ, Jain H, Ravishankar K, Amaresh A, Verma H, Deshpande J, et al. Monovalent type 1 oral poliovirus vaccine among infants in India: report of two randomized double-blind controlled clinical trials. Vaccine 2011;29:5793–801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21641951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutter RW, John TJ, Jain H, Agarkhedkar S, Ramanan PV, Verma H, et al. Immunogenicity of bivalent types 1 and 3 oral poliovirus vaccine: a randomised, double-blind, controlled trial. Lancet 2010;376: 1682–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20980048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaman K, Estivariz CF, Morales M, Yunus M, Snider CJ, Gary HE Jr, et al. Immunogenicity of type 2 monovalent oral and inactivated poliovirus vaccines for type 2 poliovirus outbreak response: an open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018;18:657–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10495755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29571817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Progress toward interruption of wild poliovirus transmission - worldwide, 2009. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2010;59:545–50</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20467412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wassilak SG, Oberste MS, Tangermann RH, Diop OM, Jafari HS, Armstrong GL. Progress toward global interruption of wild poliovirus transmission, 2010–2013, and tackling the challenges to complete eradication. J Infect Dis 2014;210(Suppl 1):S5–S15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4615678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahl S, Kumar R, Menabde N, Thapa A, McFarland J, Swezy V, et al. Polio-free certification and lessons learned–South-East Asia region, March 2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2014;63:941–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5779468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25340910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grassly NC. Immunogenicity and effectiveness of routine immunization with 1 or 2 doses of inactivated poliovirus vaccine: systematic review and meta-analysis. J Infect Dis 2014;210(Suppl 1):S439–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4197908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24634499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anand A, Zaman K, Estivariz CF, Yunus M, Gary H, E., Weldon WC, et al. Early priming with inactivated poliovirus vaccine (IPV) and intradermal fractional dose IPV administered by a microneedle device: A randomized controlled trial. Vaccine. 2015;33:6816–22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10423714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26476367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snider CJ, Zaman K, Estivariz CF, Yunus M, Weldon WC, Wannemuehler KA, et al. Immunogenicity of full and fractional dose of inactivated poliovirus vaccine for use in routine immunisation and outbreak response: an open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2019;393:2624–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7069654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31104832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resik S, Tejeda A, Sutter RW, Diaz M, Sarmiento L, Alemani N, et al. Priming after a fractional dose of inactivated poliovirus vaccine. New Eng J Med 2013;368:416–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23363495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay AS, Gast C, Rivera L, Sáez-Llorens X, Oberste MS, Weldon WC, et al. Safety and immunogenicity of inactivated poliovirus vaccine schedules for the post-eradication era: a randomised open-label, multicentre, phase 3, non-inferiority trial. Lancet Infect Dis 2020;21:559–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7992032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33284114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macklin GR, Grassly NC, Sutter RW, Mach O, Bandyopadhyay AS, Edmunds WJ, et al. Vaccine schedules and the effect on humoral and intestinal immunity against poliovirus: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Lancet Infect Dis 2019;19:1121–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31350192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem AF, Mach O, Yousafzai MT, Khan A, Weldon WC, Steven Oberste M, et al. Immunogenicity of different routine poliovirus vaccination schedules: a randomized, controlled trial in Karachi, Pakistan. J Infect Dis 2018;217:443–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7191618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29126173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibby J, Saidu Y, Umesi A, Moneke-Anyanwoke N, Bashorun AO, Hydara MB, et al. The immunogenicity of fractional intradermal doses of the inactivated poliovirus vaccine is associated with the size of the intradermal fluid bleb. Clin Infect Dis 2017;65:851–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28444156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parent du Chatelet I, Merchant AT, Fisher-Hoch S, Luby SP, Plotkin SA, Moatter T, et al. Serological response and poliovirus excretion following different combined oral and inactivated poliovirus vaccines immunization schedules. Vaccine 2003;21:1710–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12639494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutter RW, Bahl S, Deshpande JM, Verma H, Ahmad M, Venugopal P, et al. Immunogenicity of a new routine vaccination schedule for global poliomyelitis prevention: an open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2015;386:2013–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26388534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asturias EJ, Bandyopadhyay AS, Self S, Rivera L, Saez-Llorens X, Lopez E, et al. Humoral and intestinal immunity induced by new schedules of bivalent oral poliovirus vaccine and one or two doses of inactivated poliovirus vaccine in Latin American infants: an open-label randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2016;388:158–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27212429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez-Medina E, Melgar M, Gaensbauer JT, Bandyopadhyay AS, Borate BR, Weldon WC, et al. Inactivated polio vaccines from three different manufacturers have equivalent safety and immunogenicity when given as 1 or 2 additional doses after bivalent OPV: results from a randomized controlled trial in Latin America. Vaccine 2017;35:3591–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5464088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28455172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saez-Llorens X, Clemens R, Leroux-Roels G, Jimeno J, Clemens SA, Weldon WC, et al. Immunogenicity and safety of a novel monovalent high-dose inactivated poliovirus type 2 vaccine in infants: a comparative, observer-blind, randomised, controlled trial. Lancet Infect Dis 2016;16:321–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9108810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26719058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moriniere BJ, van Loon FP, Rhodes PH, Klein-Zabban ML, Frank-Senat B, Herrington JE, et al. Immunogenicity of a supplemental dose of oral versus inactivated poliovirus vaccine Lancet. 1993;341:1545–50</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8099637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanlon P, Hanlon L, Marsh V, Byass P, Sillah H, Hayes R, et al. Serological comparisons of approaches to polio vaccination in the Gambia Lancet. 1987;1:800–1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2882198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutter RW, Suleiman AJ, Malankar P, Al-Khusaiby S, Mehta F, Clements GB, et al. Trial of a supplemental dose of four poliovirus vaccines. N Engl J Med 2000;343:767–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10984564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resik S, Tejeda A, Mach O, Fonseca M, Diaz M, Alemany N, et al. Immune responses after fractional doses of inactivated poliovirus vaccine using newly developed intradermal jet injectors: a randomized controlled trial in Cuba. Vaccine 2015;33:307–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25448109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estivariz CF, Jafari H, Sutter RW, John TJ, Jain V, Agarwal A, et al. Immunogenicity of supplemental doses of poliovirus vaccine for children aged 6–9 months in Moradabad, India: a community-based, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Infect Dis 2012;12:128–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22071249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem AF, Yousafzai MT, Mach O, Khan A, Quadri F, Weldon WC, et al. Evaluation of vaccine derived poliovirus type 2 outbreak response options: a randomized controlled trial, Karachi, Pakistan. Vaccine 2018;36:1766–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5869272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29477307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarke E, Saidu Y, Adetifa JU, Adigweme I, Hydara MB, Bashorun AO, et al. Safety and immunogenicity of inactivated poliovirus vaccine when given with measles-rubella combined vaccine and yellow fever vaccine and when given via different administration routes: a phase 4, randomised, non-inferiority trial in The Gambia. Lancet Glob Health 2016;4:e534–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27364568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duintjer Tebbens RJ, Pallansch MA, Wassilak SGF, Cochi SL, Thompson KM. Characterization of outbreak response strategies and potential vaccine stockpile needs for the polio endgame. BMC Infect Dis 2016;16:137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4806487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27009272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative. GPEI tools, protocols and guidelines. Available at http://polioeradication.org/. Accessed 16 April 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linkins RW, Mansour E, Wassif O, Hassan MH, Patriarca PA. Evaluation of house-to-house versus fixed-site oral poliovirus vaccine delivery strategies in a mass immunization campaign in Egypt. Bull World Health Organ 1995;73:589–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2486824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8846484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahl S, Verma H, Bhatnagar P, Haldar P, Satapathy A, Kumar KN, et al. Fractional-dose inactivated poliovirus vaccine immunization campaign-Telangana State, India, June 2016. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2016;65:859–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27559683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daly C, Molodecky NA, Sreevatsava M, Belayneh AD, Chandio SA, Partridge J, et al. Needle-free injectors for mass administration of fractional dose inactivated poliovirus vaccine in Karachi, Pakistan: a survey of caregiver and vaccinator acceptability. Vaccine 2020;38:1893–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31983581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mbaeyi C, Wadood ZM, Moran T, Ather F, Stehling-Ariza T, Nikulin J, et al. Strategic response to an outbreak of circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus type 2 - Syria, 2017–2018. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2018;67:690–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6013082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29927908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pervaiz A, Mbaeyi C, Baig MA, Burman A, Ahmed JA, Akter S, et al. Fractional-dose inactivated poliovirus vaccine campaign - Sindh Province, Pakistan, 2016. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2017;66:1295–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5708687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29190264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem AF, Mach O, Yousafzai MT, Khan A, Weldon WC, Oberste MS, et al. Needle adapters for intradermal administration of fractional dose of inactivated poliovirus vaccine: evaluation of immunogenicity and programmatic feasibility in Pakistan. Vaccine 2017;35:3209–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5457301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28479178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikh MA, Makokha F, Hussein AM, Mohamed G, Mach O, Humayun K, et al. Combined use of inactivated and oral poliovirus vaccines in refugee camps and surrounding communities - Kenya, December 2013. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2014;63:237–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4584634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24647400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salk D Eradication of poliomyelitis in the United States II. Experience with killed poliovirus vaccine. Rev Infect Dis 1980;2:243–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6771867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oostvogel PM, van der Avoort HGAM, Mulders MN, van Loon AM, Conynvan Spaendonck MAE, Rümke HC, et al. Poliomyelitis outbreak in an unvaccinated community in the Netherlands, 1992–93. The Lancet 1994;344:665–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7915354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shulman LM, Gavrilin E, Jorba J, Martin J, Burns CC, Manor Y, et al. Molecular epidemiology of silent introduction and sustained transmission of wild poliovirus type 1, Israel, 2013. Euro Surveill 2014;19:20709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24576471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alleman MM, Jorba J, Greene SA, Diop OM, Iber J, Tallis G, et al. Update on vaccine-derived poliovirus outbreaks - worldwide, July 2019-February 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2020;69:489–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7188410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32324719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grassly NC, Wadood MZ, Safdar RM, Mahamud AS, Sutter RW. Effect of inactivated poliovirus vaccine campaigns, Pakistan, 2014–2017. Emerg Infect Dis 2018;24:2113–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6200014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30252646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duintjer Tebbens RJ, Pallansch MA, Cochi SL, Ehrhardt DT, Farag NH, Hadler SC, et al. Modeling poliovirus transmission in Pakistan and Afghanistan to inform vaccination strategies in undervaccinated subpopulations. Risk Anal 2018;38:1701–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7879700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29314143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duintjer Tebbens RJ, Thompson KM. Costs and benefits of including inactivated in addition to oral poliovirus vaccine in outbreak response after cessation of oral poliovirus vaccine use. MDM Policy &amp; Pract 2017;2:1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6124926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30288417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>