<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35502695</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1865-1682</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>69</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Transboundary and emerging diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Transbound Emerg Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Aichivirus C isolate is a diarrhoea-causing pathogen in goats.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2268</StartPage><EndPage>e2275</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e2268-e2275</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/tbed.14566</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Aichivirus C is an emerging virus in goats, but its biological significance remains unknown. In this study, 18 diarrheic and 16 non-diarrheic faecal samples of kids were collected from a farm with an on-going diarrheic outbreak in Sichuan Province, China in May 2021. Of these samples, 77.8% (14/18) of diarrheic samples were detected as Aichivirus C positive by RT-PCR, which was significantly higher than that of non-diarrheic faces (0%, p &lt; .001); meanwhile, other common diarrhoea-causing pathogens in goats were not detected in diarrheic samples, except for two samples that were detected as caprine enterovirus positive, suggesting that Aichivirus C was associated with goat diarrhoea. Furthermore, five Aichivirus C strains were successfully isolated from positive samples using Vero cell lines and two isolates were further plaque-purified, named SWUN/F5/2021(10<sup>-6.7</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> /0.1 mL) and SWUN/F6/2021(10<sup>-7</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> /0.1 mL). Interestingly, Aichivirus C strain could cause systemic infection in experimental kids via oral administration, with the main clinical manifestation being severe watery diarrhoea. Histopathological changes observed in the duodenum and jejunum were characteristic, with shedding of mucosal epithelial cells. In addition, the virus was detected in tissues of diarrhoea kids naturally infected with Aichivirus C, exhibiting pathological changes similar to those of experimental infections. Overall, this study first isolated Aichivirus C and confirmed its pathogenicity in kids, with further study needed to better understand the virus pathogenicity. As Aichivirus C has been detected in South Korea, Italy and the USA and widely prevalent in southwest China, the results obtained here have significant implications for the diagnosis and control of diarrhoea in goats.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2022 Wiley-VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abi</LastName><ForeName>Keha-Mo</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal &amp; Veterinary Sciences, Southwest Minzu University, Chengdu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Veterinary Etiological Biology, Lanzhou Veterinary Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Lanzhou, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Chen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal &amp; Veterinary Sciences, Southwest Minzu University, Chengdu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Cheng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2680-0519</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal &amp; Veterinary Sciences, Southwest Minzu University, Chengdu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jing</LastName><ForeName>Zhi Zhong</ForeName><Initials>ZZ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Veterinary Etiological Biology, Lanzhou Veterinary Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Lanzhou, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2020NTD02</GrantID><Agency>The innovation team for emerging animal diseases, Southwest Minzu University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Leading Talents Support Program of State Ethnic Affairs Committee</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021PTJS34</GrantID><Agency>Key Laboratory of Veterinary Medicine of Universities of Sichuan Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Transbound Emerg Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101319538</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1865-1674</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003967" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diarrhea</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005243" MajorTopicYN="N">Feces</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015511" MajorTopicYN="Y">Goat Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006041" MajorTopicYN="N">Goats</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D052699" MajorTopicYN="Y">Kobuvirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aichivirus C</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diarrhoea</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">goat</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">isolation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenicity</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35502695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/tbed.14566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abi, K.-M, Yu, Z., Jing, Z. Z., &amp; Tang, C. (2021). Identification of a novel Aichivirus D in sheep. Infection, Genetics and Evolution, 91, 104810.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abi, K.-M., Zhang, Q., Jing, Z. Z., &amp; Tang, C. (2020). First detection and molecular characteristics of caprine kobuvirus in goats in China. Infection, Genetics and Evolution, 85, 104566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adzhubei, A. A., Sternberg, M. J. E., &amp; Makarov, A. A. (2013). Polyproline-II helix in proteins: structure and function. Journal of Molecular Biology, 425(12), 2100-2132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amine, S. A., Melloul, M., Alaoui, E. l., M, A., Boulahyaoui, H., Loutfi, C., Touil, N., &amp; El Fahime, E. (2020). Evidence for zoonotic transmission of species A rotavirus from goat and cattle in nomadic herds in Morocco, 2012-2014. Virus Genes, 56(5), 582-593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barry, A. F., Ribeiro, J., Alfieri, A. F., Poel, W. H. M. V. D., &amp; Alfieri, A. A. (2011). First detection of kobuvirus in farm animals in Brazil and the Netherlands. Infection, Genetics and Evolution, 11(7), 1811-1814.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brichta-Harhay, D., Arthur, T., Bosilevac, J., Guerini, M., Kalchayanand, N., &amp; Koohmaraie, M. (2013). Enumeration of Salmonella and Escherichia coli O157: H7 in ground beef, cattle carcass, hide and faecal samples using direct plating methods. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 103(5), 1657-1668.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charoenkul, K., Janetanakit, T., Chaiyawong, S., Bunpapong, N., Boonyapisitsopa, S., Tangwangvivat, R., &amp; Amonsin, A. (2019). First detection and genetic characterization of canine Kobuvirus in domestic dogs in Thailand. BMC Veterinary Research, 15(1), 254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y.-S., Chen, B.-C., Lin, Y.-S., Chang, J.-T., Huang, T.-S., Chen, J.-J., &amp; Chang, T.-H. (2013). Detection of Aichi virus with antibody targeting of conserved viral protein 1 epitope. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 97(19), 8529-8536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong, X., Liu, L., Zheng, F., Chen, Q., Li, Z., Cao, X., Yin, H., Zhou, J., &amp; Cai, X. (2014). Molecular investigation of bovine viral diarrhea virus infection in yaks (Bos gruniens) from Qinghai, China. Virology Journal, 11(1), 1-7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Income, N., Kosoltanapiwat, N., Taksinoros, S., Leaungwutiwong, P., Maneekan, P., &amp; Chavez, I. F. (2019). Molecular identification of enteroviruses from cattle and goat feces and environment in Thailand. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 85(5), e02420-02418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang, S., &amp; Kim, Y.-C. (2018). Genome-based virus taxonomy with the ICTV database extension. Genomics &amp; Informatics, 16(4), e22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, M.-H., Jeoung, H.-Y., Lim, J.-A., Song, J.-Y., Song, D.-S., &amp; An, D.-J. (2012). Kobuvirus in South Korean black goats. Virus Genes, 45(1), 186-189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martino, B. D., Profio, F. D., Melegari, I., Felice, E. D., Robetto, S., Guidetti, C., Orusa, R., Martella, V., &amp; Marsilio, F. (2015). Molecular detection of kobuviruses in European roe deer (Capreolus capreolus) in Italy. Archives of Virology, 160(8), 2083-2086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melegari, I., Profio, D. i., F, S., Martella, V., Marsilio, F., &amp; Di Martino, B. (2016). First molecular evidence of kobuviruses in goats in Italy. Archives of Virology, 161(11), 3245-3248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nantel-Fortier, N., Lachapelle, V., Letellier, A., L'Homme, Y., &amp; Brassard, J. (2019). Kobuvirus shedding dynamics in a swine production system and their association with diarrhea. Veterinary Microbiology, 235, 319-326.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oem, J.-K., Lee, M.-H., Lee, K.-K., &amp; An, D.-J. (2014). Novel Kobuvirus species identified from black goat with diarrhea. Veterinary Microbiology, 172(3-4), 563-567.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh, D.-Y., Silva, P., Hauroeder, B., Diedrich, S., Cardoso, D., &amp; Schreier, E. (2006). Molecular characterization of the first Aichi viruses isolated in Europe and in South America. Archives of Virology, 151(6), 1199-1206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polci, A., Cosseddu, G., Ancora, M., Pinoni, C., El Harrak, M., Sebhatu, T., Ghebremeskel, E., Sghaier, S., Lelli, R., &amp; Monaco, F. (2015). Development and preliminary evaluation of a new real-time RT-PCR assay for detection of peste des petits ruminants virus genome. Transboundary and Emerging Diseases, 62(3), 332-338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed, L. J., &amp; Muench, H. (1938). A simple method of estimating fifty per cent endpoints. American Journal of Epidemiology, 27(3), 493-497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reuter, G., Boros, A., Pankovics, P., &amp; Egyed, L. (2010). Kobuvirus in domestic sheep, Hungary. Emerging Infectious Diseases, 16(5), 869-870.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, D., Zhang, S., Chen, J., Shi, H., Zhang, X., &amp; Feng, L. (2013). Molecular characterization of a porcine kobuvirus variant strain in China. Archives of Virology, 158(11), 2379-2383.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sobhy, N. M., Armién, A. G., Wünschmann, A., Muldoon, D., Goyal, S. M., &amp; Mor, S. K. (2020). Detection and molecular characterization of kobuvirus from diarrheic goats in Minnesota. Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation, 32(6), 873-879.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Fredrickson, R., Duncan, M., Samuelson, J., &amp; Hsiao, S.-H. (2020). Bovine Kobuvirus in calves with diarrhea, United States. Emerging Infectious Diseases, 26(1), 176-178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, F., Liu, X., Zhou, Y., Lyu, W., Xu, S., Xu, Z., &amp; Zhu, L. (2015). Histopathology of porcine kobuvirus in Chinese piglets. Virologica Sinica, 30(5), 396-399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, L., Wang, X., Ren, J., Kotecha, A., Walter, T. S., Yuan, S., Yamashita, T., Tuthill, T. J., Fry, E. E., Rao, Z., &amp; Stuart, D. I. (2016). Structure of human Aichi virus and implications for receptor binding. Nature Microbiology, 1(11), 16150.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>