<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35718835</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>94</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dynamic alterations of the mice gut virome after Coxsackievirus B3 infection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>4959</StartPage><EndPage>4969</EndPage><MedlinePgn>4959-4969</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.27946</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The gut microbiome plays an essential role in the human health and dysbiosis has been implicated in numerous diseases. Coxsackievirus B3 infects millions of humans yearly and yet limited research has explored dynamic alterations of the gut virome after infection. Here, we established the mouse model of Coxsackievirus B3 infection and collected fecal samples at several time points to investigate alterations of the gut virome using viral metagenomic analysis. We found that the mice virome was dominated by Caudovirales and Microviridae, and phylogenetic analyses showed that both Caudovirales and Microviridae had high diversity. The gut virome had significant variations with the increase of Caudovirales and the decrease of Microviridae after infection. We proposed that Caudovirales and Microviridae may be biomarkers for the Coxsackievirus infection process. This study provides a reference for the dynamic changes of the gut virome after human Enterovirus infection, which may help guide the rational drug use in clinical treatment and provide new ideas for preventing Enterovirus infection.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2022 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bao</LastName><ForeName>Siwen</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Hao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3109-7488</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, The Affiliated Huai'an Hospital of Xuzhou Medical University, Huai'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Wang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Laboratory Center, The Affiliated Taizhou People's Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Taizhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Likai</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaochun</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Quan</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Shixing</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9899-8291</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Chenglin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Laboratory Center, The Affiliated Taizhou People's Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Taizhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Wen</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6928-8135</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003384" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coxsackievirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017914" MajorTopicYN="Y">Microviridae</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000083422" MajorTopicYN="N">Virome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Caudovirales</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coxsackievirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Microviridae</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biomarker</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gut virome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral metagenomics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35718835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adak A, Khan MR. An insight into gut microbiota and its functionalities. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2019;76(3):473-493. doi:10.1007/s00018-018-2943-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lloyd-Price J, Abu-Ali G, Huttenhower C. The healthy human microbiome. Genome Med. 2016;8(1):51. doi:10.1186/s13073-016-0307-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin J, Li R, Raes J, et al. A human gut microbial gene catalogue established by metagenomic sequencing. Nature. 2010;464(7285):59-65. doi:10.1038/nature08821</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozupone CA, Stombaugh JI, Gordon JI, Jansson JK, Knight R. Diversity, stability and resilience of the human gut microbiota. Nature. 2012;489(7415):220-230. doi:10.1038/nature11550</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekirov I, Russell SL, Antunes LC, Finlay BB. Gut microbiota in health and disease. Physiol Rev. 2010;90(3):859-904. doi:10.1152/physrev.00045.2009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amrane S, Raoult D, Lagier JC. Metagenomics, culturomics, and the human gut microbiota. Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther. 2018;16(5):373-375. doi:10.1080/14787210.2018.1467268</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heintz-Buschart A, Wilmes P. Human gut microbiome: function matters. Trends Microbiol. 2018;26(7):563-574. doi:10.1016/j.tim.2017.11.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jandhyala SM, Talukdar R, Subramanyam C, Vuyyuru H, Sasikala M, Nageshwar Reddy D. Role of the normal gut microbiota. World J Gastroenterol. 2015;21(29):8787-8803. doi:10.3748/wjg.v21.i29.8787</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cresci GA, Bawden E. Gut microbiome: what we do and don't know. Nutr Clin Pract. 2015;30(6):734-746. doi:10.1177/0884533615609899</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ursell LK, Metcalf JL, Parfrey LW, Knight R. Defining the human microbiome. Nutr Rev. 2012;70(Suppl 1):S38-S44. doi:10.1111/j.1753-4887.2012.00493.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy M, Kolodziejczyk AA, Thaiss CA, Elinav E. Dysbiosis and the immune system. Nat Rev Immunol. 2017;17(4):219-232. doi:10.1038/nri.2017.7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss GA, Hennet T. Mechanisms and consequences of intestinal dysbiosis. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2017;74(16):2959-2977. doi:10.1007/s00018-017-2509-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun MF, Shen YQ. Dysbiosis of gut microbiota and microbial metabolites in Parkinson's disease. Ageing Res Rev. 2018;45:53-61. doi:10.1016/j.arr.2018.04.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall AB, Tolonen AC, Xavier RJ. Human genetic variation and the gut microbiome in disease. Nat Rev Genet. 2017;18(11):690-699. doi:10.1038/nrg.2017.63</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni J, Wu GD, Albenberg L, Tomov VT. Gut microbiota and IBD: causation or correlation? Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2017;14(10):573-584. doi:10.1038/nrgastro.2017.88</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haran JP, McCormick BA. Aging, frailty, and the microbiome-how dysbiosis influences human aging and disease. Gastroenterology. 2021;160(2):507-523. doi:10.1053/j.gastro.2020.09.060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prusa J, Missak J, Kittrell J, Evans JJ, Tapprich WE. Major alteration in coxsackievirus B3 genomic RNA structure distinguishes a virulent strain from an avirulent strain. Nucleic Acids Res. 2014;42(15):10112-10121. doi:10.1093/nar/gku706</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao Z, Song Y, Li Y, et al. Coxsackievirus B3, Shandong province, China, 1990-2010. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012;18(11):1865-1867. doi:10.3201/eid1811.120090</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang YY, Huang YC. Enteroviral infection in neonates. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2019;52(6):851-857. doi:10.1016/j.jmii.2019.08.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pallansch MA. Coxsackievirus B epidemiology and public health concerns. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol. 1997;223:13-30. doi:10.1007/978-3-642-60687-8_2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee CJ, Huang YC, Yang S, et al. Clinical features of coxsackievirus A4, B3 and B4 infections in children. PLoS One. 2014;9(2):e87391. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0087391</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazel-Sanchez B, Yildiz S, Schmolke M. Menage a trois: virus, host, and microbiota in experimental infection models. Trends Microbiol. 2019;27(5):440-452. doi:10.1016/j.tim.2018.12.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woods Acevedo MA, Pfeiffer JK. Microbiota-immune system interactions and enteric virus infection. Curr Opin Virol. 2021;46:15-19. doi:10.1016/j.coviro.2020.08.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuss SK, Best GT, Etheredge CA, et al. Intestinal microbiota promote enteric virus replication and systemic pathogenesis. Science. 2011;334(6053):249-252. doi:10.1126/science.1211057</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldridge MT, Nice TJ, McCune BT, et al. Commensal microbes and interferon-lambda determine persistence of enteric murine norovirus infection. Science. 2015;347(6219):266-269. doi:10.1126/science.1258025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kandasamy S, Vlasova AN, Fischer D, et al. Differential effects of Escherichia coli Nissle and lactobacillus rhamnosus strain GG on human rotavirus binding, infection, and B cell immunity. J Immunol. 2016;196(4):1780-1789. doi:10.4049/jimmunol.1501705</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos Rocha C, Hirao LA, Weber MG, et al. Subclinical cytomegalovirus infection is associated with altered host immunity, gut microbiota, and vaccine responses. J Virol. 2018;92:13. doi:10.1128/JVI.00167-18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conceição-Neto N, Zeller M, Lefrère H, et al. Modular approach to customise sample preparation procedures for viral metagenomics: a reproducible protocol for virome analysis. Sci Rep. 2015;5:16532. doi:10.1038/srep16532</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoyles L, McCartney AL, Neve H, et al. Characterization of virus-like particles associated with the human faecal and caecal microbiota. Res Microbiol. 2014;165(10):803-812. doi:10.1016/j.resmic.2014.10.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Li L, Deng X, et al. Viral nucleic acids in human plasma pools. Transfusion. 2016;56(9):2248-2255. doi:10.1111/trf.13692</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Li L, Deng X, Kapusinszky B, Pesavento PA, Delwart E. Faecal virome of cats in an animal shelter. J Gen Virol. 2014;95(Pt 11):2553-2564. doi:10.1099/vir.0.069674-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Yang S, Shan T, et al. Virome comparisons in wild-diseased and healthy captive giant pandas. Microbiome. 2017;5(1):90. doi:10.1186/s40168-017-0308-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Yang S, Wang Y, et al. Identification of a novel human papillomavirus by metagenomic analysis of vaginal swab samples from pregnant women. Virol J. 2016;13:122. doi:10.1186/s12985-016-0583-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kearse M, Moir R, Wilson A, et al. Geneious basic: an integrated and extendable desktop software platform for the organization and analysis of sequence data. Bioinformatics. 2012;28(12):1647-1649. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/bts199</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng X, Naccache SN, Ng T, et al. An ensemble strategy that significantly improves de novo assembly of microbial genomes from metagenomic next-generation sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Res. 2015;43(7):e46. doi:10.1093/nar/gkv002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skewes-Cox P, Sharpton TJ, Pollard KS, DeRisi JL. Profile hidden Markov models for the detection of viruses within metagenomic sequence data. PLoS One. 2014;9(8):e105067. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0105067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huson DH, Auch AF, Qi J, Schuster SC. MEGAN analysis of metagenomic data. Genome Res. 2007;17(3):377-386. doi:10.1101/gr.5969107</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Stecher G, Li M, Knyaz C, Tamura K. MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms. Mol Biol Evol. 2018;35(6):1547-1549. doi:10.1093/molbev/msy096</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huelsenbeck JP, Ronquist F. MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees. Bioinformatics. 2001;17(8):754-755. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/17.8.754</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shanahan F, Ghosh TS, O'Toole PW. The healthy microbiome-what is the definition of a healthy gut microbiome? Gastroenterology. 2021;160(2):483-494. doi:10.1053/j.gastro.2020.09.057</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minot S, Sinha R, Chen J, et al. The human gut virome: inter-individual variation and dynamic response to diet. Genome Res. 2011;21(10):1616-1625. doi:10.1101/gr.122705.111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes A, Haynes M, Hanson N, et al. Viruses in the faecal microbiota of monozygotic twins and their mothers. Nature. 2010;466(7304):334-338. doi:10.1038/nature09199</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shkoporov AN, Clooney AG, Sutton TDS, et al. The human gut virome is highly diverse, stable, and individual specific. Cell Host Microbe. 2019;26(4):527-541.e5. doi:10.1016/j.chom.2019.09.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norman JM, Handley SA, Baldridge MT, et al. Disease-specific alterations in the enteric virome in inflammatory bowel disease. Cell. 2015;160(3):447-460. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2015.01.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coughlan S, Das A, O'Herlihy E, Shanahan F, O'Toole PW, Jeffery IB. The gut virome in irritable bowel syndrome differs from that of controls. Gut Microbes. 2021;13(1):1-15. doi:10.1080/19490976.2021.1887719</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin N, Yang F, Li A, et al. Alterations of the human gut microbiome in liver cirrhosis. Nature. 2014;513(7516):59-64. doi:10.1038/nature13568</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren Z, Li A, Jiang J, et al. Gut microbiome analysis as a tool towards targeted non-invasive biomarkers for early hepatocellular carcinoma. Gut. 2019;68(6):1014-1023. doi:10.1136/gutjnl-2017-315084</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayneris-Perxachs J, Castells-Nobau A, Arnoriaga-Rodríguez M, et al. Caudovirales bacteriophages are associated with improved executive function and memory in flies, mice, and humans. Cell Host Microbe. 2022;30(3):340-356.e8. doi:10.1016/j.chom.2022.01.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim ES, Zhou Y, Zhao G, et al. Early life dynamics of the human gut virome and bacterial microbiome in infants. Nat Med. 2015;21(10):1228-1234. doi:10.1038/nm.3950</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz-Munoz SL, Sanjuan R, West S. Sociovirology: conflict, cooperation, and communication among viruses. Cell Host Microbe. 2017;22(4):437-441. doi:10.1016/j.chom.2017.09.012</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>