<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">35891919</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2778-2034</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>1</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>31</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medecine tropicale et sante internationale</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Med Trop Sante Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>[New oral polio vaccine: A turning point for the global polio eradication initiative?].</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">mtsi.2021.191</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.48327/mtsi.2021.191</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Launched in 1988, the Global Polio Eradication Initiative (GPEI) aims to eradicate polioviruses, which are the etiologic agents of poliomyelitis. Coordinated by the World Health Organization, this program relies on two pillars: mass vaccination campaigns that target children and active surveillance of the virus circulation. The GPEI has led to the eradication of two out of three serotypes of wild polioviruses and to the containment of the last serotype in two countries.Two polio vaccines exist: the injectable vaccine and the oral one. Both induce an efficient protection against poliomyelitis, but only the oral vaccine is able to stop poliovirus transmission chains. Therefore, the oral vaccine is essential to contain polioviruses and, finally, to eradicate them. In some contexts where the vaccine coverage is not sufficient, the attenuated strains contained in the oral vaccine can circulate for months and recover a pathogenic phenotype through genetic drift. In order to prevent this phenomenon, a new vaccine strain has been developed through genetic engineering: it has been designed to be as immunogenic as the historical vaccine strain, but more genetically stable to prevent the loss of its attenuation determinants. After being evaluated in vitro and through clinical trials, the novel strain has been rolled out in several African countries and in Tajikistan in 2021.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2021 SFMTSI.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bessaud</LastName><ForeName>Maël</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Unité pathogenèse &amp; populations virales, 25-28, rue du Dr Roux, 75015 Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>fre</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Le nouveau vaccin antipoliomyélitique oral : Un tournant décisif pour le programme d’éradication ?</VernacularTitle><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>France</Country><MedlineTA>Med Trop Sante Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918227363206676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2778-2034</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011055">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014943" MajorTopicYN="Y">Global Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D032541" MajorTopicYN="N">Mass Vaccination</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011055" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText>Lancé en 1988, le programme d’éradication de la poliomyélite vise à éradiquer les poliovirus, agents étiologiques de la maladie. Coordonné par l'Organisation mondiale de la santé, le programme repose sur des campagnes de vaccination de routine ciblant les enfants et sur la surveillance active de la circulation des virus. Il a permis l’éradication de deux des trois sérotypes de poliovirus sauvages et a circonscrit la circulation du sérotype restant à deux pays seulement. Deux vaccins antipoliomyélitiques existent: le vaccin injectable et le vaccin oral. Si les deux vaccins offrent une protection similaire contre la maladie, seul le second est capable de bloquer la transmission des poliovirus. Le vaccin oral est donc indispensable pour endiguer les poliovirus et, finalement, les éradiquer. Dans certains contextes où la couverture vaccinale est faible, les souches atténuées qui composent le vaccin oral peuvent circuler durant des mois et recouvrer un phénotype pathogène par dérive génétique. Afin d’éviter ce phénomène, une nouvelle souche vaccinale a été développée par génie génétique: elle a été conçue pour être aussi immunogène que la souche vaccinale historique mais beaucoup plus stable génétiquement afin d’éviter la perte des déterminants génétiques de son atténuation. Après une phase d’évaluation <i>in vitro</i> et des essais cliniques visant à confirmer ses propriétés, la nouvelle souche a été mise en œuvre dans plusieurs pays africains et au Tadjikistan en 2021.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2021 SFMTSI.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Eradication</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Oral polio vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poliomyelitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">VDPV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine-derived poliovirus</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35891919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9283809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.48327/mtsi.2021.191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">mtsi.2021.191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adebisi YA, Eliseo-Lucero Prisno D, 3rd, Nuga BB. Last fight of wild polio in Africa: Nigeria's battle. Public Health Pract (Oxf) 2020 Nov;1:100043. doi: 10.1016/j.puhip.2020.100043. Epub 2020 Dec 22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.puhip.2020.100043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7528738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34173577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alleman MM, Jorba J, Greene SA, Diop OM, Iber J, Tallis G, Goel A, Wiesen E, Wassilak SGF, Burns CC. Update on Vaccine-Derived Poliovirus Outbreaks - Worldwide, July 2019-February 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020 Apr 24;69((16)):489–495. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6916a1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6916a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7188410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32324719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almond JW. The attenuation of poliovirus neurovirulence. Annu Rev Microbiol. 1987;41:153–80. doi: 10.1146/annurev.mi.41.100187.001101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.41.100187.001101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2825586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anis E, Kopel E, Singer SR, Kaliner E, Moerman L, Moran-Gilad J, Sofer D, Manor Y, Shulman LM, Mendelson E, Gdalevich M, Lev B, Gamzu R, Grotto I. Insidious reintroduction of wild poliovirus into Israel, 2013. Euro Surveill. 2013 Sep 19;18((38)):20586. doi: 10.2807/1560-7917.es2013.18.38.20586. Erratum in: Euro Surveill. 2013;18(49):pii/20651.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.es2013.18.38.20586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24084337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burns CC, Diop OM, Sutter RW, Kew OM. Vaccine-derived polioviruses. J Infect Dis. 2014 Nov 1;210(Suppl 1):S283–93. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiu295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiu295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combelas N, Holmblat B, Joffret ML, Colbère-Garapin F, Delpeyroux F. Recombination between poliovirus and coxsackie A viruses of species C: a model of viral genetic plasticity and emergence. Viruses. 2011 Aug;3((8)):1460–84. doi: 10.3390/v3081460. Epub 2011 Aug 17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v3081460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3185806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21994791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Decina D, Fournier-Caruana J, Takane M, Ostad Ali Dehaghi R, Sutter R. Regulatory Aspects of Sabin Type 2 Withdrawal From Trivalent Oral Poliovirus Vaccine: Process and Lessons Learned. J Infect Dis. 2017 Jul 1;216((suppl_1)):S46–S51. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiw564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiw564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5853659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28838164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Coster I, Leroux-Roels I, Bandyopadhyay AS, Gast C, Withanage K, Steenackers K, De Smedt P, Aerssens A, Leroux-Roels G, Oberste MS, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Weldon WC, Fix A, Konz J, Wahid R, Modlin J, Clemens R, Costa Clemens SA, Bachtiar NS, Van Damme P. Safety and immunogenicity of two novel type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine candidates compared with a monovalent type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine in healthy adults: two clinical trials. Lancet. 2021 Jan 2;397((10268)):39–50. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32541-1. Epub 2020 Dec 9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32541-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7811203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33308429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hampton LM, Farrell M, Ramirez-Gonzalez A, Menning L, Shendale S, Lewis I, Rubin J, Garon J, Harris J, Hyde T, Wassilak S, Patel M, Nandy R, Chang-Blanc D. Immunization Systems Management Group of the Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Cessation of Trivalent Oral Poliovirus Vaccine and Introduction of Inactivated Poliovirus Vaccine - Worldwide, 2016. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2016 Sep 9;65((35)):934–8. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6535a3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6535a3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27606675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanley KA. The double-edged sword: How evolution can make or break a live-attenuated virus vaccine. Evolution (N Y) 2011 Dec;4((4)):635–643. doi: 10.1007/s12052-011-0365-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12052-011-0365-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3314307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22468165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaliner E, Kopel E, Anis E, Mendelson E, Moran-Gilad J, Shulman LM, Singer SR, Manor Y, Somekh E, Rishpon S, Leventhal A, Rubin L, Tasher D, Honovich M, Moerman L, Shohat T, Bassal R, Sofer D, Gdalevich M, Lev B, Gamzu R, Grotto I. The Israeli public health response to wild poliovirus importation. Lancet Infect Dis. 2015 Oct;15((10)):1236–1242. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(15)00064-X. Epub 2015 Jul 23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(15)00064-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26213249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanwal S, Hussain A, Mannan S, Perveen S. Regression in polio eradication in Pakistan: A national tragedy. J Pak Med Assoc. 2016 Mar;66((3)):328–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26968287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konopka-Anstadt JL, Campagnoli R, Vincent A, Shaw J, Wei L, Wynn NT, Smithee SE, Bujaki E, Te Yeh M, Laassri M, Zagorodnyaya T, Weiner AJ, Chumakov K, Andino R, Macadam A, Kew O, Burns CC. Development of a new oral poliovirus vaccine for the eradication end game using codon deoptimization. NPJ Vaccines. 2020 Mar 20;5((1)):26. doi: 10.1038/s41541-020-0176-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41541-020-0176-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7083942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32218998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makoni M. Africa eradicates wild polio. Lancet Microbe. 2020 Oct;1((6)):e243. doi: 10.1016/S2666-5247(20)30152-X. Epub 2020 Oct 7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(20)30152-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7541043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33047110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mbaeyi C, Alleman MM, Ehrhardt D, Wiesen E, Burns CC, Liu H, Ewetola R, Seakamela L, Mdodo R, Ndoutabe M, Wenye PK, Riziki Y, Borus P, Kamugisha C, Wassilak SGF. Update on Vaccine-Derived Poliovirus Outbreaks - Democratic Republic of the Congo and Horn of Africa, 2017-2018. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2019 Mar 8;68((9)):225–230. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6809a2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6809a2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6421971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30845121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minor PD. Live attenuated vaccines: Historical successes and current challenges. Virology. 2015 May;479-480:379–92. doi: 10.1016/j.virol.2015.03.032. Epub 2015 Apr 8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2015.03.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25864107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muslin C, Mac Kain A, Bessaud M, Blondel B, Delpeyroux F. Recombination in Enteroviruses, a Multi-Step Modular Evolutionary Process. Viruses. 2019 Sep 14;11((9)):859. doi: 10.3390/v11090859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v11090859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6784155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31540135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owoaje E, Rahimi AO, Kalbarczyk A, Akinyemi O, Peters MA, Alonge OO. Conflict, community, and collaboration: shared implementation barriers and strategies in two polio endemic countries. BMC Public Health. 2020 Dec 18;20((Suppl 4)):1178. doi: 10.1186/s12889-020-09235-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-020-09235-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7747362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33339525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platt LR, Estívariz CF, Sutter RW. Vaccine-associated paralytic poliomyelitis: a review of the epidemiology and estimation of the global burden. J Infect Dis. 2014 Nov 1;210(Suppl 1):S380–9. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiu184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiu184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10424844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabin AB, Boulger LR. History of Sabin attenuated poliovirus oral live vaccine strains. J Biol Stand. 1973 Jan;1((2)):115–8. doi: 10.1016/0092-1157(73)90048-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0092-1157(73)90048-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sáez-Llorens X, Bandyopadhyay AS, Gast C, Leon T, DeAntonio R, Jimeno J, Caballero MI, Aguirre G, Oberste MS, Weldon WC, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Modlin J, Bachtiar NS, Fix A, Konz J, Clemens R, Costa Clemens SA, Rüttimann R. Safety and immunogenicity of two novel type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine candidates compared with a monovalent type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine in children and infants: two clinical trials. Lancet. 2021 Jan 2;397((10268)):27–38. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32540-X. Epub 2020 Dec 9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32540-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7811205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33308427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Damme P, De Coster I, Bandyopadhyay AS, Revets H, Withanage K, De Smedt P, Suykens L, Oberste MS, Weldon WC, Costa-Clemens SA, Clemens R, Modlin J, Weiner AJ, Macadam AJ, Andino R, Kew OM, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Burns CC, Konz J, Wahid R, Gast C. The safety and immunogenicity of two novel live attenuated monovalent (serotype 2) oral poliovirus vaccines in healthy adults: a double-blind, single-centre phase 1 study. Lancet. 2019 Jul 13;394((10193)):148–158. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31279-6. Epub 2019 Jun 4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31279-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6626986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31174831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Damme P, De Coster I, Revets H, Bandyopadhyay AS. Poliopolis. Lancet. 2019 Jul 13;394((10193)):115. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31516-8. Epub 2019 Jul 11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31516-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31305249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wassilak SG, Vertefeuille JF, Martin RM. The Globally Synchronized Switch-Another Milestone Toward Achieving Polio Eradication. JAMA Pediatr. 2016 Oct 1;170((10)):927–928. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2016.1718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2016.1718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10241004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27479244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeh MT, Bujaki E, Dolan PT, Smith M, Wahid R, Konz J, Weiner AJ, Bandyopadhyay AS, Van Damme P, De Coster I, Revets H, Macadam A, Andino R. Engineering the Live-Attenuated Polio Vaccine to Prevent Reversion to Virulence. Cell Host Microbe. 2020 May 13;27((5)):736–751. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2020.04.003. Epub 2020 Apr 23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2020.04.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7566161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32330425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>