<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35959667</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>15</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1687-1634</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>28</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>31</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Eastern Mediterranean health journal = La revue de sante de la Mediterranee orientale = al-Majallah al-sihhiyah li-sharq al-mutawassit</Title><ISOAbbreviation>East Mediterr Health J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Emerging challenges to realizing global polio eradication and their solutions.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>515</StartPage><EndPage>520</EndPage><MedlinePgn>515-520</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.26719/emhj.22.045</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The Global Polio Eradication Initiative (GPEI) promised to eradicate polio by 2000, yet the disease remains endemic in 2 countries. The current threat of resurgence in countries with low vaccine coverage and circulating vaccinederived poliovirus (cVDPV) outbreaks due to oral polio vaccine warrants a strategy review.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To review the performance of the GPEI from a context based in Pakistan, identifying threats to success and suggesting strategy modifications to help achieve eradication.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This was a desk review of the effectiveness of GPEI that was launched in 1988 to eradicate polio by 2000. Subsequent failure to eradicate led to multiple iterations in strategy and planning documents. These documents were reviewed alongside relevant literature to explore the reasons for failure and emergence of cVDPV.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">GPEI has been effective in reducing the global polio disease burden by &gt; 99%, but it remains endemic in Pakistan and Afghanistan. cVDPV has caused multiple outbreaks since 2000, and caused 7 times more cases than wild poliovirus (WPV) globally in 2020. The Polio Eradication and Endgame Strategic Plan 2013-2018 aimed to eradicate WPV and cVDPV simultaneously. In 2019, Pakistan saw an upsurge in WPV amid an outbreak of cVDPV infection that continued throughout 2020. Wild polio eradication was not realized and the country was unable to transition to inactivated polio vaccine as predicted in the strategic plan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Over 20 countries now report cVDPV outbreaks and many others are at risk. A country-specific modified strategy is required to eradicate WPV and cVDPV simultaneously, more so in endemic countries.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © World Health Organization (WHO) 2022. Open Access. Some rights reserved. This work is available under the CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/igo).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>M A</LastName><ForeName>Sultan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Rawalpindi Medical University, Rawalpindi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>31</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Egypt</Country><MedlineTA>East Mediterr Health J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9608387</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1020-3397</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011054">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011055">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060740" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Eradication</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014943" MajorTopicYN="N">Global Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017589" MajorTopicYN="N">Immunization Programs</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011054" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011055" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ara"><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">التحديات الناشئة أمام تحقيق استئصال شلل الأطفال عالميًّا وحلولها. محمد سلطان.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الخلفية" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">وعدت «المبادرة العالمية لاستئصال شلل الأطفال» باستئصاله بحلول عام 2000، ومع ذلك ما يزال المرض متوطنًا في بلدين. ويستدعي التهديد الحالي بعودة ظهور الفيروس في البلدان ذات التغطية المنخفضة باللقاحات وفاشيات فيروسات شلل الأطفال الدائرة المشتقة من اللقاحات بسبب اللقاح الفموي لشلل الأطفال استعراضًا للمبادرة.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الأهداف" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">هدفت هذه الدراسة الىى استعراض أداء المبادرة العالمية لاستئصال شلل الأطفال في سياق باكستان، وتحديد التهديدات التي تواجه النجاح، واقتراح تعديلات على الاستراتيجية للمساعدة على تحقيق الاستئصال.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="طرق البحث" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">كان هذا استعراضًا مكتبيًّا لفعالية «المبادرة العالمية لاستئصال شلل الأطفال» التي أُطلقت في عام 1988، لاستئصاله بحلول عام 2000. وقد أدى الفشل اللاحق في القضاء على المرض إلى تكرارات متعددة في وثائق الاستراتيجية والتخطيط. وكذلك روجعت هذه الوثائق إلى جانب المؤلفات ذات الصلة لاستكشاف أسباب الفشل وظهور فيروسات شلل الأطفال الدائرة المشتقة من اللقاحات.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="النتائج" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">كانت «المبادرة العالمية لاستئصال شلل الأطفال» فعالة في خفض العبء العالمي للمرض بنسبة تزيد على 99٪، لكنه ما يزال متوطنًا في باكستان وأفغانستان. وقد تسببت فيروسات شلل الأطفال الدائرة المشتقة من اللقاحات في فاشيات متعددة منذ عام 2000، وتسببت في حالات إصابة أكثر 7 مرات من الحالات بسبب فيروس شلل الأطفال البري على الصعيد العالمي في عام 2020. واستهدفت «الخطة الاستراتيجية لاستئصال شلل الأطفال» والشوط الأخير من استئصاله 2013–2018 استئصال فيروس شلل الأطفال البََرِّي وفيروسات شلل الأطفال الدائرة المشتقة من اللقاحات في الوقت نفسه. وفي عام 2019، شهدت باكستان ارتفاعًا مفاجئًا في فيروس شلل الأطفال البري وسط فاشية لعدوى فيروسات شلل الأطفال الدائرة المشتقة من اللقاحات استمرت طوال عام 2020. ولم يتحقق استئصال شلل الأطفال البري، ولم يتمكن البلد من التحول إلى لقاح شلل الأطفال المعطَّل على النحو المتوقع في الخطة الاستراتيجية.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الاستنتاجات" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">أبلغ الآن أكثر من 20 بلدًا عن فاشيات فيروسات شلل الأطفال الدائرة المشتقة من اللقاحات، أيضًا هناك بلدان كثيرة أخرى معرضة للخطر. ويلزم وضع استراتيجية مُعدَّلة خاصة بكل بلد لاستئصال فيروس شلل الأطفال البََرِّي وفيروسات شلل الأطفال الدائرة المشتقة من اللقاحات في الوقت نفسه، وينطبق ذلك أكثر على البلدان التي يتوطن بها هذا المرض.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © World Health Organization (WHO) 2022. Open Access. Some rights reserved. This work is available under the CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/igo).</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">Nouveaux obstacles à l'éradication mondiale de la poliomyélite et solutions pour y remédier.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONTEXTE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">L'Initiative mondiale pour l'éradication de la poliomyélite (IMEP) s'est engagée à éradiquer la maladie à l'horizon 2000, mais celle-ci reste endémique dans deux pays. La menace actuelle de résurgence dans les pays ayant une faible couverture vaccinale et des flambées épidémiques de poliovirus circulants dérivés d'une souche vaccinale (PVDVc) imputables au vaccin antipoliomyélitique oral justifie un examen de la stratégie.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIFS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Examiner les performances de l'IMEP dans le contexte pakistanais, en identifiant les obstacles à la réussite et en suggérant des modifications de la stratégie pour parvenir à l'éradication.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MÉTHODES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Le présent article constitue un examen documentaire de l'efficacité de l'IMEP, qui a été lancée en 1988 pour éradiquer la poliomyélite à l'horizon 2000. Par la suite, l'échec de l'éradication de la maladie a conduit à plusieurs itérations dans la stratégie et la planification. Ces documents de stratégie et de planification ont été examinés parallèlement à la littérature pertinente afin d'explorer les raisons de l'échec et de l'émergence de PVDVc.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RÉSULTATS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">L'IMEP a réussi à réduire la charge mondiale de morbidité due à la poliomyélite de plus de 99 %, mais la maladie reste endémique en Afghanistan et au Pakistan. De multiples flambées de PVDVc ont eu lieu depuis 2000 et le nombre de cas enregistrés de PVDVc dans le monde en 2020 était sept fois supérieur à celui des cas de poliovirus sauvages (PVS). Le Plan stratégique pour l'éradication de la poliomyélite et la phase finale 2013-2018 visait à éradiquer simultanément le PVS et le PVDVc. En 2019, le Pakistan a connu une recrudescence du poliovirus sauvage dans un contexte de flambée de PVDVc qui s'est poursuivie tout au long de 2020. L'éradication du poliovirus sauvage n'a pas été réalisée et le pays n'a pas été en mesure de mener la transition vers le vaccin antipoliomyélitique inactivé comme le prévoyait le Plan stratégique.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Aujourd'hui, plus de 20 pays signalent des flambées épidémiques dues à des PVDVc et de nombreux autres sont à risque. Une stratégie modifiée spécifique au pays est nécessaire pour éradiquer simultanément le PVS et le PVDVc, en particulier dans les pays d'endémie.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © World Health Organization (WHO) 2022. Open Access. Some rights reserved. This work is available under the CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/igo).</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pakistan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disease eradication</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health policy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inactivated poliovirus vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliomyelitis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35959667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26719/emhj.22.045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>