<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36055595</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-1298</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>308</Volume><Issue>Pt 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Chemosphere</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Chemosphere</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Treatment of hospital wastewater by electron beam technology: Removal of COD, pathogenic bacteria and viruses.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136265</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136265</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.136265</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0045-6535(22)02758-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The effective treatment of hospital sewage is crucial to human health and eco-environment, especially during the pandemic of COVID-19. In this study, a demonstration project of actual hospital sewage using electron beam technology was established as advanced treatment process during the outbreak of COVID-19 pandemic in Hubei, China in July 2020. The results indicated that electron beam radiation could effectively remove COD, pathogenic bacteria and viruses in hospital sewage. The continuous monitoring date showed that the effluent COD concentration after electron beam treatment was stably below 30 mg/L, and the concentration of fecal Escherichia coli was below 50 MPN/L, when the absorbed dose was 4 kGy. Electron beam radiation was also an effective method for inactivating viruses. Compared to the inactivation of fecal Escherichia coli, higher absorbed dose was required for the inactivation of virus. Absorbed dose had different effect on the removal of virus. When the absorbed dose ranged from 30 to 50 kGy, Hepatitis A virus (HAV) and Astrovirus (ASV) could be completely removed by electron beam treatment. For Rotavirus (RV) and Enterovirus (EV) virus, the removal efficiency firstly increased and then decreased. The maximum removal efficiency of RV and EV was 98.90% and 88.49%, respectively. For the Norovirus (NVLII) virus, the maximum removal efficiency was 81.58%. This study firstly reported the performance of electron beam in the removal of COD, fecal Escherichia coli and virus in the actual hospital sewage, which would provide useful information for the application of electron beam technology in the treatment of hospital sewage.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2022 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jianlong</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Environmental Technology, INET, Tsinghua University, Beijing, 100084, PR China; Beijing Key Laboratory of Radioactive Wastes Treatment, Tsinghua University, Beijing, 100084, PR China. Electronic address: wangjl@tsinghua.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Shizong</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Environmental Technology, INET, Tsinghua University, Beijing, 100084, PR China; Beijing Key Laboratory of Radioactive Wastes Treatment, Tsinghua University, Beijing, 100084, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Chuanhong</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dasheng Electron Accelerator Technology Co., Ltd., China Guangdong Nuclear Group, Suzhou, Jiangsu, 215214, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Environmental Technology, INET, Tsinghua University, Beijing, 100084, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Shijun</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Environmental Technology, INET, Tsinghua University, Beijing, 100084, PR China; Dasheng Electron Accelerator Technology Co., Ltd., China Guangdong Nuclear Group, Suzhou, Jiangsu, 215214, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Yuedong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dasheng Electron Accelerator Technology Co., Ltd., China Guangdong Nuclear Group, Suzhou, Jiangsu, 215214, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Huanzheng</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dasheng Electron Accelerator Technology Co., Ltd., China Guangdong Nuclear Group, Suzhou, Jiangsu, 215214, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xipo</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dasheng Electron Accelerator Technology Co., Ltd., China Guangdong Nuclear Group, Suzhou, Jiangsu, 215214, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Dongming</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dasheng Electron Accelerator Technology Co., Ltd., China Guangdong Nuclear Group, Suzhou, Jiangsu, 215214, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Jian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dasheng Electron Accelerator Technology Co., Ltd., China Guangdong Nuclear Group, Suzhou, Jiangsu, 215214, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Chemosphere</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0320657</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0045-6535</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012722">Sewage</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Waste Water</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001419" MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004583" MajorTopicYN="N">Electrons</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004926" MajorTopicYN="N">Escherichia coli</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006761" MajorTopicYN="N">Hospitals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012722" MajorTopicYN="N">Sewage</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Disinfection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Electron beam</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emerging contaminants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hospital wastewater</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pathogenic bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36055595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9424868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.136265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0045-6535(22)02758-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Bertsch P.M., Bivins A., Bibby K., Farkas K., Gathercole A., Haramoto E., Gyawali P., Korajkic A., McMinn B.R., Mueller J.F., Simpson S.L., Smith W.J.M., Symonds E.M., Thomas K.V., Verhagen R., Kitajima M. Comparison of virus concentration methods for the RT-qPCR-based recovery of murine hepatitis virus, a surrogate for SARS-CoV-2 from untreated wastewater. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;739</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7273154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32758945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhowmick G.D., Dhar D., Nath D., Ghangrekar M.M., Banerjee R., Das S., Chatterjee J. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak: some serious consequences with urban and rural water cycle. NPJ Clean Water. 2020;3(1):32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X.Y., Zhuan R., Wang J.L. Assessment of degradation characteristic and mineralization efficiency of norfloxacin by ionizing radiation combined with Fenton-like oxidation. J. Hazard Mater. 2021;404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33049634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu L.B., Zhuang S.T., Wang J.L. Degradation kinetics and mechanism of penicillin G in aqueous matrices by ionizing radiation. Radiat. Phys. Chem. 2018;145:34–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu L.B., Wang J.L., He S.J., Chen C.H., Wojnárovits L., Takács E. Treatment of pharmaceutical wastewater by ionizing radiation: removal of antibiotics, antimicrobial resistance genes and antimicrobial activity. J. Hazard Mater. 2021;415</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34088196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu W., Fang C., Deng Y., Xu Z. Intensified disinfection amid COVID-19 pandemic poses potential risks to water quality and safety. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;55(7):4084–4086.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33119291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fout G.S., Cashdollar J.L., Varughese E.A., Parshionikar S.U., Grimm A.C. EPA Method 1615. Measurement of enterovirus and norovirus occurrence in water by culture and RT-qPCR. I. Collection of virus samples. JoVE. 2015;97</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4401389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25867928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He H., Wang S.Z., Wang J.L. Degradation of 3-methylindole by ionizing radiation: performance and pathway. Separ. Purif. Technol. 2021;278</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herraiz-Carboné M., Cotillas S., Lacasa E., de Baranda C.S., Riquelme E., Cañizares P., Rodrigo M., Sáez C. Are we correctly targeting the research on disinfection of antibiotic-resistant bacteria (ARB)? J. Clean. Prod. 2021;320</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herraiz-Carboné M., Cotillas S., Lacasa E., Cañizares P., Rodrigo M.A., Sáez C. Disinfection of urines using an electro-ozonizer. Electrochim. Acta. 2021;382</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herraiz-Carboné M., Cotillas S., Lacasa E., Vasileva M., de Baranda C.S., Riquelme E., Cañizares P., Sáez C. Disinfection of polymicrobial urines by electrochemical oxidation: removal of antibiotic-resistant bacteria and genes. J. Hazard Mater. 2022;426</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34923384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herraiz-Carboné M., Cotillas S., Lacasa E., Cañizares P., Rodrigo M.A., Sáez C. Depletion of ARGs in antibiotic-resistance Klebsiella, Pseudomonas and Staphylococcus in hospital urines by electro and photo-electro disinfection. J. Water Proc. Eng. 2022;49</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilyas S., Srivastava R.R., Kim H. Disinfection technology and strategies for COVID-19 hospital and bio-medical waste management. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;749</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7419320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32822917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kataki S., Chatterjee S., Vairale M.G., Sharma S., Dwivedi S.K. Concerns and strategies for wastewater treatment during COVID-19 pandemic to stop plausible transmission. Resour. Conserv. Recycl. 2021;164</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7473346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32921917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim J., Yeom M., Lee T., Kim H.-O., Na W., Kang A., Lim J.-W., Park G., Park C., Song D., Haam S. Porous gold nanoparticles for attenuating infectivity of influenza A virus. J. Nanobiotechnol. 2020;18(1):54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32209114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kozari A., Paloglou A., Voutsa D. Formation potential of emerging disinfection by-products during ozonation and chlorination of sewage effluents. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;700</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31639540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee O.M., Kim H.Y., Park W., Kim T.-H., Yu S. A comparative study of disinfection efficiency and regrowth control of microorganism in secondary wastewater effluent using UV, ozone, and ionizing irradiation process. J. Hazard Mater. 2015;295:201–208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25955959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D., Gu A.Z., Zeng S.Y., Yang W., He M., Shi H.C. Monitoring and evaluation of infectious rotaviruses in various wastewater effluents and receiving waters revealed correlation and seasonal pattern of occurrences. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2011;110:1129–1137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21276144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li G.Q., Wang W.L., Huo Z.Y., Lu Y., Hu H.Y. Comparison of UV-LED and low pressure UV for water disinfection: photoreactivation and dark repair of Escherichia coli. Water Res. 2017;126:134–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28941399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y.K., Hu J., Wang J.L. Fe2+ enhancing sulfamethazine degradation in aqueous solution by gamma irradiation. Radiat. Phys. Chem. 2014;96:81–87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y.K., Wang J.L. Degradation of sulfamethazine by gamma irradiation in the presence of hydrogen peroxide. J. Hazard Mater. 2013;250:99–105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23434485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazhar M.A., Khan N.A., Ahmed S., Khan A.H., Hussain A., Rahisuddin. Changani F., Yousefi M., Ahmadi S., Vambol V. Chlorination disinfection by-products in municipal drinking water-A review. J. Clean. Prod. 2020;273</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison C.M., Hogard S., Pearce R., Gerrity D., von Gunten U., Wert E.C. Ozone disinfection of waterborne pathogens and their surrogates: a critical review. Water Res. 2022;214</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35276607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwatondo M.H., Silverman A.I. Escherichia coli and Enterococcus spp. indigenous to wastewater have slower free chlorine disinfection rates than their laboratory-cultured counterparts. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2021;8(12):1091–1097.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponomarev A.V., Ershov B.G. The green method in water management: electron beam treatment. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2020;54(9):5331–5344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32267147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen Y.P., Zhuan R., Chu L.B., Xiang X., Sun H., Wang J.L. Inactivation of antibiotic resistance genes in antibiotic fermentation residues by ionizing radiation: exploring the development of recycling economy in antibiotic pharmaceutical factory. Waste Manage. (Tucson, Ariz.) 2019;84:141–146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30691886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tree J.A., Adams M.R., Lees D.N. Chlorination of indicator bacteria and viruses in primary sewage effluent. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2003;69:2038–2043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC154782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12676680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trojanowicz M. Removal of persistent organic pollutants (POPs) from waters and wastewaters by the use of ionizing radiation. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;718</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31843309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.L., Chen X.Y. Removal of antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) in various wastewater treatment processes: an overview. Crit. Rev. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2022;52:571–630.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.L., Chu L.B. Irradiation treatment of pharmaceutical and personal care products (PPCPs) in water and wastewater: an overview. Radiat. Phys. Chem. 2016;125:56–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.L., Chu L.B., Wojnarovits L., Takacs E. Occurrence and fate of antibiotics, antibiotic resistant genes (ARGs) and antibiotic resistant bacteria (ARB) in municipal wastewater treatment plant: an overview. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;744</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32755790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Shen J., Ye D., Yan X., Zhang Y., Yang W., Li X., Wang J., Zhang L., Pan L. Disinfection technology of hospital wastes and wastewater: suggestions for disinfection strategy during coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic in China. Environ. Pollut. 2020;262</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32443202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.L., Wang S.Z. Reactive species in advanced oxidation processes: formation, identification and reaction mechanism. Chem. Eng. J. 2020;401</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.L., Xu L.J. Advanced oxidation processes for wastewater treatment: formation of hydroxyl radical and application. Crit. Rev. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2012;42:251–325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.L., Zhuan R. Degradation of antibiotics by advanced oxidation processes: an overview. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;701</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31715480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.L., Zhuan R., Chu L.B. The occurrence, distribution and degradation of antibiotics by ionizing radiation: an overview. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;646:1385–1397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30235624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Ye C., Guo L., Chen C., Kong X., Chen Y., Shu L., Wang P., Yu X., Fang J. Assessment of the UV/Chlorine process in the disinfection of Pseudomonas aeruginosa: efficiency and mechanism. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;55:9221–9230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34138551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S.Z., Wang J.L. Radiation-induced degradation of sulfamethoxazole in the presence of various inorganic anions. Chem. Eng. J. 2018;351:688–696.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S.Z., Wang J.L. Degradation of chloroaniline in chemical wastewater by ionizing radiation technology: degradation mechanism and toxicity evaluation. Chemosphere. 2022;287</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34597643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S.Z., Wang J.L. Electron beam technology coupled to Fenton oxidation for advanced treatment of dyeing wastewater: from laboratory to full application. ACS EST Water. 2022;2:852–862.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S.Z., Wang J.L., Chen C.H., He S.J., Hu J., Zhang Y.X. First full-scale application of electron beam technology for treating dyeing wastewater (30,000 m3/d) in China. Radiat. Phys. Chem. 2022;196</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen G., Wan Q., Deng X., Cao R., Xu X., Chen Z., Wang J., Huang T. Reactivation of fungal spores in water following UV disinfection: effect of temperature, dark delay, and real water matrices. Chemosphere. 2019;237</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31394451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang G., Li W., Chen S., Zhou W., Chen J. Problems of conventional disinfection and new sterilization methods for antibiotic resistance control. Chemosphere. 2020;254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32957272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>