<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">36387823</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2307-8960</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>31</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>World journal of clinical cases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>World J Clin Cases</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Coxsackievirus A6 was the most common enterovirus serotype causing hand, foot, and mouth disease in Shiyan City, central China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>11358</StartPage><EndPage>11370</EndPage><MedlinePgn>11358-11370</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.12998/wjcc.v10.i31.11358</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) has become one of the most common infectious diseases in China. Before 2016, the primary causal serotypes were enterovirus A71 (EV-A71) and coxsackievirus A16 (CV-A16). Following the introduction of EV-A71 vaccines in China since 2016, the situation could change. CV-A6 has recently replaced EV-A71 and CV-A16 in some areas of China. However, the epidemiological characteristics of central China remain unknown.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To investigate the clinical symptoms and pathogen spectrum of HFMD in Shiyan City, central China, in recent years.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The epidemiological, clinical, and laboratory data from HFMD cases reported to the Shiyan Center for Disease Control and Prevention between January 2016 and December 2020 were analyzed. 196 throat swab specimens were collected from hospitalized HFMD patients between January 2018 and December 2020. To detect and genotype enteroviruses, real-time reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction and sequencing of the 5'-untranslated region were used. In Shiyan, 168 laboratory-confirmed HFMD cases were studied using a logistic regression model to determine the effect of predominant enterovirus serotypes. Based on the logistic regression model, the least absolute shrinkage and selection operator model was used to analyze the correlation between CV-A6 infection and various clinical characteristics in HFMD patients in Shiyan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">From 2016 to 2020, 35840 HFMD cases were reported in Shiyan. The number of cases decreased by 48.4% from 2016 to 2017. Approximately 1.58-fold increases were found in 2018 and 2019 when compared to the previous year, respectively. In 2020, a decrease of about 85.5% was reported when compared to 2019. The most common serotypes shifted from EV-A71 and CV-A16 (about 60%-80% in 2016 and 2018) to others (more than 80.0% in 2017, 2019, and 2020). EV-A71 lost its dominance in 2017 in Shiyan. Among 196 confirmed HFMD cases, 85.7% tested positive for enterovirus, with CV-A6 being the most common serotype (121/168, 72.0%). The positive rates for CV-A16 and CV-A10 were 4.8% and 3.0%, respectively. There was no EV-A71 discovered. Infection with CV-A6 was linked to fever, myocardial damage, increased creatine kinase MB isoenzyme, and lactate dehydrogenase levels.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">CV-A6 was the most common enterovirus serotype in Shiyan City, replacing EV-A71 and CV-A16 as the HFMD pathogen. Developing vaccines against CV-A6 or multiple pathogens, as well as rising CV-A6 surveillance, will help prevent HFMD in central China.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©The Author(s) 2022. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jing-Feng</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China. zihe1206@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Chuan-Jie</ForeName><Initials>CJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Children Health Care, Wuhan Children's Hospital (Wuhan Maternal and Child Healthcare Hospital), Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan 430061, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Ya-Wei</ForeName><Initials>YW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Services, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Chao</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Shi-Chao</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Sha-Sha</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Xin-Bing</ForeName><Initials>XB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liao</LastName><ForeName>Xing-Juan</ForeName><Initials>XJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taihe Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, Hubei Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Shou-Xin</ForeName><Initials>SX</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceuticals, Shanghai Biotecan Pharmaceuticals Co. Ltd., Shanghai 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhangjiang Center for Translational Medicine, Shanghai Zhangjiang Institute of Medical Innovation, Shanghai 442000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceuticals, Shanghai Biotecan Pharmaceuticals Co. Ltd., Shanghai 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhangjiang Center for Translational Medicine, Shanghai Zhangjiang Institute of Medical Innovation, Shanghai 442000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>World J Clin Cases</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101618806</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2307-8960</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coxsackievirus A6</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fever</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hand, foot, and mouth disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Myocardial damage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence serotype</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict-of-interest statement: All authors hereby declare that no conflict of interest exists.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36387823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9649535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v10.i31.11358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Principi N. Hand, foot and mouth disease: current knowledge on clinical manifestations, epidemiology, aetiology and prevention. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2018;37:391–398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29411190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saguil A, Kane SF, Lauters R, Mercado MG. Hand-Foot-and-Mouth Disease: Rapid Evidence Review. Am Fam Physician. 2019;100:408–414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31573162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei X, Cui S, Zhao Z, Wang J. Etiology, pathogenesis, antivirals and vaccines of hand, foot, and mouth disease. Natl Sci Rev. 2015;2:268–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noisumdaeng P, Korkusol A, Prasertsopon J, Sangsiriwut K, Chokephaibulkit K, Mungaomklang A, Thitithanyanont A, Buathong R, Guntapong R, Puthavathana P. Longitudinal study on enterovirus A71 and coxsackievirus A16 genotype/subgenotype replacements in hand, foot and mouth disease patients in Thailand, 2000-2017. Int J Infect Dis. 2019;80:84–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30639624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Liao Q, Ooi MH, Cowling BJ, Chang Z, Wu P, Liu F, Li Y, Luo L, Yu S, Yu H, Wei S. Epidemiology of Recurrent Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease, China, 2008-2015. Emerg Infect Dis. 2018;24</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5823341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29460747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Spence-Davizon E, Osborne C, Press C, Schreiner TL, Martin J, Messer R, Maloney J, Burakoff A, Barnes M, Rogers S, Lopez AS, Routh J, Gerber SI, Oberste MS, Nix WA, Abzug MJ, Tyler KL, Herlihy R, Dominguez SR. Clinical characteristics of enterovirus A71 neurological disease during an outbreak in children in Colorado, United States, in 2018: an observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:230–239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11284833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31859216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu SL, Pan H, Liu P, Amer S, Chan TC, Zhan J, Huo X, Liu Y, Teng Z, Wang L, Zhuang H. Comparative epidemiology and virology of fatal and nonfatal cases of hand, foot and mouth disease in mainland China from 2008 to 2014. Rev Med Virol. 2015;25:115–128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25704797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao QY, Wang Y, Bian L, Xu M, Liang Z. EV71 vaccine, a new tool to control outbreaks of hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) Expert Rev Vaccines. 2016;15:599–606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26732723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Jiang L, Zhang C, He W, Tan Y, Ning C. The changes in the epidemiology of hand, foot, and mouth disease after the introduction of the EV-A71 vaccine. Vaccine. 2021;39:3319–3323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33994239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osterback R, Vuorinen T, Linna M, Susi P, Hyypiä T, Waris M. Coxsackievirus A6 and hand, foot, and mouth disease, Finland. Emerg Infect Dis. 2009;15:1485–1488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2819858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19788821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Notes from the field: severe hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with coxsackievirus A6 - Alabama, Connecticut, California, and Nevada, November 2011-February 2012. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2012;61:213–214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22456122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horsten HH, Kemp M, Fischer TK, Lindahl KH, Bygum A. Atypical Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease Caused by Coxsackievirus A6 in Denmark: A Diagnostic Mimicker. Acta Derm Venereol. 2018;98:350–354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29182793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gopalkrishna V, Ganorkar N. Epidemiological and molecular characteristics of circulating CVA16, CVA6 strains and genotype distribution in hand, foot and mouth disease cases in 2017 to 2018 from Western India. J Med Virol. 2021;93:3572–3580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32833231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao TS, Du J, Sun DP, Zhu QR, Chen LY, Ye C, Wang S, Liu YQ, Cui F, Lu QB. A review and meta-analysis of the epidemiology and clinical presentation of coxsackievirus A6 causing hand-foot-mouth disease in China and global implications. Rev Med Virol. 2020;30:e2087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31811676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Zheng Y, Shi W, Guan L, Yu P, Xu J, Zhang L, Ma P. Pathogenic characteristics of hand, foot and mouth disease in Shaanxi Province, China, 2010-2016. Sci Rep. 2020;10:989.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6976675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31969644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu S, Li H, Qiao P, Xu G, Zhao D, Lin X, Qin Y, Yu H, Zhang X, Zhang W, Huang L. Neonatal hand, foot, and mouth disease due to coxsackievirus A6 in Shanghai. BMC Pediatr. 2020;20:364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7397588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32741368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y, Zhang Y, Ji T, Gu X, Yang Q, Zhu S, Xu W, Xu Y, Shi Y, Huang X, Li Q, Deng H, Wang X, Yan D, Yu W, Wang S, Yu D. Persistent circulation of Coxsackievirus A6 of genotype D3 in mainland of China between 2008 and 2015. Sci Rep. 2017;7:5491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5511160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28710474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu QB, Zhang XA, Wo Y, Xu HM, Li XJ, Wang XJ, Ding SJ, Chen XD, He C, Liu LJ, Li H, Yang H, Li TY, Liu W, Cao WC. Circulation of Coxsackievirus A10 and A6 in hand-foot-mouth disease in China, 2009-2011. PLoS One. 2012;7:e52073.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3525556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23272213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li XW, Ni X, Qian SY, Wang Q, Jiang RM, Xu WB, Zhang YC, Yu GJ, Chen Q, Shang YX, Zhao CS, Yu H, Zhang T, Liu G, Deng HL, Gao J, Ran XG, Yang QZ, Xu BL, Huang XY, Wu XD, Bao YX, Chen YP, Chen ZH, Liu QQ, Lu GP, Liu CF, Wang RB, Zhang GL, Gu F, Xu HM, Li Y, Yang T. Chinese guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of hand, foot and mouth disease (2018 edition) World J Pediatr. 2018:14: 437–447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30280313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang S, Xie Z, Liu D, Yuan Y, Chen M, Fan X, Ding X, Yu N. Evaluation of 5′-untranslated region amplification and sequencing for enterovirus serotypes identification diagnosis. Zhonghua Shiyan He Linchuang Bingduxue Zazhi. 2018;32:488–491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sauerbrei W, Royston P, Binder H. Selection of important variables and determination of functional form for continuous predictors in multivariable model building. Stat Med. 2007;26:5512–5528.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18058845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kidd AC, McGettrick M, Tsim S, Halligan DL, Bylesjo M, Blyth KG. Survival prediction in mesothelioma using a scalable Lasso regression model: instructions for use and initial performance using clinical predictors. BMJ Open Respir Res. 2018;5:e000240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5812388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29468073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seddon JH, Duff MF. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease: Coxsackie virus types A 5, A 10, and A 16 infections. N Z Med J. 1971;74:368–373.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5291880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson CR, Doane FW, Rhodes AJ. Report of an outbreak of febrile illness with pharyngeal lesions and exanthem: Toronto, summer 1957; isolation of group A Coxsackie virus. Can Med Assoc J. 1958;79:615–621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1830188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13585281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanh TH, Sabanathan S, Thanh TT, Thoa le PK, Thuong TC, Hang Vt, Farrar J, Hien TT, Chau Nv, van Doorn HR. Enterovirus 71-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease, Southern Vietnam, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012;18:2002–2005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3557876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23194699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan KP, Goh KT, Chong CY, Teo ES, Lau G, Ling AE. Epidemic hand, foot and mouth disease caused by human enterovirus 71, Singapore. Emerg Infect Dis. 2003;9:78–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2873753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12533285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn P, Stratov I, Nagarajan L, Davis S. Neurological manifestations of enterovirus 71 infection in children during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Western Australia. Clin Infect Dis. 2001;32:236–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11170913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan LG, Parashar UD, Lye MS, Ong FG, Zaki SR, Alexander JP, Ho KK, Han LL, Pallansch MA, Suleiman AB, Jegathesan M, Anderson LJ. Deaths of children during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in sarawak, malaysia: clinical and pathological characteristics of the disease. For the Outbreak Study Group. Clin Infect Dis. 2000;31:678–683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11017815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Deaths among children during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease--Taiwan, Republic of China, April-July 1998. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 1998;47:629–632.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9704628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagy G, Takátsy S, Kukán E, Mihály I, Dömök I. Virological diagnosis of enterovirus type 71 infections: experiences gained during an epidemic of acute CNS diseases in Hungary in 1978. Arch Virol. 1982;71:217–227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6285858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishimaru Y, Nakano S, Yamaoka K, Takami S. Outbreaks of hand, foot, and mouth disease by enterovirus 71. High incidence of complication disorders of central nervous system. Arch Dis Child. 1980;55:583–588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1627055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6254449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chumakov M, Voroshilova M, Shindarov L, Lavrova I, Gracheva L, Koroleva G, Vasilenko S, Brodvarova I, Nikolova M, Gyurova S, Gacheva M, Mitov G, Ninov N, Tsylka E, Robinson I, Frolova M, Bashkirtsev V, Martiyanova L, Rodin V. Enterovirus 71 isolated from cases of epidemic poliomyelitis-like disease in Bulgaria. Arch Virol. 1979;60:329–340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">228639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FLEWETT TH, WARIN RP, CLARKE SK. 'Hand, foot, and mouth disease' associated with Coxsackie A5 virus. J Clin Pathol. 1963;16:53–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC480485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13945538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nassef C, Ziemer C, Morrell DS. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease: a new look at a classic viral rash. Curr Opin Pediatr. 2015;27:486–491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26087425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koh WM, Bogich T, Siegel K, Jin J, Chong EY, Tan CY, Chen MI, Horby P, Cook AR. The Epidemiology of Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease in Asia: A Systematic Review and Analysis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2016;35:e285–e300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5130063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27273688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishimura Y, Shimizu H. Cellular receptors for human enterovirus species a. Front Microbiol. 2012;3:105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3313065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22470371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang PC, Chen SC, Chen KT. The Current Status of the Disease Caused by Enterovirus 71 Infections: Epidemiology, Pathogenesis, Molecular Epidemiology, and Vaccine Development. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2016;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5036723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27618078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li ML, Shih SR, Tolbert BS, Brewer G. Enterovirus A71 Vaccines. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7997495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33673595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He F, Rui J, Deng Z, Zhang Y, Qian K, Zhu C, Yu S, Tu J, Xia W, Zhu Q, Chen S, Chen T, Zhou X. Surveillance, Epidemiology and Impact of EV-A71 Vaccination on Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease in Nanchang, China, 2010-2019. Front Microbiol. 2021;12:811553.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8770912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35069515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian L, Gao F, Mao Q, Sun S, Wu X, Liu S, Yang X, Liang Z. Hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with coxsackievirus A10: more serious than it seems. Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther. 2019;17:233–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30793637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puenpa J, Mauleekoonphairoj J, Linsuwanon P, Suwannakarn K, Chieochansin T, Korkong S, Theamboonlers A, Poovorawan Y. Prevalence and characterization of enterovirus infections among pediatric patients with hand foot mouth disease, herpangina and influenza like illness in Thailand, 2012. PLoS One. 2014;9:e98888.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4041783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24887237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Mao N, Yu W, Chai Q, Wang H, Wang W, Wang L, Wang Z, Xu W. Genetic characterization of emerging coxsackievirus A12 associated with hand, foot and mouth disease in Qingdao, China. Arch Virol. 2014;159:2497–2502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24796551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montes M, Artieda J, Piñeiro LD, Gastesi M, Diez-Nieves I, Cilla G. Hand, foot, and mouth disease outbreak and coxsackievirus A6, northern Spain, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis. 2013;19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3647425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23751014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujimoto T, Iizuka S, Enomoto M, Abe K, Yamashita K, Hanaoka N, Okabe N, Yoshida H, Yasui Y, Kobayashi M, Fujii Y, Tanaka H, Yamamoto M, Shimizu H. Hand, foot, and mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6, Japan, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012;18:337–339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3310456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22304983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di B, Zhang Y, Xie H, Li X, Chen C, Ding P, He P, Wang D, Geng J, Luo L, Bai Z, Yang Z, Wang M. Circulation of Coxsackievirus A6 in hand-foot-mouth disease in Guangzhou, 2010-2012. Virol J. 2014;11:157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4169826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25178398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He YQ, Chen L, Xu WB, Yang H, Wang HZ, Zong WP, Xian HX, Chen HL, Yao XJ, Hu ZL, Luo M, Zhang HL, Ma HW, Cheng JQ, Feng QJ, Zhao DJ. Emergence, circulation, and spatiotemporal phylogenetic analysis of coxsackievirus a6- and coxsackievirus a10-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease infections from 2008 to 2012 in Shenzhen, China. J Clin Microbiol. 2013;51:3560–3566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3889734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23966496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SH, Wang A, Liu PP, Zhang WY, Du J, Xu S, Liu GC, Zheng BS, Huan C, Zhao K, Yu XF. Divergent Pathogenic Properties of Circulating Coxsackievirus A6 Associated with Emerging Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease. J Virol. 2018;92</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5952127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29563294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan X, Li L, Zhang B, Jorba J, Su X, Ji T, Yang D, Lv L, Li J, Xu W. Molecular epidemiology of coxsackievirus A6 associated with outbreaks of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Tianjin, China, in 2013. Arch Virol. 2015;160:1097–1104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4629805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25680566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zha J, Ma Z. Epidemiological and genetic analysis concerning the coxsackievirus A6 related endemic outbreak of hand-foot-mouth disease in Taizhou, China, during 2013. J Med Virol. 2015;87:2000–2008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25989289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan X, Zhang ZZ, Yang ZH, Zhu CM, Hu YG, Liu QB. Clinical and Etiological Characteristics of Atypical Hand-Foot-and-Mouth Disease in Children from Chongqing, China: A Retrospective Study. Biomed Res Int. 2015;2015:802046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4674665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26693489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hongyan G, Chengjie M, Qiaozhi Y, Wenhao H, Juan L, Lin P, Yanli X, Hongshan W, Xingwang L. Hand, foot and mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6, Beijing, 2013. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2014;33:1302–1303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25037037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu FY, Zhu RN, Deng J, Song QW, Jia LP, Liu LY, Qian Y. [Pathogen spectrum in enteroviral infections among children in Beijing from 2010 to 2016] Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi. 2018;56:575–581.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30078237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao J, He XY, Shi Y, Zhu G, Liu S, Zhang Z, Tang S, Zhang R, Peng B, Liu Z, Tan J, Chen Q, Wang X, Bao L, Zou L, Zhang P. Epidemiology of 45,616 suspect cases of Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease in Chongqing, China, 2011-2015. Sci Rep. 2017;7:45630.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5395817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28422128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu L, Maimaiti H, Zhou L, Gao J, Lu Y. Changing serotypes of hand, foot and mouth disease in Shanghai, 2017-2019. Gut Pathog. 2022;14:12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8935267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35313977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui Y, Yang YN, Zheng RR, Xie MZ, Zhang WX, Chen LY, Du J, Yang Y, Xi L, Li H, Li HJ, Lu QB. Epidemiological characteristics of hand, foot, and mouth disease clusters during 2016-2020 in Beijing, China. J Med Virol. 2022;94:4934–4943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35655366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang H, Zhang Z, Rao Q, Wang X, Wang M, Du T, Tang J, Long S, Zhang J, Luo J, Pan Y, Chen J, Ma J, Liu X, Fan M, Zhang T, Sun Q. The epidemiological characteristics of enterovirus infection before and after the use of enterovirus 71 inactivated vaccine in Kunming, China. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2021;10:619–628.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8018479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33682641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang F, Yuan J, Wang X, Li J, Du J, Su H, Zhou B, Jin Q. Severe hand, foot, and mouth disease and coxsackievirus A6-Shenzhen, China. Clin Infect Dis. 2014;59:1504–1505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25091307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramirez-Fort MK, Downing C, Doan HQ, Benoist F, Oberste MS, Khan F, Tyring SK. Coxsackievirus A6 associated hand, foot and mouth disease in adults: clinical presentation and review of the literature. J Clin Virol. 2014;60:381–386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24932735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris PNA, Wang AD, Yin M, Lee CK, Archuleta S. Atypical hand, foot, and mouth disease: eczema coxsackium can also occur in adults. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14:1043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25444404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justino MCA, da S Mesquita D, Souza MF, Farias FP, Dos S Alves JC, Ferreira JL, Lopes DP, Tavares FN. Atypical hand-foot-mouth disease in Belém, Amazon region, northern Brazil, with detection of coxsackievirus A6. J Clin Virol. 2020;126:104307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Liu Y, Liu F, Ren M, Nie T, Cui J, Chang Z, Li Z. Basic Reproduction Number of Enterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A16 and A6: Evidence From Outbreaks of Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease in China Between 2011 and 2018. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;73:e2552–e2559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33320199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian SS, Wei ZN, Jin WP, Wu J, Zhou YP, Meng SL, Guo J, Wang ZJ, Shen S. Efficacy of a coxsackievirus A6 vaccine candidate in an actively immunized mouse model. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2021;10:763–773.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8079124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33739899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Büttner CR, Spurný R, Füzik T, Plevka P. Cryo-electron microscopy and image classification reveal the existence and structure of the coxsackievirus A6 virion. Commun Biol. 2022;5:898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9438360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36056184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>