<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36639694</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>14</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-1654</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>33</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Reviews in medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Management of neonatal central nervous system viral infections: Knowledge gaps and research priorities.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2421</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2421</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/rmv.2421</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Congenital CMV, enteroviruses, human parechovirus and herpes simplex virus are all common causes of severe central nervous system (CNS) infection in neonates. The introduction of screening (i.e. newborn hearing screening programme), integration of molecular syndromic testing (i.e. multiplex polymerase chain reaction assays) and increase in sexually transmitted infections (i.e. anogenital herpes) have contributed to increases in each of these infections over the last decade. However, therapeutic options are highly limited in part due to the lack of epidemiological data informing trials. This review will describe our current understanding of the clinical burden and epidemiology of these severe neonatal CNS infections, outline the novel antiviral and vaccines in the pipeline and suggest future research studies which could help develop new therapeutics.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors. Reviews in Medical Virology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abeywickrema</LastName><ForeName>Movin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infection, Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kelly</LastName><ForeName>Dominic</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford and the NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kadambari</LastName><ForeName>Seilesh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatric Infectious Diseases, Great Ormond Street Hospital for Children NHS Foundation Trust, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University College London, Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9112448</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1052-9276</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020805" MajorTopicYN="Y">Central Nervous System Viral Diseases</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006566" MajorTopicYN="Y">Herpesviridae Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003586" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cytomegalovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002494" MajorTopicYN="Y">Central Nervous System Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012106" MajorTopicYN="N">Research</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CMV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">herpes simplex virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">parechovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36639694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.2421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Pollard AJ, Goldacre MJ, et al. Congenital viral infections in England over five decades: a population-based observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:220-229. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(1930416-5)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Braccio S, Ribeiro S, et al. Enterovirus and parechovirus meningitis in infants younger than 90 days old in the UK and Republic of Ireland: a British Paediatric Surveillance Unit study. Arch Dis Child. 2019;104(6):552-557. https://doi.org/10.1136/archdischild-2018-315643</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones CA, Raynes-Greenow C, Isaacs D; on behalf of the Neonatal HSV Study Investigators and Contributors to the Australian Paediatric Surveillance Unit. Population-based surveillance of neonatal herpes simplex virus infection in Australia, 1997-2011. Clin Infect Dis. 2014;59(4):525-531. https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/ciu381</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Handel S, Klingler EJ, Washburn K, Blank S, Schillinger JA. Population-based surveillance for neonatal herpes in New York City, April 2006-September 2010. Sex Transm Dis. 2011;38(8):705-711. https://doi.org/10.1097/OLQ.0b013e31821b178f</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiereghin A, Verucchi G, Lazzarotto T. CMV-specific cell-mediated immunity in immunocompetent adults with primary CMV infection: a case series and review of the literature. Viruses. 2021;13(5):816. https://doi.org/10.3390/v13050816</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kenneson A, Cannon MJ. Review and meta-analysis of the epidemiology of congenital cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection. Rev Med Virol. 2007;17(4):253-276. https://doi.org/10.1002/rmv.535</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pass RF, Zhang C, Evans A, et al. Vaccine prevention of maternal cytomegalovirus infection. N Engl J Med. 2009;360(12):1191-1199. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa0804749</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barton M, Forrester AM, McDonald J. Update on congenital cytomegalovirus infection: prenatal prevention, newborn diagnosis, and management. Paediatr Child Health. 2020;25:395-396. https://doi.org/10.1093/pch/pxaa083</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimberlin DW, Jester PM, Sánchez PJ, et al. Valganciclovir for symptomatic congenital cytomegalovirus disease. N Engl J Med. 2015;372(10):933-943. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1404599</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Retzler J, Hex N, Bartlett C, et al. Economic cost of congenital CMV in the UK. Arch Dis Child. 2019;104(6):559-563. https://doi.org/10.1136/archdischild-2018-316010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuhair M, Smit GSA, Wallis G, et al. Estimation of the worldwide seroprevalence of cytomegalovirus: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Rev Med Virol. 2019;29(3):e2034. https://doi.org/10.1002/rmv.2034</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasoona KR, Srinadh B, Sunitha T, et al. Seroprevalence and influence of torch infections in high risk pregnant women: a large study from South India. J Obstet Gynaecol India. 2015;65(5):301-309. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13224-014-0615-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marsico C, Kimberlin DW. Congenital cytomegalovirus infection: advances and challenges in diagnosis, prevention and treatment. Ital J Pediatr. 2017;43(1):38. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13052-017-0358-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dar L, Namdeo D, Kumar P, et al. Congenital cytomegalovirus infection and permanent hearing loss in rural North Indian children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2017;36(7):670-673. https://doi.org/10.1097/INF.0000000000001527</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Putri ND, Wiyatno A, Dhenni R, et al. Birth prevalence and characteristics of congenital cytomegalovirus infection in an urban birth cohort, Jakarta, Indonesia. Int J Infect Dis. 2019;86:31-39. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2019.06.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madrid L, Varo R, Maculuve S, et al. Congenital cytomegalovirus, parvovirus and enterovirus infection in Mozambican newborns at birth: a cross-sectional survey. PLoS One. 2018;13(3):e0194186. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0194186</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revello MG, Tibaldi C, Masuelli G, et al. Prevention of primary cytomegalovirus infection in pregnancy. EBioMedicine. 2015;2(9):1205-1210. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2015.08.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahar-Nissan K, Pardo J, Peled O, et al. Valaciclovir to prevent vertical transmission of cytomegalovirus after maternal primary infection during pregnancy: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2020;396(10253):779-785. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31868-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revello MG, Lazzarotto T, Guerra B, et al. A randomized trial of hyperimmune globulin to prevent congenital cytomegalovirus. N Engl J Med. 2014;370(14):1316-1326. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1310214</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimberlin DW, Lin C-Y, Sánchez PJ, et al. Effect of ganciclovir therapy on hearing in symptomatic congenital cytomegalovirus disease involving the central nervous system: a randomized, controlled trial. J Pediatr. 2003;143(1):16-25. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0022-3476(03)00192-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliver SE, Cloud GA, Sánchez PJ, et al. Neurodevelopmental outcomes following ganciclovir therapy in symptomatic congenital cytomegalovirus infections involving the central nervous system. J Clin Virol. 2009;46(suppl 4):S22-S26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2009.08.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou XJ, Gruber W, Demmler G, et al. Population pharmacokinetics of ganciclovir in newborns with congenital cytomegalovirus infections. NIAID Collaborative Antiviral Study Group. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1996;40(9):2202-2205. https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.40.9.2202</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimberlin DW, Acosta EP, Sánchez PJ, et al. Pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic assessment of oral valganciclovir in the treatment of symptomatic congenital cytomegalovirus disease. J Infect Dis. 2008;197(6):836-845. https://doi.org/10.1086/528376</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsaleem M. Intravenous immune globulin uses in the fetus and neonate: a review. Antibodies. 2020;9(4):60. https://doi.org/10.3390/antib9040060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Keyserling HL, Lee ML, Levin MJ, Rotbart HA. Neonatal enterovirus infection: virology, serology, and effects of intravenous immune globulin. Clin Infect Dis. 1995;20(5):1201-1206. https://doi.org/10.1093/clinids/20.5.1201</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yen M-H, Huang Y-C, Chen M-C, et al. Effect of intravenous immunoglobulin for neonates with severe enteroviral infections with emphasis on the timing of administration. J Clin Virol. 2015;64:92-96. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2015.01.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Izumita R, Aizawa Y, Watanabe K, Saitoh A. A role of intravenous immunoglobulin in human parechovirus type 3 infection in an in vitro model. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2016;3(suppl_1). https://doi.org/10.1093/ofid/ofw172.20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wildenbeest JG, Wolthers KC, Straver B, Pajkrt D. Successful IVIG treatment of human parechovirus-associated dilated cardiomyopathy in an infant. Pediatrics. 2013;132(1):e243-e247. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2012-1136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azuma J, Yamamoto T, Sakurai M, et al. Urinary β2-microglobulin as an early marker of infantile enterovirus and human parechovirus infections. Medicine (Baltim). 2018;97(43):e12930. https://doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000012930</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimberlin DW, Lin C-Y, Jacobs RF, et al. Safety and efficacy of high-dose intravenous acyclovir in the management of neonatal herpes simplex virus infections. Pediatrics. 2001;108(2):230-238. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.108.2.230</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Downes KJ, Boge CLK, Baro E, et al. Acute kidney injury during treatment with intravenous acyclovir for suspected or confirmed neonatal herpes simplex virus infection. J Pediatr. 2020;219:126-132.e2. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpeds.2019.12.056</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitley R, Arvin A, Prober C, et al. A controlled trial comparing vidarabine with acyclovir in neonatal herpes simplex virus infection. N Engl J Med. 1991;324(7):444-449. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJM199102143240703</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sampson MR, Bloom BT, Lenfestey RW, et al. Population pharmacokinetics of intravenous acyclovir in preterm and term infants. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2014;33(1):42-49. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.inf.0000435509.75114.3d</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimberlin DW, Whitley RJ, Wan W, et al. Oral acyclovir suppression and neurodevelopment after neonatal herpes. N Engl J Med. 2011;365(14):1284-1292. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1003509</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tod M, Lokiec F, Bidault R, et al. Pharmacokinetics of oral acyclovir in neonates and in infants: a population analysis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2001;45(1):150-157. https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.45.1.150-157.2001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID). A phase II, single stage, single-arm investigation of oral valganciclovir therapy in infants with asymptomatic congenital cytomegalovirus infection. clinicaltrials.gov. 2020. Accessed December 6, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03301415</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cytomegalovirus. Accessed January 26, 2021. https://legacyscreening.phe.org.uk/cytomegalovirus</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marshall BC, Koch WC. Antivirals for cytomegalovirus infection in neonates and infants: focus on pharmacokinetics, formulations, dosing, and adverse events. Paediatr Drugs. 2009;11(5):309-321. https://doi.org/10.2165/11316080-000000000-00000</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vora SB, Brothers AW, Englund JA. Renal toxicity in pediatric patients receiving cidofovir for the treatment of adenovirus infection. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc. 2017;6(4):399-402. https://doi.org/10.1093/jpids/pix011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tippin TK, Morrison ME, Brundage TM, Mommeja-Marin H. Brincidofovir is not a substrate for the human organic anion transporter 1: a mechanistic explanation for the lack of nephrotoxicity observed in clinical studies. Ther Drug Monit. 2016;38(6):777-786. https://doi.org/10.1097/FTD.0000000000000353</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nigro G, Sali E, Anceschi MM, et al. Foscarnet therapy for congenital cytomegalovirus liver fibrosis following prenatal ascites. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med. 2004;15(5):325-329. https://doi.org/10.1080/14767050410001701349</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knorr B, Kessler U, Pöschl J, Poschl J, Fickenscher H, Linderkamp O. A haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis (HLH)-like picture following breastmilk transmitted cytomegalovirus infection in a preterm infant. Scand J Infect Dis. 2007;39(2):173-176. https://doi.org/10.1080/00365540600786598</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabbaj S, Pass RF, Goepfert PA, et al. Glycoprotein B vaccine is capable of boosting both antibody and CD4 T-cell responses to cytomegalovirus in chronically infected women. J Infect Dis. 2011;203(11):1534-1541. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jir138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hookipa Biotech GmbH. A randomized, placebo-control, phase 2 study of HB-101, a bivalent cytomegalovirus (CMV) vaccine, in CMV-seronegative recipient (R-) patients awaiting kidney transplantation from living CMV-seropositive donors (D+). clinicaltrials.gov. 2020. Accessed December 30, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03629080</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>John S, Yuzhakov O, Woods A, et al. Multi-antigenic human cytomegalovirus mRNA vaccines that elicit potent humoral and cell-mediated immunity. Vaccine. 2018;36(12):1689-1699. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2018.01.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ModernaTX, Inc. A phase 1, randomized, observer-blind, placebo-controlled, dose-ranging study to evaluate the safety, reactogenicity, and immunogenicity of cytomegalovirus vaccines mRNA-1647 and mRNA-1443 when administered to healthy adults. clinicaltrials.gov. 2019. Accessed December 7, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03382405</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ModernaTX, Inc. A phase 2, randomized, observer-blind, placebo-controlled, dose-finding trial to evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of cytomegalovirus vaccine mRNA-1647 in healthy adults. clinicaltrials.gov. 2020. Accessed December 7, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04232280</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moderna completes enrollment of cytomegalovirus (CMV) vaccine (mRNA-1647) phase 2 study | Moderna, Inc. Accessed February 23, 2021. https://investors.modernatx.com/news-releases/news-release-details/moderna-completes-enrollment-cytomegalovirus-cmv-vaccine-mrna/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adler SP, Manganello A-M, Lee R, et al. A phase 1 study of 4 live, recombinant human cytomegalovirus towne/toledo chimera vaccines in cytomegalovirus-seronegative men. J Infect Dis. 2016;214(9):1341-1348. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiw365</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adler SP, Lewis N, Conlon A, et al. Phase 1 clinical trial of a conditionally replication-defective human cytomegalovirus (CMV) vaccine in CMV-seronegative subjects. J Infect Dis. 2019;220(3):411-419. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiz141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, La Rosa C, Li Z, et al. Vaccine properties of a novel marker gene-free recombinant modified vaccinia ankara expressing immunodominant CMV antigens pp65 and IE1. Vaccine. 2007;25(6):1132-1141. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2006.09.067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plotkin SA, Wang D, Oualim A, et al. The status of vaccine development against the human cytomegalovirus. J Infect Dis. 2020;221(supplement_1):S113-S122. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiz447</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multi-antigen CMV-modified vaccinia ankara vaccine in treating pediatric patients with positive cytomegalovirus undergoing donor stem cell transplant - full text view - ClinicalTrials.gov. Accessed December 8, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03354728</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>City of Hope Medical Center. A phase II randomized, placebo-controlled, multicenter trial to evaluate protective function of an optimized dose of CMVPepVax in recipients of an allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant. clinicaltrials.gov. 2019. Accessed December 30, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT02396134</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker RC, Kummer AW, Schultz JR, Ho M, Gonzalez del Rey J. Neurodevelopmental outcome of infants with viral meningitis in the first three months of life. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 1996;35(6):295-301. https://doi.org/10.1177/000992289603500602</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasubramanian H, Wagh D, Rao S, Keil AD, McMichael J. Developmental outcomes in cerebrospinal fluid proven enteroviral meningitis in neonates &gt; 32 weeks of gestation. J Paediatr Child Health. 2016;52(3):327-332. https://doi.org/10.1111/jpc.13083</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang L-Y, Huang L-M, Gau SS-F, et al. Neurodevelopment and cognition in children after enterovirus 71 infection. N Engl J Med. 2007;356(12):1226-1234. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa065954</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gau SS-F, Chang L-Y, Huang L-M, Fan TY, Wu YY, Lin TY. Attention-deficit/hyperactivity-related symptoms among children with enterovirus 71 infection of the central nervous system. Pediatrics. 2008;122(2):e452-e458. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2007-3799</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song JY, Nam SO, Kim YA, et al. Cerebrospinal fluid non-pleocytosis in pediatric enteroviral meningitis: large-scale review. Pediatr Int. 2018;60(9):855-861. https://doi.org/10.1111/ped.13658</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee BR, Sasidharan A, Harrison CJ, Selvarangan R. Positive impact of routine testing for enterovirus and parechovirus on length of hospitalization and antimicrobial use among inpatients ≤6 months of age. J Clin Microbiol. 2020;59(1). https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.02106-20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puenpa J, Wanlapakorn N, Vongpunsawad S, Poovorawan Y. The history of enterovirus A71 outbreaks and molecular epidemiology in the Asia-Pacific region. J Biomed Sci. 2019;26(1):75. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12929-019-0573-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagner JN, Leibetseder A, Troescher A, Panholzer J, von Oertzen TJ. Characteristics and therapy of enteroviral encephalitis: case report and systematic literature review. Int J Infect Dis. 2021;113:93-102. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2021.10.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chimerix A. Multicenter, open-label study of CMX001 treatment of serious diseases or conditions caused by dsDNA viruses. clinicaltrials.gov. 2020. Accessed November 17, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01143181</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reusser P, Einsele H, Lee J, et al. Randomized multicenter trial of foscarnet versus ganciclovir for preemptive therapy of cytomegalovirus infection after allogeneic stem cell transplantation. Blood. 2002;99(4):1159-1164. https://doi.org/10.1182/blood.v99.4.1159</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouphael NG, Hurwitz SJ, Hart M, et al. Phase Ib trial to evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics of multiple ascending doses of filociclovir (MBX-400, cyclopropavir) in healthy volunteers. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2019;63(9). https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.00717-19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gergen J, Coulon F, Creneguy A, et al. Multiplex CRISPR/Cas9 system impairs HCMV replication by excising an essential viral gene. PLoS One. 2018;13(2):e0192602. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0192602</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen S-J, Chen Y-C. Potential application of TALENs against murine cytomegalovirus latent infections. Viruses. 2019;11(5):414. https://doi.org/10.3390/v11050414</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King MW, Munger J. Editing the human cytomegalovirus genome with the CRISPR/Cas9 system. Virology. 2019;529:186-194. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2019.01.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Song Z, Qin B, et al. Rupintrivir is a promising candidate for treating severe cases of enterovirus-71 infection: evaluation of antiviral efficacy in a murine infection model. Antivir Res. 2013;97(3):264-269. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2012.12.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baggen J, Thibaut HJ, Strating JRPM, van Kuppeveld FJM. The life cycle of non-polio enteroviruses and how to target it. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2018;16(6):368-381. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-018-0005-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Michaels MG, Wald E, et al. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of pleconaril for the treatment of neonates with enterovirus sepsis. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc. 2016;5(1):53-62. https://doi.org/10.1093/jpids/piv015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Wang Y, He W, et al. Design, synthesis, and evaluation of novel enterovirus 71 inhibitors as therapeutic drug leads for the treatment of human hand, foot, and mouth disease. J Med Chem. 2020;63(3):1233-1244. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.9b01414</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wittekind SG, Allen CC, Jefferies JL, et al. Neonatal enterovirus myocarditis with severe dystrophic calcification: novel treatment with pocapavir. J Investig Med High Impact Case Rep. 2017;5(3):2324709617729393. https://doi.org/10.1177/2324709617729393</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amdani SM, Kim HS, Orvedahl A, John AO, Said A, Simpson K. Successful treatment of fulminant neonatal enteroviral myocarditis in monochorionic diamniotic twins with cardiopulmonary support, intravenous immunoglobulin and pocapavir. Case Rep. 2018;2018:bcr-2017-224133. https://doi.org/10.1136/bcr-2017-224133</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Study to evaluate the tolerance and pharmacokinetics of suramin sodium - full text view - ClinicalTrials.gov. Accessed December 13, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03804749</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren P, Zou G, Bailly B, et al. The approved pediatric drug suramin identified as a clinical candidate for the treatment of EV71 infection-suramin inhibits EV71 infection in vitro and in vivo. Emerg Microb Infect. 2014;3(1):e62-e69. https://doi.org/10.1038/emi.2014.60</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manganaro R, Zonsics B, Bauer L, et al. Synthesis and antiviral effect of novel fluoxetine analogues as enterovirus 2C inhibitors. Antivir Res. 2020;178:104781. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104781</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du R, Mao Q, Hu Y, et al. A potential therapeutic neutralization monoclonal antibody specifically against multi-coxsackievirus A16 strains challenge. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2019;15(10):2343-2350. https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2019.1565266</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou B, Xu L, Zhu R, et al. A bispecific broadly neutralizing antibody against enterovirus 71 and coxsackievirus A16 with therapeutic potential. Antivir Res. 2019;161:28-35. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.11.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strating JRPM, van der Linden L, Albulescu L, et al. Itraconazole inhibits enterovirus replication by targeting the oxysterol-binding protein. Cell Rep. 2015;10(4):600-615. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2014.12.054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shakeel S, Westerhuis BM, Ora A, et al. Structural basis of human parechovirus neutralization by human monoclonal antibodies. J Virol. 2015;89(18):9571-9580. https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.01429-15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wald A, Timmler B, Magaret A, et al. Effect of pritelivir compared with valacyclovir on genital HSV-2 shedding in patients with frequent recurrences: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2016;316(23):2495-2503. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2016.18189</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AiCuris Anti-infective Cures GmbH. A randomized, open label, multi-center, comparative trial, to assess the efficacy and safety of pritelivir versus foscarnet for the treatment of acyclovir-resistant mucocutaneous HSV (herpes simplex virus) infections in immunocompromised adults (PRIOH-1). clinicaltrials.gov. 2020. Accessed December 30, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03073967</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyring S, Wald A, Zadeikis N, Dhadda S, Takenouchi K, Rorig R. ASP2151 for the treatment of genital herpes: a randomized, double-blind, placebo- and valacyclovir-controlled, dose-finding study. J Infect Dis. 2012;205(7):1100-1110. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jis019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawashima M, Nemoto O, Honda M, et al. Amenamevir, a novel helicase-primase inhibitor, for treatment of herpes zoster: a randomized, double-blind, valaciclovir-controlled phase 3 study. J Dermatol. 2017;44(11):1219-1227. https://doi.org/10.1111/1346-8138.13948</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roehm PC, Shekarabi M, Wollebo HS, et al. Inhibition of HSV-1 replication by gene editing strategy. Sci Rep. 2016;6(1):23146. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep23146</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paavilainen H, Romanovskaya A, Nygårdas M, Bamford DH, Poranen MM, Hukkanen V. Innate responses to small interfering RNA pools inhibiting herpes simplex virus infection in astrocytoid and epithelial cells. Innate Immun. 2014;21(4):349-357. https://doi.org/10.1177/1753425914537921</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Cloud G, Bradley J, et al. Double blind placebo-controlled trial of pleconaril in infants with enterovirus meningitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2003;22(4):335-341. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.inf.0000059765.92623.70</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres-Torres S, Myers AL, Klatte JM, et al. First use of investigational antiviral drug pocapavir (V-073) for treating neonatal enteroviral sepsis. Pediatric Infect Dis J. 2015;34(1):52-54. https://doi.org/10.1097/INF.0000000000000497</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benkahla MA, Alidjinou EK, Sane F, Desailloud R, Hober D. Fluoxetine can inhibit coxsackievirus-B4 E2 in vitro and in vivo. Antivir Res. 2018;159:130-133. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.10.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Sillau S, Hopkins SE, et al. Safety, tolerability, and efficacy of fluoxetine as an antiviral for acute flaccid myelitis. Neurology. 2019;92:e2118-e2126. https://doi.org/10.1212/WNL.0000000000006670</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Immunization in the Asia-Pacific region - ScienceDirect. Accessed June 18, 2022. https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9781455700905000690</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q. The safety, immune persistence and consistency of inactivated enterovirus 71 vaccine (human diploid cell, KMB-17). clinicaltrials.gov. 2018. Accessed June 22, 2022. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT02999828</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu W, Zeng G, Hu Y-M, et al. A comparative analysis of immunogenicity and safety of an enterovirus 71 vaccine between children aged 3-5 years and infants aged 6-35 months. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2018;17(3):257-262. https://doi.org/10.1080/14760584.2018.1430572</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HK inno.N Corporation. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 1 clinical trial to investigate the safety and immunogenicity of high-dose IN-B001 after administration in healthy subjects. clinicaltrials.gov. 2020. Accessed December 10, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04637919</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tambyah PA, Oon J, Asli R, et al. An inactivated enterovirus 71 vaccine is safe and immunogenic in healthy adults: a phase I, double blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, study of two dosages. Vaccine. 2019;37(31):4344-4353. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.06.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R, Liu L, Mo Z, et al. An inactivated enterovirus 71 vaccine in healthy children. N Engl J Med. 2014;370(9):829-837. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1303224</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinimäki S, Hankaniemi MM, Sioofy-Khojine A-B, et al. Combination of three virus-derived nanoparticles as a vaccine against enteric pathogens; enterovirus, norovirus and rotavirus. Vaccine. 2019;37(51):7509-7518. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.09.072</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Zhu R, Xu L, et al. A novel combined vaccine based on monochimeric VLP co-displaying multiple conserved epitopes against enterovirus 71 and varicella-zoster virus. Vaccine. 2017;35(20):2728-2735. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.03.065</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton PN, Jones CA, Macartney K, Cheng AC. Parechovirus: an important emerging infection in young infants. Med J Aust. 2018;208(8):365-369. https://doi.org/10.5694/mja18.00149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamings A, Druce J, Caly L, et al. Evolutionary analysis of human parechovirus type 3 and clinical outcomes of infection during the 2017-18 Australian epidemic. Sci Rep. 2019;9(1):8906. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-45445-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Harvala H, Simmonds P, Pollard AJ, Sadarangani M. Strategies to improve detection and management of human parechovirus infection in young infants. Lancet Infect Dis. 2019;19(2):e51-e58. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30288-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sedmak G, Nix WA, Jentzen J, et al. Infant deaths associated with human parechovirus infection in Wisconsin. Clin Infect Dis. 2010;50(3):357-361. https://doi.org/10.1086/649863</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton PN, Dale RC, Nissen MD, et al. Parechovirus encephalitis and neurodevelopmental outcomes. Pediatrics. 2016;137(2). https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2015-2848</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson JA, Broad J, Martin NG, et al. Outcomes beyond hospital discharge in infants and children with viral meningitis: a systematic review. Rev Med Virol. 2020;30(2):e2083. https://doi.org/10.1002/rmv.2083</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Hinsbergh TMT, Elbers RG, van Furth MAM, Obihara CCC. Longitudinal association between human parechovirus central nervous system infection and gross-motor neurodevelopment in young children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2019;38(2):110-114. https://doi.org/10.1097/INF.0000000000002052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Looker KJ, Magaret AS, May MT, et al. First estimates of the global and regional incidence of neonatal herpes infection. Lancet Global Health. 2017;5(3):e300-e309. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(16)30362-X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinninti SG, Kimberlin DW. Management of neonatal herpes simplex virus infection and exposure. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2014;99(3):F240-F244. https://doi.org/10.1136/archdischild-2013-303762</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes ND, Arya K, Ward R. Congenital herpes simplex. In: StatPearls. StatPearls Publishing; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu F, Markowitz LE, Gottlieb SL, Berman SM. Seroprevalence of herpes simplex virus types 1 and 2 in pregnant women in the United States. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2007;196:43.e1-43.e436. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajog.2006.07.051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warnecke JM, Pollmann M, Borchardt-Lohölter V, et al. Seroprevalences of antibodies against ToRCH infectious pathogens in women of childbearing age residing in Brazil, Mexico, Germany, Poland, Turkey and China. Epidemiol Infect. 2020;148:e271. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0950268820002629</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ju N, Sanders EJ, Ngetsa C, et al. Seroprevalence, predictors and estimated incidence of maternal and neonatal herpes simplex virus Type 2 infection in semi-urban women in Kilifi, Kenya. BMC Infect Dis. 2011;11(1):155. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2334-11-155</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tookey P, Peckham CS. Neonatal herpes simplex virus infection in the British Isles. Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol. 1996;10(4):432-442. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3016.1996.tb00070.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Okike I, Ribeiro S, et al. Seven-fold increase in viral meningo-encephalitis reports in England and Wales during 2004-2013. J Infect. 2014;69(4):326-332. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2014.05.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs): Annual Data Tables. GOV.UK. Accessed February 23, 2021. https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/sexually-transmitted-infections-stis-annual-data-tables</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samies N. Evaluation of the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of valacyclovir in neonates with neonatal herpes simplex virus disease who have completed standard of care treatment with acyclovir. clinicaltrials.gov. 2020. Accessed December 21, 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04448392</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimberlin DW, Baley J, Brady MT, et al. Guidance on management of asymptomatic neonates born to women with active genital herpes lesions. Pediatrics. 2013;131(2):e635-e646. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2012-3216</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BASHH Guidelines. Accessed January 16, 2021. https://www.bashhguidelines.org/current-guidelines/genital-ulceration/anogenital-herpes-2014/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Smith KP. Safety of alternative antiviral agents for neonatal herpes simplex virus encephalitis and disseminated infection. J Pediatr Pharmacol Therapeut. 2014;19(2):72-82. https://doi.org/10.5863/1551-6776-19.2.72</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Haddad D, El Chaer F, Vanichanan J, et al. Brincidofovir (CMX-001) for refractory and resistant CMV and HSV infections in immunocompromised cancer patients: a single-center experience. Antivir Res. 2016;134:58-62. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2016.08.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voigt S, Hofmann J, Edelmann A, Sauerbrei A, Kuhl JS. Brincidofovir clearance of acyclovir-resistant herpes simplex virus-1 and adenovirus infection after stem cell transplantation. Transpl Infect Dis. 2016;18(5):791-794. https://doi.org/10.1111/tid.12582</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee YJ, Neofytos D, Kim SJ, et al. Efficacy of brincidofovir as prophylaxis against HSV and VZV in hematopoietic cell transplant recipients. Transpl Infect Dis. 2018;20(6):e12977. https://doi.org/10.1111/tid.12977</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majewska A, Mlynarczyk-Bonikowska B. 40 Years after the registration of acyclovir: do we need new anti-herpetic drugs? Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23(7):3431. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms23073431</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu X, Zhang Y, Li Q. Characteristics of herpes simplex virus infection and pathogenesis suggest a strategy for vaccine development. Rev Med Virol. 2019;29(4):e2054. https://doi.org/10.1002/rmv.2054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belshe RB, Leone PA, Bernstein DI, et al. Efficacy results of a trial of a herpes simplex vaccine. N Engl J Med. 2012;366(1):34-43. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1103151</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim HC, Oh DS, Park JH, et al. Multivalent DNA vaccine protects against genital herpes by T-cell immune induction in vaginal mucosa. Antivir Res. 2020;177:104755. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104755</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu W, Zhou Y, Wang Z, et al. Evaluation of recombinant adenovirus vaccines based on glycoprotein D and truncated UL25 against herpes simplex virus type 2 in mice. Microbiol Immunol. 2017;61(5):176-184. https://doi.org/10.1111/1348-0421.12482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanfield BA, Pahar B, Chouljenko VN, Veazey R, Kousoulas KG. Vaccination of rhesus macaques with the live-attenuated HSV-1 vaccine VC2 stimulates the proliferation of mucosal T cells and germinal center responses resulting in sustained production of highly neutralizing antibodies. Vaccine. 2017;35(4):536-543. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.12.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernstein DI, Pullum DA, Cardin RD, Bravo FJ, Dixon DA, Kousoulas KG. The HSV-1 live attenuated VC2 vaccine provides protection against HSV-2 genital infection in the guinea pig model of genital herpes. Vaccine. 2019;37(1):61-68. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2018.11.042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>An HSV-2 trivalent vaccine is immunogenic in rhesus macaques and highly efficacious in Guinea pigs. Accessed November 18, 2020. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5245903/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoyanova A, Nikolova I, Pürstinger G, et al. Anti-enteroviral triple combination of viral replication inhibitors: activity against coxsackievirus B1 neuroinfection in mice. Antivir Chem Chemother. 2015;24(5-6):136-147. https://doi.org/10.1177/2040206616671571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The promise of mRNA vaccines: a biotech and industrial perspective | npj Vaccines. Accessed June 24, 2022. https://www.nature.com/articles/s41541-020-0159-8</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>