<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">36723071</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2165-0497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Feb</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbiology spectrum</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microbiol Spectr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Respiratory Virus Infections during the COVID-19 Pandemic Revealed by Multiplex PCR Testing in Japan.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0416222</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0416222</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e04162-22</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/spectrum.04162-22</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Under the strict quarantine policy imposed to combat the COVID-19 (coronavirus disease 2019) pandemic in Japan, the prevalence of respiratory infections by viruses other than SARS-CoV-2 (severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2) has been largely unknown. However, such information on viral circulation is important in order to develop better management policies that are based on scientific data. Here, we retrospectively investigated respiratory virus infections in individuals who visited a community hospital with respiratory symptoms between June of 2020 and September of 2021 with the use of the BioFire FilmArray Respiratory Panel 2.1. Virus was detected in 65 out of a total of 328 subjects, with SARS-CoV-2 (67.7%), rhino/enterovirus (18.5%), and parainfluenza virus 3 (7.7%) accounting for most of the infections. No influenza virus or respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) infections were detected. The monthly cases of rhino/enterovirus infection were highest from winter to spring, with this temporal pattern differing from that of SARS-CoV-2. SARS-CoV-2 was detected more frequently (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001) in subjects with cough (31/104 cases, 29.8%) than in those without cough (13/224 cases, 5.8%), suggesting that cough might contribute to the prediction of COVID-19. Our findings also suggest that testing for rhino/enterovirus and parainfluenza virus 3, in addition to SARS-CoV-2, may be important for the rigorous diagnosis of respiratory virus infections. <b>IMPORTANCE</b> Influenza virus, RSV, adenovirus, and rhino/enterovirus were the major respiratory viruses before COVID-19 pandemic. Circulating respiratory viruses may have been affected by our strong quarantine policy during the COVID-19 pandemic. We checked the circulating respiratory viruses from our outpatients by using a multiplex PCR kit that had recently been released. SARS-CoV-2 was the most frequently detected virus, and it was followed by rhino/enterovirus and parainfluenza virus 3. No influenza virus or RSV infections were detected during our study period, suggesting that influenza virus and RSV became almost extinct. COVID-19 cases frequently experienced cough, and this frequency was statistically significantly higher than that observed in the cases without SARS-CoV-2 detection. The cough can be an indicator of COVID-19.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yamashita</LastName><ForeName>Sho</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Kyushu University, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ikegame</LastName><ForeName>Satoshi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8183-3527</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Kyushu University, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nakatomi</LastName><ForeName>Keita</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sakurai</LastName><ForeName>Yuko</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shuto</LastName><ForeName>Hiroe</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sato</LastName><ForeName>Noriko</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mizoguchi</LastName><ForeName>Yoshihiro</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Uehara</LastName><ForeName>Maki</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Kyushu University, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nakashima</LastName><ForeName>Nobutaka</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okamoto</LastName><ForeName>Isamu</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Kyushu University, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koto</LastName><ForeName>Hiroshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kyushu Central Hospital of the Mutual Aid Association of Public School Teachers, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Microbiol Spectr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101634614</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2165-0497</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FilmArray</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiplex PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory virus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36723071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10100992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.04162-22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zhou P, Yang X-L, Wang X-G, Hu B, Zhang L, Zhang W, Si H-R, Zhu Y, Li B, Huang C-L, Chen H-D, Chen J, Luo Y, Guo H, Jiang R-D, Liu M-Q, Chen Y, Shen X-R, Wang X, Zheng X-S, Zhao K, Chen Q-J, Deng F, Liu L-L, Yan B, Zhan F-X, Wang Y-Y, Xiao G-F, Shi Z-L. 2020. A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin. Nature 579:270–273. doi:10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu N, Zhang D, Wang W, Li X, Yang B, Song J, Zhao X, Huang B, Shi W, Lu R, Niu P, Zhan F, Ma X, Wang D, Xu W, Wu G, Gao GF, Tan W. China Novel Coronavirus Investigating and Research Team. 2020. A novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019. N Engl J Med 382:727–733. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa2001017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2001017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31978945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CC, Prather KA, Sznitman J, Jimenez JL, Lakdawala SS, Tufekci Z, Marr LC. 2021. Airborne transmission of respiratory viruses. Science 373. doi:10.1126/science.abd9149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abd9149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8721651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34446582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polack FP, Thomas SJ, Kitchin N, Absalon J, Gurtman A, Lockhart S, Perez JL, Pérez Marc G, Moreira ED, Zerbini C, Bailey R, Swanson KA, Roychoudhury S, Koury K, Li P, Kalina WV, Cooper D, Frenck RW, Hammitt LL, Türeci Ö, Nell H, Schaefer A, Ünal S, Tresnan DB, Mather S, Dormitzer PR, Şahin U, Jansen KU, Gruber WC. 2020. Safety and efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 vaccine. N Engl J Med 383:2603–2615. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa2034577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2034577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7745181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uriu K, Kimura I, Shirakawa K, Takaori-Kondo A, Nakada T-A, Kaneda A, Nakagawa S, Sato K. Genotype to Phenotype Japan (G2P-Japan) Consortium. 2021. Neutralization of the SARS-CoV-2 mu variant by convalescent and vaccine serum. N Engl J Med 385:2397–2399. doi:10.1056/NEJMc2114706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2114706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8609602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34731554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamasoba D, Kimura I, Nasser H, Morioka Y, Nao N, Ito J, Uriu K, Tsuda M, Zahradnik J, Shirakawa K, Suzuki R, Kishimoto M, Kosugi Y, Kobiyama K, Hara T, Toyoda M, Tanaka YL, Butlertanaka EP, Shimizu R, Ito H, Wang L, Oda Y, Orba Y, Sasaki M, Nagata K, Yoshimatsu K, Asakura H, Nagashima M, Sadamasu K, Yoshimura K, Kuramochi J, Seki M, Fujiki R, Kaneda A, Shimada T, Nakada T-A, Sakao S, Suzuki T, Ueno T, Takaori-Kondo A, Ishii KJ, Schreiber G, Sawa H, Saito A, Irie T, Tanaka S, Matsuno K, Fukuhara T, Ikeda T, Sato K. Genotype to Phenotype Japan (G2P-Japan) Consortium., et al. 2022. Virological characteristics of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA.2 spike. Cell 185:2103–2115.e19. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2022.04.035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2022.04.035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9057982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35568035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eckbo EJ, Locher K, Caza M, Li L, Lavergne V, Charles M. 2021. Evaluation of the BioFire COVID-19 test and Respiratory Panel 2.1 for rapid identification of SARS-CoV-2 in nasopharyngeal swab samples. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis 99:115260. doi:10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2020.115260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2020.115260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7654322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33340934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berry GJ, Zhen W, Smith E, Manji R, Silbert S, Lima A, Harington A, McKinley K, Kensinger B, Neff C, Lu D. 2022. Multicenter evaluation of the BioFire Respiratory Panel 2.1 (RP2.1) for detection of SARS-CoV-2 in nasopharyngeal swab samples. J Clin Microbiol 60. doi:10.1128/jcm.00066-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.00066-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9116161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35387475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies NG, Abbott S, Barnard RC, Jarvis CI, Kucharski AJ, Munday JD, Pearson CAB, Russell TW, Tully DC, Washburne AD, Wenseleers T, Gimma A, Waites W, Wong KLM, van Zandvoort K, Silverman JD, Diaz-Ordaz K, Keogh R, Eggo RM, Funk S, Jit M, Atkins KE, Edmunds WJ. CMMID COVID-19 Working Group. 2021. Estimated transmissibility and impact of SARS-CoV-2 lineage B.1.1.7 in England. Science 372. doi:10.1126/science.abg3055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abg3055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8128288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33658326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherian S, et al.. 2021. In the second wave of COVID-19 in Maharashtra, India. Microorganism 2:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8307577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34361977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leber AL, Everhart K, Daly JA, Hopper A, Harrington A, Schreckenberger P, McKinley K, Jones M, Holmberg K, Kensinger B. 2018. Multicenter evaluation of BioFire FilmArray respiratory panel 2 for detection of viruses and bacteria in nasopharyngeal swab samples. J Clin Microbiol 56. doi:10.1128/JCM.01945-17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.01945-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5971546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29593057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visseaux B, Collin G, Ichou H, Charpentier C, Bendhafer S, Dumitrescu M, Allal L, Cojocaru B, Desfrère L, Descamps D, Mandelbrot L, Houhou-Fidouh N. 2017. Usefulness of multiplex PCR methods and respiratory viruses’ distribution in children below 15 years old according to age, seasons and clinical units in France: a 3 years retrospective study. PLoS One 12:e0172809. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0172809.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0172809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5325537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28235002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsagarakis NJ, et al.. 2018. Age-related prevalence of common upper respiratory pathogens, based on the application of the FilmArray Respiratory panel in a tertiary hospital in Greece. Med (United States) 97:4–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6392546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29851817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hakim AJ, Victory KR, Chevinsky JR, Hast MA, Weikum D, Kazazian L, Mirza S, Bhatkoti R, Schmitz MM, Lynch M, Marston BJ. 2021. Mitigation policies, community mobility, and COVID-19 case counts in Australia, Japan, Hong Kong, and Singapore. Public Health 194:238–244. doi:10.1016/j.puhe.2021.02.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2021.02.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7879096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33965795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minosse C, Selleri M, Zaniratti MS, Cappiello G, Longo R, Schifano E, Spanò A, Petrosillo N, Lauria FN, Puro V, Capobianchi MR. 2008. Frequency of detection of respiratory viruses in the lower respiratory tract of hospitalized adults. J Clin Virol 42:215–220. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2008.01.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2008.01.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18343193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monto AS, Malosh RE, Petrie JG, Thompson MG, Ohmit SE. 2014. Frequency of acute respiratory illnesses and circulation of respiratory viruses in households with children over 3 surveillance seasons. J Infect Dis 210:1792–1799. doi:10.1093/infdis/jiu327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiu327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4296188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24907381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He X, Lau EHY, Wu P, Deng X, Wang J, Hao X, Lau YC, Wong JY, Guan Y, Tan X, Mo X, Chen Y, Liao B, Chen W, Hu F, Zhang Q, Zhong M, Wu Y, Zhao L, Zhang F, Cowling BJ, Li F, Leung GM. 2020. Temporal dynamics in viral shedding and transmissibility of COVID-19. Nat Med 26:672–675. doi:10.1038/s41591-020-0869-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-0869-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32296168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirotsu Y, Maejima M, Shibusawa M, Amemiya K, Nagakubo Y, Hosaka K, Sueki H, Mochizuki H, Tsutsui T, Kakizaki Y, Miyashita Y, Omata M. 2020. Analysis of Covid-19 and non-Covid-19 viruses, including influenza viruses, to determine the influence of intensive preventive measures in Japan. J Clin Virol 129:104543. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2020.104543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2020.104543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7340051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32663787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kan-O K, Washio Y, Fujimoto T, Shiroyama N, Nakano T, Wakamatsu K, Takata S, Yoshida M, Fujita M, Matsumoto K. 2022. Differences in the spectrum of respiratory viruses and detection of human rhinovirus C in exacerbations of adult asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Respir Invest 60:129–136. doi:10.1016/j.resinv.2021.08.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resinv.2021.08.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34580039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Bi-weekly Influenza Situation Update. Aug 10 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Killingley B, Mann AJ, Kalinova M, Boyers A, Goonawardane N, Zhou J, Lindsell K, Hare SS, Brown J, Frise R, Smith E, Hopkins C, Noulin N, Löndt B, Wilkinson T, Harden S, McShane H, Baillet M, Gilbert A, Jacobs M, Charman C, Mande P, Nguyen-Van-Tam JS, Semple MG, Read RC, Ferguson NM, Openshaw PJ, Rapeport G, Barclay WS, Catchpole AP, Chiu C. 2022. Safety, tolerability and viral kinetics during SARS-CoV-2 human challenge in young adults. Nat Med 28:1031–1041. doi:10.1038/s41591-022-01780-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01780-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35361992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishii T, Kushimoto S, Katori Y, Kure S, Igarashi K, Fujita M, Takayama S, Abe M, Tanaka J, Kikuchi A, Abe Y, Imai H, Inaba Y, Iwamatsu-Kobayashi Y, Nishioka T, Onodera K, Akaishi T. 2021. Predictors of SARS-CoV-2 positivity based on RT-PCR swab tests at a drive-through outpatient clinic for COVID-19 screening in Japan. Tohoku J Exp Med 253:101–108. doi:10.1620/tjem.253.101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1620/tjem.253.101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33536379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elliott J, Whitaker M, Bodinier B, Eales O, Riley S, Ward H, Cooke G, Darzi A, Chadeau-Hyam M, Elliott P. 2021. Predictive symptoms for COVID-19 in the community: REACT-1 study of over 1 million people. PLoS Med 18:e1003777. doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.1003777.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8478234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34582457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>