<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36876331</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1531-698X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>35</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current opinion in pediatrics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Opin Pediatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Update on nonpolio enterovirus and parechovirus infections in neonates and young infants.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>380</StartPage><EndPage>389</EndPage><MedlinePgn>380-389</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MOP.0000000000001236</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE OF REVIEW">To review the epidemiology, clinical manifestations, and treatment strategies of nonpolio enterovirus and parechovirus (PeV) infections, and identify research gaps.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RECENT FINDINGS">There is currently no approved antiviral agent for enterovirus or PeV infections, although pocapavir may be provided on a compassionate basis. Elucidation of the structure and functional features of enterovirus and PeV may lead to novel therapeutic strategies, including vaccine development.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUMMARY">Nonpolio human enterovirus and PeV are common childhood infections that are most severe among neonates and young infants. Although most infections are asymptomatic, severe disease resulting in substantial morbidity and mortality occurs worldwide and has been associated with local outbreaks. Long-term sequelae are not well understood but have been reported following neonatal infection of the central nervous system. The lack of antiviral treatment and effective vaccines highlight important knowledge gaps. Active surveillance ultimately may inform preventive strategies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tomatis Souverbielle</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Section of Infectious Diseases.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Erdem</LastName><ForeName>Guliz</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Section of Infectious Diseases.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sánchez</LastName><ForeName>Pablo J</ForeName><Initials>PJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Section of Infectious Diseases.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Neonatology, Department of Pediatrics, Nationwide Children's Hospital, Abigail Wexner Research Institute at Nationwide Children's Hospital, Center for Perinatal Research, The Ohio State University College of Medicine, Columbus, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Opin Pediatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9000850</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1040-8703</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000998">Antiviral Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030061" MajorTopicYN="Y">Parechovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000998" MajorTopicYN="N">Antiviral Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010850" MajorTopicYN="Y">Picornaviridae Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36876331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MOP.0000000000001236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00008480-202306000-00014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Harik N, DeBiasi RL. Neonatal nonpolio enterovirus and parechovirus infections. Semin Perinatol 2018; 42:191–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huan C, Qu X, Li Z. Host restrictive factors are the emerging storm troopers against enterovirus: a mini-review. Front Immunol 2022; 13:910780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jubelt B, Lipton HL. Enterovirus/picornavirus infections. Handb Clin Neurol 2014; 123:379–416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Link-Gelles R, Lutterloh E, Schnabel Ruppert P, et al. 2022 U.S. Poliovirus Response Team. Public health response to a case of paralytic poliomyelitis in an unvaccinated person and detection of poliovirus in wastewater - New York, June-August 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:1065–1068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, Moreni G, Wolthers KC, Pajkrt D. World-wide prevalence and genotype distribution of enteroviruses. Viruses 2021; 13:434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Infectious Diseases, Kimberlin DW, Barnett ED et al. Enterovirus (Nonpoliovirus) (Group A and B Coxsackieviruses, Echoviruses, Numbered Enteroviruses), in Red Book: 2021–2024 Report of the Committee on Infectious Diseases. 2021, American Academy of Pediatrics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domanska A, Guryanov S, Butcher SJ. A comparative analysis of parechovirus protein structures with other picornaviruses. Open Biol 2021; 11:210008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baggen J, Thibaut HJ, Strating J, van Kuppeveld FJM. The life cycle of nonpolio enteroviruses and how to target it. Nat Rev Microbiol 2018; 16:368–381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobayashi K, Koike S. Adaptation and virulence of enterovirus-A71. Viruses 2021; 13:1661.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triantafilou K, Triantafilou M, Takada Y, Fernandez N. Human parechovirus 1 utilizes integrins alphavbeta3 and alphavbeta1 as receptors. J Virol 2000; 74:5856–5862.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karelehto E, Cristella C, Yu X, et al. Polarized entry of human parechoviruses in the airway epithelium. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 2018; 8:294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pettersen EF, Goddard TD, Huang CC, et al. UCSF Chimera--a visualization system for exploratory research and analysis. J Comput Chem 2004; 25:1605–1612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abedi GR, Watson JT, Nix WA, et al. Enterovirus and parechovirus surveillance - United States, 2014-2016. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2018; 67:515–518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomatis Souverbielle C, Wang H, Feister J, et al. Year-round, routine testing of multiple body site specimens for human parechovirus in young febrile infants. J Pediatr 2021; 229:216.e2-222.e2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aizawa Y, Kasamatsu T, Nagasawa K, et al. Molecular evolution and epidemiology of parechovirus-A3 in Japan, 1997-2019. J Infect Dis 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer TK, Simmonds P, Harvala H. The importance of enterovirus surveillance in a postpolio world. Lancet Infect Dis 2022; 22:e35–e40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamings A, Druce J, Caly L, et al. Evolutionary analysis of human parechovirus type 3 and clinical outcomes of infection during the 2017-18 Australian epidemic. Sci Rep 2019; 9:8906.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sridhar A, Karelehto E, Brouwer L, et al. Parechovirus A pathogenesis and the enigma of genotype A-3. Viruses 2019; 11:1062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bendig JW, Franklin OM, Hebden AK, et al. Coxsackievirus B3 sequences in the blood of a neonate with congenital myocarditis, plus serological evidence of maternal infection. J Med Virol 2003; 70:606–609.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chambon M, Bailly JL, Beguet A, et al. An outbreak due to echovirus type 30 in a neonatal unit in France in 1997: usefulness of PCR diagnosis. J Hosp Infect 1999; 43:63–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang ML, Tsao KC, Huang CC, et al. Coxsackievirus B3 in human milk. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2006; 25:955–957.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang FL, Chen CH, Huang SK, Chen PY. An outbreak of enterovirus 71 in a nursery. Scand J Infect Dis 2010; 42:609–612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson I, Hammond GW, Verma MR. Nosocomial coxsackie B4 virus infections in two chronic-care pediatric neurological wards. J Infect Dis 1985; 151:1153–1156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konstantinidou A, Anninos H, Spanakis N, et al. Transplacental infection of Coxsackievirus B3 pathological findings in the fetus. J Med Virol 2007; 79:754–757.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maus MV, Posencheg MA, Geddes K, et al. Detection of echovirus 18 in human breast milk. J Clin Microbiol 2008; 46:1137–1140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strenger V, Diedrich S, Boettcher S, et al. Nosocomial outbreak of parechovirus 3 infection among newborns Austria, 2014. Emerg Infect Dis 2016; 22:1631–1634.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takami T, Kawashima H, Takei Y, et al. Usefulness of nested PCR and sequence analysis in a nosocomial outbreak of neonatal enterovirus infection. J Clin Virol 1998; 11:67–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tassin M, Martinovic J, Mirand A, et al. A case of congenital Echovirus 11 infection acquired early in pregnancy. J Clin Virol 2014; 59:71–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang LC, Tsai HP, Chen SH, Wang SM. Therapeutics for fulminant hepatitis caused by enteroviruses in neonates. Front Pharmacol 2022; 13:1014823.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brownell AD, Reynolds TQ, Livingston B, McCarthy CA. Human parechovirus-3 encephalitis in two neonates: acute and follow-up magnetic resonance imaging and evaluation of central nervous system markers of inflammation. Pediatr Neurol 2015; 52:245–249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Wang H, Tang J, et al. Clinical characteristics of severe neonatal enterovirus infection: a systematic review. BMC Pediatr 2021; 21:127.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Levin MJ, Rotbart HA. Profile of enterovirus disease in the first two weeks of life. Pediatr Infect Dis J 1993; 12:820–824.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verboon-Maciolek MA, Krediet TG, Gerards LJ, et al. Clinical and epidemiologic characteristics of viral infections in a neonatal intensive care unit during a 12-year period. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2005; 24:901–904.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis J, Fairley D, Christie S, et al. Human parechovirus infection in neonatal intensive care. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2015; 34:121–124.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez PJ, Woods RA, Wang H, et al. Detection of parechovirus and enterovirus among infants evaluated for late-onset sepsis in the neonatal intensive care unit: the viral respiratory infections in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit-Parechovirus-Enterovirus Study. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2022; 41:1017–1019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang YY, Huang YC. Enteroviral infection in neonates. J Microbiol Immunol Infect 2019; 52:851–857.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Hinsbergh T, Elbers RG, Bouman Z, et al. Neurodevelopmental outcomes of newborns and infants with parechovirus and enterovirus central nervous infection: a 5-year longitudinal study. Eur J Pediatr 2022; 181:2005–2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Ceano-Vivas M, Garcia ML, Velazquez A, et al. Neurodevelopmental outcomes of infants younger than 90 days old following enterovirus and parechovirus infections of the central nervous system. Front Pediatr 2021; 9:719119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Diaz A, Moyer K, et al. Molecular and clinical comparison of enterovirus D68 outbreaks among hospitalized children, Ohio, USA, 2014 and 2018. Emerg Infect Dis 2019; 25:2055–2063.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez G, Carr MJ, Kobayashi M, et al. Enterovirus-associated hand-foot and mouth disease and neurological complications in Japan and the rest of the world. Int J Mol Sci 2019; 20:5201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikonov OS, Chernykh ES, Garber MB, Nikonova EY. Enteroviruses: classification, diseases they cause, and approaches to development of antiviral drugs. Biochemistry (Mosc) 2017; 82:1615–1631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lafolie J, Labbe A, L’Honneur AS, et al. Blood Enterovirus Diagnosis Infection (BLEDI) in paediatric population study team. Assessment of blood enterovirus PCR testing in paediatric populations with fever without source, sepsis-like disease, or suspected meningitis: a prospective, multicentre, observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis 2018; 18:1385–1396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Dominguez SR. Blood PCR testing for enteroviruses in young children. Lancet Infect Dis 2018; 18:1299–1301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomatis Souverbielle C, Feister J, Leber A, et al. Multiple sites PCR testing for enteroviruses in young febrile infants. Lancet Infect Dis 2019; 19:239–240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leber AL, Everhart K, Balada-Llasat JM, et al. Multicenter evaluation of BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel for detection of bacteria, viruses, and yeast in cerebrospinal fluid specimens. J Clin Microbiol 2016; 54:2251–2261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Keyserling HL, Lee ML, et al. Neonatal enterovirus infection: virology, serology, and effects of intravenous immune globulin. Clin Infect Dis 1995; 20:1201–1206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Cloud G, Bradley J, et al. National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Collaborative Antiviral Study Group. Double blind placebo-controlled trial of pleconaril in infants with enterovirus meningitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2003; 22:335–341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotbart HA, Webster AD. Pleconaril Treatment Registry Group. Treatment of potentially life-threatening enterovirus infections with pleconaril. Clin Infect Dis 2001; 32:228–235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Michaels MG, Wald E, et al. National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Collaborative Antiviral Study Group. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of pleconaril for the treatment of neonates with enterovirus sepsis. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc 2016; 5:53–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamayoshi S, Yamashita Y, Li J, et al. Scavenger receptor B2 is a cellular receptor for enterovirus 71. Nat Med 2009; 15:798–801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakata K, Takeda S, Tanaka A, et al. Antiviral activity of acid beta-glucosidase 1 on enterovirus 71, a causative agent of hand, foot and mouth disease. J Gen Virol 2017; 98:643–651.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang Y, Liu Z, Qiu Y, et al. Inhibition of viral suppressor of RNAi proteins by designer peptides protects from enteroviral infection in vivo. Immunity 2021; 54:2231.e6–2244.e6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galabov AS, Nikolova I, Vassileva-Pencheva R, Stoyanova A. Antiviral combination approach as a perspective to combat enterovirus infections. Pril (Makedon Akad Nauk Umet Odd Med Nauki) 2015; 36:91–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Y, Abdelnabi R, Delang L, et al. New class of early-stage enterovirus inhibitors with a novel mechanism of action. Antiviral Res 2017; 147:67–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu M, Li X, Song L, et al. Lupeol alleviates coxsackievirus B3-induced viral myocarditis in mice via downregulating toll-like receptor 4. J Int Med Res 2020; 48:300060520910908.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jan MW, Su HL, Chang TH, Tsai KJ. Characterization of pathogenesis and inflammatory responses to experimental parechovirus encephalitis. Front Immunol 2021; 12:753683.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Li Y, Yang Z, et al. Effect of enterovirus 71 vaccination on the epidemiological characteristics and etiology in hospitalized children with hand-foot-and-mouth disease: a retrospective study from a tertiary children's hospital. Medicine (Baltimore) 2022; 101:e30356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shih SR, Huang CG, Weng YJ, et al. Efficacy, safety, and immunogenicity of an inactivated, adjuvanted enterovirus 71 vaccine in infants and children: a multiregion, double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet 2022; 399:1708–1717.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devi S. US CDC task force to investigate acute flaccid myelitis cases. Lancet 2018; 392:2339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao L, Fill MA, Banerjee R, Humphries RM. Notes from the field: cluster of parechovirus central nervous system infections in young infants - Tennessee. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:977–978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Hinsbergh TMT, Elbers RG, Hans Ket JCF, et al. Neurological and neurodevelopmental outcomes after human parechovirus CNS infection in neonates and young children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Child Adolesc Health 2020; 4:592–605.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>