<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedBookArticle><BookDocument><PMID Version="1">30000841</PMID><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="bookaccession">NBK501782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><Book><Publisher><PublisherName>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</PublisherName><PublisherLocation>Bethesda (MD)</PublisherLocation></Publisher><BookTitle book="lactmed">Drugs and Lactation Database (LactMed&#xae;)</BookTitle><PubDate><Year>2006</Year></PubDate><BeginningDate><Year>2006</Year></BeginningDate><Medium>Internet</Medium></Book><ArticleTitle book="lactmed" part="LM873">Garlic</ArticleTitle><Language>eng</Language><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><Abstract><AbstractText>Garlic (<i>Allium sativum</i>) contains alliin, which is metabolized by the enzyme alliinase to allicin, thought to be responsible for most of garlic's medicinal properties and odor. Garlic&#x2019;s odor in milk is attributed to allyl methyl sulfide.[1] Garlic has been used to lower cholesterol and blood pressure. It has no specific indications for use during lactation in western countries. Garlic has been used as a galactogogue in India and T&#xfc;rkiye,[2-5] although no good scientific data could be located on its use alone as a galactogogue. Galactogogues should never replace evaluation and counseling on modifiable factors that affect milk production.[6,7] Garlic has a long history of use as a food and medicine and is "generally recognized as safe" (GRAS) as a food flavoring by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration, including during lactation.[8] Garlic's odor is transmitted to breastmilk, which may increase infant sucking time acutely and might enhance the breastfed infant's food choices in the long term. Some mothers in T&#xfc;rkiye reportedly use garlic to improve the taste and quality of their milk.[4] Limited scientific data found that a few days of oral garlic supplementation caused no adverse effects in nursing mothers or infants. When used as a medicinal, garlic is generally well tolerated in adults, but gastrointestinal side effects and bad breath and body odor may occur. Garlic has anti-platelet effects and should be used cautiously by women at risk for bleeding. Garlic can cause allergies and should be avoided by persons allergic to garlic or other members of the lily family, such as hyacinth, tulip, onion, leek, and chives. Topical application of garlic can cause dermatitis and burns and should be used with caution, especially in infants. One nursing mother received severe burns to the breast from prolonged (2 days) application of a poultice of raw, crushed garlic to treat a self-diagnosed Candida infection.[9] Dietary supplements do not require extensive pre-marketing approval from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Manufacturers are responsible to ensure the safety, but do not need to <i>prove</i> the safety and effectiveness of dietary supplements before they are marketed. Dietary supplements may contain multiple ingredients, and differences are often found between labeled and actual ingredients or their amounts. A manufacturer may contract with an independent organization to verify the quality of a product or its ingredients, but that does <i>not</i> certify the safety or effectiveness of a product. Because of the above issues, clinical testing results on one product may not be applicable to other products. More detailed information about dietary supplements is available elsewhere on the LactMed Web site.</AbstractText></Abstract><Sections><Section><SectionTitle book="lactmed" part="LM873" sec="LM873.Drug_Levels_and_Effects">Drug Levels and Effects</SectionTitle></Section><Section><SectionTitle book="lactmed" part="LM873" sec="LM873.Substance_Identification">Substance Identification</SectionTitle></Section></Sections><KeywordList Owner="NLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Garlic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Garlic extract</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Garlic powder</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Extract of garlic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Garlic, ext.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Allium sativum extract</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Garlic and its derivatives</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CCRIS 7640</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EINECS 232-371-1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Allium sativum L. (Lillaceae), extract</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">8008-99-9</Keyword></KeywordList><ContributionDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></ContributionDate><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Qin W, Huber K, Popp M, et al. Quantification of allyl methyl sulfide, allyl methyl sulfoxide, and allyl methyl sulfone in human milk and urine after ingestion of cooked and roasted garlic. Front Nutr 2020;7:565496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7531236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33072797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sayed NZ, Deo R, Mukundan U. Herbal remedies used by Warlis of Dahanu to induce lactation in nursing mothers.
Indian J Tradit Knowl
2007;6:602-5. https://nopr.niscpr.res.in/handle/123456789/1009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amuthavalluvan V, Devarapalli J. Indigenous knowledge and health seeking behavior among Kattunayakan: A tribe in transition.
Glob J Human Soc Sci
2011;11:19-23. http://socialscienceresearch.org/index.php/GJHSS/article/view/198/161</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaygusuz M, G&#xfc;m&#xfc;&#x15f;tak&#x131;m R&#x15e;, Ku&#x15f; C, et al. TCM use in pregnant women and nursing mothers: A study from Turkey. Complement Ther Clin Pract 2021;42:101300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33412511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahalakshmi B, Patani J, Ekambaram G, et al. Effect of Allium sativum consumption for breast feeding among postnatal Indian mothers. Bioinformation 2023;19:698-702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10598363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37885786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodribb W. ABM Clinical Protocol #9: Use of galactogogues in initiating or augmenting maternal milk production, second revision 2018. Breastfeed Med 2018;13:307-14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29902083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breastfeeding challenges: ACOG Committee Opinion, Number 820. Obstet Gynecol 2021;137:e42-e53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33481531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Hara M, Kiefer D, Farrell K, et al. A review of 12 commonly used medicinal herbs. Arch Fam Med 1998;7:523-36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9821826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberge RJ, Leckey R, Spence R, et al. Garlic burns of the breast. Am J Emerg Med 1997;15:548.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9270405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mennella JA, Beauchamp GK. Maternal diet alters the sensory qualities of human milk and the nursling's behavior. Pediatrics 1991;88:737-44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1896276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheffler L, Sauermann Y, Zeh G, et al. Detection of volatile metabolites of garlic in human breast milk. Metabolites 2016;6:E18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4931549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27275838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheffler L, Sharapa C, Buettner A. Quantification of volatile metabolites derived from garlic in human breast milk. Food Chem 2019;274:603-10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30372984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lust KD, Brown JE, Thomas W. Maternal intake of cruciferous vegetables and other foods and colic symptoms in exclusively breast-fed infants. J Am Diet Assoc 1996;96:46-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8537569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mennella JA, Beauchamp GK. The effects of repeated exposure to garlic-flavored milk on the nursling's behavior. Pediatr Res 1993;34:805-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8108198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sholapurkar ML. 'Lactare' for improving lactation. Indian Pract 1986;39:1023-6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beauchamp GK, Mennella JA. Early flavor learning and its impact on later feeding behavior. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr 2009;48 (Suppl. 1):S25-30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19214055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></BookDocument><PubmedBookData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30000841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedBookData></PubmedBookArticle></PubmedArticleSet>