<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedBookArticle><BookDocument><PMID Version="1">30000966</PMID><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="bookaccession">NBK501906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><Book><Publisher><PublisherName>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</PublisherName><PublisherLocation>Bethesda (MD)</PublisherLocation></Publisher><BookTitle book="lactmed">Drugs and Lactation Database (LactMed&#xae;)</BookTitle><PubDate><Year>2006</Year></PubDate><BeginningDate><Year>2006</Year></BeginningDate><Medium>Internet</Medium></Book><ArticleTitle book="lactmed" part="LM985">Beta-Carotene</ArticleTitle><Language>eng</Language><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><Abstract><AbstractText>Beta-carotene is a plant pigment that is converted into vitamin A in the body. Maternal vitamin A requirements are increased during lactation, but there are no specific guidelines for increased beta-carotene intake or indications for high-dose supplementation in nursing mothers. Typical beta-carotene intake in a Western diet is 6 to 8 mg daily. Beta-carotene is a normal component of human colostrum and mature milk, where it contributes to antioxidant defenses in the neonate.[1] A systematic review found that in infants younger than 6 months, those fed primarily human milk have greater blood carotenoid concentrations than those fed formula.[2] Some evidence suggests that there is a correlation between beta-carotene and infant motor development in exclusively breastfed infants, but not in overall psychomotor performance.[3] Beta-carotene supplementation during pregnancy and for 6 months postpartum in nursing mothers with poor diets in a resource-poor setting reduced the number of days of illness in the mothers, but does not reduce infant morbidity or mortality according to another study.[4,5] The bioavailability of beta-carotene is dependent on the fat content of the meal and the form in which it is administered, with synthetic pharmaceutical forms having the best bioavailability. High-dose beta-carotene supplements lead to a slow increase in breastmilk beta-carotene concentrations, with an accumulation half-life of about 9 days. Levels drop towards baseline slowly over several weeks after discontinuation. In general, beta-carotene is well tolerated, although excessive maternal intake of beta-carotene can lead to a harmless, reversible discoloration of the breastfed infant's skin.[6] In HIV-infected women, high-dose beta-carotene plus vitamin A supplementation increases the rate of HIV viral shedding into breastmilk and increases HIV infection in breastfed infants, although the mortality rate over the first 2 years of life is not increased.[7,8] The viral shedding may be a result of an increase in subclinical mastitis caused by beta-carotene.[9] Beta-carotene concentration in breastmilk is not affected by refrigeration, freezing, or low-temperature microwaving. The concentration does decrease when milk passes through a tube feeding system, regardless of light exposure.[10] Dietary supplements do not require extensive pre-marketing approval from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Manufacturers are responsible to ensure the safety, but do not need to <i>prove</i> the safety and effectiveness of dietary supplements before they are marketed. Dietary supplements may contain multiple ingredients, and differences are often found between labeled and actual ingredients or their amounts. A manufacturer may contract with an independent organization to verify the quality of a product or its ingredients, but that does <i>not</i> certify the safety or effectiveness of a product. Because of the above issues, clinical testing results on one product may not be applicable to other products. More detailed information about dietary supplements is available elsewhere on the LactMed Web site.</AbstractText></Abstract><Sections><Section><SectionTitle book="lactmed" part="LM985" sec="LM985.Drug_Levels_and_Effects">Drug Levels and Effects</SectionTitle></Section><Section><SectionTitle book="lactmed" part="LM985" sec="LM985.Substance_Identification">Substance Identification</SectionTitle></Section></Sections><KeywordList Owner="NLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">beta-carotene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">beta Carotene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Provitamin A</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Betacarotene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">beta,beta-Carotene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Solatene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Carotaben</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Provatene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Serlabo</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Karotin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Betacaroteno</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Betacarotenum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lucaratin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">all-trans-beta-Carotene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Solatene (caps)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">BetaVit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Karotin [Czech]</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food orange 5</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Natural Yellow 26</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">KPMK</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Zlut prirodni 26</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">C.I. Food Orange 5</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Betacaroteno [Spanish]</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Zlut prirodni 26 [Czech]</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UNII-01YAE03M7J</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CCRIS 3245</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HSDB 3264</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">01YAE03M7J</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">E160A</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NSC 62794</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EINECS 230-636-6</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">C.I. 75130</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CI 40800</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CI 75130</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EC 230-636-6</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">1,3,3-trimethyl-2-[(1E,3E,5E,7E,9E,11E,13E,15E,17E)-3,7,12,16-tetramethyl-18-(2,6,6-trimethylcyclohexen-1-yl)octadeca-1,3,5,7,9,11,13,15,17-nonaenyl]cyclohexene</Keyword></KeywordList><ContributionDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></ContributionDate><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ostrea EM, Jr, Balun JE, Winkler R, et al. Influence of breast-feeding on the restoration of the low serum concentration of vitamin E and beta-carotene in the newborn infant. Am J Obstet Gynecol 1986;154:1014-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3706423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaidi Y, Stroh R, Moran NE. Systematic review of carotenoid concentrations in human milk and infant blood. Nutr Rev 2022; 80:2029-50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35389473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zielinska MA, Hamulka J, Grabowicz-Ch&#x105;drzy&#x144;ska I, et al. Association between breastmilk LC PUFA, carotenoids and psychomotor development of exclusively breastfed infants. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2019;16:1144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6479893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30935000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christian P, West KP, Jr, Khatry SK, et al. Vitamin A or beta-carotene supplementation reduces symptoms of illness in pregnant and lactating Nepali women. J Nutr 2000;130:2675-82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11053506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gogia S, Sachdev HS. Maternal postpartum vitamin A supplementation for the prevention of mortality and morbidity in infancy: A systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Int J Epidemiol 2010;39:1217-26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20522482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomson ML. Carotinaemia in a suckling. Arch Dis Child 1943;18:112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1987848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21032250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fawzi WW, Msamanga GI, Hunter D, et al. Randomized trial of vitamin supplements in relation to transmission of HIV-1 through breastfeeding and early child mortality. AIDS 2002;16:1935-44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12351954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villamor E, Koulinska IN, Aboud S, et al. Effect of vitamin supplements on HIV shedding in breast milk. Am J Clin Nutr 2010;92:881-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2937587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20739426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arsenault JE, Aboud S, Manji KP, et al. Vitamin supplementation increases risk of subclinical mastitis in HIV-infected women. J Nutr 2010;140:1788-92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2937574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20739447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tacken KJ, Vogelsang A, van Lingen RA, et al. Loss of triglycerides and carotenoids in human milk after processing. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed 2009;94:F447-50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19416803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canfield LM, Giuliano AR, Neilson EM, et al. Kinetics of the response of milk and serum beta-carotene to daily beta-carotene supplementation in healthy, lactating women. Am J Clin Nutr 1998;67:276-83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9459376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canfield LM, Giuliano AR, Neilson EM, et al. beta-Carotene in breast milk and serum is increased after a single beta-carotene dose. Am J Clin Nutr 1997;66:52-61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9209169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson EJ, Qin J, Krinsky NI, et al. Beta-carotene isomers in human serum, breast milk and buccal mucosa cells after continuous oral doses of all-trans and 9-cis beta-carotene. J Nutr 1997;127:1993-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9311956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gossage CP, Deyhim M, Yamini S, et al. Carotenoid composition of human milk during the first month postpartum and the response to beta-carotene supplementation. Am J Clin Nutr 2002;76:193-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12081834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dijkhuizen MA, Wieringa FT, West CE, et al. Zinc plus beta-carotene supplementation of pregnant women is superior to beta-carotene supplementation alone in improving vitamin A status in both mothers and infants. Am J Clin Nutr 2004;80:1299-307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15531679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rice AL, Stoltzfus RJ, de Francisco A, et al. Maternal vitamin A or beta-carotene supplementation in lactating Bangladeshi women benefits mothers and infants but does not prevent subclinical deficiency. J Nutr 1999;129:356-65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10024613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villamor E, Saathoff E, Bosch RJ, et al. Vitamin supplementation of HIV-infected women improves postnatal child growth. Am J Clin Nutr 2005;81:880-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15817867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webb AL, Aboud S, Furtado J, et al. Effect of vitamin supplementation on breast milk concentrations of retinol, carotenoids and tocopherols in HIV-infected Tanzanian women. Eur J Clin Nutr 2009;63:332-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3095494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17940544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haftel L, Berkovich Z, Reifen R. Elevated milk beta-carotene and lycopene after carrot and tomato paste supplementation. Nutrition 2015;31:443-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25701332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></BookDocument><PubmedBookData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30000966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedBookData></PubmedBookArticle></PubmedArticleSet>