<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39255380</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1708-8305</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of travel medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Travel Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>From bench to clinic: the development of VLA1553/IXCHIQ, a live-attenuated chikungunya vaccine.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">taae123</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/jtm/taae123</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Over the past 20 years, over 5 million cases of chikungunya, a mosquito-transmitted viral disease, have been reported in over 110 countries. Until recently, preventative strategies for chikungunya were largely ineffective, relying on vector control and individual avoidance of mosquito bites.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This review outlines the preclinical and clinical efficacy and safety data that led to the approval of VLA1553 (IXCHIQ&#xae;), a live-attenuated vaccine against chikungunya disease. It also describes the innovative development pathway of VLA1553, based on an immunological surrogate of protection, and discusses ongoing and future post-licensure studies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In mice and non-human primate models, VLA1553 elicited high titres of neutralizing antibodies, conferred protection against wild-type chikungunya virus challenge and raised no safety concerns. A Phase 1 clinical trial of VLA1553 demonstrated 100% seroconversion among 120 healthy participants, with sustained neutralizing antibody titres after 12 months. These results and determination of a surrogate marker of protection led to advancement of VLA1553 directly into Phase 3 clinical development, as agreed with the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the European Medicines Agency. The pivotal Phase 3 trial met its primary immunogenicity endpoint, achieving seroprotective levels based on immuno-bridging in baseline seronegative participants 28 days post-vaccination. These findings enabled submission of a Biologics License Application to the FDA for accelerated approval of VLA1553 in the US for adults aged &#x2265;18 years. Ongoing and planned studies will confirm the clinical efficacy/effectiveness and safety of VLA1553 in adults and younger individuals, and will generate data in chikungunya endemic countries that have the highest unmet need.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">VLA1553 is the first vaccine approved for the prevention of chikungunya disease in adults, following accelerated development based on a serological surrogate marker of protection. VLA1553 adds to strategies to reduce the spread and burden of chikungunya in endemic populations and travellers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; International Society of Travel Medicine 2024. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Lin H</ForeName><Initials>LH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases and Travel Medicine, Mount Auburn Hospital, Cambridge, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fritzer</LastName><ForeName>Andrea</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pre-Clinical Vaccine Development Department, Valneva Austria GmbH, Vienna, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hochreiter</LastName><ForeName>Romana</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Serology Department, Valneva Austria GmbH, Vienna, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dubischar</LastName><ForeName>Katrin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>R&amp;D Management, Valneva Austria GmbH, Vienna, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meyer</LastName><ForeName>St&#xe9;phanie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Corporate Medical Affairs, Valneva SE, Lyon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Travel Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9434456</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1195-1982</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chikungunya</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">VLA1553</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">arbovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunogenicity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surrogate of protection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39255380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jtm/taae123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">7754743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>