<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedBookArticle><BookDocument><PMID Version="1">30000829</PMID><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="bookaccession">NBK501770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><Book><Publisher><PublisherName>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</PublisherName><PublisherLocation>Bethesda (MD)</PublisherLocation></Publisher><BookTitle book="lactmed">Drugs and Lactation Database (LactMed&#xae;)</BookTitle><PubDate><Year>2006</Year></PubDate><BeginningDate><Year>2006</Year></BeginningDate><Medium>Internet</Medium></Book><ArticleTitle book="lactmed" part="LM862">St. John's Wort</ArticleTitle><Language>eng</Language><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><Abstract><AbstractText>St. John's wort (<i>Hypericum perforatum</i>) contains hypericin and hyperforin as well as flavonoids such as quercetin. It is often recommended by midwives for postpartum depression.[1,2] Both hypericin and hyperforin are poorly excreted into breastmilk; no other components have been measured in milk. One study found a slightly increased frequency of colic, drowsiness and lethargy among breastfed infants whose mothers were taking St. John's wort, but none of the effects were severe or required treatment. Most reports have related to breastfeeding older infants, rather than during the first 2 months postpartum when infants are more susceptible to adverse reactions. Conflicting information exists on whether St. John's wort can reduce serum prolactin levels or the maternal milk supply, although some mothers in T&#xfc;rkiye reportedly use it to increase their milk supply.[3] Galactogogues should never replace evaluation and counseling on modifiable factors that affect milk production.[4,5] St. John's wort adversely interacts with many drugs by increasing their metabolism, and it can occasionally cause phototoxicity. Labeling of commercially available products in the United States is often deficient with respect to these known safety issues.[6] Because there is little published experience with St. John's wort during breastfeeding, an alternate drug may be preferred, especially while nursing a newborn or preterm infant.[6] Dietary supplements do not require extensive pre-marketing approval from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Manufacturers are responsible to ensure the safety, but do not need to <i>prove</i> the safety and effectiveness of dietary supplements before they are marketed. Dietary supplements may contain multiple ingredients, and differences are often found between labeled and actual ingredients or their amounts. A manufacturer may contract with an independent organization to verify the quality of a product or its ingredients, but that does <i>not</i> certify the safety or effectiveness of a product. Because of the above issues, clinical testing results on one product may not be applicable to other products. More detailed information about dietary supplements is available elsewhere on the LactMed Web site.</AbstractText></Abstract><Sections><Section><SectionTitle book="lactmed" part="LM862" sec="LM862.Drug_Levels_and_Effects">Drug Levels and Effects</SectionTitle></Section><Section><SectionTitle book="lactmed" part="LM862" sec="LM862.Substance_Identification">Substance Identification</SectionTitle></Section></Sections><KeywordList Owner="NLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hypericum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">St. Johnswort</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Saint Johns Wort</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">St. Johns Wort</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hypericum perforatum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Saint John's Wort</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UNII-OZU2FC70HY</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Millepertius plant extract</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Saint john's wort extract</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">OZU2FC70HY</Keyword></KeywordList><ContributionDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></ContributionDate><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Allaire AD, Moos MK, Wells SR. Complementary and alternative medicine in pregnancy: A survey of North Carolina certified nurse-midwives. Obstet Gynecol 2000;95:19-23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10636495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dennehy C, Tsourounis C, Bui L, et al. The use of herbs by California midwives. J Obstet Gynecol Neonatal Nurs 2010;39:684-93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21044150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaygusuz M, G&#xfc;m&#xfc;&#x15f;tak&#x131;m R&#x15e;, Ku&#x15f; C, et al. TCM use in pregnant women and nursing mothers: A study from Turkey. Complement Ther Clin Pract 2021;42:101300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33412511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodribb W. ABM Clinical Protocol #9: Use of galactogogues in initiating or augmenting maternal milk production, second revision 2018. Breastfeed Med 2018;13:307-14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29902083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breastfeeding challenges: ACOG Committee Opinion, Number 820. Obstet Gynecol 2021;137:e42-e53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33481531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clauson KA, Santamarina ML, Rutledge JC. Clinically relevant safety issues associated with St. John's wort product labels. BMC Complement Altern Med 2008;8:42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2483264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18637192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wurglics M, Westerhoff K, Kaunzinger A, et al. Comparison of German St. John's wort products according to hyperforin and total hypericin content. J Am Pharm Assoc (Wash) 2001;41:560-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11486982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klier CM, Schafer MR, Schmid-Siegel B, et al. St. John's wort (Hypericum perforatum) -- is it safe during breastfeeding? Pharmacopsychiatry 2002;35:29-30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11819157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klier CM, Schmid-Siegel B, Schafer MR, et al. St. John's wort (Hypericum perforatum) and breastfeeding: plasma and breast milk concentrations of hyperforin for 5 mothers and 2 infants. J Clin Psychiatry 2006;67:305-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16566628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song BJ, Jouni ZE, Ferruzzi MG. Assessment of phytochemical content in human milk during different stages of lactation. Nutrition 2013;29:195-202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23237648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romaszko E, Wiczkowski W, Romaszko J, et al. Exposure of breastfed infants to quercetin after consumption of a single meal rich in quercetin by their mothers. Mol Nutr Food Res 2014;58:221-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23963751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grush LR, Nierenberg A, Keefe B, et al. St John's wort during pregnancy. JAMA 1998;280:1566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9820253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee A, Minhas R, Matsuda N, et al. The safety of St. John's wort (Hypericum perforatum) during breastfeeding. J Clin Psychiatry 2003;64:966-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12927015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canning S, Waterman M, Orsi N, et al. The efficacy of Hypericum perforatum (St John's wort) for the treatment of premenstrual syndrome: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. CNS Drugs 2010;24:207-25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20155996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franklin M, Cowen PJ. Researching the antidepressant actions of Hypericum perforatum (St. John's wort) in animals and man. Pharmacopsychiatry 2001;34 (Suppl 1):S29-37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11518072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></BookDocument><PubmedBookData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30000829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedBookData></PubmedBookArticle></PubmedArticleSet>