<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39505825</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>06</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-1654</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>34</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Reviews in medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enterovirus Antibodies: Friends and Foes.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70004</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70004</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/rmv.70004</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses (EV) initiate replication by binding to their cellular receptors, leading to the uncoating and release of the viral genome into the cytosol of the host cell. Neutralising antibodies (NAbs) binding to epitopes on enteroviral capsid proteins can inhibit this infectious process through several mechanisms of neutralisation in vitro. Fc-mediated antibody effector functions such as antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity and antibody-dependent cellular phagocytosis have also been described for some EV. However, antibody binding to virions does not always result in viral neutralisation. Non-neutralising antibodies, or sub-neutralising concentrations of antibodies, can enhance infection of viruses, leading to more severe pathologies. This phenomenon, known as antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) of infection, has been described in vitro and/or in vivo for EV including poliovirus, coxsackievirus B and EV-A71. It has been shown that ADE of EV infection is mediated by FcγRs expressed by monocytes, macrophages, B lymphocytes and granulocytes. Antibodies play a crucial role in the diagnosis and monitoring of infections. They are valuable markers that have been used to establish a link between enteroviral infection and chronic diseases such as type 1 diabetes. Monoclonal and polyclonal antibodies targeting enteroviral proteins have been developed and shown to be effective to prevent or combat EV infections in vitro and in vivo. In addition, vaccines are under development, and clinical trials of vaccines are underway or have been completed, providing hope for the prevention of diseases due to EV. However, the ADE of the infection should be considered in the development of anti-EV antibodies or safe vaccines.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Reviews in Medical Virology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mbani</LastName><ForeName>Chaldam Jespère</ForeName><Initials>CJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6488-666X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Biologie Cellulaire et Moléculaire, Faculté des Sciences et Techniques, Université Marien Ngouabi, Brazzaville, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morvan</LastName><ForeName>Corentin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-8125-2436</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nekoua</LastName><ForeName>Magloire Pandoua</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2981-0803</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Debuysschere</LastName><ForeName>Cyril</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5522-4296</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alidjinou</LastName><ForeName>Enagnon Kazali</ForeName><Initials>EK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1106-9826</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moukassa</LastName><ForeName>Donatien</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Biologie Cellulaire et Moléculaire, Faculté des Sciences et Techniques, Université Marien Ngouabi, Brazzaville, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hober</LastName><ForeName>Didier</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4301-2074</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>ULR3610</GrantID><Agency>Ministère de l'Education Nationale de la Recherche et de la Technologie, Université de Lille</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Centre Hospitalier et Universitaire de Lille</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>"SSHN JEUNE CHERCHEUR" scholarship of Ministère de l'Europe et des Affaires Etrangères</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>130771P</GrantID><Agency>Campus France</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9112448</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1052-9276</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000914">Antibodies, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D057134">Antibodies, Neutralizing</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000914" MajorTopicYN="Y">Antibodies, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057134" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Neutralizing</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019067" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibody-Dependent Enhancement</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enteroviruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">monoclonal antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neutralising antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">non‐neutralising antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polyclonal antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccines</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39505825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.70004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>ICTV, https://ictv.global/report/chapter/picornaviridae/picornaviridae/enterovirus.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Simmonds, A. E. Gorbalenya, H. Harvala, et al., “Recommendations for the Nomenclature of Enteroviruses and Rhinoviruses,” Archives of Virology 165, no. 3 (2020): 793–797, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705‐019‐04520‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Zell, E. Delwart, A. E. Gorbalenya, et al., “ICTV Virus Taxonomy Profile: Picornaviridae,” Journal of General Virology 98, no. 10 (2017): 2421–2422, https://doi.org/10.1099/jgv.0.000911.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Wang, W. Peng, J. Ren, et al., “A Sensor‐Adaptor Mechanism for Enterovirus Uncoating From Structures of EV71,” Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology 19, no. 4 (2012): 424–429, https://doi.org/10.1038/nsmb.2255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Guo, Y. Li, G. Liu, et al., “A Second Open Reading Frame in Human Enterovirus Determines Viral Replication in Intestinal Epithelial Cells,” Nature Communications 10, no. 1 (2019): 4066, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐019‐12040‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Lulla, A. M. Dinan, M. Hosmillo, et al., “An Upstream Protein‐Coding Region in Enteroviruses Modulates Virus Infection in Gut Epithelial Cells,” Nature Microbiology 4, no. 2 (2018): 280–292, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564‐018‐0297‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. L. Shingler, J. L. Yoder, M. S. Carnegie, et al., “The Enterovirus 71 A‐Particle Forms a Gateway to Allow Genome Release: A CryoEM Study of Picornavirus Uncoating,” PLoS Pathogens 9, no. 3 (2013): e1003240, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1003240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Baggen, H. J. Thibaut, J. R. P. M. Strating, and F. J. M. Van Kuppeveld, “The Life Cycle of Non‐Polio Enteroviruses and How to Target it,” Nature Reviews Microbiology 16, no. 6 (2018): 368–381, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579‐018‐0005‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Pons‐Salort, E. P. K. Parker, and N. C. Grassly, “The Epidemiology of Non‐Polio Enteroviruses: Recent Advances and Outstanding Questions,” Current Opinion in Infectious Diseases 28, no. 5 (2015): 479–487, https://doi.org/10.1097/QCO.0000000000000187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. J. Thibaut, C. Lacroix, A. M. De Palma, D. Franco, M. Decramer, and J. Neyts, “Toward Antiviral Therapy/Prophylaxis for Rhinovirus‐Induced Exacerbations of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease: Challenges, Opportunities, and Strategies,” Reviews in Medical Virology 26, no. 1 (2016): 21–33, https://doi.org/10.1002/rmv.1856.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. P. Nekoua, E. K. Alidjinou, and D. Hober, “Persistent Coxsackievirus B Infection and Pathogenesis of Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus,” Nature Reviews Endocrinology 18, no. 8 (2022): 503–516, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574‐022‐00688‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Hober and P. Sauter, “Pathogenesis of Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus: Interplay Between Enterovirus and Host,” Nature Reviews Endocrinology 6, no. 5 (2010): 279–289, https://doi.org/10.1038/nrendo.2010.27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. Maginnis, “Virus–Receptor Interactions: The Key to Cellular Invasion,” Journal of Molecular Biology 430, no. 17 (2018): 2590–2611, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2018.06.024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. A. Williams, L. Gui, N. Hom, A. Mileant, and K. K. Lee, “Dissection of Epitope‐Specific Mechanisms of Neutralization of Influenza Virus by Intact IgG and Fab Fragments,” Journal of Virology 92, no. 6 (2018): e02006–e02017, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.02006‐17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Takada, H. Feldmann, T. G. Ksiazek, and Y. Kawaoka, “Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement of Ebola Virus Infection,” Journal of Virology 77, no. 13 (2003): 7539–7544, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.77.13.7539‐7544.2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Sauter and D. Hober, “Mechanisms and Results of the Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement of Viral Infections and Role in the Pathogenesis of Coxsackievirus B‐Induced Diseases,” Microbes and Infection 11, no. 4 (2009): 443–451, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micinf.2009.01.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. J. Klasse, “Neutralization of Virus Infectivity by Antibodies: Old Problems in New Perspectives,” Advance Biology 2014 (2014): 1–24, https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/157895.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. N. Eisen, “Affinity Enhancement of Antibodies: How Low‐Affinity Antibodies Produced Early in Immune Responses Are Followed by High‐Affinity Antibodies Later and in Memory B‐Cell Responses,” Cancer Immunology Research 2, no. 5 (2014): 381–392, https://doi.org/10.1158/2326‐6066.CIR‐14‐0029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. Neuberger and C. Milstein, “Somatic Hypermutation,” Current Opinion in Immunology 7, no. 2 (1995): 248–254, https://doi.org/10.1016/0952‐7915(95)80010‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. J. Tas, L. Mesin, G. Pasqual, et al., “Visualizing Antibody Affinity Maturation in Germinal Centers,” Science 351, no. 6277 (2016): 1048–1054, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aad3439.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Di Noia and M. S. Neuberger, “Molecular Mechanisms of Antibody Somatic Hypermutation,” Annual Review of Biochemistry 76, no. 1 (2007): 1–22, https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.biochem.76.061705.090740.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Stebegg, S. D. Kumar, A. Silva‐Cayetano, V. R. Fonseca, M. A. Linterman, and L. Graca, “Regulation of the Germinal Center Response,” Frontiers in Immunology 9 (2018): 2469, https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2018.02469.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Y. A. Huang, “Structural Basis for Neutralization of Enterovirus,” Current Opinion Virology 51 (2021): 199–206, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coviro.2021.10.006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Appleyard, S. M. Russell, B. E. Clarke, S. A. Speller, M. Trowbridge, and J. Vadolas, “Neutralization Epitopes of Human Rhinovirus Type 2,” Journal of General Virology 71, no. 6 (1990): 1275–1282, https://doi.org/10.1099/0022‐1317‐71‐6‐1275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Z. Hastings, S. A. Speller, and M. J. Francis, “Neutralizing Antibodies to Human Rhinovirus Produced in Laboratory Animals and Humans That Recognize a Linear Sequence From VP2,” Journal of General Virology 71, no. 12 (1990): 3055–3059, https://doi.org/10.1099/0022‐1317‐71‐12‐3055.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. J. Smith, E. S. Chase, T. J. Schmidt, N. H. Olson, and T. S. Baker, “Neutralizing Antibody to Human Rhinovirus 14 Penetrates the Receptor‐Binding Canyon,” Nature 383, no. 6598 (1996): 350–354, https://doi.org/10.1038/383350a0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Ku, X. Ye, J. Shi, X. Wang, Q. Liu, and Z. Huang, “Single Neutralizing Monoclonal Antibodies Targeting the VP1 GH Loop of Enterovirus 71 Inhibit Both Virus Attachment and Internalization During Viral Entry,” Journal of Virology 89, no. 23 (2015): 12084–12095, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.02189‐15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Li, C. Mao, S. Ma, et al., “Generation of Neutralizing Monoclonal Antibodies Against Enterovirus 71 Using Synthetic Peptides,” Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications 390, no. 4 (2009): 1126–1128, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2009.09.103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. L. Shingler, J. O. Cifuente, R. E. Ashley, A. M. Makhov, J. F. Conway, and S. Hafenstein, “The Enterovirus 71 Procapsid Binds Neutralizing Antibodies and Rescues Virus Infection In Vitro,” Journal of Virology 89, no. 3 (2015): 1900–1908, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.03098‐14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Ye, C. Fan, Z. Ku, et al., “Structural Basis for Recognition of Human Enterovirus 71 by a Bivalent Broadly Neutralizing Monoclonal Antibody,” PLoS Pathogens 12, no. 3 (2016): e1005454, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1005454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Zhu, K. Xu, N. Wang, et al., “Neutralization Mechanisms of Two Highly Potent Antibodies Against Human Enterovirus 71,” mBio 9, no. 4 (2018), https://doi.org/10.1128/mBio.01013‐18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Y. A. Huang, D. Zhou, E. E. Fry, et al., “Structural and Functional Analysis of Protective Antibodies Targeting the Threefold Plateau of Enterovirus 71,” Nature Communications 11, no. 1 (2020): 5253, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐020‐19013‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Zhang, C. Liu, J. Shi, et al., “Molecular Mechanism of Antibody Neutralization of Coxsackievirus A16,” Nature Communications 13, no. 1 (2022): 7854, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐022‐35575‐w.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. He, L. Xu, Q. Zheng, et al., “Identification of Antibodies With Non‐Overlapping Neutralization Sites That Target Coxsackievirus A16,” Cell Host Microbe 27, no. 2 (2020): 249–261.e5, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2020.01.003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Zhang, C. Xu, W. Dai, et al., “Functional and Structural Characterization of a Two‐MAb Cocktail for Delayed Treatment of Enterovirus D68 Infections,” Nature Communications 12, no. 1 (2021): 2904, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐021‐23199‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. R. Vogt, J. Fu, N. Kose, et al., “Human Antibodies Neutralize Enterovirus D68 and Protect Against Infection and Paralytic Disease,” Science Immunology 5, no. 49 (2020): eaba4902, https://doi.org/10.1126/sciimmunol.aba4902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Zheng, R. Zhu, Z. Yin, et al., “Structural Basis for the Synergistic Neutralization of Coxsackievirus B1 by a Triple‐Antibody Cocktail,” Cell Host Microbe 30, no. 9 (2022): 1279–1294, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2022.08.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Wang, B. Zheng, L. Zhang, et al., “Serotype Specific Epitopes Identified by Neutralizing Antibodies Underpin Immunogenic Differences in Enterovirus B,” Nature Communications 11, no. 1 (2020): 4419, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐020‐18250‐w.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Feng, L. Wang, D. Shi, et al., “Structural Basis for Neutralization of an Anicteric Hepatitis Associated Echovirus by a Potent Neutralizing Antibody,” Cell Discovery 7, no. 1 (2021): 35, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41421‐021‐00264‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Qi, W. Fu, J. Fan, et al., “Structural Basis for the Immunogenicity of the C‐Terminus of VP1 of Echovirus 3 Revealed by the Binding of a Neutralizing Antibody,” Viruses 14, no. 11 (2022): 2322, https://doi.org/10.3390/v14112322.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. A. Thomas, R. Vrijsen, and A. Boeyé, “Relationship Between Poliovirus Neutralization and Aggregation,” Journal of Virology 59, no. 2 (1986): 479–485, https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.59.2.479‐485.1986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Che, N. H. Olson, D. Leippe, et al., “Antibody‐Mediated Neutralization of Human Rhinovirus 14 Explored by Means of Cryoelectron Microscopy and X‐Ray Crystallography of Virus‐Fab Complexes,” Journal of Virology 72, no. 6 (1998): 4610–4622, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.72.6.4610‐4622.1998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Colonno, P. L. Callahan, D. M. Leippe, R. R. Rueckert, and J. E. Tomassini, “Inhibition of Rhinovirus Attachment by Neutralizing Monoclonal Antibodies and Their Fab Fragments,” Journal of Virology 63, no. 1 (1989): 36–42, https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.63.1.36‐42.1989.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Bergelson and C. B. Coyne, “Picornavirus Entry,” in Viral Entry into Host Cells, eds. S. Pöhlmann and G. Simmons, Vol. 790 (New York: Springer, 2013), 24–41, https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐1‐4614‐7651‐1_2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Xu, Q. Zheng, S. Li, et al., “Atomic Structures of Coxsackievirus A6 and its Complex With a Neutralizing Antibody,” Nature Communications 8, no. 1 (2017): 505, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐017‐00477‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Kaplan, M. S. Freistadt, and V. R. Racaniello, “Neutralization of Poliovirus by Cell Receptors Expressed in Insect Cells,” Journal of Virology 64, no. 10 (1990): 4697–4702, https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.64.10.4697‐4702.1990.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Plevka, P. Y. Lim, R. Perera, et al., “Neutralizing Antibodies Can Initiate Genome Release From Human Enterovirus 71,” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 111, no. 6 (2014): 2134–2139, https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1320624111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Dong, Y. Liu, W. Jiang, T. J. Smith, Z. Xu, and M. G. Rossmann, “Antibody‐Induced Uncoating of Human Rhinovirus B14,” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 114, no. 30 (2017): 8017–8022, https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1707369114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Brioen, B. Rombaut, and A. Boeye, “Hit‐and‐Run Neutralization of Poliovirus,” Journal of General Virology 66, no. 11 (1985): 2495–2499, https://doi.org/10.1099/0022‐1317‐66‐11‐2495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Zheng, R. Zhu, L. Xu, et al., “Atomic Structures of Enterovirus D68 in Complex With Two Monoclonal Antibodies Define Distinct Mechanisms of Viral Neutralization,” Nature Microbiology 4, no. 1 (2018): 124–133, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564‐018‐0275‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Vrijsen, A. Mosser, and A. Boeyé, “Postabsorption Neutralization of Poliovirus,” Journal of Virology 67, no. 6 (1993): 3126–3133, https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.67.6.3126‐3133.1993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Touabi, F. Aflatouni, and G. R. McLean, “Mechanisms of Rhinovirus Neutralisation by Antibodies,” Viruses 13, no. 3 (2021): 360, https://doi.org/10.3390/v13030360.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. J. Charnesky, J. E. Faust, H. Lee, et al., “A Human Monoclonal Antibody Binds Within the Poliovirus Receptor‐Binding Site to Neutralize All Three Serotypes,” Nature Communications 14, no. 1 (2023): 6335, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐023‐41052‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. He, L. Xu, Q. Zheng, et al., “Identification of Antibodies With Non‐Overlapping Neutralization Sites That Target Coxsackievirus A16,” Cell Host &amp; Microbe 27, no. 2 (2020): 249–261.e5, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2020.01.003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. R. Burton, “Antiviral Neutralizing Antibodies: From In Vitro to In Vivo Activity,” Nature Reviews Immunology 23, no. 11 (2023): 720–734, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41577‐023‐00858‐w.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Behzadi, A. Choi, J. Duehr, et al., “A Cross‐Reactive Mouse Monoclonal Antibody Against Rhinovirus Mediates Phagocytosis In Vitro,” Scientific Reports 10, no. 1 (2020): 9750, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐020‐66600‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Du, C. An, X. Yao, et al., “Non‐Neutralizing Monoclonal Antibody Targeting VP2 EF Loop of Coxsackievirus A16 Can Protect Mice From Lethal Attack via Fc‐Dependent Effector Mechanism,” Emerging Microbes &amp; Infections 12, no. 1 (2023), https://doi.org/10.1080/22221751.2022.2149352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. A. McEwan, D. L. Mallery, D. A. Rhodes, J. Trowsdale, and L. C. James, “Intracellular Antibody‐Mediated Immunity and the Role of TRIM21,” BioEssays 33, no. 11 (2011): 803–809, https://doi.org/10.1002/bies.201100093.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. C. James, A. H. Keeble, Z. Khan, D. A. Rhodes, and J. Trowsdale, “Structural Basis for PRYSPRY‐Mediated Tripartite Motif (TRIM) Protein Function,” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 104, no. 15 (2007): 6200–6205, https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0609174104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. L. Mallery, W. A. McEwan, S. R. Bidgood, G. J. Towers, C. M. Johnson, and L. C. James, “Antibodies Mediate Intracellular Immunity Through Tripartite Motif‐Containing 21 (TRIM21),” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 107, no. 46 (2010): 19985–19990, https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1014074107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. E. Watkinson, W. A. McEwan, J. C. H. Tam, M. Vaysburd, and L. C. James, “TRIM21 Promotes cGAS and RIG‐I Sensing of Viral Genomes During Infection by Antibody‐Opsonized Virus,” PLoS Pathogens 11, no. 10 (2015): e1005253, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1005253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Bottermann and S. L. Caddy, “Virus Neutralisation by Intracellular Antibodies,” Seminars in Cell &amp; Developmental Biology 126 (2022): 108–116, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.semcdb.2021.10.010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Fan, D. Zhang, P. Qian, et al., “Swine TRIM21 Restricts FMDV Infection via an Intracellular Neutralization Mechanism,” Antiviral Research 127 (2016): 32–40, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2016.01.004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. R. Neutra and P. A. Kozlowski, “Mucosal Vaccines: The Promise and the Challenge,” Nature Reviews Immunology 6, no. 2 (2006): 148–158, https://doi.org/10.1038/nri1777.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Turula and C. Wobus, “The Role of the Polymeric Immunoglobulin Receptor and Secretory Immunoglobulins During Mucosal Infection and Immunity,” Viruses 10, no. 5 (2018): 237, https://doi.org/10.3390/v10050237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. D. Garcia‐Castillo, D. J. F. Chinnapen, and W. I. Lencer, “Membrane Transport Across Polarized Epithelia,” Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology 9, no. 9 (2017): a027912, https://doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a027912.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Oikarinen, S. Tauriainen, D. Hober, et al., “Virus Antibody Survey in Different European Populations Indicates Risk Association Between Coxsackievirus B1 and Type 1 Diabetes,” Diabetes 63, no. 2 (2014): 655–662, https://doi.org/10.2337/db13‐0620.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. H. Laitinen, H. Honkanen, O. Pakkanen, et al., “Coxsackievirus B1 Is Associated With Induction of β‐Cell Autoimmunity That Portends Type 1 Diabetes,” Diabetes 63, no. 2 (2014): 446–455, https://doi.org/10.2337/db13‐0619.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Sadeharju, A. M. Hämäläinen, M. Knip, et al., “Enterovirus Infections as a Risk Factor for Type I Diabetes: Virus Analyses in a Dietary Intervention Trial,” Clinical and Experimental Immunology 132, no. 2 (2003): 271–277, https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365‐2249.2003.02147.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Salminen, K. Sadeharju, M. Lönnrot, et al., “Enterovirus Infections Are Associated With the Induction of β‐cell Autoimmunity in a Prospective Birth Cohort Study,” Journal of Medical Virology 69, no. 1 (2003): 91–98, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.10260.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. B. Sioofy‐Khojine, J. Lehtonen, N. Nurminen, et al., “Coxsackievirus B1 Infections Are Associated With the Initiation of Insulin‐Driven Autoimmunity That Progresses to Type 1 Diabetes,” Diabetologia 61, no. 5 (2018): 1193–1202, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00125‐018‐4561‐y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Hyöty, M. Hiltunen, M. Knip, et al., “A Prospective Study of the Role of Coxsackie B and Other Enterovirus Infections in the Pathogenesis of IDDM,” Diabetes 44, no. 6 (1995): 652–657, https://doi.org/10.2337/diab.44.6.652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. P. Nekoua, A. Yessoufou, E. K. Alidjinou, et al., “Salivary Anti‐Coxsackievirus‐B4 Neutralizing Activity and Pattern of Immune Parameters in Patients With Type 1 Diabetes: A Pilot Study,” Acta Diabetologica 55, no. 8 (2018): 827–834, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00592‐018‐1158‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Badia‐Boungou, F. Sane, E. K. Alidjinou, et al., “Marker of Coxsackievirus‐B4 Infection in Saliva of Patients With Type 1 Diabetes,” Diabetes Metab Res Rev 33, no. 7 (2017): e2916, https://doi.org/10.1002/dmrr.2916.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Patelarou, C. Girvalaki, H. Brokalaki, A. Patelarou, Z. Androulaki, and C. Vardavas, “Current Evidence on the Associations of Breastfeeding, Infant Formula, and Cow’s Milk Introduction With Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus: A Systematic Review,” Nutrition Reviews 70, no. 9 (2012): 509–519, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1753‐4887.2012.00513.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Malcova, Z. Sumnik, P. Drevinek, J. Venhacova, J. Lebl, and O. Cinek, “Absence of Breast‐Feeding Is Associated With the Risk of Type 1 Diabetes: A Case–Control Study in a Population With Rapidly Increasing Incidence,” European Journal of Pediatrics 165, no. 2 (2006): 114–119, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00431‐005‐0008‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Sane, E. K. Alidjinou, N. Kacet, et al., “Human Milk Can Neutralize Coxsackievirus B4 In Vitro,” Journal of Medical Virology 85, no. 5 (2013): 880–887, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.23518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhou, C. Zhou, K. Wang, et al., “Diagnostic Performance of Different Specimens in Detecting Enterovirus A71 in Children With Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease,” Virologica Sinica 38, no. 2 (2023): 268–275, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virs.2022.11.004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Zhang, Y. Cheng, Y. Li, et al., “Evaluation of the Diagnostic Performance and its Associated Factors of a Commercial Anti‐EV‐A71 IgM‐Capture ELISA Kit in Hospitalized Children With Clinical Diagnostic HFMD,” Journal of Clinical Virology 130 (2020): 104582, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2020.104582.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Kordi, A. J. Chang, and M. D. Hicar, “Seasonal Testing, Results, and Effect of the Pandemic on Coxsackievirus Serum Studies,” Microorganisms 12, no. 2 (2024): 367, https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms12020367.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Terletskaia‐Ladwig, C. Metzger, G. Schalasta, and G. Enders, “Evaluation of Enterovirus Serological Tests IgM‐EIA and Complement Fixation in Patients With Meningitis, Confirmed by Detection of Enteroviral RNA by RT‐PCR in Cerebrospinal Fluid,” Journal of Medical Virology 61, no. 2 (2000): 221–227, https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1096‐9071(200006)61:2&lt;221::AID‐JMV8&gt;3.0.CO;2‐E.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. P. Parker, N. A. Molodecky, M. Pons‐Salort, K. M. O’Reilly, and N. C. Grassly, “Impact of Inactivated Poliovirus Vaccine on Mucosal Immunity: Implications for the Polio Eradication Endgame,” Expert Rev Vaccines 14, no. 8 (2015): 1113–1123, https://doi.org/10.1586/14760584.2015.1052800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. J. Mbani, M. P. Nekoua, D. Moukassa, and D. Hober, “The Fight Against Poliovirus Is Not Over,” Microorganisms 11, no. 5 (2023): 1323, https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms11051323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Zhaori, M. Sun, H. S. Faden, and P. L. Ogra, “Nasopharyngeal Secretory Antibody Response to Poliovirus Type 3 Virion Proteins Exhibit Different Specificities After Immunization With Live or Inactivated Poliovirus Vaccines,” Journal of Infectious Diseases 159, no. 6 (1989): 1018–1024, https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/159.6.1018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Shi, P. Chen, Y. Bai, X. Xu, and Y. Liu, “Seroprevalence of Coxsackievirus A6 and Enterovirus A71 Infection in Humans: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis,” Archives of Virology 168, no. 2 (2023): 37, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705‐022‐05642‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Kamau, D. Nguyen, C. Celma, et al., “Seroprevalence and Virologic Surveillance of Enterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A6, United Kingdom, 2006–2017,” Emerging Infectious Diseases 27, no. 9 (2021): 2261–2268, https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2709.204915.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. V. V. Jouppila, J. Lehtonen, E. Seppälä, et al., “Assessment of Enterovirus Antibodies During Early Childhood Using a Multiplex Immunoassay,” Microbiology Spectrum 11, no. 3 (2023), https://doi.org/10.1128/spectrum.05352‐22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. V. V. Saarinen, J. Lehtonen, R. Veijola, et al., “Multiplexed High‐Throughput Serological Assay for Human Enteroviruses,” Microorganisms 8, no. 6 (2020): 963, https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms8060963.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. E. Robinson, M. DavidC, and W.M. Mitchell, “Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement of Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1 Infection,” Lancet 331, no. 8589 (1988): 790–794, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(88)91657‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Ochiai, M. Kurokawa, S. Matsui, et al., “Infection Enhancement of Influenza A NWS Virus in Primary Murine Macrophages by Anti‐Hemagglutinin Monoclonal Antibody,” Journal of Medical Virology 36, no. 3 (1992): 217–221, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.1890360312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. B. Halstead, “Neutralization and Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement of Dengue Viruses,” in Advances in Virus Research, Vol. 60 (Elsevier, 2003), 421–467, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0065‐3527(03)60011‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Takano, M. Nakaguchi, T. Doki, and T. Hohdatsu, “Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement of Serotype II Feline Enteric Coronavirus Infection in Primary Feline Monocytes,” Archives of Virology 162, no. 11 (2017): 3339–3345, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705‐017‐3489‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. C. Katzelnick, L. Gresh, M. E. Halloran, et al., “Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement of Severe Dengue Disease in Humans,” Science 358, no. 6365 (2017): 929–932, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aan6836.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Palmer, B. Charley, B. Rombaut, M. Daëron, and P. Lebon, “Antibody‐Dependent Induction of Type I Interferons by Poliovirus in Human Mononuclear Blood Cells Requires the Type II Fcγ Receptor (CD32),” Virology 278, no. 1 (2000): 86–94, https://doi.org/10.1006/viro.2000.0627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Girn, M. Kavoosi, and J. Chantler, “Enhancement of Coxsackievirus B3 Infection by Antibody to a Different Coxsackievirus Strain,” Journal of General Virology 83, no. 2 (2002): 351–358, https://doi.org/10.1099/0022‐1317‐83‐2‐351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Kishimoto, M. Kurokawa, and H. Ochiai, “Antibody‐Mediated Immune Enhancement in Coxsackievirus B3 Myocarditis,” Journal of Molecular and Cellular Cardiology 34, no. 9 (2002): 1227–1238, https://doi.org/10.1006/jmcc.2002.2087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Chehadeh, A. Bouzidi, G. Alm, P. Wattré, and D. Hober, “Human Antibodies Isolated From Plasma by Affinity Chromatography Increase the Coxsackievirus B4‐Induced Synthesis of Interferon‐α by Human Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells In Vitro,” Journal of General Virology 82, no. 8 (2001): 1899–1907, https://doi.org/10.1099/0022‐1317‐82‐8‐1899.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Chehadeh, P. E. Lobert, P. Sauter, et al., “Viral Protein VP4 Is a Target of Human Antibodies Enhancing Coxsackievirus B4‐ and B3‐Induced Synthesis of Alpha Interferon,” Journal of Virology 79, no. 22 (2005): 13882–13891, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.79.22.13882‐13891.2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. K. Alidjinou, F. Sané, I. Engelmann, and D. Hober, “Serum‐Dependent Enhancement of Coxsackievirus B4‐Induced Production of IFNα, IL‐6 and TNFα by Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells,” Journal of Molecular Biology 425, no. 24 (2013): 5020–5031, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2013.10.008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Alidjinou, F. Sané, J. Trauet, M. C. Copin, and D. Hober, “Coxsackievirus B4 Can Infect Human Peripheral Blood‐Derived Macrophages,” Viruses 7, no. 11 (2015): 6067–6079, https://doi.org/10.3390/v7112924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Benkahla, F. Elmastour, F. Sane, et al., “Coxsackievirus‐B4E2 Can Infect Monocytes and Macrophages In Vitro and In Vivo,” Virology 522 (2018): 271–280, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2018.06.010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Sauter, P. E. Lobert, B. Lucas, et al., “Role of the Capsid Protein VP4 in the Plasma‐Dependent Enhancement of the Coxsackievirus B4E2‐Infection of Human Peripheral Blood Cells,” Virus Research 125, no. 2 (2007): 183–190, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virusres.2007.01.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Hober, W. Chehadeh, J. Weill, et al., “Circulating and Cell‐Bound Antibodies Increase Coxsackievirus B4‐Induced Production of IFN‐α by Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells From Patients With Type 1 Diabetes,” Journal of General Virology 83, no. 9 (2002): 2169–2176, https://doi.org/10.1099/0022‐1317‐83‐9‐2169.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Elmastour, H. Jaidane, L. Aguech‐Oueslati, et al., “Immunoglobulin G‐Dependent Enhancement of the Infection With Coxsackievirus B4 in a Murine System,” Virulence 7, no. 5 (2016): 527–535, https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2016.1152442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Elmastour, H. Jaïdane, M. Benkahla, et al., “Anti‐coxsackievirus B4 (CV‐B4) Enhancing Activity of Serum Associated With Increased Viral Load and Pathology in Mice Reinfected With CV‐B4,” Virulence 8, no. 6 (2017): 908–923, https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2016.1252018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Sane, A. Bertin, A. Sioofy‐Khojine, et al., “Enhancing and Neutralizing Anti‐Coxsackievirus Activities in Serum Samples From Patients Prior to Development of Type 1 Diabetes,” Diabetes Metabolism Research Review 36, no. 6 (2020), https://doi.org/10.1002/dmrr.3305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Aswathyraj, F. Sane, C. Raghu, et al., “Serum‐Derived IgG From Coxsackievirus A6‐Infected Patients Can Enhance the Infection of Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells With Coxsackievirus A6,” Microbial Pathogenesis 125 (2018): 7–11, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2018.08.064.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. F. Han, R. Y. Cao, Y. Q. Deng, et al., “Antibody Dependent Enhancement Infection of Enterovirus 71 In Vitro and In Vivo,” Virology Journal 8, no. 1 (2011): 106, https://doi.org/10.1186/1743‐422X‐8‐106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Wang, I. C. Chen, L. Y. Su, K. J. Huang, H. Y. Lei, and C. C. Liu, “Enterovirus 71 Infection of Monocytes With Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement,” Clinical and Vaccine Immunology 17, no. 10 (2010): 1517–1523, https://doi.org/10.1128/CVI.00108‐10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. C. Chen, S. M. Wang, C. K. Yu, and C. C. Liu, “Subneutralizing Antibodies to Enterovirus 71 Induce Antibody‐Dependent Enhancement of Infection in Newborn Mice,” Medical Microbiology and Immunology 202, no. 4 (2013): 259–265, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00430‐013‐0289‐y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Kawasaki, “Anti‐Islet Autoantibodies in Type 1 Diabetes,” International Journal of Molecular Sciences 24, no. 12 (2023): 10012, https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms241210012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Op de Beeck and D. L. Eizirik, “Viral Infections in Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus—Why the β Cells?,” Nature Reviews Endocrinology 12, no. 5 (2016): 263–273, https://doi.org/10.1038/nrendo.2016.30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Petzold, M. Solimena, and K. P. Knoch, “Mechanisms of Beta Cell Dysfunction Associated With Viral Infection,” Current Diabetes Reports 15, no. 10 (2015): 73, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11892‐015‐0654‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Kukreja and N. K. Maclaren, “Current Cases in Which Epitope Mimicry Is Considered as a Component Cause of Autoimmune Disease: Immune‐Mediated (Type 1) Diabetes,” Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences 57, no. 4 (2000): 534–541, https://doi.org/10.1007/PL00000715.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Jaïdane, P. Sauter, F. Sane, A. Goffard, J. Gharbi, and D. Hober, “Enteroviruses and Type 1 Diabetes: Towards a Better Understanding of the Relationship,” Reviews in Medical Virology 20, no. 5 (2010): 265–280, https://doi.org/10.1002/rmv.647.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Real‐Fernández, A. Gallo, F. Nuti, et al., “Cross‐Reactive Peptide Epitopes of Enterovirus Coxsackie B4 and Human Glutamic Acid Decarboxylase Detecting Antibodies in Latent Autoimmune Diabetes in Adults Versus Type 1 Diabetes,” Clinica Chimica Acta 515 (2021): 73–79, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cca.2021.01.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. Horwitz, L. M. Bradley, J. Harbertson, T. Krahl, J. Lee, and N. Sarvennick, “Diabetes Induced by Coxsackie Virus: Initiation by Bystander Damage and Not Molecular Mimicry,” Nature Medicine 4, no. 7 (1998): 781–785, https://doi.org/10.1038/nm0798‐781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. H. Trier, N. Valdarnini, I. Fanelli, et al., “Peptide Antibody Reactivity to Homologous Regions in Glutamate Decarboxylase Isoforms and Coxsackievirus B4 P2C,” International Journal of Molecular Sciences 23, no. 8 (2022): 4424, https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms23084424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Härkönen, A. Paananen, H. Lankinen, T. Hovi, O. Vaarala, and M. Roivainen, “Enterovirus Infection May Induce Humoral Immune Response Reacting With Islet Cell Autoantigens in Humans,” Journal of Medical Virology 69, no. 3 (2003): 426–440, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.10306.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Jartti, M. Flodström‐Tullberg, and M. M. Hankaniemi, “Enteroviruses: Epidemic Potential, Challenges and Opportunities With Vaccines,” Journal of Biomedical Science 31, no. 1 (2024): 73, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12929‐024‐01058‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Bopegamage, “Enterovirus Infections: Pivoting Role of the Adaptive Immune Response,” Virulence 7, no. 5 (2016): 495–497, https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2016.1175701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. F. Lim, Q. Jia, W. X. Khong, et al., “Characterization of an Isotype‐Dependent Monoclonal Antibody Against Linear Neutralizing Epitope Effective for Prophylaxis of Enterovirus 71 Infection,” PLoS One 7, no. 1 (2012): e29751, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0029751.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. K. Kiener, Q. Jia, T. Meng, V. T. K. Chow, and J. Kwang, “A Novel Universal Neutralizing Monoclonal Antibody Against Enterovirus 71 That Targets the Highly Conserved “Knob” Region of VP3 Protein. De Silva AM,” PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases 8, no. 5 (2014): e2895, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0002895.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Jia, Q. Ng, W. Chin, et al., “Effective In Vivo Therapeutic IgG Antibody Against VP3 of Enterovirus 71 With Receptor‐Competing Activity,” Scientific Reports 7, no. 1 (2017): 46402, https://doi.org/10.1038/srep46402.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. H. Tan, K. C. Ong, D. Perera, and K. T. Wong, “A Monoclonal Antibody to Ameliorate Central Nervous System Infection and Improve Survival in a Murine Model of Human Enterovirus‐A71 Encephalomyelitis,” Antiviral Research 132 (2016): 196–203, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2016.04.015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Xu, D. He, Z. Li, et al., “Protection Against Lethal Enterovirus 71 Challenge in Mice by a Recombinant Vaccine Candidate Containing a Broadly Cross‐Neutralizing Epitope Within the VP2 EF Loop,” Theranostics 4, no. 5 (2014): 498–513, https://doi.org/10.7150/thno.7457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Both, A. C. Banyard, C. van Dolleweerd, E. Wright, J. K. C. Ma, and A. R. Fooks, “Monoclonal Antibodies for Prophylactic and Therapeutic Use Against Viral Infections,” Vaccine 31, no. 12 (2013): 1553–1559, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2013.01.025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. X. Lim and C. L. Poh, “Insights Into Innate and Adaptive Immune Responses in Vaccine Development Against EV‐A71,” Therapy Advance Vaccines Immunother 7 (2019): 251513551988899, https://doi.org/10.1177/2515135519888998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. N. Donlan and W. A. Petri, “Mucosal Immunity and the Eradication of Polio,” Science 368, no. 6489 (2020): 362–363, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abb8588.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. M. Herremans, J. H. Reimerink, A. M. Buisman, T. G. Kimman, and M. P. Koopmans, “Induction of Mucosal Immunity by Inactivated Poliovirus Vaccine Is Dependent on Previous Mucosal Contact With Live Virus,” Journal of Immunology 162, no. 8 (1999): 5011–5018, https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.162.8.5011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. V. Nates, L. C. Martinez, P. A. Barril, et al., “Long‐Lasting Poliovirus‐Neutralizing Antibodies Among Argentinean Population Immunized With Four or Five Oral Polio Vaccine Doses 1 Month to 19 Years Previously,” Viral Immunology 20, no. 1 (2007): 3–10, https://doi.org/10.1089/vim.2006.0071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Wahid, M. J. Cannon, and M. Chow, “Virus‐Specific CD4 + and CD8 + Cytotoxic T‐Cell Responses and Long‐Term T‐Cell Memory in Individuals Vaccinated Against Polio,” Journal of Virology 79, no. 10 (2005): 5988–5995, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.79.10.5988‐5995.2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. A. Korotkova, A. P. Gmyl, M. L. Yakovenko, et al., “A Cluster of Paralytic Poliomyelitis Cases Due to Transmission of Slightly Diverged Sabin 2 Vaccine Poliovirus,” Journal of Virology 90, no. 13 (2016): 5978–5988, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.00277‐16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. De Coster, I. Leroux‐Roels, A. S. Bandyopadhyay, et al., “Safety and Immunogenicity of Two Novel Type 2 Oral Poliovirus Vaccine Candidates Compared With a Monovalent Type 2 Oral Poliovirus Vaccine in Healthy Adults: Two Clinical Trials,” Lancet 397, no. 10268 (2021): 39–50, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(20)32541‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Sáez‐Llorens, A. S. Bandyopadhyay, C. Gast, et al., “Safety and Immunogenicity of Two Novel Type 2 Oral Poliovirus Vaccine Candidates Compared With a Monovalent Type 2 Oral Poliovirus Vaccine in Children and Infants: Two Clinical Trials,” Lancet 397, no. 10268 (2021): 27–38, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(20)32540‐X.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. O. Adeyemi, C. Nicol, N. J. Stonehouse, and D. J. Rowlands, “Increasing Type 1 Poliovirus Capsid Stability by Thermal Selection,” Journal of Virology 91, no. 4 (2017), https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.01586‐16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. G. Viktorova, S. K. Khattar, D. Kouiavskaia, et al., “Newcastle Disease Virus‐Based Vectored Vaccine Against Poliomyelitis,” Journal of Virology 92, no. 17 (2018), https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.00976‐18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. W. Bahar, C. Porta, H. Fox, A. J. Macadam, E. E. Fry, and D. I. Stuart, “Mammalian Expression of Virus‐Like Particles as a Proof of Principle for Next Generation Polio Vaccines,” NPJ Vaccines 6, no. 1 (2021): 5, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41541‐020‐00267‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Xu, S. Ma, Y. Huang, et al., “Virus‐Like Particle Vaccines for Poliovirus Types 1, 2, and 3 With Enhanced Thermostability Expressed in Insect Cells,” Vaccine 37, no. 17 (2019): 2340–2347, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.03.031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. S. Bandyopadhyay, J. Garon, K. Seib, and W. A. Orenstein, “Polio Vaccination: Past, Present and Future,” Future Microbiology 10, no. 5 (2015): 791–808, https://doi.org/10.2217/fmb.15.19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. V. Andreasen, L. B. Hansen, P. Andersen, E. M. Agger, and J. Dietrich, “Aluminium Hydroxide Potentiates a Protective Th1 Biased Immune Response Against Polio Virus That Allows for Dose Sparing in Mice and Rats,” Vaccine 33, no. 15 (2015): 1873–1879, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2015.02.011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. D. Clements and E. B. Norton, “The Mucosal Vaccine Adjuvant LT(R192G/L211A) or dmLT,” mSphere 3, no. 4 (2018), https://doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00215‐18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. T. Nguyen, C. H. Chiu, C. Y. Lin, et al., “Efficacy, Safety, and Immunogenicity of an Inactivated, Adjuvanted Enterovirus 71 Vaccine in Infants and Children: A Multiregion, Double‐Blind, Randomised, Placebo‐Controlled, Phase 3 Trial,” Lancet 399, no. 10336 (2022): 1708–1717, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(22)00313‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Li, L. Liu, Z. Mo, et al., “An Inactivated Enterovirus 71 Vaccine in Healthy Children,” New England Journal of Medicine 370, no. 9 (2014): 829–837, https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1303224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. C. Zhu, F. Y. Meng, J. X. Li, et al., “Efficacy, Safety, and Immunology of an Inactivated Alum‐Adjuvant Enterovirus 71 Vaccine in Children in China: A Multicentre, Randomised, Double‐Blind, Placebo‐Controlled, Phase 3 Trial,” Lancet 381, no. 9882 (2013): 2024–2032, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(13)61049‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Wei, F. Meng, S. Wang, et al., “2‐Year Efficacy, Immunogenicity, and Safety of Vigoo Enterovirus 71 Vaccine in Healthy Chinese Children: A Randomized Open‐Label Study,” Journal of Infectious Diseases 215, no. 1 (2017): 56–63, https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiw502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. X. Li, Y. F. Song, L. Wang, et al., “Two‐Year Efficacy and Immunogenicity of Sinovac Enterovirus 71 Vaccine Against Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease in Children,” Expert Rev Vaccines 15, no. 1 (2016): 129–137, https://doi.org/10.1586/14760584.2016.1096782.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Zhu, W. Xu, J. Xia, et al., “Efficacy, Safety, and Immunogenicity of an Enterovirus 71 Vaccine in China,” New England Journal of Medicine 370, no. 9 (2014): 818–828, https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1304923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Hu, G. Zeng, K. Chu, et al., “Five‐Year Immunity Persistence Following Immunization With Inactivated Enterovirus 71 Type (EV71) Vaccine in Healthy Children: A Further Observation,” Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics 14, no. 6 (2018): 1517–1523, https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2018.1442997.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Hyöty, S. Kääriäinen, J. E. Laiho, et al., “Safety, Tolerability and Immunogenicity of PRV‐101, a Multivalent Vaccine Targeting Coxsackie B Viruses (CVBs) Associated With Type 1 Diabetes: A Double‐Blind Randomised Placebo‐Controlled Phase I Trial,” Diabetologia 67, no. 5 (2024): 811–821, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00125‐024‐06092‐w.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Erdem, I. De Coster, K. Withanage, et al., “Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of Inactivated Poliovirus Vaccine With or Without E.Coli Double Mutant Heat‐Labile Toxin (dmLT) Adjuvant in Healthy Adults; a Phase 1 Randomized Study,” Vaccine 41, no. 10 (2023): 1657–1667, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2023.01.048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Sáez‐Llorens, B. Thierry‐Carstensen, L. S. Stoey, et al., “Immunogenicity and Safety of an Adjuvanted Inactivated Polio Vaccine, IPV‐Al, Following Vaccination in Children at 2, 4, 6 and at 15–18 Months,” Vaccine 38, no. 21 (2020): 3780–3789, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.02.066.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Hu, J. Wang, G. Zeng, et al., “Immunogenicity and Safety of a Sabin Strain–Based Inactivated Polio Vaccine: A Phase 3 Clinical Trial,” Journal of Infectious Diseases 220, no. 10 (2019): 1551–1557, https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiy736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Ochoge, A. C. Futa, A. Umesi, et al., “Safety of the Novel Oral Poliovirus Vaccine Type 2 (nOPV2) in Infants and Young Children Aged 1 to &lt;5 Years and Lot‐To‐Lot Consistency of the Immune Response to nOPV2 in Infants in the Gambia: A Phase 3, Double‐Blind, Randomised Controlled Trial,” Lancet 403, no. 10432 (2024): 1164–1175, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(23)02844‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Chen, K. Chumakov, E. Dragunsky, et al., “Chimpanzee‐Human Monoclonal Antibodies for Treatment of Chronic Poliovirus Excretors and Emergency Postexposure Prophylaxis,” Journal of Virology 85, no. 9 (2011): 4354–4362, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.02553‐10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. D. Puligedda, D. Kouiavskaia, F. H. Al‐Saleem, et al., “Characterization of Human Monoclonal Antibodies That Neutralize Multiple Poliovirus Serotypes,” Vaccine 35, no. 41 (2017): 5455–5462, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.03.038.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Aswathyraj, G. Arunkumar, E. K. Alidjinou, and D. Hober, “Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease (HFMD): Emerging Epidemiology and the Need for a Vaccine Strategy,” Medical Microbiology and Immunology 205, no. 5 (2016): 397–407, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00430‐016‐0465‐y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Gonzalez, M. J. Carr, M. Kobayashi, N. Hanaoka, and T. Fujimoto, “Enterovirus‐Associated Hand‐Foot and Mouth Disease and Neurological Complications in Japan and the Rest of the World,” International Journal of Molecular Sciences 20, no. 20 (2019): 5201, https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms20205201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Liu, M. Zhang, C. Feng, et al., “Characterization of Coxsackievirus A6 Strains Isolated From Children With Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease,” Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology 11 (2021), https://doi.org/10.3389/fcimb.2021.700191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. C. Ong, S. Devi, M. J. Cardosa, and K. T. Wong, “Formaldehyde‐Inactivated Whole‐Virus Vaccine Protects a Murine Model of Enterovirus 71 Encephalomyelitis Against Disease,” Journal of Virology 84, no. 1 (2010): 661–665, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.00999‐09.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. J. Bek, K. M. Hussain, P. Phuektes, et al., “Formalin‐Inactivated Vaccine Provokes Cross‐Protective Immunity in a Mouse Model of Human Enterovirus 71 Infection,” Vaccine 29, no. 29‐30 (2011): 4829–4838, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.04.070.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Mao, T. Cheng, F. Zhu, et al., “The Cross‐Neutralizing Activity of Enterovirus 71 Subgenotype C4 Vaccines in Healthy Chinese Infants and Children,” PLoS One 8, no. 11 (2013): e79599, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0079599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. H. Chou, C. C. Liu, J. Y. Chang, et al., “Formalin‐Inactivated EV71 Vaccine Candidate Induced Cross‐Neutralizing Antibody Against Subgenotypes B1, B4, B5 and C4A in Adult Volunteers,” PLoS One 8, no. 11 (2013): e79783, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0079783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. M. Huang, C. H. Chiu, N. C. Chiu, et al., “Immunogenicity, Safety, Cross‐Reaction, and Immune Persistence of an Inactivated Enterovirus A71 Vaccine in Children Aged From Two Months to 11 Years in Taiwan,” Vaccine 37, no. 13 (2019): 1827–1835, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.02.023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Zhang, Z. Dong, Q. Wang, et al., “Characterization of an Inactivated Whole‐Virus Bivalent Vaccine That Induces Balanced Protective Immunity Against Coxsackievirus A6 and A10 in Mice,” Vaccine 36, no. 46 (2018): 7095–7104, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2018.09.069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Caine, J. Fuchs, S. Das, C. Partidos, and J. Osorio, “Efficacy of a Trivalent Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease Vaccine Against Enterovirus 71 and Coxsackieviruses A16 and A6 in Mice,” Viruses 7, no. 11 (2015): 5919–5932, https://doi.org/10.3390/v7112916.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. S. Qian, Z. N. Wei, W. P. Jin, et al., “Efficacy of a Coxsackievirus A6 Vaccine Candidate in an Actively Immunized Mouse Model,” Emerging Microbes &amp; Infections 10, no. 1 (2021): 763–773, https://doi.org/10.1080/22221751.2021.1906755.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Shen, Z. Ku, Y. Zhou, et al., “Virus‐Like Particle‐Based Vaccine Against Coxsackievirus A6 Protects Mice Against Lethal Infections,” Vaccine 34, no. 34 (2016): 4025–4031, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.06.028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Zhang, W. Dai, C. Zhang, et al., “A Virus‐Like Particle‐Based Tetravalent Vaccine for Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease Elicits Broad and Balanced Protective Immunity,” Emerging Microbes &amp; Infections 7, no. 1 (2018): 1–12, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41426‐018‐0094‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. W. Chang, C. C. Liu, M. H. Lin, et al., “Generation of Murine Monoclonal Antibodies Which Cross‐Neutralize Human Enterovirus Genogroup B Isolates,” Journal of Virological Methods 173, no. 2 (2011): 189–195, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2011.02.003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Phanthong, J. Densumite, W. Seesuay, et al., “Human Antibodies to VP4 Inhibit Replication of Enteroviruses Across Subgenotypes and Serotypes, and Enhance Host Innate Immunity,” Frontiers in Microbiology 11 (2020), https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2020.562768.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Ren, X. Wang, L. Zhu, et al., “Structures of Coxsackievirus A16 Capsids With Native Antigenicity: Implications for Particle Expansion, Receptor Binding, and Immunogenicity,” Journal of Virology 89, no. 20 (2015): 10500–10511, https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.01102‐15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Du, Q. Mao, Y. Hu, et al., “A Potential Therapeutic Neutralization Monoclonal Antibody Specifically Against Multi‐Coxsackievirus A16 Strains Challenge,” Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics 15, no. 10 (2019): 2343–2350, https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2019.1565266.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Liu, J. Shi, X. Huang, et al., “A Murine Model of Coxsackievirus A16 Infection for Anti‐Viral Evaluation,” Antiviral Research 105 (2014): 26–31, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2014.02.015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Zhu, L. Xu, Q. Zheng, et al., “Discovery and Structural Characterization of a Therapeutic Antibody Against Coxsackievirus A10,” Science Advances 4, no. 9 (2018), https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aat7459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Yang, Q. Mao, S. Li, et al., “A Neonatal Mouse Model for the Evaluation of Antibodies and Vaccines Against Coxsackievirus A6,” Antiviral Research 134 (2016): 50–57, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2016.08.025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Cao, J. Han, Y. Deng, M. Yu, E. Qin, and C. Qin, “Presence of High‐Titer Neutralizing Antibodies Against Enterovirus 71 in Intravenous Immunoglobulin Manufactured From Chinese Donors,” Clinical Infectious Diseases 50, no. 1 (2010): 125–126, https://doi.org/10.1086/649012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Wang, H. Y. Lei, M. C. Huang, et al., “Modulation of Cytokine Production by Intravenous Immunoglobulin in Patients With Enterovirus 71‐Associated Brainstem Encephalitis,” Journal of Clinical Virology 37, no. 1 (2006): 47–52, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2006.05.009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Wang, T. S. Ho, C. F. Shen, and C. C. Liu, “Enterovirus 71, One Virus and Many Stories,” Pediatry Neonatology 49, no. 4 (2008): 113–115, https://doi.org/10.1016/S1875‐9572(08)60024‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. B. Planitzer, M. R. Farcet, R. I. Schiff, H. D. Ochs, and T. R. Kreil, “Neutralization of Different Echovirus Serotypes by Individual Lots of Intravenous Immunoglobulin,” Journal of Medical Virology 83, no. 2 (2011): 305–310, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.21980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Y. Wu, H. C. Wang, K. T. Wang, et al., “Neutralization of Five Subgenotypes of Enterovirus 71 by Taiwanese Human Plasma and Taiwanese Plasma Derived Intravenous Immunoglobulin,” Biologicals 41, no. 3 (2013): 154–157, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biologicals.2013.02.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Bigay, R. Le Grand, F. Martinon, and P. Maisonnasse, “Vaccine‐Associated Enhanced Disease in Humans and Animal Models: Lessons and Challenges for Vaccine Development,” Frontiers in Microbiology 13 (2022), https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.932408.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Y. Cao, D. Y. Dong, R. J. Liu, et al., “Human IgG Subclasses Against Enterovirus Type 71: Neutralization Versus Antibody Dependent Enhancement of Infection,” PLoS One 8, no. 5 (2013): e64024, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0064024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. S. Rathore, A. Sarker, and R. D. Gupta, “Recent Developments Toward Antibody Engineering and Affinity Maturation,” Protein and Peptide Letters 25, no. 10 (2018): 886–896, https://doi.org/10.2174/0929866525666180925142757.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. P. Goncalvez, R. E. Engle, M. Claire, R. H. Purcell, and C. J. Lai, “Monoclonal Antibody‐Mediated Enhancement of Dengue Virus Infection In Vitro and In Vivo and Strategies for Prevention,” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 104, no. 22 (2007): 9422–9427, https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0703498104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Bruhns, B. Iannascoli, P. England, et al., “Specificity and Affinity of Human Fcγ Receptors and Their Polymorphic Variants for Human IgG Subclasses,” Blood 113, no. 16 (2009): 3716–3725, https://doi.org/10.1182/blood‐2008‐09‐179754.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Dai, C. Zhang, X. Zhang, et al., “A Virus‐Like Particle Vaccine Confers Protection Against Enterovirus D68 Lethal Challenge in Mice,” Vaccine 36, no. 5 (2018): 653–659, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.12.057.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. B. Rosenfeld, E. Q. L. Shen, M. Melendez, N. Mishra, W. I. Lipkin, and V. R. Racaniello, “Cross‐Reactive Antibody Responses Against Nonpoliovirus Enteroviruses,” mBio 13, no. 1 (2022), https://doi.org/10.1128/mbio.03660‐21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhang, D. D. Moore, W. A. Nix, M. S. Oberste, and W. C. Weldon, “Neutralization of Enterovirus D68 Isolated From the 2014 US Outbreak by Commercial Intravenous Immune Globulin Products,” Journal of Clinical Virology 69 (2015): 172–175, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2015.06.086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Yoshida, M. Muramatsu, and H. Shimizu, “Neutralizing Activity of Intravenous Immune Globulin Products Against Enterovirus D68 Strains Isolated in Japan,” BMC Infectious Diseases 23, no. 1 (2023): 481, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879‐023‐08429‐z.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Hixon, P. Clarke, and K. L. Tyler, “Evaluating Treatment Efficacy in a Mouse Model of Enterovirus D68–Associated Paralytic Myelitis,” Journal of Infectious Diseases 216, no. 10 (2017): 1245–1253, https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jix468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Fohlman, K. Pauksen, B. Morein, U. Bjare, N. Ilbäck, and G. Friman, “High Yield Production of an Inactivated Coxsackie B3 Adjuvant Vaccine With Protective Effect Against Experimental Myocarditis,” Scandinavian Journal of Infectious Diseases—Supplementum 88 (1993): 103–108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. G. Larsson, T. Lakshmikanth, O. H. Laitinen, et al., “A Preclinical Study on the Efficacy and Safety of a New Vaccine Against Coxsackievirus B1 Reveals No Risk for Accelerated Diabetes Development in Mouse Models,” Diabetologia 58, no. 2 (2015): 346–354, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00125‐014‐3436‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. M. Stone, M. M. Hankaniemi, E. Svedin, et al., “A Coxsackievirus B Vaccine Protects Against Virus‐Induced Diabetes in an Experimental Mouse Model of Type 1 Diabetes,” Diabetologia 61, no. 2 (2018): 476–481, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00125‐017‐4492‐z.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. M. Stone, M. M. Hankaniemi, O. H. Laitinen, et al., “A Hexavalent Coxsackievirus B Vaccine Is Highly Immunogenic and Has a Strong Protective Capacity in Mice and Nonhuman Primates,” Science Advances 6, no. 19 (2020): eaaz2433, https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aaz2433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Hankaniemi, M. A. Baikoghli, V. M. Stone, et al., “Structural Insight into CVB3‐VLP Non‐Adjuvanted Vaccine,” Microorganisms 8, no. 9 (2020): 1287, https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms8091287.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Hankaniemi, V. M. Stone, T. Andrejeff, et al., “Formalin Treatment Increases the Stability and Immunogenicity of Coxsackievirus B1 VLP Vaccine,” Antiviral Research 171 (2019): 104595, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2019.104595.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Koho, M. R. L. Koivunen, S. Oikarinen, et al., “Coxsackievirus B3 VLPs Purified by Ion Exchange Chromatography Elicit Strong Immune Responses in Mice,” Antiviral Research 104 (2014): 93–101, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2014.01.013.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>