<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39531247</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>12</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Highly Sensitive and Specific Diagnosis of Enterovirus A71 by Reverse Transcription Multiple Cross-Displacement Amplification-Labeled Nanoparticles Biosensor.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70059</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70059</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.70059</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus A71 (EVA71) is a leading causative agent of hand, foot, and mouth disease, posing a significant threat to the health of young children, particularly in the Asia-Pacific region. Currently, there is no specific antiviral drug for EVA71 infection; therefore, early and rapid diagnosis is critical for disease prevention and control. Here, we report the development of a simple, rapid, and sensitive detection method for EVA71 infection using reverse transcription-multiple cross displacement amplification (RT-MCDA) combined with nanoparticle-based lateral flow biosensors (LFB). In the RT-MCDA system, a set of 10 primers was designed to target the highly conserved region of the VP1 gene of EVA71 and amplify the genes in an isothermal amplification device. The RT-MCDA amplification reaction products could then be identified by visual detection reagent (VDR) and LFB without the need for specialized equipment. The results demonstrated that the optimal reaction condition for the EVA71-RT-MCDA assay was 65℃ for 40 min. The EVA71-RT-MCDA assay could detect as low as 40 copies of plasmid and 50 copies of pseudotyped virus in a reaction. No cross-reaction was found between EVA71 strains and non-EVA71 strains. For 125 clinical anal swab samples, with EVA71-RT-MCDA assay, 30 samples were positive, which was in consistent with the the conventional real-time quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction assays. The entire procedure, including a 15-min specimen processing step, a 40-min MCDA reaction, and result reporting within 2 min, was completed in less than 60 min. In conclusion, the EVA71-RT-MCDA-LFB assay targeting the VP1 gene is a rapid, highly sensitive, simple, and specific test that could be widely applied in point-of-care settings and basic medical facilities in rural areas.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Jinzhi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Basic Medical Sciences, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Yuhong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical laboratory, The First People's Hospital of Guiyang, Guiyang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaomin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Bacterial Infectious Disease of Experimental Center, Guizhou Provincial Centre for Disease Control and Prevention, Guiyang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Jingrun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical laboratory, The First People's Hospital of Guiyang, Guiyang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6756-8301</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical laboratory, The First People's Hospital of Guiyang, Guiyang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>This study was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant number 82460393 and 81860594), Zhu ke he tong [2021]-43-25 and GCC[2023]030 from the Science and Technology Department of Guiyang City of Guizhou Province, Qian Ke He [2018]1094 and Qian Ke He Zhi Cheng [2021] yi ban 440 from Science and Technology Department of Guizhou Province and the project for the growth of young scientific and technological talents in ordinary Colleges and Universities in Guizhou Province (Qianjiaohe KY [2022] 231).</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015374" MajorTopicYN="Y">Biosensing Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012680" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sensitivity and Specificity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053758" MajorTopicYN="Y">Nanoparticles</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D021141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Nucleic Acid Amplification Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D048348" MajorTopicYN="N">Reverse Transcription</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D025202" MajorTopicYN="N">Molecular Diagnostic Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="N">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus A71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hand‐ foot and mouth disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lateral flow biosensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">reverse transcription‐multiple cross displacement amplification</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39531247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.70059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Picornaviridae Study Group, 2023 Parechovirus A., https://www.picornastudygroup.com/types/parechovirus/parechovirus_a.htm.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. González‐Sanz, D. Casas‐Alba, C. Launes, et al., “Molecular Epidemiology of an Enterovirus A71 Outbreak Associated with Severe Neurological Disease, Spain, 2016,” Eurosurveillance 24, no. 7 (2019): 1800089, https://doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2019.24.7.1800089.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Zhang, Y. Zhang, H. Li, and L. Liu, “Hand‐Foot‐and‐Mouth Disease‐Associated Enterovirus and the Development of Multivalent Hfmd Vaccines,” International Journal of Molecular Sciences 24, no. 1 (2022): 169, https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms24010169.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Li, Y. Sun, Y. Du, et al., “Characterization of Coxsackievirus A6‐ and Enterovirus 71‐Associated Hand Foot and Mouth Disease in Beijing, China, from 2013 to 2015,” Frontiers in Microbiology 7 (2016): 391, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2016.00391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Huang, Q. Liao, M. H. Ooi, et al., “Epidemiology of Recurrent Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease, China, 2008‐2015,” Emerging Infectious Diseases 24, no. 3 (2018): 432–442, https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2403.171303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Zhang, Y. Liu, F. Liu, et al., “Basic Reproduction Number of Enterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A16 and A6: Evidence from Outbreaks of Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease in China between 2011 and 2018,” Clinical Infectious Diseases 73, no. 9 (2021): e2552–e2559, https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/ciaa1853.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Xiao, Q. Zhu, F. Yang, et al., “The Impact of Enterovirus A71 Vaccination Program on Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease in Guangdong, China: A Longitudinal Surveillance Study,” Journal of Infection 85, no. 4 (2022): 428–435, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2022.06.020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Duan, C. Zhang, X. Wang, et al., “Molecular Epidemiology and Clinical Features of Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease Requiring Hospitalization after the Use of Enterovirus A71 Inactivated Vaccine in Chengdu, China, 2017‐2022: A Descriptive Study,” Emerging Microbes &amp; Infections 11, no. 1 (2022): 2510–2519, https://doi.org/10.1080/22221751.2022.2125346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Y. Wang, T. L. Lin, H. Y. Chen, and T. S. Lin, “Early and Rapid Detection of Enterovirus 71 Infection by an IgM‐Capture ELISA,” Journal of Virological Methods 119, no. 1 (2004): 37–43, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2004.02.017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Xu, Q. Yan, H. Wang, et al., “Performance of Detecting IgM Antibodies Against Enterovirus 71 for Early Diagnosis,” PLoS One 5, no. 6 (2010): e11388, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0011388.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. C. Chen, G. W. Chen, C. A. Hsiung, et al., “Combining Multiplex Reverse Transcription‐PCR and a Diagnostic Microarray to Detect and Differentiate Enterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A16,” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 44, no. 6 (2006): 2212–2219, https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.02393-05.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Zhang, J. Wang, Q. Yan, et al., “A One‐Step, Triplex, Real‐Time Rt‐PCR Assay for the Simultaneous Detection of Enterovirus 71, Coxsackie A16 and Pan‐Enterovirus in a Single Tube,” PLoS One 9, no. 7 (2014): e102724, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0102724.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Li, X. Shen, M. Li, et al., “Applicability of Duplex Real Time and Lateral Flow Strip Reverse‐ Transcription Recombinase Aided Amplification Assays for the Detection of Enterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A16,” Virology Journal 16, no. 1 (2019): 166, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12985-019-1264-z.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Lei, H. Wen, L. Zhao, and X. Yu, “Performance of Reversed Transcription Loop‐Mediated Isothermal Amplification Technique Detecting EV71: A Systematic Review with Meta‐Analysis,” BioScience Trends 8, no. 2 (2014): 75–83, https://doi.org/10.5582/bst.8.75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wang, Y. Wang, A. J. Ma, et al., “Rapid and Sensitive Isothermal Detection of Nucleic‐Acid Sequence by Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification,” Scientific Reports 5 (2015): 11902, https://doi.org/10.1038/srep11902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Huang, Y. Tong, X. Yang, et al., “Biosensor‐Based Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification for the Rapid Detection of Mycobacterium Leprae,” ACS Infectious Diseases 9, no. 10 (2023): 1932–1940, https://doi.org/10.1021/acsinfecdis.3c00213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Dou, L. Xie, M. Gao, and D. Liu, “Development of a Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification Combined with Nanoparticles‐Based Biosensor Assay for Rapid and Sensitive Detection of Streptococcus Pyogenes,” BMC Microbiology 24, no. 1 (2024): 51, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866-024-03189-5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wang, X. Zhao, J. Cheng, et al., “Development and Application of a Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification Combined with Nanoparticle‐Based Lateral Flow Biosensor Assay to Detect Candida Tropicalis,” Frontiers in Microbiology 12 (2021): 681488, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2021.681488.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Li, W. Jiang, J. Huang, et al., “Highly Sensitive and Specific Diagnosis of COVID‐19 by Reverse Transcription Multiple Cross‐Displacement Amplification‐Labelled Nanoparticles Biosensor,” European Respiratory Journal 56, no. 6 (2020): 2002060, https://doi.org/10.1183/13993003.02060-2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Chen, S. Dong, Y. Shi, et al., “Biosensor‐Based Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification Platform for Visual and Rapid Identification of Hepatitis C Virus,” Journal of Medical Virology 96, no. 3 (2024): e29481, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.29481.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhou, F. Xiao, J. Fu, et al., “Rapid Detection of Monkeypox Virus By Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification Combined with Nanoparticle‐Based Biosensor Platform,” Journal of Medical Virology 95, no. 2 (2023): e28479, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.28479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Feng, G. Xue, X. Cui, et al., “Development of a Loop‐Mediated Isothermal Amplification Method for Rapid and Visual Detection of Monkeypox Virus,” Microbiology Spectrum 10, no. 5 (2022): e0271422, https://doi.org/10.1128/spectrum.02714-22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Wang, J. M. Nicholls, F. Liu, et al., “Pulmonary and Central Nervous System Pathology in Fatal Cases of Hand Foot and Mouth Disease Caused By Enterovirus A71 Infection,” Pathology 48, no. 3 (2016): 267–274, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pathol.2015.12.450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Crabol, P. Pean, C. Mey, et al., “A Prospective, Comparative Study of Severe Neurological and Uncomplicated Hand, Foot and Mouth Forms of Paediatric Enterovirus 71 Infections,” International Journal of Infectious Diseases 59 (2017): 69–76, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2017.04.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Wang, Y. Chen, T. Xu, et al., “A Novel Method to Diagnose the Infection of Enterovirus A71 in Children by Detecting IgA from Saliva,” Journal of Medical Virology 92, no. 8 (2020): 1059–1064, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.25672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Upala, T. Apidechkul, W. Suttana, N. Kullawong, R. Tamornpark, and C. Inta, “Molecular Epidemiology and Clinical Features of Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease in Northern Thailand in 2016: A Prospective Cohort Study,” BMC Infectious Diseases 18, no. 1 (2018): 630, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879-018-3560-4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. L. Xiao, Y. Q. He, Y. G. Yu, et al., “Simultaneous Detection of Human ENterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A16 in Clinical Specimens By Multiplex Real‐Time PCR with an Internal Amplification Control,” Archives of Virology 154, no. 1 (2009): 121–125, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-008-0266-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. L. Tan, V. Tak Kwong Chow, S. H. Quak, W. C. A. Yeo, and C. L. Poh, “Development of Multiplex Real‐Time Hybridization Probe Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction for Specific Detection and Differentiation of Enterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A16,” Diagnostic Microbiology and Infectious Disease 61, no. 3 (2008): 294–301, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2008.02.009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. W. Jiao, Y. Wang, G. R. Wang, et al., “Development and Clinical Validation of Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification Combined with Nanoparticles‐Based Biosensor for Detection of Mycobacterium Tuberculosis: Preliminary Results,” Frontiers in Microbiology 10 (2019): 2135, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.02135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Zhao, L. Niu, L. Yan, et al., “Establishment and Application of Multiple Cross Displacement Amplification Coupled with Lateral Flow Biosensor (MCDA‐LFB) for Visual and Rapid Detection of Candida Albicans in Clinical Samples,” Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology 9 (2019): 102, https://doi.org/10.3389/fcimb.2019.00102.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>