<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39536108</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2375-2548</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>46</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Science advances</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Adv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Three modes of viral adaption by the heart.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>eadp6303</StartPage><MedlinePgn>eadp6303</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">eadp6303</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1126/sciadv.adp6303</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Viruses elicit long-term adaptive responses in the tissues they infect. Understanding viral adaptions in humans is difficult in organs such as the heart, where primary infected material is not routinely collected. In search of asymptomatic infections with accompanying host adaptions, we mined for cardio-pathogenic viruses in the unaligned reads of nearly 1000 human hearts profiled by RNA sequencing. Among virus-positive cases (~20%), we identified three robust adaptions in the host transcriptome related to inflammatory nuclear factor κB (NF-κB) signaling and posttranscriptional regulation by the p38-MK2 pathway. The adaptions are not determined by the infecting virus, and they recur in infections of human or animal hearts and cultured cardiomyocytes. Adaptions switch states when NF-κB or p38-MK2 is perturbed in cells engineered for chronic infection by the cardio-pathogenic virus, coxsackievirus B3. Stratifying viral responses into reversible adaptions adds a targetable systems-level simplification for infections of the heart and perhaps other organs.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Griffiths</LastName><ForeName>Cameron D</ForeName><Initials>CD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1280-3615</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shah</LastName><ForeName>Millie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shao</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-6134-372X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Borgman</LastName><ForeName>Cheryl A</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0009-2967-3501</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Janes</LastName><ForeName>Kevin A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8028-6138</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Genetics, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Adv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101653440</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2375-2548</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016328">NF-kappa B</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="UpdateOf"><RefSource>bioRxiv. 2024 Mar 29:2024.03.28.587274. doi: 10.1101/2024.03.28.587274</RefSource><PMID Version="1">38585853</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016328" MajorTopicYN="Y">NF-kappa B</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D032383" MajorTopicYN="Y">Myocytes, Cardiac</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009206" MajorTopicYN="N">Myocardium</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054884" MajorTopicYN="N">Host-Pathogen Interactions</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059467" MajorTopicYN="N">Transcriptome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006321" MajorTopicYN="N">Heart</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015398" MajorTopicYN="N">Signal Transduction</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000222" MajorTopicYN="N">Adaptation, Physiological</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003384" MajorTopicYN="N">Coxsackievirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39536108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11559625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.adp6303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tschope C., Ammirati E., Bozkurt B., Caforio A. L. P., Cooper L. T., Felix S. B., Hare J. M., Heidecker B., Heymans S., Hubner N., Kelle S., Klingel K., Maatz H., Parwani A. S., Spillmann F., Starling R. C., Tsutsui H., Seferovic P., Van Linthout S., Myocarditis and inflammatory cardiomyopathy: Current evidence and future directions. Nat. Rev. Cardiol. 18, 169–193 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7548534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33046850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhl U., Pauschinger M., Seeberg B., Lassner D., Noutsias M., Poller W., Schultheiss H. P., Viral persistence in the myocardium is associated with progressive cardiac dysfunction. Circulation 112, 1965–1970 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16172268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Why H. J., Meany B. T., Richardson P. J., Olsen E. G., Bowles N. E., Cunningham L., Freeke C. A., Archard L. C., Clinical and prognostic significance of detection of enteroviral RNA in the myocardium of patients with myocarditis or dilated cardiomyopathy. Circulation 89, 2582–2589 (1994).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8205668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golpour A., Patriki D., Hanson P. J., McManus B., Heidecker B., Epidemiological impact of myocarditis. J. Clin. Med. 10, 603 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7915005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33562759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper L. T. Jr., Keren A., Sliwa K., Matsumori A., Mensah G. A., The global burden of myocarditis: Part 1: A systematic literature review for the Global Burden of Diseases, Injuries, and Risk Factors 2010 study. Glob. Heart 9, 121–129 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25432122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pankuweit S., Klingel K., Viral myocarditis: From experimental models to molecular diagnosis in patients. Heart Fail. Rev. 18, 683–702 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23070541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollack A., Kontorovich A. R., Fuster V., Dec G. W., Viral myocarditis—Diagnosis, treatment options, and current controversies. Nat. Rev. Cardiol. 12, 670–680 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26194549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Aty H., Boye P., Zagrosek A., Wassmuth R., Kumar A., Messroghli D., Bock P., Dietz R., Friedrich M. G., Schulz-Menger J., Diagnostic performance of cardiovascular magnetic resonance in patients with suspected acute myocarditis: Comparison of different approaches. J. Am. Coll. Cardiol. 45, 1815–1822 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15936612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultz J. C., Hilliard A. A., Cooper L. T. Jr., Rihal C. S., Diagnosis and treatment of viral myocarditis. Mayo Clin. Proc. 84, 1001–1009 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2770911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19880690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chow L. H., Gauntt C. J., McManus B. M., Differential effects of myocarditic variants of coxsackievirus B3 in inbred mice. A pathologic characterization of heart tissue damage. Lab. Invest. 64, 55–64 (1991).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1990209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gambaryan A. S., Boravleva E. Y., Matrosovich T. Y., Matrosovich M. N., Klenk H. D., Moiseeva E. V., Tuzikov A. B., Chinarev A. A., Pazynina G. V., Bovin N. V., Polymer-bound 6′ sialyl-N-acetyllactosamine protects mice infected by influenza virus. Antiviral Res. 68, 116–123 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16214231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhl U., Pauschinger M., Noutsias M., Seeberg B., Bock T., Lassner D., Poller W., Kandolf R., Schultheiss H. P., High prevalence of viral genomes and multiple viral infections in the myocardium of adults with “idiopathic” left ventricular dysfunction. Circulation 111, 887–893 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15699250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahrholdt H., Wagner A., Deluigi C. C., Kispert E., Hager S., Meinhardt G., Vogelsberg H., Fritz P., Dippon J., Bock C. T., Klingel K., Kandolf R., Sechtem U., Presentation, patterns of myocardial damage, and clinical course of viral myocarditis. Circulation 114, 1581–1590 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17015795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumata R., Ito J., Takahashi K., Suzuki T., Sato K., A tissue level atlas of the healthy human virome. BMC Biol. 18, 55 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7269688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32493363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shnayder M., Nachshon A., Krishna B., Poole E., Boshkov A., Binyamin A., Maza I., Sinclair J., Schwartz M., Stern-Ginossar N., Defining the transcriptional landscape during cytomegalovirus latency with single-cell RNA sequencing. mBio 9, e00013–e00018 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29535194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoury J. D., Tannir N. M., Williams M. D., Chen Y., Yao H., Zhang J., Thompson E. J., Network T., Meric-Bernstam F., Medeiros L. J., Weinstein J. N., Su X., Landscape of DNA virus associations across human malignant cancers: Analysis of 3,775 cases using RNA-Seq. J. Virol. 87, 8916–8926 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3754044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23740984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang K. W., Alaei-Mahabadi B., Samuelsson T., Lindh M., Larsson E., The landscape of viral expression and host gene fusion and adaptation in human cancer. Nat. Commun. 4, 2513 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3806554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24085110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zapatka M., Borozan I., Brewer D. S., Iskar M., Grundhoff A., Alawi M., Desai N., Sultmann H., Moch H., Pathogens P., Cooper C. S., Eils R., Ferretti V., Lichter P.; PCAWG Consortium , The landscape of viral associations in human cancers. Nat. Genet. 52, 320–330 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8076016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32025001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Cancer Genome Atlas Network , Comprehensive genomic characterization of head and neck squamous cell carcinomas. Nature 517, 576–582 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4311405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25631445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira D. A., McMillan N. A. J., Idris A., Genetic deletion of HPV E7 oncogene effectively regresses HPV driven oral squamous carcinoma tumour growth. Biomed. Pharmacother. 155, 113782 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36271562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GTEx Consortium , The GTEx Consortium atlas of genetic regulatory effects across human tissues. Science 369, 1318–1330 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7737656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32913098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C. F., Ni Y., Moravec C. S., Morley M., Ashley E. A., Cappola T. P., Margulies K. B., Tang W. H. W., Whole-transcriptome profiling of human heart tissues reveals the potential novel players and regulatory networks in different cardiomyopathy subtypes of heart failure. Circ. Genom. Precis. Med. 14, e003142 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7887094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33517678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinig M., Adriaens M. E., Schafer S., van Deutekom H. W. M., Lodder E. M., Ware J. S., Schneider V., Felkin L. E., Creemers E. E., Meder B., Katus H. A., Ruhle F., Stoll M., Cambien F., Villard E., Charron P., Varro A., Bishopric N. H., George A. L. Jr., Dos Remedios C., Moreno-Moral A., Pesce F., Bauerfeind A., Ruschendorf F., Rintisch C., Petretto E., Barton P. J., Cook S. A., Pinto Y. M., Bezzina C. R., Hubner N., Natural genetic variation of the cardiac transcriptome in non-diseased donors and patients with dilated cardiomyopathy. Genome Biol. 18, 170 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5598015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28903782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fairweather D., Cooper L. T. Jr., Blauwet L. A., Sex and gender differences in myocarditis and dilated cardiomyopathy. Curr. Probl. Cardiol. 38, 7–46 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4136454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23158412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manichaikul A., Mychaleckyj J. C., Rich S. S., Daly K., Sale M., Chen W. M., Robust relationship inference in genome-wide association studies. Bioinformatics 26, 2867–2873 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3025716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20926424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selitsky S. R., Marron D., Hollern D., Mose L. E., Hoadley K. A., Jones C., Parker J. S., Dittmer D. P., Perou C. M., Virus expression detection reveals RNA-sequencing contamination in TCGA. BMC Genomics 21, 79 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6986043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31992194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bock C. T., Klingel K., Kandolf R., Human parvovirus B19-associated myocarditis. N. Engl. J. Med. 362, 1248–1249 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20357294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreoletti L., Leveque N., Boulagnon C., Brasselet C., Fornes P., Viral causes of human myocarditis. Arch. Cardiovasc. Dis. 102, 559–568 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19664576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GTEx Consortium , The genotype-tissue expression (GTEx) project. Nat. Genet. 45, 580–585 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4010069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23715323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollio A. R., Fries A. C., Yang Y., Hughes J. J., Fung C. K., Conte M. A., Kuschner R. A., Collins N. D., Macias E. A., Hang J., Clustered cases of human adenovirus types 4, 7, and 14 infections in US Department of Defense beneficiaries during the 2018-2019 season. J. Med. Virol. 95, e28571 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36762593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhl U., Lassner D., Dorner A., Rohde M., Escher F., Seeberg B., Hertel E., Tschope C., Skurk C., Gross U. M., Schultheiss H. P., Poller W., A distinct subgroup of cardiomyopathy patients characterized by transcriptionally active cardiotropic erythrovirus and altered cardiac gene expression. Basic Res. Cardiol. 108, 372 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23934091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Linthout S., Elsanhoury A., Klein O., Sosnowski M., Miteva K., Lassner D., Abou-El-Enein M., Pieske B., Kuhl U., Tschope C., Telbivudine in chronic lymphocytic myocarditis and human parvovirus B19 transcriptional activity. ESC Heart Fail. 5, 818–829 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6165949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30099854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John C. R., Watson D., Russ D., Goldmann K., Ehrenstein M., Pitzalis C., Lewis M., Barnes M., M3C: Monte Carlo reference-based consensus clustering. Sci. Rep. 10, 1816 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7000518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32020004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Parmigiani G., Johnson W. E., ComBat-seq: Batch effect adjustment for RNA-seq count data. NAR Genom. Bioinform. 2, lqaa078 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7518324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33015620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Love M. I., Huber W., Anders S., Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2. Genome Biol. 15, 550 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4302049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25516281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramanian A., Tamayo P., Mootha V. K., Mukherjee S., Ebert B. L., Gillette M. A., Paulovich A., Pomeroy S. L., Golub T. R., Lander E. S., Mesirov J. P., Gene set enrichment analysis: A knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 102, 15545–15550 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1239896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16199517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaestel M., MAPKAP kinases–MKs–two’s company, three’s a crowd. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 7, 120–130 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16421520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman A. M., Steen C. B., Liu C. L., Gentles A. J., Chaudhuri A. A., Scherer F., Khodadoust M. S., Esfahani M. S., Luca B. A., Steiner D., Diehn M., Alizadeh A. A., Determining cell type abundance and expression from bulk tissues with digital cytometry. Nat. Biotechnol. 37, 773–782 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6610714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31061481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawano H., Kawai S., Nishijo T., Shirai T., Inagaki Y., Okada R., An autopsy case of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy with pathological findings suggesting chronic myocarditis. Jpn. Heart J. 35, 95–105 (1994).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8201786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsumori A., Kawai C., An animal model of congestive (dilated) cardiomyopathy: Dilatation and hypertrophy of the heart in the chronic stage in DBA/2 mice with myocarditis caused by encephalomyocarditis virus. Circulation 66, 355–360 (1982).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6212162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu D., Wang P., Yang J., Qian Q., Li M., Wei L., Xu W., Gr-1+ cells other than Ly6G+ neutrophils limit virus replication and promote myocardial inflammation and fibrosis following coxsackievirus B3 infection of mice. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 8, 157 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5962688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29868513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kenney A. D., McMichael T. M., Imas A., Chesarino N. M., Zhang L., Dorn L. E., Wu Q., Alfaour O., Amari F., Chen M., Zani A., Chemudupati M., Accornero F., Coppola V., Rajaram M. V. S., Yount J. S., IFITM3 protects the heart during influenza virus infection. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 116, 18607–18612 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6744864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31451661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindner D., Li J., Savvatis K., Klingel K., Blankenberg S., Tschope C., Westermann D., Cardiac fibroblasts aggravate viral myocarditis: Cell specific coxsackievirus B3 replication. Mediators Inflamm. 2014, 519528 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4211177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25374444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantri M., Hinchman M. M., McKellar D. W., Wang M. F. Z., Cross S. T., Parker J. S. L., De Vlaminck I., Spatiotemporal transcriptomics reveals pathogenesis of viral myocarditis. Nat. Cardiovasc. Res. 1, 946–960 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10035375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36970396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bachelier K., Biehl S., Schwarz V., Kindermann I., Kandolf R., Sauter M., Ukena C., Yilmaz A., Sliwa K., Bock C. T., Klingel K., Bohm M., Parvovirus B19-induced vascular damage in the heart is associated with elevated circulating endothelial microparticles. PLOS ONE 12, e0176311 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5439674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28531186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhl U., Pauschinger M., Schwimmbeck P. L., Seeberg B., Lober C., Noutsias M., Poller W., Schultheiss H. P., Interferon-β treatment eliminates cardiotropic viruses and improves left ventricular function in patients with myocardial persistence of viral genomes and left ventricular dysfunction. Circulation 107, 2793–2798 (2003).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12771005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim N. E., Januzzi J. L. Jr., Established and emerging roles of biomarkers in heart failure. Circ. Res. 123, 614–629 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30355136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Everett B. M., Cornel J. H., Lainscak M., Anker S. D., Abbate A., Thuren T., Libby P., Glynn R. J., Ridker P. M., Anti-inflammatory therapy with canakinumab for the prevention of hospitalization for heart failure. Circulation 139, 1289–1299 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30586730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heymans S., Pauschinger M., De Palma A., Kallwellis-Opara A., Rutschow S., Swinnen M., Vanhoutte D., Gao F., Torpai R., Baker A. H., Padalko E., Neyts J., Schultheiss H. P., Van de Werf F., Carmeliet P., Pinto Y. M., Inhibition of urokinase-type plasminogen activator or matrix metalloproteinases prevents cardiac injury and dysfunction during viral myocarditis. Circulation 114, 565–573 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16880329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunja-Smith Z., Morales A. R., Romanelli R., Woessner J. F. Jr., Remodeling of human myocardial collagen in idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy. Role of metalloproteinases and pyridinoline cross-links. Am. J. Pathol. 148, 1639–1648 (1996).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1861551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8623931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klappacher G., Franzen P., Haab D., Mehrabi M., Binder M., Plesch K., Pacher R., Grimm M., Pribill I., Eichler H. G., Glogar H. D., Measuring extracellular matrix turnover in the serum of patients with idiopathic or ischemic dilated cardiomyopathy and impact on diagnosis and prognosis. Am. J. Cardiol. 75, 913–918 (1995).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7733000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson M. M., Nesti C., Palenzuela L., Walker W. F., Hernandez E., Protas L., Hirano M., Isaac N. D., Novel cell lines derived from adult human ventricular cardiomyocytes. J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol. 39, 133–147 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15913645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garmaroudi F. S., Marchant D., Hendry R., Luo H., Yang D., Ye X., Shi J., McManus B. M., Coxsackievirus B3 replication and pathogenesis. Future Microbiol. 10, 629–653 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25865198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim K.-S., Tracy S., Tapprich W., Bailey J., Lee C.-K., Kim K., Barry W. H., Chapman N. M., 5’-Terminal deletions occur in coxsackievirus B3 during replication in murine hearts and cardiac myocyte cultures and correlate with encapsidation of negative-strand viral RNA. J. Virol. 79, 7024–7041 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1112132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15890942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouin A., Gretteau P. A., Wehbe M., Renois F., N’Guyen Y., Leveque N., Vu M. N., Tracy S., Chapman N. M., Bruneval P., Fornes P., Semler B. L., Andreoletti L., Enterovirus persistence in cardiac cells of patients with idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy is linked to 5′ terminal genomic RNA-deleted viral populations with viral-encoded proteinase activities. Circulation 139, 2326–2338 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6517084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30755025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reetoo K. N., Osman S. A., Illavia S. J., Cameron-Wilson C. L., Banatvala J. E., Muir P., Quantitative analysis of viral RNA kinetics in coxsackievirus B3-induced murine myocarditis: Biphasic pattern of clearance following acute infection, with persistence of residual viral RNA throughout and beyond the inflammatory phase of disease. J. Gen. Virol. 81, 2755–2762 (2000).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11038389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muckelbauer J. K., Kremer M., Minor I., Tong L., Zlotnick A., Johnson J. E., Rossmann M. G., Structure determination of coxsackievirus B3 to 3.5 A resolution. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr. 51, 871–887 (1995).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15299757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muckelbauer J. K., Kremer M., Minor I., Diana G., Dutko F. J., Groarke J., Pevear D. C., Rossmann M. G., The structure of coxsackievirus B3 at 3.5 A resolution. Structure 3, 653–667 (1995).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8591043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercurio F., Zhu H., Murray B. W., Shevchenko A., Bennett B. L., Li J., Young D. B., Barbosa M., Mann M., Manning A., Rao A., IKK-1 and IKK-2: Cytokine-activated IκB kinases essential for NF-κB activation. Science 278, 860–866 (1997).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9346484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brockman J. A., Scherer D. C., McKinsey T. A., Hall S. M., Qi X., Lee W. Y., Ballard D. W., Coupling of a signal response domain in IκBα to multiple pathways for NF-κB activation. Mol. Cell. Biol. 15, 2809–2818 (1995).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC230512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7739562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson E. B., Yamada D. H., Elsaesser H., Herskovitz J., Deng J., Cheng G., Aronow B. J., Karp C. L., Brooks D. G., Blockade of chronic type I interferon signaling to control persistent LCMV infection. Science 340, 202–207 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3704950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23580528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teijaro J. R., Ng C., Lee A. M., Sullivan B. M., Sheehan K. C., Welch M., Schreiber R. D., de la Torre J. C., Oldstone M. B., Persistent LCMV infection is controlled by blockade of type I interferon signaling. Science 340, 207–211 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3640797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23580529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raingeaud J., Whitmarsh A. J., Barrett T., Derijard B., Davis R. J., MKK3- and MKK6-regulated gene expression is mediated by the p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase signal transduction pathway. Mol. Cell. Biol. 16, 1247–1255 (1996).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC231107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8622669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woronicz J. D., Gao X., Cao Z., Rothe M., Goeddel D. V., IκB kinase-β: NF-κB activation and complex formation with IκB kinase-α and NIK. Science 278, 866–870 (1997).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9346485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padget R. L., Zeitz M. J., Blair G. A., Wu X., North M. D., Tanenbaum M. T., Stanley K. E., Phillips C. M., King D. R., Lamouille S., Gourdie R. G., Hoeker G. S., Swanger S. A., Poelzing S., Smyth J. W., Acute adenoviral infection elicits an arrhythmogenic substrate prior to myocarditis. Circ. Res. 134, 892–912 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11003857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38415360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah M., Smolko C. M., Kinicki S., Chapman Z. D., Brautigan D. L., Janes K. A., Profiling subcellular protein phosphatase responses to coxsackievirus B3 infection of cardiomyocytes. Mol. Cell. Proteomics 16, S244–S262 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5393398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28174228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L., Li X., Chen M., Feng Y., Xiong C., The ACE2 expression in human heart indicates new potential mechanism of heart injury among patients infected with SARS-CoV-2. Cardiovasc. Res. 116, 1097–1100 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32227090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindner D., Fitzek A., Brauninger H., Aleshcheva G., Edler C., Meissner K., Scherschel K., Kirchhof P., Escher F., Schultheiss H. P., Blankenberg S., Puschel K., Westermann D., Association of cardiac infection with SARS-CoV-2 in confirmed COVID-19 autopsy cases. JAMA Cardiol. 5, 1281–1285 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7385672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32730555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park J., Foox J., Hether T., Danko D. C., Warren S., Kim Y., Reeves J., Butler D. J., Mozsary C., Rosiene J., Shaiber A., Afshin E. E., MacKay M., Rendeiro A. F., Bram Y., Chandar V., Geiger H., Craney A., Velu P., Melnick A. M., Hajirasouliha I., Beheshti A., Taylor D., Saravia-Butler A., Singh U., Wurtele E. S., Schisler J., Fennessey S., Corvelo A., Zody M. C., Germer S., Salvatore S., Levy S., Wu S., Tatonetti N. P., Shapira S., Salvatore M., Westblade L. F., Cushing M., Rennert H., Kriegel A. J., Elemento O., Imielinski M., Rice C. M., Borczuk A. C., Meydan C., Schwartz R. E., Mason C. E., System-wide transcriptome damage and tissue identity loss in COVID-19 patients. Cell. Rep. Med. 3, 100522 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8784611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35233546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frere J. J., Serafini R. A., Pryce K. D., Zazhytska M., Oishi K., Golynker I., Panis M., Zimering J., Horiuchi S., Hoagland D. A., Moller R., Ruiz A., Kodra A., Overdevest J. B., Canoll P. D., Borczuk A. C., Chandar V., Bram Y., Schwartz R., Lomvardas S., Zachariou V., tenOever B. R., SARS-CoV-2 infection in hamsters and humans results in lasting and unique systemic perturbations after recovery. Sci. Transl. Med. 14, eabq3059 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9210449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35857629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon J. W., Shaw J. A., Kirshenbaum L. A., Multiple facets of NF-κB in the heart: To be or not to NF-κB. Circ. Res. 108, 1122–1132 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21527742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawai T., Akira S., Toll-like receptor and RIG-I-like receptor signaling. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 1143, 1–20 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19076341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun S. C., Ganchi P. A., Ballard D. W., Greene W. C., NF-κβ controls expression of inhibitor IκBα: Evidence for an inducible autoregulatory pathway. Science 259, 1912–1915 (1993).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8096091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fagerlund R., Behar M., Fortmann K. T., Lin Y. E., Vargas J. D., Hoffmann A., Anatomy of a negative feedback loop: The case of IκBα. J. R. Soc. Interface 12, 20150262 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4614452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26311312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zechner D., Thuerauf D. J., Hanford D. S., McDonough P. M., Glembotski C. C., A role for the p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway in myocardial cell growth, sarcomeric organization, and cardiac-specific gene expression. J. Cell Biol. 139, 115–127 (1997).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2139826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9314533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janes K. A., Gaudet S., Albeck J. G., Nielsen U. B., Lauffenburger D. A., Sorger P. K., The response of human epithelial cells to TNF involves an inducible autocrine cascade. Cell 124, 1225–1239 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16564013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Xia Z., Tang W., Sun Y., Wu Y., Kwok H. F., Sun F., Cao Z., p38 activation and viral infection. Expert Rev. Mol. Med. 24, e4 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35060846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong J., Si X., Angeles A., Zhang J., Shi J., Fung G., Jagdeo J., Wang T., Zhong Z., Jan E., Luo H., Cytoplasmic redistribution and cleavage of AUF1 during coxsackievirus infection enhance the stability of its viral genome. FASEB J. 27, 2777–2787 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23572232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molleston J. M., Sabin L. R., Moy R. H., Menghani S. V., Rausch K., Gordesky-Gold B., Hopkins K. C., Zhou R., Jensen T. H., Wilusz J. E., Cherry S., A conserved virus-induced cytoplasmic TRAMP-like complex recruits the exosome to target viral RNA for degradation. Genes Dev. 30, 1658–1670 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4973295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27474443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rialdi A., Hultquist J., Jimenez-Morales D., Peralta Z., Campisi L., Fenouil R., Moshkina N., Wang Z. Z., Laffleur B., Kaake R. M., McGregor M. J., Haas K., Pefanis E., Albrecht R. A., Pache L., Chanda S., Jen J., Ochando J., Byun M., Basu U., Garcia-Sastre A., Krogan N., van Bakel H., Marazzi I., The RNA exosome syncs IAV-RNAPII transcription to promote viral ribogenesis and infectivity. Cell 169, 679–692.e14 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6217988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28475896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baeza-Raja B., Munoz-Canoves P., p38 MAPK-induced nuclear factor-κB activity is required for skeletal muscle differentiation: Role of interleukin-6. Mol. Biol. Cell 15, 2013–2026 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC379295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14767066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saccani S., Pantano S., Natoli G., p38-dependent marking of inflammatory genes for increased NF-κβ recruitment. Nat. Immunol. 3, 69–75 (2002).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11743587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao S., Baltimore D., The stability of mRNA influences the temporal order of the induction of genes encoding inflammatory molecules. Nat. Immunol. 10, 281–288 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2775040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19198593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoggins J. W., Wilson S. J., Panis M., Murphy M. Y., Jones C. T., Bieniasz P., Rice C. M., A diverse range of gene products are effectors of the type I interferon antiviral response. Nature 472, 481–485 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3409588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21478870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L., Sherry B., IFN-α expression and antiviral effects are subtype and cell type specific in the cardiac response to viral infection. Virology 396, 59–68 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2787694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19896686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera-Serrano E. E., DeAngelis N., Sherry B., Spontaneous activation of a MAVS-dependent antiviral signaling pathway determines high basal interferon-β expression in cardiac myocytes. J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol. 111, 102–113 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5600710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28822807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhl U., Lassner D., von Schlippenbach J., Poller W., Schultheiss H. P., Interferon-β improves survival in enterovirus-associated cardiomyopathy. J. Am. Coll. Cardiol. 60, 1295–1296 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23017536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimes J. M., Grimes K. V., p38 MAPK inhibition: A promising therapeutic approach for COVID-19. J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol. 144, 63–65 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7228886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32422320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirali G. S., Ni J., Chinnock R. E., Johnston J. K., Rosenthal G. L., Bowles N. E., Towbin J. A., Association of viral genome with graft loss in children after cardiac transplantation. N. Engl. J. Med. 344, 1498–1503 (2001).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11357152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson D. B., Balko J. M., Compton M. L., Chalkias S., Gorham J., Xu Y., Hicks M., Puzanov I., Alexander M. R., Bloomer T. L., Becker J. R., Slosky D. A., Phillips E. J., Pilkinton M. A., Craig-Owens L., Kola N., Plautz G., Reshef D. S., Deutsch J. S., Deering R. P., Olenchock B. A., Lichtman A. H., Roden D. M., Seidman C. E., Koralnik I. J., Seidman J. G., Hoffman R. D., Taube J. M., Diaz L. A. Jr., Anders R. A., Sosman J. A., Moslehi J. J., Fulminant myocarditis with combination immune checkpoint blockade. N. Engl. J. Med. 375, 1749–1755 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5247797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27806233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palaskas N., Lopez-Mattei J., Durand J. B., Iliescu C., Deswal A., Immune checkpoint inhibitor myocarditis: Pathophysiological characteristics, diagnosis, and treatment. J. Am. Heart Assoc. 9, e013757 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7033840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31960755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Easton A. J., Eglin R. P., The detection of coxsackievirus RNA in cardiac tissue by in situ hybridization. J. Gen. Virol. 69 ( Pt. 2), 285–291 (1988).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2828513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanson P. J., Liu-Fei F., Minato T. A., Hossain A. R., Rai H., Chen V. A., Ng C., Ask K., Hirota J. A., McManus B. M., Advanced detection strategies for cardiotropic virus infection in a cohort study of heart failure patients. Lab. Invest. 102, 14–24 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8488924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34608239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klingel K., Hohenadl C., Canu A., Albrecht M., Seemann M., Mall G., Kandolf R., Ongoing enterovirus-induced myocarditis is associated with persistent heart muscle infection: Quantitative analysis of virus replication, tissue damage, and inflammation. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 89, 314–318 (1992).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC48227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1309611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleiner M., Hooper L. V., Duerkop B. A., Evaluation of methods to purify virus-like particles for metagenomic sequencing of intestinal viromes. BMC Genomics 16, 7 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4308010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25608871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilcox A. H., Delwart E., Diaz-Munoz S. L., Next-generation sequencing of dsRNA is greatly improved by treatment with the inexpensive denaturing reagent DMSO. Microb. Genom. 5, e000315 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6927307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31738702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simon L. M., Karg S., Westermann A. J., Engel M., Elbehery A. H. A., Hense B., Heinig M., Deng L., Theis F. J., MetaMap: An atlas of metatranscriptomic reads in human disease-related RNA-seq data. Gigascience 7, giy070 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6025204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29901703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burch G. E., Sun S. C., Chu K. C., Sohal R. S., Colcolough H. L., Interstitial and coxsackievirus B myocarditis in infants and children. A comparative histologic and immunofluorescent study of 50 autopsied hearts. JAMA 203, 1–8 (1968).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4864516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altmae S., Molina N. M., Sola-Leyva A., Omission of non-poly(A) viral transcripts from the tissue level atlas of the healthy human virome. BMC Biol. 18, 179 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7690156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33239005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordey S., Laubscher F., Hartley M. A., Junier T., Keitel K., Docquier M., Guex N., Iseli C., Vieille G., Le Mercier P., Gleizes A., Samaka J., Mlaganile T., Kagoro F., Masimba J., Said Z., Temba H., Elbanna G. H., Tapparel C., Zanella M. C., Xenarios I., Fellay J., D’Acremont V., Kaiser L., Blood virosphere in febrile Tanzanian children. Emerg. Microbes. Infect. 10, 982–993 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8171259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33929935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pyoria L., Pratas D., Toppinen M., Hedman K., Sajantila A., Perdomo M. F., Unmasking the tissue-resident eukaryotic DNA virome in humans. Nucleic Acids Res. 51, 3223–3239 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10123123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36951096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohn L. B., Silva I. T., Oliveira T. Y., Rosales R. A., Parrish E. H., Learn G. H., Hahn B. H., Czartoski J. L., McElrath M. J., Lehmann C., Klein F., Caskey M., Walker B. D., Siliciano J. D., Siliciano R. F., Jankovic M., Nussenzweig M. C., HIV-1 integration landscape during latent and active infection. Cell 160, 420–432 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4371550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25635456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janovitz T., Wong S., Young N. S., Oliveira T., Falck-Pedersen E., Parvovirus B19 integration into human CD36+ erythroid progenitor cells. Virology 511, 40–48 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5623651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28806616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J. I., Herpesvirus latency. J. Clin. Invest. 130, 3361–3369 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7324166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32364538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Y., Stamminger T., Hearing P., E2F/Rb family proteins mediate interferon induced repression of adenovirus immediate early transcription to promote persistent viral infection. PLOS Pathog. 12, e1005415 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4726734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26809031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerr J. R., Pathogenesis of parvovirus B19 infection: Host gene variability, and possible means and effects of virus persistence. J. Vet. Med. B Infect. Dis. Vet. Public Health 52, 335–339 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16316396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Virgin H. W., Wherry E. J., Ahmed R., Redefining chronic viral infection. Cell 138, 30–50 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19596234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holland T. L., Baddour L. M., Bayer A. S., Hoen B., Miro J. M., Fowler V. G. Jr., Infective endocarditis. Nat. Rev. Dis. Primers. 2, 16059 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5240923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27582414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopacinski A. B., Sweatt A. J., Smolko C. M., Gray-Gaillard E., Borgman C. A., Shah M., Janes K. A., Modeling the complete kinetics of coxsackievirus B3 reveals human determinants of host-cell feedback. Cell Syst 12, 304–323.e13 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8112228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33740397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin K. J., Wall E. A., Zavzavadjian J. R., Santat L. A., Liu J., Hwang J. I., Rebres R., Roach T., Seaman W., Simon M. I., Fraser I. D., A single lentiviral vector platform for microRNA-based conditional RNA interference and coordinated transgene expression. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 103, 13759–13764 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1557799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16945906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm J. S., Zhao J. J., Yao J., Kim S. Y., Firestein R., Dunn I. F., Sjostrom S. K., Garraway L. A., Weremowicz S., Richardson A. L., Greulich H., Stewart C. J., Mulvey L. A., Shen R. R., Ambrogio L., Hirozane-Kishikawa T., Hill D. E., Vidal M., Meyerson M., Grenier J. K., Hinkle G., Root D. E., Roberts T. M., Lander E. S., Polyak K., Hahn W. C., Integrative genomic approaches identify IKBKE as a breast cancer oncogene. Cell 129, 1065–1079 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17574021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janes K. A., An analysis of critical factors for quantitative immunoblotting. Sci. Signal. 8, rs2 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4401487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25852189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H., Handsaker B., Wysoker A., Fennell T., Ruan J., Homer N., Marth G., Abecasis G., Durbin R., S., Genome project data processing, the sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools. Bioinformatics 25, 2078–2079 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2723002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19505943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewels P., Magnusson M., Lundin S., Kaller M., MultiQC: Summarize analysis results for multiple tools and samples in a single report. Bioinformatics 32, 3047–3048 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5039924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27312411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D., Paggi J. M., Park C., Bennett C., Salzberg S. L., Graph-based genome alignment and genotyping with HISAT2 and HISAT-genotype. Nat. Biotechnol. 37, 907–915 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7605509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31375807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Nie J., Sicotte H., Li Y., Eckel-Passow J. E., Dasari S., Vedell P. T., Barman P., Wang L., Weinshiboum R., Jen J., Huang H., Kohli M., Kocher J. P., Measure transcript integrity using RNA-seq data. BMC Bioinformatics 17, 58 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4739097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26842848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Garrison, G. Marth, Haplotype-based variant detection from short-read sequencing. (arXiv:1207.3907 [q-bio.GN] (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium , A global reference for human genetic variation. Nature 526, 68–74 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4750478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26432245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danecek P., Auton A., Abecasis G., Albers C. A., Banks E., DePristo M. A., Handsaker R. E., Lunter G., Marth G. T., Sherry S. T., McVean G., Durbin R.; 1000 Genomes Project Analysis Group , The variant call format and VCFtools. Bioinformatics 27, 2156–2158 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3137218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21653522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purcell S., Neale B., Todd-Brown K., Thomas L., Ferreira M. A., Bender D., Maller J., Sklar P., de Bakker P. I., Daly M. J., Sham P. C., PLINK: A tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses. Am. J. Hum. Genet. 81, 559–575 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1950838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17701901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danecek P., Bonfield J. K., Liddle J., Marshall J., Ohan V., Pollard M. O., Whitwham A., Keane T., McCarthy S. A., Davies R. M., Li H., Twelve years of SAMtools and BCFtools. Gigascience 10, giab008 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7931819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33590861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson J. T., Thorvaldsdottir H., Wenger A. M., Zehir A., Mesirov J. P., Variant review with the integrative genomics viewer. Cancer Res. 77, e31–e34 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5678989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29092934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moustafa A., Xie C., Kirkness E., Biggs W., Wong E., Turpaz Y., Bloom K., Delwart E., Nelson K. E., Venter J. C., Telenti A., The blood DNA virome in 8,000 humans. PLOS Pathog. 13, e1006292 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5378407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28328962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Litvinukova M., Talavera-Lopez C., Maatz H., Reichart D., Worth C. L., Lindberg E. L., Kanda M., Polanski K., Heinig M., Lee M., Nadelmann E. R., Roberts K., Tuck L., Fasouli E. S., DeLaughter D. M., McDonough B., Wakimoto H., Gorham J. M., Samari S., Mahbubani K. T., Saeb-Parsy K., Patone G., Boyle J. J., Zhang H., Zhang H., Viveiros A., Oudit G. Y., Bayraktar O. A., Seidman J. G., Seidman C. E., Noseda M., Hubner N., Teichmann S. A., Cells of the adult human heart. Nature 588, 466–472 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7681775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32971526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durinck S., Spellman P. T., Birney E., Huber W., Mapping identifiers for the integration of genomic datasets with the R/Bioconductor package biomaRt. Nat. Protoc. 4, 1184–1191 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3159387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19617889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovaka S., Zimin A. V., Pertea G. M., Razaghi R., Salzberg S. L., Pertea M., Transcriptome assembly from long-read RNA-seq alignments with StringTie2. Genome Biol. 20, 278 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6912988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31842956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anders S., Huber W., Differential expression analysis for sequence count data. Genome Biol. 11, R106 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3218662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20979621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becht E., McInnes L., Healy J., Dutertre C. A., Kwok I. W. H., Ng L. G., Ginhoux F., Newell E. W., Dimensionality reduction for visualizing single-cell data using UMAP. Nat. Biotechnol. 37, 38–44 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30531897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stephens M., False discovery rates: A new deal. Biostatistics 18, 275–294 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5379932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27756721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Gennady, S. Vladimir, B. Nikolay, S. Boris, N. A. Maxim, S. Alexey, Fast gene set enrichment analysis. bioRxiv 060012 [Preprint] (2021); 10.1101/060012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/060012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liberzon A., Birger C., Thorvaldsdottir H., Ghandi M., Mesirov J. P., Tamayo P., The Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) hallmark gene set collection. Cell. Syst. 1, 417–425 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4707969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26771021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakheet T., Hitti E., Khabar K. S. A., ARED-Plus: An updated and expanded database of AU-rich element-containing mRNAs and pre-mRNAs. Nucleic Acids Res. 46, D218–D220 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5753209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29077946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rusinova I., Forster S., Yu S., Kannan A., Masse M., Cumming H., Chapman R., Hertzog P. J., Interferome v2.0: An updated database of annotated interferon-regulated genes. Nucleic Acids Res. 41, D1040–D1046 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3531205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23203888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sievers F., Wilm A., Dineen D., Gibson T. J., Karplus K., Li W., Lopez R., McWilliam H., Remmert M., Soding J., Thompson J. D., Higgins D. G., Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using Clustal Omega. Mol. Syst. Biol. 7, 539 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3261699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21988835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waterhouse A. M., Procter J. B., Martin D. M., Clamp M., Barton G. J., Jalview version 2—A multiple sequence alignment editor and analysis workbench. Bioinformatics 25, 1189–1191 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2672624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19151095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crooks G. E., Hon G., Chandonia J. M., Brenner S. E., WebLogo: A sequence logo generator. Genome Res. 14, 1188–1190 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC419797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15173120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller-Jensen K., Janes K. A., Brugge J. S., Lauffenburger D. A., Common effector processing mediates cell-specific responses to stimuli. Nature 448, 604–608 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17637676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>