<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39558236</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2334</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Analyzing prognosis and comparing predictive scoring systems for mortality of COVID-19 patients with liver cirrhosis: a multicenter retrospective study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1315</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1315</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12879-024-10223-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Limited research suggested that liver cirrhosis is an independent risk factor for severe COVID-19, leading to higher hospitalization and mortality rates. This study aimed to identify the prognostic factors and validate scoring systems for predicting mortality in COVID-19 patients with liver cirrhosis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This retrospective cohort study extracted electronic health records of patients with COVID-19 who visited the emergency department between April 2021 and September 2022. Adult COVID-19 patients with liver cirrhosis were included, excluding those aged &lt; 18 years and who did not require hospitalization. The primary outcome was in-hospital mortality. The effectiveness of the scoring systems were analyzed for COVID-19 in-house mortality prediction.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 1,368 adult COVID-19 patients with liver cirrhosis were included in this study. Compared with the survival group, the non-survival group had lower vital signs such as systolic blood pressure and blood oxygen saturation, higher levels of white blood cells, creatinine, bilirubin, and C-reactive protein, and longer prothrombin time. Higher rates of intubation, oxygen use, and dexamethasone use were observed in the non-survivor group. The WHO ordinal scale, MELD, and MELD-Na scores showed good predictive ability for in-hospital mortality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The WHO ordinal scale showed the best performance in predicting mortality in patients with cirrhosis and COVID-19. MELD and MELD-Na scores were also found good performance for mortality prediction. Coagulation function, intubation, and dexamethasone administration were the most significant prognostic factors.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Shou-Yen</ForeName><Initials>SY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Chang Gung University College of Medicine, No. 5 Fushing St., Gueishan Shiang, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate Institute of Management, College of Management, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ng</LastName><ForeName>Chip-Jin</ForeName><Initials>CJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Chang Gung University College of Medicine, No. 5 Fushing St., Gueishan Shiang, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Yan-Bo</ForeName><Initials>YB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Chang Gung University College of Medicine, No. 5 Fushing St., Gueishan Shiang, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lo</LastName><ForeName>Hsiang-Yun</ForeName><Initials>HY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Chang Gung University College of Medicine, No. 5 Fushing St., Gueishan Shiang, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan. hsiangyunlo@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016448">Multicenter Study</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968551</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2334</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008103" MajorTopicYN="Y">Liver Cirrhosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011379" MajorTopicYN="N">Prognosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017052" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hospital Mortality</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012720" MajorTopicYN="N">Severity of Illness Index</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012307" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Liver cirrhosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MELD score</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MELD-Na score</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mortality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">WHO ordinal scale</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Human ethics approval</b> The study was approved by the institutional review board of the Chang-Gung Memorial hospital, Taiwan (IRB no. 202301643B0). This is a retrospective study conducted from de-identified database and informed consent of participation is waived by the Institutional Review Board of CGMH, Taiwan. <b>Consent to participate</b> This is a retrospective study conducted from de-identified database and informed consent of participation is waived by the Institutional Review Board of CGMH, Taiwan (IRB no. 202301643B0). <b>Competing interests</b> The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39558236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-024-10223-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12879-024-10223-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Stokes EK, Zambrano LD, Anderson KN, Marder EP, Raz KM, El Burai Felix S, Tie Y, Fullerton KE. Coronavirus Disease 2019 Case Surveillance - United States, January 22-May 30, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020;69(24):759–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6924e2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32555134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7302472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Number of COVID-19 deaths reported to WHO. (cumulative total) [ https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/deaths?n=c ]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan WJ, Ni ZY, Hu Y, Liang WH, Ou CQ, He JX, Liu L, Shan H, Lei CL, Hui DSC, et al. Clinical characteristics of Coronavirus Disease 2019 in China. N Engl J Med. 2020;382(18):1708–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2002032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32109013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chams N, Chams S, Badran R, Shams A, Araji A, Raad M, Mukhopadhyay S, Stroberg E, Duval EJ, Barton LM, et al. COVID-19: a multidisciplinary review. Front Public Health. 2020;8:383.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.00383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32850602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7403483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ginès P, Krag A, Abraldes JG, Solà E, Fabrellas N, Kamath PS. Liver cirrhosis. Lancet. 2021;398(10308):1359–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)01374-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34543610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhary NS, Dhampalwar S, Saraf N, Soin AS. Outcomes of COVID-19 in patients with cirrhosis or liver transplantation. J Clin Exp Hepatol. 2021;11(6):713–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jceh.2021.05.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33994708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8112901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P, Kumar A, Anikhindi S, Bansal N, Singla V, Shivam K, Arora A. Effect of COVID-19 on pre-existing liver disease: what hepatologist should know? J Clin Exp Hepatol. 2021;11(4):484–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jceh.2020.12.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33398223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai MS, Lin MH, Lee CP, Yang YH, Chen WC, Chang GH, Tsai YT, Chen PC, Tsai YH. Chang Gung Research Database: a multi-institutional database consisting of original medical records. Biomed J. 2017;40(5):263–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bj.2017.08.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29179881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6138604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio-Rivas M, Mora-Luján JM, Formiga F, Arévalo-Cañas C, Lebrón Ramos JM, Villalba García MV, Fonseca Aizpuru EM, Díez-Manglano J, Arnalich Fernández F, Romero Cabrera JL, et al. WHO Ordinal Scale and inflammation risk categories in COVID-19. Comparative study of the Severity scales. J Gen Intern Med. 2022;37(8):1980–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-022-07511-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35396659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8992782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio-Rivas M, Corbella X, Formiga F, Menéndez Fernández E, Martín Escalante MD, Baños Fernández I, Arnalich Fernández F, Del Corral-Beamonte E, Lalueza A, Parra Virto A et al. Risk categories in COVID-19 based on degrees of inflammation: data on more than 17,000 patients from the Spanish SEMI-COVID-19 Registry. J Clin Med 2021, 10(10).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamath PS, Wiesner RH, Malinchoc M, Kremers W, Therneau TM, Kosberg CL, D’Amico G, Dickson ER, Kim WR. A model to predict survival in patients with end-stage liver disease. Hepatology. 2001;33(2):464–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/jhep.2001.22172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11172350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim WR, Biggins SW, Kremers WK, Wiesner RH, Kamath PS, Benson JT, Edwards E, Therneau TM. Hyponatremia and mortality among patients on the liver-transplant waiting list. N Engl J Med. 2008;359(10):1018–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0801209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18768945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4374557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernardi M, Moreau R, Angeli P, Schnabl B, Arroyo V. Mechanisms of decompensation and organ failure in cirrhosis: from peripheral arterial vasodilation to systemic inflammation hypothesis. J Hepatol. 2015;63(5):1272–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2015.07.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26192220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middleton P, Hsu C, Lythgoe MP. Clinical outcomes in COVID-19 and cirrhosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies. BMJ Open Gastroenterol 2021, 8(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chai X, Hu L, Zhang Y, Han W, Lu Z, Ke A, Zhou J, Shi G, Fang N, Fan J. Specific ACE2 expression in cholangiocytes may cause liver damage after 2019-nCoV infection. biorxiv 2020:2020.2002. 2003.931766.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grace JA, Casey S, Burrell LM, Angus PW. Proposed mechanism for increased COVID-19 mortality in patients with decompensated cirrhosis. Hepatol Int. 2020;14(5):884–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12072-020-10084-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32886332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>新型冠狀病毒(SARS-CoV-2.)感染臨床處置指引 [ https://www.cdc.gov.tw/Category/Page/xCSwc5oznwcqunujPc-qmQ ]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IDSA Guidelines on the Treatment and Management of Patients with COVID-19. [ https://www.idsociety.org/practice-guideline/covid-19-guideline-treatment-and-management/#Recommendations7-9:Glucocorticoids]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tobin MJ. Basing Respiratory Management of COVID-19 on physiological principles. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2020;201(11):1319–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.202004-1076ED</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32281885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7258630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tobin MJ, Laghi F, Jubran A. Caution about early intubation and mechanical ventilation in COVID-19. Ann Intensive Care. 2020;10(1):78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13613-020-00692-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32519064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7281696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Said A, Williams J, Holden J, Remington P, Gangnon R, Musat A, Lucey MR. Model for end stage liver disease score predicts mortality across a broad spectrum of liver disease. J Hepatol. 2004;40(6):897–903.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2004.02.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15158328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsoris A, Marlar CA. Use of the child pugh score in Liver Disease. edn. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing Copyright © 2023. StatPearls Publishing LLC.; 2023. StatPearls.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marjot T, Moon AM, Cook JA, Abd-Elsalam S, Aloman C, Armstrong MJ, Pose E, Brenner EJ, Cargill T, Catana MA, et al. Outcomes following SARS-CoV-2 infection in patients with chronic liver disease: an international registry study. J Hepatol. 2021;74(3):567–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2020.09.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33035628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu PJ, Feng IC, Lai CC, Ho CH, Kan WC, Sheu MJ, Kuo HT. The mortality of hospitalized patients with COVID-19 and non-cirrhotic chronic liver disease: a retrospective multi-center study. PeerJ. 2023;11:e16582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.16582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38077441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10702333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Nafea HM, Al-Qahtani MT, Al Gahtani FH, Tabassum H. Blood coagulation, risk factors and associated complications in COVID-19 patients in Saudi Arabia: a retrospective cohort study. Med (Baltim). 2023;102(43):e35621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000035621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alizad G, Ayatollahi AA, Shariati Samani A, Samadizadeh S, Aghcheli B, Rajabi A, Nakstad B, Tahamtan A. Hematological and Biochemical Laboratory Parameters in COVID-19 Patients: A Retrospective Modeling Study of Severity and Mortality Predictors. Biomed Res Int 2023, 2023:7753631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu ML, Chen PJ, Dai CY, Hu TH, Huang CF, Huang YH, Hung CH, Lin CY, Liu CH, Liu CJ, et al. 2020 Taiwan consensus statement on the management of hepatitis C: part (I) general population. J Formos Med Assoc. 2020;119(6):1019–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfma.2020.04.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32359879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wait S, Chen DS. Towards the eradication of hepatitis B in Taiwan. Kaohsiung J Med Sci. 2012;28(1):1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.kjms.2011.10.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22226055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhont S, Derom E, Van Braeckel E, Depuydt P, Lambrecht BN. The pathophysiology of ‘happy’ hypoxemia in COVID-19. Respir Res. 2020;21(1):198.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12931-020-01462-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32723327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7385717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malinchoc M, Kamath PS, Gordon FD, Peine CJ, Rank J, ter Borg PC. A model to predict poor survival in patients undergoing transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunts. Hepatology. 2000;31(4):864–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/he.2000.5852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10733541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiesner R, Edwards E, Freeman R, Harper A, Kim R, Kamath P, Kremers W, Lake J, Howard T, Merion RM, et al. Model for end-stage liver disease (MELD) and allocation of donor livers. Gastroenterology. 2003;124(1):91–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/gast.2003.50016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12512033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luca A, Angermayr B, Bertolini G, Koenig F, Vizzini G, Ploner M, Peck-Radosavljevic M, Gridelli B, Bosch J. An integrated MELD model including serum sodium and age improves the prediction of early mortality in patients with cirrhosis. Liver Transpl. 2007;13(8):1174–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/lt.21197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17663415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Londoño MC, Cárdenas A, Guevara M, Quintó L, de Las Heras D, Navasa M, Rimola A, Garcia-Valdecasas JC, Arroyo V, Ginès P. MELD score and serum sodium in the prediction of survival of patients with cirrhosis awaiting liver transplantation. Gut. 2007;56(9):1283–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/gut.2006.102764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17452425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">1954951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Haan L, Ten Wolde M, Beudel M, Olde Engberink RHG, Appelman B, Haspels-Hogervorst EK, Rusch D, van den Gritters NC, Simsek S, Paternotte N, et al. What is the aetiology of dysnatraemia in COVID-19 and how is this related to outcomes in patients admitted during earlier and later COVID-19 waves? A multicentre, retrospective observational study in 11 Dutch hospitals. BMJ Open. 2023;13(11):e075232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-075232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37963704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10649520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman FU, Rehan ST, Rind BJ, Valliani K, Asghar MS, Omair F. Hyponatremia causing factors and its association with disease severity and length of stay in COVID-19 patients: a retrospective study from tertiary care hospital. Med (Baltim). 2023;102(45):e35920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000035920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gheorghe G, Ilie M, Bungau S, Stoian AMP, Bacalbasa N, Diaconu CC. Is there a relationship between COVID-19 and Hyponatremia? Med (Kaunas) 2021, 57(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousaf Z, Al-Shokri SD, Al-Soub H, Mohamed MFH. COVID-19-associated SIADH: a clue in the times of pandemic! Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2020;318(6):E882–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00178.2020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32396497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7276977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Moore MJ, Vasilieva N, Sui J, Wong SK, Berne MA, Somasundaran M, Sullivan JL, Luzuriaga K, Greenough TC, et al. Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 is a functional receptor for the SARS coronavirus. Nature. 2003;426(6965):450–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature02145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14647384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7095016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muaddi L, Ledgerwood C, Sheridan R, Dumont T, Nashar K. Acute renal failure and its complications, indications for Emergent Dialysis, and Dialysis modalities. Crit Care Nurs Q. 2022;45(3):258–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CNQ.0000000000000410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35617092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valizadeh R, Baradaran A, Mirzazadeh A, Bhaskar L. Coronavirus-nephropathy; renal involvement in COVID-19. J Ren Inj Prev. 2020;9(2):e18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34172/jrip.2020.18</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt RH, East JE, Lanas A, Malfertheiner P, Satsangi J, Scarpignato C, Webb GJ. COVID-19 and gastrointestinal disease: implications for the gastroenterologist. Dig Dis. 2021;39(2):119–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000512152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33040064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiersinga WJ, Rhodes A, Cheng AC, Peacock SJ, Prescott HC. Pathophysiology, transmission, diagnosis, and treatment of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19): a review. JAMA. 2020;324(8):782–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.12839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32648899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moga TV, Foncea C, Bende R, Popescu A, Burdan A, Heredea D, Danilă M, Miutescu B, Ratiu I, Bizerea-Moga TO et al. Impact of COVID-19 on patients with decompensated liver cirrhosis. Diagnostics (Basel) 2023, 13(4).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sproston NR, Ashworth JJ. Role of C-Reactive protein at sites of inflammation and infection. Front Immunol. 2018;9:754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.00754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29706967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5908901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Knovich MA, Coffman LG, Torti FM, Torti SV. Serum ferritin: past, present and future. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2010;1800(8):760–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2010.03.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20304033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2893236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>