<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39556297</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-3432</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of autism and developmental disorders</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Autism Dev Disord</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Determinants of Positive Evolution of Symptoms in Children with Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD) during the COVID-19 Lockdown in the Democratic Republic of Congo. (DRC).</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10803-024-06621-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Lockdown imposed by the COVID 19 pandemic increased the time families spent together at home. A negative impact of the lock-down on children with autism has been reported. Few studies described the positive impact of parents' presence on the severity of their children's autism symptoms during lockdown. To describe the positive impact of the COVID-19 lockdown on the evolution of Children' Symptoms with autism and parents' emotional status and to determine which variables had a positive or negative impact on the severity of autism features in Kinshasa. From April 15 to July 15, 2020, we analyzed the evolution of core symptoms of 68 children with autism and correlated these findings with the presence of a parent at home during lockdown. We performed multivariate logistic regression to assess the factors associated to autism symptoms improvement after adjustment by sex, age at ASD diagnosis, education, parent occupation, child's occupancy time, presence of parent's depression, and presence of comorbidities and core symptoms in children. Parents reported ASD symptom improvement in 42.6% of children. Factors positively associate with ASD symptoms improvement were presence of a parent for more than 8 h per day, improvement of social communication and autonomy. In contrast, severe to moderate depression in parents and presence of main comorbidities in children were associated with more severe autistic symptoms in their children. The presence of a parent at home, improved child communication and autonomy improved autism symptoms. On the other hand, parental depression and comorbidities in children with ASD aggravated the symptoms during lockdown in Kinshasa/DRC. These findings emphasize the importance of the physical presence of parents as well as the length of time they spend with their children with ASD. In addition, they show that depressive feelings in parents and comorbidities in ASD have a negative impact in the severity of their symptoms during lockdown.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mpaka</LastName><ForeName>Davin Mbeya</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0002-4038-2827</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, the Neuro-Psycho-Pathological Center, University of Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), P.O. Box: 825, Kinshasa, XI DRC, Congo. davmpaka@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lukusa</LastName><ForeName>Luck</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre (RI-MUHC), Montreal, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Muchanga</LastName><ForeName>Sifa Marie Joelle</ForeName><Initials>SMJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Kinshasa, Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vogels</LastName><ForeName>Annick</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre of Human Genetics, University Hospital of Leuven, Leuven, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ndjukendi</LastName><ForeName>Ally Omba</ForeName><Initials>AO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, the Neuro-Psycho-Pathological Center, University of Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), P.O. Box: 825, Kinshasa, XI DRC, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mutonji</LastName><ForeName>Arsene Bukama</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Supérieur de Statistique de Lubumbashi, (ISS-L'shi), Lubumbashi, Democratic Republic of Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kavira</LastName><ForeName>Dorah Lwanzo</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International University of East Africa, Kampala, Uganda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nzuzi</LastName><ForeName>Julienne Managa</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, the Neuro-Psycho-Pathological Center, University of Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), P.O. Box: 825, Kinshasa, XI DRC, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Matonda-Ma-Nzuzi</LastName><ForeName>Thierry</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, the Neuro-Psycho-Pathological Center, University of Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), P.O. Box: 825, Kinshasa, XI DRC, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mampunza</LastName><ForeName>Samuel Ma-Miezi</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, the Neuro-Psycho-Pathological Center, University of Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), P.O. Box: 825, Kinshasa, XI DRC, Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mukau</LastName><ForeName>Joachim Ebwel</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Centre d'Evaluation et d'Intervention pour Enfants avec Handicap Mental et/ou Autisme (CEIEHMA), The National University of Education (UPN), Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Autism Dev Disord</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7904301</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0162-3257</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Autism spectrum disorder</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DRC</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lockdown</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parental depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parental presence at home</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Positive evolution of ASD symptoms</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39556297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10803-024-06621-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10803-024-06621-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>American Psychiatric Association (2013). Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (5th ed.). https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.books.9780890425596</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asbury, K., Fox, L., Deniz, E., Code, A., &amp; Toseeb, U. (2021). How is COVID-19 affecting the mental health of children with special educational needs and disabilities and their families? Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, 51(5), 1772–1780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10803-020-04577-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32737668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakare, M. O., &amp; Mounir, K. M. (2011). Autism spectrum disorders (ASD) in Africa: A Perspective African. Journal of Psychiatry, 14, 208–210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellomo, T. R., Prasad, S., Munzer, T., &amp; Laventhal, N. (2020). The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on children with autism spectrum disorders. Journal of Pediatric Rehabilitation Medicine, 13(3), 349–354. https://doi.org/10.3233/PRM-200740</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/PRM-200740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32986631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berard, M., Rattaz, C., Peries, M., Loubersac, J., Munir, K., &amp; Baghdadli, A. (2021). Impact of containment and mitigation measures on children and youth with SD during the COVID-19 pandemic: Report from the ELENA cohort. Journal of Psychiatric Research, 137, 73–80. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.02.041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.02.041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33662654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7898988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berry, D., &amp; O’Connor, E. (2010). Behavioral risk, teacher–child relationships, and social skill development across middle childhood: A child-by-environment analysis of change. Journal of Applied Developmental Psychology, 31(1), 1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.appdev.2009.05.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat, A. (2021). Analysis of the SPARK study COVID-19 parent survey: Early impact of the pandemic on access to services, child/ parent mental health, and benefts of online services. Autism Research, 14(11), 2454–2470. https://doi.org/10.1002/aur.2618</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/aur.2618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34591364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8578426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christensen, D. L., Braun, K. V. N., Baio, J., Bilder, D., Charles, J., Constantino, J. N., &amp; Lee, L. C. (2018). Prevalence and characteristics of autism spectrum disorder among children aged 8 years—autism and developmental disabilities monitoring. Network, 11 sites, United States, 2012. MMWR Surveillance Summaries, 65(13), 1. https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.ss6513a1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.ss6513a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6237390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung, G., Lanier, P., &amp; Wong, P. Y. J. (2022). Mediating effects of parental stress on harsh parenting and parent-child relationship during coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic in Singapore. Journal of Family Violence, 37(5), 801–812. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10896-020-00200-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10896-020-00200-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32895601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colizzi, M., Sironi, E., Antonini, F., Ciceri, M. L., Bovo, C., &amp; Zoccante, L. (2020). Psychosocial and behavioral impact of COVID-19 in autism spectrum disorder: An online parent surveys. Brain Sciences, 10(6), 341. https://doi.org/10.3390/brainsci10060341</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/brainsci10060341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32503172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7349059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dal Pai, J., Wolff, C. G., Aranchipe, C. S., Kepler, C. K., Dos Santos, G. A., Canton, L. A., de Carvalho, A. B., Richter, S. A., &amp; Nunes, M. L. (2022). COVID-19 pandemic and autism spectrum disorder, consequences to Children and adolescents - a systematic review. Review Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, 1–26. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40489-022-00344-4 . Advance online publication.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Renzo, M., Di Castelbianco, F. B., Vanadia, E., Petrillo, M., D’Errico, S., Racinaro, L., &amp; Rea, M. (2020). Parent-reported behavioural changes in Children with Autism Spectrum Disorder during the COVID-19 Lockdown in Italy. Continuity in Education, 1(1), –117. https://doi.org/10.5334/cie.20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eckes, T., Buhlmann, U., Holling, H. D., &amp; Möllmann, A. (2023). Comprehensive ABA-based interventions in the treatment of children with autism spectrum disorder - a meta-analysis. BMC Psychiatry, 23(1), 133. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-022-04412-</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-022-04412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36864429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9983163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eikeseth, S., Smith, T., Jahr, E., &amp; Eldevik, S. (2007). Outcome for children with autism who began intensive behavioral treatment between ages 4 and 7: A comparison controlled study. Behavior Modification, 31(3), 264–278. https://doi.org/10.1177/0145445506291396</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0145445506291396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17438342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elsabbagh, M., Divan, G., Koh, Y. J., Kim, Y. S., Kauchali, S., Marcín, C., Montiel-Nava, Patel, V., Paula, C. S., Wang, C., Yasamy, M. T., &amp; Fombonne, E. (2012). Global prevalence of autism and other pervasive developmental disorders. Autism Research: Official Journal of the International Society for Autism Research, 5(3), 160–179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/aur.239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22495912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eshraghi, A. A., Li, C., Alessandri, M., Messinger, D. S., Eshraghi, R. S., Mittal, R., et al. (2020). COVID-19: Overcoming the challenges faced by individuals with autism and their families. The Lancet Psychiatry, 7(6), 481–483. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30197-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30197-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32445682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7239613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghebreyesus, T. A. (2020). WHO Director-General’s opening remarks at the media briefng on COVID-19 - 11 March 2020. WHO Director-General’s Speeches.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldberg, D. P., &amp; Hillier, V. F. (1979). A scaled version of the General Health Questionnaire. Psychological Medicine, 9(1), 139–145. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291700021644</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0033291700021644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">424481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsiao, Y., Higgins, K., Pierce, T., Schaefer Whitby, P. J., &amp; Tandy, R. D. (2017). Parental stress, family quality of life, and family-teacher partnerships: Families of children with autism spectrum disorder. Research in Developmental Disabilities, 70, 152–162. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ridd.2017.08.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2017.08.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28942105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janssen, L. H. C., Kullberg, M. J., Verkuil, B., van Zwieten, N., Wever, M. C. M., van Houtum, L. A. E. M., Wentholt, W. G. M., &amp; Elzinga, B. M. (2020). Does the COVID-19 pandemic impact parents’ and adolescents’ well-being? An EMA-study on daily affect and parenting. PloS One, 15(10), e0240962. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0240962</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0240962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33064778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7567366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreysa, H., Schneider, D., Kowallik, A. E., Dastgheib, S. S., Doğdu, C., Kühn, G., Ruttloff, J. M., &amp; Schweinberger, S. R. (2022). Psychosocial and behavioral effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on children and adolescents with autism and their families: Overview of the literature and initial data from a multinational online survey. Healthcare, 10, 714. https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare10040714</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/healthcare10040714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35455891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9028372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levante, A., Petrocchi, S., Bianco, F., Castelli, I., Colombi, C., Keller, R., et al. (2021). Psychological impact of COVID-19 outbreaks on families of children with autism spectrum disorder and typically developing peers: An online survey. Brain Sci, 11, 808. https://doi.org/10.3390/brainsci11060808</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/brainsci11060808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34207173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8235600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lovaas, O. I., Koegel, R., Simmons, J. Q., &amp; Long, J. S. (1973). Some generalization and follow-up measures on autistic children in behavior therapy. Journal of Applied Behavior Analysis, 6(1), 131–165. https://doi.org/10.1901/jaba.1973.6-131</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1901/jaba.1973.6-131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16795385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">1310815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luiselli, J. K. (Ed.). (2017). Applied behavior analysis advanced guidebook: A manual. For professional practice. Elsevier Academic.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpaka, D. M., Okitundu, D. L., Ndjukendi, A. O., N’situ, A. M., Kinsala, S. Y., Mukau, J., Ngoma, E., Kashala-Abotnes, V. M., Ma-Miezi-Mampunza, E., Vogels, S., &amp; Steyaert, A., J (2016). Prevalence and comorbidities of autism among children referred to the outpatient clinics for neurodevelopmental disorders. The Pan African Medical Journal, 25, 82. https://doi.org/10.11604/pamj.2016.25.82.4151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11604/pamj.2016.25.82.4151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28292045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5324163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mumbardó-Adam, C., Barnet-López, S., &amp; Balboni, G. (2021). How have youth with autism spectrum disorder managed quarantine derived from COVID-19 pandemic?An approach to families’ perspectives. Research in Developmental Disabilities, 110(Mar). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ridd.2021.103860</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mutluer, T., Doenyas, C., &amp; Genc, H. A. (2020). Behavioral implications of the Covid-19 process for autism spectrum disorder, and individuals’ comprehension of and reactions to the pandemic conditions. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 11, 561882. https://doi.org/10. 3389/fpsyt.2020.561882. https://Www.Frontiersin.Org</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.561882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33304279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7701051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narzisi, A. (2020). Handle the autism spectrum condition during coronavirus (COVID-stay-at-home period: Ten tips for helping parents and caregivers of young children. Brain Science, 10(4), 207. https://doi.org/10.3390/brainsci10040207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/brainsci10040207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters-Scheffer, N., Didden, R., Korzilius, H., &amp; Sturmey, P. (2011). A meta-analytic study on the effectiveness of comprehensive ABA-based early intervention. Programs for children with autism spectrum disorders. Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders, 5(1), 60–69. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rasd.2010.03.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2010.03.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pickard, H., Rijsdijk, F., Happ´e, F., &amp; Mandy, W. (2017). Are social and communication. Difficulties a risk factor for the development of social anxiety? Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 56(4), 344–351. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2017.01.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2017.01.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28335879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5376399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pottie, C. G., Cohen, J., &amp; Ingram, K. M. (2009). Parenting a child with autism: Contextual factors associated with enhanced daily parental mood. Journal of Pediatric Psychology, 34(4), 419–429. https://doi.org/10.1093/jpepsy/jsn094</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jpepsy/jsn094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18794189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero, E., López-Romero, L., Domínguez-Álvarez, B., Villar, P., &amp; Gómez-Fraguela, J. (2020). Testing the effects of COVID-19 confinement in Spanish Children: The role of parents’ distress, emotional problems and specific parenting. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17(19), 6975.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17196975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32987641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7578923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sallows, G. O., &amp; Graupner, T. D. (2005). Intensive behavioral treatment for children with autism: Four-year outcome and predictors. American Journal of Mental Retardation: AJMR, 110(6), 417–438. https://doi.org/10.1352/0895-8017(2005)110[417IBTFCW]2.0.CO;2 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1352/0895-8017(2005)110[417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16212446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schopler, E., Reichler, R., &amp; Renner, B. R. (1993). Childhood autism rating scale (CARS). Western Psychological Services.Los Angeles.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sergi, L., Mingione, E., Ricci, M. C., Cavallaro, A., Russo, F., Corrivetti, G., Operto, F. F., &amp; Frolli, A. (2021). Autism, therapy, and COVID-19. Pediatric Reports, 13, 35–44. https://doi.org/10.3390/ pediatric13010005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pediatric13010005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33466265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7838872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spinelli, M., Lionetti, F., Pastore, M., &amp; Fasolo, M. (2020). Parents’ stress and children’s psychological problems in families facing the COVID-19 outbreak in Italy. Frontiers in Psychology, 11, 1713. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01713</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32719646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7350926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tokatly Latzer, I., Leitner, Y., &amp; Karnieli-Miller, O. (2021). Core experiences of parents of children with autism during the COVID-19 pandemic lockdown. Autism, 25(4), 1047–1059. https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361320984317</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1362361320984317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33435701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Steensel, F. J. A., &amp; Heeman, E. J. (2017). Anxiety levels in children with autism spectrum disorder: A meta-analysis. Journal of Child and Family Studies, 26(7), 1753–1767. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826-017-0687-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10826-017-0687-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28680259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5487760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>