<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39557345</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-3304</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Survey of ophthalmology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Surv Ophthalmol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association between retinal vessels caliber and systemic health: A comprehensive review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0039-6257(24)00138-3</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.survophthal.2024.11.009</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The unique nature of the retinal microvasculature that permits non-invasive visualization has garnered interest as a potential method for detecting microvascular alterations indicative of systemic diseases. This concept, supported by advancements in imaging technologies, has been increasingly validated by studies linking retinal microvasculature with systemic conditions such as diabetes, hypertension, and cerebrovascular disease. Structural changes in the retinal microvasculature are associated with cardiovascular risk factors, metabolic diseases, and are significant predictors of systemic hypertensive damage and mortality. Given that most systemic diseases present life-long burdens and complications if undetected or untreated, the development of diagnostic tools like retinal vascular imaging becomes important for early detection, monitoring of disease progression, and facilitating timely interventions. Technological advancements have enabled objective and accurate quantification of retinal microvascular characteristics. We consolidate current literature on retinal vascular changes across various systemic health conditions, including metabolic diseases, cerebrovascular diseases, pregnancy complications, systemic inflammatory conditions, leukemia, human immunodeficiency virus infection, and COVID-19. We also emphasizes the need for dynamic parameters, an understanding of 3-dimensional vascular architecture, and larger-scale longitudinal studies to elucidate the temporal relationship between retinal vascular changes and systemic diseases, helping shape future diagnostic and monitoring approaches.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Si Jin Vanessa</ForeName><Initials>SJV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, National Healthcare Group Eye Institute, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>FRCOphth</LastName><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, National Healthcare Group Eye Institute, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goh</LastName><ForeName>Ying Qi</ForeName><Initials>YQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lee Kong Chian School of Medicine, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rojas-Carabali</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, National Healthcare Group Eye Institute, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore; Lee Kong Chian School of Medicine, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore; Programme for Ocular Inflammation and Infection Translational Research (PROTON), Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cifuentes-González</LastName><ForeName>Carlos</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, National Healthcare Group Eye Institute, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore; Programme for Ocular Inflammation and Infection Translational Research (PROTON), Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheung</LastName><ForeName>Carol Y</ForeName><Initials>CY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programme for Ocular Inflammation and Infection Translational Research (PROTON), Singapore; Department of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arora</LastName><ForeName>Atul</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, Advanced Eye Centre, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de-la-Torre</LastName><ForeName>Alejandra</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programme for Ocular Inflammation and Infection Translational Research (PROTON), Singapore; Ophthalmology Interest Group, Neuroscience (NEUROS) Research Group,Neurovitae Research Center, Institute of Translational Medicine (IMT), Escuela de Medicina y Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad del Rosario, Bogotá, Colombia; Neuroscience Research Group (NEUROS), Neurovitae Center for Neuroscience, Institute of Translational Medicine (IMT), Escuela de Medicina y Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad del Rosario, Bogotá, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gupta</LastName><ForeName>Vishali</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programme for Ocular Inflammation and Infection Translational Research (PROTON), Singapore; Ophthalmology Interest Group, Neuroscience (NEUROS) Research Group,Neurovitae Research Center, Institute of Translational Medicine (IMT), Escuela de Medicina y Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad del Rosario, Bogotá, Colombia; Neuroscience Research Group (NEUROS), Neurovitae Center for Neuroscience, Institute of Translational Medicine (IMT), Escuela de Medicina y Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad del Rosario, Bogotá, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agrawal</LastName><ForeName>Rupesh</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, National Healthcare Group Eye Institute, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore; Lee Kong Chian School of Medicine, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore; Programme for Ocular Inflammation and Infection Translational Research (PROTON), Singapore; Singapore Eye Research Institute, Singapore; Duke NUS Medical School, Singapore. Electronic address: rupeshttsh@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Surv Ophthalmol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0404551</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0039-6257</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HIV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Microvasculature</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrovascular</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">imaging</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inflammation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">leukaemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metabolic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pregnancy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">retina</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">smoking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vessels</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.survophthal.2024.11.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0039-6257(24)00138-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>