<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553359</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1841-9038</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Maedica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Maedica (Bucur)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 among Physically Active and Physically Inactive Individuals.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>594</StartPage><EndPage>599</EndPage><MedlinePgn>594-599</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.26574/maedica.2024.19.3.594</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">COVID-19 was first reported in Wuhan, China, and subsequently spread worldwide. There were numerous restrictions on daily life activities, including lifestyles, social distancing, isolation and access to many forms of exercise and home confinement. All these activities have health benefits, as they enhance the immune system, which is the need of the hour during the COVID-19 pandemic. There is little data regarding the occurrence of COVID-19 among marathon runners, cyclists and yoga practitioners. The aim of the present study was to find the prevalence of COVID-19 among physically active and physically inactive individuals and to compare it among those groups.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIAL AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Physically active individuals were selected as per the Global Recommendations on Physical Activity for Health 2010, in the age group of 18-60 years, and included runners, yoga practitioners and cyclists from the Hyderabad club. A prevalidated questionnaire was circulated among the study groups through Google form. The data was analyzed statistically.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">There was a high proportion of persons affected by COVID-19 in the physically inactive group (75.75%) when compared to the active group (17.17%). The percentages of subjects who tested positive for COVID-19 were as follows: 16.16% cyclists, 29.29% runners and 27.27% yoga practitioners among the physically active individuals, and 51.51% of physically inactive subjects.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Physical activity acts as a barrier against COVID-19 infections and enhances the immune system. Therefore, it has to be prioritized by public health agencies and incorporated into routine medical care.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kalpana</LastName><ForeName>Medala</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Associate Professor, Department of Physiology, AIIMS Bibinagar, Hyderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Katta</LastName><ForeName>Roja</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Assistant Professor, CMR Institute of Medical Sciences, Hyderabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madhusudhan</LastName><ForeName>Umesh</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Assistant Professor, Department of Physiology, AIIMS Bibinagar, Hyderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gaur</LastName><ForeName>Archana</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Assistant Professor, Department of Physiology, AIIMS Bibinagar, Hyderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ganji</LastName><ForeName>Vidya</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Assistant Professor, Department of Physiology, AIIMS Bibinagar, Hyderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taranikanti</LastName><ForeName>Madhuri</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Additional Professor, Department of Physiology, AIIMS Bibinagar, Hyderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nitin</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Professor and Head, Department of Physiology, AIIMS Bibinagar, Hyderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kasturi</LastName><ForeName>Vasanth Kumar</ForeName><Initials>VK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tutor, College of Nursing, AIIMS Bibinagar, Hyderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016421">Editorial</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Romania</Country><MedlineTA>Maedica (Bucur)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101526930</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1841-9038</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: none declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11565149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26574/maedica.2024.19.3.594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Singhal T. A Review of Coronavirus Disease-2019 (COVID-19). Indian J Pediatr. 2020;87:281–286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7090728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32166607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai C-C, Shih T-P, Ko W-C, Tang H-J, Hsueh P-R. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19): The epidemic and the challenges. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2020;55:105924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32081636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur H, Singh T, Arya YK, Mittal S. Physical Fitness and Exercise During the COVID-19 Pandemic: A Qualitative Enquiry. Front Psychol. 2020;11:2943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7673425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33250827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amini H, Habibi S, Islamoglu AH, et al. COVID-19 pandemic-induced physical inactivity: the necessity of updating the Global Action Plan on Physical Activity 2018-2030. Environ Health Prev Med. 2021;26:32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7937363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33678154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunton GF, Do B, Wang SD. Early effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on physical activity and sedentary behaviour in children living in the U.S. BMC Public Health. 2020;20:1351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7472405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32887592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obasi C, Brown R, Ewers T, et al. Advantage of meditation over exercise in reducing cold and flu illness is related to improved function and quality of life. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2012;7:938–944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3582749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23170828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma K, Anand A, Kumar R. The role of Yoga in working from home during the COVID-19 global lockdown. Work. 2020;66:731–737.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32925134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cloosterman KLA, van Middelkoop M, Krastman P, de Vos R-J. Running behaviour and symptoms of respiratory tract infection during the COVID-19 pandemic: A large prospective Dutch cohort study. J Sci Med Sport. 2021;24:332–337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7575428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33189596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khammassi M, Ouerghi N, Said M, et al. Continuous Moderate-Intensity but Not High-Intensity Interval Training Improves Immune Function Biomarkers in Healthy Young Men. J Strength Cond Res. 2020;34:249–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30102685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubey S, Biswas P, Ghosh R, et al. Psychosocial impact of COVID-19. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2020;14:779–788.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7255207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32526627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad AR, Murad HR. The Impact of Social Media on Panic During the COVID-19 Pandemic in Iraqi Kurdistan: Online Questionnaire Study. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22:e19556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7238863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luan X, Tian X, Zhang H, et al. Exercise is a prescription for patients with various diseases. J Sport Health Sci. 2019;8:422–441.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6742679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31534817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C, Wang Y, Li X, et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet Lond Engl. 2020;395:497–506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu J, Ji P, Pang J, et al. Clinical characteristics of 3062 COVID-19 patients: A meta□analysis. J Med Virol. 2020;92:1902–1914.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32293716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cloosterman KLA, van Middelkoop M, Krastman P, de Vos R-J. Running behaviour and symptoms of respiratory tract infection during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Sci Med Sport. 2021;24:332–337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7575428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33189596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Global recommendations on physical activity for health. Geneva: World Health Organization. 2010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26180873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thivel D, Tremblay A, Genin PM, et al. Physical Activity, Inactivity, and Sedentary Behaviors: Definitions and Implications in Occupational Health. Front. Public Health. 2018;6:288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6182813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30345266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bull FC, Armstrong TP, Dixon T, et al. Physical inactivity, Comparative quantification of health risks: global and regional burden of disease attributable to selected major risk factors. Vol. 1. Geneva: World Health Organization. 2004, pp 729-882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thanamee S, Pinyopornpanish K, Wattanapisit A, et al. A population-based survey on physical inactivity and leisure time physical activity among adults in Chiang Mai, Thailand, 2014. Arch Public Health. 2017;75:41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5623978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29026542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collie S, Saggers RT, Bandini R, et al. Association between regular physical activity and the protective effect of vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 in a South African case-control study. Br J Sports Med. 2023;57:205–211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36280289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma W, Murray E, Nguyen LH, et al. Physical Activity, Sedentary Behavior, and Risk of Coronavirus Disease 2019. Am J Med. 2023;136:568–576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9842390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36657558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell JP, Turner JE. Debunking the Myth of Exercise-Induced Immune Suppression: Redefining the Impact of Exercise on Immunological Health Across the Lifespan. Front Immunol. 2018;9:648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5911985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29713319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nieman DC, Wentz LM. The compelling link between physical activity and the body’s defense system. J. Sport Health Sci. 2019;8:201–217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6523821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31193280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu L, She ZG, Cheng X, et al. Association of Blood Glucose Control and Outcomes in Patients with COVID-19 and Pre-existing Type 2 Diabetes. Cell Metab. 2020;31:1068–1077.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7252168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codo AC, Davanzo GG, Monteiro LB, et al. Elevated Glucose Levels Favor Sars-Cov-2 Infection and Monocyte Response Through a Hif-1a/Glycolysis Dependent Axis. Cell Metab. 2020;32:437–446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7367032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32697943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W, Li M, Dong Y, Zhou H, Zhang Z, Tian C, Qin R, Wang H, Shen Y, Du K, Zhao L. Diabetes is a risk factor for the progression and prognosis of COVID‐19. Diabetes Met Res Rev. 2020;36:e3319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7228407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32233013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petermann-Rocha F, Chen M, Gray SR, et al. New versus old guidelines for sarcopenia classification: What is the impact on prevalence and health outcomes? Age Ageing. 2020;49:300–304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31728486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunningham C, OS R, Caserotti P, Tully MA. Consequences of physical inactivity in older adults: A systematic review of reviews and meta-analyses. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2020;30:816–827.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32020713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowden DKA, Pickles S, Sprung VS, et al. Reduced physical activity in young and older adults: metabolic and musculoskeletal implications. Ther Adv Endocrinol Metab. 2019;10:2042018819888824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6878603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31803464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Liu B, Liang C, et al. Cytokine Signaling in Skeletal Muscle Wasting. Trends Endocrinol Metab. 2016;27:335–347.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27025788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flynn MG, Markofski MM, Carrillo AE. Elevated Inflammatory Status and Increased Risk of Chronic Disease in Chronological Aging: Inflamm-aging or Inflamm-inactivity? Aging Dis 2019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6345337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30705775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bigley AB, Rezvani K, Chew C, et al. Acute exercise preferentially redeploys NK-cells with a highly-differentiated phenotype and augments cytotoxicity against lymphoma and multiple myeloma target cells. Brain Behav Immun. 2014;39:160–171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24200514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idorn M, Hojman P. Exercise-Dependent Regulation of NK Cells in Cancer Protection. Trends Mol Med. 2016;22:565–577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27262760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olivo CR, Miyaji EN, Oliveira ML, et al. Aerobic exercise attenuates pulmonary inflammation induced by Streptococcus pneumoniae. J Appl Physiol (Bethesda Md 1985) 2014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25190745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Araujo AL, Silva LC, Fernandes JR, et al. Elderly men with moderate and intense training lifestyle present sustained higher antibody responses to influenza vaccine. Age (Dordrecht Netherlands) 2015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5005841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26480853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sim YJ, Yu S, Yoon KJ, et al. Chronic exercise reduces illness severity, decreases viral load, and results in greater anti-inflammatory effects than acute exercise during influenza infection. J Infect Dis. 2009;200:1434–1442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2812897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19811098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uggal NA, Pollock RD, Lazarus NR, et al. Major features of immune senescence,including reduced thymic output, are ameliorated by high levels of physical activity in adulthood. Aging Cell. 2018;17:1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5847865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29517845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen G, Wu D, Guo W, et al. Clinical and immunological features of severe and moderate coronavirus disease 2019. J Clin Invest. 2020;130:2620–2629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7190990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mobius-Winkler S, Hilberg T, Menzel K, et al. Time-dependent mobilization of circulating progenitor cells during strenuous exercise in healthy individuals. J Appl Physiol (Bethesda Md 1985) 2009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19797690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmer P, Schenk A, Kieven M, et al. Exercise induced alterations in NK-cell cytotoxicity - methodological issues and future perspectives. Exercise Immunol Rev. 2017;23:66–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28230531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huh JY. The role of exercise-induced myokines in regulating metabolism. Arch pharmacal Res. 2018;41:14–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29177585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>