<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39557407</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2383-7837</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>58</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of pathology and translational medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Pathol Transl Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development of CytoAcademy: a new web- and mobile-based E-learning platform for cytopathologists and cytotechnologists by the Korean Society for Cytopathology in the post-pandemic era.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>261</StartPage><EndPage>264</EndPage><MedlinePgn>261-264</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4132/jptm.2024.10.02</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Since the late 1990s, online e-learning has offered unparalleled convenience and affordability, becoming increasingly popular among pathologists. Traditional learning theories have been successfully applied to web/mobile-based learning systems, with mobile technologies even enhancing conventional offline education. In cytopathology, hands-on microscope training has traditionally been paramount, complemented by real-case presentations and lectures. However, the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic disrupted regular academic activities, making online e-learning platforms essential. We designed a web/mobile-based learning platform to enhance continued medical education in cytopathology at various levels, particularly during the era of COVID-19 and beyond. Since 2021, we have integrated curriculum materials, virtual education files, and whole-slide images (WSIs) of cytopathology, submitted from over 200 institutions across Korea, with the support of numerous instructors. We develop a new e-learning platform named "CytoAcademy" composed of a basic session for each organ and level across the range of morphologic findings; on-demand lectures to enhance cytopathologic knowledge; WSI archives that allow users to explore various histologically confirmed cases; and a self-assessment test to help organize diagnostic knowledge acquired through the web/mobile-friendly learning system. The platform provides not just an opportunity to achieve a correct diagnosis, but also a learning experience based on problem-solving point. Members interact, identify their deficiencies, and focus on specific educational materials. In this manner, all participants can actively engage in creating and maintaining knowledge and foster a proactive approach to learning.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hong</LastName><ForeName>Ran</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Chosun University College of Medicine, Gwangju, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chong</LastName><ForeName>Yosep</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hospital Pathology, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chae</LastName><ForeName>Seung Wan</ForeName><Initials>SW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Kangbuk Samsung Hospital, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Seung-Sook</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Korea Institute of Radiological and Medical Sciences, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gong</LastName><ForeName>Gyungyub</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>J Pathol Transl Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101650151</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2383-7837</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Continuing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cytology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Self-assessment</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4132/jptm.2024.10.02</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">jptm.2024.10.02</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>