<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553371</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1841-9038</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Maedica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Maedica (Bucur)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Incidence of Myocardial Infarction after Vaccination against COVID-19: a Meta-Analysis and Systematic Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>587</StartPage><EndPage>593</EndPage><MedlinePgn>587-593</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.26574/maedica.2024.19.3.587</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Vaccines were developed to stop the pandemic stage of COVID-19. A wide range of adverse effects, including vascular complications, has been reported after vaccination. Up to now, various studies have reported different rates of myocardial infarction (MI) after COVID-19 vaccination. So, this meta-analysis and systematic review study was designed to estimate the pooled incidence of MI after COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Two experienced researchers conducted searches in various databases and sources such as EMBASE, Scopus, Web of Science, Google Scholar, PubMed and gray literature, including references from studies published before March 2023. They collected information on participant count, the number of individuals who experienced MI after vaccination, average age, vaccine type, primary author, publication year and country of origin.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 385 articles were revealed by a literature search, and for further evaluation, 248 studies remained after removing duplicates. Seven articles remained for meta-analysis. Three studies provided the number of controls and the incidence of MI in both vaccinated and non-vaccinated groups. The incidence of MI after COVID-19 vaccines was ignorable (0%, I<sup>2</sup>=99%, P&lt;0.001). After COVID-19 vaccines, the odds of MI were 0.99 (95% CI 0.84-1.18) (I<sup>2</sup>=0, p=0.9).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">As shown by the results of the present meta-analysis and systematic review, the incidence of MI after COVID-19 vaccination can be ignorable and the risk was not increased by vaccination.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sadatnaseri</LastName><ForeName>Azadeh</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Sina Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghoshouni</LastName><ForeName>Hamed</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Isfahan Neurosciences Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Razavi</LastName><ForeName>Seyede Zahra Emami</ForeName><Initials>SZE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brain and Spinal Cord Injury Research Center, Neuroscience Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Associate Professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Imam Khomeini Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mirmosayyeb</LastName><ForeName>Omid</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Isfahan Neurosciences Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universal Council of Epidemiology (UCE), Universal Scientific Education and Research Network (USERN), Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azadvari</LastName><ForeName>Mohaddeseh</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Associate Professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Sina &amp; Imam Khomeini Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Urology Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hosseini</LastName><ForeName>Maryam</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Imam Khomeini Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guitynavard</LastName><ForeName>Fatemeh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Urology Research Center, Urology Department, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghajarzadeh</LastName><ForeName>Mahsa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universal Council of Epidemiology (UCE), Universal Scientific Education and Research Network (USERN), Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pourshams</LastName><ForeName>Maryam</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Golestan Hospital, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016421">Editorial</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Romania</Country><MedlineTA>Maedica (Bucur)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101526930</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1841-9038</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: none declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11565153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26574/maedica.2024.19.3.587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Moghadasi AN, Mirmosayyeb O, Barzegar M, et al. The prevalence of COVID-19 infection in patients with multiple sclerosis (MS): a systematic review and meta-analysis. Neurological Sciences. 2021;42:3093–3099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8184129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34100130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saluja P, Gautam N, Yadala S, Venkata AN. Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP) after COVID-19 vaccination: A systematic review of reported cases. Thromb Res. 2022;214:115–121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9060716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35533526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leemans W, Antonis S, De Vooght W, et al. Neuromuscular complications after COVID-19 vaccination: a series of eight patients. Acta Neurol Belg. 2022;122:753–761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9059449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35499704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizzo AC, Giussani G, Agostoni EC. Ischemic Stroke and Vaccine-Induced Immune Thrombotic Thrombocytopenia following COVID-19 Vaccine: A Case Report with Systematic Review of the Literature. Cerebrovasc Dis. 2022;51:722–734.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9148883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35512656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Azorin D, Baykan B, Beghi E, et al. Timing of headache after COVID-19 vaccines and its association with cerebrovascular events: An analysis of 41,700 VAERS reports. Cephalalgia 2022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35514199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>LBD Double Burden of Malnutrition Collaborators. Mapping local patterns of childhood overweight and wasting in low- and middle-income countries between 2000 and 2017. Nat Med. 2020;26:750–759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7220891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32313249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wise J. Covid-19: European countries suspend use of Oxford-AstraZeneca vaccine after reports of blood clots. BMJ. 2021;372:n699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33707182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aye YN, Mai AS, Zhang A, et al. Acute myocardial infarction and myocarditis following COVID-19 vaccination. QJM. 2023;116:279–283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8522388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34586408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kounis NG, Mazarakis A, Tsigkas G, et al. Kounis syndrome: a new twist on an old disease. Future Cardiology. 2011;7:805–824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22050066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boivin Z, Martin J. Untimely myocardial infarction or COVID-19 vaccine side effect. Cureus. 2021;13:e13651.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8012173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33824804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sung JG, Sobieszczyk PS, Bhatt DL. Acute myocardial infarction within 24 hours after COVID-19 vaccination. Am J Cardiol. 2021;156:129–131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8272970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34364657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardenheier BH, Gravenstein S, Blackman C, et al. Adverse events following mRNA SARS-CoV-2 vaccination among US nursing home residents. Vaccine. 2021;39:3844–3851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8162901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34092431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pottegård A, Lund LC, Karlstad Ø, et al. Arterial events, venous thromboembolism, thrombocytopenia, and bleeding after vaccination with Oxford-AstraZeneca ChAdOx1-S in Denmark and Norway: population based cohort study. BMJ. 2021;373:n1114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8097496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33952445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whiteley WN, Ip S, Cooper JA, et al. Association of COVID-19 vaccines ChAdOx1 and BNT162b2 with major venous, arterial, or thrombocytopenic events: A population-based cohort study of 46 million adults in England. PLoS Med. 2022;19:e1003926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8863280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35192597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mani A, Ojha V. Thromboembolism after COVID-19 vaccination: a systematic review of such events in 286 patients. Ann Vasc Surg. 2022;84:12–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9093198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35568325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>