<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39554890</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2307-8960</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>32</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>World journal of clinical cases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>World J Clin Cases</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Classification and detection of dental images using meta-learning.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>6559</StartPage><EndPage>6562</EndPage><MedlinePgn>6559-6562</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.12998/wjcc.v12.i32.6559</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Meta-learning of dental X-rays is a machine learning technique that can be used to train models to perform new tasks quickly and with minimal input. Instead of just memorizing a task, this is accomplished through teaching a model how to learn. Algorithms for meta-learning are typically trained on a collection of training problems, each of which has a limited number of labelled instances. Multiple X-ray classification tasks, including the detection of pneumonia, coronavirus disease 2019, and other disorders, have demonstrated the effectiveness of meta-learning. Meta-learning has the benefit of allowing models to be trained on dental X-ray datasets that are too few for more conventional machine learning methods. Due to the high cost and lengthy collection process associated with dental imaging datasets, this is significant for dental X-ray classification jobs. The ability to train models that are more resistant to fresh input is another benefit of meta-learning.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©The Author(s) 2024. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yadalam</LastName><ForeName>Pradeep Kumar</ForeName><Initials>PK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Periodontics, Saveetha Dental College and Hospital, Saveetha Institute of Medical and Technical Sciences, Saveetha University, Chennai 600077, Tamil Nadu, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anegundi</LastName><ForeName>Raghavendra Vamsi</ForeName><Initials>RV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Periodontics, Saveetha Dental College and Hospital, Saveetha Institute of Medical and Technical Sciences, Saveetha University, Chennai 600077, Tamil Nadu, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alarcón-Sánchez</LastName><ForeName>Mario Alberto</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South Pacific Dental Institute, Chilpancingo de los Bravo 39022, Guerrero, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heboyan</LastName><ForeName>Artak</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Prosthodontics, Faculty of Stomatology, Yerevan State Medical University after Mkhitar Heratsi, Yerevan 0025, Armenia. heboyan.artak@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>World J Clin Cases</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101618806</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2307-8960</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Artificial intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dental diagnosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dental radiography</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Image segmentation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical image interpretation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meta-learning</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict-of-interest statement: All the authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39554890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11438644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v12.i32.6559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Miao R, Dong X, Xie SL, Liang Y, Lo SL. UMLF-COVID: an unsupervised meta-learning model specifically designed to identify X-ray images of COVID-19 patients. BMC Med Imaging. 2021;21:174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8607405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34809589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A, Bhadauria HS, Singh A. Descriptive analysis of dental X-ray images using various practical methods: A review. PeerJ Comput Sci. 2021;7:e620.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8459782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34616881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ching T, Himmelstein DS, Beaulieu-Jones BK, Kalinin AA, Do BT, Way GP, Ferrero E, Agapow PM, Zietz M, Hoffman MM, Xie W, Rosen GL, Lengerich BJ, Israeli J, Lanchantin J, Woloszynek S, Carpenter AE, Shrikumar A, Xu J, Cofer EM, Lavender CA, Turaga SC, Alexandari AM, Lu Z, Harris DJ, DeCaprio D, Qi Y, Kundaje A, Peng Y, Wiley LK, Segler MHS, Boca SM, Swamidass SJ, Huang A, Gitter A, Greene CS. Opportunities and obstacles for deep learning in biology and medicine. J R Soc Interface. 2018;15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5938574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29618526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khadka R, Jha D, Hicks S, Thambawita V, Riegler MA, Ali S, Halvorsen P. Meta-learning with implicit gradients in a few-shot setting for medical image segmentation. Comput Biol Med. 2022;143:105227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35124439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabaghi A, Oghbaie M, Hashemifard K, Akbari M. Deep learning meets liveness detection: Recent advancements and challenges. 2021 Preprint. Available from: arXiv:211214796.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Li Y. MetaSeg: A survey of meta-learning for image segmentation. Cognitive Robotics. 2021;1:83–91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cremer CZ. Deep limitations? Examining expert disagreement over deep learning. Prog Artif Intell. 2021;10:449–464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arsiwala-Scheppach LT, Chaurasia A, Müller A, Krois J, Schwendicke F. Machine Learning in Dentistry: A Scoping Review. J Clin Med. 2023;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9918184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36769585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Zhao D, Xie J, Wen H, Liu C, Li Y, Li W, Wang S. Deep learning for classifying the stages of periodontitis on dental images: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Oral Health. 2023;23:1017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10729340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38114946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaurasia A, Namachivayam A, Koca-Ünsal RB, Lee JH. Deep-learning performance in identifying and classifying dental implant systems from dental imaging: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Periodontal Implant Sci. 2024;54:3–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10901682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37154107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>