<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553844</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2331-5180</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of particle therapy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Part Ther</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic on Carbon-Ion Radiation Therapy in Japan: A Japanese National Registry Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100634</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100634</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100634</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijpt.2024.100634</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study aimed to investigate the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on carbon-ion radiation therapy (CIRT) in Japan by evaluating patient numbers and treatment trends from 2019 to 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PATIENTS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Data from 5 CIRT facilities were analyzed, encompassing a total of 13 224 patients treated over the 4-year period. Patient demographics, cancer types, treatment protocols, and adherence to national health insurance coverage were examined. The study period was divided into unaffected (2019), significantly affected (2020-2021), and poststabilization (2022) phases, corresponding to progression of the pandemic. For monthly analysis, the period during which a state of emergency was declared by the Japanese government was defined as the pandemic period.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Prostate cancer comprised the majority of CIRT cases (62.4%), followed by hepatocellular carcinoma, bone and soft tissue tumors, locally advanced pancreatic cancer, and nonsquamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Despite the pandemic, the annual reduction in CIRT patients remained &lt;5%, suggesting treatment continuity. Analysis of monthly treatment figures revealed a significant reduction in the number of patients with nonprostate cancers treated during the state of emergency, while a reduction in the number of prostate cancer treatments was observed approximately 6 months later. Although the number of COVID-19 patients continued to increase after 2022, the number of patients receiving CIRT increased after the state of emergency was declared.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Although there was a reduction in monthly CIRT patient numbers during the COVID-19 pandemic, yearly analysis revealed that this amounted to &lt;5%.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kubo</LastName><ForeName>Nobuteru</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gunma University Heavy Ion Medical Center, Gunma, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ozawa</LastName><ForeName>Toshiki</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gunma University Heavy Ion Medical Center, Gunma, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shioyama</LastName><ForeName>Yoshiyuki</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ion Beam Therapy Center, SAGA-HIMAT Foundation, Saga, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yamada</LastName><ForeName>Shigeru</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>QST Hospital, National Institutes for Quantum Science and Technology, Chiba, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Katoh</LastName><ForeName>Hiroyuki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiation Oncology, Kanagawa Cancer Center, Kanagawa, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okimoto</LastName><ForeName>Tomoaki</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Hyogo Ion Beam Medical Center, Hyogo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ohno</LastName><ForeName>Tatsuya</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gunma University Heavy Ion Medical Center, Gunma, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Part Ther</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101674108</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2331-5180</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Carbon-ion radiation therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Hiroyuki Katoh reports financial support was provided by Toshiba Energy Systems &amp; Solutions Corporation. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11566714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijpt.2024.100634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2331-5180(24)00700-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Okamoto S. State of emergency and human mobility during the COVID-19 pandemic in Japan. J Transp Health. 2022;26</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9167861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35694018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuniya T. Evaluation of the effect of the state of emergency for the first wave of COVID-19 in Japan. Infect Dis Model. 2020;5:580–587.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7429510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32844135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka T., Okamoto S. Increase in suicide following an initial decline during the COVID-19 pandemic in Japan. Nat Hum Behav. 2021;5:229–238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33452498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onyeaka H., Anumudu C.K., Al-Sharify Z.T., et al. COVID-19 pandemic: a review of the global lockdown and its far-reaching effects. Sci Prog. 2021;104 368504211019854.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10454957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34061685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okuyama A., Watabe M., Makoshi R., et al. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the diagnosis of cancer in Japan: analysis of hospital-based cancer registries. Jpn J Clin Oncol. 2022;52:1215–1224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9384600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35909325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sato Y., Yamamoto H., Ikeda N., et al. The impact of COVID-19 on thoracic surgical procedures in Japan: analysis of data from the National Clinical Database. Lung Cancer. 2022;172:127–135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9383954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36084376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiroshita H., Endo H., Inomata M., et al. The clinical impact of COVID-19 on endoscopic surgery in Japan: analysis of data from the National Clinical Database. Ann Gastroenterol Surg. 2023;7:572–582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10319603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37416738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guckenberger M., Belka C., Bezjak A., et al. Practice recommendations for lung cancer radiotherapy during the COVID-19 pandemic: an ESTRO-ASTRO consensus statement. Radiother Oncol. 2020;146:223–229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7252074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32342863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomson D.J., Palma D., Guckenberger M., et al. Practice recommendations for risk-adapted head and neck cancer radiation therapy during the COVID-19 pandemic: an ASTRO-ESTRO consensus statement. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2020;107:618–627.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamada T., Tsujii H., Blakely E.A., et al. Carbon ion radiotherapy in Japan: an assessment of 20 years of clinical experience. Lancet Oncol. 2015;16:e93–e100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25638685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Particle Therapy Co-Operative Group (PTCOG). Accessed April 4, 2024. https://www.ptcog.site/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubo N., Suefuji H., Nakajima M., et al. Five-year survival outcomes after carbon-ion radiotherapy for operable stage I NSCLC: a Japanese National Registry Study (J-CROS-LUNG) J Thorac Oncol. 2024;19:491–499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37924974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare. Number of newly confirmed COVID-19 cases (daily). Accessed April 4, 2024. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/covid-19/open-data.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team . R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2023. https://www.R-project.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawamura H., Kubo N., Sato H., et al. Group for genitourinary tumors at Gunma University Heavy Ion Medical Center. Moderately hypofractionated carbon ion radiotherapy for prostate cancer; a prospective observational study ‘GUNMA0702’. BMC Cancer. 2020;20:75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6990498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32000716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siavashpour Z., Goharpey N., Mobasheri M. Radiotherapy based management during COVID-19 pandemic - a systematic review of presented consensus and guidelines. Crit Rev Oncol Hematol. 2021;164</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34214608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maeda H., Endo H., Yamamoto H., et al. Effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on gastroenterological surgeries in 2020: a study using the National Clinical Database of Japan. Ann Gastroenterol Surg. 2023;7:407–418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10154870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37152784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamari K., Nagata Y., Nishiki S., et al. Nationwide survey of COVID-19 prevention measures in Japanese radiotherapy departments via online questionnaire for radiation oncologists. Radiother Oncol. 2020;149:219–221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7256533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32474125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamari K., Nagata Y., Mizowaki T., et al. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on radiotherapy in Japan: nationwide surveys from May 2020 through June 2021. J Radiat Res. 2023;64:126–132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9494496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36109327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare. High-cost medical expense benefit (Eligibility certificate for ceiling-amount application). Accessed April 4, 2024. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/seisakunitsuite/bunya/kenkou_iryou/iryou/kokusai/setsumeisiryo/dl/en09.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood L., Giles E., Cunningham L., Le H., Zientara N., Short M. Proton radiation therapy patient selection and impacts of COVID-19: a scoping review. J Med Radiat Sci. 2024;71:37–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11011594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37431794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barcellini A., Massaro M., Dal Mas F., et al. A year of pandemic for European particle radiotherapy: a survey on behalf of EPTN working group. Clin Transl Radiat Oncol. 2022;34:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8885798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35243028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>