<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39556174</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1435-4373</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European journal of clinical microbiology &amp; infectious diseases : official publication of the European Society of Clinical Microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Analysis of the potentially pathogenic bacteria of lower respiratory tract infections in children per-, during and post-COVID-19: a retrospective study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10096-024-04991-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has caused significant changes in lower respiratory tract infections (LRTIs). This study aimed to characterize potentially pathogenic bacterial infections in paediatric patients hospitalized for LRTIs per-, during and post-COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Sputum culture data from 85,659 children with LRTIs at the Children's Hospital of Soochow University from January 2016 to May 2024 were analyzed for eight bacteria: Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae, Staphylococcus aureus, Moraxella catarrhalis, Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Klebsiella pneumoniae, and Acinetobacter baumannii. The data during the pandemic (2020-2022, during COVID-19) and after the pandemic (January 2023-May 2024, post-COVID-19) were compared with those before the pandemic (2016-2019).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Overall, 85,659 children with LRTIs were enrolled. Of these, 42,567 cases (49.7%) were diagnosed in the pre-COVID-19 period, 22,531 cases (26.3%) during the COVID-19 period and 20,561 cases (24.0%) in the post-COVID-19 period. The overall positive rate for pathogenic bacteria was 37.1%, with the top three being S. pneumoniae (14.5%), H. influenzae (12.1%) and S. aureus (6.5%). Compared to the average pre-COVID-19 levels, the bacterial pathogen positive rate decreased by 3.5% during the COVID-19 period (OR: 0.94, 95% CI: 0.91-0.98) and by 23.4% in the post-COVID-19 period (OR: 0.66, 95% CI: 0.64-0.69). During the COVID-19 period, the positive rates for S. pneumoniae, H. influenzae, E. coli, K. pneumoniae and mixed infections decreased by 11.7%, 35.3%, 22.2%, 33.3% and 45.7% respectively, while the positive rates for S. aureus, M. catarrhalis and P. aeruginosa increased by 21.7%, 44.7% and 25% respectively. In the post-COVID-19 period, the positive rates for S. pneumoniae, H. influenzae, E. coli, P. aeruginosa, K. pneumoniae, A. baumannii and mixed infections decreased by 50.0%, 7.4%, 22.2%, 50.0%, 44.4%, 60.0% and 32.6% respectively, while there was no statistical change in the positive rates for S. aureus and M. catarrhalis. Bacteria case detection decreases in 2020 (67.0%), 2021 (60.5%), 2022 (76.3%) and 2023 (72.7%) compared to predicted cases.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Measures to restrict COVID-19 as a driver of declining bacterial positive rates. Respiratory bacteria in children are change across COVID-19 phases, age groups and seasons. After COVID-19, clinicians should continue to increase surveillance for pathogenic bacteria, especially drug-resistant flora.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Xuena</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children's Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Meng</LastName><ForeName>Lingjian</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children's Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Xuzhou Medical University Affiliated Hospital, Xuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jiaoyang</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children's Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yizhu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children's Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Bingjie</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children's Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Wujun</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children's Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, China. jwj8701@suda.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hao</LastName><ForeName>Chuangli</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children's Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, China. hcl_md@sina.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>Y120211H03</GrantID><Agency>the Ili State Institute of Clinical Medicine Research Fund Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>YZ2022Y019</GrantID><Agency>the Autonomous Prefecture Science and Technology Programme Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>82270018 and 82070009</GrantID><Agency>the National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>BE2021656</GrantID><Agency>the Jiangsu Province Key Research and Development Programme (Social Development Project)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8804297</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0934-9723</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lower respiratory tract infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sputum culture</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Ethics approval and consent to participate</b> All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.The study was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of the Children’s Hospital of Soochow University under approval number 2,013,002. Written informed consent to participate in this study was provided by the participants’ legal guardian/next of kin. <b>Consent to participate</b> Informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in this study. <b>Clinical trial number</b> Not applicable. <b>Human ethics and consent to participate declarations</b> Not applicable. <b>Competing interests</b> The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39556174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10096-024-04991-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10096-024-04991-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Li ZJ, Zhang HY, Ren LL, Lu QB, Ren X, Zhang CH, Wang YF, Lin SH, Zhang XA, Li J et al (2021) Etiological and epidemiological features of acute respiratory infections in China. Nat Commun 12(1):5026. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-25120-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-25120-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34408158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8373954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The top 10 causes of death [ https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/the-top-10-causes-of-death</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tregoning JS, Schwarze J (2010) Respiratory viral infections in infants: causes, clinical symptoms, virology, and immunology. Clin Microbiol Rev 23(1):74–98. https://doi.org/10.1128/cmr.00032-09</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/cmr.00032-09</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20065326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2806659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global, regional, and national incidence and mortality burden of non-COVID-19 lower respiratory infections and aetiologies, 1990-2021: a systematic analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. Lancet Infect Dis. 2024;24(9):974–1002. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1473-3099(24)00176-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global incidence, prevalence, years lived with disability (YLDs), disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs), and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 371 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories and 811 subnational locations, 1990–2021: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. Lancet (London, England). 2024;403(10440):2133–2161. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140-6736(24)00757-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu BM, Beck EM, Fisher MA (2021) The brief case: Ventilator-Associated Corynebacterium accolens Pneumonia in a patient with respiratory failure due to COVID-19. J Clin Microbiol 59(9):e0013721. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.00137-21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.00137-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34406882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu B, Totten M, Nematollahi S, Datta K, Memon W, Marimuthu S, Wolf LA, Carroll KC, Zhang SX (2020) Development and evaluation of a fully automated Molecular Assay Targeting the mitochondrial small subunit rRNA gene for the detection of Pneumocystis Jirovecii in Bronchoalveolar Lavage fluid specimens. J Mol Diagnostics: JMD 22(12):1482–1493. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmoldx.2020.10.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmoldx.2020.10.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ieven M, Coenen S, Loens K, Lammens C, Coenjaerts F, Vanderstraeten A, Henriques-Normark B, Crook D, Huygen K, Butler CC et al (2018) Aetiology of lower respiratory tract infection in adults in primary care: a prospective study in 11 European countries. Clinical microbiology and infection: the official publication of the European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious diseases. 24(11):1158–1163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2018.02.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popova G, Boskovska K, Arnaudova-Danevska I, Smilevska-Spasova O, Jakovska T (2019) Sputum Quality Assessment regarding Sputum Culture for diagnosing lower respiratory tract infections in children. Open Access Macedonian J Med Sci 7(12):1926–1930. https://doi.org/10.3889/oamjms.2019.551</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3889/oamjms.2019.551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang L, Jing W, Liu J, Liu M (2023) Trends of global and regional aetiologies, risk factors and mortality of lower respiratory infections from 1990 to 2019: an analysis for the global burden of Disease Study 2019. Respirology (Carlton, Vic). 28(2):166–175. https://doi.org/10.1111/resp.14389</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun YP, Zheng XY, Zhang HX, Zhou XM, Lin XZ, Zheng ZZ, Zhang J, Su YY, Zhou YL (2021) Epidemiology of respiratory pathogens among children hospitalized for Pneumonia in Xiamen: a retrospective study. Infectious diseases and therapy. 10(3):1567–1578. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40121-021-00472-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inagaki K, Ansari MAY, Hobbs CV (2021) Readmission after hospitalization with Staphylococcus aureus bacteremia in children. Am J Infect Control 49(11):1402–1407. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajic.2021.04.088</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2021.04.088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33989724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni D, Wang X, Sharland E, Stansfield D, Campbell H, Nair H (2022) The global burden of hospitalisation due to pneumonia caused by Staphylococcus aureus in the under-5 years children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. EClinicalMedicine 44:101267. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101267</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35072019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8763635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu BM, Rakhmanina NY, Yang Z, Bukrinsky MI (2024) Mpox (Monkeypox) Virus and its co-infection with HIV, sexually transmitted infections, or bacterial superinfections: double whammy or a new Prime Culprit? Viruses. 16(5):784. https://doi.org/10.3390/v16050784</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chertow DS, Memoli MJ (2013) Bacterial coinfection in influenza: a grand rounds review. JAMA 309(3):275–282. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2012.194139</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2012.194139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23321766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan WJ, Ni ZY, Hu Y, Liang WH, Ou CQ, He JX, Liu L, Shan H, Lei CL, Hui DSC et al (2020) Clinical characteristics of Coronavirus Disease 2019 in China. N Engl J Med 382(18):1708–1720. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa2002032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2002032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32109013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cucinotta D, Vanelli M (2020) WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic. Acta Bio-medica. Atenei Parmensis 91(1):157–160. https://doi.org/10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiehao C, Jin X, Daojiong L, Zhi Y, Lei X, Zhenghai Q, Yuehua Z, Hua Z, Ran J, Pengcheng L et al (2020) A Case Series of Children with 2019 Novel Coronavirus infection: clinical and epidemiological features. Clin Infect Diseases: Official Publication Infect Dis Soc Am 71(6):1547–1551. https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/ciaa198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, McGoogan JM (2020) Characteristics of and important lessons from the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: Summary of a report of 72 314 cases from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. JAMA 323(13):1239–1242. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2020.2648</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.2648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang ML, Xu YP, Wu H, Zhu RN, Sun Y, Chen DM, Wang F, Zhou YT, Guo Q, Wu A et al (2023) Changes in endemic patterns of respiratory syncytial virus infection in pediatric patients under the pressure of nonpharmaceutical interventions for COVID-19 in Beijing, China. J Med Virol 95(1):e28411. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.28411</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36524893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu X, Pan Z, Dong H, Zhang Y, Xu L, Wang P, Wang Y, Li J, Jiang W, Hao C Inhibition, transition, and surge: dynamic evolution of pediatric respiratory pathogen trends amid COVID-19 pandemic policy adjustments. Front Public Health 2024 12:1420929. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2024.1420929</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu R, Zhang J, Mo L (2023) Analysis of respiratory virus detection in hospitalized children with acute respiratory infection during the COVID-19 pandemic. Virol J 20(1):253. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12985-023-02218-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-023-02218-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37919789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10623845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mamun AA, Saatchi A, Xie M, Lishman H, Blondel-Hill E, Marra F, Patrick DM (2021) Community Antibiotic Use at the Population Level during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic in British Columbia, Canada. Open forum infectious diseases. 8(6):ofab185. https://doi.org/10.1093/ofid/ofab185</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedli O, Gasser M, Cusini A, Fulchini R, Vuichard-Gysin D, Halder Tobler R, Wassilew N, Plüss-Suard C, Kronenberg A (2022) Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on Inpatient Antibiotic Consumption in Switzerland. Antibiotics (Basel, Switzerland). 11(6). https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics11060792</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brueggemann AB, van Jansen MJ, Shaw D, McCarthy ND, Jolley KA, Maiden MCJ, van der Linden MPG, Amin-Chowdhury Z, Bennett DE, Borrow R et al (2021) Changes in the incidence of invasive disease due to Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae, and Neisseria meningitidis during the COVID-19 pandemic in 26 countries and territories in the invasive respiratory infection Surveillance Initiative: a prospective analysis of surveillance data. Lancet Digit Health 3(6):e360–e370. https://doi.org/10.1016/s2589-7500(21)00077-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s2589-7500(21)00077-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34045002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8166576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasad N, Rhodes J, Deng L, McCarthy NL, Moline HL, Baggs J, Reddy SC, Jernigan JA, Havers FP, Sosin DM et al (2023) Changes in the incidence of Invasive Bacterial Disease during the COVID-19 pandemic in the United States, 2014–2020. J Infect Dis 227(7):907–916. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiad028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiad028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36723871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng Q, Li W, Jiang H, Yan H, Wang H, Ye B, Zhou L, Chen Y (2023) Comparison of the distribution and changes in the Antibiotic Resistance of Clinical Bacterial isolates from the Lower Respiratory Tract of children in Shenzhen before the Epidemic, during the Epidemic, and during the period of normalized Prevention and Control of COVID-19. Infect Dis Therapy 12(2):563–575. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40121-022-00751-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40121-022-00751-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou YL, Liu JR, Yi QW, Chen LN, Han ZY, Xu CD, Liu SY, Hao CL, Liu J, Li QL et al (2021) [A multicenter retrospective study on the etiology of necrotizing pneumonia in children]. Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi = Chin J Pediatr 59(8):658–664. https://doi.org/10.3760/cma.j.cn112140-20210126-00072</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3760/cma.j.cn112140-20210126-00072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herfst S, Böhringer M, Karo B, Lawrence P, Lewis NS, Mina MJ, Russell CJ, Steel J, de Swart RL, Menge C (2017) Drivers of airborne human-to-human pathogen transmission. Curr Opin Virol 22:22–29. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coviro.2016.11.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2016.11.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27918958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Q, Wischmeyer J, Gonzalez E, Pichichero ME (2017) Nasopharyngeal polymicrobial colonization during health, viral upper respiratory infection and upper respiratory bacterial infection. J Infect 75(1):26–34. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2017.04.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2017.04.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28412081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5505505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard LM, Grijalva CG (2024) Impact of respiratory viral infections on nasopharyngeal pneumococcal colonization dynamics in children. Curr Opin Infect Dis 37(3):170–175. https://doi.org/10.1097/qco.0000000000001008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/qco.0000000000001008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38437245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serigstad S, Markussen DL, Ritz C, Ebbesen MH, Knoop ST, Kommedal Ø, Heggelund L, Ulvestad E, Bjørneklett RO, Grewal HMS (2022) The changing spectrum of microbial aetiology of respiratory tract infections in hospitalized patients before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMC Infect Dis 22(1):763. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879-022-07732-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-022-07732-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36180842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9523652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AliMohammadi A, Chezani-Sharahi N, Hezaveh ZA, Abbasi E, Shariati A, Ghaznavi-Rad E The significant role of Carbapenems-resistant Acinetobacter Baumannii in mortality rate of patients with COVID-19. Vacunas 2023 Jan-Mar 24(1):13–18. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vacun.2022.10.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong D, Nielsen TB, Bonomo RA, Pantapalangkoor P, Luna B, Spellberg B (2017) Clinical and pathophysiological overview of Acinetobacter infections: a Century of challenges. Clin Microbiol Rev 30(1):409–447. https://doi.org/10.1128/cmr.00058-16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/cmr.00058-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27974412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falagas ME, Rafailidis PI (2007) Attributable mortality of Acinetobacter baumannii: no longer a controversial issue. Critical care (London, England). 11(3):134. https://doi.org/10.1186/cc5911</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dijkshoorn L, Nemec A, Seifert H (2007) An increasing threat in hospitals: multidrug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii. Nat Rev Microbiol 5(12):939–951. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1789</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18007677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boral J, Genç Z, Pınarlık F, Ekinci G, Kuskucu MA, İrkören P, Kapmaz M, Tekin S, Çakar N, Şentürk E et al (2022) The association between Acinetobacter baumannii infections and the COVID-19 pandemic in an intensive care unit. Sci Rep 12(1):20808. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-25493-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-25493-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36460749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9716169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gellatly SL, Hancock RE (2013) Pseudomonas aeruginosa: new insights into pathogenesis and host defenses. Pathogens Disease 67(3):159–173. https://doi.org/10.1111/2049-632x.12033</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/2049-632x.12033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23620179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent JL, Sakr Y, Singer M, Martin-Loeches I, Machado FR, Marshall JC, Finfer S, Pelosi P, Brazzi L, Aditianingsih D et al (2020) Prevalence and outcomes of infection among patients in Intensive Care Units in 2017. JAMA 323(15):1478–1487. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2020.2717</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.2717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32207816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7093816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latchmore T, Lavallee S, Boudou M, McDermott K, Brown RS, Hynds P, Majury A (2022) Impacts of COVID-19 lockdown on private domestic groundwater sample numbers, E. Coli presence and E. Coli concentration across Ontario, January 2020-March 2021: an interrupted time-series analysis. Sci Total Environ 814:152634. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152634</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34974018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ficik J, Andrezál M, Drahovská H, Böhmer M, Szemes T, Liptáková A, Slobodníková L (2023) Carbapenem-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae in COVID-19 Era-challenges and solutions. Antibiotics (Basel, Switzerland). 12(8). https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics12081285</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belvisi V, Del Borgo C, Vita S, Redaelli P, Dolce P, Pacella D, Kertusha B, Carraro A, Marocco R, De Masi M et al (2021) Impact of SARS CoV-2 pandemic on carbapenemase-producing Klebsiella pneumoniae prevention and control programme: convergent or divergent action? J Hosp Infect 109:29–31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhin.2020.11.030</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2020.11.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33338560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiri B, Sensi E, Marsiliani V, Cantarini M, Priante G, Vernelli C, Martella LA, Costantini M, Mariottini A, Andreani P et al (2020) Antimicrobial stewardship program, COVID-19, and infection control: spread of Carbapenem-resistant Klebsiella Pneumoniae colonization in ICU COVID-19 patients. What Did Not Work? J Clin Med 9(9). https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm9092744</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterjee N, Nirwan PK, Srivastava S, Rati R, Sharma L, Sharma P, Dwivedi P, Jaggi N (2023) Trends in carbapenem resistance in Pre-COVID and COVID times in a tertiary care hospital in North India. Annals of clinical microbiology and antimicrobials. 22(1):1. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12941-022-00549-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrade DC, Borges IC, Bouzas ML, Oliveira JR, Käyhty H, Ruuskanen O, Nascimento-Carvalho C (2018) Antibody responses against Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae and Moraxella catarrhalis in children with acute respiratory infection with or without nasopharyngeal bacterial carriage. Infectious diseases (London, England). 50(9):705–713. https://doi.org/10.1080/23744235.2018.1463451</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park DE, Baggett HC, Howie SRC, Shi Q, Watson NL, Brooks WA, Deloria Knoll M, Hammitt LL, Kotloff KL, Levine OS et al (2017) Colonization density of the Upper Respiratory Tract as a predictor of Pneumonia-Haemophilus influenzae, Moraxella catarrhalis, Staphylococcus aureus, and Pneumocystis Jirovecii. Clin Infect Diseases: Official Publication Infect Dis Soc Am 64(suppl3):S328–s336. https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/cix104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/cix104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu BM, Carlisle CP, Fisher MA, Shakir SM (2021) The brief case: Capnocytophaga sputigena bacteremia in a 94-Year-old male with type 2 diabetes Mellitus, Pancytopenia, and Bronchopneumonia. J Clin Microbiol 59(7):e0247220. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.02472-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.02472-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34142857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu B (2017) Universal PCR primers are critical for direct sequencing-based enterovirus genotyping. J Clin Microbiol 55(1):339–340. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.01801-16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.01801-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28031445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu B, Forman M, Valsamakis A (2019) Optimization and evaluation of a novel real-time RT-PCR test for detection of parechovirus in cerebrospinal fluid. J Virol Methods 272:113690. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2019.113690</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2019.113690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31283959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>