<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39557747</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-1497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of general internal medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Gen Intern Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effectiveness of a Novel Global Telemedicine Curriculum for Medical Students.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11606-024-09190-y</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine collaborated with The Addis Clinic to create a global telemedicine elective for fourth-year medical students during the COVID-19 pandemic. The elective aimed to promote cross-cultural understanding by providing unique, hands-on telemedicine experience.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To assess the effectiveness of the telemedicine elective, four of five medical students and 11 of 12 Kenyan clinical officers completed one-on-one interviews and surveys.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="METHODS">Students and global health faculty connected virtually with patients and clinical officers from several rural clinics in Kenya during the 4-week elective.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PARTICIPANTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Per elective month, participants of the course included two fourth-year medical students and five Kenyan clinical officers.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PROGRAM DESCRIPTION" NlmCategory="METHODS">A medical school elective designed in collaboration with The Addis Clinic, using WhatsApp and Telemedicus platform, in which each medical student virtually assisted a team of Kenyan clinical officers with a variety of active patient cases.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PROGRAM EVALUATION" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Qualitative analysis of interviews with medical students and Kenyan clinical officers yielded themes of increased competency with clinical decision-making and culturally appropriate care delivery.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Implementation of a unique global telemedicine elective was feasible and well received by both medical students and clinical officers in Kenya. The elective can be implemented at other institutions with faculty experienced in global health who would like to partner with The Addis Clinic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Society of General Internal Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Doshi</LastName><ForeName>Pranav</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Donovan</LastName><ForeName>Anna K</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Erin J</ForeName><Initials>EJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Addis Clinic, Nashville, TN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moretti</LastName><ForeName>Meghan</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Addis Clinic, Nashville, TN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chan</LastName><ForeName>Stephen Y</ForeName><Initials>SY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Pittsburgh Heart, Lung, and Blood Vascular Medicine Institute, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Veldkamp</LastName><ForeName>Peter J</ForeName><Initials>PJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schikowski</LastName><ForeName>Erin M</ForeName><Initials>EM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5819-7796</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, Pittsburgh, PA, USA. schikowskiem@upmc.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Gen Intern Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8605834</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0884-8734</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">global health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medical education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telemedicine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations:</b> <b>Conflict of Interest:</b> S.Y.C. is a founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the Addis Clinic. S.Y.C. has served as a consultant for Merck and United Therapeutics. S.Y.C. is a director, officer, and shareholder in Synhale Therapeutics. S.Y.C. has held research grants from United Therapeutics and Bayer. S.Y.C. has filed patent applications regarding the targeting of metabolism in pulmonary hypertension (Patent: Compositions and Methods for Treating Pulmonary Vascular Disease, US10925869B2). The other authors declare no competing interests. All remaining authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-024-09190-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11606-024-09190-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>eHealth WHOGOf. mHealth: new horizons for health through mobile technologies: second global survey on eHealth. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cornes S, Gelfand Jeffrey M, Calton B. Foundational Telemedicine Workshop for First-Year Medical Students Developed During a Pandemic. MedEdPORTAL.17:11171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moschovis PP, Dinesh A, Boguraev AS, Nelson BD. Remote online global health education among U.S. medical students during COVID-19 and beyond. BMC Med Educ. 2022;22(1):353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim EJ, Fox S, Moretti ME, Turner M, Girard TD, Chan SY. Motivations and Barriers Associated with Physician Volunteerism for an International Telemedicine Organization. Front Public Health. 2019;7:224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2019.00224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31457002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6701451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wootton R, Bonnardot L. Experience of Supporting Telemedicine Networks with the Collegium System: First 6 Years. Front Public Health. 2019;7:226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2019.00226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31497587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6712066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manji K, Hanefeld J, Vearey J, Walls H, de Gruchy T. Using WhatsApp messenger for health systems research: a scoping review of available literature. Health Policy Plan. 2021;36(5):594-605.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/heapol/czab024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33860314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green T, Green H, Scandlyn J, Kestler A. Perceptions of short-term medical volunteer work: a qualitative study in Guatemala. Global Health. 2009;5:4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1744-8603-5-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19245698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2662818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crabtree BF, Miller WL. Doing Qualitative Research. SAGE; 2012</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>