<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553360</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1841-9038</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Maedica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Maedica (Bucur)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comprehensive Analysis of COVID-19 Symptomatology among Healthcare Workers: Insights from a Tertiary Hospital.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>600</StartPage><EndPage>606</EndPage><MedlinePgn>600-606</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.26574/maedica.2024.19.3.600</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This paper presents a thorough examination of COVID-19 symptomatology among healthcare workers from All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS), Nagpur, India. Through meticulous analysis spanning from May 2020 to October 2020, we enrolled 73 healthcare workers engaged in COVID-19 screening, care and testing. Our study aimed to elucidate the spectrum of symptoms, adherence to protective measures and implications for early detection and intervention. Key findings revealed a diverse range of symptoms, including body ache, fatigue, headache, sore throat, fever, cough and loss of taste, among others. Notably, 21% of all positive cases were asymptomatic, underscoring the variability in clinical presentation. Adherence to personal protective measures varied across work areas, highlighting the importance of stringent compliance. Our discussion emphasizes the significance of early identification and tailored monitoring systems for mitigating transmission risks and ensuring healthcare worker safety. Additionally, addressing the mental health needs of healthcare workers is crucial for comprehensive pandemic management. Overall, this study contributes essential insights into COVID-19 symptomatology among healthcare workers, offering valuable guidance for infection control and prevention strategies in the pandemic.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shrikrishna</LastName><ForeName>B H</ForeName><Initials>BH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology and Head Neck Surgery, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Hyderabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bidkar</LastName><ForeName>Vijay</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology and Head Neck Surgery, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Nagpur, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dabhekar</LastName><ForeName>Sandeep</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology and Head Neck Surgery, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Nagpur, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kirankumar</LastName><ForeName>Prathipati</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology and Head Neck Surgery, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Nagpur, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deepa</LastName><ForeName>Gadwal</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anatomy, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Hyderabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016421">Editorial</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Romania</Country><MedlineTA>Maedica (Bucur)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101526930</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1841-9038</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: none declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11565133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26574/maedica.2024.19.3.600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lauer SA, Grantz KH, Bi Q, et al. The Incubation Period of Corona virus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) From Publicly Reported Confirmed Cases: Estimation and Application. Ann Intern Med. 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7081172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. WHO Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) Dashboard. Available from: https:// covid19.who.int/?gclid=CjwKCAjw07qDB hBxEiwA6pPbHosu1YlGF0952RkSwwGS- Of5mYyKGdcD3fztCmSr iCeroLMixD38xoCRmUQAvD_BwE. Accessed 9 April 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. The Incubation Period of Corona virus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) From Publicly Reported Confirmed Cases: Estimation and Application. Available from: https://covid19.who.int/region/searo/ country/in. Accessed 9 April 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7081172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joseph B, Joseph M. The health of the healthcare workers. Indian J Occup Environ Med. 2016;20:71–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5299814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28194078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C, Wang Y, Li X, et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet. 2020;395:497–506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai Y, Yao L, Wei T, et al. Presumed asymptomatic carrier transmission of COVID-19. JAMA. 2020;323:1406–1407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7042844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32083643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothe C, Schunk M, Sothmann P, et al. Transmission of 2019-nCOV infection from an asymptomatic contact in Germany. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:970–971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7120970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32003551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong Z-D, Tang A, Li K-F, et al. Potential presymptomatic transmission of SARS-CoV-2, Zhejiang Province, China, 2020. Emerg Infect Dis. 2020;26:1052–1054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7181913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye F, Xu S, Rong Z, et al. Delivery of infection from asymptomatic carriers of COVID-19 in a familial cluster. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;94:133–138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7129961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32247826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiaoquan Lai, et al. Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-2019) Infection Among Health Care Workers and Implications for Prevention Measures in a Tertiary Hospital in Wuhan, China. JAMA Network Open 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7243089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen LH, et al. Risk of COVID-19 among front-line health-care workers and the general community: a prospective cohort study. Lancet Public Health. 2020;5:e475–e483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7491202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32745512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zabarsky TF, Bhullar D, Silva SY, et al. What are the sources of exposure in healthcare personnel with coronavirus disease 2019 infection? Am J Infect Control. 2020;49:392–395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7419261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32795495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shrestha NK, Canosa MF, Nowacki AS, et al. Distribution of transmission potential during non-severe COVID-19 illness. Clin Infect Dis 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7337652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32594116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roxby AC, Greninger AL, Hatfield KM, et al. Outbreak investigation of COVID-19 among residents and staff of an independent and assisted living community for older adults – Seattle, Washington. JAMA Intern Med. 2020;69:416–418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mani NS, Budak JZ, Lan KF, et al. Prevalence of COVID-19 infection and outcomes among asymptomatic healthcare workers in Seattle, Washington. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:2702–2707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7337651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32548613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ran L, Chen X, Wang Y, et al. Risk factors of healthcare workers with corona virus disease 2019: A retrospective cohort study in a designated hospital of Wuhan in China. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:2218–2221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32179890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giannis D, Geropoulos G, Matenoglou E, et al. Impact of coronavirus disease 2019 on healthcare workers: beyond the risk of exposure. Postgrad Med J. 2020;0:1–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10016952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32561596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anelli F, Leoni G, Monaco R, et al. Italian doctors call for protecting healthcare workers and boosting community surveillance during COVID-19 outbreak. BMJ. 2020;368:m1254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petzold MB, Plag J, Ströhle A. Umgang mit psychischer Belastung bei Gesundheitsfachkräften im Rahmen der COVID-19-Pandemie. Nervenarzt. 2020;91:417–421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7100457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32221635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weaver MD, Landrigan CP, Sullivan JP, et al. The association between resident physician work hour regulations and physician safety and health. Am J Med. 2020;133:e343–e354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7469904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32061733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewey C, Hingle S, Goelz E, et al. Supporting clinicians during the COVID-19 pandemic. Ann Intern Med 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7106065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32196544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenberg N, Docherty M, Gnanapragasam S, et al. Managing mental health challenges faced by healthcare workers during COVID-19 pandemic. BMJ. 2020;368:m1211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>