<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39557875</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2059-0105</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>NPJ vaccines</Title><ISOAbbreviation>NPJ Vaccines</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Obesity does not influence SARS-CoV-2 humoral vaccine immunogenicity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>226</StartPage><MedlinePgn>226</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41541-024-01022-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Obesity is a recognized factor influencing immune function and infectious disease outcomes. Characterization of the influence of obesity on SARS-CoV-2 humoral vaccine immunogenicity is required to properly tailor vaccine type (mRNA, viral-vector, protein subunit vaccines) and dosing schedule. Data from a prospective cohort study collected over 34 months was used to evaluate the slope of antibody production and decay and neutralizing capacity following SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in individuals with and without obesity at baseline. Most participants were female (65.4%), white (92.4%), and received mRNA vaccines. 210 were obese and 697 non-obese. Sex and infection-acquired immunity were identified as effect modifiers for the relationship between obesity and COVID-19 vaccine humoral immunogenicity. No consistent influence of obesity on peak titres, titre retention, antibody isotype (IgG, IgM, IgA), or neutralization was identified when controlling for other key variables. It may not be necessary to consider this variable when developing SARS-CoV-2 vaccine dosing strategies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>D'Souza</LastName><ForeName>Mathieu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Keeshan</LastName><ForeName>Alexa</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Epidemiology and Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gravel</LastName><ForeName>Christopher A</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Epidemiology and Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Occupational Health, McGill University, Montreal, QC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Data Literacy Research Institute, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Langlois</LastName><ForeName>Marc-André</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Microbiology and Immunology, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cooper</LastName><ForeName>Curtis L</ForeName><Initials>CL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, Ottawa, ON, Canada. ccooper@toh.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Epidemiology and Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON, Canada. ccooper@toh.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON, Canada. ccooper@toh.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>424425</GrantID><Acronym>CAPMC</Acronym><Agency> CIHR</Agency><Country>Canada</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>424425</GrantID><Acronym>CAPMC</Acronym><Agency> CIHR</Agency><Country>Canada</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>156941</GrantID><Agency>Coronavirus Variants Rapid Response Network (CoVaRR-Net)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>156941</GrantID><Agency>Coronavirus Variants Rapid Response Network (CoVaRR-Net)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>NPJ Vaccines</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101699863</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2059-0105</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement><b>Competing interests</b> The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41541-024-01022-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41541-024-01022-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hu, B., Guo, H., Zhou, P. &amp; Shi, Z. L. Characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 19, 141 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-00459-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33024307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J. J., Dong, X., Liu, G. H. &amp; Gao, Y. D. Risk and Protective Factors for COVID-19 Morbidity, Severity, and Mortality. Clin. Rev. Allergy Immunol. 64, 90 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12016-022-08921-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35044620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falahi, S. &amp; Kenarkoohi, A. Host factors and vaccine efficacy: Implications for COVID‐19 vaccines. J. Med Virol. 94, 1330 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34845730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmermann, P. &amp; Curtis, N. Factors That Influence the Immune Response to Vaccination. Clin. Microbiol. Rev. 32, e00084-18 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popkin, B. M. et al. Individuals with obesity and COVID-19: A global perspective on the epidemiology and biological relationships. Obes. Rev. 21, e13128 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/obr.13128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32845580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7461480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faizo, A. A. et al. A potential association between obesity and reduced effectiveness of COVID‐19 vaccine‐induced neutralizing humoral immunity. J. Med. Virol. 95, e28130 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kara, Z. et al. Antibody Response to SARS-CoV-2 Vaccines in People with Severe Obesity. Obes. Surg. 32, 2987–2993 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11695-022-06181-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35802279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9263798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ou, X. et al. Antibody responses to COVID‐19 vaccination in people with obesity: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Influenza Other Respir. Viruses 17, e13078 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Klaauw, A. A. et al. Accelerated waning of the humoral response to COVID-19 vaccines in obesity. Nat. Med 29, 1146 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-023-02343-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37169862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10202802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levin, E. G. et al. Waning Immune Humoral Response to BNT162b2 Covid-19 Vaccine over 6 Months. N. Engl. J. Med. 385, e84 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lobstein, T., Jackson-Leach, R., Powis, J., Brinsden, H. &amp; Gray, M. World Obesity Atlas 2023. (World Obesity Federation, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Controlling the global obesity epidemic. https://www.who.int/activities/controlling-the-global-obesity-epidemic (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pugliese, G. et al. Obesity and infectious diseases: pathophysiology and epidemiology of a double pandemic condition. Int J. Obes. (Lond.) 46, 449–465 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41366-021-01035-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35058571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obesity, Race/Ethnicity, and COVID-19, Overweight Obesity, CDC. https://www.cdc.gov/obesity/data/obesity-and-covid-19.html (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasr, M. J. C., Geerling, E. &amp; Pinto, A. K. Impact of Obesity on Vaccination to SARS-CoV-2. Front. Endocrinol. 13, 898810 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szczerbiński, Ł. et al. Immune Response to Vaccination against COVID-19 at Different Second-Dose Intervals and Their Associations with Metabolic Parameters. Vaccines 11, 149 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kara, Z. et al. Risk Factors Influencing Seroconversion after Inactive SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination in People Living with Obesity. Res. Artic. Obes. Facts 15, 648–654 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000525555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nam, S. Y., Jeon, S. W., Jung, D. K. &amp; Heo, S. J. Body Weight is Inversely Associated with Anti-SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Levels after BNT162b2 mRNA Vaccination in Young and Middle Aged Adults. Infect. Chemother. 54, 504 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3947/ic.2022.0089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36196609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9533164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellini, R. et al. Early Onset of SARS-COV-2 Antibodies after First Dose of BNT162b2: Correlation with Age, Gender and BMI. Vaccines 9, 685 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golec, M. et al. Relationship between anthropometric and body composition parameters and anti-SARS-CoV-2 specific IgG titers in females vaccinated against COVID-19 according to the heterologous vaccination course: A cohort study. PLoS One 18, e0287128 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phumisantiphong, U. et al. Comparison of antibody responses before and after booster doses with the Pfizer-BioNTech or Oxford–AstraZeneca vaccines in healthcare workers in Thailand. Vaccine X 13, 100277 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, Y., Zhang, H., Meng, L., Li, F. &amp; Yu, C. Comparison of Immune Responses Elicited by SARS-CoV-2 mRNA and Recombinant Protein Vaccine Candidates. Front. Immunol. 13, 906457 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naranbhai, V. et al. Comparative Immunogenicity and Effectiveness of mRNA-1273, BNT162b2, and Ad26.COV2.S COVID-19 Vaccines. J. Infect. Dis. 225, 1141 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiab593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34888672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben Ahmed, M. et al. Humoral and Cellular Immunogenicity of Six Different Vaccines against SARS-CoV-2 in Adults: A Comparative Study in Tunisia (North Africa). Vaccines 10, 1189 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Self, W. H. et al. Comparative Effectiveness of Moderna, Pfizer-BioNTech, and Janssen (Johnson &amp; Johnson) Vaccines in Preventing COVID-19 Hospitalizations Among Adults Without Immunocompromising Conditions — United States, March–August 2021. Morbidity Mortal. Wkly. Rep. 70, 1337 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7038e1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong, M. Z. W. et al. Elevated BMI reduces the humoral response to SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Clin. Transl Immunol. 12, e1476 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balkan, İ. İ. et al. Waning immunity to inactive SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in healthcare workers: booster required. Ir. J. Med Sci. 192, 19 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11845-022-02984-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35344137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotsiou, O. S. et al. The Comparative Superiority of SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Response in Different Immunization Scenarios. J. Pers. Med. 12, 1756 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hidayat, R. et al. Evaluation of SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Response Post Third Dose COVID-19 mRNA Vaccination at Universitas Indonesia Hospital. Acta Med. Acad. 51, 69 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5644/ama2006-124.374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36317998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9982858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayart, J. L. et al. Confounding factors influencing the kinetics and magnitude of serological response following administration of nt162b2. Microorganisms 9, 1340 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms9061340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34205564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8235462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellini, R. et al. Initial observations on age, gender, BMI and hypertension in antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2 BNT162b2 vaccine. EClinicalMedicine 36, 100928 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34109307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8177433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Held, J. et al. Reactogenicity correlates only weakly with humoral immunogenicity after COVID-19 vaccination with BNT162b2 mRNA (Comirnaty®). Vaccines 9, 1063 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali, H. et al. Robust Antibody Levels in Both Diabetic and Non-Diabetic Individuals After BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 Vaccination. Front. Immunol. 12, 752233 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.752233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34899701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8652288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bates, J. T. et al. IgG Antibody Response to the Pfizer BNT162b2 SARS-CoV-2 Vaccine in Healthcare Workers with Healthy Weight, Overweight, and Obesity. Vaccines 10, 512 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, J., Mu, H., Pan, X. &amp; Guo, W. Studying the effects of booster shots and antibody responses to the SARS-CoV-2 vaccination over time in health personnel. Front. Cell Infect. Microbiol. 13, 1138631 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2023.1138631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37009493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10060948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, A. K. et al. Humoral antibody kinetics with ChAdOx1-nCOV (Covishield<sup>TM</sup>) and BBV-152 (Covaxin<sup>TM</sup>) vaccine among Indian Healthcare workers: A 6-month longitudinal cross-sectional Coronavirus Vaccine-induced antibody titre (COVAT) study. Diabetes Metab. Syndr. 16, 102424 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2022.102424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35150961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8816907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherry, N. et al. Determinants of SARS-CoV-2 IgG response and decay in Canadian healthcare workers: A prospective cohort study. Vaccine 42, 1168–1178 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2024.01.052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38278628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campo, F. et al. Antibody Persistence 6 Months Post-Vaccination with BNT162b2 among Health Care Workers. Vaccines 9, 1125 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barocci, S. et al. Evaluation of Two-Month Antibody Levels after Heterologous ChAdOx1-S/BNT162b2 Vaccination Compared to Homologous ChAdOx1-S or BNT162b2 Vaccination. Vaccines 10, 491 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coggins, S. A. et al. Adverse Effects and Antibody Titers in Response to the BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 Vaccine in a Prospective Study of Healthcare Workers. Open Forum Infect. Dis. 9, ofab575 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papaioannidou, P. et al. Age, Sex and BMI Relations with Anti-SARS-CoV-2-Spike IgG Antibodies after BNT162b2 COVID-19 Vaccine in Health Care Workers in Northern Greece. Microorganisms 11, 1279 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, S. W. et al. Anti-SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein RBD Antibody Levels After Receiving a Second Dose of ChAdOx1 nCov-19 (AZD1222) Vaccine in Healthcare Workers: Lack of Association With Age, Sex, Obesity, and Adverse Reactions. Front. Immunol. 12, 779212 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kara, Z. et al. Antibody Response to Inactive SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination in a Cohort of Elderly Patients Living with Obesity. Obes. Facts 16, 374 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000530315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37231909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10443995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palacka, P. et al. Effectiveness, Adverse Events, and Immune Response Following Double Vaccination with BNT162b2 in Staff at the National Comprehensive Cancer Center (NCCC). Vaccines 10, 558 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10040558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35455308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9026370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe, M. et al. Central obesity, smoking habit, and hypertension are associated with lower antibody titres in response to COVID-19 mRNA vaccine. https://doi.org/10.1002/dmrr.3465 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeshan, A. et al. Results of the Stop the Spread Ottawa (SSO) cohort study: a Canadian urban-based prospective evaluation of antibody responses and neutralisation efficiency to SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination. BMJ Open 13, 77714 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J. S. et al. Demographic and Clinical Factors Associated With SARS-CoV-2 Spike 1 Antibody Response Among Vaccinated US Adults: the C4R Study. Nat Commun 15, 1492 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto, S. et al. Sex‐associated differences between BMI and SARS‐CoV‐2 antibody titers following the BNT162b2 vaccine. Obesity 30, 999 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/oby.23417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35226399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garner-Spitzer, E. et al. Obesity and Sex Affect the Immune Responses to Tick-Borne Encephalitis Booster Vaccination. Front Immunol. 11, 860 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32528467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7266951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AbdelWareth, L. et al. Natural infection versus hybrid (natural and vaccination) humoral immune response to SARS-CoV-2: a comparative paired analysis. Front Immunol. 14, 1230974 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1230974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37720219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10502301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolscheid-Pommerich, R. et al. Correlation between a quantitative anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 IgG ELISA and neutralization activity. J. Med Virol. 94, 388 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34415572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlton, C. et al. COVID-19: A year later: Practical guidance for clinical laboratories for SARS-CoV-2 serology testing. Can. Communicable Dis. Rep. 47, 171 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14745/ccdr.v47i04a01</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takahashi, T. et al. Assessment of antibody dynamics and neutralizing activity using serological assay after SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination. PLoS One 18, e0291670 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung, K. et al. Performance evaluation of three automated quantitative immunoassays and their correlation with a surrogate virus neutralization test in coronavirus disease 19 patients and pre‐pandemic controls. J. Clin. Lab. Anal. 35, e23921 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoury, D. S. et al. Correlates of Protection, Thresholds of Protection, and Immunobridging among Persons with SARS-CoV-2 Infection. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 29, 381 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid2902.221422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36692375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9881762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cromer, D. et al. Neutralising antibody titres as predictors of protection against SARS-CoV-2 variants and the impact of boosting: a meta-analysis. Lancet Microbe 3, e52 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00267-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34806056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cromer, D. et al. Predicting vaccine effectiveness against severe COVID-19 over time and against variants: a meta-analysis. Nat. Commun. 14, 1633 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauvin, C., Retnakumar, S. V. &amp; Bayry, J. Obesity negatively impacts maintenance of antibody response to COVID-19 vaccines. Cell Rep. Med. 4, 101117 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vulturar, D. M. et al. Obesity Impact on SARS-CoV-2 Infection: Pros and Cons ‘Obesity Paradox’-A Systematic Review. J. Clin. Med. 11, 3844 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, D.-Y. et al. Effectiveness of Covid-19 Vaccines over a 9-Month Period in North Carolina. N. Engl. J. Med. 386, 933–941 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2117128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35020982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauring, A. S. et al. Clinical severity of, and effectiveness of mRNA vaccines against, covid-19 from omicron, delta, and alpha SARS-CoV-2 variants in the United States: prospective observational study. The BMJ 376, e069761 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin, S. C. et al. Cytokine fingerprint differences following infection and vaccination - what can we learn from COVID-19? Eur. Cytokine Netw. 35, 13–19 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1684/ecn.2024.0494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38909356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Meara, T. R. et al. Reduced SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine immunogenicity and protection in mice with diet-induced obesity and insulin resistance. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 152, 1107–1120.e6 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2023.06.031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37595760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10841117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y. et al. COVID-19 mRNA vaccine protects against SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA.1 infection in diet-induced obese mice through boosting host innate antiviral responses. EBioMedicine 89, 104485 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chambers, E. S. et al. Influence of individuals’ determinants including vaccine type on cellular and humoral responses to SARS-CoV-2 vaccination. NPJ Vaccines 9, 87 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, H. et al. Immunogenicity after Second ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 (AZD1222) Vaccination According to the Individual Reactogenicity, Health Status and Lifestyle. Vaccines 9, 1473 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herzberg, J. et al. Persistence of Immune Response in Health Care Workers After Two Doses BNT162b2 in a Longitudinal Observational Study. Front. Immunol. 13, 839922 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, Q. et al. Weakened humoral and cellular immune response to the inactivated COVID-19 vaccines in Chinese individuals with obesity/overweight. Genes Dis. 10, 608–617 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gendis.2022.10.023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36466314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, J. et al. Comparative effectiveness of BNT162b2 and ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccines against COVID-19. BMC Med 21, 78 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collins, E. et al. Cohort profile: Stop the Spread Ottawa (SSO)-a community-based prospective cohort study on antibody responses, antibody neutralisation efficiency and cellular immunity to SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination. BMJ Open 12, 62187 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-062187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>About Adult BMI. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention https://www.cdc.gov/healthyweight/assessing/bmi/adult_bmi/index.html (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colwill, K. et al. A scalable serology solution for profiling humoral immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination. Clin. Transl. Immunol. 11, e1380 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cti2.1380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forgacs, D. et al. SARS-CoV-2 mRNA Vaccines Elicit Different Responses in Immunologically Naïve and Pre-Immune Humans. Front. Immunol. 12, 728021 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nam, S. Y. et al. Demographic and Clinical Factors Associated With Anti–SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Levels After 2 BNT162b2 mRNA Vaccine Doses. JAMA Netw. Open 5, E2212996 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.12996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35587345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9121186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bürkner, P.-C. Bayesian Regression Models using ‘Stan’. vol. 2.21.0. https://cloud.r-project.org/web/packages/brms/index.html , https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/brms/brms.pdf (2024).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>