<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39557412</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-2659</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>18</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Influenza and other respiratory viruses</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Technological Barriers to Routine Genomic Surveillance for Vaccine Development Against SARS-CoV-2 in Africa: A Systematic Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70047</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70047</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/irv.70047</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The Global Initiative on Sharing All Influenza Data, a public-access database for sharing severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 genomic sequencing data, has received significantly less data from African countries compared to the global total. Furthermore, the contribution of these data was infrequent and, for some countries, non-existent. The primary aim of this review is to identify the technological barriers to routine genomic surveillance in Africa. PubMed and Google Scholar were searched for the relevant articles, and other eligible articles were identified from the reference list examination according to the PRISMA checklist. Eighty-four full-text articles were analysed for eligibility, and 49 published full-texted articles were included in the final qualitative analysis. The main technological barriers identified were limited genomic surveillance capacity, limited genomic sequencing infrastructure, lack of resources and skilled or trained scientists, and the high cost of importing, establishing, and maintaining a genomic sequencing facility. The Africa Pathogen Genomics Initiative aims to improve genomic surveillance capacity across Africa, through resources, training, education, infrastructure, and regional sequencing centres. Furthermore, collaborations between African governments and international partners or national, private, and academic institutions are imperative to sustain genomic surveillance in Africa, and investment in genomic sequencing and research and development is paramount. Longer turnaround times interfere with global viral evolution monitoring and national implementation of effective policies to reduce the burden and disease. Establishing effective genomic surveillance systems guides public health responses and vaccine development for diseases endemic in Africa.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Influenza and Other Respiratory Viruses published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Konono</LastName><ForeName>Kimberly Cheryl Chido</ForeName><Initials>KCC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, University of Siena, Siena, SI, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Msusa</LastName><ForeName>Keiko</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Clinical Development and Operations, BioNTech SE, Mainz, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Operations, TRIFT Alliance Ltd, Kigali, Rwanda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mpinganjira</LastName><ForeName>Samuel</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, University of Siena, Siena, SI, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amani</LastName><ForeName>Adidja</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, University of Siena, Siena, SI, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nyagupe</LastName><ForeName>Charles</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Microbiology Research Laboratory, Harare Central Hospital, Harare, Zimbabwe.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ngigi</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, University of Siena, Siena, SI, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101304007</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1750-2640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000349" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Africa</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D023281" MajorTopicYN="Y">Genomics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000087506" MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine Development</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016679" MajorTopicYN="N">Genome, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Africa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">genomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">technological barriers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine development</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/irv.70047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>M. T. Adil, R. D. Rumana, J. Vigyan, et al., “SARS‐CoV‐2 and the Pandemic of Covid‐19,” Postgraduate Medical Journal 97, no. 1144 (2021): 110–116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation, “WHO Coronavirus (Covid‐19) Dashboard,” (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GISAID, “Submission Tracker Global 2022,” https://www.gisaid.org/submission‐tracker‐global/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronaviridae Study Group of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses, “The Species Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome‐Related Coronavirus: Classifying 2019‐nCoV and Naming It SARS‐CoV‐2,” Nature Microbiology 5, no. 4 (2020): 536–544.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Zhou, Y. Qiu, and X. Ge, “The Taxonomy, Host Range and Pathogenicity of Coronaviruses and Other Viruses in the Nidovirales Order,” Animal Diseases 1, no. 1 (2021): 1–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. C. Bergmann and R. H. Silverman, “Covid‐19: Coronavirus Replication, Pathogenesis, and Therapeutic Strategies,” Cleveland Clinic Journal of Medicine 87, no. 6 (2020): 321–327.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Lamptey, F. O. Oyelami, M. Owusu, et al., “Genomic and Epidemiological Characteristics of SARS‐CoV‐2 in Africa,” PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases 15, no. 4 (2021): 1–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. D. Robishaw, S. M. Alter, J. J. Solano, et al., “Genomic Surveillance to Combat COVID‐19: Challenges and Opportunities,” Lancet Microbe 2, no. 9 (2021): e481–e484.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Hirabara, T. D. A. Serdan, R. Gorjao, et al., “SARS‐COV‐2 Variants: Differences and Potential of Immune Evasion,” Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology 11 (2021): 1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Wahid, A. Jawed, R. K. Mandal, et al., “Variants of SARS‐CoV‐2, Their Effects on Infection, Transmission, and Neutralization by Vaccine‐Induced Antibodies,” European Review for Medical and Pharmacological Sciences 25, no. 18 (2021): 5857–5864.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Deb, M. M. A. Molla, K. Saif‐Ur‐Rahman, M. C. Das, and D. Das, “A Review of Epidemiology, Clinical Features and Disease Course, Transmission Dynamics, and Neutralization Efficacy of SARS‐CoV‐2 Variants,” Egyptian Journal of Bronchology 15, no. 1 (2021): 1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, “Variants and Genomic Surveillance for SARS‐CoV‐2,” (2022), https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019‐ncov/variants/variant‐surveillance.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. C. M. Kirsebom, N. Andrews, J. Stowe, et al., “Covid‐19 Vaccine Effectiveness Against the Omicron (BA.2) Variant in England,” Lancet Infectious Diseases 22 (2022): 931–933.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GISAID, “Tracking of hCoV‐19 Variants,” (2024), https://gisaid.org/hcov19‐variants/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation, “Global Genomic Surveillance Strategy for Pathogens With Pandemic and Epidemic Potential, 2022–2032,” (2022), https://www.who.int/initiatives/genomic‐surveillance‐strategy.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, “What Is Genomic Surveillance?,” (2022), https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019‐ncov/variants/genomic‐surveillance.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation, “The Effects of Virus Variants on COVID‐19 Vaccines,” (2021), https://www.who.int/news‐room/feature‐stories/detail/the‐effects‐of‐virus‐variants‐on‐covid‐19‐vaccines.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. J. Page, D. Moher, P. M. Bossuyt, et al., “PRISMA 2020 Explanation and Elaboration: Updated Guidance and Exemplars for Reporting Systematic Reviews,” BMJ 372 (2022): 1–36, https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.n160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Adepoju, “Challenges of SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance in Africa,” Lancet Microbe 2, no. 4 (2021): 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Al Kalamouni, F. F. Abou Hassan, M. Bou Hamdan, et al., “Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 in COVID‐19 Vaccinated Healthcare Workers in Lebanon,” BMC Medical Genomics 16, no. 1 (2023): 1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Bahouq, M. Bahouq, and A. Soulaymani, “Overview of Genomic Surveillance Related to Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS‐CoV‐2),” E3S Web of Conferences 319 (2021): 1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. F. Brito, E. Semenova, G. Dudas, et al., “Global Disparities in SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance,” Nature Communications 13, no. 1 (2022): 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Butera, S. L. Hong, M. Semakula, et al., “SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance in Rwanda: Introductions and Local Transmission of the B.1.617.2 (Delta) Variant of Concern,” medRxiv [Preprint], (2022);1–42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Butera, E. Mukantwari, M. Artesi, et al., “Genomic Sequencing of SARS‐CoV‐2 in Rwanda Reveals the Importance of Incoming Travelers on Lineage Diversity,” Nature Communications 12, no. 1 (2021): 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Chen, A. S. Azman, X. Chen, et al., “Global Landscape of SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance and Data Sharing,” Nature Genetics 54, no. 4 (2022): 499–507.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Cyranoski, “Alarming COVID Variants Show the Vital Role of Genomic Surveillance,” Nature 589, no. 7842 (2021): 337–338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Dzinamarira, S. Mukwenha, Z. Mukandavire, et al., “Insights From Zimbabwe's SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance,” Lancet Global Health 9, no. 12 (2021): e1624–e1625, https://doi.org/10.1016/s2214‐109x(21)00451‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Furuse, “Genomic Sequencing Effort for SARS‐CoV‐2 by Country During the Pandemic,” International Journal of Infectious Diseases 103 (2021): 305–307.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. X. Han, A. Toporowski, J. A. Sacks, et al., “Low Testing Rates Limit the Ability of Genomic Surveillance Programs to Monitor SARS‐CoV‐2 Variants: A Mathematical Modelling Study,” medRxiv [Preprint], (2022);1–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. K. Harsha, C. Pattabiraman, A. K. George, et al., “The Role of SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance and Innovative Analytical Platforms for Informing Public Health Preparedness in Bengaluru, India,” medRxiv [Preprint]. 2022;1–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Hosch, M. Mpina, E. Nyakurungu, et al., “Genomic Surveillance Enables the Identification of Co‐infections With Multiple SARS‐CoV‐2 Lineages in Equatorial Guinea,” Frontiers in Public Health 9 (2021): 1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Kalia, G. Saberwal, and G. Sharma, “The Lag in SARS‐CoV‐2 Genome Submissions to GISAID,” Nature Biotechnology 39, no. 9 (2021): 1058–1060.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. O. Kuja, B. N. Kanoi, C. Shiluli, et al., “Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 Reveals Diverse Circulating Variant Lineages in Nairobi and Kiambu County, Kenya,” BMC Genomics 23 (2022): 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. Mahanta, G. Saberwal, and G. Sharma, “Are Countries Becoming Better at SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance?,” Frontiers in Public Health 10 (2022): 1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. S. Malick and H. Fernandes, “The Genomic Landscape of SARS‐CoV‐2: Surveillance of Variants of Concern,” Advances in Molecular Pathology 4 (2021): 231–235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Mashe, F. T. Takawira, L. de Oliveira Martins, et al., “Genomic Epidemiology and the Role of International and Regional Travel in the SARS‐CoV‐2 Epidemic in Zimbabwe: A Retrospective Study of Routinely Collected Surveillance Data,” Lancet Global Health 9, no. 12 (2021): e1658–e1666.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Menon, “Genomic Sequence of Worldwide Strains of SARS‐CoV‐2: Insights on the Role of Variants in Disease Epidemiology,” International Journal of Advanced Research and Development (IJARD) 6, no. 4 (2021): 14–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Merhi, J. Koweyes, T. Salloum, C. A. Khoury, S. Haidar, and S. Tokajian, “SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Epidemiology: Data and Sequencing Infrastructure,” Future Microbiology 17 (2022): 1001–1007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Murewanhema, F. Mutsigiri‐Murewanhema, and E. Kunonga, “Enhancing SARS‐CoV‐2 Surveillance Through Regular Genomic Sequencing Is an Essential Element of COVID‐19 Control in Resource‐Limited Settings,” Pan African Medical Journal 41 (2022): 88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Napit, P. Manandhar, A. Chaudhary, et al., “Rapid Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 in a Dense Urban Community of Kathmandu Valley Using Sewage Samples,” PLoS ONE 18, no. 3 (2023): 1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Ntoumi, C. C. Mfoutou Mapanguy, A. Tomazatos, et al., “Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 in the Republic of Congo,” International Journal of Infectious Diseases 105 (2021): 735–738.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. A. Ortiz‐Pineda and C. H. Sierra‐Torres, “Evolutionary Traits and Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 in South America,” Global Health, Epidemiology and Genomics 2022 (2022): 1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. B. Pisano, P. Sicilia, M. Zeballos, et al., “SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance Enables the Identification of Delta/Omicron Co‐infections in Argentina,” Frontiers in Virology 2 (2022): 1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. M. Romano and F. L. Melo, “Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2: A Race Against Time,” Lancet Regional Health–Americas 1 (2021): 1–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. S. Salles, A. C. Cavalcanti, F. B. da Costa, et al., “Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 Spike Gene by Sanger Sequencing,” PLoS ONE 17, no. 1 (2022): 1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. O. Shaibu, C. K. Onwuamah, A. B. James, et al., “Full‐Length Genomic Sanger Sequencing and Phylogenetic Analysis of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS‐CoV‐2) in Nigeria,” PLoS ONE 16, no. 1 (2021): 1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Souho, L. Lamboni, B. M. Bakadia, E. Taale, K. K. Palanga, and S. K. Amouzou, “Study of the SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Data Generation to Evaluate the Introduction of Genomics in Epidemiological Surveillance and Public Health Decision‐Making,” Pan African Medical Journal 41, no. 55 (2022): 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Tegally, J. E. San, M. Cotten, et al., “The Evolving SARS‐CoV‐2 Epidemic in Africa: Insights From Rapidly Expanding Genomic Surveillance,” Science 368, no. 6615 (2022): 1–58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Wilkinson, M. Giovanetti, H. Tegally, et al., “A Year of Genomic Surveillance Reveals How the SARS‐CoV‐2 Pandemic Unfolded in Africa,” Science 374, no. 6566 (2021): 423–431.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Chen, A. S. Azman, X. Chen, et al., “Global Landscape of SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance and Data Sharing,” Nat Genet 54, no. 4 (2022): 499–507, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588‐022‐01033‐y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Adepoju, “African Coronavirus Surveillance Network Provides Early Warning for World,” Nature Biotechnology 40, no. 2 (2022): 147–148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Andersen, L. T. Mamo, and O. Sisay, “Variants in Africa: Recommendations for Preventing an Enduring Pandemic,” Tony Blair Institute for Global Change, (2021), https://institute.global/sites/default/files/articles/Variants‐in‐Africa‐Recommendations‐for‐Preventing‐an‐Enduring‐Pandemic.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Dzobo, G. Musuka, T. Mashe, and T. Dzinamarira, “Inadequate SARS‐CoV‐2 Genetic Sequencing Capacity in Zimbabwe: A Call to Urgently Address This Key Gap to Control Current and Future Waves,” IJID Regions 1 (2021): 3–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Giandhari, S. Pillay, E. Wilkinson, et al., “Early Transmission of SARS‐CoV‐2 in South Africa: An Epidemiological and Phylogenetic Report,” International Journal of Infectious Diseases 103 (2021): 234–241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. C. Inzaule, S. K. Tessema, Y. Kebede, A. E. Ogwell Ouma, and J. N. Nkengasong, “Genomic‐Informed Pathogen Surveillance in Africa: Opportunities and Challenges,” Lancet Infectious Diseases 21, no. 9 (2021): e281–e289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Makoni, “Africa's $100‐Million Pathogen Genomics Initiative,” Lancet Microbe 1 (2020): e318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Mashe, F. T. Takawira, H. Gumbo, et al., “Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 in Zimbabwe Shows Dominance of Variants of Concern,” Lancet Microbe 2, no. 5 (2021): e177, https://doi.org/10.1016/s2666‐5247(21)00061‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Mboowa, S. Mwesigwa, D. Kateete, et al., “Whole‐Genome Sequencing of SARS‐CoV‐2 in Uganda: Implementation of the Low‐Cost Artic Protocol in Resource‐Limited Settings,” F1000Research 10 (2021): 1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Msomi, K. Mlisana, T. De Oliveira, et al., “A Genomics Network Established to Respond Rapidly to Public Health Threats in South Africa,” Lancet Microbe 1, no. 6 (2020): e229–e230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>“Statement on Variants of SARS‐CoV‐2 in Nigeria [Press Release],” Nigeria Centre for Disease Control, (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. K. Onwuamah, A. Kanteh, B. S. Abimbola, et al., “SARS‐CoV‐2 Sequencing Collaboration in West Africa Shows Best Practices,” Lancet Global Health 9, no. 11 (2021): e1499–e1500.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Otu, E. Agogo, and B. Ebenso, “Africa Needs More Genome Sequencing to Tackle New Variants of SARS‐CoV‐2,” Nature Medicine 27, no. 5 (2021): 744–745.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Pillay, J. Giandhari, H. Tegally, et al., “Whole Genome Sequencing of SARS‐CoV‐2: Adapting Illumina Protocols for Quick and Accurate Outbreak Investigation During a Pandemic,” Genes 11, no. 8 (2020): 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. K. Tessema, S. C. Inzaule, A. Christoffels, et al., “Accelerating Genomics‐Based Surveillance for Covid‐19 Response in Africa,” Lancet Microbe 1, no. 6 (2020): e227–e228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Viana, S. Moyo, D. G. Amoako, et al., “Rapid Epidemic Expansion of the SARS‐CoV‐2 Omicron Variant in Southern Africa,” Nature 603, no. 7902 (2022): 679–686.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO, “Guidance for Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 Variants: Interim Guidance, 9 August 2021.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Abrudan, A. Matimba, D. Nikolic, et al., “Train‐the‐Trainer as an Effective Approach to Building Global Networks of Experts in Genomic Surveillance of Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR),” Clinical Infectious Diseases 73, no. Suppl_4 (2021): S283–s289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID‐19 Genomics UK (COG‐UK) consortium, “How the COVID‐19 Pandemic and Viral Genomic Sequencing Could Change the UK's Approach to Infection Control,” (2022), https://www.cogconsortium.uk/how‐the‐covid‐19‐pandemic‐and‐viral‐genomic‐sequencing‐could‐change‐the‐uks‐approach‐to‐infection‐control/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. I. Nelson and P. Thielen, “Coordinating SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance in the United States,” Virus Evolution 7, no. 2 (2021): veab053.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Ariani, “Large Scale Genomic Surveillance of SARS‐CoV‐2 in the UK: Challenges and Lessons Learned,” Pan American Health Organization, (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artic Network, “SARS‐CoV‐2,” (2020), https://artic.network/ncov‐2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CD Genomics, “How Does Amplicon‐Based Target Enrichment Work for Disease Panel,” (2022), https://www.cd‐genomics.com/diseasepanel/how‐does‐amplicon‐based‐target‐enrichment‐work‐for‐disease‐panel.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation, “Genomic Sequencing of SARS‐CoV‐2: A Guide to Implementation for Maximum Impact on Public Health,” (2021), https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240018440.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>“Covid‐19 Genome Sequencing Laboratory Network Launches in Africa [Press Release],” Africa CDC, (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID‐19 Genomics UK (COG‐UK) consortium, “An Integrated National Scale SARS‐CoV‐2 Genomic Surveillance Network,” Lancet Microbe 1, no. 3 (2020): e99–e100.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>