<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39556882</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0258</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Statistics in medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Stat Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Reinforced Borrowing Framework: Leveraging Auxiliary Data for Individualized Inference.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/sim.10267</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Increasingly during the past decade, researchers have sought to leverage auxiliary data for enhancing individualized inference. Many existing methods, such as multisource exchangeability models (MEM), have been developed to borrow information from multiple supplemental sources to support parameter inference in a primary source. MEM and its alternatives decide how much information to borrow based on the exchangeability of the primary and supplemental sources, where exchangeability is defined as equality of the target parameter. Other information that may also help determine the exchangeability of sources is ignored. In this article, we propose a generalized reinforced borrowing framework (RBF) leveraging auxiliary data for enhancing individualized inference using a distance-embedded prior which uses data not only about the target parameter but also uses different types of auxiliary information sources to "reinforce" inference on the target parameter. RBF improves inference with minimal additional computational burden. We demonstrate the application of RBF to a study investigating the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on individual activity and transportation behaviors, where RBF achieves 20%-40% lower MSE compared with existing methods.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Statistics in Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Ziyu</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2612-0524</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Biostatistics &amp; Health Data Science, School of Public Health, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wolfson</LastName><ForeName>Julian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Biostatistics &amp; Health Data Science, School of Public Health, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Stat Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8215016</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0277-6715</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bayesian method</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">individualized inference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multisource data borrowing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">supplemental data</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39556882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/sim.10267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>S. R. Steinhubl, E. D. Muse, and E. J. Topol, “The Emerging Field of Mobile Health,” Science Translational Medicine 7, no. 283 (2015): 283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Cai, R. Chen, and X. Mg, “Individualized Inference Through Fusion Learning,” Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Computational Statistics 12, no. 5 (2020): 1498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Shen, R. Y. Liu, and M. Xie, “iFusion: Individualized Fusion Learning,” Journal of the American Statistical Association 115, no. 531 (2020): 1251–1267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhou, J. Ding, K. M. Tan, and V. Tarokh, “Model Linkage Selection for Cooperative Learning,” Journal of Machine Learning Research 22 (2021): 256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhang, L. Deng, M. Schiffman, J. Qin, and K. Yu, “Generalized Integration Model for Improved Statistical Inference by Leveraging External Summary Data,” Biometrika 107, no. 3 (2020): 689–703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Kaizer, B. P. Hobbs, and J. S. Koopmeiners, “A Multi‐Source Adaptive Platform Design for Testing Sequential Combinatorial Therapeutic Strategies,” Biometrics 74, no. 3 (2018): 1082–1094.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. A. Hoeting, D. Madigan, A. E. Raftery, and C. T. Volinsky, “Bayesian Model Averaging: A Tutorial,” Statistical Science 14, no. 4 (1999): 382–417.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. M. Fragoso, W. Bertoli, and F. Louzada, “Bayesian Model Averaging: A Systematic Review and Conceptual Classification,” International Statistical Review 86, no. 1 (2018): 1–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Berry, J. K. Wathen, and M. Newell, “Bayesian Model Averaging in Meta‐Analysis: Vitamin E Supplementation and Mortality,” Clinical Trials 6, no. 1 (2009): 28–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. H. Wright, “Forecasting US Inflation by Bayesian Model Averaging,” Journal of Forecasting 28, no. 2 (2009): 131–144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. E. Raftery, T. Gneiting, F. Balabdaoui, and M. Polakowski, “Using Bayesian Model Averaging to Calibrate Forecast Ensembles,” Monthly Weather Review 133, no. 5 (2005): 1155–1174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Neuenschwander, S. Wandel, S. Roychoudhury, and S. Bailey, “Robust Exchangeability Designs for Early Phase Clinical Trials With Multiple Strata,” Pharmaceutical Statistics 15, no. 2 (2016): 123–134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. P. Hobbs and R. Landin, “Bayesian Basket Trial Design With Exchangeability Monitoring,” Statistics in Medicine 37, no. 25 (2018): 3557–3572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Kaizer, J. S. Koopmeiners, M. J. Kane, S. Roychoudhury, D. S. Hong, and B. P. Hobbs, “Basket Designs: Statistical Considerations for Oncology Trials,” JCO Precision Oncology 3 (2019): 1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Brown, Y. Fan, K. Das, and J. Wolfson, “Iterated Multisource Exchangeability Models for Individualized Inference With an Application to Mobile Sensor Data,” Biometrics 77, no. 2 (2021): 401–412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Kotalik, D. M. Vock, E. C. Donny, D. K. Hatsukami, and J. S. Koopmeiners, “Dynamic Borrowing in the Presence of Treatment Effect Heterogeneity,” Biostatistics 22, no. 4 (2021): 789–804.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. X. Ling, B. P. Hobbs, A. M. Kaizer, and J. S. Koopmeiners, “Calibrated Dynamic Borrowing Using Capping Priors,” Journal of Biopharmaceutical Statistics 31, no. 6 (2021): 852–867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Ji and J. Wolfson, “A Flexible Bayesian Framework for Individualized Inference via Adaptive Borrowing,” Biostatistics 24, no. 3 (2023): 669–685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Kaizer, J. S. Koopmeiners, and B. P. Hobbs, “Bayesian Hierarchical Modeling Based on Multisource Exchangeability,” Biostatistics 19, no. 2 (2018): 169–184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Kotalik, D. M. Vock, B. P. Hobbs, and J. S. Koopmeiners, “A Group‐Sequential Randomized Trial Design Utilizing Supplemental Trial Data,” Statistics in Medicine 41, no. 4 (2022): 698–718.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Morita, P. F. Thall, and P. Müller, “Determining the Effective Sample Size of a Parametric Prior,” Biometrics 64, no. 2 (2008): 595–602.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team, R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing (Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing, 2021), https://www.R‐project.org/.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>