<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309996</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of education and health promotion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Educ Health Promot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Modeling the structural equations of the corona anxiety level based on psychological hardness and physical activities in the treatment staff of Ilam Province with the mediator role of professional identity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>249</StartPage><MedlinePgn>249</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">249</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jehp.jehp_694_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The increase in deaths due to COVID-19 has increased anxiety among the treatment staff. Therefore, the purpose of this research was to model the structural equations of the anxiety level of corona based on psychological hardness and physical activities in the treatment staff of Ilam province with the mediator role of professional identity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Based on the purpose, the method of this research is applied and based on how to obtain the data it is descriptive-correlational. The statistical population of the research includes all the treatment staff of Ilam province, with the number of 1900 people who were selected using Morgan's table, 320 people with the stratified sampling method as the sample. To collect the data, four standard questionnaires were used: Alipour <i>et al</i>. (2020) coronavirus anxiety questionnaire, Kiamarsi <i>et al</i>. (1998) psychological hardness, Baecke <i>et al</i>. (1982) physical activity, Hao <i>et al</i>. (2014) professional identity, and their validity and reliability were also confirmed. To analyze the data, from the indicators of descriptive statistics, Pearson's correlation coefficient test and structural equation model method (SEM) were used using SPSS and Amos software.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The results of the research showed that psychological hardness, physical activities, and professional identity have a significant and inverse effect on the anxiety caused by corona, and the mediator role of professional identity in the relationship between physical activities and corona anxiety was confirmed, but this role was not confirmed in the relationship between psychological hardness and corona anxiety.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">To reduce the anxiety of the coronavirus in the treatment staff, the managers of the health and treatment centers of Ilam province should pay special attention to the employees' perceptions of psychological hardness, physical activities, and professional identity and provide them with the opportunity to create sports activities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Education and Health Promotion.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rezaei</LastName><ForeName>Shamseddin</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Education, Ilam University, Ilam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shams</LastName><ForeName>Morteza</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zoonotic Diseases Research Center, Ilam University of Medical Sciences, Ilam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azizifar</LastName><ForeName>Akbar</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psycholinguistics, School of Medicine, Ilam University of Medical Sciences, Ilam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aibod</LastName><ForeName>Sehat</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Psychosocial Injuries Research Center, Ilam University of Medical Sciences, Ilam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gohari</LastName><ForeName>Ziba</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Master of Sports Management, Ilam University, Ilam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Educ Health Promot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101593794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Corona anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">physical activities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">professional identity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychological hardness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">treatment staff</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_694_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JEHP-13-249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Haji Molla Mirzayi H, Sadegh Poorsaeid Esfahani M, Fazelzadeh R. Establishment a relation between successful fulfillments of strategic planning systems and internal reward of human resource. J Res Hum Resour Manag. 2016;8:131–52. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maiorano T, Vagni M, Giostra V, Pajardi D. COVID-19: Risk factors and protective role of resilience and coping strategies for emergency stress and secondary trauma in medical staff and emergency workers—An online-based inquiry. Sustainability. 2020 Oct 29;12(21):9004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazarpour S, Mehrabizadeh Honarmand M, Enayeti S. Comparison of mental health of shift working nurses. J Med Sci. 2007;6:431–8. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boseley S, Devlin H, Belam M. Coronavirus symptoms: What are they and should I see a doctor. The Guardian. 2020.  
https://www. The guardian. com/world/2020/mar/05/what-iscoronavirus-symptomsinfection-wuhan-chinacovid-19. 
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khani H, Tabarraei A, Moradi A. Survey of coronaviruses infection among patients with flu-like symptoms in the Golestan Province, Iran. Med Lab J. 2018;12:1–4. doi: 10.29252/mlj. 12.6.1. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai CC, Shih TP, Ko WC, Tang HJ, Hsueh PR. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-Cov-2) and coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19): The epidemic and the challenges. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2020;55:112–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32081636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu P, Hao X, Lau EH, Wong JY, Leung KS, Wu JT, et al. Real-time tentative assessment of the epidemiological characteristics of novel coronavirus infections in Wuhan, China, as at 22 January 2020. Eurosurveillance. 2020;25:74–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6988272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31992388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farnoosh G, Alishiri G, Hosseini Zijoud SR, Dorostkar R, Jalali Farahani A. Understanding the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and coronavirus disease base on available evidence-A narrative review. J Mil Med. 2020;22:1–11. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Tang J, Wei F. Updated understanding of the outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) in Wuhan, China. J Med Virol. 2020;396:231–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31994742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C, Wang Y, Li X, Ren L, Zhao J, Hu Y, et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet. 2019;395:497–506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F, Zhao S, Yu B, Chen YM, Wang W, Song ZG, et al. A new coronavirus associated with human respiratory disease in China. Nature. 2020;32:261–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu N, Zhang D, Wang W, Li X, Yang B, Song J, et al. A novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019. N Engl J Med. 2020;1:34–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31978945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan WJ, Ni ZY, Hu Y, Liang WH, Ou CQ, He JX, et al. Clinical characteristics of 2019 novel coronavirus infection in China. medRxiv. 2020;396:477–882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Guan X, Wu P, Wang X, Zhou L, Tong Y, et al. Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus–infected pneumonia. N Engl J Med. 2020;1:202–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7121484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31995857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Jung S-M, Linton NM, Kinoshita R, Yang Y, Hayashi K, et al. The extent of transmission of novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China, 2020. J Clin Med. 2020;9:1–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7073674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31991628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Rabiaah A, Temsah M-H, Al-Eyadhy AA, Hasan GM, Al-Zamil F, Al-Subaie S. Middle East respiratory syndrome-corona virus (MERS-CoV) associated stress among medical students at a university teaching hospital in Saudi Arabia. J Infect Public Health. 2020;13:687–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32001194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajema KL, Oster AM, McGovern OL, Lindstrom S, Stenger MR, Anderson TC, Isenhour C, Clarke KR, Evans ME, Chu VT, Biggs HM. Persons evaluated for 2019 novel coronavirus—United States, January 2020. Morbidity and mortality weekly report. 2020 Feb 2;69(6):166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7017962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32053579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaei SH. The effects of Covid-19 prevalence on the levels of sport activities in Ilamcity. Sociol Stud Youth. 2022;13:99–114. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asnaani A, Tyler J, McCann J, Brown L, Zang Y. Anxiety sensitivity and emotion regulation as mechanisms of successful CBT outcome for anxiety-related disorders in a naturalistic treatment setting. J Affect Disord. 2020;267:86–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32063577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadock BJ, Sadock VA. 10th. Philadephia (PA): Lippincott Williams and Wilkins; 2011. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhlaghifard M, Meraji N. Predicting corona anxiety based on emotional turmoil (depression, anxiety and stress) and spiritual health in nurses and aides. Rooyesh-e-Ravanshenasi Journal (RRJ) 2021;10:161–70. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eskandarnejad M, Alizadeh Z, Molayaei F. The predictive role of physical activity level on the level of anxiety in medical staff during corona peak. Sport Psychol Stud. 2020;9:185–200. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kahvazi A. The relationship between corona anxiety and psychological capital and spirituality. New Ideas Psychol. 2022;12:1–16. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Yang Y, Qiu X, Yang X, Pan H, Ban B, Qiao Z, Wang L, Wang W. Serial multiple mediation of organizational commitment and job burnout in the relationship between psychological capital and anxiety in Chinese female nurses: A cross-sectional questionnaire survey. International journal of nursing studies. 2018 Jul 1;83:75–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29702357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Pan R, Wan X, Tan Y, Xu L, Ho CS, et al. Immediate psychological responses and associated factors during the initial stage of the 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) epidemic among the general population in China. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:1–25. doi: 10.3390/ijerph 17051729.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7084952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32155789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaei S, Salehipour M. Analysis of effective factors in development of Iran sport industry using grounded theory approach. J Hum Resour Manag Sport. 2019;6:89–107. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaei SH. Effects of the Covid-19 on the sport for all in Iran. Strateg Stud Youth Sports. 2023;22:395–412. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nieman DC, Nehlsen-Cannarella SL. The immune response to exercise. Semin Hematol. 1994;31:166–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8066473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosseinpour E, Godarzi S. Evaluating the role of exercise and practicing religious beliefs on medical staff anxiety caused by coronavirus. Occup Hyg Health Promot. 2022;6:1–12. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Momtazbakhsh M, Zarei A, Ashraf Ganjouie F, Daneshpazhooh M, Fakour Y. The effect of recreational sport on anxiety and depression in patients with pemphigus vulgaris. Iran J Psychiatric Nurs. 2021;9:1–10. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghorbanzadeh B, Lotfi M. The effect of physical exercise on self-control skills and aggression among addicted women. J Sport Psychol Stud. 2017;21:43–60. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lesser IA, Nienhuis CP. The impact of COVID-19 on physical activity behavior and well-being of Canadians. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:3899. doi: 10.3390/ijerph17113899.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7312579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32486380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin F, Song Y, Nassis GP, Zhao L, Cui S, Lai L, Wu Z, Xu M, Qu C, Dong Y, Wang Z. Prevalence of insufficient physical activity, sedentary screen time and emotional well-being during the early days of the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19) outbreak in China: a national cross-sectional study</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brand R, Timme S, Nosrat S. Regular Exercise Before the COVID-19 Pandemic was a Protective Factor for Well-Being During It. University of Potsdam. 2020:1–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahmani B, Najjar MM, Sayyah M, ShafiAbadi MA, Kashani HH. The effectiveness of cognitive-existential group therapy on increasing hope and decreasing depression in women-treated with haemodialysis. Glob J Health Sci. 2016;8:219–31. [Persian]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4954871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26755466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park JH, Lee EN, Kong KR, Jang MJ. Hardiness mediates stress and impact level in ED nurses who experienced a violent event. J Emerg Nurs. 2017;43:539–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28577877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey D, Shrivastava P. Mediation effect of social support on the association between hardiness and immune response. Asian J Psychiatry. 2017;30:52–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28483091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashemi M, Darvishzeh Z, Yazdi M. Comparison of psychological hardiness and cognitive emotion regulation in students with social anxiety disorder and normal students. Q J Psychol Stud. 2019;15:41–56. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aybek A, Yetim A, Aybek S. The study of psychological endurance of the elite athletes in Turkey depending on their ages and the league playing in. Univers J Educ Res. 2019;7:937–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikhesmaeili D, Hatamyan P, Karami J, Lorestani E, Morovati F. The prediction of sleep quality based on psychological hardiness and happiness in elderly. Aging Psychol. 2020;6:27–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoraminejad A, Jahan F. The structural model of self-esteem of athletes based on psychological hardiness and perfectionism with mediator affective control. Sport Psychol Stud. 2020;9:109–28. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousefi Afrashteh M, Golmohammadi F, Tmjidi N. The path analysis of mediating role of hope of life in relationship between psychological hardiness and the power to tolerate ambiguity and death anxiety for MS patients. Med J Mashhad Univ Med Sci. 2021;63:2768–78. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slay HS, Smith DA. Professional identity construction: Using narrative to understand the negotiation of professional and stigmatized cultural identities. Hum Relat. 2011;64:85–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valizadeh L, Ghorbani F. Nurses’ professional identity and Related Factors in formation it: A review article. Nurs Res. 2015;10:88–97. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polifko KA. Concept of the Nursing Profession. Thomson Delmar Learning. 2007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karimi Johani R, Hosseinzade S, Karimi Johani F, Hamdolahi M. The formation process of professional identity in nurses. Dev Nurs Health. 2020;11:18–28. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alipour A, Ghadami A, Alipour Z, Abdollahzadeh H. Preliminary validation of the corona disease anxiety scale (CDAS) in the Iranian sample. Q J Health Psychol. 2020;8:163–75. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baecke JA, Burema J, Frijters JE. A short questionnaire for the measurement of habitual physical activity in epidemiological studies. Am J Clin Nutr. 1982;36:936–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7137077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiamarsi A, Najarian B. Mehrabizade Honarmand M. Validity of scale for assessment psychological hardiness. Psychology. 1998;7:271–84. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao YF, Niu HJ, Li LP, Yue SJ, Liu XH. Measurement of professional identity in Chinese nursing students. Int J Nurs Sci. 2014;1:137–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Psychou D, Kokaridas D, Koulouris N, Theodorakis Y, Krommidas C, Psycho C. Impact of exercise intervention on anxiety levels and mood profile of Greek prison inmates. J Hum Sport Exerc. 2021;16:147–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Zheng Y, Gao D, Hu M, Yuan T. Effects of exercise on depression, anxiety, cognitive control, craving, physical fitness and quality of life in methamphetamine-dependent patients. Front Psychiatry. 2020;10:999. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt. 2019.00999.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6997340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32047445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Liu S, Wang L, Smith L. Mind–body exercise for anxiety and depression in COPD patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:22. doi: 10.3390/ijerph 17010022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6981896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31861418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ströhle A. Physical activity, exercise, depression and anxiety disorders. J Neural Transm. 2009;116:777–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18726137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartley CA, Hay M, Bloch MH. Meta-analysis: Aerobic exercise for the treatment of anxiety disorders. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry. 2013;45:34–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23643675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearsall R, Smith DJ, Pelosi A, Geddes J. Exercise therapy in adults with serious mental illness: A systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Psychiatry. 2014;14:1–17. doi: 10.1186/1471-244X-14-117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4018503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24751159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalali M. The effect of physical exercise on anxiety. Dev Physical Educ Train Mag. 2016;18:56–8. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khosravi N, Hadavi F, Farahani A. The correlation between physical activity and depression and anxiety among high school students in Saveh, Iran. Sport Psychol Stud. 2010;1:7–14. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehsani Farid E, Peikari HR, Golshiri P. Correlation of professional identity dimensions with role stress in nurses. J Health Promot Manag. 2019;8:1–8. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalhori M. Predicting corona anxiety based on coping strategies, psychological hardiness and turbulence tolerance in nurses and treatment staff in Kermanshah in 2020-2021. Paramed Sci Mil Health. 2021;16:25–33. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khosravian T, Chahardoli K. Prediction of corona virus anxiety based on resilience and psychological Hardness of nurses Kermanshah. J N Adv Behav Sci. 2021;55:231–41. [Persian]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks SK, Webster RK, Smith LE, Woodland L, Wessely S, Greenberg N, et al. The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: Rapid review of the evidence. Lancet. 2020;395:912–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7158942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32112714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>