<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39307619</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0929-6646</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the Formosan Medical Association = Taiwan yi zhi</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Formos Med Assoc</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhancing Traditional Chinese Medicine healthcare system in Taiwan post-COVID-19 pandemic: A strategic focus on specialization.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0929-6646(24)00432-7</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jfma.2024.09.012</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Despite the advancements in precision medicine, regenerative medicine, and smart healthcare, traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) remains vital in Taiwan, reflecting its cultural and historical heritage. TCM is commonly used in conjunction with or as an alternative to conventional medicine and is reimbursed by Taiwan's National Health Insurance, enabling the Taiwanese people to integrate traditional and modern treatments for comprehensive healthcare. This article explores the critical role of specialization in TCM amid evolving healthcare challenges. This highlights the need for specialized knowledge among TCM physicians to manage iatrogenic risks, such as drug-herb interactions, and to improve healthcare outcomes, particularly when integrating TCM with Western medicine. Specialization enhances treatment precision, patient outcomes, and clinical research quality. Drawing on South Korea's experience in establishing a specialist physician system for traditional Korean medicine, Taiwan's Ministry of Health and Welfare's initiatives to advance systematic TCM training and regulatory frameworks were examined, showcasing the development and implementation of a TCM specialist physician training program. In conclusion, specialized physician training in TCM improves patient care, optimizes healthcare utilization, and promotes long-term sustainability of the health insurance system by aligning TCM practices with modern healthcare needs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Formosan Medical Association. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Shun-Ku</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Public Health, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei City, 112, Taiwan; Department of Chinese Medicine, Taipei City Hospital, Renai Branch, Taipei City, 106, Taiwan; General Education Center, University of Taipei, Taipei City, 111, Taiwan; The Institute of Traditional Medicine, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei City, 112, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lai</LastName><ForeName>Jung-Nien</ForeName><Initials>JN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Traditional Medicine, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei City, 112, Taiwan. Electronic address: ericlai111@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Singapore</Country><MedlineTA>J Formos Med Assoc</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9214933</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0929-6646</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health insurance system</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Healthcare integration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Iatrogenic risks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Specialization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Traditional Chinese Medicine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing interest The authors of the manuscript titled “Enhancing Taiwan's Traditional Chinese Medicine Healthcare System Following the COVID-19 Pandemic Through Specialization in TCM” declare that there are no financial or non-financial conflicts of interest that could have influenced the work reported in this manuscript. Financial Conflicts of Interest: None. Non-Financial Conflicts of Interest: None. The authors affirm that the research findings are presented as objectively as possible, ensuring that the results and discussion are evidence-based and free from any potential bias.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39307619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfma.2024.09.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0929-6646(24)00432-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>