<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309472</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1875-855X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>18</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Asian biomedicine : research, reviews and news</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Asian Biomed (Res Rev News)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of the relationship between <i>ACE2 G8790A</i> and <i>AT2R A1675G</i> gene polymorphisms in COVID-19 patients with and without lung involvement.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>157</StartPage><EndPage>170</EndPage><MedlinePgn>157-170</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2478/abm-2024-0022</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The SARS-CoV-2 virus produces severe acute respiratory syndrome. The severity of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infection is determined by a number of factors, including inherited ones.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Our goal is to investigate the link between <i>ACE2 G8790A</i> (rs2285666) and <i>AT2R A1675G</i> (rs14035430) gene polymorphisms in COVID-19 patients with and without lung involvement.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 160 COVID-19 patients were divided into 2 groups based on their clinical symptoms: those without lung involvement (control group) and those with lung involvement (infected group). The <i>ACE2 G8790A</i> and <i>AT2R A1675G</i> gene polymorphisms were analyzed using the PCR-RFLP methods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The GG genotype, G allele of <i>ACE2 G8790A</i>, and GG genotype of <i>AT2R A1675G</i> were significantly higher in the control group and had a protective effect against COVID-19 as well as decreased the development of lung involvement (OR = 0.29, 95% CI = 0.10-0.84; OR = 0.40, 95% CI = 0.22-0.72; and OR = 0.33, 95% CI = 0.14-0.78, respectively). Moreover, we found that the AA genotype, A allele of <i>ACE2 G8790A</i>, and AG genotype of <i>AT2R A1675G</i> increased the risk of COVID-19 in the infected group (OR = 3.50, 95% CI = 1.18-10.3; OR = 2.49, 95% CI = 1.39-4.48; and OR = 3.08, 95% CI = 1.28-7.38, respectively).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">These results revealed that a greater frequency of COVID-19 lung involvement in the Turkish population was connected with the AA genotype, the A allele of <i>ACE2 G8790A</i>, and the AG genotype of <i>AT2R A1675G</i>.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Raziye Akcilar et al., published by Sciendo.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akcilar</LastName><ForeName>Raziye</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, Kütahya Health Sciences University, Faculty of Medicine, Kutahya 43100, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kocak</LastName><ForeName>Fatma Emel</ForeName><Initials>FE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biochemistry, Kütahya Health Sciences University, Faculty of Medicine, Kutahya 43100, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kar</LastName><ForeName>Fatih</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Basic Sciences, Kütahya Health Sciences University, Faculty of Natural and Engineering Sciences, Kutahya 43100, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Isiklar</LastName><ForeName>Ozben Ozden</ForeName><Initials>OO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biochemistry, Kütahya Health Sciences University, Faculty of Medicine, Kutahya 43100, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Atlanoglu</LastName><ForeName>Sahinde</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Kütahya Health Sciences University, Faculty of Medicine, Kutahya 43100, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Genc</LastName><ForeName>Ozlem</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Microbiology, Kütahya Health Sciences University, Faculty of Medicine, Kutahya 43100, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yaman</LastName><ForeName>Fatima</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Kütahya Health Sciences University, Faculty of Medicine, Kutahya 43100, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Thailand</Country><MedlineTA>Asian Biomed (Res Rev News)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101465147</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1875-855X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ACE2 G8790A</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AT2R A1675G</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gene polymorphism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lung involvement</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2478/abm-2024-0022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">abm-2024-0022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tipnis SR, Hooper NM, Hyde R, Karran E, Christie G, Turner AJ. A human homolog of angiotensin-converting enzyme. Cloning and functional expression as a captopril-insensitive carboxypeptidase. J Biol Chem. 2000;275:33238–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10924499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devaux CA, Rolain JM, Raoult D. ACE2 receptor polymorphism: susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2, hypertension, multi-organ failure, and COVID-19 disease outcome. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2020;53:425–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7201239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32414646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keidar S, Kaplan M, Gamliel-Lazarovich A. ACE2 of the heart: from angiotensin I to angiotensin (1–7) Cardiovasc Res. 2007;73:463–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17049503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donoghue M, Hsieh F, Baronas E, Godbout K, Gosselin M, Stagliano N. et al. A novel angiotensin-converting enzyme-related carboxypeptidase (ACE2) converts angiotensin I to angiotensin 1–9. Circ Res. 2000;87:E1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10969042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamsi-Pasha MA, Shao Z, Tang WH. Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 as a therapeutic target for heart failure. Curr Heart Fail Rep. 2014;11:58–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3944399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24293035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiese O, Zemlin AE, Pillay TS. Molecules in pathogenesis: angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) J Clin Pathol. 2021;74:285–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32759311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemarié CA, Schiffrin EL. The angiotensin II type 2 receptor in cardiovascular disease. J Renin Angiotensin Aldosterone Syst. 2010;11:19–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19861349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima N, Patel SN, Hussain T. Angiotensin II type 2 receptor: a target for protection against hypertension, metabolic dysfunction, and organ remodeling. Hypertension. 2021;77:1845–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8115429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33840201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazard D, Briend-Sutren MM, Villageois P, Mattei MG, Strosberg AD, Nahmias C. Molecular characterization and chromosome localization of a human angiotensin II AT2 receptor gene highly expressed in fetal tissues. Recept Channels. 1994;2:271–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7719706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inagami T. Molecular biology and signaling of angiotensin receptors: an overview. J Am Soc Nephrol. 1999;10(Suppl 11):S2–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9892133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin MM, Elton TS. The sequence and genomic organization of the human type 2 angiotensin II receptor. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1995;209:554–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7733925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein S, Herbert JA, McNamara PS, Hedrich CM. COVID-19: immunology and treatment options. Clin Immunol. 2020;215:108448. doi: 10.1016/j.clim.2020.108448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2020.108448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7185015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32353634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni W, Yang X, Yang D, Bao J, Li R, Xiao Y. et al. Role of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) in COVID-19. Crit Care. 2020;24:422. doi: 10.1186/s13054-020-03120-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13054-020-03120-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7356137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32660650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huertas A, Montani D, Savale L, Pichon J, Tu L, Parent F. et al. Endothelial cell dysfunction: a major player in SARS-CoV-2 infection (COVID-19)? Eur Respir J. 2020;56:2001634. doi: 10.1183/13993003.01634-2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/13993003.01634-2020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7301835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32554538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuba K, Imai Y, Rao S, Gao H, Guo F, Guan B. et al. A crucial role of angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) in SARS coronavirus-induced lung injury. Nat Med. 2005;11:875–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16007097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Little J, Higgins JP, Ioannidis JP, Moher D, Gagnon F, von Elm E. et al. Strengthening the reporting of genetic association studies (STREGA): an extension of the STROBE statement. Hum Genet. 2009;125:131–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19184668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Living guidance clinical management of COVID-19.  [Internet]. 2023. [cited 2023 January 15]. Available from: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-clinical-2021-2 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fistera D, Risse J, Manegold R, Pabst D, Konik M, Dolff S. et al. [COVID-19 triage: who is an inpatient? the Essen triage model] Dtsch Med Wochenschr. 2020;145:e87–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32422662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson S, Kay FU, Abbara S, Bhalla S, Chung JH, Chung M. et al. Radiological society of North America expert consensus document on reporting chest CT findings related to COVID-19: endorsed by the Society of Thoracic Radiology, the American College of Radiology, and RSNA. Radiol Cardiothorac Imaging. 2020;2:e200152. doi: 10.1148/ryct.2020200152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/ryct.2020200152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7233447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33778571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernheim A, Mei X, Huang M, Yang Y, Fayad ZA, Zhang N. et al. Chest CT findings in coronavirus disease-19 (COVID-19): relationship to duration of infection. Radiology. 2020;295:200463. doi: 10.1148/radiol.2020200463.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/radiol.2020200463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7233369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32077789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Yu T, Du R, Fan G, Liu Y, Liu Z. et al. Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020;395:1054–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C, Chen X, Cai Y, Xia J, Zhou X, Xu S. et al. Risk factors associated with acute respiratory distress syndrome and death in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 pneumonia in Wuhan, China. JAMA Intern Med. 2020;180:934–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7070509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32167524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C, Wang Y, Li X, Ren L, Zhao J, Hu Y. et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet. 2020;395:497–506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang N, Li D, Wang X, Sun Z. Abnormal coagulation parameters are associated with poor prognosis in patients with novel coronavirus pneumonia. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:844–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7166509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32073213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui S, Chen S, Li X, Liu S, Wang F. Prevalence of venous thromboembolism in patients with severe novel coronavirus pneumonia. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1421–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32271988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang N, Bai H, Chen X, Gong J, Li D, Sun Z. Anticoagulant treatment is associated with decreased mortality in severe coronavirus disease 2019 patients with coagulopathy. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1094–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32220112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ge H, Wang X, Yuan X, Xiao G, Wang C, Deng T. et al. The epidemiology and clinical information about COVID-19. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2020;39:1011–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7154215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32291542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang D, Hu B, Hu C, Zhu F, Liu X, Zhang J. et al. Clinical characteristics of 138 hospitalized patients with 2019 novel coronavirus-infected pneumonia in Wuhan, China. JAMA. 2020;323:1061–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7042881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32031570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu XW, Wu XX, Jiang XG, Xu KJ, Ying LJ, Ma CL. et al. Clinical findings in a group of patients infected with the 2019 novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) outside of Wuhan, China: retrospective case series. BMJ. 2020;368:m606. doi: 10.1136/bmj.m606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7224340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32075786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kocak FE, Akcilar R, Kar F, Isiklar OO, Atlanoglu S, Genc O, Yaman F. The D allele of angiotensin-converting enzyme gene insertion/deletion polymorphism is associated with the lung involvement in COVID-19. Turkish J Biochem. 2022;48:160–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos RAS, Sampaio WO, Alzamora AC, Motta-Santos D, Alenina N, Bader M, Campagnole-Santos MJ. The ACE2/angiotensin-(1–7)/MAS axis of the renin-angiotensin system: focus on angiotensin-(1–7) Physiol Rev. 2018;98:505–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7203574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29351514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imai Y, Kuba K, Rao S, Huan Y, Guo F, Guan B. et al. Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 protects from severe acute lung failure. Nature. 2005;436:112–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16001071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sriram K, Insel PA. A hypothesis for pathobiology and treatment of COVID-19: the centrality of ACE1/ACE2 imbalance. Br J Pharmacol. 2020;177:4825–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7572451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32333398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramkowski K, Mogielnicki A, Buczko W. The physiological significance of the alternative pathways of angiotensin II production. J Physiol Pharmacol. 2006;57:529–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17229979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou Y, Zhao J, Martin W, Kallianpur A, Chung MK, Jehi L. et al. New insights into genetic susceptibility of COVID-19: an ACE2 and TMPRSS2 polymorphism analysis. BMC Med. 2020;18:216. doi: 10.1186/s12916-020-01673-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12916-020-01673-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7360473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32664879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karakaş Çelik S, Çakmak Genç G, Pişkin N, Açikgöz B, Altinsoy B, Kurucu İşsiz B, Dursun A. Polymorphisms of ACE (I/D) and ACE2 receptor gene (Rs2106809, Rs2285666) are not related to the clinical course of COVID-19: a case study. J Med Virol. 2021;93:5947–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8426884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34170561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novelli A, Biancolella M, Borgiani P, Cocciadiferro D, Colona VL, D'Apice MR. et al. Analysis of ACE2 genetic variants in 131 Italian SARS-CoV-2-positive patients. Hum Genomics. 2020;14:29. doi: 10.1186/s40246-020-00279-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40246-020-00279-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7483483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32917283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik GH, Bhat IA, Rasool S, Bashir I, Bashir A, Dar TA. et al. SARS-CoV-2-IgG response and the role of ACE2 G8790A and ACE I/D polymorphic variants as determinants of Covid-19 severity-a genetic association study in north Indian population. Research Square. 2021 doi: 10.21203/rs.3.rs-764798/v1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-764798/v1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Möhlendick B, Schönfelder K, Breuckmann K, Elsner C, Babel N, Balfanz P. et al. ACE2 polymorphism and susceptibility for SARS-CoV-2 infection and severity of COVID-19. Pharmacogenet Genomics. 2021;31:165–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8415730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34001841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava A, Bandopadhyay A, Das D, Pandey RK, Singh V, Khanam N. et al. Genetic association of ACE2 rs2285666 polymorphism with COVID-19 spatial distribution in India. Front Genet. 2020;25:564741. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2020.564741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fgene.2020.564741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7545580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33101387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asselta R, Paraboschi EM, Mantovani A, Duga S. ACE2 and TMPRSS2 variants and expression as candidates to sex and country differences in COVID-19 severity in Italy. Aging (Albany NY) 2020;12:10087–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7346072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32501810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez J, Albaiceta GM, García-Clemente M, López-Larrea C, Amado-Rodríguez L, Lopez-Alonso I. et al. Angiotensin-converting enzymes (ACE, ACE2) gene variants and COVID-19 outcome. Gene. 2020;762:145102. doi: 10.1016/j.gene.2020.145102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2020.145102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7456966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32882331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel SK, Juno JA, Lee WS, Wragg KM, Hogarth PM, Kent SJ, Burrell LM. Plasma ACE2 activity is persistently elevated following SARS-CoV-2 infection: implications for COVID-19 pathogenesis and consequences. Eur Respir J. 2021;57:2003730. doi: 10.1183/13993003.03730-2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/13993003.03730-2020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7830336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33479113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Lier D, Kox M, Santos K, van der Hoeven H, Pillay J, Pickkers P. Increased blood angiotensin converting enzyme 2 activity in critically ill COVID-19 patients. ERJ Open Res. 2021;7:00848–2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7848790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33738305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagy B Jr, Fejes Z, Szentkereszty Z, Sütő R, Várkonyi I, Ajzner É. et al. A dramatic rise in serum ACE2 activity in a critically ill COVID-19 patient. Int J Infect Dis. 2021;103:412–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7689308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33249290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kornilov SA, Lucas I, Jade K, Dai CL, Lovejoy JC, Magis AT. Plasma levels of soluble ACE2are associated with sex, Metabolic Syndrome, and its biomarkers in a large cohort, pointing to a possible mechanism for increased severity in COVID-19. Crit Care. 2020;24:452. doi: 10.1186/s13054-020-03141-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13054-020-03141-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7373836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32698840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu YH, Li JY, Wang C, Zhang LM, Qiao H. The ACE2 G8790A polymorphism: involvement in type 2 diabetes mellitus combined with cerebral stroke. J Clin Lab Anal. 2017;31:e22033. doi: 10.1002/jcla.22033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcla.22033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6817163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27500554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steckelings UM, Sumners C. Correcting the imbalanced protective RAS in COVID-19 with angiotensin AT2-receptor agonists. Clin Sci (Lond) 2020;134:2987–3006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33210709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gumashta J, Gumashta R. Role of the backbenchers of the renin-angiotensin system ACE2 and AT2 receptors in COVID-19: lessons from SARS. Cureus. 2020;12:e8411. doi: 10.7759/cureus.8411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.8411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7331779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32626626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Živković M, Kolaković A, Stojković L, Dinčić E, Kostić S, Alavantić D, Stanković A. Renin-angiotensin system gene polymorphisms as risk factors for multiple sclerosis. J Neurol Sci. 2016;15:29–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27000216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>