<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39308303</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2753</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of evaluation in clinical practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Eval Clin Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Examination of diet quality and alcohol on serum IgG levels after first and second COVID-19 vaccines.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jep.14146</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="RATIONALE" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The change of IgG of COVID-19 vaccine was thought to be an effect of diet quality or daily habits.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIMS AND OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study aimed to correlate diet quality and healthy living factors with serum IgG response in the blood.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Participants were selected from volunteers who had their first vaccination and did not have COVID-19 disease (Male = 21 Female = 40). Serum IgG levels were measured on average (avg) 28 days after the COVID-19 vaccine. Information was obtained directly from the participants by questionnaire method (Food consumption record, frequency of food consumption, Diet Quality Index [(DQI], etc.).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A significant difference was observed in the IgG levels of the second measurement of age (young/middle) and gender (male/female) (p &lt; 0.05). A significant difference was found in the first measurement of serum IgG levels and IgG avgs of those with medium diet quality and those who did not drink alcohol (p &lt; 0.05). When the IgG2/1 ratio was examined between alcohol users and nonalcohol, a significant increase was observed about two times in non-alcohol users (p = 0.039). There is a positive significant moderate strength relationship between the second measurements of IgG and anthropometric measurements and the first, second, and avg measurements of IgG with DQI. It was found that there was a negative significant medium-strength relationship between individuals' amount of alcohol consumption and IgG avg (r = -0.535, p = 0.009).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Medium diet quality has been seen to affect antibody levels positively. At the same time, it is thought that alcohol use negatively affects serum IgG antibody response in the long term. Other than that, there was shown to be a correlation between IgG levels and DQI.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cesur</LastName><ForeName>Fatih</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2062-098X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, Institute of Health Science, Ege University, İzmir, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Research Promotion Program of Avrasya University 2021/02 number</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Eval Clin Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9609066</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1356-1294</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19 vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">alcohol</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diet quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunoglobulin G</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39308303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jep.14146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Rai P, Kumar BK, Deekshit VK, Karunasagar I, Karunasagar I. Detection technologies and recent developments in the diagnosis of COVID‐19 infection. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2021;105(2):441‐455. doi:10.1007/S00253-020-11061-5/FIGURES/5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phelan AL, Katz R, Gostin LO. The novel coronavirus originating in wuhan, China: challenges for global health governance. JAMA. 2020;323(8):709‐710. doi:10.1001/JAMA.2020.1097</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumder J, Minko T. Recent developments on therapeutic and diagnostic approaches for COVID‐19. AAPS J. 2021;23(1):14. doi:10.1208/S12248-020-00532-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen N, Zhou M, Dong X, et al. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a descriptive study. Lancet. 2020;395(10223):507‐513. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30211-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zabetakis I, Lordan R, Norton C, Tsoupras A. COVID‐19: the inflammation link and the role of nutrition in potential mitigation. Nutrients. 2020;12(5):1466. doi:10.3390/NU12051466</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández‐Quintela A, Milton‐Laskibar I, Trepiana J, et al. Key aspects in nutritional management of covid‐19 patients. J Clin Med. 2020;9(8):2589. doi:10.3390/jcm9082589</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghelani D, Alesi S, Mousa A. Vitamin D and COVID‐19: an overview of recent evidence. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(19):10559. doi:10.3390/ijms221910559</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He F, Deng Y, Li W. Coronavirus disease 2019: what we know. J Med Virol. 2020;92(7):719‐725. doi:10.1002/JMV.25766</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iddir M, Brito A, Dingeo G, et al. Strengthening the immune system and reducing inflammation and oxidative stress through diet and nutrition: considerations during the covid‐19 crisis. Nutrients. 2020;12(6):1562. doi:10.3390/nu12061562</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lordan R, Tsoupras A, Zabetakis I. Platelet activation and prothrombotic mediators at the nexus of inflammation and atherosclerosis: potential role of antiplatelet agents. Blood Rev. 2021;45:100694. doi:10.1016/J.BLRE.2020.100694</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maggini S, Pierre A, Calder PC. Immune function and micronutrient requirements change over the life course. Nutrients. 2018;10(10):1531. doi:10.3390/NU10101531</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alwarawrah Y, Kiernan K, MacIver NJ. Changes in nutritional status impact immune cell metabolism and function. Front Immunol. 2018;9:1055. doi:10.3389/FIMMU.2018.01055/BIBTEX</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barazzoni R, Bischoff SC, Breda J, et al. ESPEN expert statements and practical guidance for nutritional management of individuals with SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Clin Nutr. 2020;39(6):1631‐1638. doi:10.1016/j.clnu.2020.03.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashouri M, Nehzat Norozi tehrani S, Karuppasamy Govindasamy, Zouhal H. Effect of Covid‐19 on the lifestyles of vaccinated and unvaccinated elite athletes: a cross‐country analysis. Health Nexus. 2023;1(2):1‐6. doi:10.61838/kman.hn.1.2.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reifer J, Hayum N, Heszkel B, Klagsbald I, Streva VA. SARS‐CoV‐2 IgG antibody responses in New York city. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2020;98(3):115128. doi:10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2020.115128</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez Bernal J, Andrews N, Gower C, et al. Effectiveness of the Pfizer‐BioNTech and Oxford‐AstraZeneca vaccines on covid‐19 related symptoms, hospital admissions, and mortality in older adults in England: test negative case‐control study. BMJ. 2021;373:n1088. doi:10.1136/BMJ.N1088</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamkhi S, Dhaouadi T, Sfar I, et al. Comparative study of six SARS‐CoV‐2 serology assays: diagnostic performance and antibody dynamics in a cohort of hospitalized patients for moderate to critical COVID‐19. Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol. 2022;36:205873842110732. doi:10.1177/20587384211073232</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cesur F, Atasever Z, Özoran Y. Impact of vitamin D3 supplementation on COVID‐19 vaccine response and immunoglobulin G antibodies in deficient women: a randomized controlled trial. Vaccine. 2023;41(17):2860‐2867. doi:10.1016/J.VACCINE.2023.03.046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newby P, Hu FB, Rimm EB, et al. Reproducibility and validity of the Diet Quality Index revised as assessed by use of a food‐frequency questionnaire. Am J Clin Nutr. 2003;78(5):941‐949. doi:10.1093/ajcn/78.5.941</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cesur F, Öztürk Kara G. Can consumption of type 4 resistant starch reduce high blood glucose fluctuations? A randomised trial. Int J Food Sci Technol. 2024;59(6):3989‐3998. doi:10.1111/ijfs.17151</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cesur F, Seçkiner S, Kucukerdonmez O, Cagindi O, Saygili LF, Meseri R. Can Enzyme‐resistant starch snack prevent blood glucose fluctuations? A pilot trial in patients with insulin‐treated type 2 diabetes. Starch ‐ Stärke. 2023;75(9‐10):2200279. doi:10.1002/star.202200279</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vural S, Hacıbekiroğlu M, Yıldız FR, Vural P. Pandemide COVID‐19 geçirmiş ve geçirmemiş bir grup sağlık çalışanında aşı sonrası gelişen immünolojik cevap. Ankem Dergi̇si̇. 2021;35(2):45‐52. doi:10.5222/ankem.2021.045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Xu Y, Li X, et al. Real‐world effectiveness and protection of SARS‐CoV‐2 vaccine among patients hospitalized for COVID‐19 in Xi'an, China, December 8, 2021, to January 20, 2022: a retrospective study. Front Immunol. 2022;13:978977. doi:10.3389/FIMMU.2022.978977</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corman LC. The relationship between nutrition, infection, and immunity. Med Clin North Am. 1985;69(3):519‐531. doi:10.1016/S0025-7125(16)31030-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper EL, Ma MJ. Understanding nutrition and immunity in disease management. J Tradit Complement Med. 2017;7(4):386‐391. doi:10.1016/J.JTCME.2016.12.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunningham‐Rundles S. Analytical methods for evaluation of immune response in nutrient intervention. Nutr Res. 1998;56(1 Pt 2):S27‐S37. doi:10.1111/J.1753-4887.1998.TB01641.X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikezaki H, Nomura H, Shimono N. Dynamics of anti‐spike IgG antibody level after the second BNT162b2 COVID‐19 vaccination in health care workers. J Infect Chemother. 2022;28(6):802‐805. doi:10.1016/J.JIAC.2022.02.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nomura Y, Sawahata M, Nakamura Y, et al. Age and smoking predict antibody titres at 3 months after the second dose of the BNT162b2 COVID‐19 vaccine. Vaccines. 2021;9(9):1042. doi:10.3390/VACCINES9091042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu W, Tao ZW, Wang L, et al. Analysis of factors associated with disease outcomes in hospitalized patients with 2019 novel coronavirus disease. Chin Med J. 2020;133(9):1032‐1038. doi:10.1097/CM9.0000000000000775</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomaselli V, Ferrara P, Cantone GG, et al. The effect of laboratory‐verified smoking on SARS‐CoV‐2 infection: results from the Troina sero‐epidemiological survey. Intern Emerg Med. 2022;17(6):1617‐1630. doi:10.1007/S11739-022-02975-1/TABLES/4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mori Y, Tanaka M, Kozai H, et al. Antibody response of smokers to the COVID‐19 vaccination: evaluation based on cigarette dependence. Drug Discov Ther. 2022;16(2):78‐84. doi:10.5582/DDT.2022.01022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarbiah N, Todd I, Tighe PJ, Fairclough LC. Cigarette smoking differentially affects immunoglobulin class levels in serum and saliva: an investigation and review. Basic Clin Pharmacol Toxicol. 2019;125(5):474‐483. doi:10.1111/BCPT.13278</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrara P, Ponticelli D, Agüero F, et al. Does smoking have an impact on the immunological response to COVID‐19 vaccines? Evidence from the VASCO study and need for further studies. Public Health. 2022;203:97‐99. doi:10.1016/J.PUHE.2021.12.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto S, Tanaka A, Ohmagari N, et al. Use of heated tobacco products, moderate alcohol drinking, and anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 IgG antibody titers after BNT162b2 vaccination among Japanese healthcare workers. Prev Med. 2022;161:107123. doi:10.1016/J.YPMED.2022.107123</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kantele A, Lääveri T, Kareinen L, et al. SARS‐CoV‐2 infections among healthcare workers at Helsinki university hospital, Finland, spring 2020: serosurvey, symptoms and risk factors. Travel Med Infect Dis. 2021;39:101949. doi:10.1016/J.TMAID.2020.101949</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messaoudi I, Pasala S, Grant K. Could moderate alcohol intake be recommended to improve vaccine responses. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2014;13:817‐819. doi:10.1586/14760584.2014.924405</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chastin SFM, Abaraogu U, Bourgois JG, et al. Effects of regular physical activity on the immune system, vaccination and risk of community‐acquired infectious disease in the general population: systematic review and meta‐analysis. Sports Med. 2021;51(8):1673‐1686. doi:10.1007/S40279-021-01466-1/FIGURES/5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pündük Z. Does the COVID‐19 outbreak, global trends, physical inactivity and sedentary behavior effects? Turkiye Klinikleri J Sports Sci. 2020;12(2):241‐246. doi:10.5336/sportsci.2020-76411</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanar O, Aykol G, Topkara EF, Solmaz FG, Mercan S, Eski A. An example of the effect of diet quality on the immune system of an infected insect: Uresiphita gilvata (FABRICIUS, 1794). Fresenius Environ Bull. 2021;30(5):4749‐4755. https://www.researchgate.net/publication/351915250</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Percival SS. Nutrition and immunity: balancing diet and immune function. Nutr Today. 2011;46(1):12‐17. doi:10.1097/NT.0B013E3182076FC8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erkul C. Covi̇d 19 ve immunonütri̇syon. Eur J Math Eng Nat Med Sci. 2020;7(12):1. doi:10.38065/euroasiaorg.264</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merino J, Joshi AD, Nguyen LH, et al. Diet quality and risk and severity of COVID‐19: a prospective cohort study. Gut. 2021;70(11):2096‐2104. doi:10.1136/gutjnl-2021-325353</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>