<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309756</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2160-1992</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>American journal of blood research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Am J Blood Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Synonymous variant of TLR7 at restriction site rs864058 identified in Covid 19 Pakistani patients.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>6</StartPage><EndPage>13</EndPage><MedlinePgn>6-13</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.62347/YSKN6673</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">TLR7, the receptor accountable for immune response to RNA viruses, has been studied extensively to identify its variants related to the severity of Covid-19 in different populations worldwide. However, the genotype of Pakistani population is still unknown. This study aimed to determine the TLR7 genotypes and their relation with severity in our population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This cross sectional study collected data on 151 Covid-19 positive patients (aged 18-80 years), from June 2022 to May 2023, after an informed consent, from Ziauddin University and Hospital. Prior to that approval from ethics review committee was taken. The demographic variables and comorbidities were recorded along with health status till LAMA (Leave Against Medical Advise), recovery or death. The DNA was extracted from collected blood samples, PCR and Sanger sequencing was done for identification of TLR7 variants. SPSS was used for data analyses and Chi-Square for categorical variables. <i>P</i>-values of &lt;0.05 was considered significant.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Out of 151 patients' sequencing was done for 59 samples. The restriction site, rs864058 of TLR7 gene, identified G/A and G/G variants. This missense variant of TLR7 identified at rs864058 of TLR7 gene, has not been previously reported in population control databases. The genotype G/G was main variant of 49 (83%) patients, whereas, G/A was found in 10 (17%). Majority, 25 (51%) of patients with mild covid-19 had GG genotype but results were not significant (P=0.684). Among female patients the main genotype was GA 8 (80%) while male had G/G 29 (59.2%) with significant results (P=0.024). Since G/G genotype was the major genotype, high percentage was found in hypertensives [20 (40.8%)], Diabetics [13 (26.5%)], depression [24 (49%)] and pneumonia patients [20 (40.8%)]. However, significant association (P=0.023) was only found with pneumonia. Males, in majority had severe [17 (68%)] infection and death [40 (26.4%)], whereas, females had mild [14 (25%)] with [12 (7.9%)] deaths.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">A variant rs864058 "G/A" of TLR7, in relation to covid-19 were found in our population. Males were found more at risk of morbidity and mortality due to covid-19. Larger studies are required to further confirm these results.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>AJBR Copyright © 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khalid</LastName><ForeName>Beenish</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Hamdard University Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farukh</LastName><ForeName>Sadia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Health Sciences, Aga Khan University Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Ashokh</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonologist, Ziauddin Hospital Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baig</LastName><ForeName>Saeeda</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Ziauddin University Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shahid</LastName><ForeName>Moazzam Ali</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Research, Ziauddin University Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Am J Blood Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101569577</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2160-1992</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RNA viruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TLR7</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Toll-like receptors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mRNA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polymorphism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">single nucleotide</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>None.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11411202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.62347/YSKN6673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Duan T, Du Y, Xing C, Wang HY, Wang RF. Toll-like receptor signaling and its role in cell-mediated immunity. Front Immunol. 2022;13:812774.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8927970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35309296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee S, Huda S, Sinha Babu SP. Toll-like receptor polymorphism in host immune response to infectious diseases: a review. Scand J Immunol. 2019;90:e12771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31054156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hemmi H, Kaisho T, Takeuchi O, Sato S, Sanjo H, Hoshino K, Horiuchi T, Tomizawa H, Takeda K, Akira S. Small anti-viral compounds activate immune cells via the TLR7 MyD88-dependent signaling pathway. Nat Immunol. 2002;3:196–200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11812998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du X, Poltorak A, Wei Y, Beutler B. Three novel mammalian toll-like receptors: gene structure, expression, and evolution. Eur Cytokine Netw. 2000;11:362–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11022119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang TH, Ulevitch RJ. Cloning and characterization of a sub-family of human toll-like receptors: hTLR7, hTLR8 and hTLR9. Eur Cytokine Netw. 2000;11:372–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11022120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alseoudy MM, Elgamal M, Abdelghany DA, Borg AM, El-Mesery A, Elzeiny D, Hammad MO. Prognostic impact of toll-like receptors gene polymorphism on outcome of COVID-19 pneumonia: a case-control study. Clin Immunol. 2022;235:108929.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8767970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35063671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Hefnawy SM, Eid HA, Mostafa RG, Soliman SS, Omar TA, Azmy RM. COVID-19 susceptibility, severity, clinical outcome and Toll-like receptor (7) mRNA expression driven by TLR7 gene polymorphism (rs3853839) in middle-aged individuals without previous comorbidities. Gene Rep. 2022;27:101612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9013694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35463461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nilsson D, Andiappan AK, Halldén C, De Yun W, Säll T, Tim CF, Cardell LO. Toll-like receptor gene polymorphisms are associated with allergic rhinitis: a case control study. BMC Med Genet. 2012;13:66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3459792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22857391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willie B, Hall NB, Stein CM, Jurevic RJ, Weinberg A, Mehlotra RK, Zimmerman PA. Association of Toll-like receptor polymorphisms with HIV status in North Americans. Genes Immun. 2014;15:569–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4257894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25253287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moller-Larsen S, Nyegaard M, Haagerup A, Vestbo J, Kruse TA, Borglum AD. Association analysis identifies TLR7 and TLR8 as novel risk genes in asthma and related disorders. Thorax. 2008;63:1064–1069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18682521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen X, Song S, Li C, Zhang J. Synonymous mutations in representative yeast genes are mostly strongly non-neutral. Nature. 2022;606:725–731.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9650438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35676473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fakhir FZ, Lkhider M, Badre W, Alaoui R, Meurs EF, Pineau P, Ezzikouri S, Benjelloun S. Genetic variations in toll-like receptors 7 and 8 modulate natural hepatitis C outcomes and liver disease progression. Liver Int. 2018;38:432–442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28752959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauhkonen E, Koponen P, Vuononvirta J, Teräsjärvi J, Nuolivirta K, Toikka JO, Helminen M, He Q, Korppi M. Gene polymorphism of toll-like receptors and lung function at five to seven years of age after infant bronchiolitis. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0146526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4704821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26741133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang T, Zhu J, Su B, Cao L, Li Z, Wei H, Huang X, Zheng K, Li A, Chen N, Liu L, Xia W, Wu H, He Q. Effects of TLR7 polymorphisms on the susceptibility and progression of HIV-1 infection in Chinese MSM population. Front Immunol. 2020;11:589010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7649213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33193416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue M, Feng L, Tang SD, Wang JJ, Xue XX, Ding WL, Zhang Y, Deng XZ. Sex-specific association between X-linked Toll-like receptor 7 with the outcomes of hepatitis C virus infection. Gene. 2014;548:244–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25034660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee S, Tripathi A. Contribution of Toll like receptor polymorphisms to dengue susceptibility and clinical outcome among eastern Indian patients. Immunobiology. 2019;224:774–785.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31481269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutta SK, Tripathi A. Association of toll-like receptor polymorphisms with susceptibility to chikungunya virus infection. Virology. 2017;511:207–213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28888110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fakhir FZ, Lkhider M, Badre W, Alaoui R, Meurs EF, Pineau P, Ezzikouri S, Benjelloun S. Genetic variations in toll-like receptors 7 and 8 modulate natural hepatitis C outcomes and liver disease progression. Liver Int. 2018;38:432–442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28752959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauhkonen E, Koponen P, Vuononvirta J, Teräsjärvi J, Nuolivirta K, Toikka JO, Helminen M, He Q, Korppi M. Gene polymorphism of toll-like receptors and lung function at five to seven years of age after infant bronchiolitis. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0146526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4704821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26741133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dudley JP, Lee NT. Disparities in age-specific morbidity and mortality from SARS-CoV-2 in China and the Republic of Korea. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:863–865.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32232322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer J, Jung N, Robinson N, Lehmann C. Sex differences in immune responses to infectious diseases. Infection. 2015;43:399–403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25956991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Jerkic M, Slutsky AS, Zhang H. Molecular mechanisms of sex bias differences in COVID-19 mortality. Crit Care. 2020;24:405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7347256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32646459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein SL, Marriott I, Fish EN. Sex-based differences in immune function and responses to vaccination. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2015;109:9–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4447843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25573105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>vom Steeg LG, Klein SL. SeXX matters in infectious disease pathogenesis. PLoS Pathog. 2016;12:e1005374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4759457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26891052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei XY, Xiao YT, Wang J, Chen R, Zhang W, Yang Y, Lv DJ, Qin C, Gu D, Zhang B, Chen WD, Hou JQ, Song NH, Zeng GH, Ren SC. Sex differences in severity and mortality among patients with COVID-19: evidence from pooled literature analysis and insights from integrated bioinformatic analysis. arXiv:200313547. 2020. https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2003.13547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziegler SM, Beisel C, Sutter K, Griesbeck M, Hildebrandt H, Hagen SH, Dittmer U, Altfeld M. Human pDCs display sex-specific differences in type I interferon subtypes and interferon α/β receptor expression. Eur J Immunol. 2017;47:251–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27891600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokes EK, Zambrano LD, Anderson KN, Marder EP, Raz KM, El Burai Felix S, Tie Y, Fullerton KE. Coronavirus disease 2019 case surveillance - United States, January 22-May 30, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020;69:759–765.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7302472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32555134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Yu T, Du R, Fan G, Liu Y, Liu Z, Xiang J, Wang Y, Song B, Gu X, Guan L, Wei Y, Li H, Wu X, Xu J, Tu S, Zhang Y, Chen H, Cao B. Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020;395:1054–1062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison SL, Fazio-Eynullayeva E, Lane DA, Underhill P, Lip GYH. Comorbidities associated with mortality in 31,461 adults with COVID-19 in the United States: a federated electronic medical record analysis. PLoS Med. 2020;17:e1003321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7482833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32911500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah R, Shah J, Kunyiha N, Ali SK, Sayed S, Surani S, Saleh M. Demographic, clinical, and co-morbidity characteristics of COVID-19 patients: a retrospective cohort from a Tertiary Hospital in Kenya. Int J Gen Med. 2022;15:4237–4246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9037723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35480998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/pakistan/; https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/india/; https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/iran/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwok AJ, Mentzer A, Knight JC. Host genetics and infectious disease: new tools, insights and translational opportunities. Nat Rev Genet. 2021;22:137–153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7716795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33277640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>