<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309992</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of education and health promotion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Educ Health Promot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Developing and validating of educational-therapeutic package based on psychological flexibility for nurses in the intensive care unit of COVID-19: Application of grounded theory.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>274</StartPage><MedlinePgn>274</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">274</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jehp.jehp_908_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Caring for COVID-19 patients has caused high stress and burnses. Therefore, the current research aims to develop and validate an educational-therapeutic package based on psychological flexibility for COVID-19 nurses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The approach of this research was Exploratory Sequential Mixed Method, which was carried out in 2019 to 2021. In the qualitative phase, to identify the paradigm model of the research, the grounded theory of the Strauss and Corbin model, purposeful sampling, and in-depth semi-structured interviews with 12 nurses were used. Goba and Lincoln's criteria were used to ensure the accuracy and reliability of the data. In the quantitative phase, based on the Paradarim model, a training package according to psychological flexibility was developed with the approval of 10 experts from the fields of medical, psychology and nursing education.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The qualitative analysis of the data obtained from the interviews led to the identification of 29 primary concept codes, 8 subcategories, and 3 categories in the conceptual format of context, process, and consequence. The categories included "psychological insecurity in the workplace," "strategic immunization in facing special conditions," and "safe communication." "Psychologically safe exposure" was identified as the central category. In several stages, based on the findings of the qualitative stage, the educational-therapeutic package was compiled. The validity of the package was confirmed by calculating two relative coefficients of content validity ratio (CVR) and content validity index (CVI) equal to 0.91 and 0.85, respectively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This research led to the development of an educational-therapeutic package of safe psychological exposure for nurses, which can be used by managers and nurse educators through in-service training courses. Therefore, it is suggested to use training and safe coping strategies to improve the quality of life in nurses.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Education and Health Promotion.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ebrahimi</LastName><ForeName>Amrollah</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Associate professor, Behavioral Sciences Research Center and Department of Health Psychology, School of Medicine, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khorasani</LastName><ForeName>Parvaneh</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing and Midwifery Care Research Center, Department of Community Health and Geriatric Nursing, School of Nursing and Midwifery, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andalib</LastName><ForeName>Sima</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PhD in psychology, Psychology Islamic Azad University Science and Research Branch, Tehran (Isfahan), Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmadi</LastName><ForeName>Mahnaz</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PhD Student, Department of Psychology, School of Educational Sciences and Psychology, University of Isfahan, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mousavi</LastName><ForeName>Sayed Mohammad Hossain</ForeName><Initials>SMH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Behavioral Sciences Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Educ Health Promot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101593794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coping strategies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intensive care units</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nurses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psycho-educational program</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychological flexibility</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_908_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JEHP-13-274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Pan Y, Guan H, Zhou S, Wang Y, Li Q, Zhu T, et al. Initial CT findings and temporal changes in patients with the novel coronavirus pneumonia (2019-nCoV): A study of 63 patients in Wuhan, China. Eur Radiol. 2020;30:3306–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7087663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32055945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalateh Sadati A, Zarei L, Shahabi S, Heydari ST, Taheri V, Jiriaei R, et al. Nursing experiences of COVID-19 outbreak in Iran: A qualitative study. Nurs Open. 2021;8:72–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7461197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32904939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith GD, Ng F, Ho Cheung Li W. COVID-19: Emerging compassion, courage and resilience in the face of misinformation and adversity. J Clin Nurs. 2020;29:1425–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7166833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32155302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarcan GY, Tarcan M, Top M. An analysis of relationship between burnout and job satisfaction among emergency health professionals. Total Qual Manag Bus Excell. 2017;28:1339–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28342622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrokhian AR, Motaghi M, Sharif MR. Quality of life in nurses; case study of Shahid Beheshti Hospital of Kashan City, Iran. Int Arch Heal Sci. 2016;3:93–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khedmati N. The role of self-compassion and psychological flexibility in predicting the burnout of nurses. Rooyesh-e-Ravanshenasi J. 2020;9:2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mo Y, Deng L, Zhang L, Lang Q, Liao C, Wang N, et al. Work stress among Chinese nurses to support Wuhan in fighting against COVID-19 epidemic. J Nurs Manag. 2020;28:1002–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32255222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun YH, Lee MK, Chang YJ, You CH, Kim S, Choi JS, et al. The life-sustaining treatments among cancer patients at end of life and the caregiver’s experience and perspectives. Supp Care Cancer. 2010;18:189–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19399527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao W, Fang Z, Hou G, Han M, Xu X, Dong J, et al. The psychological impact of the COVID-19 epidemic on college students in China. Psychiatry Res. 2020;287:112934.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32229390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catton H. Global challenges in health and health care for nurses and midwives everywhere. Int Nurs Rev. 2020;67:4–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7165846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32083728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Q, Luo D, Haase JE, Guo Q, Wang XQ, Liu S, et al. The experiences of health-care providers during the COVID-19 crisis in China: A qualitative study. Lancet Glob Heal. 2020;8:e790–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7190296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32573443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allan SM, Bealey R, Birch J, Cushing T, Parke S, Sergi G, et al. The prevalence of common and stress-related mental health disorders in healthcare workers based in pandemic-affected hospitals: A rapid systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur J Psychotraumatol. 2020;11:1810903.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7678680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33244359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joob B, Wiwanitkit V. Medical personnel, COVID-19 and emotional impact. Psychiatry Res. 2020;288:112952.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7152901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32335465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan BYQ, Chew NWS, Lee GKH, Jing M, Goh Y, Yeo LLL, et al. Psychological impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on health care workers in Singapore. Ann Intern Med. 2020;173:317–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7143149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32251513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Losa Iglesias ME, Vallejo RB de B, Fuentes PS. The relationship between experiential avoidance and burnout syndrome in critical care nurses: A cross-sectional questionnaire survey. Int J Nurs Stud. 2010;47:30–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19625023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buus N, Perron A. The quality of quality criteria: Replicating the development of the Consolidated Criteria for Reporting Qualitative Research (COREQ) Int J Nurs Stud. 2020;102:103452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31726311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawshe CH. A quantitative approach to content validity. Personnel psychology. 1975;28:563–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherry KM, Vander Hoeven E, Patterson TS, Lumley MN. Defining and measuring “psychological flexibility”: A narrative scoping review of diverse flexibility and rigidity constructs and perspectives. Clin Psychol Rev. 2021;84:101973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33550157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dawson DL, Golijani-Moghaddam N. COVID-19: Psychological flexibility, coping, mental health, and wellbeing in the UK during the pandemic. J Contextual Behav Sci. 2020;17:126–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ching SSY, Cheung K, Hegney D, Rees CS. Stressors and coping of nursing students in clinical placement: A qualitative study contextualizing their resilience and burnout. Nurse Educ Pract. 2020;42:102690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31881460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien WH, Horan KA, Singh SR, Moeller MM, Wasson RS, Jex SM, et al. Relationships among training, mindfulness, and workplace injuries among nurse aides working in long-term care settings. Occup Heal Sci. 2019;3:45–58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kashdan TB, Rottenberg J. Clinical Psychology Review. Vol. 30. Elsevier Inc: 2010. Psychological flexibility as a fundamental aspect of health; pp. 865–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2998793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21151705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kent W, Hochard KD, Hulbert-Williams NJ. Perceived stress and professional quality of life in nursing staff: How important is psychological flexibility? J Context Behav Sci. 2019;14:11–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramaci T, Bellini D, Presti G, Santisi G. Psychological flexibility and mindfulness as predictors of individual outcomes in hospital health workers. Front Psychol. 2019;10:1302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6582771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31249541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’brien WH, Singh RS, Horan K, Moeller MT, Wasson R, Jex SM. Group-based acceptance and commitment therapy for nurses and nurse aides working in long-term care residential settings. J Altern Complement Med. 2019;25:753–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31314564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson V, Murphy D, Greenberg N. COVID-19 and experiences of moral injury in front-line key workers. Occup Med. 2020;70:317–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32239155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi M, Bagherian-Sararoudi R, Mosavi SMH. Mentalization and its multidimensional nature. RBS. 2021;18:616–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suarez-Garcia JM, Maestro-Gonzalez A, Zuazua-Rico D, Sánchez-Zaballos M, Mosteiro-Diaz MP. Stressors for Spanish nursing students in clinical practice. Nurse Educ Today. 2018;64:16–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29454874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham H. A Labour of Love: Women, Work and Caring. Vol. 5. Taylor and Francis: 2022. Caring: A labour of love; pp. 13–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neff KD. Self-compassion: Theory, method, research, and intervention. Annu Rev Psychol. 2023;74:193–218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35961039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan ATC, Yan ATC. Prediction of perceived stress of Hong Kong nursing students with coping behaviors over clinical practicum: A cross-sectional study. J Biosci Med. 2019;7:50–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latif RA, Nor MZM. Stressors and coping strategies during clinical practice among diploma nursing students. Malaysian J Med Sci. 2019;26:88–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6687220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31447612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wendsche J, Ghadiri A, Bengsch A, Wegge J. Antecedents and outcomes of nurses’ rest break organization: A scoping review. Int J Nurs Stud. 2017;75:65–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28750245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>