<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309884</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>18</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The issue of interconnections and mutual influence of digital transformation in international trade: How digitization affects customer satisfaction?</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e36854</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e36854</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e36854</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36854</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This research aims to investigate the relationships and mutual influence between the digitalization of international trade and customer satisfaction in the context of the post-COVID-19 economy. To achieve this objective, a comprehensive research project has been developed, involving a quantitative approach that combines the advantages of experiments and surveys. Customer satisfaction was assessed based on key service quality parameters in the SERVQUAL model. The study involved 4 stores operating on the AliExpress international trading platform. The sample included a total of 3796 customers. The research findings confirmed the impact of digitalization on customer satisfaction in international trading operations across nearly all dimensions of the SERVQUAL model. The implementation of basic digital innovations substantially enhanced reliability, order processing and delivery speed, product packaging, and the process of selecting and ordering goods, as well as the regularity of notifications and data security. However, the introduction of a chatbot significantly reduced customer satisfaction with the provision of additional information, leading to a decrease in customer empathy. The academic contribution of this study lies in its ability to complement and expand the scientific understanding of the impact of digitalization on customer satisfaction in international trade in the post-COVID-19 era. The study demonstrated that not all digital innovations are perceived equally positively by customers and do not necessarily lead to increased satisfaction. Accordingly, the practical outcome of this research is the empirical confirmation of the need to test customer satisfaction when implementing digital innovations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Guangying</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of International Business, Qingdao Huanghai University, Qingdao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of International Commerce &amp; Business, Konkuk University, Seoul, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Customer satisfaction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Digital innovations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Digitization of international trade</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Expectancy-confirmation theory</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SERVQUAL</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11416575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)12885-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Li L. Digital transformation and sustainable performance: the moderating role of market turbulence. Ind. Mark. Manag. 2022;104:28–37. doi: 10.1016/j.indmarman.2022.04.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indmarman.2022.04.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geum Y., Kim M.S., Lee S. Service technology: definition and characteristics based on a patent database. Serv. Sci. 2017;9(2):147–166. doi: 10.1287/serv.2016.0170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1287/serv.2016.0170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmedov I. The impact of digital economy on international trade. Eur. J. Bus. Manag. Res. 2020;5(4):1–7. doi: 10.24018/ejbmr.2020.5.4.389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.24018/ejbmr.2020.5.4.389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bask A., Merisalo-Rantanen H., Tuunanen T. Developing a modular service architecture for E-store supply chains: the small-and medium-sized enterprise perspective. Serv. Sci. 2014;6(4):251–273. doi: 10.1287/serv.2014.0082.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1287/serv.2014.0082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katz R.L., Callorda F.M., Jung J. Can digitization mitigate COVID-19 damages? Evidence from developing countries. Evidence from Developing Countries. 2020 doi: 10.2139/ssrn.3600829. ePub ahead of print May 14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3600829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scarlat C., Stănciulescu G.D., Panduru D.A. COVID-19 Pandemic as accelerator: opportunity for digital acceleration, JIEBS 2022. 2022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5171/2022.296375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasetyo Y.T., Tanto H., Mariyanto M., Hanjaya C., Young M.N., Persada S.F., Miraja B.A., Redi A.A.N.P. Factors affecting customer satisfaction and loyalty in online food delivery service during the COVID-19 pandemic: its relation with open innovation. J. Open Innov. Technol. Mark. Complex. 2021;7(1):76. doi: 10.3390/joitmc7010076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/joitmc7010076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng X., Ketron S.C., Wan Y. Identifying consumer segments based on COVID-19 pandemic perceptions and responses. J. Consum. Aff. 2022;56(1):34–67. doi: 10.1111/joca.12413.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joca.12413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8662050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34908579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal R., Dhingra S. Factors influencing cloud service quality and their relationship with customer satisfaction and loyalty. Heliyon. 2023;9(4) doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e15177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e15177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10123211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37101644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia M., Kim H.S., Tao S. B&amp;B customer experience and satisfaction: evidence from online customer reviews. Serv. Sci. 2023;16(1):42–54. doi: 10.1287/serv.2022.0080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1287/serv.2022.0080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nigatu A.G., Belete A.A., Habtie G.M. Effects of automated teller machine service quality on customer satisfaction: evidence from commercial bank of Ethiopia. Heliyon. 2023;9(8) doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e19132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e19132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10457530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37636405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kliestik T., Kovalova E., Lăzăroiu G. Cognitive decision-making algorithms in data-driven retail intelligence: consumer sentiments, choices, and shopping behaviors, J. Self-Gov. Manag. Econ. 2022;10(1):30–42. doi: 10.22381/jsme10120222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22381/jsme10120222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rydell L., Kucera J. Cognitive attitudes, behavioral choices, and purchasing habits during the COVID-19 pandemic. J. Self-Gov. Manag. Econ. 2021;9(4):35–47. doi: 10.22381/jsme9420213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22381/jsme9420213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins E. Machine learning tools, algorithms, and techniques. J. Self-Gov. Manag. Econ. 2022;10(1):43–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kliestik T., Zvarikova K., Lăzăroiu G. Data-driven machine learning and neural network algorithms in the retailing environment: consumer engagement, experience, and purchase behaviors, Econ. Manag. Financ. Mark. 2022;17(1):57–69. doi: 10.22381/emfm17120224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22381/emfm17120224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watson R., Popescu G.H. Will the COVID-19 pandemic lead to long-term consumer perceptions, behavioral intentions, and acquisition decisions? Econ. Manag. Finan. Mark. 2021;16(4):70–83. doi: 10.22381/emfm16420215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22381/emfm16420215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loh H.S., Lee J.L., Gu Y., Chen H.S., Tay H.L. The effects of digital platforms on customers' satisfaction in international shipping business. Rev. Int. Bus. Strat. 2024;34(2):231–244. doi: 10.1108/RIBS-07-2023-0072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/RIBS-07-2023-0072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awadhi J., Obeidat B., Alshurideh M. The impact of customer service digitalization on customer satisfaction: evidence from telecommunication industry. Int. J. Data Network Sci. 2021;5(4):815–830. doi: 10.5267/j.ijdns.2021.x.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5267/j.ijdns.2021.x.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akram U., Fülöp M.T., Tiron-Tudor A., Topor D.I., Căpușneanu S. Impact of digitalization on customers' well-being in the pandemic period: challenges and opportunities for the retail industry. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2021;18(14):7533. doi: 10.3390/ijerph18147533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18147533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8303578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34299984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekici A., Watson F. A model of consumer life-satisfaction amidst the COVID-19 pandemic: evidence and policy implications. J. Consum. Aff. 2022;56(1):158–179. doi: 10.1111/joca.12393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joca.12393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8446941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34548693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anand B., Chakravarty H., Athalye S.G., Varalaxmi P., Mishra A.K. Understanding consumer behaviour in the digital age: a study of online shopping habits. Shodha Prabha (UGC CARE Journal) 2003;48(3):84–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lasrado F., Thaichon P., Nyadzayo M.W. Exploring the role of relationship management and relationship quality in B2B: empirical insights and future research directions. J. Bus. Ind. Mark. 2023;38(5):1055–1086. doi: 10.1108/JBIM-05-2021-0267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/JBIM-05-2021-0267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yüksel A., Yüksel F. Tourist Satisfaction and Complaining Behavior: Measurement and Management Issues in the Tourism and Hospitality Industry. Nova Science Publishers; New York: 2008. Consumer satisfaction theories: a critical review; pp. 65–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Festinger L. Stanford University; Stanford: 1957. A Theory of Cognitive Dissonance.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardozo R.N. An experimental study of customer effort, expectation, and satisfaction. J. Mark. Res. 1965;2(3):244–249. doi: 10.1177/002224376500200303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/002224376500200303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardozo R.N., Cagley J.W. Experimental study of industrial buyer behavior. J. Mark. Res. 1971;8(3):329–334. doi: 10.1177/002224377100800308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/002224377100800308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi Y. In: Review of Marketing. Zeithaml V.A., editor. American Marketing Association; Chicago: 1990. A critical review of consumer satisfaction; pp. 68–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper J. Cognitive dissonance: where we’ve been and where we’re going. Int. Rev. Soc. Psychol. 2019;32:1–11. doi: 10.5334/irsp.277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5334/irsp.277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yakın V., Güven H., David S., Güven E., Bărbuță-Mișu N., Güven E.T.A., Virlanuta F.O. The effect of cognitive dissonance theory and brand loyalty on consumer complaint behaviors: a cross-cultural study. Sustainability. 2023;15(6):4718. doi: 10.3390/su15064718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su15064718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson R.E. Consumer dissatisfaction: the effect of disconfirmed expectancy on perceived product performance. J. Mark. Res. 1973;10(1):38–44. doi: 10.1177/002224377301000106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/002224377301000106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cotton J.L. In: Selective Exposure to Communication. Zillmann D., Bryant J., editors. Routledge; New York: 2013. Cognitive dissonance in selective exposure; pp. 11–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olson J.C., Dover P.A. Disconfirmation of consumer expectations through product trial. J. Appl. Psychol. 1979;64(2):179–189. https://psycnet.apa.org/doi/10.1037/0021-9010.64.2.179</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.64.2.179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brent S.B. Motivation, steady-state, and structural development: a general model of psychological homeostasis. Motiv. Emot. 1978;2:299–332. doi: 10.1007/BF00993327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF00993327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards J. Harry Helson's adaptation-level theory, happiness treadmills, and behavioral economics. J. History Econ. Thought. 2018;40(1):1–22. doi: 10.1017/S1053837216001140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1053837216001140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro-González S., Fernández-Ferrín P., Bande B., Losada F. Building food consumer loyalty through economic corporate social responsibility: the moderating effects of environmental and social dimensions. J. Environ. Plan. Manag. 2023 doi: 10.1080/09640568.2023.2286434. ePub ahead of print March 22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09640568.2023.2286434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesh R., Haslinda A., Raghavan S. Customer satisfaction: an interpretation of theories with disconfirmation paradigm. Int. J. Bus. Manag. 2016;4(12):269–273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sirgy M.J. Self-concept in consumer behavior: a critical review. J. Consum. Res. 1982;9(3):287–300. doi: 10.1086/208924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/208924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Awadhi J., Obeidat B., Alshurideh M.T. The impact of customer service digitalization on customer satisfaction: evidence from telecommunication industry. Int. J. Data Netw. Sci. 2021;5:815–830.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliver R.L. Effect of expectation and disconfirmation on postexposure product evaluations: an alternative interpretation. J. Appl. Psychol. 1977;62(4):480–486. https://psycnet.apa.org/doi/10.1037/0021-9010.62.4.480</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.62.4.480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parasuraman A.B.L.L., Zeithaml V.A., Berry L. In: The Retailing Reader. Dawson J., Findlay A., Sparks L., editors. Routledge; New York: 1988. SERVQUAL: a multiple-item scale for measuring consumer perceptions of service quality; pp. 12–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoque U.S., Akhter N., Absar N., Khandaker M.U., Al-Mamun A. Assessing service quality using SERVQUAL Model: an empirical study on some private universities in Bangladesh. Trends High. Educ. 2023;2:255–269. doi: 10.3390/higheredu2010013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/higheredu2010013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wider W., Tan F.P., Tan Y.P., Lin J., Fauzi M.A., Wong L.S., Tanucan J.C.M., Hossain S.F.A. Service quality (SERVQUAL) model in private higher education institutions: a bibliometric analysis of past, present, and future prospects. Soc. Sci. Humanit. Open. 2024;9 doi: 10.1016/j.ssaho.2024.100805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ssaho.2024.100805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Melo F.J.C., de Arruda Xavier L., de Albuquerque A.P.G., de Medeiros D.D. Evaluation of quality of online shopping services in times of COVID-19 based on E-S-QUAL model and Fuzzy TOPSIS method. Soft Comput. 2023;27:7497–7511. doi: 10.1007/s00500-022-07696-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00500-022-07696-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9750054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36536665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goutam D., Gopalakrishna B.V., Ganguli S. Determinants of customer satisfaction and loyalty in e-commerce settings: an emerging economy perspective. Int. J. Internet Mark. Advert. 2021;15(3):327–348. doi: 10.1504/IJIMA.2021.115437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1504/IJIMA.2021.115437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aagaard A. Palgrave Macmillan; Cham: 2019. Digital Business Models.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elg M., Birch-Jensen A., Gremyr I., Martin J., Melin U. Digitalisation and quality management: problems and prospects. Prod. Plan Control. 2021;32(12):990–1003. doi: 10.1080/09537287.2020.1780509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09537287.2020.1780509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vadana I.I., Kuivalainen O., Torkkeli L., Saarenketo S. The role of digitalization on the internationalization strategy of born-digital companies. Sustainability. 2021;13(24) doi: 10.3390/su132414002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su132414002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pradhan R.P., Arvin M.B., Nair M., Bennett S.E., Hall J.H. The information revolution, innovation diffusion and economic growth: an examination of causal links in European countries. Qual. Quant. 2019;53:1529–1563. doi: 10.1007/s11135-018-0826-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11135-018-0826-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>On the approval of the Concept of the development of the digital economy and society of Ukraine for 2018-2020 and the approval of the plan of measures for its implementation. https://zakon.rada.gov.ua/laws/show/67-2018-%D1%80#Text Order of the Cabinet of Ministers from 17.01.2018, No. 67, Official site of the Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine, 2018, Available online:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dost B., Illyas M., Rehman C.A. Online shopping trends and its effects on consumer buying behavior: a case study of young generation of Pakistan, NG-J. Soc. Dev. 2015;417(3868):1–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grieve P. Grieve Patrick customer Orientation: definition, examples, skills. 2020. https://www.zendesk.com/blog/customer-oriented-support/ Available online:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paulus M., Jordanow S., Millemann J.A. Adoption factors of digital services—a systematic literature review. Serv. Sci. 2022;14(4):318–350. doi: 10.1287/serv.2022.0305.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1287/serv.2022.0305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins E. Machine learning tools, algorithms, and techniques. J. Self-Gov. Manag. Econ. 2022;10(1):43–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diebner R., Malfara D., Neher K., Thompson M., Vancauwenberghe M. Prediction: future of CX. McKinsey. 2021 https://www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/marketing-and-sales/our-insights/prediction-the-future-of-cx Available online:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandon U., Kiran R., Sah A.N. Customer satisfaction as mediator between website service quality and repurchase intention: an emerging economy case. Serv. Sci. 2017;9(2):106–120. doi: 10.1287/serv.2016.0159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1287/serv.2016.0159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nica E., Sabie O.M., Mascu S., Luţan A.G. Artificial intelligence decision-making in shopping patterns: consumer values, cognition, and attitudes. Econ. Manag. Financ. Mark. 2022;17(1):31–43. doi: 10.22381/emfm17120222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22381/emfm17120222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alibaba.com  Alibaba Group official portal. 2023. https://www.alibaba.com/ Available online:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNeish D., Wolf M.G. Thinking twice about sum scores. Behav. Res. Methods. 2020;52(6):2287–2305. doi: 10.3758/s13428-020-01398-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3758/s13428-020-01398-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32323277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marzi G., Balzano M., Egidi L., Magrini A. CLC estimator: a tool for latent construct estimation via congeneric approaches in survey research. Multivar. Behav. Res. 2023;58(6):1160–1164. doi: 10.1080/00273171.2023.2193718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00273171.2023.2193718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37038660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>YachouAityassine F.L., Al-Ajlouni M.M., Mohammad A. The effect of digital marketing strategy on customer and organizational outcomes. Mark. Manag. Innov. 2022;4:45–54. doi: 10.21272/mmi.2022.4-05.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21272/mmi.2022.4-05</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández-Portillo A., Ramos-Vecino N., Ramos-Mariño A., Cachón-Rodríguez G. How the digital business ecosystem affects stakeholder satisfaction: its impact on business performance. Rev. Manag. Sci. 2024 doi: 10.1007/s11846-023-00720-2. (in press)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11846-023-00720-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akram U., Fülöp M.T., Tiron-Tudor A., Topor D.I., Căpușneanu S. Impact of digitalization on customers' well-being in the pandemic period: Challenges and opportunities for the retail industry. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2021;18(14):7533. doi: 10.3390/ijerph18147533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18147533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8303578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34299984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demirel D. The effect of service quality on customer satisfaction in digital age: customer satisfaction based examination of digital CRM. J. Bus. Econ. Manag. 2022;23(3):507–531. doi: 10.3846/jbem.2022.15328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3846/jbem.2022.15328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balzano M. Serendipity in management studies: a literature review and future research directions. Manag. Decis. 2022;60(13):130–152. doi: 10.1108/MD-02-2022-0245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/MD-02-2022-0245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazari-Shirkouhi S., Badizadeh A., Dashtpeyma M., Ghodsi R. A model to improve user acceptance of e-services in healthcare systems based on technology acceptance model: an empirical study. J. Ambient. Intell. Humaniz. Comput. 2023;14(6):7919–7935. doi: 10.1007/s12652-023-04601-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12652-023-04601-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10080501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37228695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pascucci F., Savelli E., Gistri G. How digital technologies reshape marketing: evidence from a qualitative investigation. Ital. J. Mark. 2023;2023:27–58. doi: 10.1007/s43039-023-00063-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43039-023-00063-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perifanis N.-A., Kitsios F. Investigating the influence of artificial intelligence on business value in the digital era of strategy: a literature review. Information. 2023;14(2):85. doi: 10.3390/info14020085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/info14020085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>