<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309349</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1936-1521</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>17</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of child &amp; adolescent trauma</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Child Adolesc Trauma</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>What Predicts COVID-Specific Symptoms of Stress in Children and Adolescents, Virus Threats or Social Distancing?</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>957</StartPage><EndPage>967</EndPage><MedlinePgn>957-967</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40653-024-00623-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The COVID-19 crisis may have deleterious effects on children's and adolescents' mental health. However, there have been no published studies in which the COVID-related stress symptoms were investigated in a French ordinary pediatric population. The main objective of this study was to examine virus threats and social distancing measures to determine which were more disturbing for children and adolescents, and which were better predictors of post traumatic stress symptoms (PTSS). 1639 parents of children aged between 1 and 18 participated in an online survey. Parents completed questionnaires regarding their children's and adolescents' mental health while in the first French confinement. The data showed that most children and adolescents had PTSS, such as irritability and tantrums, intrusive thoughts or memories, difficulties in falling asleep, aggression, trouble concentrating, and negative emotions. Multiple linear models supported that both virus threats and social distancing- related disturbances were predictors of PTSS scores, with social distancing being a stronger predictor of PTSS scores than virus threats. Additional analyses across age groups revealed that social distancing measures predicted two times more PTSS than virus threat measures in toddlers, while virus threat measures were a stronger predictor of PTSS in adolescents. This is the first study that has investigated stress symptoms in a French pediatric population during the first French confinement episode because of the COVID-19 crisis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soubelet</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9263-4785</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Cote d'Azur, 98 bd Edouard Herriot, Nice, 06000 France.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.460782.f</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 4910 6551</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>J Child Adolesc Trauma</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101306630</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1936-1521</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social distancing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Stress symptoms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestThe author certifies that she has NO affiliations with or involvement in any organization or entity with any financial interest (such as honoraria; educational grants; participation in speakers’ bureaus; membership, employment, consultancies, stock ownership, or other equity interest; and expert testimony or patent licensing arrangements), or non-financial interest (such as personal or professional relationships, affiliations, knowledge or beliefs) in the subject matter or materials discussed in this manuscript.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11413290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40653-024-00623-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Almeida, I. L. L., Rego, J. F., Teixeira, A. C. G., &amp; Moreira, M. R. (2021). Social isolation and its impact on child and adolescent development: A systematic review. Revista paulista de pediatria: orgao oficial da Sociedade de Pediatria de Sao Paulo, 40, e2020385. 10.1590/1984-0462/2022/40/2020385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8543788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34614137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Psychiatric Association (2013). Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of mental Disorder-5. Washington DC.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks, S. K., Webster, R. K., Smith, L. E., Woodland, L., Wessely, S., Greenberg, N., &amp; Rubin, G. J. (2020). The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: Rapid review of the evidence. The Lancet, 395(10227), 912–920. 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30460-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7158942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32112714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brummelman, E., Terburg, D., Smit, M., Bögels, S. M., &amp; Bos, P. A. (2019). Parental touch reduces social vigilance in children. Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience, 35, 87–93. 10.1016/j.dcn.2018.05.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6968960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29784619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cascio, C. J., Moore, D., &amp; McGlone, F. (2019). Social touch and human development. Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience, 35, 5–11. 10.1016/j.dcn.2018.04.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6968965</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29731417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charton, L., Labrecque, L., &amp; Josy Lévy, J. (2022). La pandémie de COVID-19: quelles répercussions sur les familles? Enfances Familles Générations, 40, retrieved from http://journals.openedition.org/efg/15152 on January, the 3rd of 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y., Zhu, Z., Lei, F., Lei, S., &amp; Chen, J. (2021). Prevalence and risk factors of post traumatic stress disorder symptoms in students aged 8–18 in Wuhan, China 6 months after the control of COVID-19. Frontiers in Psychology, 4651, 40575. 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.740575.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8548756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34721214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Childline Support Center Japan (2020). Document 2: Children’s voice associated with COVID-19 (preliminary data).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Los Reyes, A., Augenstein, T. M., Wang, M., Thomas, S. A., Drabick, D. A., Burgers, D. E., et al. (2015). The validity of the multi-informant approach to assessing child and adolescent mental health. Psychological Bulletin, 141(4), 858–900. pmid:25915035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4486608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25915035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deighton, J., Lereya, S. T., Casey, P., Patalay, P., Humphrey, N., &amp; Wolpert, M. (2019). Prevalence of mental health problems in schools: Poverty and other risk factors among 28 000 adolescents in England. The British Journal of Psychiatry: The Journal of Mental Science, 1–3. 10.1192/bjp.2019.19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7557860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30698513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunn, E. C., Nishimi, K., Powers, A., &amp; Bradley, B. (2017). Is developmental timing of trauma exposure associated with depressive and post-traumatic stress disorder symptoms in adulthood? Journal of Psychiatric Research, 84, 119–127. 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.09.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5479490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27728852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Khomri, M., Cornet, T., &amp; Bendavid, R. (2020). Le moral et les attentes des salariés pendant le second confinement. Dossier Spécial IFOP 22/12/2020. Retrieved from https://www.ifop.com/publication/webinar-le-moral-et-les-attentes-des-salaries-pendant-le-second-confinement/ on January; the 3rd of 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gil, E. (Ed.). (2010). Children’s self-initiated gradual exposure: The wonders of posttraumatic play and behavioral reenactments. Working with children to heal interpersonal trauma: The power of play (pp. 44–63). Guilford Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gindt, M., Richez, A., Battista, M., Fabre, R., Thümmler, S., Fernandez, A., &amp; Askenazy, F. (2021). Validation of the French Version of the child post-traumatic stress checklist in French School-aged children. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 11. 10.3389/fpsyt.2021.678916.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8418351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34489751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gross, J. J., &amp; Thompson, R. A. (2007). Emotion regulation: Conceptual foundations. In J. J. Gross (Ed.), Handbook of emotion regulation (pp. 3–26). Guilford Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, J., Fu, M., Liu, D., Zhan, B., Wang, X., &amp; van IJzendoorn, M. H. (2020). Is the psychological impact of exposure to COVID-19 stronger in adolescents with pre-pandemic maltreatment experiences? A survey of rural Chinese adolescents. Child Abuse &amp; Neglect, 104667. 10.1016/j.chiabu.2020.104667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32859393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Husky, M. M., Lépine, J. P., Gasquet, I., &amp; Kovess-Masfety, V. (2015). Exposure to traumatic events and posttraumatic stress disorder in France: Results from the WMH Survey. Journal of Traumatic Stress, 28(4), 275–282. 10.1002/jts.22020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26179388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karbasi, Z., &amp; Eslami, P. (2022). Prevalence of post-traumatic stress disorder during the COVID-19 pandemic in children: A review and suggested solutions. Middle East Current Psychiatry, 29, 74. 10.1186/s43045-022-00240-x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koenen, K. C., Ratanatharathorn, A., Ng, L., McLaughlin, K. A., Bromet, E. J., Stein, D. J., Karam, E. G., Ruscio, M., Benjet, A., Scott, C., Atwoli, K., Petukhova, L., Lim, M., Aguilar-Gaxiola, C. C. W., Al-Hamzawi, S., Alonso, A., Bunting, J., Ciutan, B., de Girolamo, M., Degenhardt, G., &amp; Kessler, L., R. C (2017). Posttraumatic stress disorder in the World Mental Health surveys. Psychological Medicine, 47(13), 2260–2274. 10.1017/S0033291717000708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6034513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28385165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loades, M. E., Chatburn, E., Higson-Sweeney, N., Reynolds, S., Shafran, R., Brigden, A., Linney, C., McManus, M. N., Borwick, C., &amp; Crawley, E. (2020). Rapid systematic review: The impact of social isolation and loneliness on the mental health of children and adolescents in the Context of COVID-19. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, S0890856720303373. 10.1016/j.jaac.2020.05.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7267797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32504808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merikangas, K. R., He, J. P., Burstein, M., Swanson, S. A., Avenevoli, S., Cui, L., Benjet, C., Georgiades, K., &amp; Swendsen, J. (2010). Lifetime prevalence of mental disorders in U.S. adolescents: Results from the National Comorbidity Survey replication–adolescent supplement (NCS-A). Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 49(10), 980–989. 10.1016/j.jaac.2010.05.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2946114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20855043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moriguchi, Y. (2014). The early development of executive function and its relation to social interaction: A brief review. Frontiers in Psychology, 5, 10.3389/fpsyg.2014.00388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4010730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24808885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norton, B., Ferriegel, M., &amp; Norton, C. (2011). Somatic expressions of trauma in experiential play therapy. International Journal of Play Therapy, 20, 138–152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orben, A., Tomova, L., &amp; Blakemore, S. J. (2020). The effects of social deprivation on adolescent development and mental health. The Lancet Child &amp; Adolescent Health, 22, S2352464220301863. 10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30186-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32540024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozamiz, N., Mondragon, N., Santamaria, M., &amp; Gorrotxategi, M. (2020). Psychological symptoms during the two stages of lockdown in response to the COVID-19 outbreak: An investigation in a sample of citizens in Northern Spain. Frontiers in Psychology, 11, 1491. 10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7314923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32625157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandita, S., Mishra, G., H., &amp; Chib, S. (2020). Psychological impact of COVID 19 crises on students through the lens of stimulus-organism-response (SOR) model. Children and Youth Services Review, 105783. 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33518862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rescorla, L. A., Ginzburg, S., Achenbach, T. M., Ivanova, M. Y., Almqvist, F., Begovac, I., et al. (2013). Cross-informant agreement between parent-reported and adolescent self-reported problems in 25 societies. Journal of Clinical Child &amp; Adolescent Psychology, 42(2), 262–273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23009025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russotti, J., Warmingham, J. M., Duprey, E. B., Handley, E. D., Manly, J. T., Rogosh, F. A., &amp; Cicchetti, D. (2021). Child maltreatment and the development of psychopathology: The role of developmental timing and chronicity. Child Abuse &amp; Neglect, 120, 105215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8384692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34293550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salmon, K., &amp; Bryant, R. A. (2002). Posttraumatic stress disorder in children. The influence of developmental factors. Clinical Psychology Review, 22, 163–188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11806018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sayed, M. H., Hegazi, M. A., El-Baz, M. S., Alahmadi, T. S., Zubairi, N. A., Altuwiriqi, M. A. (2021). COVID-19 related posttraumatic stress disorder in children and adolescents in Saudi Arabia. PLoS ONE 16(8): e025544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8336789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34347842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheeringa, M. S. (2010). Young Child PTSD Checklist (YCPC). Tulane University. Version 5/23/14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheeringa, M. (2014). Child PTSD checklist-Child version and parent version [Measurement instrument]. New Orleans, LA: Tulane Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences. http://medicine.tulane.edu/departments/psychiatry/research/dr-scheeringas-lab/manuals-measures-trainings.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schore, A. (2003). Affect dysregulation and disorders of the self. Norton.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selçuk, E. B., Demir, A., Erbay, L. G., Özcan, Ö. Ö., Gürer, H., &amp; Dönmez, Y. E. (2021). Anxiety, depression and post-traumatic stress disorder symptoms in adolescents during the COVID-19 outbreak and associated factors. International Journal of Clinical Practice, 75, e14880. 10.1111/ijcp.14880.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34528350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shafiq, S., Nipa, S., Sultana, S., Rifat-Ur-Rahman, M., &amp; Mostafizur Rahman, M. (2020). Exploring the triggering factors for mental stress of University students amid COVID-19 in Bangladesh: A perception-based study. Children and Youth Services Review, 105789. 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7837045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33518863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stadler, C., &amp; Walitza, S. COVID-19 Ein Virus Nimmt Einfluss auf Unsere Psyche. Einschätzungen und Maßnahmen aus Psychologischer Perspektive. 2., Erweiterte und Überarbeitete Auflage Kohlhammer; Stuttgart, Germany: 2021. Risikofaktoren und Resilienz für die kindliche Entwicklung in der COVID-19 Krise.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strassle, P. D., Stewart, A. L., Quintero, S. M., Bonilla, J., Alhomsi, A., Santana-Ufret, V., Maldonado, A. I., Forde, A. T., &amp; Napoles, A. M. (2022). COVID-19-related discrimination among racial/ethnic minorities and other marginalized communities in the Unites States. American Journal of Public Health, 112, 453–466. 10.2105/AJPH.2021.306594.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8887166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35196054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terr, L. (1991). Childhood traumas: An outline and overview. American Journal of Psychiatry, 148, 10–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1824611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thümmler, S., Gindt, M., Maria, F., Nachon, O., Battista, M., &amp; Askenazy, F. (2017). Young Child PTSD checklist (YCPC) (French Version 18/05/17 of YCPC DSM-5, Scheeringa 23/05/14). Retrieved from http://medicine.tulane.edu/departments/psychiatry/research/dr-scheeringas-lab/manuals-measures-trainings.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thümmler, S., Gindt, M., Maria, F., Nachon, O., Batttista, M., &amp; Askenazy, F. (2017). Child PTSD checklist (CPC) (French Version 18/05/17 of CPC DSM-5, Scheeringa 23/05/14). Retrieved from http://medicine.tulane.edu/departments/psychiatry/research/dr2-scheeringas-lab/manuals-measures-trainings.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trickey, D., Siddaway, A. P., Meiser-Stedman, R., Serpell, L., &amp; Field, A. P. (2012). A meta-analysis of risk factors for post-traumatic stress disorder in children and adolescents. Clinical Psychology Review, 32(2), 122–138. 10.1016/j.cpr.2011.12.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22245560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsur, N., &amp; Abu-Raiya, H. (2020). COVID-19-related fear and stress among individuals who experienced child abuse: The mediating effect of complex posttraumatic stress disorder. Child Abuse &amp; Neglect, 104694. 10.1016/j.chiabu.2020.104694.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7430290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32900515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Kolk, B., McFarlane, A., &amp; Weisaeth, L. (Eds.). (1996). Traumatic stress: The effects of overwhelming experience on the mind, body, and society. The Guilford.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, F., Wen, J., Huang, N., Riem, M., Lodder, P., &amp; Guo, J. (2022). Prevalence and related factors of child posttraumatic stress disorder during COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and meta-analysis. European Psychiatry, 65(1), E37. 10.1192/j.eurpsy.2022.31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9280924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35726735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>YoungMinds (2020). Coronavirus: Impact on young people with mental health needs. https://youngminds.org.uk/media/3708/coronavirus-report_march2020.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Shuai, L., Yu, H., Wang, Z., Qiu, M., Lu, L., &amp; Chen, R. (2020). Acute stress, behavioural symptoms and mood states among school-age children with attention deficit/hyperactive disorder during the COVID-19 outbreak. Asian Journal of Psychiatry, 51, 102077doi. 10.1016/j.ajp.2020.102077.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32315967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., Pan, R., Cai, Y., &amp; Pan, J. (2021). The prevalence of post-traumatic stress disorder in the General Population during the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and single-arm Meta-analysis. Psychiatry Investig, 18(5), 426–433. 10.30773/pi.2020.0458.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8169329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33910325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>