<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39308836</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Integration of Diagnostic Lung Ultrasound Into Clinical Practice by Hospitalists in an Academic Medical Center: A Retrospective Chart Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69796</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69796</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69796</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69796</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background Point-of-care lung ultrasound (LUS) is a guideline-recommended imaging modality that has been shown to be more accurate than chest radiography for multiple causes of dyspnea. This study was conducted to understand the impact of LUS on real-world clinical decision-making among hospitalists. Methods  A retrospective chart review was conducted of patients who received a LUS while hospitalized at a quaternary care academic medical center between July 2020 and June 2022. Data was extracted from the electronic health record (EHR) into a standardized REDCap form. Cases were defined as patients who had received a LUS that (1) had images archived and accessible to viewing through the EHR and (2) had an imaging report documented in the EHR. Results Of the 820 LUSs reviewed, 297 (36.2%) were performed to evaluate for appropriateness of thoracentesis, 205 (25%) for diagnosing or monitoring of pneumonia related to COVID-19, 169 (20.6%) for volume status assessment, 136 (16.6%) for worsening respiratory status, 114 (13.9%) for monitoring pleural effusions, 64 (7.8%) for diagnosing or monitoring of pneumonia not related to COVID-19, and 12 (1.5%) for monitoring of diuresis. Documentation was sufficient to determine clinical decision-making in 730 (89%) of LUSs reviewed, 739 (90.1%) were considered to be diagnostically useful, and 327 (39.9%) changed management. Conclusions These findings suggest LUS was diagnostically useful and routinely changed management in hospitalist practice. Further, documentation in the EHR was sufficient to allow for the evaluation of real-world clinical decision-making using LUS, which is an important gap in both the education and health services research literature.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Slaugh et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Slaugh</LastName><ForeName>John-David</ForeName><Initials>JD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Issa</LastName><ForeName>Meltiady</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Internal Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grimm</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Calderon</LastName><ForeName>Antonio J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sindelar</LastName><ForeName>Solomon</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Van Hook</LastName><ForeName>Reed</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McBeth</LastName><ForeName>Lauren</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maw</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">decision-making</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hospitalists</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lung ultrasound</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">point of care</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: This research was supported by the National Institutes of Health (NIH)/National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) Colorado Clinical and Translational Science Awards (CTSA) Grant Number UL1 TR002535. Its contents are the authors' sole responsibility and do not necessarily represent official NIH views. Financial relationships: Anna Maw declare(s) consultant honoraria from UltraSight. Dr. Maw declares that consultant honoraria from the company "UltraSight" were paid to her institution. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>39</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39308836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11416203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Appropriate use of point-of-care ultrasonography in patients with acute dyspnea in emergency department or inpatient settings: a clinical guideline from the American College of Physicians. Qaseem A, Etxeandia-Ikobaltzeta I, Mustafa RA, et al. Ann Intern Med. 2021;174:985–993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33900792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Accuracy of lung ultrasonography versus chest radiography for the diagnosis of adult community-acquired pneumonia: review of the literature and meta-analysis. Ye X, Xiao H, Chen B, Zhang S. PLoS One. 2015;10:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4479467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26107512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnostic accuracy of point-of-care lung ultrasonography and chest radiography in adults with symptoms suggestive of acute decompensated heart failure: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Maw AM, Hassanin A, Ho PM, et al. JAMA Netw Open. 2019;2:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6484641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30874784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Point-of-care ultrasonography for the diagnosis of acute cardiogenic pulmonary edema in patients presenting with acute dyspnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Al Deeb M, Barbic S, Featherstone R, Dankoff J, Barbic D. Acad Emerg Med. 2014;21:843–852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25176151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnostic accuracy and reproducibility of pleural and lung ultrasound in discriminating cardiogenic causes of acute dyspnea in the emergency department. Cibinel GA, Casoli G, Elia F, Padoan M, Pivetta E, Lupia E, Goffi A. Intern Emerg Med. 2012;7:65–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22033792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ultrasound in the diagnosis and management of pleural effusions. Soni NJ, Franco R, Velez MI, Schnobrich D, Dancel R, Restrepo MI, Mayo PH. J Hosp Med. 2015;10:811–816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4715558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26218493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pleural ultrasonography versus chest radiography for the diagnosis of pneumothorax: review of the literature and meta-analysis. Alrajab S, Youssef AM, Akkus NI, Caldito G. Crit Care. 2013;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4057340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24060427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>2021 ESC guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure: developed by the task force for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) with the special contribution of the Heart Failure Association (HFA) of the ESC. McDonagh TA, Metra M, Adamo M, et al. Rev Esp Cardiol (Engl Ed) 2022;75:523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35636830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>2022 AHA/ACC/HFSA guideline for the management of heart failure: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Joint Committee on Clinical Practice Guidelines. Heidenreich PA, Bozkurt B, Aguilar D, et al. Circulation. 2022;145:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35363499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>New international guidelines and consensus on the use of lung ultrasound. Demi L, Wolfram F, Klersy C, et al. J Ultrasound Med. 2023;42:309–344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10086956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35993596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hospitalist perceptions of barriers to lung ultrasound adoption in diverse hospital environments. Maw AM, Ho PM, Morris MA, et al. Diagnostics (Basel) 2021;11:1451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8391960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34441385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barriers to learning and using point-of-care ultrasound: a survey of practicing internists in six North American institutions. Wong J, Montague S, Wallace P, et al. Ultrasound J. 2020;12:19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32307598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Using Iterative RE-AIM to enhance hospitalist adoption of lung ultrasound in the management of patients with COVID-19: an implementation pilot study. Maw AM, Morris MA, Glasgow RE, et al. Implement Sci Commun. 2022;3:89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9372925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35962441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers E. Simon and Schuster, New York, NY. New York: Free Press; 2003. Diffusion of innovations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disseminating innovations in health care. Berwick DM. JAMA. 2003;289:1969–1975.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12697800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Research electronic data capture (REDCap)—a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. Harris PA, Taylor R, Thielke R, Payne J, Gonzalez N, Conde JG. J Biomed Inform. 2009;42:377–381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2700030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18929686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of lung ultrasound on clinical-decision making across departments: a systematic review. Heldeweg ML, Vermue L, Kant M, et al. Ultrasound J. 2022;14:5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8748548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35006383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Could the use of bedside lung ultrasound reduce the number of chest x-rays in the intensive care unit? Brogi E, Bignami E, Sidoti A, et al. Cardiovasc Ultrasound. 2017;15:23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5597991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28903756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lung ultrasound scanning for respiratory failure in acutely ill patients: a review. Koenig S, Mayo P, Volpicelli G, Millington SJ. Chest. 2020;158:2511–2516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7442567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32835706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prognostic value of residual pulmonary congestion at discharge assessed by lung ultrasound imaging in heart failure. Coiro S, Rossignol P, Ambrosio G, et al. Eur J Heart Fail. 2015;17:1172–1181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26417699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lung ultrasound in internal medicine efficiently drives the management of patients with heart failure and speeds up the discharge time. Mozzini C, Di Dio Perna M, Pesce G, et al. Intern Emerg Med. 2018;13:27–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28803375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lung ultrasound in acute and chronic heart failure: a clinical consensus statement of the European Association of Cardiovascular Imaging (EACVI) Gargani L, Girerd N, Platz E, et al. Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2023;24:1569–1582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11032195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37450604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emergency departments, acute heart failure, and admissions: one size does not fit all. Pang PS, Schuur JD. JACC Heart Fail. 2014;2:278–280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24952695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zero to 50,000 - the 20th anniversary of the hospitalist. Wachter RM, Goldman L. N Engl J Med. 2016;375:1009–1011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27508924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>