<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39307843</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2044-8279</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The British journal of educational psychology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Br J Educ Psychol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A machine-learning model of academic resilience in the times of the COVID-19 pandemic: Evidence drawn from 79 countries/economies in the PISA 2022 mathematics study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/bjep.12715</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Given that students from socio-economically disadvantaged family backgrounds are more likely to suffer from low academic performance, there is an interest in identifying features of academic resilience, which may mitigate the relationship between disadvantaged socio-economic status and academic performance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study sought to combine machine learning and explainable artificial intelligence (XAI) technique to identify key features of academic resilience in mathematics learning during COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Based on PISA 2022 data in 79 countries/economies, the random forest model coupled with Shapley additive explanations (SHAP) value technique not only uncovered the key features of academic resilience but also examined the contributions of each key feature.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Findings indicated that 35 features were identified in the classification of academically resilient and non-academically resilient students, which largely validated the previous academic resilient framework. Notably, gender differences were shown in the distribution of some key features. Research findings also indicated that resilient students tended to have a stable emotional state, high levels of self-efficacy, low levels of truancy and positive future aspirations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study has established a research paradigm essentially methodological in nature to bridge the gap between psychological theories and big data in the field of educational psychology.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">To sum up, our study shed light on the issues of education equity and quality from a global perspective in the times of the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 British Psychological Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheung</LastName><ForeName>Kwok-Cheung</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0115-0866</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Educational Testing and Assessment Research Centre, Faculty of Education, University of Macau, Macao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sit</LastName><ForeName>Pou-Seong</ForeName><Initials>PS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7044-3128</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Educational Testing and Assessment Research Centre, Faculty of Education, University of Macau, Macao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Jia-Qi</ForeName><Initials>JQ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9004-8336</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Educational Testing and Assessment Research Centre, Faculty of Education, University of Macau, Macao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lam</LastName><ForeName>Chi-Chio</ForeName><Initials>CC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-3219-999X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Educational Testing and Assessment Research Centre, Faculty of Education, University of Macau, Macao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mak</LastName><ForeName>Soi-Kei</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9011-5607</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Educational Testing and Assessment Research Centre, Faculty of Education, University of Macau, Macao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ieong</LastName><ForeName>Man-Kai</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6923-9069</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Educational Testing and Assessment Research Centre, Faculty of Education, University of Macau, Macao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Br J Educ Psychol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370636</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0007-0998</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PISA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">academic resilience</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">explainable artificial intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gender differences</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">machine learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mathematical literacy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39307843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjep.12715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adger, W. N. (2000). Social and ecological resilience: Are they related? Progress in Human Geography, 24(3), 347–364. https://doi.org/10.1191/030913200701540465</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agasisti, T., Avvisati, F., Borgonovi, F., &amp; Longobardi, S. (2021). What school factors are associated with the success of socio‐economically disadvantaged students? An empirical investigation using PISA data. Social Indicators Research, 157, 749–781. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205‐021‐02668‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agasisti, T., &amp; Longobardi, S. (2014). Inequality in education: Can Italian disadvantaged students close the gap? Journal of Behavioral and Experimental Economics, 52, 8–20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socec.2014.05.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agasisti, T., Longobardi, S., &amp; Regoli, A. (2017). A cross‐country panel approach to exploring the determinants of educational equity through PISA data. Quality &amp; Quantity, 51, 1243–1260. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11135‐016‐0328‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alivernini, F., Manganelli, S., &amp; Lucidi, F. (2016). The last shall be the first: Competencies, equity and the power of resilience in the Italian school system. Learning and Individual Differences, 51, 19–28. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lindif.2016.08.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al‐Najjar, H. A., Pradhan, B., Beydoun, G., Sarkar, R., Park, H. J., &amp; Alamri, A. (2023). A novel method using explainable artificial intelligence (XAI)‐based Shapley additive explanations for spatial landslide prediction using time‐series SAR dataset. Gondwana Research, 123, 107–124. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gr.2022.08.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydın, M., &amp; Erdem, C. (2023). Profiles of academically resilient students: An examination on TIMSS mathematics data. Current Psychology, 42(22), 18916–18927. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12144‐022‐03055‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batista, G. E. A. P. A., Bazzan, A. L. C., &amp; Monard, M. A. (2003). Balancing training data for automated annotation of keywords: Case study. In Proceedings of the second Brazilian workshop on bioinformatics (pp. 35–43).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekkar, M., Djemaa, H. K., &amp; Alitouche, T. A. (2013). Evaluation measures for models' assessment over imbalanced data sets. Journal of Information Engineering and Applications, 3(10), 27–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bloem, J., Flunger, B., Stroet, K., &amp; Hornstra, L. (2023). Differences in need‐supportive teaching toward students from different socioeconomic backgrounds and the role of teachers' attitudes. Social Psychology of Education, 27, 955–1005. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11218‐023‐09831‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borman, G. D., &amp; Overman, L. T. (2004). Academic resilience in mathematics among poor and minority students. The Elementary School Journal, 104(3), 177–195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breiman, L. (2001). Random forests. Machine Learning, 45(1), 5–32. https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1010933404324</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bronfenbrenner, U. (1979). The ecology of human development: Experiments by nature and design. Harvard University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bu, Y., &amp; Chen, F. (2023). What key contextual factors contribute to students' reading literacy among top‐performing countries and economies? Statistical and machine learning analyses. International Journal of Educational Research, 122, 102267. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijer.2023.102267</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bzdok, D., Altman, N., &amp; Krzywinski, M. (2018). Statistics versus machine learning. Nature Methods, 15(4), 233–234. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.4642</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, F., Sakyi, A., &amp; Cui, Y. (2022). Identifying key contextual factors of digital reading literacy through a machine learning approach. Journal of Educational Computing Research, 60(7), 1763–1795. https://doi.org/10.1177/07356331221083215</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheung, K. C. (2017). The effects of resilience in learning variables on mathematical literacy performance: A study of learning characteristics of the academic resilient and advantaged low achievers in Shanghai, Singapore, Hong Kong, Taiwan and Korea. Educational Psychology, 37(8), 965–982. https://doi.org/10.1080/01443410.2016.1194372</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheung, K. C., Mak, S. K., Sit, P. S., &amp; Ieong, M. K. (2021). Secondary analysis of PISA data for grade level effect due to grade repetition on improvement in reading performance. International Journal of Education and Psychology in the Community, 11(1/2), 180–194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheung, K. C., Sit, P. S., Soh, K. C., Ieong, M. K., &amp; Mak, S. K. (2014). Predicting academic resilience with reading engagement and demographic variables: Comparing Shanghai, Hong Kong, Korea, and Singapore from the PISA perspective. The Asia‐Pacifc Education Researcher, 23, 895–909. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40299‐013‐0143‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clavel, J. G., García Crespo, F. J., &amp; Sanz San Miguel, L. (2022). Rising above their circumstances: What makes some disadvantaged east and south‐east Asian students perform far better in science than their background predicts? Asia Pacific Journal of Education, 42(4), 714–729. https://doi.org/10.1080/02188791.2021.1886905</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deci, E. L., &amp; Ryan, R. M. (2000). The “what” and “why” of goal pursuits: Human needs and the self‐determination of behavior. Psychological Inquiry, 11(4), 227–268. https://doi.org/10.1207/S15327965PLI1104_01</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domínguez, M., Vieira, M. J., &amp; Vidal, J. (2012). The impact of the programme for international student assessment on academic journals. Assessment in Education: Principles, Policy &amp; Practice, 19(4), 393–409. https://doi.org/10.1080/0969594X.2012.659175</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwivedi, R., Dave, D., Naik, H., Singhal, S., Omer, R., Patel, P., Qian, B., Wen, Z., Shah, T., Morgan, G., &amp; Ranjan, R. (2023). Explainable AI (XAI): Core ideas, techniques, and solutions. ACM Computing Surveys, 55(9), 1–33. https://doi.org/10.1145/3561048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García‐Crespo, F. J., Fernández Alonso, R., &amp; Muñiz Fernández, J. (2019). Resilient and low performer students: Personal and family determinants in European countries. Psicothema, 31(4), 363–375. https://doi.org/10.7334/psicothema2019.245</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García‐Crespo, F. J., Fernández Alonso, R., &amp; Muñiz, J. (2022). Academic resilience in mathematics and science: Europe TIMSS‐2019 data. Psicothema, 34(2), 217–225. https://doi.org/10.7334/psicothema2021.486</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gizir, C. A., &amp; Aydin, G. (2009). Protective factors contributing to the academic resilience of students living in poverty in Turkey. Professional School Counseling, 13(1), 2156759X0901300103. https://doi.org/10.1177/2156759X0901300103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorostiaga, A., &amp; Rojo‐Álvarez, J. L. (2016). On the use of conventional and statistical‐learning techniques for the analysis of PISA results in Spain. Neurocomputing, 171, 625–637. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neucom.2015.07.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunderson, L. H. (2000). Ecological resilience—In theory and application. Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics, 31(1), 425–439. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.31.1.425</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartanto, A., Yang, H., &amp; Yang, S. (2018). Bilingualism positively predicts mathematical competence: Evidence from two large‐scale studies. Learning and Individual Differences, 61, 216–227. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lindif.2017.12.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, J., Dong, X., &amp; Peng, Y. (2022). Discovery of the key contextual factors relevant to the reading performance of elementary school students from 61 countries/regions: Insight from a machine learning‐based approach. Reading and Writing, 35(1), 93–127. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11145‐021‐10176‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, H., Tang, X., Zhang, Y., Sun, Y., Zhang, X., &amp; Salmela‐Aro, K. (2023). Mathematics learning gap during pandemic among early adolescents: Roles of own aspiration and parental involvement. Learning and Individual Differences, 106, 102343. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lindif.2023.102343</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, J., &amp; Ling, C. X. (2005). Using AUC and accuracy in evaluating learning algorithms. IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering, 17(3), 299–310. https://doi.org/10.1109/TKDE.2005.50</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jonathan, B., Putra, P. H., &amp; Ruldeviyani, Y. (2020). Observation imbalanced data text to predict users selling products on female daily with smote, tomek, and smote‐tomek. In 2020 IEEE international conference on industry 4.0, artificial intelligence, and communications technology (IAICT) (pp. 81–85). IEEE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan, N. C., &amp; Levine, S. C. (2009). Socioeconomic variation, number competence, and mathematics learning difficulties in young children. Developmental Disabilities Research Reviews, 15(1), 60–68. https://doi.org/10.1002/ddrr.46</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juba, B., &amp; Le, H. S. (2019). Precision‐recall versus accuracy and the role of large data sets. Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, 33(1), 4039–4048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalaycioglu, D. B. (2015). The influence of socioeconomic status, self‐efficacy, and anxiety on mathematics achievement in England, Greece, Hong Kong, The Netherlands, Turkey, and the USA. Educational Sciences: Theory and Practice, 15(5), 1391–1401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang, H., &amp; Cogan, L. (2022). The differential role of socioeconomic status in the relationship between curriculum‐based mathematics and mathematics literacy: The link between TIMSS and PISA. International Journal of Science and Mathematics Education, 20, 133–148. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10763‐020‐10133‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitto, K., Hicks, B., &amp; Buckingham Shum, S. (2023). Using causal models to bridge the divide between big data and educational theory. British Journal of Educational Technology, 54(5), 1095–1124. https://doi.org/10.1111/bjet.13321</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhn, M., &amp; Johnson, K. (2013). Data pre‐processing applied predictive modeling. Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni, A., Chong, D., &amp; Batarseh, F. A. (2020). Foundations of data imbalance and solutions for data democracy. In Data democracy (pp. 83–106). Academic Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni, V. Y., &amp; Sinha, P. K. (2013). Random forest classifiers: A survey and future research directions. International Journal of Advanced Computing, 36(1), 1144–1153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lezhnina, O., &amp; Kismihók, G. (2022). Combining statistical and machine learning methods to explore German students' attitudes towards ICT in PISA. International Journal of Research &amp; Method in Education, 45(2), 180–199. https://doi.org/10.1080/1743727X.2021.1963226</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Liu, J., Zhang, D., &amp; Liu, H. (2021). Examining the relationships between cognitive activation, self‐efficacy, socioeconomic status, and achievement in mathematics: A multi‐level analysis. British Journal of Educational Psychology, 91(1), 101–126. https://doi.org/10.1111/bjep.12351</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liaw, A., &amp; Wiener, M. (2002). Classification and regression by random forest. R News, 2(3), 18–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Love, H., May, R. W., Cui, M., &amp; Fincham, F. D. (2020). Helicopter parenting, self‐control, and school burnout among emerging adults. Journal of Child and Family Studies, 29, 327–337. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826‐019‐01560‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundberg, S. M., &amp; Lee, S. I. (2017). A unified approach to interpreting model predictions. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 30, 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mak, S. K., Cheung, K. C., Soh, K. C., Sit, P. S., &amp; Ieong, M. K. (2017). An examination of student‐ and across‐level mechanisms accounting for gender differences in reading performance: A multilevel analysis of reading engagement. Educational Psychology, 37(10), 1206–1221. https://doi.org/10.1080/01443410.2016.1242712</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcílio, W. E., &amp; Eler, D. M. (2020). From explanations to feature selection: Assessing SHAP values as feature selection mechanism. In 2020 33rd SIBGRAPI conference on graphics, patterns and images (SIBGRAPI) (pp. 340–347). IEEE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Margolis, H., &amp; McCabe, P. P. (2006). Improving self‐efficacy and motivation: What to do, what to say. Intervention in School and Clinic, 41(4), 218–227. https://doi.org/10.1177/10534512060410040401</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin, A. J., &amp; Marsh, H. W. (2006). Academic resilience and its psychological and educational correlates: A construct validity approach. Psychology in the Schools, 46(1), 53–83. https://doi.org/10.1002/pits.20149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maxwell, A. E., Sharma, M., &amp; Donaldson, K. A. (2021). Explainable boosting machines for slope failure spatial predictive modeling. Remote Sensing, 13(24), 4991. https://doi.org/10.3390/rs13244991</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merrick, L., &amp; Taly, A. (2020). The explanation game: Explaining machine learning models using shapley values. In Machine learning and knowledge extraction: 4th IFIP TC 5, TC 12, WG 8.4, WG 8.9, WG 12.9 international cross‐domain conference, CD‐MAKE 2020, Dublin, Ireland, August 25–28, 2020, Proceedings 4 (pp. 17–38). Springer International Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>More, A. S., &amp; Rana, D. P. (2017). Review of random forest classification techniques to resolve data imbalance. In 2017 1st international conference on intelligent systems and information management (ICISIM) (pp. 72–78). IEEE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namaziandost, E., Heydarnejad, T., &amp; Azizi, Z. (2023). To be a language learner or not to be? The interplay among academic resilience, critical thinking, academic emotion regulation, academic self‐esteem, and academic demotivation. Current Psychology, 42, 17147–17162. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12144‐023‐04676‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathans, L. L., Oswald, F. L., &amp; Nimon, K. (2012). Interpreting multiple linear regression: A guidebook of variable importance. Practical Assessment, Research &amp; Evaluation, 17(9), 1–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng, C. (2020). Disadvantaged students' motivation, aspiration and subject choice in mathematics: A prospective qualitative investigation. International Journal of Science and Mathematics Education, 18(5), 945–964. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10763‐019‐09981‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). (2009). PISA data analysis manual: SPSS (2nd ed.). OECD Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1787/9789264056275‐en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). (2011). Against the odds: Disadvantaged students who succeed in school. OECD Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). (2012). PISA 2009 technical report. OECD Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). (2023a). PISA 2022 results (volume I): The state of learning and equity in education. OECD Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). (2023b). PISA 2022 assessment and analytical framework. OECD Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). (2023c). PISA 2022 technical report. OECD Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özberk, E. B. Ü., Yılmaz, L., &amp; Özberk, E. H. (2018). Investigation of the variables affecting the math achievement of resilient students at school and student level. Education and Science, 43, 1–19. https://doi.org/10.15390/EB.2018.7153</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parmar, A., Katariya, R., &amp; Patel, V. (2019). A review on random forest: An ensemble classifier. In International conference on intelligent data communication technologies and internet of things (ICICI) 2018 (pp. 758–763). Springer International Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramnarain, U. (2014). Empowering educationally disadvantaged mathematics students through a strategies‐based problem‐solving approach. The Australian Educational Researcher, 41, 43–57. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13384‐013‐0098‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ricketts, S. N., Engelhard, G., Jr., &amp; Chang, M. L. (2017). Development and validation of a scale to measure academic resilience in mathematics. European Journal of Psychological Assessment, 33(2), 79–86. https://doi.org/10.1027/1015‐5759/a000274</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudd, G., Meissel, K., &amp; Meyer, F. (2021). Measuring academic resilience in quantitative research: A systematic review of the literature. Educational Research Review, 34, 100402. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.edurev.2021.100402</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan, R. M., &amp; Deci, E. L. (2000). Intrinsic and extrinsic motivations: Classic definitions and new directions. Contemporary Educational Psychology, 25(1), 54–67. https://doi.org/10.1006/ceps.1999.1020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salvo‐Garrido, S., Miranda Vargas, H., Vivallo Urra, O., Luis Galvez‐Nieto, J., &amp; Miranda‐Zapata, E. (2020). Resilient students in the area of mathematics: Examining protective and risk factors in an emerging country. Revista Iberoamericana de Diagnóstico y Evaluación‐e Avaliação Psicológica, 2(55), 43–57. https://doi.org/10.21865/RIDEP55.2.04</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandoval‐Hernández, A., &amp; Białowolski, P. (2016). Factors and conditions promoting academic resilience: A TIMSS‐based analysis of five Asian education systems. Asia Pacific Education Review, 17(3), 511–520. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12564‐016‐9447‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanguanmak, Y., &amp; Hanskunatai, A. (2016). DBSM: The combination of DBSCAN and SMOTE for imbalanced data classification. In 2016 13th international joint conference on computer science and software engineering (JCSSE) (pp. 1–5). IEEE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, Í., &amp; Centeno, V. G. (2021). Inspirations from abroad: The impact of PISA on countries' choice of reference societies in education. Compare: A Journal of Comparative and International Education, 53, 1–19. https://doi.org/10.1080/03057925.2021.1906206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schiffrin, H. H., Liss, M., Miles‐McLean, H., Geary, K. A., Erchull, M. J., &amp; Tashner, T. (2014). Helping or hovering? The effects of helicopter parenting on college students' well‐being. Journal of Child and Family Studies, 23, 548–557. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826‐013‐9716‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senaviratna, N. A. M. R., &amp; Cooray, T. M. J. A. (2019). Diagnosing multicollinearity of logistic regression model. Asian Journal of Probability and Statistics, 5(2), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215‐0366(19)30434‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sit, P. S., Cheung, K. C., Cheong, W. C., Mak, S. K., Soh, K. C., &amp; Ieong, M. K. (2015). What studying problems are faced by the adolescent grade repeaters in Macao: Uncovering underlying mechanisms based on evidences from the PISA 2012 study. Asia Pacific Education Review, 16(3), 367–377. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12564‐015‐9388‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, C., Fu, Z., &amp; Wang, J. (2019). Social support and academic stress in the development of psychological adjustment in Chinese migrant children: Examination of compensatory model of psychological resilience. Child Indicators Research, 12, 1275–1286. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12187‐018‐9577‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamannaeifar, M., &amp; Shahmirzaei, S. (2019). Prediction of academic resilience based on coping styles and personality traits. Practice in Clinical Psychology, 7(1), 1–10. https://doi.org/10.32598/jpcp.7.1.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, L., Chen, F., &amp; Wei, B. (2024). Examining key capitals contributing to students' science‐related career expectations and their relationship patterns: A machine learning approach. Journal of Research in Science Teaching, 1–36. https://doi.org/10.1002/tea.21939</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teng, Y. (2020). The relationship between school climate and students' mathematics achievement gaps in Shanghai China: Evidence from PISA 2012. Asia Pacific Journal of Education, 40(3), 356–372. https://doi.org/10.1080/02188791.2019.1682516</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tudor, K., Sarkar, M., &amp; Spray, C. M. (2020). Resilience in physical education: A qualitative exploration of protective factors. European Physical Education Review, 26(1), 284–302. https://doi.org/10.1177/1356336X19854477</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ungar, M. (2011). The social ecology of resilience: Addressing contextual and cultural ambiguity of a nascent construct. American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 81(1), 1742–1748. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.childyouth.2011.04.027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ungar, M., &amp; Theron, L. (2020). Resilience and mental health: How multisystemic processes contribute to positive outcomes. The Lancet Psychiatry, 7(5), 441–448. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215‐0366(19)30434‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valadi, S., Gabbard, C., &amp; Hooshyari, F. (2020). Effects of affordances in the home environment on children's personal‐social, problem‐solving, and communication skills. Child: Care, Health and Development, 46(4), 429–435. https://doi.org/10.1111/cch.12756</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vicente, I., Pastor, J. M., &amp; Soler, Á. (2021). Improving educational resilience in the OECD countries: Two convergent paths. Journal of Policy Modeling, 43(6), 1149–1166. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpolmod.2021.09.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, F., King, R. B., Fu, L., Chai, C. S., &amp; Leung, S. O. (2024). Overcoming adversity: Exploring the key predictors of academic resilience in science. International Journal of Science Education, 46(4), 313–337. https://doi.org/10.1080/09500693.2023.2231117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, F., King, R. B., &amp; Leung, S. O. (2022). Beating the odds: Identifying the top predictors of resilience among Hong Kong students. Child Indicators Research, 1–24, 1921–1944. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12187‐022‐09939‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M. C., Haertel, G. D., &amp; Walberg, H. J. (1994). Educational resilience in inner cities. In M. C. Wang &amp; E. W. Gordon (Eds.), Educational resilience in inner‐city America: Challenges and prospects (pp. 45–72). Erlbaum.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitten, K., &amp; Weaver, S. (2010). Adoptive family relationships and healthy adolescent development: A risk and resilience analysis. Adoption Quarterly, 13(3–4), 209–226. https://doi.org/10.1080/10926755.2010.524873</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Windle, G. (2011). What is resilience? A review and concept analysis. Reviews in Clinical Gerontology, 21(2), 152–169. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0959259810000420</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winters, T. (2022). Academic resilience as a concept for creative arts higher education: A thematic review. International Journal of Art &amp; Design Education, 41(3), 464–481. https://doi.org/10.1111/jade.12419</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, M. (2005). The role of plausible values in large‐scale surveys. Studies in Educational Evaluation, 31(2–3), 114–128. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.stueduc.2005.05.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xenofontos, C., &amp; Mouroutsou, S. (2023). Resilience in mathematics education research: A systematic review of empirical studies. Scandinavian Journal of Educational Research, 67(7), 1041–1055. https://doi.org/10.1080/00313831.2022.2115132</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, J., Broadhurst, D., Wilson, M., &amp; Wishart, D. (2013). Translational biomarker discovery in clinical metabolomics: An introductory tutorial. Metabolomics, 9, 280–299. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11306‐012‐0482‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yavuz, H., &amp; Kutlu, Ö. (2016). Investigation of the factors affecting the academic resilience of economically disadvantaged high school students. Egitim ve Bilim‐Education and Science, 41(186), 1–19. https://doi.org/10.15390/EB.2016.5497</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye, W., Strietholt, R., &amp; Blömeke, S. (2021). Academic resilience: Underlying norms and validity of definitions. Educational Assessment, Evaluation and Accountability, 33(1), 169–202. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11092‐020‐09351‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai, X., Yuan, W., Liu, T., &amp; Wang, Q. (2024). Machine learning investigation of optimal psycho‐emotional well‐being factors for students' reading literacy. Education and Information Technologies, 1–29. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10639‐024‐12580‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, J. Q., Cheung, K. C., &amp; Sit, P. S. (2024a). Identifying key features of resilient students in digital reading: Insights from a machine learning approach. Education and Information Technologies, 29, 2277–2301. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10639‐023‐11908‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, J. Q., Cheung, K. C., &amp; Sit, P. S. (2024b). A systematic review of academic resilience in East Asia: Evidence from the large‐scale assessment research. Psychology in the Schools, 61, 1238–1254. https://doi.org/10.1002/pits.23109</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>