<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39308057</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2046-2344</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nursing children and young people</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nurs Child Young People</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development of a structured, digital nutrition awareness tool, the Pedi R-MAPP.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7748/ncyp.2024.e1518</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic led to an unprecedented change in healthcare systems, including the swift roll-out of technology-enabled care services, such as remote consultations. Interventions such as nutrition assessments for children are likely to continue to be conducted remotely as part of an online consultation. This article considers nutrition screening and nutritional assessment in children in acute and primary care settings. The article also provides an overview of the development of the Paediatric Remote Malnutrition Application (Pedi-R-MAPP), designed to assist healthcare professionals to undertake a standardised, nutrition-focused assessment via remote consultation and/or in primary care settings. The aim of the Pedi-R-MAPP is to help identify children with declining nutritional status or new nutritional concerns and to recommend frequency of review based on the outcomes of the assessment.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 RCN Publishing Company Ltd. All rights reserved. Not to be copied, transmitted or recorded in any way, in whole or part, without prior permission of the publishers.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marino</LastName><ForeName>Luise Victoria</ForeName><Initials>LV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South West Yorkshire NHS Partnership Foundation Trust, Wakefield, England and associate professor (Hon) University of Southampton, Southampton, England.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Nurs Child Young People</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101554473</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2046-2336</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">child development</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">child health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">innovation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutrition</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutritional assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutritional status</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">professional</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">professional issues</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">technology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Luise Marino has received honorarium to give educational lectures for Abbott Laboratories, Danone and Nestle, who had no role in role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript; or in the decision to publish the results. Luise Marino also reports the development of Pedi-R-MAPP was supported by an unrestricted grant from Abbott Laboratories, who had no role in role in the design of the study; data collection, analyses, or interpretation of data or writing of the manuscript the idea of which was developed by Weber Shandwick</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39308057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7748/ncyp.2024.e1518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">e1518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>