<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39308881</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2094-9278</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>58</Volume><Issue>15</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Acta medica Philippina</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acta Med Philipp</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Risk Factor Analysis of Death due to COVID-19 with Comorbid Condition in the Community of the Wetland Environment in Banjar District.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>74</StartPage><EndPage>80</EndPage><MedlinePgn>74-80</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.47895/amp.vi0.6409</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The prevalence of confirmed cases of COVID-19 is high and tends to continue to increase in Indonesia. Based on data, the Province of South Kalimantan, Indonesia in early mid-2021 experienced a high spike in cases, resulting in a large number of deaths, especially in Banjar Regency. Active COVID-19 cases in South Kalimantan in July 2021 were recorded at 5,279 (12.41%) out of 42,527 positive cases. Data compiled from the COVID-19 Task Force (Satgas) showed that Banjar Regency was the third highest area of the cumulative number of deaths, with as many as 47 people dying in one day. The results of many research on risk factors for COVID-19 cases vary widely. People with comorbidities are a very vulnerable group.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study aims to identify the relationship between comorbid conditions and death based on data from COVID-19 admission in the Wetland Environment community in Banjar Regency, South Kalimantan, Indonesia in the years 2020-2021.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This is a retrospective analytical observational study which used purposive sampling. The data were collected from the case form report (CFR). The dependent variable in this study was inpatients at Ratu Zaleha Hospital who died and were diagnosed as positive for COVID-19, while the independent variables were age (productive/non-productive), tuberculosis, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, asthma, pneumonia, heart disease, COPD (lung disease), HIV/AIDS, chronic kidney disease (CKD), and stroke (CVA). Data were analyzed by univariate, bivariate, and multivariate analyses with logistic regression method to obtain adjusted OR.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Out of 700 patients with confirmed COVID-19 infection, 273 (39%) had no comorbidity while 427 (61%) had at least one comorbid condition. There were 330 (47.1%) male patients and 370 (52.9%) female patients. There were 565 (80.7%) patients who belong in the productive age and 135 (19.35%) in the non-productive age. Results showed that age (p=0.002), asthma (p=0.026), chronic kidney disease (p=0.000), and heart disease (p=0.002) are significant risk factors of COVID-19 death in Banjar Regency.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Based on our analysis of COVID-19-related deaths in Banjar Regency in Ratu Zaleha Hospital on the year 2020-2021, diabetes, pneumonia, kidney failure, and COPD were associated with increased mortality.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Acta Medica Philippina.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaidah</LastName><ForeName>Siti</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Study Program, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aflanie</LastName><ForeName>Iwan</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Study Program, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahman</LastName><ForeName>Fauzie</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Policy Administration of Public Health Study Program, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Doctoral Program Medical Science Study Program, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yolanda</LastName><ForeName>Zuhrufa Wanna</ForeName><Initials>ZW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Association of Alumni, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Master Public Health Study, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fatimah</LastName><ForeName>Husnul</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Association of Alumni, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Master Public Health Study, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ridwan</LastName><ForeName>Agus Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Master Public Health Study, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Padillah</LastName><ForeName>Rizky</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Undergraduate Public Health Study Program, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Syarif</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Undergraduate Public Health Study Program, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hidayati</LastName><ForeName>Fahrina</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Association of Alumni, Faculty of Medicine, Lambung Mangkurat University, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ratu Zaleha Hospital, Banjar District, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Philippines</Country><MedlineTA>Acta Med Philipp</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0312677</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0001-6071</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">comorbidity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>All authors declared no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39308881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11413458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47895/amp.vi0.6409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">AMP-58-15-6409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ejaz H, Alsrhani A, Zafar A, Javed H, Junaid K, Abdalla AE, et al. . COVID-19 and comorbidities: Deleterious impact on infected patients. J Infect Public Health. 2020. Dec;13(12):1833-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jiph.2020.07.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2020.07.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7402107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32788073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health of the Republic of Indonesia . 13.2 Percent of COVID-19 Patients Who Died Have Disease Hypertension [Internet]. 2020. 
[cited 2022 Mar]. Available from: www.Depkes.Go.Id.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nugroho TE, Mochamat M, Famila F. Use of high-dose heparin in COVID-19 patients with ARDS and hypertension in the Intensive Care Unit (ICU). JAI (Jurnal Anestesiologi Indonesia). 2020; 12(3):1-8. doi:10.14710/jai.v12i3.34246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14710/jai.v12i3.34246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>PERKENI . Official Statements and Recommendations for Handling Diabetes Mellitus in the era of the COVID-19 Pandemic. The Indonesian Society of Endocrinology; 
[Internet]. 2020. 
[cited 2022 Mar]. Available from: https://pbperkeni.or.id/info-perkeni</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndera MLD, Nani S, Agustin R. Comorbid factors against COVID-19 at the Puskesmas. Bioscience Journal. 2020;3(2):1-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan WJ, Liang WH, Zhao Y, Liang HR, Chen ZS, Li YM, et al. . Comorbidity and its impact on 1590 patients with COVID-19 in China: a nationwide analysis. Eur Respir J. 2020. May;55(5): 2000547. doi: 10.1183/13993003.00547-2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/13993003.00547-2020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7098485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karyono DR, Wicaksana AL. Current prevalence, characteristics, and comorbidities of patients with COVID-19 in Indonesia. JCOEMPH. 2020;3(2):77-84. doi:10.22146/jcoemph.57325</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22146/jcoemph.57325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J, Zheng Y, Gou X, Pu K, Chen Z, Guo Q, et al. . Prevalence of comorbidities and its effects in patients infected with SARS-CoV-1: a systematic review and metaanalysis. Int J Infect Dis. 2020. May; 94: 91-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2020.03.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.03.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32173574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DKI Jakarta Health Office . DKI Jakarta COVID-19 Monitoring Data 2020 [Internet]. 2020. 
[cited 2022 Mar]. Available from: https://corona.jakarta.go.id/en/data-pemantauan</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drew C, Adisasmita AC. Symptoms and comorbidities affecting mortality of COVID-19 positive patients in East Jakarta, March-September 2020. Tarumanagara Med J. 2021;3(1):42-51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahayu LAD, Admiyanti JC, Khalda YI, Ahda FR, Agistany NFF, Setiawati S, et al. . Hypertension, diabetes mellitus, and obesity as the main comorbidity factors of mortality in COVID-19 patients: a literature review. JIMKI. 2021;9(1):90-7. doi.org/10.53366/jimki.v9i1.342</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Group Indonesia's COVID-19 Task . Map of the spread of COVID-19 in Indonesia [Internet]. 2020[cited 2022 Mar]. Available from: https://covid19.go.id/peta-sebaran</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ichsan MN, Kusadhiani I, Latuconsina VZ. 2020. Relationships comorbid with duration care patient COVID-19 at Bhayangkara Hospital and RS TK. II Prof. Dr. JA. Latumeten in Ambon City in 2020. Mollucca Medica. 2022;15(1):29-40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanti NPED, Nugraha IMADP, Wisnawa GA, Agustina NPD, Diantari NPA. Public knowledge about COVID-19 and public behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic. Jurnal Keperawatan Jiwa. 2020;8(4):491-504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Putri NA, Putra AE, Mariko R. Relationship between age, gender and symptoms with the -incidence of COVID-19 in West Sumatra. Andalas Medical Magazine. 2021;44(2):104-11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faurin M, Fauzar F, Kurniati R, Kam A, Decroli E. COVID-19 with comorbidity tuberculosis lungs and diabetes mellitus. JIKESI. 2020;1(3):1-12. doi:10.25077/jikesi.v1i3.466</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.25077/jikesi.v1i3.466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Q, Meng M, Kumar R, Wu Y, Huang J, Lian N, et al. . The impact of COPD and smoking history on the severity of COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Med Virol. 2020. Oct;92(10):1915-21. doi: 10.1002/jmv.25889.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.25889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32293753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aslam S, Mehra MR. COVID-19: Yet another corona virus challenge in transplantation. J Heart Lung Transplant. 2020. May;39(5): 408-9. doi: 10.1016/j.healun.2020.03.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.healun.2020.03.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7141445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32253113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson EJ, Walker AJ, Bhaskaran K, Bacon S, Bates C, Morton CE, et al. . Factors associated with COVID-19-related death using OpenSAFELY. Nature. 2020. Aug;584(7821):430–6. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2521-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2521-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7611074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32640463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anastasia T, Diana C, Barry I. Characteristics of acute ischemic stroke patients with COVID-19 entering the Intensive Care Room. E-ClinicC. 2021;9(1):161-6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cibro AAL, Skripsiana NS, Muthmainah N, Heriyani F, Zaitun N. Overview characteristics and disease comorbid on patient confirmation of COVID-19 at Ulin Hospital Banjarmasin 2020. Homeostasis. 2022;5(1):11-18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenham C, Smith J, Morgan R, Gender and COVID-19 Working Group . COVID-19: the gendered impacts of the outbreak. Lancet. 2020. Mar;395(10227):846–8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30526-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30526-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7124625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32151325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oktaviani HP, Yulyani V, Wulandari M, Prasetia T. Toni P. Relationship between diabetes mellitus and hypertension on patient suspect Covid-19 symptoms are mild to moderate at RSD Dr. H. Abdul Moeloek Lampung Province in 2020. Jurnal Formil (Forum Ilmiah) KesMas Respati. 2021;6(2):145-53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Almeida-Pititto B, Dualib PM, Zajdenverg L, Dantas JR, de Souza FD, Rodacki M, et al. . Severity and mortality of COVID-19 in patients with diabetes, hypertension, and cardiovascular disease: a meta-analysis. Diabetol Metab Syndr. 2020. Aug;12:75. doi: 10.1186/s13098-020-00586-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13098-020-00586-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7456786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32874207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parveen R, Sehar N, Bajpai R, Agarwal NB. Association of diabetes and hypertension with disease severity in COVID-19 patients: a systematic literature review and exploratory meta-analysis. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2020. Aug;166:108295. doi: 10.1016/j.diabres.2020.108295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2020.108295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7332452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32623032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambrosioni J, Blanco JL, Reyes-Uruña JM, Davies MA, Sued O, Marcos MA, et al. . Overview of SAR CoV-2 infection in adults living with HIV. Lancet HIV. 2021. May;8(5):e294–e305. doi: 10.1016/S2352-3018(21)00070-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(21)00070-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8075775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33915101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>