<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309291</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2093-7911</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Safety and health at work</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Saf Health Work</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association Between Organizational Downsizing and Depressive Symptoms Among Korean Workers: A Cross-sectional Analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>352</StartPage><EndPage>359</EndPage><MedlinePgn>352-359</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.shaw.2024.06.005</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Organizational downsizing may be significantly linked to depressive symptoms, yet research on this impact in Asian contexts is limited. This study investigates the association between downsizing during the COVID-19 pandemic and depressive symptoms across diverse employment statuses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study used the data from 6th Korean Working Conditions Survey. Depressive symptoms were measured using WHO-5 well-being index with a cut-off of 50. Downsizing was defined as decrease in the number of employees during last three years. Multivariable logistic regression adjusted for socio-demographic and occupational factors was used to estimate the adjusted odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence interval (CI) for depressive symptoms associated with downsizing, including subgroup analyses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Among 26,247 Korean workers (mean age: 43.4, men: 47.5%), the prevalence of depressive symptoms was 29.5% (<i>n</i> = 7,751), and the proportion of downsizing was 15.2% (<i>n</i> = 3,978). The prevalence of depressive symptoms was significantly higher among the downsizing group (36.7%, <i>n</i> = 1,460) than among the no-downsizing group (28.3%, <i>n</i> = 6,291). The result of logistic regression revealed a significant association between downsizing and depressive symptoms (adjusted OR [95% CI]: 1.39 [1.29-1.50]), particularly pronounced among high socioeconomic status workers.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study underscores the significant association between depressive symptoms and organizational downsizing, especially high vulnerability of socioeconomically advantaged and stable workers. These findings highlight the necessity for targeted mental health support and further longitudinal research to clarify the relationship between employment changes and mental health within the Korean workforce.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute. Published by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Institute, Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute, Korea Occupational Safety and Health Agency.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Youngsun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oh</LastName><ForeName>Juyeon</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Graduate School, Yonsei University, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Heejoo</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Graduate School, Yonsei University, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Jian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Graduate School, Yonsei University, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yun</LastName><ForeName>Byungyoon</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoon</LastName><ForeName>Jin-Ha</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute for Occupational Health, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Innovation in Digital Healthcare, Yonsei University Health System, Seoul 03722, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Saf Health Work</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101542940</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2093-7911</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depressive symptoms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Employment status</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Korean workforce</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Organizational downsizing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11410490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.shaw.2024.06.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2093-7911(24)00051-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Pratt L.A. 2014. Depression in the US household population, 2009-2012: US department of health and human services, centers for disease control and ….</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization W.H. World Health Organization; 2017. Depression and other common mental disorders: global health estimates.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim G.Y., Tam W.W., Lu Y., Ho C.S., Zhang M.W., Ho R.C. Prevalence of depression in the community from 30 countries between 1994 and 2014. Scientific Rep. 2018;8(1):2861.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5809481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29434331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santomauro D.F., Herrera A.M.M., Shadid J., Zheng P., Ashbaugh C., Pigott D.M., Abbafati C., Adolph C., Amlag J.O., Aravkin A.Y. Global prevalence and burden of depressive and anxiety disorders in 204 countries and territories in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. The Lancet. 2021;398(10312):1700–1712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34634250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lépine J.-P., Briley M. The increasing burden of depression. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2011;7(Suppl. 1):3–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3131101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21750622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McTernan W.P., Dollard M.F., LaMontagne A.D. Depression in the workplace: an economic cost analysis of depression-related productivity loss attributable to job strain and bullying. Work Stress. 2013;27(4):321–338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badellino H., Gobbo M.E., Torres E., Aschieri M.E., Biotti M., Alvarez V., Gigante C., Cachiarelli M. It’s the economy, stupid’: lessons of a longitudinal study of depression in Argentina. Inter J Soc Psychiatr. 2022;68(2):384–391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33706611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lerner D., Adler D.A., Rogers W.H., Lapitsky L., McLaughlin T., Reed J. Work performance of employees with depression: the impact of work stressors. Am J Health Promot. 2010;24(3):205–213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4174367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20073388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nielsen M.B.D., Bültmann U., Madsen I.E., Martin M., Christensen U., Diderichsen F., Rugulies R. Health, work, and personal-related predictors of time to return to work among employees with mental health problems. Disabil Rehabil. 2012;34(15):1311–1316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22200251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tourigny L., Baba V.V., Wang X. Burnout and depression among nurses in Japan and China: the moderating effects of job satisfaction and absence. Inter J Human Res Manage. 2010;21(15):2741–2761.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rönnblad T., Grönholm E., Jonsson J., Koranyi I., Orellana C., Kreshpaj B., Chen L., Stockfelt L., Bodin T. Precarious employment and mental health. Scandinavian J Work Environment Health. 2019;45(5):429–443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31165899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikeda T., Nakata A., Takahashi M., Hojou M., Haratani T., Nishikido N., Kamibeppu K. Correlates of depressive symptoms among workers in small-and medium-scale manufacturing enterprises in Japan. J Occupat Health. 2009;51(1):26–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19057116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theorell T., Hammarström A., Aronsson G., Träskman Bendz L., Grape T., Hogstedt C., Marteinsdottir I., Skoog I., Hall C. A systematic review including meta-analysis of work environment and depressive symptoms. BMC Public Health. 2015;15(1):1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4522058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26232123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi S.S. 2022. To study the impact of downsizing on survivor's productivity at managerial level with reference to multinational engineering companies in Pune city: Tilak Maharashtra Vidyapeeth.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cascio W.F. Downsizing: what do we know? What have we learned? Acad Manage Perspect. 1993;7(1):95–104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shwedeh F., Aburayya A., Alfaisal R., Adelaja A.A., Ogbolu G., Aldhuhoori A., Salloum S. SMEs’ innovativeness and technology adoption as downsizing strategies during COVID-19: the moderating role of financial sustainability in the tourism industry using structural equation modelling. Sustainability. 2022;14(23)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandolfi F. Why do firms downsize? J Manage Res. 2014;14(1):3–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luthans B.C., Sommer S.M. The impact of downsizing on workplace attitudes: differing reactions of managers and staff in a health care organization. Group Organ Manage. 1999;24(1):46–70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blien U., Dauth W., Roth D.H. Occupational routine intensity and the costs of job loss: evidence from mass layoffs. Labour Econo. 2021;68</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frone M.R., Blais A.-R. Organizational downsizing, work conditions, and employee outcomes: identifying targets for workplace intervention among survivors. Inter J Environ Res Pub Health. 2020;17(3):719.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7037986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31979122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreeva E., Magnusson Hanson L.L., Westerlund H., Theorell T., Brenner M.H. Depressive symptoms as a cause and effect of job loss in men and women: evidence in the context of organisational downsizing from the Swedish Longitudinal Occupational Survey of Health. BMC Pub Health. 2015;15:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4603822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26458894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appelbaum S.H., Delage C., Labib N., Gault G. The survivor syndrome: aftermath of downsizing. Career Develop Inter. 1997;2(6):278–286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brenner M.H., Andreeva E., Theorell T., Goldberg M., Westerlund H., Leineweber C., Hanson L.L.M., Imbernon E., Bonnaud S. Organizational downsizing and depressive symptoms in the European recession: the experience of workers in France, Hungary, Sweden and the United Kingdom. PloS One. 2014;9(5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4026141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24841779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam M.R., Nahar Z., Hossain M.S., Hossain M.J., Shahriar M., Islam S.M.A., Bhuiyan M.A. Prevalence and associated factors for elevated fear and depressive symptoms among the private service holders in Bangladesh during the Covid-19 pandemic: a cross-sectional study. Health Sci Rep. 2022;5(5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9399449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36032517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho Y. Data resource profile: the Korean working conditions survey (KWCS) Ann Occupat Environ Med. 2023;35</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10751213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38148917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ariza-Montes A., Giorgi G., Hernández-Perlines F., Fiz-Perez J. Decent work as a necessary condition for sustainable well-being. A tale of Pi (i) gs and farmers. Sustainability. 2019;11(4):1051.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topp C.W., Østergaard S.D., Søndergaard S., Bech P. The WHO-5 Well-Being Index: a systematic review of the literature. Psychother Psychoso. 2015;84(3):167–176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25831962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seo H.J. Development of a tailored analysis system for Korean working conditions survey. Safe Health Work. 2016;7(3):201–207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5011101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27630788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung J., Ko K., Park J.B., Lee K.-J., Cho Y.H., Jeong I. Association between commuting time and subjective well-being in relation to regional differences in Korea. J Korean Med Sci. 2023;38(15)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10111043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37069812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park J.W., Cho S.S., Lee J., Hwang J., Kim J.I., Kim B.G., Hong Y.S. Association between employment status and sickness presenteeism among Korean employees: a cross-sectional study. Ann Occupat Environ Med. 2020;32</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7332349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32676195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee H.-E., Kim M.-H., Choi M., Kim H.-R., Kawachi I. Variability in daily or weekly working hours and self-reported mental health problems in Korea, Korean working condition survey, 2017. Archi Pub Health. 2021;79:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7912832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33640025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y.-J., Lee J. Association between depressive symptoms and employment type of Korean workers: the Fifth Korean Working Conditions Survey. BMC Pub Health. 2024;24(1):93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10768360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38178074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han E., Kim U.-J., Lee Y., Lee S., Ham S., Lee W., Choi W.-J., Kang S.-K. Association between lone work and self-rated health status: using the 5th Korean Working Conditions Survey. Ann Occupat Environ Med. 2023;35</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10493374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37701491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik M.I., Ahmad A., Hussain S. How downsizing affects the job satisfaction and life satisfaction of layoff survivors. African J Business Manage. 2010;4(16):3564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López Bohle S.A., Chambel M.J., Diaz-Valdes Iriarte A. Job insecurity, procedural justice and downsizing survivor affects. Inter J Human Res Manage. 2021;32(3):596–615.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rugulies R., Bültmann U., Aust B., Burr H. Psychosocial work environment and incidence of severe depressive symptoms: prospective findings from a 5-year follow-up of the Danish work environment cohort study. Am J Epidemiol. 2006;163(10):877–887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16571741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quesnel-Vallée A., DeHaney S., Ciampi A. Temporary work and depressive symptoms: a propensity score analysis. Soc Sci Med. 2010;70(12):1982–1987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3762747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20371142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahn J., Kim N.-S., Lee B.-K., Park J., Kim Y. Non-standard workers have poorer physical and mental health than standard workers. J Occupat Environ Med. 2019;61(10):e413–e421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31348413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vahtera J., Kivimäki M., Pentti J., Linna A., Virtanen M., Virtanen P., Ferrie J.E. Organisational downsizing, sickness absence, and mortality: 10-town prospective cohort study. Bmj. 2004;328(7439):555.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC381046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14980982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robone S., Jones A.M., Rice N. Contractual conditions, working conditions and their impact on health and well-being. Europ J Health Econo. 2011;12:429–444.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20499127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitch T.J., Moran J., Villanueva G., Sagiraju H.K.R., Quadir M.M., Alamgir H. Prevalence and risk factors of depression among garment workers in Bangladesh. Inter J Soc Psychiatr. 2017;63(3):244–254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28466750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian Z., Pines A., Stone B.V., Lipsitz S.R., Moran L.V., Trinh Q.-D. Changes in anxiety and depression in patients with different income levels through the COVID-19 pandemic. J Affect Disorder. 2023;338:17–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10236917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37271292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam M.S., Ferdous M.Z., Potenza M.N. Panic and generalized anxiety during the COVID-19 pandemic among Bangladeshi people: an online pilot survey early in the outbreak. J Affect Disorder. 2020;276:30–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7362838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32697713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niknian M., Linnan L.A., Lasater T.M., Carleton R.A. Use of population-based data to assess risk factor profiles of blue and white collar workers. J Occupat Med. 1991:29–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1995799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellante D., Link A.N. Are public sector workers more risk averse than private sector workers? ILR Review. 1981;34(3):408–412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobfoll S.E. Conservation of resources: a new attempt at conceptualizing stress. Am Psychol. 1989;44(3):513.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2648906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobfoll S.E., Vinokur A.D., Pierce P.F., Lewandowski-Romps L. The combined stress of family life, work, and war in Air Force men and women: a test of conservation of resources theory. Inter J Stress Manage. 2012;19(3):217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grissom N., Bhatnagar S. Habituation to repeated stress: get used to it. Neurobiol Learn Memory. 2009;92(2):215–224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2773683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18667167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith H.J., Pettigrew T.F., Pippin G.M., Bialosiewicz S. Relative deprivation: a theoretical and meta-analytic review. Person Soc Psychol Rev. 2012;16(3):203–232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22194251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra S., Carleton R.N. Subjective relative deprivation is associated with poorer physical and mental health. Soc Sci Med. 2015;147:144–149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26575605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceylan R.F., Ozkan B. The economic effects of epidemics: from SARS and MERS to COVID-19. Res J Adv Human. 2020;1(2):21–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreeva E., Brenner M.H., Theorell T., Goldberg M. Risk of psychological ill health and methods of organisational downsizing: a cross-sectional survey in four European countries. BMC Pub Health. 2017;17:1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5622469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28962605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blomqvist S., Högnäs R.S., Virtanen M., LaMontagne A.D., Hanson L.L.M. Job loss and job instability during the COVID-19 pandemic and the risk of depression and anxiety among Swedish employees. SSM-Popul Health. 2023;22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10158169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37159634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theorell T. Downsizing in Europe: a social perspective. Scandinavian J Pub Health. 2018;46(1):42–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29191083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>