<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310238</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2222-0682</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>World journal of methodology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>World J Methodol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 mutations: An overview.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>89761</StartPage><MedlinePgn>89761</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">89761</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5662/wjm.v14.i3.89761</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) belongs to the genus Beta coronavirus and the family of Coronaviridae. It is a positive-sense, non-segmented single-strand RNA virus. Four common types of human coronaviruses circulate globally, particularly in the fall and winter seasons. They are responsible for 10%-30% of all mild upper respiratory tract infections in adults. These are 229E, NL63 of the Alfacoronaviridae family, OC43, and HKU1 of the Betacoronaviridae family. However, there are three highly pathogenic human coronaviruses: SARS-CoV-2, Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus, and the latest pandemic caused by the SARS-CoV-2 infection. All viruses, including SARS-CoV-2, have the inherent tendency to evolve. SARS-CoV-2 is still evolving in humans. Additionally, due to the development of herd immunity, prior infection, use of medication, vaccination, and antibodies, the viruses are facing immune pressure. During the replication process and due to immune pressure, the virus may undergo mutations. Several SARS-CoV-2 variants, including the variants of concern (VOCs), such as B.1.1.7 (Alpha), B.1.351 (Beta), B.1.617/B.1.617.2 (Delta), P.1 (Gamma), and B.1.1.529 (Omicron) have been reported from various parts of the world. These VOCs contain several important mutations; some of them are on the spike proteins. These mutations may lead to enhanced infectivity, transmissibility, and decreased neutralization efficacy by monoclonal antibodies, convalescent sera, or vaccines. Mutations may also lead to a failure of detection by molecular diagnostic tests, leading to a delayed diagnosis, increased community spread, and delayed treatment. We searched PubMed, EMBASE, Covariant, the Stanford variant Database, and the CINAHL from December 2019 to February 2023 using the following search terms: VOC, SARS-CoV-2, Omicron, mutations in SARS-CoV-2, <i>etc.</i> This review discusses the various mutations and their impact on infectivity, transmissibility, and neutralization efficacy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©The Author(s) 2024. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarkar</LastName><ForeName>Malay</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary Medicine, Indira Gandhi Medical College, Shimla 171001, Himachal Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madabhavi</LastName><ForeName>Irappa</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical and Pediatric Oncology and Hematology, J N Medical College, and KAHER, Belagavi, Karnataka 590010, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical and Pediatric Oncology and Hematology, Kerudi Cancer Hospital, Bagalkot, Karnataka 587103, India. irappamadabhavi@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>World J Methodol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101628739</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2222-0682</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">E484K mutation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">N501Y mutation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Omicron</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Variant of concern</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict-of-interest statement: Authors declare no conflicts of interest while publishing this research work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11230071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5662/wjm.v14.i3.89761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation> Coronavirus Mutations and Variants: What Does It Mean? Available from: https://srhd.org/news/2021/coronavirus-mutations-and-variants-what-does-it-mean .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanjuán R, Domingo-Calap P. Mechanisms of viral mutation. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2016;73:4433–4448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5075021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27392606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callaway E. The coronavirus is mutating - does it matter? Nature. 2020;585:174–177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32901123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashley Hagen, M  S. Is the Science Communications Specialist at the American Society for Microbiology. Available from: https://asm.org/Biographies/Ashley-Hagen .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minskaia E, Hertzig T, Gorbalenya AE, Campanacci V, Cambillau C, Canard B, Ziebuhr J. Discovery of an RNA virus 3'-&gt;5' exoribonuclease that is critically involved in coronavirus RNA synthesis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2006;103:5108–5113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1458802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16549795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denison MR, Graham RL, Donaldson EF, Eckerle LD, Baric RS. Coronaviruses: an RNA proofreading machine regulates replication fidelity and diversity. RNA Biol. 2011;8:270–279.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3127101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21593585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham RL, Baric RS. Recombination, reservoirs, and the modular spike: mechanisms of coronavirus cross-species transmission. J Virol. 2010;84:3134–3146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2838128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19906932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gribble J, Stevens LJ, Agostini ML, Anderson-Daniels J, Chappell JD, Lu X, Pruijssers AJ, Routh AL, Denison MR. The coronavirus proofreading exoribonuclease mediates extensive viral recombination. PLoS Pathog. 2021;17:e1009226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7846108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33465137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson B, Boni MF, Bull MJ, Colleran A, Colquhoun RM, Darby AC, Haldenby S, Hill V, Lucaci A, McCrone JT, Nicholls SM, O'Toole Á, Pacchiarini N, Poplawski R, Scher E, Todd F, Webster HJ, Whitehead M, Wierzbicki C COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium, Loman NJ, Connor TR, Robertson DL, Pybus OG, Rambaut A. Generation and transmission of interlineage recombinants in the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. Cell. 2021;184:5179–5188.e8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8367733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34499854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P. Rampant C→U Hypermutation in the Genomes of SARS-CoV-2 and Other Coronaviruses: Causes and Consequences for Their Short- and Long-Term Evolutionary Trajectories. mSphere. 2020;5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7316492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32581081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Dorp L, Richard D, Tan CCS, Shaw LP, Acman M, Balloux F. No evidence for increased transmissibility from recurrent mutations in SARS-CoV-2. Nat Commun. 2020;11:5986.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7688939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33239633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otto SP, Day T, Arino J, Colijn C, Dushoff J, Li M, Mechai S, Van Domselaar G, Wu J, Earn DJD, Ogden NH. The origins and potential future of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern in the evolving COVID-19 pandemic. Curr Biol. 2021;31:R918–R929.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8220957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34314723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Pipes L, Nielsen R. Synonymous mutations and the molecular evolution of SARS-CoV-2 origins. Virus Evol. 2021;7:veaa098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7798566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33500788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker AS, Vihta KD, Gethings O, Pritchard E, Jones J, House T, Bell I, Bell JI, Newton JN, Farrar J, Diamond I, Studley R, Rourke E, Hay J, Hopkins S, Crook D, Peto T, Matthews PC, Eyre DW, Stoesser N, Pouwels KB Covid-19 Infection Survey Team. Tracking the Emergence of SARS-CoV-2 Alpha Variant in the United Kingdom. N Engl J Med. 2021;385:2582–2585.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8693687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34879193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown KA, Gubbay J, Hopkins J, Patel S, Buchan SA, Daneman N, Goneau LW. S-Gene Target Failure as a Marker of Variant B.1.1.7 Among SARS-CoV-2 Isolates in the Greater Toronto Area, December 2020 to March 2021. JAMA. 2021;325:2115–2116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8033504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33830171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> SARS-CoV-2 Viral Mutations: Impact on COVID-19 Tests. Available from: https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/coronavirus-covid-19-and-medical-devices/sars-cov-2-viral-mutations-impact-covid-19-tests .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chi X, Yan R, Zhang J, Zhang G, Zhang Y, Hao M, Zhang Z, Fan P, Dong Y, Yang Y, Chen Z, Guo Y, Li Y, Song X, Chen Y, Xia L, Fu L, Hou L, Xu J, Yu C, Li J, Zhou Q, Chen W. A neutralizing human antibody binds to the N-terminal domain of the Spike protein of SARS-CoV-2. Science. 2020;369:650–655.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7319273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32571838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walls AC, Park YJ, Tortorici MA, Wall A, McGuire AT, Veesler D. Structure, Function, and Antigenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Glycoprotein. Cell. 2020;181:281–292.e6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32155444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tortorici MA, Veesler D. Structural insights into coronavirus entry. Adv Virus Res. 2019;105:93–116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31522710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ascoli CA. Could mutations of SARS-CoV-2 suppress diagnostic detection? Nat Biotechnol. 2021;39:274–275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33603204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> SARS-CoV-2 variant classifications and definitions. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/variants/variant-classifications.html .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cella E, Benedetti F, Fabris S, Borsetti A, Pezzuto A, Ciotti M, Pascarella S, Ceccarelli G, Zella D, Ciccozzi M, Giovanetti M. SARS-CoV-2 Lineages and Sub-Lineages Circulating Worldwide: A Dynamic Overview. Chemotherapy. 2021;66:3–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8089399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33735881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> Global Consultation on a Decision Framework for Assessing the Impact of SARS-CoV-2 Variants of Concern on Public Health Interventions. Available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/events/detail/2021/03/29/default-calendar/global-consultation-on-a-decision-framework-for-assessing-the-impact-of-sars-cov-2-variants-of-concern-on-public-health-interventions .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel D, Venus B. Portable chest x-rays in the intensive care unit: importance of erect position. Crit Care Med. 1988;16:299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3342638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei Z, Zhang D, Yang RP, Li J, Du WX, Liu YQ, Tan HB, Liu ZX, Liu L. Substitutions and codon usage in SARS-CoV-2 in mammals indicate natural selection and host adaptation. 2021 Preprint.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu Y, Huang Y, Rao J, Zeng F, Yang R, Tan H, Liu Z, Du W, Liu L. Host adaptation of codon usage in SARS-CoV-2 from mammals indicates potential natural selection and viral fitness. Arch Virol. 2022;167:2677–2688.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9514192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36166106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> A Primer on Coronavirus, Variants, Mutation and Evolution. Available from: https://cals.ncsu.edu/applied-ecology/news/a-primer-on-coronavirus-variants-mutation-and-evolution/ </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation> Natural selection vs creation: a literature review on the origin of SARS-CoV-2. Available from: https://www.infezmed.it/media/journal/Vol_28_3_2020_3.pdf .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32920565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio-Casillas A, Redwan EM, Uversky VN. SARS-CoV-2 Intermittent Virulence as a Result of Natural Selection. COVID. 2022;2:1089–1101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib MT, Rahman S, Afrad MH, Howlader AM, Khan MH, Khanam F, Alam AN, Chowdhury EK, Rahman Z, Rahman M, Shirin T, Qadri F. Natural selection shapes the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron in Bangladesh. Front Genet. 2023;14:1220906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10446972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37621704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Z, Barrett J, He X. Immune Imprinting and Implications for COVID-19. Vaccines (Basel) 2023;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10142218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37112787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chemaitelly H, Ayoub HH, Abu-Raddad LJ. COVID-19 Primary Series and Booster Vaccination and Potential for Immune Imprinting. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2023;10 Suppl 2:ofad500.1954.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation> SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern as of 15 March 2024. Available from: https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/covid-19/variants-concern .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zárate S, Taboada B, Muñoz-Medina JE, Iša P, Sanchez-Flores A, Boukadida C, Herrera-Estrella A, Selem Mojica N, Rosales-Rivera M, Gómez-Gil B, Salas-Lais AG, Santacruz-Tinoco CE, Montoya-Fuentes H, Alvarado-Yaah JE, Molina-Salinas GM, Espinoza-Ayala GE, Enciso-Moreno JA, Gutiérrez-Ríos RM, Loza A, Moreno-Contreras J, García-López R, Rivera-Gutierrez X, Comas-García A, Wong-Chew RM, Jiménez-Corona ME, Del Angel RM, Vazquez-Perez JA, Matías-Florentino M, Pérez-García M, Ávila-Ríos S, Castelán-Sánchez HG, Delaye L, Martínez-Castilla LP, Escalera-Zamudio M, López S, Arias CF. The Alpha Variant (B.1.1.7) of SARS-CoV-2 Failed to Become Dominant in Mexico. Microbiol Spectr. 2022;10:e0224021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9045257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35389245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies NG, Jarvis CI CMMID COVID-19 Working Group, Edmunds WJ, Jewell NP, Diaz-Ordaz K, Keogh RH. Increased mortality in community-tested cases of SARS-CoV-2 lineage B.1.1.7. Nature. 2021;593:270–274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9170116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33723411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volz E, Mishra S, Chand M, Barrett JC, Johnson R, Geidelberg L, Hinsley WR, Laydon DJ, Dabrera G, O'Toole Á, Amato R, Ragonnet-Cronin M, Harrison I, Jackson B, Ariani CV, Boyd O, Loman NJ, McCrone JT, Gonçalves S, Jorgensen D, Myers R, Hill V, Jackson DK, Gaythorpe K, Groves N, Sillitoe J, Kwiatkowski DP COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) consortium, Flaxman S, Ratmann O, Bhatt S, Hopkins S, Gandy A, Rambaut A, Ferguson NM. Assessing transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2 lineage B.1.1.7 in England. Nature. 2021;593:266–269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33767447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen X, Tang H, McDanal C, Wagh K, Fischer W, Theiler J, Yoon H, Li D, Haynes BF, Sanders KO, Gnanakaran S, Hengartner N, Pajon R, Smith G, Glenn GM, Korber B, Montefiori DC. SARS-CoV-2 variant B.1.1.7 is susceptible to neutralizing antibodies elicited by ancestral spike vaccines. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29:529–539.e3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7934674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33705729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration.  Fact sheet for health careproviders emergency use authorization (EUA) of bamlanivimaband etesevimab. Available from: https://www.fda.gov/media/145802/download .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration.  Fact sheet for health care providers emergency use authorization (EUA) of REGEN-COV (casirivimab with imdevimab). Available from: https://www.fda.gov/media/145611/download .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration.  Fact sheet for health careproviders emergency use authorization (EUA) of sotrovimab. Available from: https://www.fda.gov/media/149534/download .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jangra S, Ye C, Rathnasinghe R, Stadlbauer D Personalized Virology Initiative study group, Krammer F, Simon V, Martinez-Sobrido L, García-Sastre A, Schotsaert M. SARS-CoV-2 spike E484K mutation reduces antibody neutralisation. Lancet Microbe. 2021;2:e283–e284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8026167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33846703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emary KRW, Golubchik T, Aley PK, Ariani CV, Angus B, Bibi S, Blane B, Bonsall D, Cicconi P, Charlton S, Clutterbuck EA, Collins AM, Cox T, Darton TC, Dold C, Douglas AD, Duncan CJA, Ewer KJ, Flaxman AL, Faust SN, Ferreira DM, Feng S, Finn A, Folegatti PM, Fuskova M, Galiza E, Goodman AL, Green CM, Green CA, Greenland M, Hallis B, Heath PT, Hay J, Hill HC, Jenkin D, Kerridge S, Lazarus R, Libri V, Lillie PJ, Ludden C, Marchevsky NG, Minassian AM, McGregor AC, Mujadidi YF, Phillips DJ, Plested E, Pollock KM, Robinson H, Smith A, Song R, Snape MD, Sutherland RK, Thomson EC, Toshner M, Turner DPJ, Vekemans J, Villafana TL, Williams CJ, Hill AVS, Lambe T, Gilbert SC, Voysey M, Ramasamy MN, Pollard AJ COVID-19 Genomics UK consortium; AMPHEUS Project; Oxford COVID-19 Vaccine Trial Group. Efficacy of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 (AZD1222) vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern 202012/01 (B.1.1.7): an exploratory analysis of a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2021;397:1351–1362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8009612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33798499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez Bernal J, Andrews N, Gower C, Gallagher E, Simmons R, Thelwall S, Stowe J, Tessier E, Groves N, Dabrera G, Myers R, Campbell CNJ, Amirthalingam G, Edmunds M, Zambon M, Brown KE, Hopkins S, Chand M, Ramsay M. Effectiveness of Covid-19 Vaccines against the B.1.617.2 (Delta) Variant. N Engl J Med. 2021;385:585–594.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8314739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34289274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruxvoort KJ, Sy LS, Qian L, Ackerson BK, Luo Y, Lee GS, Tian Y, Florea A, Aragones M, Tubert JE, Takhar HS, Ku JH, Paila YD, Talarico CA, Tseng HF. Effectiveness of mRNA-1273 against delta, mu, and other emerging variants of SARS-CoV-2: test negative case-control study. BMJ. 2021;375:e068848.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8671836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34911691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tegally H, Wilkinson E, Giovanetti M, Iranzadeh A, Fonseca V, Giandhari J, Doolabh D, Pillay S, San EJ, Msomi N, Mlisana K, von Gottberg A, Walaza S, Allam M, Ismail A, Mohale T, Glass AJ, Engelbrecht S, Van Zyl G, Preiser W, Petruccione F, Sigal A, Hardie D, Marais G, Hsiao NY, Korsman S, Davies MA, Tyers L, Mudau I, York D, Maslo C, Goedhals D, Abrahams S, Laguda-Akingba O, Alisoltani-Dehkordi A, Godzik A, Wibmer CK, Sewell BT, Lourenço J, Alcantara LCJ, Kosakovsky Pond SL, Weaver S, Martin D, Lessells RJ, Bhiman JN, Williamson C, de Oliveira T. Detection of a SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern in South Africa. Nature. 2021;592:438–443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33690265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega MA, García-Montero C, Fraile-Martinez O, Colet P, Baizhaxynova A, Mukhtarova K, Alvarez-Mon M, Kanatova K, Asúnsolo A, Sarría-Santamera A. Recapping the Features of SARS-CoV-2 and Its Main Variants: Status and Future Paths. J Pers Med. 2022;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9225183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35743779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> COVID-19: Epidemiology, virology, and prevention. Available from: https://www.uptodate.com/contents/covid-19-epidemiology-virology-and-prevention .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng B, Gao L, Zhou Q, Yu K, Sun F. Effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines against SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Med. 2022;20:200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9126103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35606843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> SARS-CoV-2 Gamma variant. Available from: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SARS-CoV-2_Gamma_variant .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faria NR, Mellan TA, Whittaker C, Claro IM, Candido DDS, Mishra S, Crispim MAE, Sales FCS, Hawryluk I, McCrone JT, Hulswit RJG, Franco LAM, Ramundo MS, de Jesus JG, Andrade PS, Coletti TM, Ferreira GM, Silva CAM, Manuli ER, Pereira RHM, Peixoto PS, Kraemer MUG, Gaburo N Jr, Camilo CDC, Hoeltgebaum H, Souza WM, Rocha EC, de Souza LM, de Pinho MC, Araujo LJT, Malta FSV, de Lima AB, Silva JDP, Zauli DAG, Ferreira ACS, Schnekenberg RP, Laydon DJ, Walker PGT, Schlüter HM, Dos Santos ALP, Vidal MS, Del Caro VS, Filho RMF, Dos Santos HM, Aguiar RS, Proença-Modena JL, Nelson B, Hay JA, Monod M, Miscouridou X, Coupland H, Sonabend R, Vollmer M, Gandy A, Prete CA Jr, Nascimento VH, Suchard MA, Bowden TA, Pond SLK, Wu CH, Ratmann O, Ferguson NM, Dye C, Loman NJ, Lemey P, Rambaut A, Fraiji NA, Carvalho MDPSS, Pybus OG, Flaxman S, Bhatt S, Sabino EC. Genomics and epidemiology of the P.1 SARS-CoV-2 lineage in Manaus, Brazil. Science. 2021;372:815–821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8139423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33853970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> How Dangerous Is the Delta Variant (B.1.617.2)? Available from: https://asm.org/Articles/2021/July/How-Dangerous-is-the-Delta-Variant-B-1-617-2#:~:text=Data%20indicate%20that%20Delta%20is%2040-60%25%20more%20transmissible,airways%20of%20patients%20infected%20with%20the%20Delta%20variant .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li B, Deng A, Li K, Hu Y, Li Z, Shi Y, Xiong Q, Liu Z, Guo Q, Zou L, Zhang H, Zhang M, Ouyang F, Su J, Su W, Xu J, Lin H, Sun J, Peng J, Jiang H, Zhou P, Hu T, Luo M, Zhang Y, Zheng H, Xiao J, Liu T, Tan M, Che R, Zeng H, Zheng Z, Huang Y, Yu J, Yi L, Wu J, Chen J, Zhong H, Deng X, Kang M, Pybus OG, Hall M, Lythgoe KA, Li Y, Yuan J, He J, Lu J. Viral infection and transmission in a large, well-traced outbreak caused by the SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant. Nat Commun. 2022;13:460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8786931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35075154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public Health England.  Investigation of novel SARS-CoV-2 variant: technical briefing. Available from: https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/957504/Variant_of_Concern_VOC_202012_01_Technical_Briefing_5_England.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikh A, McMenamin J, Taylor B, Robertson C Public Health Scotland and the EAVE II Collaborators. SARS-CoV-2 Delta VOC in Scotland: demographics, risk of hospital admission, and vaccine effectiveness. Lancet. 2021;397:2461–2462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8201647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34139198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> Risk assessment for SARS-CoV-2 variant: Delta (VOC-21APR-02, B.1.617.2) Public Health England. Available from: https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/991135/3_June_2021_Risk_assessment_for_SARS-CoV-2_variant_DELTA.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation> Update on omicron-World Health Organization. 2021. Available from: https://www.who.int/news/item/28-11-2021-update-on-omicron .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tegally H, Moir M, Everatt J, Giovanetti M, Scheepers C, Wilkinson E, Subramoney K, Makatini Z, Moyo S, Amoako DG, Baxter C, Althaus CL, Anyaneji UJ, Kekana D, Viana R, Giandhari J, Lessells RJ, Maponga T, Maruapula D, Choga W, Matshaba M, Mbulawa MB, Msomi N NGS-SA consortium, Naidoo Y, Pillay S, Sanko TJ, San JE, Scott L, Singh L, Magini NA, Smith-Lawrence P, Stevens W, Dor G, Tshiabuila D, Wolter N, Preiser W, Treurnicht FK, Venter M, Chiloane G, McIntyre C, O'Toole A, Ruis C, Peacock TP, Roemer C, Kosakovsky Pond SL, Williamson C, Pybus OG, Bhiman JN, Glass A, Martin DP, Jackson B, Rambaut A, Laguda-Akingba O, Gaseitsiwe S, von Gottberg A, de Oliveira T. Emergence of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron lineages BA.4 and BA.5 in South Africa. Nat Med. 2022;28:1785–1790.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9499863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35760080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meo SA, Meo AS, Al-Jassir FF, Klonoff DC. Omicron SARS-CoV-2 new variant: global prevalence and biological and clinical characteristics. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2021;25:8012–8018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34982465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Beltran WF, St Denis KJ, Hoelzemer A, Lam EC, Nitido AD, Sheehan ML, Berrios C, Ofoman O, Chang CC, Hauser BM, Feldman J, Roederer AL, Gregory DJ, Poznansky MC, Schmidt AG, Iafrate AJ, Naranbhai V, Balazs AB. mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccine boosters induce neutralizing immunity against SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant. Cell. 2022;185:457–466.e4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8733787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34995482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grabowski F, Kochańczyk M, Lipniacki T. The Spread of SARS-CoV-2 Variant Omicron with a Doubling Time of 2.0-3.3 Days Can Be Explained by Immune Evasion. Viruses. 2022;14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8875689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35215887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson N, Ghani A, Cori A, Hogan A, Hinsley W, Volz E on behalf of the Imperial College COVID-19 response team.  Imperial College London. Report 49 - Growth, population distribution and immune escape of the Omicron in England. Available from: https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2021-12-16-COVID19-Report-49.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdullah F, Myers J, Basu D, Tintinger G, Ueckermann V, Mathebula M, Ramlall R, Spoor S, de Villiers T, Van der Walt Z, Cloete J, Soma-Pillay P, Rheeder P, Paruk F, Engelbrecht A, Lalloo V, Myburg M, Kistan J, van Hougenhouck-Tulleken W, Boswell MT, Gray G, Welch R, Blumberg L, Jassat W. Decreased severity of disease during the first global omicron variant covid-19 outbreak in a large hospital in tshwane, south africa. Int J Infect Dis. 2022;116:38–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8713416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34971823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue C, Song W, Wang L, Jian F, Chen X, Gao F, Shen Z, Wang Y, Wang X, Cao Y. ACE2 binding and antibody evasion in enhanced transmissibility of XBB.1.5. Lancet Infect Dis. 2023;23:278–280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9897732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36746173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M, Krüger N, Schulz S, Cossmann A, Rocha C, Kempf A, Nehlmeier I, Graichen L, Moldenhauer AS, Winkler MS, Lier M, Dopfer-Jablonka A, Jäck HM, Behrens GMN, Pöhlmann S. The Omicron variant is highly resistant against antibody-mediated neutralization: Implications for control of the COVID-19 pandemic. Cell. 2022;185:447–456.e11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8702401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35026151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumdar S, Sarkar R. Mutational and phylogenetic analyses of the two lineages of the Omicron variant. J Med Virol. 2022;94:1777–1779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9015627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34964502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu N, Joyal-Desmarais K, Ribeiro PAB, Vieira AM, Stojanovic J, Sanuade C, Yip D, Bacon SL. Long-term effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines against infections, hospitalisations, and mortality in adults: findings from a rapid living systematic evidence synthesis and meta-analysis up to December, 2022. Lancet Respir Med. 2023;11:439–452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9917454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36780914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews N, Stowe J, Kirsebom F, Toffa S, Rickeard T, Gallagher E, Gower C, Kall M, Groves N, O'Connell AM, Simons D, Blomquist PB, Zaidi A, Nash S, Iwani Binti Abdul Aziz N, Thelwall S, Dabrera G, Myers R, Amirthalingam G, Gharbia S, Barrett JC, Elson R, Ladhani SN, Ferguson N, Zambon M, Campbell CNJ, Brown K, Hopkins S, Chand M, Ramsay M, Lopez Bernal J. Covid-19 Vaccine Effectiveness against the Omicron (B.1.1.529) Variant. N Engl J Med. 2022;386:1532–1546.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8908811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35249272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collie S, Champion J, Moultrie H, Bekker LG, Gray G. Effectiveness of BNT162b2 Vaccine against Omicron Variant in South Africa. N Engl J Med. 2022;386:494–496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8757569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34965358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu Y, McCauley J. GISAID: Global initiative on sharing all influenza data - from vision to reality. Euro Surveill. 2017;22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5388101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28382917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korber B, Fischer WM, Gnanakaran S, Yoon H, Theiler J, Abfalterer W, Hengartner N, Giorgi EE, Bhattacharya T, Foley B, Hastie KM, Parker MD, Partridge DG, Evans CM, Freeman TM, de Silva TI Sheffield COVID-19 Genomics Group, McDanal C, Perez LG, Tang H, Moon-Walker A, Whelan SP, LaBranche CC, Saphire EO, Montefiori DC. Tracking Changes in SARS-CoV-2 Spike: Evidence that D614G Increases Infectivity of the COVID-19 Virus. Cell. 2020;182:812–827.e19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7332439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32697968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plante JA, Liu Y, Liu J, Xia H, Johnson BA, Lokugamage KG, Zhang X, Muruato AE, Zou J, Fontes-Garfias CR, Mirchandani D, Scharton D, Bilello JP, Ku Z, An Z, Kalveram B, Freiberg AN, Menachery VD, Xie X, Plante KS, Weaver SC, Shi PY. Spike mutation D614G alters SARS-CoV-2 fitness. Nature. 2021;592:116–121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8158177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33106671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou YJ, Chiba S, Halfmann P, Ehre C, Kuroda M, Dinnon KH 3rd, Leist SR, Schäfer A, Nakajima N, Takahashi K, Lee RE, Mascenik TM, Graham R, Edwards CE, Tse LV, Okuda K, Markmann AJ, Bartelt L, de Silva A, Margolis DM, Boucher RC, Randell SH, Suzuki T, Gralinski LE, Kawaoka Y, Baric RS. SARS-CoV-2 D614G variant exhibits efficient replication ex vivo and transmission in vivo. Science. 2020;370:1464–1468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7775736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33184236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M, Kleine-Weber H, Schroeder S, Krüger N, Herrler T, Erichsen S, Schiergens TS, Herrler G, Wu NH, Nitsche A, Müller MA, Drosten C, Pöhlmann S. SARS-CoV-2 Cell Entry Depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and Is Blocked by a Clinically Proven Protease Inhibitor. Cell. 2020;181:271–280.e8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M, Kleine-Weber H, Pöhlmann S. A Multibasic Cleavage Site in the Spike Protein of SARS-CoV-2 Is Essential for Infection of Human Lung Cells. Mol Cell. 2020;78:779–784.e5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32362314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yurkovetskiy L, Wang X, Pascal KE, Tomkins-Tinch C, Nyalile TP, Wang Y, Baum A, Diehl WE, Dauphin A, Carbone C, Veinotte K, Egri SB, Schaffner SF, Lemieux JE, Munro JB, Rafique A, Barve A, Sabeti PC, Kyratsous CA, Dudkina NV, Shen K, Luban J. Structural and Functional Analysis of the D614G SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein Variant. Cell. 2020;183:739–751.e8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7492024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32991842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kannan SR, Spratt AN, Quinn TP, Heng X, Lorson CL, Sönnerborg A, Byrareddy SN, Singh K. Infectivity of SARS-CoV-2: there Is Something More than D614G? J Neuroimmune Pharmacol. 2020;15:574–577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7490321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32930936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Jackson CB, Mou H, Ojha A, Peng H, Quinlan BD, Rangarajan ES, Pan A, Vanderheiden A, Suthar MS, Li W, Izard T, Rader C, Farzan M, Choe H. SARS-CoV-2 spike-protein D614G mutation increases virion spike density and infectivity. Nat Commun. 2020;11:6013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7693302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33243994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson CB, Zhang L, Farzan M, Choe H. Functional importance of the D614G mutation in the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2021;538:108–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7664360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33220921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Cai Y, Xiao T, Lu J, Peng H, Sterling SM, Walsh RM Jr, Rits-Volloch S, Zhu H, Woosley AN, Yang W, Sliz P, Chen B. Structural impact on SARS-CoV-2 spike protein by D614G substitution. Science. 2021;372:525–530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8139424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33727252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Beltran WF, Lam EC, Astudillo MG, Yang D, Miller TE, Feldman J, Hauser BM, Caradonna TM, Clayton KL, Nitido AD, Murali MR, Alter G, Charles RC, Dighe A, Branda JA, Lennerz JK, Lingwood D, Schmidt AG, Iafrate AJ, Balazs AB. COVID-19-neutralizing antibodies predict disease severity and survival. Cell. 2021;184:476–488.e11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7837114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33412089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauring AS, Hodcroft EB. Genetic Variants of SARS-CoV-2-What Do They Mean? JAMA. 2021;325:529–531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33404586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luan B, Wang H, Huynh T. Enhanced binding of the N501Y-mutated SARS-CoV-2 spike protein to the human ACE2 receptor: insights from molecular dynamics simulations. FEBS Lett. 2021;595:1454–1461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33728680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H, Zhang Q, Wei P, Chen Z, Aviszus K, Yang J, Downing W, Jiang C, Liang B, Reynoso L, Downey GP, Frankel SK, Kappler J, Marrack P, Zhang G. The basis of a more contagious 501Y.V1 variant of SARS-CoV-2. Cell Res. 2021;31:720–722.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8063779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33893398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Starr TN, Greaney AJ, Stewart CM, Walls AC, Hannon WW, Veesler D, Bloom JD. Deep mutational scans for ACE2 binding, RBD expression, and antibody escape in the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA.1 and BA.2 receptor-binding domains. PLoS Pathog. 2022;18:e1010951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9674177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36399443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laffeber C, de Koning K, Kanaar R, Lebbink JHG. Experimental Evidence for Enhanced Receptor Binding by Rapidly Spreading SARS-CoV-2 Variants. J Mol Biol. 2021;433:167058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8139174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34023401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu X, Mannar D, Srivastava SS, Berezuk AM, Demers JP, Saville JW, Leopold K, Li W, Dimitrov DS, Tuttle KS, Zhou S, Chittori S, Subramaniam S. Cryo-electron microscopy structures of the N501Y SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in complex with ACE2 and 2 potent neutralizing antibodies. PLoS Biol. 2021;19:e3001237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8112707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33914735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teruel N, Mailhot O, Najmanovich RJ. Modelling conformational state dynamics and its role on infection for SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein variants. PLoS Comput Biol. 2021;17:e1009286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8384204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34351895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai Y, Zhang J, Xiao T, Lavine CL, Rawson S, Peng H, Zhu H, Anand K, Tong P, Gautam A, Lu S, Sterling SM, Walsh RM Jr, Rits-Volloch S, Lu J, Wesemann DR, Yang W, Seaman MS, Chen B. Structural basis for enhanced infectivity and immune evasion of SARS-CoV-2 variants. Science. 2021;373:642–648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9245151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34168070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung K, Shum MH, Leung GM, Lam TT, Wu JT. Early transmissibility assessment of the N501Y mutant strains of SARS-CoV-2 in the United Kingdom, October to November 2020. Euro Surveill. 2021;26</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7791602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33413740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisblum Y, Schmidt F, Zhang F, DaSilva J, Poston D, Lorenzi JC, Muecksch F, Rutkowska M, Hoffmann HH, Michailidis E, Gaebler C, Agudelo M, Cho A, Wang Z, Gazumyan A, Cipolla M, Luchsinger L, Hillyer CD, Caskey M, Robbiani DF, Rice CM, Nussenzweig MC, Hatziioannou T, Bieniasz PD. Escape from neutralizing antibodies by SARS-CoV-2 spike protein variants. Elife. 2020;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7723407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33112236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Copin R, Baum A, Wloga E, Pascal KE, Giordano S, Fulton BO, Zhou A, Negron N, Lanza K, Chan N, Coppola A, Chiu J, Ni M, Wei Y, Atwal GS, Hernandez AR, Saotome K, Zhou Y, Franklin MC, Hooper AT, McCarthy S, Hamon S, Hamilton JD, Staples HM, Alfson K, Carrion R Jr, Ali S, Norton T, Somersan-Karakaya S, Sivapalasingam S, Herman GA, Weinreich DM, Lipsich L, Stahl N, Murphy AJ, Yancopoulos GD, Kyratsous CA. The monoclonal antibody combination REGEN-COV protects against SARS-CoV-2 mutational escape in preclinical and human studies. Cell. 2021;184:3949–3961.e11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8179113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34161776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang P, Nair MS, Liu L, Iketani S, Luo Y, Guo Y, Wang M, Yu J, Zhang B, Kwong PD, Graham BS, Mascola JR, Chang JY, Yin MT, Sobieszczyk M, Kyratsous CA, Shapiro L, Sheng Z, Huang Y, Ho DD. Antibody resistance of SARS-CoV-2 variants B.1.351 and B.1.1.7. Nature. 2021;593:130–135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33684923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rees-Spear C, Muir L, Griffith SA, Heaney J, Aldon Y, Snitselaar JL, Thomas P, Graham C, Seow J, Lee N, Rosa A, Roustan C, Houlihan CF, Sanders RW, Gupta RK, Cherepanov P, Stauss HJ, Nastouli E SAFER Investigators, Doores KJ, van Gils MJ, McCoy LE. The effect of spike mutations on SARS-CoV-2 neutralization. Cell Rep. 2021;34:108890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7936541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33713594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edara VV, Hudson WH, Xie X, Ahmed R, Suthar MS. Neutralizing Antibodies Against SARS-CoV-2 Variants After Infection and Vaccination. JAMA. 2021;325:1896–1898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7980146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33739374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wise J. Covid-19: The E484K mutation and the risks it poses. BMJ. 2021;372:n359.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33547053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collier DA, De Marco A, Ferreira IATM, Meng B, Datir RP, Walls AC, Kemp SA, Bassi J, Pinto D, Silacci-Fregni C, Bianchi S, Tortorici MA, Bowen J, Culap K, Jaconi S, Cameroni E, Snell G, Pizzuto MS, Pellanda AF, Garzoni C, Riva A CITIID-NIHR BioResource COVID-19 Collaboration, Elmer A, Kingston N, Graves B, McCoy LE, Smith KGC, Bradley JR, Temperton N, Ceron-Gutierrez L, Barcenas-Morales G; COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium, Harvey W, Virgin HW, Lanzavecchia A, Piccoli L, Doffinger R, Wills M, Veesler D, Corti D, Gupta RK. Sensitivity of SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.7 to mRNA vaccine-elicited antibodies. Nature. 2021;593:136–141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33706364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greaney AJ, Loes AN, Crawford KHD, Starr TN, Malone KD, Chu HY, Bloom JD. Comprehensive mapping of mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 receptor-binding domain that affect recognition by polyclonal human plasma antibodies. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29:463–476.e6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7869748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33592168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, VanBlargan LA, Bloyet LM, Rothlauf PW, Chen RE, Stumpf S, Zhao H, Errico JM, Theel ES, Liebeskind MJ, Alford B, Buchser WJ, Ellebedy AH, Fremont DH, Diamond MS, Whelan SPJ. Identification of SARS-CoV-2 spike mutations that attenuate monoclonal and serum antibody neutralization. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29:477–488.e4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7839837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33535027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson G, BuzkoO, SpilmanP, Niazi K, Rabizadeh S, Soon-Shiong P. Molecular dynamic simulation reveals E484K mutation enhances spike RBD-ACE2 affinity and the combination of E484K, K417N and N501Y mutations (501Y.V2 variant) induces conformational change greater than N501Y mutant alone, potentially resulting in an escape mutant. 2021 Preprint.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahradník J, Marciano S, Shemesh M, Zoler E, Harari D, Chiaravalli J, Meyer B, Rudich Y, Li C, Marton I, Dym O, Elad N, Lewis MG, Andersen H, Gagne M, Seder RA, Douek DC, Schreiber G. SARS-CoV-2 variant prediction and antiviral drug design are enabled by RBD in vitro evolution. Nat Microbiol. 2021;6:1188–1198.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34400835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Schmidt F, Weisblum Y, Muecksch F, Barnes CO, Finkin S, Schaefer-Babajew D, Cipolla M, Gaebler C, Lieberman JA, Oliveira TY, Yang Z, Abernathy ME, Huey-Tubman KE, Hurley A, Turroja M, West KA, Gordon K, Millard KG, Ramos V, Da Silva J, Xu J, Colbert RA, Patel R, Dizon J, Unson-O'Brien C, Shimeliovich I, Gazumyan A, Caskey M, Bjorkman PJ, Casellas R, Hatziioannou T, Bieniasz PD, Nussenzweig MC. mRNA vaccine-elicited antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 and circulating variants. Nature. 2021;592:616–622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8503938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33567448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> Genome Sequencing by INSACOG shows variants of concern and a Novel variant in India. Available from: https://pib.gov.in/PressReleaseIframePage.aspx?PRID=1707177 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherian S, Potdar V, Jadhav S, Yadav P, Gupta N, Das M, Rakshit P, Singh S, Abraham P, Panda S, Team N. SARS-CoV-2 Spike Mutations, L452R, T478K, E484Q and P681R, in the Second Wave of COVID-19 in Maharashtra, India. Microorganisms. 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8307577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34361977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng X, Garcia-Knight MA, Khalid MM, Servellita V, Wang C, Morris MK, Sotomayor-González A, Glasner DR, Reyes KR, Gliwa AS, Reddy NP, Sanchez San Martin C, Federman S, Cheng J, Balcerek J, Taylor J, Streithorst JA, Miller S, Sreekumar B, Chen PY, Schulze-Gahmen U, Taha TY, Hayashi JM, Simoneau CR, Kumar GR, McMahon S, Lidsky PV, Xiao Y, Hemarajata P, Green NM, Espinosa A, Kath C, Haw M, Bell J, Hacker JK, Hanson C, Wadford DA, Anaya C, Ferguson D, Frankino PA, Shivram H, Lareau LF, Wyman SK, Ott M, Andino R, Chiu CY. Transmission, infectivity, and neutralization of a spike L452R SARS-CoV-2 variant. Cell. 2021;184:3426–3437.e8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8057738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33991487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motozono C, Toyoda M, Zahradnik J, Saito A, Nasser H, Tan TS, Ngare I, Kimura I, Uriu K, Kosugi Y, Yue Y, Shimizu R, Ito J, Torii S, Yonekawa A, Shimono N, Nagasaki Y, Minami R, Toya T, Sekiya N, Fukuhara T, Matsuura Y, Schreiber G Genotype to Phenotype Japan (G2P-Japan) Consortium, Ikeda T, Nakagawa S, Ueno T, Sato K. SARS-CoV-2 spike L452R variant evades cellular immunity and increases infectivity. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29:1124–1136.e11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8205251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34171266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian D, Sun Y, Zhou J, Ye Q. The Global Epidemic of the SARS-CoV-2 Delta Variant, Key Spike Mutations and Immune Escape. Front Immunol. 2021;12:751778.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8669155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34917076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> How the coronavirus infects cells — and why Delta is so dangerous. Scientists are unpicking the life cycle of SARS-CoV-2 and how the virus uses tricks to evade detection. By Megan Scudellari. Available from: https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02039-y .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34321669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saito A, Irie T, Suzuki R, Maemura T, Nasser H, Uriu K, Kosugi Y, Shirakawa K, Sadamasu K, Kimura I, Ito J, Wu J, Iwatsuki-Horimoto K, Ito M, Yamayoshi S, Loeber S, Tsuda M, Wang L, Ozono S, Butlertanaka EP, Tanaka YL, Shimizu R, Shimizu K, Yoshimatsu K, Kawabata R, Sakaguchi T, Tokunaga K, Yoshida I, Asakura H, Nagashima M, Kazuma Y, Nomura R, Horisawa Y, Yoshimura K, Takaori-Kondo A, Imai M Genotype to Phenotype Japan (G2P-Japan) Consortium, Tanaka S, Nakagawa S, Ikeda T, Fukuhara T, Kawaoka Y, Sato K. Enhanced fusogenicity and pathogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 Delta P681R mutation. Nature. 2022;602:300–306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8828475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34823256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Liu J, Johnson BA, Xia H, Ku Z, Schindewolf C, Widen SG, An Z, Weaver SC, Menachery VD, Xie X, Shi PY. Delta spike P681R mutation enhances SARS-CoV-2 fitness over Alpha variant. bioRxiv. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9050581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35550680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> How the coronavirus infects cells — and why Delta is so dangerous? Available from: https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02039-y .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34321669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haynes WA, Kamath K, Lucas C, Shon J, Iwasaki A. Impact of B.1.1.7 variant mutations on antibody recognition of linear SARSCoV-2 epitopes. 2021 Preprint.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lan J, Ge J, Yu J, Shan S, Zhou H, Fan S, Zhang Q, Shi X, Wang Q, Zhang L, Wang X. Structure of the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain bound to the ACE2 receptor. Nature. 2020;581:215–220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32225176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pascarella S, Ciccozzi M, Zella D, Bianchi M, Benedetti F, Benvenuto D, Broccolo F, Cauda R, Caruso A, Angeletti S, Giovanetti M, Cassone A. SARS-CoV-2 B.1.617 Indian variants: Are electrostatic potential changes responsible for a higher transmission rate? J Med Virol. 2021;93:6551–6556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8426736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34260088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Giacomo S, Mercatelli D, Rakhimov A, Giorgi FM. Preliminary report on severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) Spike mutation T478K. J Med Virol. 2021;93:5638–5643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33951211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomson EC, Rosen LE, Shepherd JG, Spreafico R, da Silva Filipe A, Wojcechowskyj JA, Davis C, Piccoli L, Pascall DJ, Dillen J, Lytras S, Czudnochowski N, Shah R, Meury M, Jesudason N, De Marco A, Li K, Bassi J, O'Toole A, Pinto D, Colquhoun RM, Culap K, Jackson B, Zatta F, Rambaut A, Jaconi S, Sreenu VB, Nix J, Zhang I, Jarrett RF, Glass WG, Beltramello M, Nomikou K, Pizzuto M, Tong L, Cameroni E, Croll TI, Johnson N, Di Iulio J, Wickenhagen A, Ceschi A, Harbison AM, Mair D, Ferrari P, Smollett K, Sallusto F, Carmichael S, Garzoni C, Nichols J, Galli M, Hughes J, Riva A, Ho A, Schiuma M, Semple MG, Openshaw PJM, Fadda E, Baillie JK, Chodera JD ISARIC4C Investigators; COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium, Rihn SJ, Lycett SJ, Virgin HW, Telenti A, Corti D, Robertson DL, Snell G. Circulating SARS-CoV-2 spike N439K variants maintain fitness while evading antibody-mediated immunity. Cell. 2021;184:1171–1187.e20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7843029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33621484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey WT, Carabelli AM, Jackson B, Gupta RK, Thomson EC, Harrison EM, Ludden C, Reeve R, Rambaut A COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium, Peacock SJ, Robertson DL. SARS-CoV-2 variants, spike mutations and immune escape. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2021;19:409–424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8167834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34075212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou W, Xu C, Wang P, Luo M, Xu Z, Cheng R, Jin X, Guo Y, Xue G, Juan L, Anashkina AA, Nie H, Jiang Q. N439K Variant in Spike Protein Alter the Infection Efficiency and Antigenicity of SARS-CoV-2 Based on Molecular Dynamics Simulation. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2021;9:697035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8369991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34414185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oude Munnink BB, Sikkema RS, Nieuwenhuijse DF, Molenaar RJ, Munger E, Molenkamp R, van der Spek A, Tolsma P, Rietveld A, Brouwer M, Bouwmeester-Vincken N, Harders F, Hakze-van der Honing R, Wegdam-Blans MCA, Bouwstra RJ, GeurtsvanKessel C, van der Eijk AA, Velkers FC, Smit LAM, Stegeman A, van der Poel WHM, Koopmans MPG. Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 on mink farms between humans and mink and back to humans. Science. 2021;371:172–177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7857398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33172935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammer AS, Quaade ML, Rasmussen TB, Fonager J, Rasmussen M, Mundbjerg K, Lohse L, Strandbygaard B, Jørgensen CS, Alfaro-Núñez A, Rosenstierne MW, Boklund A, Halasa T, Fomsgaard A, Belsham GJ, Bøtner A. SARS-CoV-2 Transmission between Mink (Neovison vison) and Humans, Denmark. Emerg Infect Dis. 2021;27:547–551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7853580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33207152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fonager J.  Working paper on SARS-CoV-2 spike mutations arising in Danish mink, their spread to humans and neutralization data. Available from: https://files.ssi.dk/Mink-cluster-5-short-report_AFO2 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren W, Lan J, Ju X, Gong M, Long Q, Zhu Z, Yu Y, Wu J, Zhong J, Zhang R, Fan S, Zhong G, Huang A, Wang X, Ding Q. Mutation Y453F in the spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 enhances interaction with the mink ACE2 receptor for host adaption. PLoS Pathog. 2021;17:e1010053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8601601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34748603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baum A, Fulton BO, Wloga E, Copin R, Pascal KE, Russo V, Giordano S, Lanza K, Negron N, Ni M, Wei Y, Atwal GS, Murphy AJ, Stahl N, Yancopoulos GD, Kyratsous CA. Antibody cocktail to SARS-CoV-2 spike protein prevents rapid mutational escape seen with individual antibodies. Science. 2020;369:1014–1018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7299283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32540904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R, Zhang Q, Ge J, Ren W, Zhang R, Lan J, Ju B, Su B, Yu F, Chen P, Liao H, Feng Y, Li X, Shi X, Zhang Z, Zhang F, Ding Q, Zhang T, Wang X, Zhang L. Analysis of SARS-CoV-2 variant mutations reveals neutralization escape mechanisms and the ability to use ACE2 receptors from additional species. Immunity. 2021;54:1611–1621.e5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8185182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34166623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandel D, Gupta D, Sah V, Harshan KH. N440K variant of SARS-CoV-2 has higher infectious ftness. 2021 Preprint.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta V, Bhoyar RC, Jain A, Srivastava S, Upadhayay R, Imran M, Jolly B, Divakar MK, Sharma D, Sehgal P, Ranjan G, Gupta R, Scaria V, Sivasubbu S. Asymptomatic Reinfection in 2 Healthcare Workers From India With Genetically Distinct Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;73:e2823–e2825.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7543380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32964927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jolly B, Rophina M, Shamnath A, Imran M, Bhoyar RC, Divakar MK, Roja Rani P, Ranjan G, Sehgal P, Chandrasekhar P, Afsar S, Vijaya Lakshmi J, Surekha A, Sivasubbu S, Scaria V. Genetic epidemiology of variants associated with immune escape from global SARS-CoV-2 genomes. 2020 Preprint.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnes CO, Jette CA, Abernathy ME, Dam KA, Esswein SR, Gristick HB, Malyutin AG, Sharaf NG, Huey-Tubman KE, Lee YE, Robbiani DF, Nussenzweig MC, West AP Jr, Bjorkman PJ. SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody structures inform therapeutic strategies. Nature. 2020;588:682–687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8092461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33045718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta RK. Will SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern affect the promise of vaccines? Nat Rev Immunol. 2021;21:340–341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8082481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33927376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng B, Kemp SA, Papa G, Datir R, Ferreira IATM, Marelli S, Harvey WT, Lytras S, Mohamed A, Gallo G, Thakur N, Collier DA, Mlcochova P COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium, Duncan LM, Carabelli AM, Kenyon JC, Lever AM, De Marco A, Saliba C, Culap K, Cameroni E, Matheson NJ, Piccoli L, Corti D, James LC, Robertson DL, Bailey D, Gupta RK. Recurrent emergence of SARS-CoV-2 spike deletion H69/V70 and its role in the Alpha variant B.1.1.7. Cell Rep. 2021;35:109292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8185188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34166617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Starr TN, Greaney AJ, Addetia A, Hannon WW, Choudhary MC, Dingens AS, Li JZ, Bloom JD. Prospective mapping of viral mutations that escape antibodies used to treat COVID-19. Science. 2021;371:850–854.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7963219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33495308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Nie J, Wu J, Zhang L, Ding R, Wang H, Zhang Y, Li T, Liu S, Zhang M, Zhao C, Liu H, Nie L, Qin H, Wang M, Lu Q, Li X, Liu J, Liang H, Shi Y, Shen Y, Xie L, Qu X, Xu W, Huang W, Wang Y. SARS-CoV-2 501Y.V2 variants lack higher infectivity but do have immune escape. Cell. 2021;184:2362–2371.e9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7901273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33735608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>