<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39313862</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2198-3844</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced science (Weinheim, Baden-Wurttemberg, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Sci (Weinh)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Novel Self-Amplifying mRNA with Decreased Cytotoxicity and Enhanced Protein Expression by Macrodomain Mutations.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2402936</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2402936</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/advs.202402936</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The efficacy and safety of self-amplifying mRNA (saRNA) have been demonstrated in COVID-19 vaccine applications. Unlike conventional non-replicating mRNA (nrmRNA), saRNA offers a key advantage: its self-replication mechanism fosters efficient expression of the encoded protein, leading to substantial dose savings during administration. Consequently, there is a growing interest in further optimizing the expression efficiency of saRNA. In this study, in vitro adaptive passaging of saRNA is conducted under exogenous interferon pressure, which revealed several mutations in the nonstructural protein (NSP). Notably, two stable mutations, Q48P and I113F, situated in the NSP3 macrodomain (MD), attenuated its mono adenosine diphosphate ribose (MAR) hydrolysis activity and exhibited decreased replication but increased payload expression compared to wild-type saRNA (wt saRNA). Transcriptome sequencing analysis unveils diminished activation of the double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) sensor and, consequently, a significantly reduced innate immune response compared to wt saRNA. Furthermore, the mutant saRNA demonstrated less translation inhibition and cell apoptosis than wt saRNA, culminating in higher protein expression both in vitro and in vivo. These findings underscore the potential of reducing saRNA replication-dependent dsRNA-induced innate immune responses through genetic modification as a valuable strategy for optimizing saRNA, enhancing payload translation efficiency, and mitigating saRNA cytotoxicity.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Virogin Biotech Ltd. Advanced Science published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gong</LastName><ForeName>Yue</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-1596-9682</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Virogin Biotech Co. Ltd, Jiading District, Shanghai, 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yong</LastName><ForeName>Danni</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Virogin Biotech Co. Ltd, Jiading District, Shanghai, 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Gensheng</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Virogin Biotech Co. Ltd, Jiading District, Shanghai, 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jiang</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Virogin Biotech Co. Ltd, Jiading District, Shanghai, 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ding</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Virogin Biotech Co. Ltd, Jiading District, Shanghai, 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Virogin Biotech Canada Ltd, Vancouver, BC, V6V 3A4, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jia</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2755-6821</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Virogin Biotech Co. Ltd, Jiading District, Shanghai, 200000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Virogin Biotech Canada Ltd, Vancouver, BC, V6V 3A4, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Sci (Weinh)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101664569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2198-3844</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">innate immune response</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">protein expression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">self‐amplifying RNA</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39313862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.202402936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>J. R. da Silva, K. B. Rodrigues, G. F. Pelegrin, N. S. Sales, H. Muramatsu, M. d. O. Silva, B. F. M. M. Porchia, A. C. R. Moreno, L. R. M. M. Aps, A. A. Venceslau‐Carvalho, I. Tombácz, W. L. Fotoran, K. Karikó, P. J. C. Lin, Y. K. Tam, M. d. O. Diniz, N. Pardi, L. C. d. S. Ferreira, Sci. Transl. Med. 2023, 15, eabn3464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Palladino, C. Chang, C. Lee, N. Music, I. D. Souza, J. Nolasco, S. Amoah, P. Suphaphiphat, G. R. Otten, E. C. Settembre, Y. Wen, Mol. Ther. Methods Clin. Dev. 2022, 25, 225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. McCafferty, A. A. Haque, A. Vandierendonck, B. Weidensee, M. Plovyt, M. Stuchlíková, N. François, S. Valembois, L. Heyndrickx, J. Michiels, K. K. Ariën, L. Vandekerckhove, R. Abdelnabi, C. S. Foo, J. Neyts, I. Sahu, N. N. Sanders, Mol. Ther. 2022, 30, 2968.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Silva‐Pilipich, A. Lasarte‐Cía, T. Lozano, C. Martín‐Otal, J. J. Lasarte, C. Smerdou, Mol. Ther.–Nucleic Acids 2022, 29, 387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Luisi, K. M. Morabito, K. E. Burgomaster, M. Sharma, W.‐P. Kong, B. M. Foreman, S. Patel, B. Fisher, M. A. Aleshnick, J. Laliberte, M. Wallace, T. J. Ruckwardt, D. N. Gordon, C. Linton, N. Ruggiero, J. L. Cohen, R. Johnson, K. Aggarwal, S.‐Y. Ko, E. S. Yang, R. S. Pelc, K. A. Dowd, D. O'Hagan, J. Ulmer, S. Mossman, A. Sambor, E. Lepine, J. R. Mascola, T. C. Pierson, B. S. Graham, et al., Sci. Adv. 2020, 6, eaba5068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Li, Z. Su, W. Zhao, X. Zhang, N. Momin, C. Zhang, K. D. Wittrup, Y. Dong, D. J. Irvine, R. Weiss, Nat. Cancer 2020, 1, 882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Lundstrom, Int. Rev. Cell Mol. Biol. 2022, 372, 97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. C. Rupp, K. J. Sokoloski, N. N. Gebhart, R. W. Hardy, J. Gen. Virol. 2015, 96, 2483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Du, W. Li, Y. Zhang, Y. Xue, X. Hou, J. Yan, J. Cheng, B. Deng, D. W. McComb, J. Lin, H. Zeng, X. Cheng, D. J. Irvine, R. Weiss, Y. Dong, Adv. Sci. 2023, 10, 2300188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Xue, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhong, S. Du, X. Hou, W. Li, H. Li, S. Wang, C. Wang, J. Yan, D. D. Kang, B. Deng, D. W. McComb, D. J. Irvine, R. Weiss, Y. Dong, Nat. Commun. 2024, 15, 739.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Dolgin, Nature 2023, 624, 236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y.‐H. Chang, M.‐W. Lin, M.‐C. Chien, G.‐M. Ke, I.‐E. Wu, R.‐L. Lin, C.‐Y. Lin, Y.‐C. Hu, J. Control. Release 2021, 338, 694.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. D. G. Comes, G. P. Pijlman, T. A. H. Hick, Trends Biotechnol. 2023, 41, 1417.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Warren, P. D. Manos, T. Ahfeldt, Y.‐H. Loh, H. Li, F. Lau, W. Ebina, P. K. Mandal, Z. D. Smith, A. Meissner, G. Q. Daley, A. S. Brack, J. J. Collins, C. Cowan, T. M. Schlaeger, D. J. Rossi, Cell Stem Cell 2010, 7, 618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Karikó, M. Buckstein, H. Ni, D. Weissman, Immunity 2005, 23, 165.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Komori, A. L. Morey, A. A. Quiñones‐Molina, J. Fofana, L. Romero, E. Peters, K. Matsuda, S. Gummuluru, J. F. Smith, W. Akahata, H. Akiyama, bioRxiv 2023, https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.11.01.565056.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. E. McGee, J. R. Kirsch, D. Kenney, E. Chavez, T.‐Y. Shih, F. Douam, W. W. Wong, M. W. Grinstaff, bioRxiv 2023, https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.15.557994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Pepini, A.‐M. Pulichino, T. Carsillo, A. L. Carlson, F. Sari‐Sarraf, K. Ramsauer, J. C. Debasitis, G. Maruggi, G. R. Otten, A. J. Geall, D. Yu, J. B. Ulmer, C. Iavarone, J. Immunol. 2017, 198, 4012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Zhong, S. McCafferty, L. Opsomer, H. Wang, H. Huysmans, J. D. Temmerman, S. Lienenklaus, J. P. P. Catani, F. Combes, N. N. Sanders, Mol. Ther. 2021, 29, 1370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Blakney, P. F. McKay, C. R. Bouton, K. Hu, K. Samnuan, R. J. Shattock, Mol. Ther. 2021, 29, 1174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Beissert, L. Koste, M. Perkovic, K. C. Walzer, S. Erbar, A. Selmi, M. Diken, S. Kreiter, Ö. Türeci, U. Sahin, Hum. Gene Ther. 2017, 28, 1138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Dominguez, O. Palchevska, E. I. Frolova, I. Frolov, J. Virol. 2023, 97, e01225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Y. Kim, S. Atasheva, A. J. McAuley, J. A. Plante, E. I. Frolova, D. W. C. Beasley, I. Frolov, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2014, 111, 10708.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhong, P. Gastaminza, G. Cheng, S. Kapadia, T. Kato, D. R. Burton, S. F. Wieland, S. L. Uprichard, T. Wakita, F. V. Chisari, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2005, 102, 9294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Frolov, T. A. Hoffman, B. M. Prágai, S. A. Dryga, H. V. Huang, S. Schlesinger, C. M. Rice, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 1996, 93, 11371.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Kawamoto, T. Yamaji, K. Saito, Y. Shirasago, K. Satomura, T. Endo, M. Fukasawa, K. Hanada, N. Osada, Front. Genet. 2020, 11, 546106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Abdullah, N. Ahemad, K. Aliazis, J. E. Khairat, T. C. Lee, S. A. A. Ahmad, N. A. A. Adnan, N. O. Macha, S. S. Hassan, Viruses 2021, 13, 1021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. L. McPherson, R. Abraham, E. Sreekumar, S.‐E. Ong, S.‐J. Cheng, V. K. Baxter, H. A. V. Kistemaker, D. V. Filippov, D. E. Griffin, A. K. L. Leung, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2017, 114, 1666.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. S. Voth, J. J. O'Connor, C. M. Kerr, E. Doerger, N. Schwarting, P. Sperstad, D. K. Johnson, A. R. Fehr, J. Virol. 2021, 95, e00766.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. M. O. Alhammad, M. M. Kashipathy, A. Roy, J.‐P. Gagné, P. McDonald, P. Gao, L. Nonfoux, K. P. Battaile, D. K. Johnson, E. D. Holmstrom, G. G. Poirier, S. Lovell, A. R. Fehr, J. Virol. 2021, 95, e01969.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Park, D. E. Griffin, Virology 2009, 388, 305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Petrakova, E. Volkova, R. Gorchakov, S. Paessler, R. M. Kinney, I. Frolov, J. Virol. 2005, 79, 7597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Li, B. Teague, Y. Zhang, Z. Su, E. Porter, B. Dobosh, T. Wagner, D. J. Irvine, R. Weiss, Sci. Rep. 2019, 9, 6932.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. G. English, R. H. J. Olsen, K. Lansu, M. Patel, K. White, A. S. Cockrell, D. Singh, R. T. Strachan, D. Wacker, B. L. Roth, Cell 2019, 178, 1030.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Abraham, D. Hauer, R. L. McPherson, A. Utt, I. T. Kirby, M. S. Cohen, A. Merits, A. K. L. Leung, D. E. Griffin, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2018, 115, E10457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Akhrymuk, I. Frolov, E. I. Frolova, Virology 2016, 487, 230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Luan, L. Wang, G. Song, W. Zhou, Front. Immunol. 2024, 15, 1287940.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Li, S. Banerjee, Y. Wang, S. A. Goldstein, B. Dong, C. Gaughan, R. H. Silverman, S. R. Weiss, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2016, 113, 2241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Cappuccio, C. Maisse, Cells 2020, 9, 2612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Baer, L. Lundberg, D. Swales, N. Waybright, C. Pinkham, J. D. Dinman, J. L. Jacobs, K. Kehn‐Hall, J. Virol. 2016, 90, 3558.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Zuo, M. Wakimoto, N. Kozaiwa, Y. Shirasaka, S.‐W. Oh, S. Fujiwara, H. Miyachi, A. Kogure, H. Kato, T. Fujita, Cell Death Dis. 2022, 13, 707.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Salaun, I. Coste, M.‐C. Rissoan, S. J. Lebecque, T. Renno, J. Immunol. 2006, 176, 4894.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. A. B. Rex, T. S. K. Prasad, R. K. Kandasamy, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2022, 23, 7023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. F. R. Boehmer, S. Formisano, C. C. d. O. Mann, S. A. Mueller, M. Kluge, P. Metzger, M. Rohlfs, C. Hörth, L. Kocheise, S. F. Lichtenthaler, K.‐P. Hopfner, S. Endres, S. Rothenfusser, C. C. Friedel, P. Duewell, M. Schnurr, L. M. Koenig, Sci. Immunol. 2021, 6, eabe2550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Li, S. Banerjee, S. A. Goldstein, B. Dong, C. Gaughan, S. Rath, J. Donovan, A. Korennykh, R. H. Silverman, S. R. Weiss, eLife 2017, 6, e25687.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Bauernfried, M. J. Scherr, A. Pichlmair, K. E. Duderstadt, V. Hornung, Science 2021, 371, eabd0811.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Shen, R. Li, R. Negro, J. Cheng, S. M. Vora, T.‐M. Fu, A. Wang, K. He, L. Andreeva, P. Gao, Z. Tian, R. A. Flavell, S. Zhu, H. Wu, Cell 2021, 184, 5759.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Zhang, C. Yin, D. F. Boyd, G. Quarato, J. P. Ingram, M. Shubina, K. B. Ragan, T. Ishizuka, J. C. Crawford, B. Tummers, D. A. Rodriguez, J. Xue, S. Peri, W. J. Kaiser, C. B. López, Y. Xu, J. W. Upton, P. G. Thomas, D. R. Green, S. Balachandran, Cell 2020, 180, 1115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Basavaraju, S. Mishra, R. Jindal, S. Kesavardhana, mBio 2022, 13, e00401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. T. Ho, S. G. Hughes, V. T. Ta, L. T. Phan, Q. Đo, T. V. Nguyen, A. T. V. Pham, M. T. N. Đang, L. V. Nguyen, Q. V. Trinh, H. N. Pham, M. V. Chu, T. T. Nguyen, Q. C. Lưong, V. T. T. Lê, T. V. Nguyen, L.‐T.‐L. Tran, A. T. V. Luu, A. N. Nguyen, N.‐T.‐H. Nguyen, H.‐S. Vu, J. M. Edelman, S. Parker, B. Sullivan, S. Sullivan, Q. Ruan, B. Clemente, B. Luk, K. Lindert, D. Berdieva, Nat. Commun. 2024, 15, 4081.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Hou, Y. Zhang, X. Liu, Y. M. Murad, J. Xu, Z. Yu, X. Hua, Y. Song, J. Ding, H. Huang, R. Zhao, W. Jia, X. Yang, Nat. Commun. 2023, 14, 5925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Liu, J. Ewald, Z. Pang, E. Legrand, Y. S. Jeon, J. Sangiovanni, O. Hacariz, G. Zhou, J. A. Head, N. Basu, J. Xia, Nat. Commun. 2023, 14, 2995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Ewald, G. Zhou, Y. Lu, J. Xia, Curr. Protoc. 2023, 3, e922.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>