<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314612</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Maternal Health Experiences, Depression, and Anxiety Among Refugees and Displaced Persons in Iraq: A Cross-Sectional Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67645</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67645</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67645</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67645</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Improving maternal health is one of the World Health Organization's (WHO) key priorities, grounded in a human rights approach and linked to efforts on universal health coverage. This study aimed to assess maternal health experiences among refugees and displaced women in Iraq during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A cross-sectional study was done on 1321 women of reproductive age living in four camps supervised by the Barzani Foundation Charity in the Kurdistan Region of Iraq from June to August 2021. Researchers developed a questionnaire, and the data was collected by four staff members working in the camps through direct interviews with women. The World Health Organization Brief (WHOQOL-BREF), generalized anxiety disorder seven-item (GAD-7), and Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) scales were used to measure quality of life (QoL), anxiety, and depression. The frequency, percentage, percentile, and the Chi-square test were used for data analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS"> The women's mean age (SD) was 31.9 (±7.7) years. Around two-thirds of women attended the camp's healthcare facilities, and 16.4% attended the private facilities. Women mentioned the following as barriers to seeking health services: COVID-19 (387/29.3%), transportation (351/26.6%), lack of someone watching children (300/22.7%), and language (242/18.3%). The rate of high-level QoL among currently pregnant women (8/8.7%) was significantly (p = 0.002) less than the rate among nonpregnant women (297/24.2%). More than half (734/55.6%) of the women had mild depression, 247/18.7% had major depression, and 50/3.8% had severe major depression. Regarding anxiety, 580/43.9% had minimal anxiety, 467/35.4% had mild anxiety, 173/13.1% had moderate anxiety, and only 101/7.6% had severe anxiety.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Refugees and internal displaced women in Iraq have barriers to seeking maternal healthcare. They suffer from low QoL, depression, and anxiety. Factors affecting the quality and accessibility of maternal healthcare in the camps should be studied. Health policymakers have to consider its improvement.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Mirkhan Ahmed et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mirkhan Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Hamdia</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physiotherapy Department, College of Health Sciences, Hawler Medical University, Erbil, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, University of Kitab, Perde, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed Abdulla</LastName><ForeName>Salih</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, College of Nursing, Hawler Medical University, Erbil, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Tawil</LastName><ForeName>Namir</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Community Medicine Department, Hawler Medical University, Erbil, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mishkin</LastName><ForeName>Kathryn</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research, Private Practice, Rockville, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">idp</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">iraq</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">maternal care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">quality of life</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">refugee</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">syria</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ethics Committee of College of Health Sciences, Hawler Medical University issued approval Sc.E.C.4. The Scientific and Ethics Committee of the College of Health Sciences, Hawler Medical University approved the study proposal. Informed verbal consent was obtained from the study sample, and participants were free to withdraw from the study during data collection. . Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Donnelly ER, Muthiah V. Brussels: European Research Council; 2019. Protecting women and girls in refugee camps: states' obligations under international law.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maternal health.  [
Jul;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.who.int/health-topics/maternal-health https://www.who.int/health-topics/maternal-health</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maternal, newborn, child and adolescent health.  [
Jul;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.emro.who.int/iraq/priority-areas/maternal-newborn-child-and-adolescent-health.html https://www.emro.who.int/iraq/priority-areas/maternal-newborn-child-and-adolescent-health.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurdistan Region. Kurdistan region: a beacon of hope for displaced persons and refugees.  [
Jul;
2024 
]. 2024. https://gov.krd/dmi-en/activities/news-and-press-releases/2024/march/kurdistan-region-a-beacon-of-hope-for-displaced-persons-and-refugees/ https://gov.krd/dmi-en/activities/news-and-press-releases/2024/march/kurdistan-region-a-beacon-of-hope-for-displaced-persons-and-refugees/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syrian crisis Iraq impact assessment: IOM.  [
Jul;
2024 
]. 2013. https://www.iom.int/news/syrian-crisis-iraq-impact-assessment-iom https://www.iom.int/news/syrian-crisis-iraq-impact-assessment-iom</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maternal and child health of internally displaced persons in Ukraine: a qualitative study. Nidzvetska S, Rodriguez-Llanes JM, Aujoulat I, Gil Cuesta J, Tappis H, van Loenhout JA, Guha-Sapir D. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2017;14:54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5295305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28075363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evaluations of reproductive health programs in humanitarian settings: a systematic review. Casey SE. Confl Health. 2015;9:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4328944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25685183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of living arrangements (in-camp versus out-of-camp) on the quality of life. Case study of Syrian refugees in Jordan. Obi CT. https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Chinedu-Obi/publication/349589462_The_Impact_of_Living_Arrangements_In-Camp_versus_Out-of-Camp_on_the_Quality_of_Life_Case_Study_of_Syrian_Refugees_in_Jordan/links/603764c14585158939ca6a81/The-Impact-of-Living-Arrangements-In-Camp-versus-Out-of-Camp-on-the-Quality-of-Life-Case-Study-of-Syrian-Refugees-in-Jordan.pdf?origin=journalDetail&amp;_tp=eyJwYWdlIjoiam91cm5hbERldGFpbCJ9 World Bank Working Paper . 2021;9533</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The reliability and validity of the Arabic World Health Organization quality of life-BREF instrument among family caregivers of relatives with psychiatric illnesses in Jordan. Dalky HF, Meininger JC, Al-Ali NM. J Nurs Res. 2017;25:224–230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28481818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adaptation, validity, and reliability of the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) in the Kurdistan Region of Iraq. Policastro F, Rossi A, Sulaiman HM, Taib NI. Healthcare (Basel) 2023;11:598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9957208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36833131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Utilization of antenatal care services in Syrian refugee camps in Erbil, Iraq. Fareed SM, Ismail KH. Zanco J Med Sci. 2019;23:250–256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assessment of knowledge and practices of internally displaced pregnant women attending to antenatal clinic center at Arbat camp in Sulaimani, Kurdistan Region of Iraq. Abass LA. KJAR. 2018;3:52–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Refugees and internally displaced populations.  [
Jul;
2024 
]. 2020. https://extranet.who.int/kobe_centre/sites/default/files/WHO%20Guidance_Research%20Methods_Health%20EDRM_2021_Chapter-5.3.pdf https://extranet.who.int/kobe_centre/sites/default/files/WHO%20Guidance_Research%20Methods_Health%20EDRM_2021_Chapter-5.3.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health and well-being of refugees, asylum seekers, undocumented migrants, and internally displaced persons under COVID-19: a scoping review. El Arab RA, Somerville J, Abuadas FH, Rubinat-Arnaldo E, Sagbakken M. Front Public Health. 2023;11:1145002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10169615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37181725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barriers and facilitators of access to sexual and reproductive health services among migrant, internally displaced, asylum seeking and refugee women: a scoping review. Sawadogo PM, Sia D, Onadja Y, et al. PLoS One. 2023;18:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10501608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37708137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Experiences from the field: a qualitative study exploring barriers to maternal and child health service utilization in IDP settings Somalia. Mohamed AA, Bocher T, Magan MA, et al.  https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.2147/IJWH.S330069 International Journal of Women's Health. 2021:1147–1160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8630365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34858064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Experiences from the field: a qualitative study exploring barriers to maternal and child health service utilization in IDP settings Somalia. Mohamed AA, Bocher T, Magan MA, Omar A, Mutai O, Mohamoud SA, Omer M. https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.2147/IJWH.S330069. Int J Womens Health. 2021;13:1147–1160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8630365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34858064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 on women who are refugees and mothering: a critical ethnographic study. Hirani SA, Wagner J. https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/23333936221121335 Glob Qual Nurs Res. 2022;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9465568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36105717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The health-related quality of life of Syrian refugee women in their reproductive age. Nabolsi M, Safadi R, Sun C, et al. PeerJ. 2020;8:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7519719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33024636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors influencing quality of life among Syrian refugees pregnant women in Jordan: a cross-sectional study. Alnuaimi K, Alshraifeen A, Aljaraedah H. Heliyon. 2022;8:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9526160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36193516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Women's mental health in Iraq post-conflict. Lafta RK, Merza AK. Med Confl Surviv. 2021;37:146–159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34182837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Post-traumatic stress disorder and depression among Syrian refugees residing in the Kurdistan region of Iraq. Mahmood HN, Ibrahim H, Goessmann K, Ismail AA, Neuner F. Confl Health. 2019;13:51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6842196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31728157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assessment of perinatal depression risk among internally displaced Yazidi women in Iraq: a descriptive cross-sectional study. Seidi PA, Abas NQ, Jaff D, et al. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2022;22:359.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9040272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35468737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gender differences in depression levels at refugee camps in Duhok City, Kurdistan Region of Iraq. Abas NQ. JUG. 2018;5:423–433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The association of conflict-related trauma with markers of mental health among Syrian refugee women: the role of social support and post-traumatic growth. Kheirallah KA, Al-Zureikat SH, Al-Mistarehi AH, et al. Int J Womens Health. 2022;14:1251–1266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9462433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36092127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Major depressive disorder prevalence and risk factors among Syrian asylum seekers in Greece. Poole DN, Hedt-Gauthier B, Liao S, Raymond NA, Bärnighausen T. BMC Public Health. 2018;18:908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6056929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30041693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>PTSD, depression, and migration-related experiences among Syrian refugees living in camp vs urban settings. Isik E, Sismanlar SG, Tekeli-Yesil S. Transcult Psychiatry. 2024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38775131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>