<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39313793</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6963</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC health services research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Health Serv Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessing the impact of Delta and Omicron in German intensive care units: a retrospective, nationwide multistate analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1107</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1107</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1107</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12913-024-11493-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The spread of several severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus type 2 (SARS-CoV-2) variants of concern (VOCs) has repeatedly led to increasing numbers of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients in German intensive care units (ICUs), resulting in capacity shortages and even transfers of COVID-19 intensive care patients between federal states in late 2021. In this respect, there is scarce evidence on the impact of predominant VOCs in German ICUs at the population level.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A retrospective cohort study was conducted from July 01, 2021, to May 31, 2022, using daily nationwide inpatient billing data from German hospitals on COVID-19 intensive care patients and SARS-CoV-2 sequence data from Germany. A multivariable Poisson regression analysis was performed to estimate the incidence rate ratios (IRRs) of transfer (to another hospital during inpatient care), discharge (alive) and death of COVID-19 intensive care patients associated with Delta or Omicron, adjusted for age group and sex. In addition, a multistate approach was used for the clinical trajectories of COVID-19 intensive care patients to estimate their competing risk of transfer, discharge or death associated with Delta or Omicron, specifically concerning patient age.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 6046 transfers, 33256 discharges, and 12114 deaths were included. Poisson regression analysis comparing Omicron versus Delta yielded an estimated adjusted IRR of 1.23 (95% CI 1.16-1.30) for transfers, 2.27 (95% CI 2.20-2.34) for discharges and 0.98 (95% CI 0.94-1.02) for deaths. For ICU deaths in particular, the estimated adjusted IRR increased from 0.14 (95% CI 0.08-0.22) for the 0-9 age group to 4.09 (95% CI 3.74-4.47) for those aged 90 and older compared to the reference group of 60-69-year-olds. Multistate analysis revealed that Omicron was associated with a higher estimated risk of discharge for COVID-19 intensive care patients across all ages, while Delta infection was associated with a higher estimated risk of transfer and death.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Retrospective, nationwide comparisons of transfers, discharges and deaths of COVID-19 intensive care patients during Delta- and Omicron-dominated periods in Germany suggested overall less severe clinical trajectories associated with Omicron. Age was confirmed to be an important determinant of fatal clinical outcomes in COVID-19 intensive care patients, necessitating close therapeutic care for elderly people and appropriate public health control measures.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lottes</LastName><ForeName>Matthäus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Robert Koch Institute, Seestraße 10, 13353, Berlin, Germany. lottesm@rki.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grodd</LastName><ForeName>Marlon</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biometry and Statistics, Medical Center-University of Freiburg, Stefan-Meier-Straße 26, 79104, Freiburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grabenhenrich</LastName><ForeName>Linus</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Method Development, Research Infrastructure and Information Technology, Robert Koch Institute, Nordufer 20, 13353, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wolkewitz</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biometry and Statistics, Medical Center-University of Freiburg, Stefan-Meier-Straße 26, 79104, Freiburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Health Serv Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088677</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6963</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Organism" UI="C000711908">SARS-CoV-2 variants</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005858" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Germany</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007362" MajorTopicYN="Y">Intensive Care Units</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000369" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged, 80 and over</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010360" MajorTopicYN="N">Patient Transfer</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Competing risk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intensive care unit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multistate model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Variant of concern</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39313793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11421169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-024-11493-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12913-024-11493-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Fiske A, McLennan S, Buyx A. Ethical insights from the COVID-19 pandemic in Germany: considerations for building resilient healthcare systems in Europe. Lancet Reg Health - Europe. 2021;9:100213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8513413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34661187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Busemeyer MR. The welfare state in really hard times: political trust and satisfaction with the German healthcare system during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Eur Social Policy. 2022;32(4):393–406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9096177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38603158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer V, Papazova I, Thoma A, Kunz M, Falkai P, Schneider-Axmann T, et al. Subjective burden and perspectives of German healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin NeuroSci. 2021;271(2):271–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7437642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32815019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morawa E, Schug C, Geiser F, Beschoner P, Jerg-Bretzke L, Albus C, et al. Psychosocial burden and working conditions during the COVID-19 pandemic in Germany: the VOICE survey among 3678 health care workers in hospitals. J Psychosom Res. 2021;144:110415.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7944879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33743398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC). Data on Hospital and ICU Admission Rates and Current Occupancy for COVID-19. 2023. https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/download-data-hospital-and-icu-admission-rates-and-current-occupancy-covid-19. Accessed 18 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DIVI-Intensivregister. Aktuelle Lage. Bundesland-Berichte. Deutschland insgesamt. 2023. https://www.intensivregister.de/#/aktuelle-lage/bundesland-berichte/bericht/ALL. Accessed 18 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hubner J, Schewe DM, Katalinic A, Frielitz FS. [Legal Issues of Resource Allocation in the COVID-19 pandemic - between Utilitarianism and Life Value Indifference]. Dtsch Med Wochenschr. 2020;145(10):687–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7295273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32236913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marckmann G, Neitzke G, Schildmann J, Michalsen A, Dutzmann J, Hartog C, et al. Decisions on the allocation of intensive care resources in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic: clinical and ethical recommendations of DIVI, DGINA, DGAI, DGIIN, DGNI, DGP, DGP and AEM. Med Klin Intensivmed Notfmed. 2020;115(Suppl 3):115–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7387419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32728768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gräsner J-T, Wnent J, Hannappel Leonie Uhrig A, Brandenburger T, Karagiannidis C. COVID-19-Intensivpatienten: Kriterien für eine Verlegung innerhalb Deutschlands. Deutsches Ärztelatt. 2021;118 (17): A 870–2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert Koch-Institut (RKI). Wochenberichte zu COVID-19. 2023. https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/InfAZ/N/Neuartiges_Coronavirus/Situationsberichte/Wochenbericht/Wochenberichte_Tab.html. Accessed 18 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert Koch-Institut (RKI). SARS-CoV-2 Sequenzdaten aus Deutschland. Zenodo. 2023. 10.5281/zenodo.8144414</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wise J. Covid-19: Delta variant doubles risk of hospital admission compared with alpha variant, study shows. BMJ. 2021;374:n2152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34470744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Twohig KA, Nyberg T, Zaidi A, Thelwall S, Sinnathamby MA, Aliabadi S, et al. Hospital admission and emergency care attendance risk for SARS-CoV-2 delta (B.1.617.2) compared with alpha (B.1.1.7) variants of concern: a cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):35–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8397301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34461056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuppert A, Polotzek K, Schmitt J, Busse R, Karschau J, Karagiannidis C. Different spreading dynamics throughout Germany during the second wave of the COVID-19 pandemic: a time series study based on national surveillance data. Lancet Reg Health Eur. 2021;6:100151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8454815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34557834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karagiannidis C, Windisch W, McAuley DF, Welte T, Busse R. Major differences in ICU admissions during the first and second COVID-19 wave in Germany. Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9(5):e47–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8078895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33684356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viana R, Moyo S, Amoako DG, Tegally H, Scheepers C, Althaus CL, et al. Rapid epidemic expansion of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant in southern Africa. Nature. 2022;603(7902):679–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8942855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35042229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian D, Sun Y, Xu H, Ye Q. The emergence and epidemic characteristics of the highly mutated SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant. J Med Virol. 2022;94(6):2376–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9015498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35118687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sievers C, Zacher B, Ullrich A, Huska M, Fuchs S, Buda S, et al. SARS-CoV-2 omicron variants BA.1 and BA.2 both show similarly reduced disease severity of COVID-19 compared to Delta, Germany, 2021 to 2022. Euro Surveill. 2022;27(22):2200396.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9164675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35656831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyberg T, Ferguson NM, Nash SG, Webster HH, Flaxman S, Andrews N, et al. Comparative analysis of the risks of hospitalisation and death associated with SARS-CoV-2 omicron (B.1.1.529) and delta (B.1.617.2) variants in England: a cohort study. Lancet. 2022;399(10332):1303–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8926413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35305296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hachmann NP, Miller J, Collier AY, Ventura JD, Yu J, Rowe M, et al. Neutralization escape by SARS-CoV-2 Omicron subvariants BA.2.12.1, BA.4, and BA.5. N Engl J Med. 2022;387(1):86–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9258748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35731894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gräsner J-T, Hannappel L, Bathe J, Wnent J, Brandenburger T, Karagiannidis C. COVID-19-Pandemie: Wie Intensivpatienten über das Kleeblattkonzept Verlegt Werden. Deutsches Ärztelatt. 2021;118(50):A2376–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bundesamt für Bevölkerungsschutz und Katastrophenhilfe (BBK). Länderübergreifende Verlegung von Intensivpatienten. 2021. https://www.bbk.bund.de/DE/Infothek/Fokusthemen/Corona-Pandemie/Kleeblattkonzept/Neuigkeiten-Kleeblatt/Archiv/artikel-2021-11-26.html?nn=83560. Accessed 18 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen PK, Keiding N. Multi-state models for event history analysis. Stat Methods Med Res. 2002;11(2):91–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12040698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le-Rademacher JG, Therneau TM, Ou F-S. The utility of Multistate models: a flexible Framework for Time-to-Event Data. Curr Epidemiol Rep. 2022;9(3):183–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9392702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36003089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institut für das Entgeltsystem im Krankenhaus GmbH (InEK). Datenlieferung gem. § 21 Abs. 3b KHEntgG. 2023. https://www.g-drg.de/datenlieferung-gem.-21-khentgg/datenlieferung-gem.-21-abs.-3b-khentgg. Accessed 18 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen PK, Abildstrom SZ, Rosthøj S. Competing risks as a multi-state model. Stat Methods Med Res. 2002;11(2):203–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12040697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Putter H, Fiocco M, Geskus RB. Tutorial in biostatistics: competing risks and multi-state models. Stat Med. 2007;26(11):2389–430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17031868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Cube M, Schumacher M, Wolkewitz M. Basic parametric analysis for a multii-state model in hospital epidemiology. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2017;17(1):111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5520301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28728582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dadras O, SeyedAlinaghi S, Karimi A, Shamsabadi A, Qaderi K, Ramezani M, et al. COVID-19 mortality and its predictors in the elderly: a systematic review. Health Sci Rep. 2022;5(3):e657.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9125886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35620541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero Starke K, Reissig D, Petereit-Haack G, Schmauder S, Nienhaus A, Seidler A. The isolated effect of age on the risk of COVID-19 severe outcomes: a systematic review with meta-analysis. BMJ Glob Health. 2021;6(12):e006434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8678541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34916273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henkens M, Raafs AG, Verdonschot JAJ, Linschoten M, van Smeden M, Wang P, et al. Age is the main determinant of COVID-19 related in-hospital mortality with minimal impact of pre-existing comorbidities, a retrospective cohort study. BMC Geriatr. 2022;22(1):184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8897728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35247983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lederer DJ, Bell SC, Branson RD, Chalmers JD, Marshall R, Maslove DM, et al. Control of confounding and reporting of results in causal inference studies. Guidance for authors from editors of respiratory, sleep, and critical care journals. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2019;16(1):22–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30230362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez M-A, Vuagnat A, Grimaud O, Leray E, Philippe J-M, Lescure F-X, et al. Impact of ICU transfers on the mortality rate of patients with COVID-19: insights from comprehensive national database in France. Ann Intensiv Care. 2021;11(1):151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8546754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34698966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonsignore M, Hohenstein S, Kodde C, Leiner J, Schwegmann K, Bollmann A, et al. The Disease Course of hospitalized COVID-19 patients during the Delta and Omicron periods in consideration of Vaccination Status. Dtsch Arztebl Int. 2022;119(35–36):605–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9749846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36474339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leiner J, Pellissier V, Hohenstein S, Konig S, Schuler E, Moller R, et al. Characteristics and outcomes of COVID-19 patients during B.1.1.529 (Omicron) dominance compared to B.1.617.2 (Delta) in 89 German hospitals. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):802.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9610359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36303111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adjei S, Hong K, Molinari NM, Bull-Otterson L, Ajani UA, Gundlapalli AV, et al. Mortality risk among patients hospitalized primarily for COVID-19 during the omicron and Delta variant pandemic periods - United States, April 2020-June 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71(37):1182–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9484808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36107788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A, Mojoli F, Pellegrinelli L, Ceriotti F, Valzano A, Grasselli G, et al. Impact of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron and Delta variants in patients requiring intensive care unit (ICU) admission for COVID-19, Northern Italy, December 2021 to January 2022. Respiratory Med Res. 2023;83:100990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9984278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36871459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieillard-Baron A, Flicoteaux R, Salmona M, Chariot A, D’Ableiges BDM, Darmon M, Batteux F. Omicron variant in the critical care units of the Paris Metropolitan Area: the reality Research Group. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2022;206(3):349–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9890255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35536284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arabi M, Al-Najjar Y, Mhaimeed N, Salameh MA, Paul P, AlAnni J, et al. Severity of the Omicron SARS-CoV-2 variant compared with the previous lineages: a systematic review. J Cell Mol Med. 2023;27(11):1443–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10243162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37203288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC). Public health control measures for COVID-19. 2023. https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/infectious-disease-topics/z-disease-list/covid-19/facts/public-health-control-measures-covid-19. Accessed 18 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dettori JR, Norvell DC, Chapman JR, Risks. Rates and odds: what’s the difference and why does it Matter? Global Spine J. 2021;11(7):1156–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8351073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34238044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen PK, Geskus RB, de Witte T, Putter H. Competing risks in epidemiology: possibilities and pitfalls. Int J Epidemiol. 2012;41(3):861–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3396320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22253319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>