<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39311044</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1440-1789</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Neuropathology : official journal of the Japanese Society of Neuropathology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Neuropathology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Neurolymphomatosis mimicking a Guillain-Barré syndrome triggered by COVID-19 vaccination.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/neup.13003</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Guillain-Barré syndrome (GBS) is an acute disorder of the peripheral nervous system, causing flaccid paralysis, areflexia, and variable sensory involvement. Proximal as well distal muscles of the limbs can be involved, and in most severe and advanced cases progresses to respiratory failure and death. GBS is considered an autoimmune disease, and at the basis of the attack at the peripheral nervous system different mechanisms have been recognized, in particular viral infections or other immune stimulations. Cranial nerve involvement in patients with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) and primary central nervous system lymphoma are rare conditions that could present with similar clinical features. Here we present a case of a 36-year-old man hospitalized for acute polyradiculoneuritis of the cranial nerves and lumbar roots that arose a 14 days after severe acute respiratory syndrome COVID-19 2 (Sars-CoV-2) vaccination. Most of the main criteria for the diagnosis of GBS were met, including clinical and electrophysiological criteria. Albuminocytologic dissociation and high protein level in cerebrospinal fluid were also found. Therefore, the patient was treated with a cycle of intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) with notable improvement of symptoms and gradual recovery of motility. A five months later, following SARS-CoV-2 infection, the patient presented with worsening of neurological symptoms and was readmitted to the hospital. He underwent instrumental tests again and was treated with repeated cycles of IVIG and then with a cycle of plasmapheresis without any improvement. In the following 10 days he developed very serious conditions; he was transferred to intensive care unit and deceased after 6 days. The cause of the neurological syndrome was determined only after autoptic analysis, which revealed the presence of primary peripheral nervous system (PNS) DLBCL. The reported case highlights that GBS-like presentation always requires a careful differential diagnosis, and physicians should also consider the possibility of an occult cancer.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Neuropathology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Neuropathology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Colombo</LastName><ForeName>Daniele</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathology Unit, National Institute for Infectious Diseases "Lazzaro Spallanzani," IRCCS, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Falasca</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8752-2415</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Electron Microscopy, National Institute for Infectious Diseases "Lazzaro Spallanzani," IRCCS, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monardo</LastName><ForeName>Francesca</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, "San Giovanni Addolorata" Hospital, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>D'Ambrosio</LastName><ForeName>Mario</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology and Critical Care, "San Giovanni Addolorata" Hospital, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Di Napoli</LastName><ForeName>Arianna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Molecular Medicine, Sapienza University, School of Medicine and Psychology, Sant'Andrea Hospital, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salerno</LastName><ForeName>Antonio</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology and Stroke Unit, "San Giovanni Addolorata" Hospital, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Del Nonno</LastName><ForeName>Franca</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathology Unit, National Institute for Infectious Diseases "Lazzaro Spallanzani," IRCCS, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Comanducci</LastName><ForeName>Giovanna</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology and Stroke Unit, "San Giovanni Addolorata" Hospital, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>Neuropathology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9606526</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0919-6544</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diffuse Large B Cell Lymphoma (DLBCL)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Guillain–Barré syndrome (GBS)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">autopsy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cranial nerves</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39311044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/neup.13003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Yuki N, Hartung HP. Guillain‐Barré syndrome. N Engl J Med 2012; 366: 2294–2304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koike H, Fukami Y, Nishi R et al. Ultrastructural mechanisms of macrophage‐induced demyelination in Guillain‐Barré syndrome. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 2020; 91: 650–659.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffin JW, Li CY, Ho TW et al. Guillain‐Barré syndrome in northern China. The spectrum of neuropathological changes in clinically defined cases. Brain 1995; 118: 577–595.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winer JB. Guillain Barré syndrome. Mol Pathol 2001; 54: 381–385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hegen H, Ladstätter F, Bsteh G et al. Cerebrospinal fluid protein in Guillain‐Barré syndrome: Need for age‐dependent interpretation. Eur J Neurol 2021; 28: 965–973.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finsterer J. Triggers of Guillain‐Barré syndrome: Campylobacter jejuni predominates. Int J Mol Sci 2022; 23: 14222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toscano G, Palmerini F, Ravaglia S et al. Guillain‐Barré syndrome associated with SARS‐CoV‐2. N Engl J Med 2020; 382: 2574–2576.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babazadeh A, Mohseni Afshar Z, Javanian M et al. Influenza vaccination and Guillain‐Barré syndrome: Reality or fear. J Transl Int Med 2019; 7: 137–142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toussirot É, Bereau M. Vaccination and induction of autoimmune diseases. Inflamm Allergy Drug Targets 2015; 14: 94–98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al‐Attas AA, Aldayel AY, Al Najjar SA, Alkhonezan SM. Guillain‐Barré syndrome heralding the diagnosis of Hodgkin lymphoma: A case report. Case Rep Neurol 2020; 12: 365–372.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giglio P, Gilbert MR. Neurologic complications of non‐Hodgkin's lymphoma. Curr Hematol Malig Rep 2006; 1: 214–219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Florian IA, Lupan I, Sur L, Samasca G, Timiș TL. To be, or not to be… Guillain‐Barré syndrome. Autoimmun Rev 2021; 20: 102983.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirian A, Nicolle MW, Budhram A. Guillain‐Barré syndrome. CMAJ 2021; 193: E378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dimachkie MM, Barohn RJ. Guillain‐Barré syndrome and variants. Neurol Clin 2013; 31: 491–510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaffry M, Mostafa F, Mandava K et al. No significant increase in Guillain‐Barré syndrome after COVID‐19 vaccination in adults: A vaccine adverse event reporting system study. Vaccine 2022; 40: 5791–5797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury S, Chowdhury S. Association of Guillain‐Barré syndrome following COVID‐19 vaccination. Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol 2023; 37: 1–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao SC, Wang CH, Chang KC, Hung MJ, Chen HY, Liao SC. Guillain‐Barré syndrome associated with COVID‐19 vaccination. Emerg Infect Dis 2021; 27: 3175–3178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levison LS, Thomsen RW, Sindrup SH, Andersen H. Association between incident cancer and Guillain‐Barré syndrome development: A Nationwide case‐control study. Neurology 2022; 98: e1555–e1561.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van BK, Ha CS, Murphy S et al. Risk factors, treatment, and outcome of central nervous system recurrence in adults with intermediate‐grade and immunoblastic lymphoma. Blood 1998; 91: 1178–1184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li GZ, Hu YH, Li DY et al. Vincristine‐induced peripheral neuropathy: A mini‐review. Neurotoxicology 2020; 81: 161–171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hughes RA, Britton T, Richards M. Effects of lymphoma on the peripheral nervous system. J R Soc Med 1994; 87: 526–530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Harris NL et al. WHO Classification of Tumors of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues, 4rd edn, Vol. 2. Lyon: International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montesinos‐Rongen M, Purschke FG, Brunn A et al. Primary central nervous system (CNS) lymphoma B cell receptors recognize CNS proteins. J Immunol 2015; 195: 1312–1319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ducatel P, Michaud M, Viala K et al. Neurolymphomatosis: Involvement of peripheral nervous system revealing hematologic malignancy, a report of nine cases. J Peripher Nerv Syst 2023; 28: 252–261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu W, Li K, Cui T, Yan Y. Detection of anti‐ganglioside antibodies in Guillain‐Barré syndrome. Ann Transl Med 2023; 11: 289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meena AK, Archana AD, Reddy GC, Ramakrishna D, Rao P. Antiganglioside antibodies in sub types of Guillain‐Barre syndrome in an Indian population. J Med Sci 2010; 10: 138–142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noguchi M, Mori K, Yamazaki S, Suda K, Sato N, Oshimi K. Multifocal motor neuropathy caused by a B‐cell lymphoma producing a monoclonal IgM autoantibody against peripheral nerve myelin glycolipids GM1 and GD1b. Br J Haematol 2003; 123: 600–605.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pal I, Ramsey JD. The role of the lymphatic system in vaccine trafficking and immune response. Adv Drug Deliv Rev 2011; 63: 909–922.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekizawa A, Hashimoto K, Kobayashi S et al. Rapid progression of marginal zone B‐cell lymphoma after COVID‐19 vaccination (BNT162b2): A case report. Front Med (Lausanne) 2022; 9: 963393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanna L, Grassi SO, Ruffini L et al. Non‐Hodgkin lymphoma developed shortly after mRNA COVID‐19 vaccination: Report of a case and review of the literature. Medicina 2023; 59: 157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Largeaud L, Ribes A, Dubois‐Galopin F et al. Major rise of a chronic lymphoid leukemia clone during the course of COVID‐19. Int J Lab Hematol 2021; 43: e82–e83.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>