<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310477</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Simulation-Based Enhancement of Patient Safety During Intrahospital Transport of Trauma Patients With COVID-19: A Helipad Scenario.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67484</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67484</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67484</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67484</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Trauma resulting from accidents, violence, or war claims over five million lives annually, with traffic accidents and falls being predominant causes. The COVID-19 pandemic has posed unprecedented challenges in trauma care. Even though the number of injuries decreased during the lockdown period, the transportation of trauma patients became even more challenging due to concerns about infection control and the need for enhanced protective measures. This simulation workshop was conducted in a controlled environment to test and refine protocols for the safe transport of trauma patients with COVID-19. Our goal was to develop comprehensive guidance on the intrahospital transportation of these patients, ensuring the highest level of patient care and safety. We detail a five-step approach from preparation to the pre-landing, initial assessment, patient transfer, and patient handover phases, emphasizing adherence to protocols, equipment readiness, and personal protective equipment (PPE) use. The primary issues we encountered were related to time management, the decision-making process for applying lifesaving procedures in an open environment, and the risk of cross-infection. The workshop underscored the importance of swift and coordinated care, balancing life-saving interventions with efficient transport to a definitive care facility.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Arslan et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arslan</LastName><ForeName>Banu</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Basaksehir Cam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, TUR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sutasir</LastName><ForeName>Mehmet Necmeddin</ForeName><Initials>MN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Basaksehir Cam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, TUR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kapci</LastName><ForeName>Mucahit</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Basaksehir Cam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, TUR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Korkut</LastName><ForeName>Semih</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Basaksehir Cam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, TUR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Altinarik</LastName><ForeName>Selim</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Health Services, Istanbul Provincial Health Directorate, Istanbul, TUR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">helipad</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">patient safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">patient transport</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">simulation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11416032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2014) Injuries and Violence: The Facts 2014.  [
Nov;
2023 
]. 2014. https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/149798 https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/149798</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology of traumatic deaths: comprehensive population-based assessment. Evans JA, van Wessem KJ, McDougall D, Lee KA, Lyons T, Balogh ZJ. World J Surg. 2010;34:158–163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19882185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Changing pattern of trauma during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Abhilash KP, Paul AJ, Das S, Hazra D, Jain S, Dhinakar Arelly SP. Med J Armed Forces India. 2021;77:0–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8313048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34334902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patterns and mechanisms of major trauma injuries during and after the UK Covid-19 Nationwide lockdown: analysis from a UK Major Trauma Centre. Adiamah A, Lewis-Lloyd C, Seehra JK, et al. Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg. 2022;48:2831–2839.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9115743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35583669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The ICON Trauma Study: the impact of the COVID-19 lockdown on major trauma workload in the UK. Adiamah A, Thompson A, Lewis-Lloyd C, et al. Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg. 2021;47:637–645.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7871318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33559697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of trauma center designation on outcomes: is there a difference between Level I and Level II trauma centers? Glance LG, Osler TM, Mukamel DB, Dick AW. J Am Coll Surg. 2012;215:372–378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22632909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Level I versus Level II trauma centers: an outcomes-based assessment. Cudnik MT, Newgard CD, Sayre MR, Steinberg SM. J Trauma. 2009;66:1321–1326.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19430234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effectiveness of prehospital trauma triage systems in selecting severely injured patients: is comparative analysis possible? van Rein EA, van der Sluijs R, Houwert RM, Gunning AC, Lichtveld RA, Leenen LP, van Heijl M. Am J Emerg Med. 2018;36:1060–1069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29395772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incidents relating to the intra-hospital transfer of critically ill patients. An analysis of the reports submitted to the Australian Incident Monitoring Study in Intensive Care. Beckmann U, Gillies DM, Berenholtz SM, Wu AW, Pronovost P. Intensive Care Med. 2004;30:1579–1585.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14991102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Challenges relating to the inter-facility transport of high acuity paediatric cases. Vincent-Lambert C, Wade G. Afr J Emerg Med. 2018;8:29–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6376918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30815340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 may transmit through aerosol. Wang J, Du G. Ir J Med Sci. 2020;189:1143–1144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32212099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Risk factors for COVID-19 infection among healthcare workers. A first report from a living systematic review and meta-analysis. Dzinamarira T, Nkambule SJ, Hlongwa M, et al. Saf Health Work. 2022;13:263–268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9004144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35433073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EMS disease exposure, transmission, and prevention: a review article. Bitely C, Miller B, Glauser J. Curr Emerg Hosp Med Rep. 2019;7:135–140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7100409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32226658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interhospital transport of critically ill patients: experiences and challenges, a qualitative study. Eiding H, Kongsgaard UE, Braarud AC. Scand J Trauma Resusc Emerg Med. 2019;27:27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6399939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30832699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exsanguination in trauma: a review of diagnostics and treatment options. Geeraedts LM Jr, Kaasjager HA, van Vugt AB, Frölke JP. Injury. 2009;40:11–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19135193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fluid resuscitation in tactical combat casualty care: brief history and current status. Butler F. J Trauma. 2011;70:0–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21841558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transfer of the critically ill adult patient. Bourn S, Wijesingha S, Nordmann G. BJA Educ. 2018;18:63–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7807912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33456812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transport of the patient with trauma: a narrative review. Spoelder EJ, Slagt C, Scheffer GJ, van Geffen GJ. Anaesthesia. 2022;77:1281–1287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9826434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36089885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>