<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310244</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2222-0682</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>World journal of methodology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>World J Methodol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Anticoagulant use before COVID-19 diagnosis prevent COVID-19 associated acute venous thromboembolism or not: A systematic review and meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>92983</StartPage><MedlinePgn>92983</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">92983</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5662/wjm.v14.i3.92983</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Coagulopathy and thromboembolic events are associated with poor outcomes in coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients. There is conflicting evidence on the effects of chronic anticoagulation on mortality and severity of COVID-19 disease.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To summarize the body of evidence on the effects of pre-hospital anticoagulation on outcomes in COVID-19 patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A Literature search was performed on LitCovid PubMed, WHO, and Scopus databases from inception (December 2019) till June 2023 for original studies reporting an association between prior use of anticoagulants and patient outcomes in adults with COVID-19. The primary outcome was the risk of thromboembolic events in COVID-19 patients taking anticoagulants. Secondary outcomes included COVID-19 disease severity, in terms of intensive care unit admission or invasive mechanical ventilation/intubation requirement in patients hospitalized with COVID-19 infection, and mortality. The random effects models were used to calculate crude and adjusted odds ratios (aORs) with 95% confidence intervals (95%CIs).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Forty-six observational studies met our inclusion criteria. The unadjusted analysis found no association between prior anticoagulation and thromboembolic event risk [<i>n</i> = 43851, 9 studies, odds ratio (OR)= 0.67 (0.22, 2.07); <i>P</i> = 0.49; <i>I</i> <sup>2</sup> = 95%]. The association between prior anticoagulation and disease severity was non-significant [<i>n</i> = 186782; 22 studies, OR = 1.08 (0.78, 1.49); <i>P</i> = 0.64; <i>I</i> <sup>2</sup> = 89%]. However, pre-hospital anticoagulation significantly increased all-cause mortality risk [<i>n</i> = 207292; 35 studies, OR = 1.72 (1.37, 2.17); <i>P</i> &lt; 0.00001; <i>I</i> <sup>2</sup> = 93%]. Pooling adjusted estimates revealed a statistically non-significant association between pre-hospital anticoagulation and thromboembolic event risk [aOR = 0.87 (0.42, 1.80); <i>P</i> = 0.71], mortality [aOR = 0.94 (0.84, 1.05); <i>P</i> = 0.31], and disease severity [aOR = 0.96 (0.72, 1.26); <i>P</i> = 0.76].</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Prehospital anticoagulation was not significantly associated with reduced risk of thromboembolic events, improved survival, and lower disease severity in COVID-19 patients.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©The Author(s) 2024. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iqbal</LastName><ForeName>Kinza</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow Medical College, Karachi 74200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Banga</LastName><ForeName>Akshat</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Sawai Man Singh Medical College, Jaipur 302004, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arif</LastName><ForeName>Taha Bin</ForeName><Initials>TB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow Medical College, Karachi 74200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rathore</LastName><ForeName>Sawai Singh</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dr. Sampurnanand Medical College, Jodhpur 342003, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhurwal</LastName><ForeName>Abhishek</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Rutgers Robert Wood Johnson School of Medicine, New Brunswick, NJ 08901, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Naqvi</LastName><ForeName>Syeda Kisa Batool</ForeName><Initials>SKB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow Medical College, Karachi 74200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mehdi</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow Medical College, Karachi 74200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Pankaj</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow Medical College, Karachi 74200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salklan</LastName><ForeName>Mitali Madhu</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Pandit Bhagwat Dayal Sharma Post Graduate Institute of Medical Sciences, Rohtak 124001, Haryana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iqbal</LastName><ForeName>Ayman</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow Medical College, Karachi 74200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Jawad</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow Medical College, Karachi 74200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Nikhil</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology and Hypertension, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN 55905, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lal</LastName><ForeName>Amos</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN 55905, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kashyap</LastName><ForeName>Rahul</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Research, Wellspan Health, York, PA 17403, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bansal</LastName><ForeName>Vikas</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology and Hypertension, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN 55905, United States. bansal.vikas@mayo.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Domecq</LastName><ForeName>Juan Pablo</ForeName><Initials>JP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology and Hypertension, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN 55905, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>World J Methodol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101628739</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2222-0682</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chronic anticoagulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mortality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prehospital anticoagulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prior anticoagulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Severity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Thromboembolic events</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict-of-interest statement: Dr. Bansal has nothing to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11230074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5662/wjm.v14.i3.92983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zhu N, Zhang D, Wang W, Li X, Yang B, Song J, Zhao X, Huang B, Shi W, Lu R, Niu P, Zhan F, Ma X, Wang D, Xu W, Wu G, Gao GF, Tan W China Novel Coronavirus Investigating and Research Team. A Novel Coronavirus from Patients with Pneumonia in China, 2019. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:727–733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31978945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Outcomes of Patients With Coronavirus Disease 2019 Receiving Organ Support Therapies: The International Viral Infection and Respiratory Illness Universal Study Registry: Erratum. Crit Care Med. 2021;49:e562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9520995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33555777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menon T, Sharma R, Earthineni G, Iftikhar H, Sondhi M, Shams S, Khurshid Ahmed N, Khan H, Rathore SS, Singh R. Association of Gastrointestinal System With Severity and Mortality of COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Cureus. 2021;13:e13317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7957843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33738161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menon T, Sharma R, Kataria S, Sardar S, Adhikari R, Tousif S, Khan H, Rathore SS, Singh R, Ahmed Z. The Association of Acute Kidney Injury With Disease Severity and Mortality in COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Cureus. 2021;13:e13894.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8045562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33880250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rathore SS, Rojas GA, Sondhi M, Pothuru S, Pydi R, Kancherla N, Singh R, Ahmed NK, Shah J, Tousif S, Baloch UT, Wen Q. Myocarditis associated with Covid-19 disease: A systematic review of published case reports and case series. Int J Clin Pract. 2021;75:e14470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34235815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah K, Bedi S, Onyeaka H, Singh R, Chaudhari G. The Role of Psychological First Aid to Support Public Mental Health in the COVID-19 Pandemic. Cureus. 2020;12:e8821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7384717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32742836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah K, Mann S, Singh R, Bangar R, Kulkarni R. Impact of COVID-19 on the Mental Health of Children and Adolescents. Cureus. 2020;12:e10051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7520396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32999774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheraton M, Deo N, Kashyap R, Surani S. A Review of Neurological Complications of COVID-19. Cureus. 2020;12:e8192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7243063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32455089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Kashyap R, Hutton A, Sharma M, Surani S. A Review of Cardiac Complications in Coronavirus Disease 2019. Cureus. 2020;12:e8034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7282366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32528770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Rathore SS, Khan H, Bhurwal A, Sheraton M, Ghosh P, Anand S, Makadia J, Ayesha F, Mahapure KS, Mehra I, Tekin A, Kashyap R, Bansal V. Mortality and Severity in COVID-19 Patients on ACEIs and ARBs-A Systematic Review, Meta-Analysis, and Meta-Regression Analysis. Front Med (Lausanne) 2021;8:703661.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8784609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35083229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie J, Zu Y, Alkhatib A, Pham TT, Gill F, Jang A, Radosta S, Chaaya G, Myers L, Zifodya JS, Bojanowski CM, Marrouche NF, Mauvais-Jarvis F, Denson JL. Metabolic Syndrome and COVID-19 Mortality Among Adult Black Patients in New Orleans. Diabetes Care. 2020;44:188–193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7783937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32843337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denson JL, Gillet AS, Zu Y, Brown M, Pham T, Yoshida Y, Mauvais-Jarvis F, Douglas IS, Moore M, Tea K, Wetherbie A, Stevens R, Lefante J, Shaffer JG, Armaignac DL, Belden KA, Kaufman M, Heavner SF, Danesh VC, Cheruku SR, St Hill CA, Boman K, Deo N, Bansal V, Kumar VK, Walkey AJ, Kashyap R Society of Critical Care Medicine Discovery Viral Infection and Respiratory Illness Universal Study (VIRUS): COVID-19 Registry Investigator Group. Metabolic Syndrome and Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome in Hospitalized Patients With COVID-19. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:e2140568.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8696573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34935924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bansal V, Mahapure KS, Bhurwal A, Gupta I, Hassanain S, Makadia J, Madas N, Armaly P, Singh R, Mehra I, O'Horo JC, Kashyap R. Mortality Benefit of Remdesivir in COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Front Med (Lausanne) 2020;7:606429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7873594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33585508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bansal V, Mahapure KS, Mehra I, Bhurwal A, Tekin A, Singh R, Gupta I, Rathore SS, Khan H, Deshpande S, Gulati S, Armaly P, Sheraton M, Kashyap R. Mortality Benefit of Convalescent Plasma in COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Front Med (Lausanne) 2021;8:624924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8062901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33898477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Shaik L, Mehra I, Kashyap R, Surani S. Novel and Controversial Therapies in COVID-19. Open Respir Med J. 2020;14:79–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7931150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33717367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bikdeli B, Madhavan MV, Jimenez D, Chuich T, Dreyfus I, Driggin E, Nigoghossian C, Ageno W, Madjid M, Guo Y, Tang LV, Hu Y, Giri J, Cushman M, Quéré I, Dimakakos EP, Gibson CM, Lippi G, Favaloro EJ, Fareed J, Caprini JA, Tafur AJ, Burton JR, Francese DP, Wang EY, Falanga A, McLintock C, Hunt BJ, Spyropoulos AC, Barnes GD, Eikelboom JW, Weinberg I, Schulman S, Carrier M, Piazza G, Beckman JA, Steg PG, Stone GW, Rosenkranz S, Goldhaber SZ, Parikh SA, Monreal M, Krumholz HM, Konstantinides SV, Weitz JI, Lip GYH Global COVID-19 Thrombosis Collaborative Group, Endorsed by the ISTH, NATF, ESVM, and the IUA, Supported by the ESC Working Group on Pulmonary Circulation and Right Ventricular Function. COVID-19 and Thrombotic or Thromboembolic Disease: Implications for Prevention, Antithrombotic Therapy, and Follow-Up: JACC State-of-the-Art Review. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2020;75:2950–2973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32311448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Violi F, Pastori D, Cangemi R, Pignatelli P, Loffredo L. Hypercoagulation and Antithrombotic Treatment in Coronavirus 2019: A New Challenge. Thromb Haemost. 2020;120:949–956.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7295290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32349133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson SP, Darbousset R, Schoenwaelder SM. Thromboinflammation: challenges of therapeutically targeting coagulation and other host defense mechanisms. Blood. 2019;133:906–918.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30642917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paranjpe I, Fuster V, Lala A, Russak AJ, Glicksberg BS, Levin MA, Charney AW, Narula J, Fayad ZA, Bagiella E, Zhao S, Nadkarni GN. Association of Treatment Dose Anticoagulation With In-Hospital Survival Among Hospitalized Patients With COVID-19. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2020;76:122–124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7202841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32387623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, Shamseer L, Tetzlaff JM, Akl EA, Brennan SE, Chou R, Glanville J, Grimshaw JM, Hróbjartsson A, Lalu MM, Li T, Loder EW, Mayo-Wilson E, McDonald S, McGuinness LA, Stewart LA, Thomas J, Tricco AC, Welch VA, Whiting P, Moher D. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;372:n71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhari PB, Banga A. Writing strategies for improving the access of medical literature. World J Exp Med. 2023;13:50–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10308323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37396881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Working Group on the Clinical Characterisation and Management of COVID-19 infection. A minimal common outcome measure set for COVID-19 clinical research. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:e192–e197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32539990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cochrance Training.  Review Manager (RevMan). [cited 24 April 2022]. Available from: https://training.cochrane.org/online-learning/core-software/revman .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brüggemann P, Rajguru K. Comprehensive Meta-Analysis (CMA) 3.0: a software review. J Market Anal. 2022:10: 425–429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins JPT, Thomas J, Chandler J, Cumpston M, Li T, Page MJ, Welch VA. Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions. 2019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10284251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31643080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wells GA, Shea B, O'Connell D, Peterson J, Welch V, Tugwell P.  The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) for assessing the quality of nonrandomised studies in meta-analyses. 2000. [cited 24 April 2022]. Available from: https://cmr.cochrane.org/?CRGReportID=2972 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schünemann HJ, Oxman AD, Brozek J, Glasziou P, Jaeschke R, Vist GE, Williams JW, Kunz R, Craig J, Montori VM, Bossuyt P, Guyatt GH. Grading quality of evidence and strength of recommendations for diagnostic tests and strategies. BMJ. 2008;336:1106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2386626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18483053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ageno W, De Candia E, Iacoviello L, Di Castelnuovo A CORIST investigators. Protective effect of oral anticoagulant drugs in atrial fibrillation patients admitted for COVID-19: Results from the CORIST study. Thromb Res. 2021;203:138–141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8123369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34020162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arachchillage DJ, Rajakaruna I, Odho Z, Crossette-Thambiah C, Nicolson PLR, Roberts LN, Allan C, Lewis S, Riat R, Mounter P, Lynch C, Langridge A, Oakes R, Aung N, Drebes A, Dutt T, Raheja P, Delaney A, Essex S, Lowe G, Sutton D, Lentaigne C, Sayar Z, Kilner M, Everington T, Shapiro S, Alikhan R, Szydlo R, Makris M, Laffan M. Clinical outcomes and the impact of prior oral anticoagulant use in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 admitted to hospitals in the UK - a multicentre observational study. Br J Haematol. 2022;196:79–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34500500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corrochano M, Acosta-Isaac R, Mojal S, Miqueleiz S, Rodriguez D, Quijada-Manuitt MÁ, Fraga E, Castillo-Ocaña M, Amaro-Hosey K, Albiol N, Soria JM, Antonijoan RM, Souto JC. Impact of pre-admission antithrombotic therapy on disease severity and mortality in patients hospitalized for COVID-19. J Thromb Thrombolysis. 2022;53:96–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8210515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34138399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fröhlich GM, Jeschke E, Eichler U, Thiele H, Alhariri L, Reinthaler M, Kastrati A, Leistner DM, Skurk C, Landmesser U, Günster C. Impact of oral anticoagulation on clinical outcomes of COVID-19: a nationwide cohort study of hospitalized patients in Germany. Clin Res Cardiol. 2021;110:1041–1050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7791911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33416918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gülcü O, Aksakal E, Aydemir S, Doğan R, Saraç İ, Aydın SŞ, Öztürk M, Aksu U, Kalkan K, Tanboğa İH. Association between previous anticoagulant use and mortality among hospitalized patients with COVID-19. J Thromb Thrombolysis. 2022;53:88–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8171228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34080103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanif A, Khan S, Mantri N, Hanif S, Saleh M, Alla Y, Chinta S, Shrestha N, Ji W, Attwood K, Adrish M, Jain KR. Thrombotic complications and anticoagulation in COVID-19 pneumonia: a New York City hospital experience. Ann Hematol. 2020;99:2323–2328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7430929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32808105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison RF, Forte K, Buscher MG Jr, Chess A, Patel A, Moylan T, Mize CH, Werdmann M, Ferrigno R. The Association of Preinfection Daily Oral Anticoagulation Use and All-Cause in Hospital Mortality From Novel Coronavirus 2019 at 21 Days: A Retrospective Cohort Study. Crit Care Explor. 2021;3:e0324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7838002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33521644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hozayen SM, Zychowski D, Benson S, Lutsey PL, Haslbauer J, Tzankov A, Kaltenborn Z, Usher M, Shah S, Tignanelli CJ, Demmer RT. Outpatient and inpatient anticoagulation therapy and the risk for hospital admission and death among COVID-19 patients. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;41:101139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8461367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34585129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Xu S, Yu M, Wang K, Tao Y, Zhou Y, Shi J, Zhou M, Wu B, Yang Z, Zhang C, Yue J, Zhang Z, Renz H, Liu X, Xie J, Xie M, Zhao J. Risk factors for severity and mortality in adult COVID-19 inpatients in Wuhan. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2020;146:110–118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7152876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32294485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rieder M, Gauchel N, Kaier K, Jakob C, Borgmann S, Classen AY, Schneider J, Eberwein L, Lablans M, Rüthrich M, Dolff S, Wille K, Haselberger M, Heuzeroth H, Bode C, von Zur Mühlen C, Rieg S, Duerschmied D. Pre-medication with oral anticoagulants is associated with better outcomes in a large multinational COVID-19 cohort with cardiovascular comorbidities. Clin Res Cardiol. 2022;111:322–332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8453472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34546427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera-Caravaca JM, Núñez-Gil IJ, Vivas D, Viana-Llamas MC, Uribarri A, Becerra-Muñoz VM, Trabattoni D, Fernández Rozas I, Feltes G, López-Pais J, El-Battrawy I, Macaya C, Fernandez-Ortiz A, Estrada V, Marín F HOPE COVID-19 Investigators. Clinical profile and prognosis in patients on oral anticoagulation before admission for COVID-19. Eur J Clin Invest. 2021;51:e13436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7645931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33080051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Togano T, Uemura Y, Asai Y, Hayakawa K, Matsunaga N, Terada M, Ohtsu H, Suzuki S, Toyoda A, Hara H, Sato R, Ishikane M, Kinoshita-Iwamoto N, Hangaishi A, Ohmagari N. The influence of pre-admission antiplatelet and anticoagulation therapy on the illness severity in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 in Japan. J Infect Chemother. 2021;27:1498–1503.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8302845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34340930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buenen AG, Sinkeldam M, Maas ML, Verdonschot M, Wever PC. Prior use of anticoagulation is associated with a better survival in COVID-19. J Thromb Thrombolysis. 2021;52:1207–1211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8166893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34061283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chocron R, Galand V, Cellier J, Gendron N, Pommier T, Bory O, Khider L, Trimaille A, Goudot G, Weizman O, Alsac JM, Geneste L, Schmeltz A, Panagides V, Philippe A, Marsou W, Ben Abdallah I, Deney A, El Batti S, Attou S, Juvin P, Delmotte T, Messas E, Pezel T, Planquette B, Duceau B, Gaussem P, Sutter W, Sanchez O, Waldman V, Diehl JL, Mirault T, Bonnet G, Cohen A, Smadja DM Critical COVID‐19 France Investigators. Anticoagulation Before Hospitalization Is a Potential Protective Factor for COVID-19: Insight From a French Multicenter Cohort Study. J Am Heart Assoc. 2021;10:e018624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8174166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33550816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covino M, De Matteis G, Della Polla D, Burzo ML, Pascale MM, Santoro M, De Cristofaro R, Gasbarrini A, De Candia E, Franceschi F. Does chronic oral anticoagulation reduce in-hospital mortality among COVID-19 older patients? Aging Clin Exp Res. 2021;33:2335–2343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8254066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34216379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denas G, Gennaro N, Ferroni E, Fedeli U, Lorenzoni G, Gregori D, Iliceto S, Pengo V. Reduction in all-cause mortality in COVID-19 patients on chronic oral anticoagulation: A population-based propensity score matched study. Int J Cardiol. 2021;329:266–269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33309764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fumagalli S, Trevisan C, Del Signore S, Pelagalli G, Volpato S, Gareri P, Mossello E, Malara A, Monzani F, Coin A, Bellelli G, Zia G, Antonelli Incalzi R GeroCovid Working Group. COVID-19 and Atrial Fibrillation in Older Patients: Does Oral Anticoagulant Therapy Provide a Survival Benefit?-An Insight from the GeroCovid Registry. Thromb Haemost. 2022;122:105–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33962480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho G, Dusendang JR, Schmittdiel J, Kavecansky J, Tavakoli J, Pai A. Association of chronic anticoagulant and antiplatelet use on disease severity in SARS-COV-2 infected patients. J Thromb Thrombolysis. 2021;52:476–481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7849957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33527183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olcott F, Hunt C, Chan T, Williams G. Pre-admission anti-coagulation does not improve all-cause mortality in geriatric COVID-19 patients. Clin Med (Lond) 2021;21:7–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34078675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker K, Hamilton P, Hanumapura P, Castelino L, Murphy M, Challiner R, Thachil J, Ebah L. Chronic anticoagulation is not associated with a reduced risk of acute kidney injury in hospitalised Covid-19 patients. BMC Nephrol. 2021;22:224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8208381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34134645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo V, Bottino R, D'Andrea A, Silverio A, Di Maio M, Golino P, Nigro G, Valsecchi O, Attena E, Canonico ME, Galasso G, Parodi G, Scudiero F. Chronic Oral Anticoagulation and Clinical Outcome in Hospitalized COVID-19 Patients. Cardiovasc Drugs Ther. 2022;36:705–712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8120255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33988835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sivaloganathan H, Ladikou EE, Chevassut T. COVID-19 mortality in patients on anticoagulants and antiplatelet agents. Br J Haematol. 2020;190:e192–e195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32584423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spiegelenberg JP, van Gelder MMHJ, Maas ML, Hovens MMC, Esselink A, Dofferhoff ASM, Janssen R, van de Maat J, Janssen N, Blaauw M, Hassing RJ, van Apeldoorn M, Kerckhoffs A, Veerman K, Hoogerwerf J, Kramers C, Leentjens J. Prior use of therapeutic anticoagulation does not protect against COVID-19 related clinical outcomes in hospitalized patients: A propensity score-matched cohort study. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2021;87:4839–4847.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33899226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Haaps TF, Collard D, van Osch FHM, Middeldorp S, Coppens M, de Kruif MD, Vlot EA, Douma RA, Ten Cate H, Juffermans NP, Gritters N, Vlaar AP, Reidinga AC, Heuvelmans MA, Oudkerk M, Büller HR, van den Bergh JPW, Maas A, Ten Wolde M, Simsek S Corona Research Fund Amsterdam UMC, Beudel M, van Es N; Dutch COVID &amp; Thrombosis Coalition. Pre-admission anticoagulant therapy and mortality in hospitalized COVID-19 patients: A retrospective cohort study. Thromb Res. 2021;208:35–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8518131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34688100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Z, Peng F, Xu B, Zhao J, Liu H, Peng J, Li Q, Jiang C, Zhou Y, Liu S, Ye C, Zhang P, Xing Y, Guo H, Tang W. Risk factors of critical &amp; mortal COVID-19 cases: A systematic literature review and meta-analysis. J Infect. 2020;81:e16–e25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7177098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32335169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouns SH, Brüggemann R, Linkens AEMJH, Magdelijns FJ, Joosten H, Heijnen R, Ten Cate-Hoek AJ, Schols JMGA, Ten Cate H, Spaetgens B. Mortality and the Use of Antithrombotic Therapies Among Nursing Home Residents with COVID-19. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2020;68:1647–1652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32633418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fauvel C, Weizman O, Trimaille A, Mika D, Pommier T, Pace N, Douair A, Barbin E, Fraix A, Bouchot O, Benmansour O, Godeau G, Mecheri Y, Lebourdon R, Yvorel C, Massin M, Leblon T, Chabbi C, Cugney E, Benabou L, Aubry M, Chan C, Boufoula I, Barnaud C, Bothorel L, Duceau B, Sutter W, Waldmann V, Bonnet G, Cohen A, Pezel T Critical Covid-19 France Investigators. Pulmonary embolism in COVID-19 patients: a French multicentre cohort study. Eur Heart J. 2020;41:3058–3068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7528952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32656565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aslan B, Akyüz A, Işık F, Çap M, İnci Ü, Kaya İ, Karahan MZ, Aktan A, Bilge Ö, Özbek M, Altıntaş B, Boyraz B. The effect of chronic DOAC treatment on clinical outcomes of hospitalized patients with COVID-19. Int J Clin Pract. 2021;75:e14467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8237002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34107130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruzhentsova TA, Khavkina DA, Chukhliaev PV, Garbuzov AA, Ploskireva AA. [Effect of anticoagulant therapy on the course of COVID-19 in comorbid patients] Vopr Virusol. 2021;66:40–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33683064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossi R, Coppi F, Talarico M, Boriani G. Protective role of chronic treatment with direct oral anticoagulants in elderly patients affected by interstitial pneumonia in COVID-19 era. Eur J Intern Med. 2020;77:158–160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7275180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32564905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera-Caravaca JM, Buckley BJR, Harrison SL, Fazio-Eynullayeva E, Underhill P, Marín F, Lip GYH. Direct-acting oral anticoagulants use prior to COVID-19 diagnosis and associations with 30-day clinical outcomes. Thromb Res. 2021;205:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8236305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34218058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flam B, Wintzell V, Ludvigsson JF, Mårtensson J, Pasternak B. Direct oral anticoagulant use and risk of severe COVID-19. J Intern Med. 2021;289:411–419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7753564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33258156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ménager P, Brière O, Gautier J, Riou J, Sacco G, Brangier A, Annweiler C Geria-Covid Study Group OBOT. Regular Use of VKA Prior to COVID-19 Associated with Lower 7-Day Survival in Hospitalized Frail Elderly COVID-19 Patients: The GERIA-COVID Cohort Study. Nutrients. 2020;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7824717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33374341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klok FA, Kruip MJHA, van der Meer NJM, Arbous MS, Gommers D, Kant KM, Kaptein FHJ, van Paassen J, Stals MAM, Huisman MV, Endeman H. Confirmation of the high cumulative incidence of thrombotic complications in critically ill ICU patients with COVID-19: An updated analysis. Thromb Res. 2020;191:148–150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7192101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32381264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middeldorp S, Coppens M, van Haaps TF, Foppen M, Vlaar AP, Müller MCA, Bouman CCS, Beenen LFM, Kootte RS, Heijmans J, Smits LP, Bonta PI, van Es N. Incidence of venous thromboembolism in hospitalized patients with COVID-19. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1995–2002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7497052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natali KM, Chan KH, Atallah L, Nagarakanti S, Slim J. 552. Could Anticoagulant Use Prior to Infection with COVID-19 Decrease Mortality? Open Forum Infect Di. 2020;7:S342–S342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reilev M, Kristensen KB, Pottegård A, Lund LC, Hallas J, Ernst MT, Christiansen CF, Sørensen HT, Johansen NB, Brun NC, Voldstedlund M, Støvring H, Thomsen MK, Christensen S, Gubbels S, Krause TG, Mølbak K, Thomsen RW. Characteristics and predictors of hospitalization and death in the first 11 122 cases with a positive RT-PCR test for SARS-CoV-2 in Denmark: a nationwide cohort. Int J Epidemiol. 2020;49:1468–1481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7499657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32887982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wargny M, Potier L, Gourdy P, Pichelin M, Amadou C, Benhamou PY, Bonnet JB, Bordier L, Bourron O, Chaumeil C, Chevalier N, Darmon P, Delenne B, Demarsy D, Dumas M, Dupuy O, Flaus-Furmaniuk A, Gautier JF, Guedj AM, Jeandidier N, Larger E, Le Berre JP, Lungo M, Montanier N, Moulin P, Plat F, Rigalleau V, Robert R, Seret-Bégué D, Sérusclat P, Smati S, Thébaut JF, Tramunt B, Vatier C, Velayoudom FL, Vergès B, Winiszewski P, Zabulon A, Gourraud PA, Roussel R, Cariou B, Hadjadj S CORONADO investigators. Predictors of hospital discharge and mortality in patients with diabetes and COVID-19: updated results from the nationwide CORONADO study. Diabetologia. 2021;64:778–794.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7890396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33599800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philipose Z, Smati N, Wong CSJ, Aspey K, Mendall MA.  Obesity, old age and frailty are the true risk factors for COVID-19 mortality and not chronic disease or ethnicity in Croydon. 2020 Preprint. Available from: https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.08.12.20156257v3 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Molinero A, Gálvez-Barrón C, Miñarro A, Macho O, López GF, Robles MT, Dapena MD, Martínez S, Milà Ràfols N, Monaco EE, Hidalgo García A COVID-19 Research Group of CSAPG. Association between COVID-19 prognosis and disease presentation, comorbidities and chronic treatment of hospitalized patients. PLoS One. 2020;15:e0239571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7561079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33057443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boari GEM, Chiarini G, Bonetti S, Malerba P, Bianco G, Faustini C, Braglia-Orlandini F, Turini D, Guarinoni V, Saottini M, Viola S, Ferrari-Toninelli G, Pasini G, Mascadri C, Bonzi B, Desenzani P, Tusi C, Zanotti E, Nardin M, Rizzoni D. Prognostic factors and predictors of outcome in patients with COVID-19 and related pneumonia: a retrospective cohort study. Biosci Rep. 2020;40</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7724688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33201172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tehrani S, Killander A, Åstrand P, Jakobsson J, Gille-Johnson P. Risk factors for death in adult COVID-19 patients: Frailty predicts fatal outcome in older patients. Int J Infect Dis. 2021;102:415–421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33130213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tremblay D, van Gerwen M, Alsen M, Thibaud S, Kessler A, Venugopal S, Makki I, Qin Q, Dharmapuri S, Jun T, Bhalla S, Berwick S, Feld J, Mascarenhas J, Troy K, Cromwell C, Dunn A, Oh WK, Naymagon L. Impact of anticoagulation prior to COVID-19 infection: a propensity score-matched cohort study. Blood. 2020;136:144–147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7332896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32462179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer AZ, Gore R, Sama SR, Rosiello R, Garber L, Sundaresan D, McDonald A, Arruda P, Kriebel D. Hypertension, medications, and risk of severe COVID-19: A Massachusetts community-based observational study. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich) 2021;23:21–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7753489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33220171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iaccarino G, Grassi G, Borghi C, Grassi D, Mancusi C, Muiesan ML, Salvetti M, Volpe M, Ferri C. Preexisting Oral Anticoagulant Therapy Ameliorates Prognosis in Hospitalized COVID-19 Patients. Front Cardiovasc Med. 2021;8:633878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8155285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34055928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lodigiani C, Iapichino G, Carenzo L, Cecconi M, Ferrazzi P, Sebastian T, Kucher N, Studt JD, Sacco C, Bertuzzi A, Sandri MT, Barco S Humanitas COVID-19 Task Force. Venous and arterial thromboembolic complications in COVID-19 patients admitted to an academic hospital in Milan, Italy. Thromb Res. 2020;191:9–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7177070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32353746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schiavone M, Gasperetti A, Mancone M, Curnis A, Mascioli G, Mitacchione G, Busana M, Sabato F, Gobbi C, Antinori S, Galli M, Forleo GB. Oral anticoagulation and clinical outcomes in COVID-19: An Italian multicenter experience. Int J Cardiol. 2021;323:276–280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7476907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32911000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui S, Chen S, Li X, Liu S, Wang F. Prevalence of venous thromboembolism in patients with severe novel coronavirus pneumonia. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1421–1424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32271988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Shen L, Le KJ, Pan MM, Kong LC, Gu ZC, Xu H, Zhang Z, Ge WH, Lin HW. Incidence of Venous Thromboembolism in Hospitalized Coronavirus Disease 2019 Patients: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Front Cardiovasc Med. 2020;7:151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7423832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32850990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costela-Ruiz VJ, Illescas-Montes R, Puerta-Puerta JM, Ruiz C, Melguizo-Rodríguez L. SARS-CoV-2 infection: The role of cytokines in COVID-19 disease. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 2020;54:62–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7265853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32513566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Libby P, Lüscher T. COVID-19 is, in the end, an endothelial disease. Eur Heart J. 2020;41:3038–3044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7470753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32882706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowenstein CJ, Solomon SD. Severe COVID-19 Is a Microvascular Disease. Circulation. 2020;142:1609–1611.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7580651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32877231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teuwen LA, Geldhof V, Pasut A, Carmeliet P. Author Correction: COVID-19: the vasculature unleashed. Nat Rev Immunol. 2020;20:448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32499635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talaei F, Banga A, Pursell A, Gage A, Pallipamu N, Seri AR, Adhikari R, Kashyap R, Surani S. New-onset atrial fibrillation among COVID-19 patients: A narrative review. World J Crit Care Med. 2023;12:236–247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10768419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38188450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuker A, Tseng EK, Nieuwlaat R, Angchaisuksiri P, Blair C, Dane K, Davila J, DeSancho MT, Diuguid D, Griffin DO, Kahn SR, Klok FA, Lee AI, Neumann I, Pai A, Pai M, Righini M, Sanfilippo KM, Siegal D, Skara M, Touri K, Akl EA, Bou Akl I, Boulos M, Brignardello-Petersen R, Charide R, Chan M, Dearness K, Darzi AJ, Kolb P, Colunga-Lozano LE, Mansour R, Morgano GP, Morsi RZ, Noori A, Piggott T, Qiu Y, Roldan Y, Schünemann F, Stevens A, Solo K, Ventresca M, Wiercioch W, Mustafa RA, Schünemann HJ. American Society of Hematology 2021 guidelines on the use of anticoagulation for thromboprophylaxis in patients with COVID-19. Blood Adv. 2021;5:872–888.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7869684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33560401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rentsch CT, Beckman JA, Tomlinson L, Gellad WF, Alcorn C, Kidwai-Khan F, Skanderson M, Brittain E, King JT Jr, Ho YL, Eden S, Kundu S, Lann MF, Greevy RA Jr, Ho PM, Heidenreich PA, Jacobson DA, Douglas IJ, Tate JP, Evans SJW, Atkins D, Justice AC, Freiberg MS. Early initiation of prophylactic anticoagulation for prevention of coronavirus disease 2019 mortality in patients admitted to hospital in the United States: cohort study. BMJ. 2021;372:n311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7876672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33574135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang N, Bai H, Chen X, Gong J, Li D, Sun Z. Anticoagulant treatment is associated with decreased mortality in severe coronavirus disease 2019 patients with coagulopathy. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1094–1099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32220112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamel AM, Sobhy M, Magdy N, Sabry N, Farid S. Anticoagulation outcomes in hospitalized Covid-19 patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis of case-control and cohort studies. Rev Med Virol. 2021;31:e2180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7646049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33022834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hottz ED, Azevedo-Quintanilha IG, Palhinha L, Teixeira L, Barreto EA, Pão CRR, Righy C, Franco S, Souza TML, Kurtz P, Bozza FA, Bozza PT. Platelet activation and platelet-monocyte aggregate formation trigger tissue factor expression in patients with severe COVID-19. Blood. 2020;136:1330–1341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7483437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32678428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maier CL, Truong AD, Auld SC, Polly DM, Tanksley CL, Duncan A. COVID-19-associated hyperviscosity: a link between inflammation and thrombophilia? Lancet. 2020;395:1758–1759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7247793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32464112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panigada M, Bottino N, Tagliabue P, Grasselli G, Novembrino C, Chantarangkul V, Pesenti A, Peyvandi F, Tripodi A. Hypercoagulability of COVID-19 patients in intensive care unit: A report of thromboelastography findings and other parameters of hemostasis. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1738–1742.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranucci M, Ballotta A, Di Dedda U, Baryshnikova E, Dei Poli M, Resta M, Falco M, Albano G, Menicanti L. The procoagulant pattern of patients with COVID-19 acute respiratory distress syndrome. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1747–1751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connors JM, Levy JH. Thromboinflammation and the hypercoagulability of COVID-19. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1559–1561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9770920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fogarty H, Townsend L, Ni Cheallaigh C, Bergin C, Martin-Loeches I, Browne P, Bacon CL, Gaule R, Gillett A, Byrne M, Ryan K, O'Connell N, O'Sullivan JM, Conlon N, O'Donnell JS. COVID19 coagulopathy in Caucasian patients. Br J Haematol. 2020;189:1044–1049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32330308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kollias A, Kyriakoulis KG, Dimakakos E, Poulakou G, Stergiou GS, Syrigos K. Thromboembolic risk and anticoagulant therapy in COVID-19 patients: emerging evidence and call for action. Br J Haematol. 2020;189:846–847.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32304577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thachil J, Tang N, Gando S, Falanga A, Cattaneo M, Levi M, Clark C, Iba T. ISTH interim guidance on recognition and management of coagulopathy in COVID-19. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1023–1026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32338827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>