<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310476</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Delayed Diagnosis of a Submassive Pulmonary Embolism Following Influenza A Infection Treated With Half-Dose Tenecteplase: A Case Report.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67392</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67392</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67392</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67392</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has brought renewed attention to thrombotic complications arising from respiratory viral infections, driven by inflammatory responses and activation of the coagulation cascade. While influenza typically resolves on its own, information about its thromboembolic risks remains limited. The persistence of symptoms and the similarity between influenza symptoms and those of pulmonary embolism (PE) often lead to diagnostic delays, which can significantly impact patient outcomes. We discuss a case of a 62-year-old woman with a history of hypertension and hyperlipidemia who presented with dyspnea, syncope, and persistent symptoms following influenza A infection. Despite initial treatment with Tamiflu and subsequent antibiotics for presumed pneumonia, her condition worsened, leading to syncope and admission to the hospital. A diagnostic workup revealed saddle pulmonary emboli with right ventricular strain. She was treated with a half-dose of tenecteplase, resulting in significant clinical improvement and a notable reduction in thrombus burden on follow-up imaging. The thromboembolic complications of influenza A are not extensively documented compared to COVID-19, yet they can present with severe outcomes. Submassive PE, characterized by hemodynamic stability with signs of right ventricular strain, poses treatment challenges. While full-dose thrombolytics are generally avoided in intermediate-risk PE due to bleeding risks, half-dose thrombolytics such as tenecteplase can offer a safer alternative. Though not FDA-approved specifically for PE, tenecteplase has shown efficacy and was effectively used in this case. Half-dose thrombolytics, including tenecteplase, may be a viable treatment option for certain cases of PE, offering a balance between efficacy and safety. This case highlights the importance of considering PE in patients with persistent respiratory symptoms post-influenza and demonstrates the potential of tenecteplase in managing submassive PE.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Jorat et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jorat</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Vahid</ForeName><Initials>MV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, West Anaheim Medical Center, Anaheim, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shankar</LastName><ForeName>Abhirami</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, West Anaheim Medical Center, Anaheim, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garabetian</LastName><ForeName>Christine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, West Anaheim Medical Center, Anaheim, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Geha</LastName><ForeName>Marie J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, West Anaheim Medical Center, Anaheim, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bogseth</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emegency Medicine, West Anaheim Medical Center, Anaheim, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chou</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin F</ForeName><Initials>BF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, West Anaheim Medical Center, Anaheim, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">half dose systemic thrombolytic therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">influenza a infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">saddle pulmonary embolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">submassive pulmonary embolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tenecteplase</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Thromboembolic events in patients with influenza: a scoping review. Rubino R, Imburgia C, Bonura S, Trizzino M, Iaria C, Cascio A. Viruses. 2022;14:16–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9785394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Submassive pulmonary embolism: current perspectives and future directions. Nguyen PC, Stevens H, Peter K, McFadyen JD. J Clin Med. 2021;10:26–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8347177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34362166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenecteplase in pulmonary embolism patients: a meta-analysis and systematic review. Zhang Z, Xi L, Zhang S, et al. Front Med (Lausanne) 2022;9:860565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9008780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35433747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low-dose thrombolysis for submassive pulmonary embolism. Yilmaz ES, Uzun O. J Investig Med. 2021;69:1439–1446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8639905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34099544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bach KT, Lui F. Treasure Island, FL: StatPearls Publishing; 2024. Tenecteplase.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37276288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>