<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39313634</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-7284</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>39</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European journal of epidemiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur J Epidemiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>IDcare - a longitudinal register study of pre-pandemic and pandemic health care utilization and diagnostic profiles among people with intellectual disabilities in southern Sweden.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1063</StartPage><EndPage>1071</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1063-1071</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10654-024-01151-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The aim of the creation of this cohort was to investigate patterns of health and health care utilisation before and during the COVID-19 pandemic, overall and in relation to specific diagnoses, among people with intellectual disabilities (ID) compared to the general population. People living in Skåne, the southernmost region of Sweden, on 1st of January 2014 with at least one diagnosis of ID (ICD-10 codes F70-F79) or Down syndrome (DS; Q90), or support and/or services according to the LSS act comprised the ID cohort (n = 14 716). People living in the same family and/or household as a person in the ID cohort constituted the ID family cohort (n = 31 688), and those remaining comprised the general population cohort (gPop; n = 1 226 955). Data has been collected for all three cohorts from several national and regional registers. These include registers for health care (2014-2021), deaths (2014-2021), COVID-19-related health care (vaccinations, intensive care, palliative care, 2020-2021). The prevalence of ID was 1.2%. In the ID cohort, 77.9% had at least one measure of support, 5.8% at least one Q90-diagnosis and 63.8% had at least one F7-diagnosis (26.9% mild (F70), 7.4% moderate (F71), 2.8% severe (F72), 1.4% profound (F73), and 25.4% other/unknown (F78/F79)). Compared to the gPop there were more people in the younger age groups in the ID cohort. At this point, no additional collection of data will be carried out. However, there is a possibility to add data from the registers to include years after 2021 or from additional registers. Future publications will explore relevant research questions and report key findings in relation to health among people with ID. Future results will be used to inform policy and practice on people with ID.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sandberg</LastName><ForeName>Magnus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8915-8730</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, Lund University, Lund, Sweden. magnus.sandberg@med.lu.se.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kristensson</LastName><ForeName>Jimmie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3659-7860</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Palliative Care, Lund University and Region Skåne, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Axmon</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4539-8337</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology, Population Research, and Infrastructures at Lund University, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Eur J Epidemiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8508062</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0393-2990</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013548" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Sweden</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012042" MajorTopicYN="Y">Registries</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008607" MajorTopicYN="Y">Intellectual Disability</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008137" MajorTopicYN="N">Longitudinal Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010342" MajorTopicYN="Y">Patient Acceptance of Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diagnosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Healthcare utilisation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intellectual disabilities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Registers</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39313634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11470885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10654-024-01151-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10654-024-01151-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation (WHO). International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, 10th Revision. 2015. http://apps.who.int/classifications/icd/en/. Accessed 11 October 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation (WHO). International Classification of Functioning, disability and health (ICF). Geneva: World Health Organisation; 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Association on Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities (AAIDD). Defining Criteria for Intellectual Disability. http://aaidd.org/intellectual-disability/definition#.WJsHrzt97b0. Accessed 11 October 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowring DL, Totsika V, Hastings RP, et al. Challenging behaviours in adults with an intellectual disability: a total population study and exploration of risk indices. Br J Clin Psychol. 2017;56(1):16–32. 10.1111/bjc.12118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27878840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones S, Cooper SA, Smiley E, et al. Prevalence of, and factors associated with, problem behaviors in adults with intellectual disabilities. J Nerv Ment Dis. 2008;196(9):678–86. 10.1097/NMD.0b013e318183f85c.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18791429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundqvist LO. Prevalence and risk markers of behavior problems among adults with intellectual disabilities: a total population study in Örebro County, Sweden. Res Dev Disabil. 2013;34(4):1346–56. 10.1016/j.ridd.2013.01.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23417139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Einfeld SL, Emerson E. Challenging Behaviour. 3 ed. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai D-C, Tseng Y-C, Hou Y-M, et al. Gender and geographic differences in the prevalence of intellectual disability in children: analysis of data from the national disability registry of Taiwan. Res Dev Disabil. 2012;33(6):2301–07.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22877930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McConkey R, Mulvany F, Barron S. Adult persons with intellectual disabilities on the island of Ireland. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2006;50(3):227–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16430733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz-Fernandez F. Descriptive epidemiology of registered mentally retarded persons in Galicia (northwest Spain). Am J Ment Retard. 1988;92(4):385–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3342142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patja K, Iivanainen M, Vesala H, et al. Life expectancy of people with intellectual disability: a 35-year follow‐up study. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2000;44(5):591–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11079356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Westerinen H, Kaski M, Virta L, et al. Prevalence of intellectual disability: a comprehensive study based on national registers. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2007;51(9):715–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17845240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Schrojenstein Lantman-de Valk H, Wullink M, Van Den Akker M, et al. The prevalence of intellectual disability in Limburg, the Netherlands. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2006;50(1):61–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16316431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper SA, Henderson A, Kinnear D, et al. Cohort profile: Scotland’s record-linkage e-cohorts of people with intellectual disabilities, and autistic people (SCIDA). BMJ open. 2022;12(5):e057230. 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-057230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9109103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35568493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng N, Sandberg M, Ahlstrom G. Prevalence of older people with intellectual disability in Sweden: a spatial epidemiological analysis. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2015;59(12):1155–67. 10.1111/jir.12219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26306552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maulik PK, Mascarenhas MN, Mathers CD, et al. Prevalence of intellectual disability: a meta-analysis of population-based studies. Res Dev Disabil. 2011;32(2):419–36. 10.1016/j.ridd.2010.12.018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21236634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKenzie K, Milton M, Smith G, et al. Systematic review of the prevalence and incidence of intellectual disabilities: current trends and issues. Curr Dev Disorders Rep. 2016;3:104–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao P, Vajdic C, Trollor J, et al. Prevalence and incidence of physical health conditions in people with intellectual disability – a systematic review. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(8):e0256294. 10.1371/journal.pone.0256294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8384165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34428249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van den Bemd M, Schalk BWM, Bischoff E, et al. Chronic diseases and comorbidities in adults with and without intellectual disabilities: comparative cross-sectional study in Dutch general practice. Fam Pract. 2022;39(6):1056–62. 10.1093/fampra/cmac042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9680667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35579254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazza MG, Rossetti A, Crespi G, et al. Prevalence of co-occurring psychiatric disorders in adults and adolescents with intellectual disability: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. J Appl Res Intellect Disabil. 2020;33(2):126–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31430018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandberg M, Ahlström G, Axmon A, et al. Somatic healthcare utilisation patterns among older people with intellectual disability: an 11-year register study. BMC Health Serv Res. 2016;16(1):642. 10.1186/s12913-016-1880-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5103402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27829424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandberg M, Axmon A, Ahlström G, et al. Predictors of specialist somatic healthcare utilization among older people with intellectual disability and their age-peers in the general population: a national register study. BMJ open. 2023;13(7):e072679. 10.1136/bmjopen-2023-072679.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10335550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37407048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ailey SH, Heller T, Brown HE. Mental Health of older adults with intellectual disability. J Psychosoc Nurs Ment Health Serv. 2022;60(7):10–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35858172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carey IM, Hosking FJ, Harris T et al. Health Services and Delivery Research. An evaluation of the effectiveness of annual health checks and quality of health care for adults with intellectual disability: an observational study using a primary care database. Southampton (UK): NIHR Journals Library.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28930382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCarron M, Cleary E, McCallion P. Health and health-care utilization of the older population of Ireland: comparing the intellectual disability population and the general population. Res Aging. 2017;39(6):693–718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28566009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicholson E, Doherty E, Guerin S, et al. Healthcare utilisation and unmet health needs in children with intellectual disability: a propensity score matching approach using longitudinal cohort data. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2022;66(5):442–53. 10.1111/jir.12927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9310956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35285998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maltais J, Morin D, Tassé MJ. Healthcare services utilization among people with intellectual disability and comparison with the general population. J Appl Res Intellect Disabil. 2020;33(3):552–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32064737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glover G, Williams R, Tompkins G, et al. An observational study of the use of acute hospital care by people with intellectual disabilities in England. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2019;63(2):85–99. 10.1111/jir.12544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30221429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahlström G, Axmon A, Sandberg M, et al. Specialist psychiatric health care utilization among older people with intellectual disability–predictors and comparisons with the general population: a national register study. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7027029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32066421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coppus AM. People with intellectual disability: what do we know about adulthood and life expectancy? Dev Disabil Res Rev. 2013;18(1):6–16. 10.1002/ddrr.1123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23949824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Englund A, Jonsson B, Zander CS, et al. Changes in mortality and causes of death in the Swedish down syndrome population. Am J Med Genet Part A. 2013;161(4):642–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23436430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heslop P, Blair PS, Fleming P, et al. The Confidential Inquiry into premature deaths of people with intellectual disabilities in the UK: a population-based study. Lancet. 2014;383(9920):889–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24332307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heller T, Stafford P, Davis L, et al. People with intellectual and developmental disabilities growing old: an overview. Impact: Feature Issue Aging People Intellect Dev Disabil. 2010;23(1):2–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirvikoski T, Boman M, Tideman M, et al. Association of Intellectual Disability with all-Cause and cause-specific mortality in Sweden. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(6):e2113014–14. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.13014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8220491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34156453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosking FJ, Carey IM, Shah SM, et al. Mortality among adults with intellectual disability in England: comparisons with the General Population. Am J Public Health. 2016;106(8):1483–90. 10.2105/ajph.2016.303240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4940652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27310347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy JM, Botuck S, Rimmerman A. Examining outpatient health care utilization among adults with severe or profound intellectual disabilities living in an urban setting: a brief snap shot. J Soc Work Disabil Rehabil. 2007;6(3):33–45. 10.1300/J198v06n03_02.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17989033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loh CH, Lin JD, Choi IC, et al. Longitudinal analysis of inpatient care utilization among people with intellectual disabilities: 1999–2002. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2007;51(Pt 2):101–8. 10.1111/j.1365-2788.2006.00822.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17217474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turk V, Kerry S, Corney R, et al. Why some adults with intellectual disability consult their general practitioner more than others. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2010;54(9):833–42. 10.1111/j.1365-2788.2010.01312.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20712697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beange H, McElduff A, Baker W. Medical disorders of adults with mental retardation: a population study. Am J Ment Retard. 1995;99(6):595–604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7632427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halstead SM, Bradley F, Milne S, et al. Annual Primary Health Care contacts by people with intellectual disabilities: a comparison of three matched groups. J Appl Res Intellect Disabil. 2000;13(2):100–07. 10.1046/j.1468-3148.2000.00013.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markovic-Jovanovic SR, Milovanovic JD, Jovanovic AN, et al. Comorbidities in children with intellectual disabilities. Birth Defects Res. 2020;112(1):54–61. 10.1002/bdr2.1587.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31502761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall A, Wood D, Hou T, et al. Patterns in primary health care utilization among individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities in Florida. Intellect Dev Disabil. 2007;45(5):310–22. 10.1352/0047-6765(2007)45[310:piphcu]2.0.co;2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17887908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lunsky Y, Lin E, Balogh R, et al. Are adults with developmental disabilities more likely to visit EDs? Am J Emerg Med. 2011;29(4):463–5. 10.1016/j.ajem.2010.12.028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21316180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Straetmans JM, van Lantman-de Valk S, Schellevis HM. Health problems of people with intellectual disabilities: the impact for general practice. Br J Gen Pract. 2007;57(534):64–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2032703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17244427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistiska Centralbyrån [Statistics Sweden]. Statistical database: Statistiska Centralbyrån. 2024. https://www.statistikdatabasen.scb.se/pxweb/en/ssd/START__BE__BE0101/. Accessed 15 Jan 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hälso- och sjukvårdslag [The Health and Medical Service Act]. SFS 2017:30. Stockholm: Socialdepartementet. 2017. https://www.riksdagen.se/sv/dokument-lagar/dokument/svenskforfattningssamling/halso--och-sjukvardslag_sfs-2017-30. Accessed 15 Jan 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lag om stöd och service till vissa funktionshindrade (LSS) [Act concerning Support and Service for Persons with Certain Functional Impairments]. SFS 1993:387. Stockholm: Socialdepartementet. 1993. https://www.riksdagen.se/sv/dokument-lagar/dokument/svensk-forfattningssamling/lag-1993387-om-stod-och-service-till-vissa_sfs-1993-387. Accessed 15 Jan 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Socialtjänstlagen [The Social Services Act]. SFS 2001:453. Sweden, Stockholm: Socialdepartementet. 2001. https://www.riksdagen.se/sv/dokument-lagar/dokument/svensk-forfattningssamling/socialtjanstlag-2001453_sfs-2001-453. Accessed 15 Jan 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Socialstyrelsen [The National Board of Health and Welfare]. Registers [Online]. 2024. https://www.socialstyrelsen.se/en/statistics-and-data/registers/ (accessed 15 Jan 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sveriges Kommuner och Regioner [Swedish Association of Local Authorities and Regions]. Quality registries. 2024. https://skr.se/en/kvalitetsregister/omnationellakvalitetsregister.52218.html. Accessed 18 Dec 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ludvigsson JF, et al. The Swedish personal identity number: possibilities and pitfalls in healthcare and medical research. Eur J Epidemiol. 2009;24(11):659–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2773709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19504049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Löfvendahl S, Schelin MEC, Jöud A. The value of the Skåne Health-Care Register: prospectively collected individual-level data for population-based studies. Scand J Public Health. 2020;48(1):56–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31814536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ludvigsson JF, et al. External review and validation of the Swedish national inpatient register. BMC Public Health. 2011;11:450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3142234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21658213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>