<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39312203</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1399-3062</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Transplant infectious disease : an official journal of the Transplantation Society</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Transpl Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Infections following chimeric antigen receptor T cell therapy: 2018-2022.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e14376</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e14376</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/tid.14376</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T-cell therapy is an emerging therapeutic modality for relapsed and refractory hematological malignancies. Infectious complications following CAR T-cell therapy are not well defined.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This is a retrospective analysis of data on patients who received CAR T-cell therapy between April 2018 and December 2022 at the Karmanos Cancer Center, Detroit. Patients' data were collected up to their last known clinic or inpatient follow-up visit. An infectious episode was defined as any microbiologically proven or clinically documented infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Seventy-six patients received therapy with FDA-approved CAR T-cell products. Thirty-three patients (43.4%) had at least one infectious episode. There were 61 infectious episodes during a median follow-up of 184 (96-340) days. Median duration for the onset of infection was 59 (22-209) days. Bacterial and viral infections occurred in 42.6% and 41% of the infectious episodes, respectively. COVID-19 was the most common infectious complication (14.8%). Time-to-event analysis showed that most infections occurred within the first 100 days. Empirical antibiotic use during Cytokine Release Syndrome/Immune effector Cell-Associated Neurotoxicity Syndrome (CRS/ICANS) in the absence of documented bacterial infection was reported in 85.7% of patients. Clostridioides difficile accounted for 11.5% of all infectious episodes. Five of six patients with C. difficile infection had CRS/ICANS and received antibiotics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">COVID-19 and C. difficile infection were the most common infections following CAR T-cell therapy. Most infections occurred within the first 100 days. Empiric antibiotic use and C. difficile infection were common in patients with CRS/ICANS, in the absence of documented bacterial infection, thus providing an excellent opportunity for antimicrobial stewardship in this population.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Keri</LastName><ForeName>Vishakh C</ForeName><Initials>VC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1109-8739</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious diseases, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monday</LastName><ForeName>Lea M</ForeName><Initials>LM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious diseases, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramakrishna</LastName><ForeName>Jahanavi M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vyas</LastName><ForeName>Rahul</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deol</LastName><ForeName>Abhinav</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Karmanos Cancer Center, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Saadi</LastName><ForeName>Mahmoud</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious diseases, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chandrasekar</LastName><ForeName>Pranatharthi H</ForeName><Initials>PH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious diseases, Karmanos Cancer Center, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Denmark</Country><MedlineTA>Transpl Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100883688</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1398-2273</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CAR T‐cell therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clostridioides difficile</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infections</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39312203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/tid.14376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Gill S, Brudno JN. CAR T‐cell therapy in hematologic malignancies: clinical role, toxicity, and unanswered questions. Am Soc Clin Oncol Educ Book. 2021;41:e246‐e265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kampouri E, Walti CS, Gauthier J, Hill JA. Managing hypogammaglobulinemia in patients treated with CAR‐T‐cell therapy: key points for clinicians. Expert Rev Hematol. 2022;15:305‐320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kambhampati S, Sheng Y, Huang C‐Y, et al. Infectious complications in patients with relapsed refractory multiple myeloma after BCMA CAR T‐cell therapy. Blood Adv. 2022;6:2045‐2054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logue JM, Peres LC, Hashmi H, et al. Early cytopenias and infections after standard of care idecabtagene vicleucel in relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Blood Adv. 2022;6:6109‐6119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Little JS, Tandon M, Hong JS, et al. Respiratory infections predominate after day 100 following B‐cell maturation antigen‐directed CAR T‐cell therapy. Blood Adv. 2023;7:5485‐5495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee DW, Santomasso BD, Locke FL, et al. ASTCT consensus grading for cytokine release syndrome and neurologic toxicity associated with immune effector cells. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2019;25:625‐638.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Ming Y, Fu R, et al. The pathogenesis, diagnosis, prevention, and treatment of CAR‐T cell therapy‐related adverse reactions. Front Pharmacol. 2022;13. https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2022.950923</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gudiol C, Lewis RE, Strati P, Kontoyiannis DP. Chimeric antigen receptor T‐cell therapy for the treatment of lymphoid malignancies: is there an excess risk for infection? Lancet Haematol. 2021;8:e216‐e228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill JA, Seo SK. How I prevent infections in patients receiving CD19‐targeted chimeric antigen receptor T cells for B‐cell malignancies? Blood. 2020;136:925‐935.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemoine J, Bachy E, Cartron G, et al. Nonrelapse mortality after CAR T‐cell therapy for large B‐cell lymphoma: a LYSA study from the DESCAR‐T registry. Blood Adv. 2023;7:6589‐6598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonald LC, Gerding DN, Johnson S, et al. Clinical Practice Guidelines for Clostridium difficile Infection in Adults and Children: 2017 update by the Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA) and Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America (SHEA). Clin Infect Dis. 2018;66:e1‐e48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donnelly JP, Chen SC, Kauffman CA, et al. Revision and update of the consensus definitions of invasive fungal disease from the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer and the Mycoses Study Group Education and Research Consortium. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:1367‐1376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banegas M, Bindal P, Woodbine MJH, et al. 2694. Infectious complications in CAR‐T cell therapy recipients: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2023;10:ofad500.2305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rejeski K, Perez A, Sesques P, et al. CAR‐HEMATOTOX: a model for CAR T‐cell–related hematologic toxicity in relapsed/refractory large B‐cell lymphoma. Blood. 2021;138:2499‐2513.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rejeski K, Perez A, Iacoboni G, et al. The CAR‐HEMATOTOX risk‐stratifies patients for severe infections and disease progression after CD19 CAR‐T in R/R LBCL. J Immunother Cancer. 2022;10:e004475.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Los‐Arcos I, Iacoboni G, Aguilar‐Guisado M, et al. Recommendations for screening, monitoring, prevention, and prophylaxis of infections in adult and pediatric patients receiving CAR T‐cell therapy: a position paper. Infection. 2021;49:215‐231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma N, Reagan PM, Liesveld JL. Cytopenia after CAR‐T cell therapy—a brief review of a complex problem. Cancers. 2022;14:1501.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Li J, Ni F, et al. CAR‐T cell therapy‐related cytokine release syndrome and therapeutic response is modulated by the gut microbiome in hematologic malignancies. Nat Commun. 2022;13:5313.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abid MB, Shah NN, Maatman TC, Hari PN. Gut microbiome and CAR‐T therapy. Exp Hematol Oncol. 2019;8:31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asokan S, Cullin N, Stein‐Thoeringer CK, Elinav E. CAR‐T cell therapy and the gut microbiota. Cancers. 2023;15:794.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill JA, Li D, Hay KA, et al. Infectious complications of CD19‐targeted chimeric antigen receptor‐modified T‐cell immunotherapy. Blood. 2018;131:121‐130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park JH, Romero FA, Taur Y, et al. Cytokine release syndrome grade as a predictive marker for infections in patients with relapsed or refractory B‐cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia treated with chimeric antigen receptor T cells. Clin Infect Dis. 2018;67:533‐540.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logue JM, Zucchetti E, Bachmeier CA, et al. Immune reconstitution and associated infections following axicabtagene ciloleucel in relapsed or refractory large B‐cell lymphoma. Haematologica. 2020;106:978‐986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wudhikarn K, Palomba ML, Pennisi M, et al. Infection during the first year in patients treated with CD19 CAR T cells for diffuse large B cell lymphoma. Blood Cancer J. 2020;10:79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wittmann Dayagi T, Sherman G, Bielorai B, et al. Characteristics and risk factors of infections following CD28‐based CD19 CAR‐T cells. Leuk Lymphoma. 2021;62:1692‐1701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korell F, Schubert M‐L, Sauer T, et al. Infection complications after lymphodepletion and dosing of chimeric antigen receptor T (CAR‐T) cell therapy in patients with relapsed/refractory acute lymphoblastic leukemia or B cell non‐Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancers. 2021;13:1684.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huggins J, Messina JA, Saullo J, et al. 2708 Infectious complications among CD19 Chimeric antigen receptor T‐cell recipients. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2023;10:ofad500.2319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen G, Herr M, Nowak J, et al. Cytomegalovirus reactivation after CD19 CAR T‐cell therapy is clinically significant. Haematologica. 2022;108:615‐620.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khawaja F, Prakash R, Sassine J, et al. Cytomegalovirus (CMV) reactivation within in the first year after chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cell therapy: experience from the first two years at a major cancer center. Blood. 2022;140:7533‐7535.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Márquez‐Algaba E, Iacoboni G, Pernas B, et al. Impact of cytomegalovirus replication in patients with aggressive B cell lymphoma treated with chimeric antigen receptor T cell therapy. Transpl Cell Ther. 2022;28:851.e1‐851.e8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kampouri E, Ibrahimi SS, Xie H, et al. CMV reactivation and CMV‐specific cell‐mediated immunity after chimeric antigen receptor T‐cell therapy. Clin Infect Dis. 2024;78:1022‐1032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammond SP, Little JS. The clinical significance of cytomegalovirus viremia after chimeric antigen receptor T‐cell therapy. Clin Infect Dis 2024;ciae053.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>