<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314675</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1687-6415</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>2024</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of telemedicine and applications</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Telemed Appl</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Environmental Factors for Sustained Telehealth Use in Mental Health Services: A Mixed Methods Analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>8835933</StartPage><MedlinePgn>8835933</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">8835933</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1155/2024/8835933</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><b>Background:</b> The mental health service delivery gap remains high globally. Appropriate telehealth use may increase capacity through flexible remote care provision. Despite the historical lack of telehealth integration into publicly funded mental health services, during COVID-19 lockdowns, services rapidly switched to telephone and audiovisual care provision. In Aotearoa New Zealand (NZ), this was abandoned when no longer required by COVID-19 restrictions. This study explores environmental factors associated with telehealth implementation and ongoing use or discontinuation across a multiregional outpatient mental health service. This work contributes to understanding system-level factors influencing telehealth use and thus informs policy and practice in postpandemic environments. <b>Methods:</b> This mixed methods study applied an interpretive description methodology. Semistructured interviews with 33 mental health clinicians were thematically analysed. Qualitative findings were reframed and evaluated using time series analyses of population-level quantitative data (prior to and throughout the pandemic). Findings were synthesised with qualitative themes to develop an understanding of environmental factors contributing to telehealth use. <b>Results:</b> Findings highlighted an increase in clients assessed by mental health services and declining clinician numbers, contributing to pressure placed on clinicians. There was a lack of culture supporting telehealth, including limited awareness, leadership, and champions to facilitate implementation. Some teams provided services suited to telehealth; other subspeciality teams had limited applications for telehealth. There was a general lack of policy and guidelines to support telehealth use and limited technical support for clinicians unfamiliar with audiovisual software. <b>Conclusion:</b> Disorganised telehealth adoption in the study regions provides insight into wider environmental drivers affecting telehealth uptake. For telehealth to become a workable service delivery mode following COVID-19, stewardship and culture shifts are required, including policy development, technical support, and resources to support clinical teams. Telehealth may address growing service demand by improving interfaces with primary care and providing timely access to specialist input.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Benjamin Werkmeister et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Werkmeister</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3273-0345</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Te Herenga Waka-Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychological Medicine Te Whatu Ora-Health New Zealand, Wellington, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychological Medicine University of Otago-Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haase</LastName><ForeName>Anne M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8556-2165</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Te Herenga Waka-Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fleming</LastName><ForeName>Theresa</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5174-9359</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Te Herenga Waka-Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Officer</LastName><ForeName>Tara N</ForeName><Initials>TN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2322-2525</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing Midwifery and Health Practice Te Herenga Waka-Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Egypt</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Telemed Appl</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101467196</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1687-6415</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinician</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">interpretive description</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mixed methods research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telehealth</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The lead author worked in the outpatient services within the study region, as a psychiatric registrar (physician training in psychiatry).</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2024/8835933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 
World Mental Health Report: Transforming Mental Health for All
. World Health Organization; 2022.  
 https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/356119/9789240049338-eng.pdf?sequence=1
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health. 
Office of the Director of Mental Health and Addiction Services: Annual Report 2017
. Ministry of Health; 2019.  
 https://www.health.govt.nz/publication/office-director-mental-health-and-addiction-services-annual-report-2017
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Te Pou o te Whakaaro Nui. 
Workforce stocktake
. Te Pou; 2018.  
 https://mentalhealth.inquiry.govt.nz/assets/Summary-reports/Te-Pou-Stocktake.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>New Zealand Government. 
He Ara Oranga: Report of the Government Inquiry into Mental Health and Addiction
. Government Inquiry into Mental Health and Addiction; 2018.  
 https://mentalhealth.inquiry.govt.nz/assets/Summary-reports/He-Ara-Oranga.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Druss B. G., Cohen A. N., Brister T., et al. Supporting the mental health workforce during and after COVID-19. Psychiatric Services . 2021;72(10):1222–1224. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.202000509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202000509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33882690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams R., Ryan T., Wood E. Understanding the factors that affect retention within the mental health nursing workforce: a systematic review and thematic synthesis. International Journal of Mental Health Nursing . 2021;30(6):1476–1497. doi: 10.1111/inm.12904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/inm.12904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34184394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendrickson R. C., Slevin R. A., Hoerster K. D., et al. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental health, occupational functioning, and professional retention among health care workers and first responders. Journal of General Internal Medicine . 2022;37(2):397–408. doi: 10.1007/s11606-021-07252-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-021-07252-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8675543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34918181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paris M., Hoge M. A. Burnout in the mental health workforce: a review. The Journal of Behavioral Health Services &amp; Research . 2010;37(4):519–528. doi: 10.1007/s11414-009-9202-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11414-009-9202-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20013066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Busaidi I. S., Martin M. The transition to a "virtual practice" in primary care during the COVID-19 pandemic: experience from one medical centre in New Zealand. The New Zealand Medical Journal . 2020;133(1520):91–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32994597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay G., Meltzer A. Let us unite against COVID-19 – a New Zealand perspective. Irish Journal of Psychological Medicine . 2020;37(3):218–221. doi: 10.1017/ipm.2020.44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/ipm.2020.44</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7322157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32404225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development. The COVID-19 pandemic and the future of telemedicine . OECD Publishing; 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1787/ac8b0a27-en</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaver J. The state of telehealth before and after the COVID-19 pandemic. Primary Care . 2022;49(4):517–530. doi: 10.1016/j.pop.2022.04.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pop.2022.04.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9035352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36357058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bower M., Smout S., Donohoe-Bales A., et al. A hidden pandemic? An umbrella review of global evidence on mental health in the time of COVID-19. Frontiers in Psychiatry . 2023;14 doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1107560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1107560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10032377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36970258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummings J. R., Zhang X., Gandré C., et al. Challenges facing mental health systems arising from the COVID-19 pandemic: evidence from 14 European and North American countries. Health Policy . 2023;136, article 104878 doi: 10.1016/j.healthpol.2023.104878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.healthpol.2023.104878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37611521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santomauro D. F., Mantilla Herrera A. M., Shadid J., et al. Global prevalence and burden of depressive and anxiety disorders in 204 countries and territories in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Lancet . 2021;398(10312):1700–1712. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02143-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02143-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34634250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vadivel R., Shoib S., Halabi S. E., et al. Mental health in the post-COVID-19 era: challenges and the way forward. General Psychiatry . 2021;34(1, article e100424) doi: 10.1136/gpsych-2020-100424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/gpsych-2020-100424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7875255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33644689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Officer T. N., Tait M., McBride-Henry K., Burnett L., Werkmeister B. J. Mental health client experiences of telehealth in Aotearoa New Zealand during the COVID-19 pandemic: Lessons and implications. JMIR Formative Research . 2023;7, article e47008 doi: 10.2196/47008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/47008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10257105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37234041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werkmeister B. J., Haase A. M., Fleming T., Officer T. N. Experiences of the COVID-19 lockdown and telehealth in Aotearoa New Zealand: lessons and insights from mental health clinicians. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health . 2023;20(6):p. 4791. doi: 10.3390/ijerph20064791.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20064791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10049248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36981699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jennett P. A., Hall L. A., Hailey D., et al. The socio-economic impact of telehealth: a systematic review. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare . 2003;9(6):311–320. doi: 10.1258/135763303771005207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1258/135763303771005207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14680514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterton M. L., Marangu E., Clancy E. M., et al. Telehealth service delivery in an Australian regional mental health service during COVID-19: a mixed methods analysis. International Journal of Mental Health Systems . 2022;16(1):p. 43. doi: 10.1186/s13033-022-00553-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13033-022-00553-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9388972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35986332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambert D., Gale J., Hartley D., Croll Z., Hansen A. Understanding the business case for telemental health in rural communities. The Journal of Behavioral Health Services &amp; Research . 2016;43(3):366–379. doi: 10.1007/s11414-015-9490-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11414-015-9490-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26695645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoud H., Vogt E. L., Dahdouh R., Raymond M. L. Using continuous quality improvement to design and implement a telepsychiatry program in rural Illinois. Psychiatric Services . 2020;71(8):860–863. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.201900231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.201900231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32290807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swanson C. L., Trestman R. L. Rural assertive community treatment and telepsychiatry. Journal of Psychiatric Practice . 2018;24(4):269–273. doi: 10.1097/PRA.0000000000000313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PRA.0000000000000313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30427810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drago A., Winding T., Antypa N. Videoconferencing in psychiatry, a meta-analysis of assessment and treatment. European Psychiatry . 2016;36:29–37. doi: 10.1016/j.eurpsy.2016.03.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eurpsy.2016.03.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27311105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koblauch H., Reinhardt S. M., Lissau W., Jensen P.-L. The effect of telepsychiatric modalities on reduction of readmissions in psychiatric settings: a systematic review. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare . 2018;24(1):31–36. doi: 10.1177/1357633X16670285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1357633X16670285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5768249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27663681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kummervold P. E., Johnsen J.-A. K., Skrovseth S. O., Wynn R. Using noninferiority tests to evaluate telemedicine and e-health services: systematic review. Journal of Medical Internet Research . 2012;14(5):p. e132. doi: 10.2196/jmir.2169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.2169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3510769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23022989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunjaya A. P., Chris A., Novianti D. Efficacy, patient-doctor relationship, costs and benefits of utilizing telepsychiatry for the management of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD): a systematic review. Trends in Psychiatry and Psychotherapy . 2020;42(1):102–110. doi: 10.1590/2237-6089-2019-0024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/2237-6089-2019-0024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32321088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carretier E., Bastide M., Lachal J., Moro M. R. Evaluation of the rapid implementation of telehealth during the COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative study among adolescents and their parents. European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry . 2023;32(6):963–973. doi: 10.1007/s00787-022-02108-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-022-02108-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9652600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36370315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felker B. L., McGinn M. M., Shearer E. M., et al. Implementation of a telemental health training program across a mental health department. Telemedicine Reports . 2021;2(1):26–31. doi: 10.1089/tmr.2020.0011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/tmr.2020.0011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7869919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33575684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hensel J., Graham R., Isaak C., Ahmed N., Sareen J., Bolton J. A novel emergency telepsychiatry program in a Canadian urban setting: identifying and addressing perceived barriers for successful implementation: un nouveau programme de télépsychiatrie d'urgence en milieu urbain canadien: identifier et aborder les obstacles perçus d'une mise en oeuvre réussie. The Canadian Journal of Psychiatry . 2020;65(8):559–567. doi: 10.1177/0706743719900465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0706743719900465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7492888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31969011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lynch D. A., Stefancic A., Cabassa L. J., Medalia A. Client, clinician, and administrator factors associated with the successful acceptance of a telehealth comprehensive recovery service: a mixed methods study. Psychiatry Research . 2021;300, article 113871 doi: 10.1016/j.psychres.2021.113871.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2021.113871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8141021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33887517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uscher-Pines L., Sousa J., Raja P., Mehrotra A., Barnett M. L., Huskamp H. A. Suddenly becoming a "virtual doctor": experiences of psychiatrists transitioning to telemedicine During the COVID-19 pandemic. Psychiatric Services . 2020;71(11):1143–1150. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.202000250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202000250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7606640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32933411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yellowlees P., Nakagawa K., Pakyurek M., Hanson A., Elder J., Kales H. C. Rapid conversion of an outpatient psychiatric clinic to a 100% virtual telepsychiatry clinic in response to COVID-19. Psychiatric Services . 2020;71(7):749–752. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.202000230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202000230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32460683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bright A.-M., Doody O. Mental health service users' experiences of telehealth interventions facilitated during the COVID-19 pandemic and their relevance to nursing: an integrative review. Journal of Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing . 2023;30(6):1114–1129. doi: 10.1111/jpm.12943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jpm.12943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37278201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekori-Domachevsky E., Matalon N., Mayer Y., et al. Internalizing symptoms impede adolescents' ability to transition from in-person to online mental health services during the 2019 coronavirus disease pandemic. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare . 2023;29(9):725–730. doi: 10.1177/1357633x211021293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1357633x211021293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34328367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puspitasari A. J., Heredia D., Coombes B. J., et al. Feasibility and initial outcomes of a group-based teletherapy psychiatric day program for adults with serious mental illness: open, nonrandomized trial in the context of COVID-19. JMIR Mental Health . 2021;8(3, article e25542) doi: 10.2196/25542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/25542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7954114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33651706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Villa E., Rozatkar A. R., Kumar M., et al. Cross cultural and global uses of a digital mental health app: results of focus groups with clinicians, patients and family members in India and the United States. Global Mental Health . 2021;8:p. e30. doi: 10.1017/gmh.2021.28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/gmh.2021.28</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8392688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34512999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vera San Juan N., Shah P., Schlief M., et al. Service user experiences and views regarding telemental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: a co-produced framework analysis. PLoS One . 2021;16(9, article e0257270) doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0257270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0257270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8445423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34529705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebbert J. O., Ramar P., Tulledge-Scheitel S. M., et al. Patient preferences for telehealth services in a large multispecialty practice. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare . 2023;29(4):298–303. doi: 10.1177/1357633x20980302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1357633x20980302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33461397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goetter E. M., Iaccarino M. A., Tanev K. S., Furbish K. E., Xu B., Faust K. A. Telemental health uptake in an outpatient clinic for veterans during the COVID-19 pandemic and assessment of patient and provider attitudes. Professional Psychology: Research and Practice . 2022;53(2):151–159. doi: 10.1037/pro0000437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/pro0000437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagi K., Kurokawa S., Takamiya A., et al. Telepsychiatry versus face-to-face treatment: systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. The British Journal of Psychiatry . 2023;223(3):407–414. doi: 10.1192/bjp.2023.86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.2023.86</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10895502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37655816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee H., Palmer J., Mullick P., Kiely C. Patient experience with telehealth service in a mental health setting. Archives of Psychiatric Nursing . 2023;43:150–152. doi: 10.1016/j.apnu.2023.03.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apnu.2023.03.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10008765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37032009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Link K., Christians S., Hoffmann W., Grabe H. J., van den Berg N. Telemedicine treatment of patients with mental disorders during and after the first COVID-19 pandemic lockdown in Germany – an observational study on feasibility and patient satisfaction. BMC Psychiatry . 2023;23(1):p. 654. doi: 10.1186/s12888-023-05140-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-023-05140-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10478407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37670236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikh Y., Ali A., Khasati A., et al. Benefits and challenges of video consulting for mental health diagnosis and follow-up: a qualitative study in community care. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health . 2023;20(3):p. 2595. doi: 10.3390/ijerph20032595.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20032595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9915222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36767957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torales J., Vilallba-Arias J., Bogado J. A., et al. Satisfaction with telepsychiatry during the COVID-19 pandemic: patients’ and psychiatrists’ report from a university hospital. International Journal of Social Psychiatry . 2023;69(1):156–160. doi: 10.1177/00207640211070762.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/00207640211070762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9936176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34991382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greer B., Robotham D., Simblett S., Curtis H., Griffiths H., Wykes T. Digital exclusion among mental health service users: qualitative investigation. Journal of Medical Internet Research . 2019;21(1, article e11696) doi: 10.2196/11696.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/11696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6329420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30626564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liberati E., Richards N., Parker J., et al. Remote care for mental health: qualitative study with service users, carers and staff during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMJ Open . 2021;11(4, article e049210) doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-049210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-049210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8068948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33888531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werkmeister B. J., Haase A. M., Fleming T., Officer T. N. Global implications from the rise and recession of telehealth in Aotearoa New Zealand mental health services during the COVID-19 pandemic: mixed methods study. JMIR Formative Research . 2023;7, article e50486 doi: 10.2196/50486.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/50486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10519279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37738075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>New Zealand Government. 
The future of health
. Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet; 2022.  
 https://www.futureofhealth.govt.nz/
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrett A. M., Hogreve J., Brüggen E. C. Coping with governmental restrictions: the relationship between stay-at-home orders, resilience, and functional, social, mental, physical, and financial well-being. Frontiers in Psychology . 2021;11 doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2020.577972.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2020.577972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7838344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33519594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tull M. T., Edmonds K. A., Scamaldo K. M., Richmond J. R., Rose J. P., Gratz K. L. Psychological outcomes associated with stay-at-home orders and the perceived impact of COVID-19 on daily life. Psychiatry Research . 2020;289, article 113098 doi: 10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7252159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32434092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorne S., Kirkham S. R., MacDonald-Emes J. Interpretive description: a noncategorical qualitative alternative for developing nursing knowledge. Research in Nursing and Health . 1997;20(2):169–177. doi: 10.1002/(SICI)1098-240X(199704)20:2&lt;169::AID-NUR9&gt;3.0.CO;2-I.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-240X(199704)20:2&lt;169::AID-NUR9&gt;3.0.CO;2-I</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9100747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorne S., Kirkham S. R., O'Flynn-Magee K. The analytic challenge in interpretive description. International Journal of Qualitative Methods . 2004;3(1):1–11. doi: 10.1177/160940690400300101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/160940690400300101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorne S. Interpretive Description . 1st. Left Coast Press; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorne S. Interpretive Description: Qualitative Research for Applied Practice . 2nd. Taylor &amp; Francis; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanos P., Ziedonis D. The patient-oriented clinician-researcher: advantages and challenges of being a double agent. Psychiatric Services . 2006;57(2):249–253. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.57.2.249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.57.2.249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1383049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16452704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt M. R. Strengths and challenges in the use of interpretive description: reflections arising from a study of the moral experience of health professionals in humanitarian work. Qualitative Health Research . 2009;19(9):1284–1292. doi: 10.1177/1049732309344612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1049732309344612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19690208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolan S., Nowell L., Moules N. J. Interpretive description in applied mixed methods research: exploring issues of fit, purpose, process, context, and design. Nursing Inquiry . 2023;30(3, article e12542) doi: 10.1111/nin.12542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nin.12542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36464974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V., Clarke V.  
Thematic Analysis: A Practical Guide
. 1st. Sage Publications; 2021.  
 https://uk.sagepub.com/en-gb/eur/thematic-analysis/book248481
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mays N., Pope C. Qualitative research: rigour and qualitative research. British Medical Journal . 1995;311(6997):109–112. doi: 10.1136/bmj.311.6997.109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.311.6997.109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2550154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7613363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>New Zealand Government. 
New Zealand COVID-19 alert levels summary
. New Zealand Government; 2021.  
 https://covid19.govt.nz/about-our-covid-19-response/history-of-the-covid-19-alert-system/#printable-resources
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>New Zealand Government. Mental Health (Compulsory Assessment and Treatment) Act 1992. 2022.  
 https://www.legislation.govt.nz/act/public/1992/0046/latest/whole.html
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centre for Community Child Health. Policy Brief . Melbourne, Australia: Murdoch Children's Research Institute; 2020. Pushing the boundaries: using telehealth to improve regional access and care.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C. K., Palfrey A., Shreck E., et al. Implementation of telemental health (TMH) psychological services for rural veterans at the VA New York Harbor Healthcare System. Psychological Services . 2021;18(1):1–10. doi: 10.1037/ser0000323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/ser0000323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30742470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kannarkat J. T., Smith N. N., McLeod-Bryant S. A. Mobilization of telepsychiatry in response to COVID-19–moving toward 21st century access to care. Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research . 2020;47(4):489–491. doi: 10.1007/s10488-020-01044-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10488-020-01044-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7180652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32333227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neufeld J., Case R. Walk-in telemental health clinics improve access and efficiency: a 2-year follow-up analysis. Telemedicine and e-Health . 2013;19(12):938–941. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2013.0076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/tmj.2013.0076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3850444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24050609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health. 
Office of the Director of Mental Health and Addiction Services Annual Report 2018 and 2019
. Ministry of Health; 2021.  
 https://www.health.govt.nz/publication/office-director-mental-health-and-addiction-services-annual-report-2018-and-2019
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moitra M., Owens S., Hailemariam M., et al. Global mental health: where we are and where we are going. Current Psychiatry Reports . 2023;25(7):301–311. doi: 10.1007/s11920-023-01426-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11920-023-01426-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10230139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37256471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Te Pou o te Whakaaro Nui. 
DHB Mental Health and Addiction Employees: 2019 Profile
. Te Pou; 2020.  
 https://www.tepou.co.nz/resources/dhb-mental-health-and-addiction-employees-2019-profile
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spagnolo J., Beauséjour M., Fleury M.-J., et al. Perceptions on barriers, facilitators, and recommendations related to mental health service delivery during the COVID-19 pandemic in Quebec, Canada: a qualitative descriptive study. BMC Primary Care . 2022;23(1):p. 32. doi: 10.1186/s12875-022-01634-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12875-022-01634-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8860461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35189813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore T., Sutton K., Maybery D. Rural mental health workforce difficulties: a management perspective. Rural and Remote Health . 2010;10(4):85–94. doi: 10.22605/RRH1519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22605/RRH1519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20932079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavlova A., Paine S.-J., Sinclair S., O'Callaghan A., Consedine N. S. Working in value-discrepant environments inhibits clinicians’ ability to provide compassion and reduces well-being: a cross-sectional study. Journal of Internal Medicine . 2023;293(6):704–723. doi: 10.1111/joim.13615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joim.13615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36843313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheather J., Slattery D. The great resignation—how do we support and retain staff already stretched to their limit? British Medical Journal . 2021;375, article n2533 doi: 10.1136/bmj.n2533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n2533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34663568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sibeoni J., Manolios E., Costa-Drolon E., Meunier J.-P., Verneuil L., Revah-Levy A. Clinical practice during the COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative study among child and adolescent psychiatrists across the world. Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Mental Health . 2021;15(1):p. 68. doi: 10.1186/s13034-021-00417-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13034-021-00417-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8608359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34809693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 
Mental Health and Psychosocial Considerations During the COVID-19 Outbreak, 18 March 2020
. World Health Organization; 2020.  
 https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/331490
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hames J. L., Bell D. J., Perez-Lima L. M., et al. Navigating uncharted waters: considerations for training clinics in the rapid transition to telepsychology and telesupervision during COVID-19. Journal of Psychotherapy Integration . 2020;30(2):348–365. doi: 10.1037/int0000224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/int0000224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snowdon D. A., Sargent M., Williams C. M., Maloney S., Caspers K., Taylor N. F. Effective clinical supervision of allied health professionals: a mixed methods study. BMC Health Services Research . 2020;20(1):p. 2. doi: 10.1186/s12913-019-4873-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-019-4873-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6937808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31888611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Browne D., Roy S., Phillips M., Shamon S., Stephenson M. Supporting patient and clinician mental health during COVID-19: via trauma-informed interdisciplinary systems. Canadian Family Physician . 2020;66(7):e190–e192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7365150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32675108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesan B., Al-Jumaily A., Fong K. N. K., Prasad P., Meena S. K., Tong R. K.-Y. Impact of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak quarantine, isolation, and lockdown policies on mental health and suicide. Frontiers in Psychiatry . 2021;12 doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2021.565190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.565190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8085354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33935817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panchal U., Salazar de Pablo G., Franco M., et al. The impact of COVID-19 lockdown on child and adolescent mental health: systematic review. European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry . 2023;32(7):1151–1177. doi: 10.1007/s00787-021-01856-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-021-01856-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8371430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34406494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Every-Palmer S., Jenkins M., Gendall P., et al. Psychological distress, anxiety, family violence, suicidality, and wellbeing in New Zealand during the COVID-19 lockdown: a cross-sectional study. PLoS One . 2020;15(11, article e0241658) doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0241658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0241658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7641386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33147259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Officer T. N., Imlach F., McKinlay E., et al. COVID-19 pandemic lockdown and wellbeing: experiences from Aotearoa New Zealand in 2020. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health . 2022;19(4):p. 2269. doi: 10.3390/ijerph19042269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19042269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8871666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35206457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prickett K. C., Fletcher M., Chapple S., Doan N., Smith C. Life in Lockdown: The Economic and Social Effect of Lockdown During Alert Level 4 in New Zealand . Victoria University of Wellington; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanielu R., Ika A.  
The State of our Communities 2020 (3)
 Social Policy and Parliamentary Unit; 2020.  
 https://www.salvationarmy.org.nz/article/state-our-communities-report-2020
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoenfelder Gonzalez E., Jungbluth N., McCarty C. A., Hilt R. Barriers to increasing access to brief pediatric mental health treatment from primary care. Psychiatric Services . 2022;73(2):235–238. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.202000457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202000457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34126777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frueh B. Solving mental healthcare access problems in the twenty-first century. Australian Psychologist . 2015;50(4):304–306. doi: 10.1111/ap.12140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ap.12140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahtta D., Daher M., Lee M. T., Sayani S., Shishehbor M., Virani S. S. Promise and perils of telehealth in the current era. Current Cardiology Reports . 2021;23(9):p. 115. doi: 10.1007/s11886-021-01544-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11886-021-01544-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8283748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34269884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uscher-Pines L., Rudin R. S. Lessons learned from the MAVEN project pilot: using physician volunteers to increase access to care via telehealth. Rand Health Quarterly . 2020;9(1):p. 9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7371357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32742751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hensel J. M., Ellard K., Koltek M., Wilson G., Sareen J. Digital health solutions for indigenous mental well-being. Current Psychiatry Reports . 2019;21(8):p. 68. doi: 10.1007/s11920-019-1056-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11920-019-1056-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6602981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31263971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rantanen T., Gluschkoff K., Silvennoinen P., Heponiemi T. The associations between mental health problems and attitudes toward web-based health and social care services: evidence from a Finnish population-based study. Journal of Medical Internet Research . 2021;23(9, article e28066) doi: 10.2196/28066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/28066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8493458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34546184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Citizens Advice Bureaux New Zealand. Face to face with digital exclusion: a CAB spotlight report into the impacts of digital public services on inclusion and wellbeing. 2020.  
 https://www.cab.org.nz/assets/Documents/Face-to-Face-with-Digital-Exclusion-/9c5f26012e/Face-to-face-with-Digital-Exclusion.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Digital Inclusion Research Group. Digital New Zealanders: the pulse of our nation–a report to MBIE and DIA. 2017.  
 https://www.mbie.govt.nz/dmsdocument/3228-digital-new-zealanders-the-pulse-of-our-nation-pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimes A., White D. Digital inclusion and wellbeing in New Zealand . Wellington, New Zealand: Motu Economic and Public Policy Research Trust; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics New Zealand. 
Transport and communications in New Zealand
. StatsNZ; 2015.  
 https://www.stats.govt.nz/infographics/transport-and-communications-in-new-zealand
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pihama L., Cameron N., Te Nana R.  
Historical trauma and whānau violence
. New Zealand Family Violence Clearinghouse. (Issues Paper 15); 2019.  
 https://nzfvc.org.nz/sites/default/files/NZFVC-Issues-Paper-15-historical-trauma_0.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pihama L., Reynolds P., Smith C., Reid J., Smith L. T., Nana R. T. Positioning historical trauma theory within Aotearoa New Zealand. AlterNative: An International Journal of Indigenous Peoples . 2014;10(3):248–262. doi: 10.1177/117718011401000304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/117718011401000304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith C., Tinirau R.  
He Rau murimuri aroha: wāhine Māori insights into historical trauma and healing
. Te Atawhai o Te Ao: Independent Māori Institute for Environment &amp; Health; 2019.  
 https://teatawhai.maori.nz/resources/he-rau-murimuri-aroha/
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crawford A., Serhal E. Digital health equity and COVID-19: the innovation curve cannot reinforce the social gradient of health. Journal of Medical Internet Research . 2020;22(6, article e19361) doi: 10.2196/19361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/19361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7268667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32452816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmons S., Alverson D., Poropatich R., D’Iorio J., DeVany M., Doarn C. R. Applying telehealth in natural and anthropogenic disasters. Telemedicine and e-Health . 2008;14(9):968–971. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2008.0117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/tmj.2008.0117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19035809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor A., Caffery L. J., Gesesew H. A., et al. How Australian health care services adapted to telehealth during the COVID-19 pandemic: a survey of telehealth professionals. Frontiers in Public Health . 2021;9 doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2021.648009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.648009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7952432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33718325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T., Rosen R., Shaw S. E., et al. Planning and evaluating remote consultation services: a new conceptual framework incorporating complexity and practical ethics. Frontiers in Digital Health . 2021;3 doi: 10.3389/fdgth.2021.726095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.726095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8521880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34713199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams R. B., Nelson V. R., Holtz B. E. Barriers for telemedicine use among nonusers at the beginning of the pandemic. Telemedicine Reports . 2021;2(1):211–216. doi: 10.1089/tmr.2021.0022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/tmr.2021.0022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9049802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35720746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haque S. N. Telehealth beyond COVID-19. Psychiatric Services . 2021;72(1):100–103. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.202000368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202000368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32811284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw S. E., Hughes G., Wherton J., et al. Achieving spread, scale up and sustainability of video consulting services during the COVID-19 pandemic? Findings from a comparative case study of policy implementation in England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland. Frontiers in Digital Health . 2021;3 doi: 10.3389/fdgth.2021.754319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.754319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8720935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34988546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royal Australian &amp; New Zealand College of Psychiatrists. Professional Practice Guideline 19, Telehealth in Psychiatry . 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman R. E., Boggs K. M., Zachrison K. S., et al. National study of telepsychiatry use in U.S. emergency departments. Psychiatric Services . 2020;71(6):540–546. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.201900237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.201900237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32019430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman R. E., Zhong C., Bahar P., et al. U.S. emergency department telepsychiatry use in 2019. Telemedicine and e-Health . 2023;29(3):366–375. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2022.0191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/tmj.2022.0191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10024260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35867053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rains L. S., Dalton-Locke C., Landau S., Needle J. J., Johnson S. Variations in the uptake of telemental health technologies in community and crisis mental health services during the early pandemic: a survey of mental health professionals in the UK. BMC Psychiatry . 2022;22(1):p. 776. doi: 10.1186/s12888-022-04385-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-022-04385-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9733196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36494646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roddy M. K., Chen P., Jeffery A. D., et al. Telemental health in emergency care settings: a qualitative analysis of considerations for sustainability and spread. Academic Emergency Medicine . 2023;30(4):368–378. doi: 10.1111/acem.14682.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/acem.14682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10983773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36786633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGinn M. M., Roussev M. S., Shearer E. M., McCann R. A., Rojas S. M., Felker B. L. Recommendations for using clinical video telehealth with patients at high risk for suicide. Psychiatric Clinics . 2019;42(4):587–595. doi: 10.1016/j.psc.2019.08.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psc.2019.08.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31672209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iturralde E., Fazzolari L., Shia M., et al. Closing the care gap for people with severe and persistent mental illness: collaborative care, telehealth, and clinical pharmacy. NEJM Catalyst . 2022;3(5) doi: 10.1056/CAT.21.0417.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/CAT.21.0417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9788801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36569369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joergensen S., Lee K., Harnow Klausen S., Nedenskov Petersen E., Nørgaard B. The experience of telehealth and user involvement for patients with mental illness. International Journal of Integrated Care . 2022;22(s3):p. 293. doi: 10.5334/ijic.ICIC22293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5334/ijic.ICIC22293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gros D. F., Veronee K., Strachan M., Ruggiero K. J., Acierno R. Managing suicidality in home-based telehealth. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare . 2011;17(6):332–335. doi: 10.1258/jtt.2011.101207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1258/jtt.2011.101207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21844180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zalewski M., Walton C. J., Rizvi S. L., et al. Lessons learned conducting dialectical behavior therapy via telehealth in the age of COVID-19. Cognitive and Behavioral Practice . 2021;28(4):573–587. doi: 10.1016/j.cbpra.2021.02.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cbpra.2021.02.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8488181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34629837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health. Repealing and replacing the Mental Health Act. 2024.  
 https://www.health.govt.nz/our-work/mental-health-and-addiction/mental-health-legislation/repealing-and-replacing-mental-health-act
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrer L., Batterham P., Gulliver A., et al. The factors associated with telehealth use and avoidance during the COVID-19 Pandemic: Longitudinal Survey. Journal of Medical Internet Research . 2023;25, article e43798 doi: 10.2196/43798.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/43798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9947771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36649254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valentine L. M., Donofry S. D., Sexton M. B. Demographic and psychiatric predictors of engagement in psychotherapy services conducted via clinical video telehealth. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare . 2020;26(1-2):113–118. doi: 10.1177/1357633X18801713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1357633X18801713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30261806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guillen A. G., Reddy M., Saadat S., Chakravarthy B. Utilization of telehealth solutions for patients with opioid use disorder using buprenorphine: a scoping review. Telemedicine and e-Health . 2022;28(6):761–767. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2021.0308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/tmj.2021.0308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34714172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mark T. L., Treiman K., Padwa H., Henretty K., Tzeng J., Gilbert M. Addiction treatment and telehealth: review of efficacy and provider insights during the COVID-19 pandemic. Psychiatric Services . 2022;73(5):484–491. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.202100088.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202100088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34644125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anthony B., Jr. Implications of telehealth and digital care solutions during COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative literature review. Informatics for Health and Social Care . 2021;46(1):68–83. doi: 10.1080/17538157.2020.1839467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/17538157.2020.1839467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33251894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jonasdottir S. K., Thordardottir I., Jonsdottir T. Health professionals’ perspective towards challenges and opportunities of telehealth service provision: a scoping review. International Journal of Medical Informatics . 2022;167, article 104862 doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2022.104862.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2022.104862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36179598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snoswell C., Smith A. C., Scuffham P. A., Whitty J. A. Economic evaluation strategies in telehealth: obtaining a more holistic valuation of telehealth interventions. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare . 2017;23(9):792–796. doi: 10.1177/1357633x16671407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1357633x16671407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27789615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>