<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39312524</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2767-3375</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PLOS global public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLOS Glob Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Data-driven nexus between malaria incidence and World Bank indicators in the Mekong River during 2000-2022.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0003764</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0003764</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0003764</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pgph.0003764</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The increase in hydro dams in the Mekong River amidst the prevalence of multidrug-resistant malaria in Cambodia has raised concerns about global public health. Political conflicts during Covid-19 pandemic led cross-border movements of malaria cases from Myanmar and caused health care burden in Thailand. While previous publications used climatic indicators for predicting mosquito-borne diseases, this research used globally recognizable World Bank indicators to find the most impactful indicators related with malaria and shed light on the predictability of mosquito-borne diseases. The World Bank datasets of the World Development Indicators and Climate Change Knowledge Portal contain 1494 time series indicators. They were stepwise screened by Pearson and Distance correlation. The sets of five and four contain respectively 19 and 149 indicators highly correlated with malaria incidence which were found similarly among five and four GMS countries. Living areas, ages, career, income, technology accessibility, infrastructural facilities, unclean fuel use, tobacco smoking, and health care deficiency have affected malaria incidence. Tonle Sap Lake, the largest freshwater lake in Southeast Asia, could contribute to the larval habitat. Seven groups of indicator topics containing 92 indicators with not-null datapoints were analyzed by regression models, including Multiple Linear, Ridge, Lasso, and Elastic Net models to choose 7 crucial features for malaria prediction via Long Short Time Memory network. The indicator of people using at least basic sanitation services and people practicing open defecation were health factors had most impacts on regression models. Malaria incidence could be predicted by one indicator to reach the optimal mean absolute error which was lower than 10 malaria cases (per 1,000 population at risk) in the Long Short Time Memory model. However, public health crises caused by political problems should be analyzed by political indexes for more precise predictions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Phuong Hoang Ngoc Nguyen. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nguyen</LastName><ForeName>Phuong Hoang Ngoc</ForeName><Initials>PHN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6397-7562</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Biotechnology and Biotransformation, Faculty of Biology and Biotechnology, University of Science, Vietnam National University of Ho Chi Minh City (VNUHCM-US), Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLOS Glob Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918283779606676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2767-3375</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39312524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0003764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PGPH-D-24-00208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Factsheet about vector-borne diseases. 2020.  [cited 2 Mar 2020]. Available: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/vector-borne-diseases</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. World malaria report
2023. Available: https://www.who.int/teams/global-malaria-programme/reports/world-malaria-report-2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dell’Acqua R, Fabrizio C, Di Gennaro F, Lo Caputo S, Saracino A, Menegon M, et al.. An intricate case of multidrug resistant Plasmodium falciparum isolate imported from Cambodia. Malaria Journal. 2017;16: 149. doi: 10.1186/s12936-017-1795-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-017-1795-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5391556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28410610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Fact sheet about malaria. 2023.  [cited 1 Feb 2023]. Available: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/malaria</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan SJ, Carlson CJ, Mordecai EA, Johnson LR. Global expansion and redistribution of Aedes-borne virus transmission risk with climate change. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2019;13: e0007213. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0007213</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6438455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30921321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebi KL, Nealon J. Dengue in a changing climate. Environmental Research. 2016;151: 115–123. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2016.07.026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2016.07.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27475051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Factsheet about dengue and severe dengue. 2023.  [cited 30 Jan 2023]. Available: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/dengue-and-severe-dengue</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziegler AD, Petney TN, Grundy-Warr C, Andrews RH, Baird IG, Wasson RJ, et al.. Dams and Disease Triggers on the Lower Mekong River. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2013;7: e2166. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0002166</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3682813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23853695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center Stimson. 2020 Status of Lower Mekong Mainstream and Tributary Dams. 2020.  [cited 24 Sep 2023]. Available: https://www.stimson.org/2020/2020-status-of-lower-mekong-mainstream-and-tributary-dams/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Abri SS, Abdel-Hady DM, Al Mahrooqi SS, Al-Kindi HS, Al-Jardani AK, Al-Abaidani IS. Epidemiology of travel-associated infections in Oman 1999–2013: A retrospective analysis. Travel Med Infect Dis. 2015;13: 388–393. doi: 10.1016/j.tmaid.2015.08.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2015.08.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7110695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26363628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lühken R, Brattig N, Becker N. Introduction of invasive mosquito species into Europe and prospects for arbovirus transmission and vector control in an era of globalization. Infect Dis Poverty. 2023;12: 109. doi: 10.1186/s40249-023-01167-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40249-023-01167-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10687857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38037192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imperato PJ. The Convergence of a Virus, Mosquitoes, and Human Travel in Globalizing the Zika Epidemic. J Community Health. 2016;41: 674–679. doi: 10.1007/s10900-016-0177-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10900-016-0177-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26969497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacific Asia Travel Association. PATA: Mekong tourism grows 13%—TTR Weekly.
2018.  [cited 14 Feb 2023]. Available: https://www.ttrweekly.com/site/2018/06/pata-mekong-tourism-grows-13/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawpoolsri S, Kaewkungwal J, Khamsiriwatchara A, Sovann L, Sreng B, Phommasack B, et al.. Data quality and timeliness of outbreak reporting system among countries in Greater Mekong subregion: Challenges for international data sharing. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2018;12: e0006425. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0006425</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0006425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5937798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29694372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vannavong N, Seidu R, Stenström T-A, Dada N, Overgaard HJ. Effects of socio-demographic characteristics and household water management on Aedes aegypti production in suburban and rural villages in Laos and Thailand. Parasites &amp; Vectors. 2017;10: 170. doi: 10.1186/s13071-017-2107-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13071-017-2107-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5381031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28376893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinszer K, Verma AD, Charland K, Brewer TF, Brownstein JS, Sun Z, et al.. A scoping review of malaria forecasting: past work and future directions. BMJ Open. 2012;2: e001992. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001992</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3533056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23180505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mai ST, Phi HT, Abubakar A, Kilpatrick P, Nguyen HQV, Vandierendonck H. Dengue Fever: From Extreme Climates to Outbreak Prediction. 2022 IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM). 2022. pp. 1083–1088. doi: 10.1109/ICDM54844.2022.00135</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ICDM54844.2022.00135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tangena J-AA, Thammavong P, Wilson AL, Brey PT, Lindsay SW. Risk and Control of Mosquito-Borne Diseases in Southeast Asian Rubber Plantations. Trends in Parasitology. 2016;32: 402–415. doi: 10.1016/j.pt.2016.01.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2016.01.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26907494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham NTT, Nguyen CT, Vu HH. Assessing and modelling vulnerability to dengue in the Mekong Delta of Vietnam by geospatial and time-series approaches. Environ Res. 2020;186: 109545. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2020.109545</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.109545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32361079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hochreiter S, Schmidhuber J. Long Short-Term Memory. Neural Computation. 1997;9: 1735–1780. doi: 10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9377276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamana E, Zhao J, Bai D. Predicting the impact of climate change on the re-emergence of malaria cases in China using LSTMSeq2Seq deep learning model: a modelling and prediction analysis study. BMJ Open. 2022;12: e053922. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-053922</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-053922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8971767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35361642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen V-H, Tuyet-Hanh TT, Mulhall J, Minh HV, Duong TQ, Chien NV, et al.. Deep learning models for forecasting dengue fever based on climate data in Vietnam. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2022;16: e0010509. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0010509</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0010509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9232166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35696432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonald GC. Ridge regression. WIREs Computational Statistics. 2009;1: 93–100. doi: 10.1002/wics.14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/wics.14</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoerl RW. Ridge Regression: A Historical Context. Technometrics. 2020;62: 420–425. doi: 10.1080/00401706.2020.1742207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00401706.2020.1742207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tibshirani R. Regression Shrinkage and Selection via the Lasso. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series B (Methodological). 1996;58: 267–288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bank World. World Development Indicators. 2023.  [cited 14 Feb 2023]. Available: https://datacatalog.worldbank.org/search/dataset/0037712/World-Development-Indicators</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bank World. Climate Change Knowledge Portal. 2023.  [cited 18 Jan 2023]. Available: https://climateknowledgeportal.worldbank.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirch W, editor. Pearson’s Correlation Coefficient. Encyclopedia of Public Health. Dordrecht: Springer Netherlands; 2008. pp. 1090–1091. doi: 10.1007/978-1-4020-5614-7_2569</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4020-5614-7_2569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Székely GJ, Rizzo ML, Bakirov NK. Measuring and testing dependence by correlation of distances. The Annals of Statistics. 2007;35: 2769–2794. doi: 10.1214/009053607000000505</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/009053607000000505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton WL, Amato R, van der Pluijm RW, Jacob CG, Quang HH, Thuy-Nhien NT, et al.. Evolution and expansion of multidrug-resistant malaria in southeast Asia: a genomic epidemiology study. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2019;19: 943–951. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(19)30392-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(19)30392-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6715858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31345709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Servadio JL, Rosenthal SR, Carlson L, Bauer C. Climate patterns and mosquito-borne disease outbreaks in South and Southeast Asia. J Infect Public Health. 2018;11: 566–571. doi: 10.1016/j.jiph.2017.12.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2017.12.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29274851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samal RR, Gupta S, Kumar S. An overview of factors affecting dengue transmission in Asian region and its predictive models. Journal of Applied and Natural Science. 2020;12: 460–470. doi: 10.31018/jans.v12i3.2360</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31018/jans.v12i3.2360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiwanitkit V. An observation on correlation between rainfall and the prevalence of clinical cases of dengue in Thailand. J Vector Borne Dis. 2006;43: 73–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16967819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandfort M, Vantaux A, Kim S, Obadia T, Pepey A, Gardais S, et al.. Forest malaria in Cambodia: the occupational and spatial clustering of Plasmodium vivax and Plasmodium falciparum infection risk in a cross-sectional survey in Mondulkiri province, Cambodia. Malar J. 2020;19: 413. doi: 10.1186/s12936-020-03482-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-020-03482-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7678315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33213471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rani A, Gupta A, Nagpal BN, Mehta SS. Mosquito borne diseases and Sanitation in Ghaziabad district, Uttar Pradesh, India. Int J Mosq Res. 2018;5: 25–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen-Tien T, Bui AN, Ling J, Tran-Hai S, Pham-Thanh L, Bui VN, et al.. The Distribution and Composition of Vector Abundance in Hanoi City, Vietnam: Association with Livestock Keeping and Flavivirus Detection. Viruses. 2021;13: 2291. doi: 10.3390/v13112291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v13112291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8621768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34835097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakobsen F, Nguyen-Tien T, Thanh LP-, Bui VN, Nguyen-Viet H, Hai ST-, et al.. Urban livestock-keeping and dengue in urban and peri-urban Hanoi, Vietnam. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2019;13: e0007774. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0007774</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007774</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6879131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31770384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyagi V, Saikia S, Dey D, Naorem AS, Tyagi V, Chattopadhyay P, et al.. Sewage and Wastewater Management to Combat Different Mosquito Vector Species. In: Kashyap BK, Solanki MK, editors. Current Research Trends and Applications in Waste Management. Singapore: Springer Nature Singapore; 2023. pp. 101–117. doi: 10.1007/978-981-99-3106-4_4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-981-99-3106-4_4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knudsen AB, Slooff R. Vector-borne disease problems in rapid urbanization: new approaches to vector control. Bull World Health Organ. 1992;70: 1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2393336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1568273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham-Duc B, Papa F, Prigent C, Aires F, Biancamaria S, Frappart F. Variations of Surface and Subsurface Water Storage in the Lower Mekong Basin (Vietnam and Cambodia) from Multisatellite Observations. Water. 2019;11: 75. doi: 10.3390/w11010075</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w11010075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark TD, Greenhouse B, Njama-Meya D, Nzarubara B, Maiteki-Sebuguzi C, Staedke SG, et al.. Factors determining the heterogeneity of malaria incidence in children in Kampala, Uganda. J Infect Dis. 2008;198: 393–400. doi: 10.1086/589778</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/589778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18522503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alemu A, Tsegaye W, Golassa L, Abebe G. Urban malaria and associated risk factors in Jimma town, south-west Ethiopia. Malar J. 2011;10: 173. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-10-173</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-10-173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3128012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21699741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corder RM, Paula GA, Pincelli A, Ferreira MU. Statistical modeling of surveillance data to identify correlates of urban malaria risk: A population-based study in the Amazon Basin. PLOS ONE. 2019;14: e0220980. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0220980</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6688813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31398228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma RK, Singh MP, Saha KB, Bharti PK, Jain V, Singh PP, et al.. Socio-economic &amp; household risk factors of malaria in tribal areas of Madhya Pradesh, central India. Indian J Med Res. 2015;141: 567–575. doi: 10.4103/0971-5916.159515</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0971-5916.159515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4510754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26139773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dekker T, Geier M, Cardé RT. Carbon dioxide instantly sensitizes female yellow fever mosquitoes to human skin odours. J Exp Biol. 2005;208: 2963–2972. doi: 10.1242/jeb.01736</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1242/jeb.01736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16043601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacey ES, Ray A, Cardé RT. Close encounters: contributions of carbon dioxide and human skin odour to finding and landing on a host in Aedes aegypti. Physiol Entomol. 2014;39: 60–68. doi: 10.1111/phen.12048</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/phen.12048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4019456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24839345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spanoudis CG, Andreadis SS, Bray DP, Savopoulou-Soultani M, Ignell R. Behavioural response of the house mosquitoes Culex quinquefasciatus and Culex pipiens molestus to avian odours and its reliance on carbon dioxide. Med Vet Entomol. 2020;34: 129–137. doi: 10.1111/mve.12429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/mve.12429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31912522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu F, Ye Z, Baker A, Sun H, Zwiebel LJ. Gene editing reveals obligate and modulatory components of the CO2 receptor complex in the malaria vector mosquito, Anopheles coluzzii. Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology. 2020;127: 103470. doi: 10.1016/j.ibmb.2020.103470</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2020.103470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7704673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32966873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mburu MM, Mweresa CK, Omusula P, Hiscox A, Takken W, Mukabana WR. 2-Butanone as a carbon dioxide mimic in attractant blends for the Afrotropical malaria mosquitoes Anopheles gambiae and Anopheles funestus. Malar J. 2017;16: 351. doi: 10.1186/s12936-017-1998-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-017-1998-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5571623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28836977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babu AN, Niehaus E, Shah S, Unnithan C, Ramkumar PS, Shah J, et al.. Smartphone geospatial apps for dengue control, prevention, prediction, and education: MOSapp, DISapp, and the mosquito perception index (MPI). Environmental Monitoring and Assessment. 2019;191: 393. doi: 10.1007/s10661-019-7425-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-019-7425-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31254076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takken W, Kline DL. Carbon dioxide and 1-octen-3-ol as mosquito attractants. J Am Mosq Control Assoc. 1989;5: 311–316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2573687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBride CS. Genes and odors underlying the recent evolution of mosquito preference for humans. Curr Biol. 2016;26: R41–R46. doi: 10.1016/j.cub.2015.11.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.11.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4714039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26766234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takken W, Dekker T, Wijnholds YG. Odor-mediated flight behavior of Anopheles gambiae gilesSensu Stricto andAn. stephensi liston in response to CO2, acetone, and 1-octen-3-ol (Diptera: Culicidae). J Insect Behav. 1997;10: 395–407. doi: 10.1007/BF02765606</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF02765606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vythilingam I, Chiang GL, Chan ST. Evaluation of carbon dioxide and 1-octen-3-ol as mosquito attractants. Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health. 1992;23: 328–331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1359652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Healy TP, Copland MJ. Activation of Anopheles gambiae mosquitoes by carbon dioxide and human breath. Med Vet Entomol. 1995;9: 331–336. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2915.1995.tb00143.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.1995.tb00143.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7548953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindsay S, Ansell J, Selman C, Cox V, Hamilton K, Walraven G. Effect of pregnancy on exposure to malaria mosquitoes. Lancet. 2000;355: 1972. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(00)02334-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(00)02334-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10859048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braks MA, Anderson RA, Knols BG. Infochemicals in mosquito host selection: human skin microflora and Plasmodium parasites. Parasitol Today. 1999;15: 409–413. doi: 10.1016/s0169-4758(99)01514-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0169-4758(99)01514-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10481153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frei J, Kröber T, Troccaz M, Starkenmann C, Guerin PM. Behavioral response of the malaria mosquito, Anopheles gambiae, to human sweat inoculated with axilla bacteria and to volatiles composing human axillary odor. Chem Senses. 2017;42: 121–131. doi: 10.1093/chemse/bjw106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/chemse/bjw106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27789516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>