<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39312337</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-5964</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>38</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Medicine (Baltimore)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Critical care in older adults: Research landscape and hotspots from a bibliometric perspective.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e39754</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e39754</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e39754</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MD.0000000000039754</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>As the population ages, there will be an increasing demand for health care resources, particularly in intensive care. Therefore, critically ill older adults are receiving increasing attention and have been extensively studied. However, the research landscape, dynamic patterns, and emerging topics in this area have scarcely been reviewed. This study aimed to delve into the current status and emerging trends (publication volume and research topics) in critical care for older adults (including interventions, outcomes, and complications) using bibliometric analysis. We retrieved original articles and reviews focusing on critical care for older adults published between 2013 and 2022 from the Web of Science core database. To examine and present the research trends, we employed VOSviewer and CiteSpace software for analysis and visualization. The cooperative network of countries and institutions, cocited authorship network, cocited references, and cooccurrence network of keywords were analyzed. Overall, 6356 articles and reviews published between 2013 and 2022 were analyzed, revealing a noticeable upward trend in the number of publications focused on critical care for older adults. In total, 34,654 authors from 7989 institutions across 131 countries collaborated to publish 6356 papers related to critical care for older adults in 1715 academic journals. The United States of America and China were the top contributors in terms of research studies, while Bertrand Guidet was the most prolific author with the highest number of articles. A dual-map overlay of the literature revealed that research papers published in Molecular/Biology/Genetics and Health/Nursing/Medicine journals were frequently referenced in Medicine/Medical/Clinical journals. Older patients with coronavirus disease 2019, delirium, and frailty were new trends and developing areas of interest. This is the first bibliometric study focusing on critical care in older adults. The research topics indicate that a comprehensive geriatric assessment, tailored interventions, and specific therapeutic algorithms among older adults are recommended to improve outcomes. Furthermore, this study provides valuable insights for clinical decision-making, guideline development, and resource allocation in critical care settings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Zhe</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Trauma Center, Peking University People's Hospital, National Center for Trauma Medicine, Key Laboratory of Trauma and Neural Regeneration (Ministry of Education), Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Fang</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Tianbing</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5279-9737</Identifier></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Medicine (Baltimore)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985248R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0025-7974</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015706" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bibliometrics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003422" MajorTopicYN="Y">Critical Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D035843" MajorTopicYN="N">Biomedical Research</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000639" MajorTopicYN="N">trends</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016638" MajorTopicYN="N">Critical Illness</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39312337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000039754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00005792-202409200-00038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lone NI, Suntharalingam G. Critical care in an ageing world: too much of a good thing, or a rising challenge. Anaesthesia. 2021;76:1291–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33887062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardin SR. Vulnerability of older patients in critical care. Crit Care Nurse. 2015;35:55–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26033101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angus DC, Kelley MA, Schmitz RJ, White A, Popovich J; Committee on Manpower for Pulmonary and Critical Care Societies (COMPACCS). Caring for the critically ill patient. Current and projected workforce requirements for care of the critically ill and patients with pulmonary disease: can we meet the requirements of an aging population. JAMA. 2000;284:2762–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11105183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaatten H, de Lange DW, Artigas A, et al. . The status of intensive care medicine research and a future agenda for very old patients in the ICU. Intensive Care Med. 2017;43:1319–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28238055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brunker LB, Boncyk CS, Rengel KF, Hughes CG. Elderly patients and management in Intensive Care Units (ICU): clinical challenges. Clin Interv Aging. 2023;18:93–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9879046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36714685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Klein SL, Garibaldi BT, et al. . Aging in COVID-19: vulnerability, immunity and intervention. Ageing Res Rev. 2021;65:101205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7604159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33137510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duggan MC, Van J, Ely EW. Delirium assessment in critically ill older adults: considerations during the COVID-19 pandemic. Crit Care Clin. 2021;37:175–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7427547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33190768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Statistics. WHO.
2023. https://www.who.int/data/gho/publications/world-health-statistics. Accessed May 20, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geen O, Rochwerg B, Wang XM. Optimizing care for critically ill older adults. CMAJ. 2021;193:E1525–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8568082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34607846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He S, Liang Q, Zhu J, et al. . Research landscape and emerging trends of diabetes-associated cognitive dysfunction: a bibliometric analysis. Front Neurosci. 2023;17:1214301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10416239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37575299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Yuan L, Zhou X, Hua X, Yuan X. Bibliometric analysis of the Vogt–Koyanagi–Harada disease literature. Int Ophthalmol. 2023;43:4137–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10520158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37552428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang R, Zhang S, Ding C, Zhu M, Gao Y. Artificial intelligence in intensive care medicine: bibliometric analysis. J Med Internet Res. 2022;24:e42185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9752463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36449345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang F, Xia Q, Zhang L, Wang H, Bai Y, Wu W. A bibliometric and visualized analysis of early mobilization in intensive care unit from 2000 to 2021. Front Neurol. 2022;13:848545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9339903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35923825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Z, Wang Z, Guo F, Wang T. Dynamic structures and emerging trends in the management of major trauma: a bibliometric analysis of publications between 2012 and 2021. Front Public Health. 2022;10:1017817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9663840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36388390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue JH, Li A, Cui X, et al. . Bibliometric analysis of acupuncture for headache from 1974 to 2022: a scoping literature review based on international database. Medicine (Baltim). 2023;102:e34590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10402990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37543789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Z, Wang T. Knowledge domain and dynamic patterns in multimodal molecular imaging from 2012 to 2021: a visual bibliometric analysis. Medicine (Baltim). 2023;102:e32780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9875962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36705366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Yu T, Du R, et al. . Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020;395:1054–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaatten H, De Lange DW, Morandi A, et al. . VIP1 Study Group. The impact of frailty on ICU and 30-day mortality and the level of care in very elderly patients (&gt;/= 80 years). Intensive Care Med. 2017;43:1820–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28936626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72 314 Cases From the Chinese center for disease control and prevention. JAMA. 2020;323:1239–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C, Wang Y, Li X, et al. . Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet. 2020;395:497–506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan WJ, Ni ZY, Hu Y, et al. . China Medical Treatment Expert Group for Covid-19. Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:1708–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32109013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wernly B, Bruno RR, Beil M, et al. . Frailty’s influence on 30-day mortality in old critically ill ICU patients: a Bayesian analysis evaluating the clinical frailty scale. Ann Intensive Care. 2023;13:126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10719192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38091131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wernly B, Flaatten H, Beil M, et al. . A retrospective cohort study comparing differences in 30-day mortality among critically ill patients aged &gt;/= 70 years treated in European tax-based healthcare systems (THS) versus social health insurance systems. Sci Rep. 2022;12:17460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9580441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36261587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beil M, van Heerden PV, Joynt GM, et al. . Limiting life-sustaining treatment for very old ICU patients: cultural challenges and diverse practices. Ann Intensive Care. 2023;13:107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10603016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37884827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vallet H, Guidet B, Boumendil A, et al. . The impact of age-related syndromes on ICU process and outcomes in very old patients. Ann Intensive Care. 2023;13:68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10403479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37542186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mousai O, Tafoureau L, Yovell T, et al. . The role of clinical phenotypes in decisions to limit life-sustaining treatment for very old patients in the ICU. Ann Intensive Care. 2023;13:40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10170430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37162595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polok K, Fronczek J, Guidet B, et al. . COVIP &amp; VIP2 Study Groups. Outcomes of patients aged &gt;/=80 years with respiratory failure initially treated with non-invasive ventilation in European intensive care units before and during COVID-19 pandemic. Ann Intensive Care. 2023;13:82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10497468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37698708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urbina T, Gabarre P, Bonny V, et al. . Corticosteroids induce an early but limited decrease in IL-6 dependent pro-inflammatory responses in critically ill COVID-19 patients. Minerva Anestesiol. 2024;90:172–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38287776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bianco C, Guidet B, Flaatten H, Dechartres A, Vallet H. Mortality in older patients admitted to an ICU for COVID-19: a systematic review. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2023;67:1140–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37323022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung C, Mamandipoor B, Fjolner J, et al. . Disease-course adapting machine learning prognostication models in elderly patients critically Ill With COVID-19: multicenter cohort study with external validation. JMIR Med Inform. 2022;10:e32949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9015783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35099394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takagi K, Akiyama E, Paternot A, et al. . Early echocardiography by treating physicians and outcome in the critically ill: an ancillary study from the prospective multicenter trial FROG-ICU. J Crit Care. 2022;69:154013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35278876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei N, Xu Y, Li Y, et al. . A bibliometric analysis of T cell and atherosclerosis. Front Immunol. 2022;13:948314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9606647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36311729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiersinga WJ, Rhodes A, Cheng AC, Peacock SJ, Prescott HC. Pathophysiology, transmission, diagnosis, and treatment of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a review. JAMA. 2020;324:782–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32648899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baena C, Joarder T, Ahmed NU, Chowdhury R. Aging and the COVID-19 pandemic: the inter-related roles of biology, physical wellbeing, social norms and global health systems. Maturitas. 2023;167:99–104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9328837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36335853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tana C, Moffa L, Falasca K, et al. . Approach to COVID-19 in older adults and indications for improving the outcomes. Ann Med. 2023;55:2265298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10578089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37839411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinatizadeh MR, Zarandi PK, Ghiasi M, et al. . Immunosenescence and inflamm-ageing in COVID-19. Ageing Res Rev. 2023;84:101818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9741765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36516928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh ES, Fong TG, Hshieh TT, Inouye SK. Delirium in older persons: advances in diagnosis and treatment. JAMA. 2017;318:1161–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5717753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28973626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcantonio ER. Postoperative delirium: a 76-year-old woman with delirium following surgery. JAMA. 2012;308:73–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3604975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22669559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ely EW, Shintani A, Truman B, et al. . Delirium as a predictor of mortality in mechanically ventilated patients in the intensive care unit. JAMA. 2004;291:1753–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15082703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcantonio ER. Delirium in hospitalized older adults. N Engl J Med. 2017;377:1456–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5706782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29020579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Geriatrics Society Expert Panel on Postoperative Delirium in Older Adults. American Geriatrics Society abstracted clinical practice guideline for postoperative delirium in older adults. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2015;63:142–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5901697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25495432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young J, Murthy L, Westby M, Akunne A, O'Mahony R; Guideline Development Group. Diagnosis, prevention, and management of delirium: summary of NICE guidance. BMJ. 2010;341:c3704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20667955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasin L, Boraso S, Golino G, Fakhr BS, Tiberio I, Trevisan C. The impact of frailty on mortality in older patients admitted to an Intensive Care Unit. Med Intensiva (Engl Ed). 2022;46:23–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34991871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crooms RC, Gelfman LP. Palliative care and end-of-life considerations for the Frail Patient. Anesth Analg. 2020;130:1504–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7536652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32384340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muscedere J, Waters B, Varambally A, et al. . The impact of frailty on intensive care unit outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Intensive Care Med. 2017;43:1105–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5501903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28676896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan L, Tan J, Qi B, et al. . The bibliometric and altmetric analysis of chronic traumatic encephalopathy research: how great is the impact? Front Neurol. 2024;15:1294125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10883053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38390592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Z, Wang T. A bibliometric analysis of publications on trauma-related hemorrhagic shock from 2012 to 2022: research landscape and future trends. Medicine (Baltim). 2023;102:e33814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10194525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37335729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Zhang L, Huang X, et al. . Emotional labour in nursing research: a bibliometric analysis [published online ahead of print May 13, 2024]. J Adv Nurs. doi: 10.1111/jan.16233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38738461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S, Liu X, Ma R, et al. . Global trends in research of pseudomyxoma peritonei: a bibliometric and visualization analysis. Front Oncol. 2024;14:1323796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10883648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38390264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian SC, Yang J, Li X, Huang R-X, Chen J. Bibliometric and visual analysis of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (2004-2023). Front Oncol. 2024;14:1377486.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11076682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38720800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Deng K, Liu Y, Xia M, Lei M, Wu M. Global research trends on innate lymphoid cells in the brain, gut and lung field: a bibliometric and visualized analysis. Front Immunol. 2024;15:1336666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10879818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38384457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>