<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39319311</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1662-4548</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>18</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in neuroscience</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Neurosci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comprehensive MRI assessment reveals subtle brain findings in non-hospitalized post-COVID patients with cognitive impairment.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1435218</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1435218</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1435218</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fnins.2024.1435218</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Impaired cognitive ability is one of the most frequently reported neuropsychiatric symptoms in the post-COVID phase among patients. It is unclear whether this condition is related to structural or functional brain changes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In this study, we present a multimodal magnetic resonance imaging study of 36 post-COVID patients and 36 individually matched controls who had a mild form of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS CoV-2) infection from March 2020 to February 2022. This study aimed to investigate structural and functional brain alterations and their correlation with post-COVID symptoms and neurocognitive functions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The study protocol comprised an assessment of physical fatigue [Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS)], mental fatigue (Mental Fatigue Scale (MFS)], depression [Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)], anxiety [Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HAD)], post-COVID Symptoms Severity Score, and neurocognitive status [Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status Update (RBANS)]. The magnetic resonance imaging protocol included morphological sequences, arterial spin labeling (ASL) and dynamic susceptibility contrast-enhanced (DSC) perfusion, diffusion tensor imaging (DTI), and resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) sequences. Using these protocols, the assessments of macrostructural abnormalities, perfusion, gray matter density, white matter integrity, and brain connectivity were performed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Post-COVID patients had higher levels of physical fatigue, mental fatigue, depression, and anxiety than controls and showed cognitive impairment in all the RBANS domains except in Visuospatial/Construction. The subjective mental fatigue correlated with objective impaired cognitive ability in the RBANS test, particularly in the Attention domain. There were no differences between patients and controls regarding macrostructural abnormalities, regional volumes, regional perfusion metrics, gray matter density, or DTI parameters. We observed a significant positive correlation between RBANS Total Scale Index score and gray matter volume in the right superior/middle-temporal gyrus (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) and a significant negative correlation between the white matter integrity and post-COVID symptoms (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) in the same area. The connectivity differences were observed between patients and controls in a few regions, including the right middle frontal gyrus, an important area of convergence of the dorsal and ventral attention networks. We also noted a positive correlation between post-COVID symptoms and increased connectivity in the right temporoparietal junction, which is part of the ventral attention system.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In non-hospitalized subjects with post-COVID, we did not find any structural brain changes or changes in perfusion, compared to controls. However, we noted differences in connectivity within an important area for attention processes, which may be associated with post-COVID brain fog.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Fineschi, Fahlström, Fällmar, Haller and Wikström.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fineschi</LastName><ForeName>Serena</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health and Caring Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Östhammar Health Care Centre, Östhammar, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fahlström</LastName><ForeName>Markus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fällmar</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Uppsala University Hospital, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haller</LastName><ForeName>Sven</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Radiodiagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wikström</LastName><ForeName>Johan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Uppsala University Hospital, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Neurosci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101478481</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1662-453X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MRI</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">attention network</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cognitive impairment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">post-COVID</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">resting state fMRI</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">right middle frontal gyrus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">right temporoparietal junction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39319311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11420131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnins.2024.1435218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ajčević M., Iscra K., Furlanis G., Michelutti M., Miladinović A., Buoite Stella A., et al. . (2023). Cerebral hypoperfusion in post-COVID-19 cognitively impaired subjects revealed by arterial spin labeling MRI. Sci. Rep. 13:5808. 10.1038/s41598-023-32275-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-32275-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10086005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37037833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsop D. C., Detre J. A., Golay X., Günther M., Hendrikse J., Hernandez-Garcia L., et al. . (2015). Recommended implementation of arterial spin-labeled perfusion MRI for clinical applications: a consensus of the ISMRM perfusion study group and the European consortium for ASL in dementia. Magn. Reson. Med. 73, 102–116. 10.1002/mrm.25197</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mrm.25197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4190138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24715426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andriuta D., Si-Ahmed C., Roussel M., Constans J. M., Makki M., Aarabi A., et al. . (2022). Clinical and imaging determinants of neurocognitive disorders in post-acute COVID-19 patients with cognitive complaints. J. Alzheimers Dis. 87, 1239–1250. 10.3233/JAD-215506</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/JAD-215506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35431242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badenoch J. B., Rengasamy E. R., Watson C., Jansen K., Chakraborty S., Sundaram R. D., et al. . (2022). Persistent neuropsychiatric symptoms after COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Brain Commun. 4:fcab297. 10.1093/braincomms/fcab297</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/braincomms/fcab297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8833580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35169700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnden L. R., Shan Z. Y., Staines D. R., Marshall-Gradisnik S., Finegan K., Ireland T., et al. . (2019). Intra brainstem connectivity is impaired in chronic fatigue syndrome. Neuroimage Clin. 24:102045. 10.1016/j.nicl.2019.102045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2019.102045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6835065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31671321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bendella Z., Widmann C. N., Layer J. P., Layer Y. L., Haase R., Sauer M., et al. . (2023). Brain volume changes after COVID-19 compared to healthy controls by artificial intelligence-based MRI volumetry. Diagnostics 13:1716. 10.3390/diagnostics13101716</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/diagnostics13101716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10216908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37238200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birberg Thornberg U., Andersson A., Lindh M., Hellgren L., Divanoglou A., Levi R., et al. . (2022). Neurocognitive deficits in COVID-19 patients five months after discharge from hospital. Neuropsychol. Rehabil. 14, 1–25. 10.1080/09602011.2022.2125020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09602011.2022.2125020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36239662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonilla H., Quach T. C., Tiwari A., Bonilla A. E., Miglis M., Yang P. C., et al. . (2023). Myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome is common in post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection (PASC): results from a post-COVID-19 multidisciplinary clinic. Front. Neurol. 14:1090747. 10.3389/fneur.2023.1090747</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fneur.2023.1090747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9998690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36908615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cecchetti G., Agosta F., Canu E., Basaia S., Barbieri A., Cardamone R., et al. . (2022). Cognitive, EEG, and MRI features of COVID-19 survivors: a 10-month study. J. Neurol. 269, 3400–3412. 10.1007/s00415-022-11047-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00415-022-11047-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8898558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35249144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Churchill N. W., Roudaia E., Chen J. J., Gilboa A., Sekuler A., Ji X., et al. . (2023). Effects of post-acute COVID-19 syndrome on the functional brain networks of non-hospitalized individuals. Front. Neurol. 14:1136408. 10.3389/fneur.2023.1136408</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fneur.2023.1136408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10083436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37051059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corbetta M., Patel G., Shulman G. L. (2008). The reorienting system of the human brain: from environment to theory of mind. Neuron 58, 306–24. 10.1016/j.neuron.2008.04.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.04.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2441869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18466742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Díez-Cirarda M., Yus M., Gómez-Ruiz N., Polidura C., Gil-Martínez L., Delgado-Alonso C., et al. . (2023). Multimodal neuroimaging in post-COVID syndrome and correlation with cognition. Brain 146, 2142–2152. 10.1093/brain/awac384</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/brain/awac384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9620345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36288544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douaud G., Lee S., Alfaro-Almagro F., Arthofer C., Wang C., McCarthy P., et al. . (2022). SARS-CoV-2 is associated with changes in brain structure in UK Biobank. Nature 604, 697–707. 10.1038/s41586-022-04569-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04569-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9046077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35255491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Y. Y., Zhao W., Zhou X. L., Zeng M., Yang D. H., Xie X. Z., et al. . (2022). Survivors of COVID-19 exhibit altered amplitudes of low frequency fluctuation in the brain: a resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging study at 1-year follow-up. Neural Regen Res. 17, 1576–1581. 10.4103/1673-5374.327361</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/1673-5374.327361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8771089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34916443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fazekas F., Chawluk J. B., Alavi A., Hurtig H. I., Zimmerman RA. (1987). MR signal abnormalities at 1.5 T in Alzheimer's dementia and normal aging. AJR Am. J. Roentgenol. 149, 351–356. 10.2214/ajr.149.2.351</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2214/ajr.149.2.351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3496763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández-de-Las-Peñas C., Rodríguez-Jiménez J., Cancela-Cilleruelo I., Guerrero-Peral A., Martín-Guerrero J. D., García-Azorín D., et al. . (2022). Post-COVID-19 symptoms 2 years after SARS-CoV-2 Infection among hospitalized vs. nonhospitalized patients. JAMA Netw. Open 5:e2242106. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.42106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.42106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9667330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36378309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox M. D., Corbetta M., Snyder A. Z., Vincent J. L., Raichle M. E. (2006). Spontaneous neuronal activity distinguishes human dorsal and ventral attention systems. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 103, 10046–10051. 10.1073/pnas.0604187103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0604187103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1480402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16788060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham E. L., Clark J. R., Orban Z. S., Lim P. H., Szymanski A. L., Taylor C., et al. . (2021). Persistent neurologic symptoms and cognitive dysfunction in non-hospitalized Covid-19 “long haulers”. Ann. Clin. Transl. Neurol. 8, 1073–1085. 10.1002/acn3.51350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/acn3.51350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8108421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33755344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gregoire S. M., Chaudhary U. J., Brown M. M., Yousry T. A., Kallis C., Jäger H. R., et al. . (2009). The Microbleed Anatomical Rating Scale (MARS): reliability of a tool to map brain microbleeds. Neurology 73, 1759–1766. 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181c34a7d</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181c34a7d</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19933977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hafiz R., Gandhi T. K., Mishra S., Prasad A., Mahajan V., Di X., et al. . (2022). Higher limbic and basal ganglia volumes in surviving COVID-negative patients and the relations to fatigue. Neuroimage Rep. 2:100095. 10.1016/j.ynirp.2022.100095</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ynirp.2022.100095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9040524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35496469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heine J., Schwichtenberg K., Hartung T. J., Rekers S., Chien C., Boesl F., et al. . (2023). Structural brain changes in patients with post-COVID fatigue: a prospective observational study. EClinicalMedicine 58:101874. 10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.101874</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.101874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9969172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36873426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inderyas M., Thapaliya K., Marshall-Gradisnik S., Barth M., Barnden L. (2024). Subcortical and default mode network connectivity is impaired in myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome. Front. Neurosci. 17:1318094. 10.3389/fnins.2023.1318094</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnins.2023.1318094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10859529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38347875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaltuszewska S., Chojnacka-Szawlowska G., Majkowicz M., Zdonczyk S., Homenda W., Hebel K., et al. . (2023). Illness perception and the severity of depression and anxiety symptoms in patients with multimorbidity: observational cohort studies. J. Clin. Med. 13:69. 10.3390/jcm13010069</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm13010069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10780102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38202075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenkinson M., Beckmann C. F., Behrens T. E., Woolrich M. W., Smith S. M. (2012). FSL. Neuroimage 62, 782–790. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.09.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.09.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21979382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johansson B., Starmark A., Berglund P., Rödholm M., Rönnbäck L. (2010). A self-assessment questionnaire for mental fatigue and related symptoms after neurological disorders and injuries. Brain Inj. 24, 2–12. 10.3109/02699050903452961</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/02699050903452961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20001478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krupp L. B., LaRocca N. G., Muir-Nash J., Steinberg A. D. (1989). The fatigue severity scale. Application to patients with multiple sclerosis and systemic lupus erythematosus. Arch. Neurol. 46, 1121–1123. 10.1001/archneur.1989.00520460115022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archneur.1989.00520460115022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2803071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latini F., Fahlström M., Fällmar D., Marklund N., Cunningham J. L., Feresiadou A., et al. . (2022). Can diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) outperform standard magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) investigations in post-COVID-19 autoimmune encephalitis? Ups J. Med. Sci. 127. 10.48101/ujms.v127.8562</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.48101/ujms.v127.8562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9169543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35722186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Legler F., Meyer-Arndt L., Mödl L., Kedor C., Freitag H., Stein E., et al. . (2023). Long-term symptom severity and clinical biomarkers in post-COVID-19/chronic fatigue syndrome: results from a prospective observational cohort. EClinicalMedicine 63:102146. 10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.102146</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.102146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10469383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37662515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Y., Li X., Geng D., Mei N., Wu P. Y., Huang C. C., et al. . (2020). Cerebral micro-structural changes in COVID-19 patients - an MRI-based 3-month Follow-up Study. EClinicalMedicine 25:100484. 10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100484</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7396952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32838240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montgomery S. A., Asberg M. (1979). A new depression scale designed to be sensitive to change. Br J Psychiatry. 134, 382–389. 10.1192/bjp.134.4.382</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.134.4.382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">444788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mouridsen K., Hansen M. B., Østergaard L., Jespersen S. N. (2014). Reliable estimation of capillary transit time distributions using DSC-MRI. J. Cereb. Blood Flow. Metab. 34, 1511–1521. 10.1038/jcbfm.2014.111</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/jcbfm.2014.111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4158667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24938401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paolini M., Palladini M., Mazza M. G., Colombo F., Vai B., Rovere-Querini P., et al. . (2023). Brain correlates of subjective cognitive complaints in COVID-19 survivors: a multimodal magnetic resonance imaging study. Eur. Neuropsychopharmacol. 68, 1–10. 10.1016/j.euroneuro.2022.12.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2022.12.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9742225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36640728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasquier F., Leys D., Weerts J. G., Mounier-Vehier F., Barkhof F., Scheltens P., et al. . (1996). Inter- and intraobserver reproducibility of cerebral atrophy assessment on MRI scans with hemispheric infarcts. Eur. Neurol. 36, 268–72. 10.1159/000117270</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000117270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8864706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Planchuelo-Gómez Á., García-Azorín D., Guerrero Á. L., Rodríguez M., Aja-Fernández S., de Luis-García R. (2023). Structural brain changes in patients with persistent headache after COVID-19 resolution. J. Neurol. 270, 13–31. 10.1007/s00415-022-11398-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00415-022-11398-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9522538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36178541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin Y., Wu J., Chen T., Li J., Zhang G., Wu D., et al. . (2021). Long-term microstructure and cerebral blood flow changes in patients recovered from COVID-19 without neurological manifestations. J. Clin. Invest. 131:e147329. 10.1172/JCI147329</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1172/JCI147329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8262559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33630760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Randolph C., Tierney M. C., Mohr E., Chase T. N. (1998). The Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS): preliminary clinical validity. J. Clin. Exp. Neuropsychol. 20, 310–3109. 10.1076/jcen.20.3.310.823</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1076/jcen.20.3.310.823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9845158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S., Meher N., Mohammed A., Razab M. K. A. A., Bhaskar L. V. K. S., Nawi N. M., et al. . (2023). Neurological infection and complications of SARS-CoV-2: a review. Medicine 102:e30284. 10.1097/MD.0000000000030284</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000030284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9901962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36749239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith S. M., Nichols T. E. (2009). Threshold-free cluster enhancement: addressing problems of smoothing, threshold dependence and localisation in cluster inference. Neuroimage 44, 83–98. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.03.061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.03.061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18501637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soriano J. B., Murthy S., Marshall J. C., Relan P., Diaz J. V., WHO Clinical Case Definition Working Group on Post-COVID-19 Condition (2022). A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. Lancet Infect. Dis. 22, e102–e107. 10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8691845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34951953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thapaliya K., Marshall-Gradisnik S., Barth M., Eaton-Fitch N., Barnden L. (2023). Brainstem volume changes in myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome and long COVID patients. Front Neurosci. 17:1125208. 10.3389/fnins.2023.1125208</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnins.2023.1125208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10017877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36937672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tu Y., Zhang Y., Li Y., Zhao Q., Bi Y., Lu X., et al. . (2021). Post-traumatic stress symptoms in COVID-19 survivors: a self-report and brain imaging follow-up study. Mol Psychiatry. 26, 7475–7480. 10.1038/s41380-021-01223-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41380-021-01223-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8290134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34285348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasilev Y., Blokhin I., Khoruzhaya A., Kodenko M., Kolyshenkov V., Nanova O., et al. . (2023). Routine brain MRI findings on the long-term effects of COVID-19: a scoping review. Diagnostics 13:2533. 10.3390/diagnostics13152533</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/diagnostics13152533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10417725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37568896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zigmond A. S., Snaith R. P. (1983). The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr. Scand. 67, 361–370. 10.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6880820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>