<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314647</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2377-9608</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jan-Dec</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>SAGE open nursing</Title><ISOAbbreviation>SAGE Open Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Telepalliative Care in Home-Based Nursing Care for Older Adults With Metastatic Cancer Post COVID-19: An Ethnoscientific Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>23779608241279908</StartPage><MedlinePgn>23779608241279908</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">23779608241279908</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/23779608241279908</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The post-COVID-19 pandemic caused the whole world to make several changes to the nursing healthcare system. This sudden shift raised questions about telepalliative care in home-based nursing care in the context of healthcare utilization, including meeting the needs of older adults with metastatic cancer. The evidence suggests that telepalliative care in home-based nursing care is acceptable to most advanced practice nurses, but the extent of their use for metastatic cancer patients has not been defined.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To explore the use of telepalliative care in home-based nursing care for older adults with metastatic cancer in central Thailand following the post-COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A qualitative approach with an ethnoscientific design was used to collect data from a purposive sample of 15 advanced practice nurses from May to September 2023. The interview transcripts were analyzed using componential analysis (core coding, categorizing, theme, and emerging theory).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The componential analysis revealed two themes of telepalliative care in home-based nursing care for older adults with metastatic cancer in the post COVID-19 pandemic. The first theme is telepalliative care delivery, with subthemes of delivering practice, nurse-mediated feedback and supportive care, remote monitoring of real-time emergencies, and transferring medical data. The second theme is advanced practice nurses' (APN) role in telepalliative nursing care, including the subthemes of virtual monitoring, life-threatening cancer, side effects, caregiving capacity, continuity of care, and long-term care services. The study found that caregiving capacity, continuity of care, and long-term care services were formed of telepalliative care in home-based nursing care for cancer patients following the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Telepalliative care in home-based nursing care is effective in delivering services to older adults with metastatic cancer during the post-COVID-19 pandemic. The findings suggested that remote monitoring of real-time emergencies, life-threatening cancer, and long-term care services are part of telepalliative care in home-based nursing care. Adapting the telepalliative competency standards of advanced practice nurses is needed to ensure high-quality healthcare access for older adults with metastatic cancer during the post-COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sathiyamas</LastName><ForeName>Jinpitcha</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1749-3326</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Adult Nursing and the Aged, Faculty of Nursing, Thammasat University, Pathum Thani, Thailand.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">65100</Identifier></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Creative Engineering Design and Development, Faculty of Engineering, Thammasat University, Pathum Thani, Thailand.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">65100</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mingmalairak</LastName><ForeName>Chatchai</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Faculty of Medicine, Thammasat University, Pathum Thani, Thailand.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">65100</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rungroungdouyboon</LastName><ForeName>Bunyong</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Adult Nursing and the Aged, Faculty of Nursing, Thammasat University, Pathum Thani, Thailand.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">65100</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sri-Ngernyuang</LastName><ForeName>Chawakorn</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Engineering and Agro-Industry, Maejo University, Chiang Mai, Thailand.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">54779</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>SAGE Open Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101724853</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2377-9608</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Thailand</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">advanced practice nursing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cancer survivor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">home-based nursing care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">palliative supportive care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telecare</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11418230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/23779608241279908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_23779608241279908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aldana G. L., Evoh O. V., Reddy A. (2023). Best practices for providing patient-centered tele-palliative care to cancer patients. Cancers, 15(6), 1809. 10.3390/cancers15061809</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cancers15061809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10046317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36980695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alom S., Chiu C. M., Jha A., Lai S. H. D., Yau T. H. L., Harky A. (2021). The effects of COVID-19 on cancer care provision: A systematic review. Cancer Control, 28, 1–29. 10.1177/1073274821997425</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1073274821997425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8482720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33631953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee S. C., Staley J. M., Howell F., Malling C., Moreno A., Kotsen C., Parikh D., Parker P. A. (2022). Communicating effectively via tele-oncology (Comskil TeleOnc): A guide for best practices for communication skills in virtual cancer care. Journal of Cancer Education, 37(5), 1343–1348. 10.1007/s13187-021-01959-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13187-021-01959-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7862043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33544315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barratt M. J., Ferris J. A., Lenton S. (2015). Hidden populations, online purposive sampling, and external validity: Taking off the blindfold. Field Methods, 27(1), 3–21. 10.1177/1525822X14526838</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1525822X14526838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer E. H., Schultz ANØ, Brandt F., Smith A. C., Bollig G., Dieperink K. B. (2022). Protocol for an integrative review: Patient and families’ perspectives on telehealth in palliative care. BMJ Open, 12(9), e062723. 10.1136/bmjopen-2022-062723</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-062723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9454006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36688736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berreman G. D. (1966). Anemic and emetic analyses in social anthropology. American Anthropologist, 68(2), 346–354. 10.1525/aa.1966.68.2.02a00020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1525/aa.1966.68.2.02a00020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burbury K., Wong Z. W., Yip D., Thomas H., Brooks P., Gilham L., Piper A., Solo I., Underhill C. (2021). Telehealth in cancer care: During and beyond the COVID-19 pandemic. Internal Medicine Journal, 51(1), 125–133. 10.1111/imj.15039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/imj.15039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8014764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33572014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calton B. A., Rabow M. W., Branagan L., Dionne-Odom J. N., Oliver P., Bakitas D., Fratkin M. A., Lustbader M. D., Jones D., Ritchie C. A., S C. (2019). Top ten tips palliative care clinicians should know about telepalliative care. Journal of Palliative Medicine, 22(8), 981–985. 10.1089/jpm.2019.0278</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jpm.2019.0278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31237467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y., Qiao C., Zhang X., Li W., Yang H. (2023). The effect of tele-palliative care on patient and caregiver outcomes: A systematic review. American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine, 40(8), 907–925. 10.1177/10499091221123566</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/10499091221123566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36113129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua I. S., Olmsted M., Plotke R., Turk Y., Trotter C., Rinaldi S., Kamdar M., Jackson V. A., Gallagher-Medeiros E. R., El-Jawahri A., Temel J. S., Greer J. A. (2022). Video and in-person palliative care delivery challenges before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. Journal of Pain and Symptom Management, 64(6), 577–587. 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2022.08.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2022.08.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9383956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35985551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung V., Sun V., Ruel N., Smith T. J., Ferrell B. R. (2022). Improving palliative care and quality of life in pancreatic cancer patients. Journal of Palliative Medicine, 25(5), 720–727. 10.1089/jpm.2021.0187</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jpm.2021.0187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9080991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34704841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cormi C., Petit M., Auclair J., Bagaragaza E., Colombet I., Sanchez S. (2021). Building a telepalliative care strategy in nursing homes: A qualitative study with mobile palliative care teams. BMC Palliative Care, 20(1), 156. 10.1186/s12904-021-00864-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12904-021-00864-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8514278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34645445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cornetta K., Nyariki S., Manji I., Kiplimo I., Korir M., Muinga E., Busakhala N., Elias H. (2023). Telehospice for cancer patients discharged from a tertiary care hospital in Western Kenya. Journal of Pain and Symptom Management, 65(5), 378–387. 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2023.01.027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2023.01.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10106447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36773732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duangchan C., Steffen A., Matthews A. K. (2021). Perspectives and practices regarding colorectal cancer survivorship care: Online survey results from oncology nurses in Thailand. European Journal of Oncology Nursing, 55, 102048. 10.1016/j.ejon.2021.102048</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejon.2021.102048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34634574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahimabadi M., Rafiei F., Nejat N. (2021). Can tele-nursing affect the supportive care needs of patients with cancer undergoing chemotherapy? A randomized controlled trial follow-up study. Supportive Care in Cancer, 29(10), 5865–5872. 10.1007/s00520-021-06056-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00520-021-06056-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7987327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33758968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graffigna G., Vegni E., Barello S., Olson K., Bosio C. A. (2011). Studying the social construction of cancer-related fatigue experience: The heuristic value of ethnoscience. Patient Education and Counseling, 82(3), 402–409. 10.1016/j.pec.2010.12.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pec.2010.12.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21292426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grudzen C. R., Barker P. C., Bischof J. J., Cuthel A. M., Isaacs E. D., Southerland L. T., Yamarik R. L. (2022). Palliative care models for patients living with advanced cancer: A narrative review for the emergency department clinician. Emergency Cancer Care, 1(1), 1–10. 10.1186/s44201-022-00010-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s44201-022-00010-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9362452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35966217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanna T. P., King W. D., Thibodeau S., Jalink M., Paulin G. A., Harvey-Jones E., O'Sullivan D. E., Booth C. M., Sullivan R., Aggarwal A. (2020). Mortality due to cancer treatment delay: Systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ, 371, 1–11. 10.1136/bmj.m4087</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m4087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7610021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33148535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J., Chan S. C., Tin M. S., Liu X., Lok V. T. T., Ngai C. H., Zhang L., Lucero-Prisno D. E., Xu W., Zheng Z. J., Chiu P. K., Ng A. C., Enikeev D., Nicol D., Spiess P. E., Laguna P., Teoh J. Y., Wong M. C. S. (2022). Worldwide distribution, risk factors, and temporal trends of testicular cancer incidence and mortality: A global analysis. European Urology Oncology, 5(5), 566–576. 10.1016/j.euo.2022.06.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euo.2022.06.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35863988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutchinson R. N., Anderson E. C., Ruben M. A., Manning N., John L., Daruvala A., Rizzo D. M., Eppstein M. J., Gramling R., Han P. K. J. (2022). A formative mixed-methods study of emotional responsiveness in telepalliative care. Journal of Palliative Medicine, 25(8), 1258–1267. 10.1089/jpm.2021.0589</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jpm.2021.0589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9347382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35417249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Insamran W., Sangrajrang S. (2020). National cancer control program of Thailand. Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, 21(3), 577–582. 10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.3.577</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.3.577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7437310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32212781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang D. M., Berlin A., Moody L., Kumar R., Hannon B., Krzyzanowska M. K., Dhani N., Cole H., Elliott M., Sridhar S. S. (2020). Transitioning to a new normal in the post-COVID era. Current Oncology Reports, 22(7), 73. 10.1007/s11912-020-00956-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11912-020-00956-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7306409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32566960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jefford M., Howell D., Li Q., Lisy K., Maher J., Alfano C. M., Rynderman M., Emery J. (2022). Improved models of care for cancer survivors. The Lancet, 399(10334), 1551–1560. 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00306-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00306-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9009839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35430022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kashyap K., Panda S. (2020). Psycho-perceptual aspects of positive behaviour among patients with head and neck cancer. The Journal of Behavioral Science, 15(3), 1–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerr H., Donovan M., McSorley O. (2021). Evaluation of the role of the clinical nurse specialist in cancer care: An integrative literature review. European Journal of Cancer Care, 30(3), e13415. 10.1111/ecc.13415</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ecc.13415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33501707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korstjens I., Moser A. (2018). Series: Practical guidance to qualitative research. Part 4: Trustworthiness and publishing. European Journal of General Practice, 24(1), 120–124. 10.1080/13814788.2017.1375092</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13814788.2017.1375092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8816392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29202616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leininger M. (1990). Ethnomethods: The philosophic and epistemic bases to explicate transcultural nursing knowledge. Journal of Transcultural Nursing, 1(2), 40–51. 10.1177/104365969000100206</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/104365969000100206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2363862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levoy K., Foxwell A., Rosa W. E. (2022). Palliative care delivery changes during COVID-19 and enduring implications in oncology nursing: A rapid review. Current Opinion in Supportive and Palliative Care, 16(3), 94–101. 10.1097/SPC.0000000000000603</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SPC.0000000000000603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9364779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35929556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowe A., Norris A. C., Farris A. J., Babbage D. R. (2018). Quantifying thematic saturation in qualitative data analysis. Field Methods, 30(3), 191–207. 10.1177/1525822X17749386</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1525822X17749386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mamom J., Daovisan H. (2024). Telenursing: How do caregivers treat and prevent pressure injury in bedridden patients during the COVID-19 pandemic in Thailand? Using an embedded approach. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare, 30(3), 589–596. 10.1177/1357633X221078485</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1357633X221078485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8927889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35293254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merlino C., Klaiman T., Beidas R., Courtright K. (2022). Improving implementation of tele-palliative care in nursing homes for patients with serious illness (RP521). Journal of Pain and Symptom Management, 63(6), 1109. 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2022.04.087</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2022.04.087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morey N. C., Luthans F. (1984). An emic perspective and ethnoscience methods for organizational research. Academy of Management Review, 9(1), 27–36. 10.5465/amr.1984.4277836</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5465/amr.1984.4277836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papautsky E. L., Hamlish T. (2020). Patient-reported treatment delays in breast cancer care during the COVID-19 pandemic. Breast Cancer Research and Treatment, 184(1), 249–254. 10.1007/s10549-020-05828-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10549-020-05828-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7415197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32772225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasanen L., Le Gautier R., Wong A., Wawryk O., Collins A., Schwetlik S., Philip J. (2022). Telehealth in outpatient delivery of palliative care: A qualitative study of patient and physician views. Palliative &amp; Supportive Care, 21(6), 980–987. 10.1017/S1478951522000670</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1478951522000670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35818898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pengput A., Schwartz D. G. (2022). Telemedicine in Southeast Asia: A systematic review. Telemedicine and e-Health, 28(12), 1711–1733. 10.1089/tmj.2021.0516</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/tmj.2021.0516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35417250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pumipak B., Jittimanee S., Thananun S., Mathong K., Poungdok J., Sinsap M., Sueathong T., Kongruang O., Faungprachakorn S., Thunyaphun T., Insook P., Soontornmon K. (2023). Symptom experience and perceived health status of people with long COVID in Thailand. SAGE Open Nursing, 9, 1–10. 10.1177/23779608231206748</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/23779608231206748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10580730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37854789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosa W. E., Lynch K. A., Hadler R. A., Mahoney C., Parker P. A. (2023). It took away and stripped a part of myself”: Clinician distress and recommendations for future telepalliative care delivery in the cancer context. American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine, 40(2), 235–243. 10.1177/10499091221101883</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/10499091221101883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9663759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35574961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schenker Y., Althouse A. D., Rosenzweig M., White D. B., Chu E., Smith K. J., Resick J. M., Belin S., Park S. Y., Smith T. J., Bakitas M. A., Arnold R. M. (2021). Effect of an oncology nurse-led primary palliative care intervention on patients with advanced cancer: The CONNECT cluster randomized clinical trial. JAMA Internal Medicine, 181(11), 1451–1460. 10.1001/jamainternmed.2021.5185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2021.5185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8438619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34515737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmitt S., Ebby C., Doshi A., Bower K., Marc-Aurele K. (2022). Retrospective pediatric telepalliative care experience. Journal of Palliative Medicine, 25(2), 274–281. 10.1089/jpm.2021.0173</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jpm.2021.0173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34550796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silapavit K. (2021). News from advanced practice nurse association (Thailand). Thai Journal of Nursing and Midwifery Practice, 8(1), 120–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stewart I., Leary A., Khakwani A., Borthwick D., Tod A., Hubbard R., Beckett P., Tata L. J. (2021). Do working practices of cancer nurse specialists improve clinical outcomes? Retrospective cohort analysis from the English national lung cancer audit. International Journal of Nursing Studies, 118, 103718. 10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103718</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32859375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan A. J., Yamarik R., Brody A. A., Chung F. R., Grudzen C., &amp; EMPallA Telephonic Working Group. (2021). Development and protocol for a nurse-led telephonic palliative care program. Nursing Outlook, 69(4), 626–631. 10.1016/j.outlook.2020.12.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.outlook.2020.12.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8046383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33485590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiyawatanaroj A., Sudtikoonaseth P., Chayangsu O. (2022). Basal cell carcinoma trends in Thailand: A 10-year retrospective study of demographic, clinical and histopathological features. Dermatology Reports, 14(1), 9413. 10.4081/dr.2022.9413</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/dr.2022.9413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8969878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35371421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A., Sainsbury P., Craig J. (2007). Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): A 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. International Journal for Quality in Health Care, 19(6), 349–357. 10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Upasen R., Thanasilp S., Akkayagorn L., Chimluang J., Tantitrakul W., Doutrich D. L., Saengpanya W. (2022). Death acceptance process in Thai Buddhist patients with life-limiting cancer: A grounded theory. Global Qualitative Nursing Research, 9, 1–10. 10.1177/23333936221111809</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/23333936221111809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9284199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35845864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>