<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39312309</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-5964</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>38</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Medicine (Baltimore)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Patients' experience of telehealth clinics during the COVID-19 pandemic: Cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e39837</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e39837</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e39837</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MD.0000000000039837</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Globally, the Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic in 2019 has accelerated the adoption of telehealth technologies. The implementation of the Saudi Telemedicine Network (STN) and other digital health initiatives, such as the telehealth clinic (THC) at King Abdullah bin Abdulaziz University Hospital (KAAUH), exemplifies this trend in Saudi Arabia. The aim of this study was to explore the patients' experience of THC in KAAUH during the COVID-19 pandemic and their' beliefs about their readiness to replace the traditional onsite clinical visits with THC from March to September 2020. A cross-sectional study targeted all 1398 patients who utilized THC at KAAUH. A self-administrated, validated survey collected the data. The survey used a Likert scale and included questions on satisfaction with THC services and the perceived effectiveness of telehealth as a substitute for in-person visits. The collected data was analyzed using frequency and percentage. A total of 252 patients responded to the THC postvisit survey. Overall, 217 patients (86%) were satisfied, 32 patients (13%) were dissatisfied, and only 3 patients (1%) were neutral about THC. Most patients (65.5%) agree that THC provided enough information about their health conditions, which can substitute for clinical visits. About 18.3% of patients were neutral, while 16.3% disagreed with the effectiveness of THC services and believed that they could not replace onsite visits. During the COVID-19 pandemic, most patients were satisfied at KAAUH-THC in Saudi Arabia and believed that it could replace the onsite visit to a physician's clinic. The 2 main causes of the patient's belief that THC could not replace an onsite clinical visit were: First, nonadherence to appointments led to missed calls and a complete medical service. Second, the patient's perception is that a physical examination and lab investigation cannot be completed through THC.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>AlRadini</LastName><ForeName>Faten A</ForeName><Initials>FA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7835-8681</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Family and Community Medicine, College of Medicine, Princess Nourah bint Abdulrahman University, Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdulrahim</LastName><ForeName>Maha</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5002-9635</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research &amp; Academic Accreditation Office, King Abdullah bin Abdulaziz University Hospital, Princess Nourah bint Abdulrahman University, Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>AlOtaibi</LastName><ForeName>Naif</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Patients' Experience Office, King Abdullah bin Abdulaziz University Hospital, Princess Nourah bint Abdulrahman University, Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Amri</LastName><ForeName>Fahad A</ForeName><Initials>FA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7336-162</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Center for Mass Gatherings Medicine, Public Health Agency, Ministry of Health, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amer</LastName><ForeName>Samar Ahmed</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9475-6372</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health and Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Zagazig University, 11459 Zagazig, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of General Practitioners, Royal College of General Practioners, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Medicine (Baltimore)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985248R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0025-7974</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017216" MajorTopicYN="Y">Telemedicine</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012529" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Saudi Arabia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017060" MajorTopicYN="Y">Patient Satisfaction</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39312309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000039837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00005792-202409200-00010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ramaswamy A, Yu M, Drangsholt S, et al. . Patient satisfaction with telemedicine during the COVID-19 pandemic: retrospective cohort study. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22:e20786.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7511224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32810841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alaboudi A, Atkins A, Sharp B, Balkhair A, Alzahrani M, Sunbul T. Barriers and challenges in adopting the Saudi telemedicine network: the perceptions of decision-makers of healthcare facilities in Saudi Arabia. J Infect Public Health. 2016;9:725–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27649882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Telemedicine: Opportunities and Developments in Member States. Report on the Second Global Survey on eHealth. Regional office: World Health Organization; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bashir A, Bastola DR. Perspectives of nurses toward telehealth efficacy and quality of health care: pilot study. JMIR Med Inform. 2018;6:e35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5993972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29802089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Betancourt JA, Rosenberg MA, Zevallos A, Brown JR, Mileski M. The impact of COVID-19 on telemedicine utilization across multiple service lines in the United States. Healthcare (Basel). 2020;8:380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7712432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33019667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Baalharith I, Al Sherim M, Almutairi SHG, Albaqami ASA. Telehealth and transformation of nursing care in Saudi Arabia: a systematic review. Int J Telemed Appl. 2022;2022:8426095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9553846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36249324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isautier JM, Copp T, Ayre J, et al. . People’s experiences and satisfaction with telehealth during the COVID-19 pandemic in Australia: cross-sectional survey study. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22:e24531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7732356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33156806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moynihan R, Sanders S, Michaleff ZA, et al. . Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on utilisation of healthcare services: a systematic review. BMJ Open. 2021;11:e045343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7969768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33727273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlBar AM, Hoque MR. Factors affecting cloud ERP adoption in Saudi Arabia: an empirical study. Inf Dev. 2019;35:150–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury MZ, Hossan MT, Shahjalal M, Hasan MK, Jang YM. A new 5G eHealth architecture based on optical camera communication: an overview, prospects, and applications. IEEE Consum Electron Mag. 2020;9:23–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Princess Nourah bint Abdulrahman University. Available at:
https://www.pnu.edu.sa/en/centers/kaauh/pages/health_care.aspx. Accessed January 11, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuschieri S. The STROBE guidelines. Saudi J Anaesth. 2019;13:S31–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6398292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30930717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peytremann-Bridevaux I, Scherer F, Peer L, et al. . Satisfaction of patients hospitalised in psychiatric hospitals: a randomised comparison of two psychiatric-specific and one generic satisfaction questionnaires. BMC Health Serv Res. 2006;6:108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1560120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16938136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazor KM, Clauser BE, Field T, Yood RA, Gurwitz JH. A demonstration of the impact of response bias on the results of patient satisfaction surveys. Health Serv Res. 2002;37:1403–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1464019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12479503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Etter JF, Perneger TV. Analysis of non-response bias in a mailed health survey. J Clin Epidemiol. 1997;50:1123–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9368520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross S, Grant A, Counsell C, Gillespie W, Russell I, Prescott R. Barriers to participation in randomised controlled trials: a systematic review. J Clin Epidemiol. 1999;52:1143–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10580777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boshuizen HC, Viet AL, Picavet HS, Botterweck A, van Loon AJ. Non-response in a survey of cardiovascular risk factors in the Dutch population: determinants and resulting biases. Public Health. 2006;120:297–308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16364384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gayet-Ageron A, Agoritsas T, Schiesari L, Kolly V, Perneger TV. Barriers to participation in a patient satisfaction survey: who are we missing? PLoS One. 2011;6:e26852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3202588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22046382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Napi NM, Zaidan AA, Zaidan BB, Albahri OS, Alsalem MA, Albahri AS. Medical emergency triage and patient prioritisation in a telemedicine environment: a systematic review. Health Technol. 2019;9:679–700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwamm LH. Telehealth: seven strategies to successfully implement disruptive technology and transform health care. Health Aff (Millwood). 2014;33:200–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24493761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaliyadan F, Amin TT, Kuruvilla J, Ali WH. Mobile teledermatology—patient satisfaction, diagnostic and management concordance, and factors affecting patient refusal to participate in Saudi Arabia. J Telemed Telecare. 2013;19:315–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24163295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed TJ, Baig M, Bashir MA, Gazzaz ZJ, Butt NS, Khan SA. Knowledge, attitudes, and perceptions related to telemedicine among young doctors and nursing staff at the King Abdul-Aziz University Hospital Jeddah, KSA. Niger J Clin Pract. 2021;24:464–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33851665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabesan S, Simcox K, Marr I. Medical oncology clinics through videoconferencing: an acceptable telehealth model for rural patients and health workers. Intern Med J. 2012;42:780–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21627743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alharbi KG, Aldosari MN, Alhassan AM, Alshallal KA, Altamimi AM, Altulaihi BA. Patient satisfaction with virtual clinic during the Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic in primary healthcare, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. J Family Community Med. 2021;28:48–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7927967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33679189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abrams DJ, Geier MR. A comparison of patient satisfaction with telehealth and on-site consultations: a pilot study for prenatal genetic counseling. J Genet Couns. 2006;15:199–205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16779676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nanda M., Sharma R. A review of patient satisfaction and experience with telemedicine: a virtual solution during and beyond the COVID-19 pandemic. Telemed J E Health. 2021;27:1325–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33719577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nochomovitz M, Sharma R. Is it time for a new medical specialty? The medical virtualist. JAMA. 2018;319:437–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29181539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasser AA, Alzahrani RM, Fellah CA, et al. . Measuring the patients’ satisfaction about telemedicine used in Saudi Arabia during the COVID-19 pandemic. Cureus. 2021;13:e13382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7972323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33754105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris NP. Virtual visits and the future of no-shows. J Gen Intern Med. 2020;35:2449–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7279631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32514899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saif U, Sangeetha R, Todd L, et al. . Why do patients miss their appointments at primary care clinics? J Fam Med Dis Prev. 2018;4:090.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkamel N, Jamal A, Alnobani O, et al. . Understanding the stakeholders’ preferences on a mobile application to reduce door to balloon time in the management of ST-elevated myocardial infarction patients—a qualitative study. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2020;20:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7457529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32867749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sykes Corporation. Survey Report: Americans’ perceptions of telemedicine in the era of COVID-19.
Available at https://www.sykes.com/resources/reports/2020-telehealth-survey/. [access date: May 7, 2021].</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>