<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314610</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Brain Arteriovenous Malformation Hemorrhage and Pituitary Adenoma in a COVID-19-Positive Patient.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67644</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67644</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67644</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67644</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Brain arteriovenous malformations (AVMs) are usually asymptomatic. They can cause intense pain or bleeding or lead to other serious medical problems. We present a rare case of a woman who presented with a severe headache and was brought to the emergency service for an intracerebral hemorrhage due to a ruptured AVM. During the surgery, a sellar mass was identified that was also resected. AVM showed vasculitis, endarteritis, endothelial damage, leukocyte plug, and damage to the vessel wall with fragmentation of the collagen and actin filaments. The sellar mass showed a non-functioning pituitary adenoma with hemorrhagic foci and necrosis as well as a proteinaceous vs. lipid material deposition with minimal vascular changes such as endothelial hyperplasia with minimal vasculitis and hyperplasia of reticular stellate cells, with positive glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP), which expressed low expression of luteinizing hormone (LH) and follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH), IL6, IL10, IL17, tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNFa), HIF1a, factor VIII (FVIII), platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF), vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), and VEGF receptor 2 (VEGFR2). The patient's polymerase chain reaction COVID-19 test was positive, and she died three days after the surgery procedure. In our knowledge of COVID-19 brain lesions and in the literature review, this was a rare case of a double pathology associated with COVID-19 infection characterized by rupture of the AVM with hemorrhages and brain infarcts associated with endarteritis, vessel wall injuries, and pituitary apoplexy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Nathal et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nathal</LastName><ForeName>Edgar</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Instituto Nacional de Neurología y Neurocirugía Manuel Velasco Suárez, Mexico City, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Villanueva-Castro</LastName><ForeName>Eliezer</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Instituto Nacional de Neurología y Neurocirugía Manuel Velasco Suárez, Mexico City, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ortiz-Plata</LastName><ForeName>Alma</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Experimental Neuropathology, Instituto Nacional de Neurología y Neurocirugía Manuel Velasco Suárez, Mexico City, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Serrano-Rubio</LastName><ForeName>Alejandro</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Instituto Nacional de Neurología y Neurocirugía Manuel Velasco Suárez, Mexico City, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tena Suck</LastName><ForeName>Martha Lilia</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neuropathology, Instituto Nacional de Neurología y Neurocirugía Manuel Velasco Suárez, Mexico City, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">brain arteriovenous malformation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrovascular disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pituitary adenoma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pituitary apoplexy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11417440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Acute ischemic and hemorrhagic stroke and COVID-19: case series. Fatehi P, Hesam-Shariati N, Abouzaripour M, Fathi F, Hesam Shariati MB. SN Compr Clin Med. 2020;2:2396–2401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7529351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33024934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerebrovascular disease in patients with COVID-19 infection: a case series from Lebanon. El Mawla Z, El Saddik G, Zeineddine M, Hassoun M, El Hajj T. Ann Med Surg (Lond) 2023;85:3701–3708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10328564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37427218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Intracerebral hemorrhage in young people: analysis of risk factors, location, causes, and prognosis. Ruíz-Sandoval JL, Cantú C, Barinagarrementeria F. Stroke. 1999;30:537–541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10066848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A systematic review of the frequency and prognosis of arteriovenous malformations of the brain in adults. Al-Shahi R, Warlow C. Brain. 2001;124:1900–1926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11571210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The natural history and predictive features of hemorrhage from brain arteriovenous malformations. da Costa L, Wallace MC, Ter Brugge KG, O'Kelly C, Willinsky RA, Tymianski M. Stroke. 2009;40:100–105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19008469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Recommendations for the management of intracranial arteriovenous malformations: a statement for healthcare professionals from a special writing group of the Stroke Council, American Stroke Association. Ogilvy CS, Stieg PE, Awad I, et al. Circulation. 2001;103:2644–2657.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11382737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hypoxia-induced hyperpermeability in brain microvessel endothelial cells involves VEGF-mediated changes in the expression of zonula occludens-1. Fischer S, Wobben M, Marti HH, Renz D, Schaper W. Microvasc Res. 2002;63:70–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11749074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interplay between VEGF and Nrf2 regulates angiogenesis due to intracranial venous hypertension. Li L, Pan H, Wang H, et al. Sci Rep. 2016;6:37338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5116754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27869147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pituitary apoplexy as a complication of COVID-19 infection. Hussain H, Janaka K, Muthukuda DT, Perera SG. Cureus. 2023;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10500954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37719628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SARS-CoV-2 infection, a risk factor for pituitary apoplexy? A case series and literature review. Hazzi C, Villemure-Poliquin N, Nadeau S, Champagne PO. Ear Nose Throat J. 2024;103:153–161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10261951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37291861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Role of PDGF-B and PDGFR-beta in recruitment of vascular smooth muscle cells and pericytes during embryonic blood vessel formation in the mouse. Hellström M, Kalén M, Lindahl P, Abramsson A, Betsholtz C. Development. 1999;126:3047–3055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10375497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Relationship between intratumoral hemorrhage and overexpression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) in pituitary adenoma. Arita K, Kurisu K, Tominaga A, et al.  https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15453394/ Hiroshima J Med Sci. 2004;53:23–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15453394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reductions in brain pericytes are associated with arteriovenous malformation vascular instability. Winkler EA, Birk H, Burkhardt JK, et al.  https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29303444/ J Neurosurg. 2018;129:1464–1474.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6033689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29303444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pericytes of the neurovascular unit: key functions and signaling pathways. Sweeney MD, Ayyadurai S, Zlokovic BV. Nat Neurosci. 2016;19:771–783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5745011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27227366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Risk factors for COVID-19-related mortality in people with type 1 and type 2 diabetes in England: a population-based cohort study. Holman N, Knighton P, Kar P, et al. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2020;8:823–833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7426091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32798471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 related neuroimaging findings: a signal of thromboembolic complications and a strong prognostic marker of poor patient outcome. Jain R, Young M, Dogra S, et al. J Neurol Sci. 2020;414:116923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7236667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32447193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>High risk of thrombosis in patients with severe SARS-CoV-2 infection: a multicenter prospective cohort study. Helms J, Tacquard C, Severac F, et al. Intensive Care Med. 2020;46:1089–1098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7197634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32367170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cross-talk between key players in patients with COVID-19 and ischemic stroke: a review on neurobiological insight of the pandemic. Kaushik P, Kaushik M, Parveen S, Tabassum H, Parvez S. Mol Neurobiol. 2020;57:4921–4928.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7434850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32813238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SARS-CoV-2 and spinal cord ischemia: a systematic review on clinical presentations, diagnosis, treatment, and outcomes. Sourani A, Vahdat N, Bowers CA, et al. Spine J. 2024;24:979–988.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38365009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathophysiology of SARS-CoV-2: targeting of endothelial cells renders a complex disease with thrombotic microangiopathy and aberrant immune response. The Mount Sinai COVID-19 autopsy experience. [PREPRINT] Bryce C, Grimes Z, Pujadas E, et al. medRxiv. 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SARS-CoV-2 infection and spontaneous spinal hemorrhage: a systematic review. Sourani A, Vahdat N, Son C, et al. Neurosurg Rev. 2023;46:300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37966587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Microvascular injury and hypoxic damage: emerging neuropathological signatures in COVID-19. Jaunmuktane Z, Mahadeva U, Green A, et al. Acta Neuropathol. 2020;140:397–400.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7340758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32638079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19: role of neutrophil extracellular traps in acute lung injury. Yaqinuddin A, Kvietys P, Kashir J. Respir Investig. 2020;58:419–420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7318928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32611518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The procoagulant pattern of patients with COVID-19 acute respiratory distress syndrome. Ranucci M, Ballotta A, Di Dedda U, et al. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1747–1751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 and the pituitary. Frara S, Allora A, Castellino L, di Filippo L, Loli P, Giustina A. Pituitary. 2021;24:465–481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8089131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33939057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pituitary apoplexy and COVID-19 vaccination: a case report and literature review. Aliberti L, Gagliardi I, Rizzo R, et al. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 2022;13:1035482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9712198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36465651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>