<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39312567</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of a collaborative model on community clinician confidence in child and adolescent mental health care, wellbeing, and access to child psychiatry expertise.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0310377</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0310377</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0310377</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0310377</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic was associated with an increase in child and adolescent mental health disorders, with subsequent worsening of patient access to specialist mental health care. Clinicians working in the community were faced with increased demands to diagnose and manage pediatric mental health disorders, without always having the confidence and knowledge to do so. We therefore developed COnnecting Mental-health PAediatric Specialists and community Services (COMPASS)-a collaborative model designed to upskill community clinicians in child and adolescent mental health care and provide them with better access to child and adolescent psychiatry expertise. COMPASS comprises (1) an online Community of Practice (CoP) with fortnightly one-hour sessions covering: anxiety; aggression and challenging behaviours; depression; self-harm and suicidality; eating disorders; and autism spectrum disorder/complex cases and (2) primary and secondary consultations for general practitioners and paediatricians with an experienced child psychiatrist. We aimed to assess the impact of COMPASS on community clinician self-reported confidence in: managing common child and adolescent mental health disorders (Objective 1, primary outcome); navigating the mental health care system (i.e. knowing how services are organised, accessed, and how to refer patients, Objective 2); diagnosing conditions (Objective 3); prescribing psychotropic medications (Objective 4) as well as the impact on, clinician practice and wellbeing (Objective 5) and outcomes of patients referred by COMPASS clinicians to the child psychiatrist (Objective 6).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We evaluated COMPASS in its first year, with COMPASS running from March to July 2021. Participating clinicians completed pre-post surveys evaluating change in Objectives 1 to 4 above, using study-designed measures. A purposive sample of clinicians was then invited to a semi-structured interview to understand their experience of COMPASS and its impacts on practice and wellbeing (Objective 5). We adopted an inductive approach to the qualitative analysis using the Framework Method. This involved selecting five random transcripts which were double coded and categorized, to generate an initial framework against which all subsequent transcripts were analysed. Themes and subthemes were generated from the data set, by reviewing the matrix and making connections within and between clinicians, codes and categories One child psychiatrist completed a 2-week logbook of the nature and outcomes of primary and secondary consultations (Objective 6).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">51 (86%) clinicians attended CoP sessions and completed pre-post surveys, with 92% recommending COMPASS to peers. Clinicians reported increased confidence in the pharmacological and non-pharmacological management of all conditions, most notably for management of self-harm. They also reported increased knowledge of how to navigate the mental health system and prescribe medications. Qualitative analysis (n = 27 interviews) found that COMPASS increased clinician wellbeing and reduced feelings of professional isolation and burnout. Over the 2-week snapshot, the child psychiatrist consulted on 22 patients and referred all back to the community clinician.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">COMPASS is associated with improved clinician confidence to manage child and adolescent mental health concerns, navigate the mental health system, improved clinician wellbeing, and reduced need for ongoing mental health care by specialists.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 D’Abaco et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>D'Abaco</LastName><ForeName>Elise</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Community Child Health, Royal Children's Hospital Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khano</LastName><ForeName>Sonia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Murdoch Children's Research Institute, Health Services, Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Services Research Unit, Royal Children's Hospital Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giles-Kaye</LastName><ForeName>Al</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Murdoch Children's Research Institute, Health Services, Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Melbourne Graduate School of Education, University of Melbourne Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dhaliwal</LastName><ForeName>Jag</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>North Western Melbourne Primary Health Network, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haslam</LastName><ForeName>Ric</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3598-775X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mental Health, Royal Children's Hospital Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prakash</LastName><ForeName>Chidambaram</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mental Health, Royal Children's Hospital Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hiscock</LastName><ForeName>Harriet</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3017-2770</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Community Child Health, Royal Children's Hospital Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Murdoch Children's Research Institute, Health Services, Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Services Research Unit, Royal Children's Hospital Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002665" MajorTopicYN="Y">Child Psychiatry</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001523" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Disorders</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006297" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Services Accessibility</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000296" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent Psychiatry</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008605" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Health Services</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008603" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003156" MajorTopicYN="N">Community Mental Health Services</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39312567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0310377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-23-14369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO. Adolescent Mental Health
2021.  [cited 2021 21 December]. Available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/adolescent-mental-health.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawrence D, Johnson S, Hafekost J, Boterhoven de Haan K, Sawyer M, Ainley J, et al.. The mental health of children and adolescents: Report on the second Australian child and adolescent survey of mental health and wellbeing. 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodsell B LD, Ainley J, Sawyer M, Zubrick SR, Maratos J Child and Adolescent Mental health and educational outcomes. An analysis of educational outcomes from Young Minds Matter: the second Australian Child and Adolescent Survey of Mental Health and Wellbeing. Perth: Graduate School of Education, The University of Western Australia.; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erath SA, Flanagan KS, Bierman KL. Social anxiety and peer relations in early adolescence: Behavioral and cognitive factors. Journal of abnormal child psychology. 2007;35:405–16. doi: 10.1007/s10802-007-9099-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10802-007-9099-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17265192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawrence D, Dawson V, Houghton S, Goodsell B, Sawyer MG. Impact of mental disorders on attendance at school. Australian Journal of Education. 2019;63(1):5–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranøyen I, Lydersen S, Larose TL, Weidle B, Skokauskas N, Thomsen PH, et al.. Developmental course of anxiety and depression from adolescence to young adulthood in a prospective Norwegian clinical cohort. European child &amp; adolescent psychiatry. 2018;27:1413–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29502316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodward LJ, Fergusson DM. Life course outcomes of young people with anxiety disorders in adolescence. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry. 2001;40(9):1086–93. doi: 10.1097/00004583-200109000-00018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00004583-200109000-00018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11556633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royal Commission into Victoria’s Mental Health System, Final Report, Summary and recommendations, Parl Paper No. 202, Session 2018–21 (document 1 of 6).
2021.  [Available from: https://finalreport.rcvmhs.vic.gov.au/download-report/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NHMRC. National Mental Health Commission: Monitoring mental health and suicide prevention reform: National Report 2020
2021.  [Available from: https://www.mentalhealthcommission.gov.au/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulraney M, Hiscock H, Sciberras E, Coghill D, Sawyer M. Mental health difficulties across childhood and mental health service use: findings from a longitudinal population-based study. The British Journal of Psychiatry. 2020;217(1):364–9. doi: 10.1192/bjp.2019.32</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.2019.32</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30810103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheek JA, Craig SS, West A, Lewena S, Hiscock H. Emergency department utilisation by vulnerable paediatric populations during the COVID-19 pandemic. Emergency Medicine Australasia. 2020;32(5):870–1. doi: 10.1111/1742-6723.13598</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1742-6723.13598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7404865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32705775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiscock H, Chu W, O’Reilly G, Freed GL, White M, Danchin M, et al.. Association between COVID-19 restrictions and emergency department presentations for paediatric mental health in Victoria, Australia. Australian Health Review. 2022;46(5):529–36. doi: 10.1071/AH22015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1071/AH22015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35787299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paton K, Gillam L, Warren H, Mulraney M, Coghill D, Efron D, et al.. Clinicians’ perceptions of the Australian Paediatric Mental Health Service System: Problems and solutions. Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry. 2021:0004867420984242. doi: 10.1177/0004867420984242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0004867420984242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33461341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenger E. Communities of practice: A brief introduction University of Oregon Scholars’ Bank2011 [Available from: https://scholarsbank.uoregon.edu/xmlui/handle/1794/11736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li LC, Grimshaw JM, Nielsen C, Judd M, Coyte PC, Graham ID. Evolution of Wenger’s concept of community of practice. Implementation Science. 2009;4(1):11. doi: 10.1186/1748-5908-4-11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1748-5908-4-11</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2654669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19250556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seibert S. The Meaning of a Healthcare Community of Practice. Nursing Forum. 2015;50(2):69–74. doi: 10.1111/nuf.12065</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nuf.12065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24392653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranmuthugala G, Plumb JJ, Cunningham FC, Georgiou A, Westbrook JI, Braithwaite J. How and why are communities of practice established in the healthcare sector? A systematic review of the literature. BMC Health Services Research. 2011;11(1):273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3219728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21999305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barwick MA, Peters J, Boydell K. Getting to uptake: do communities of practice support the implementation of evidence-based practice? J Can Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;18(1):16–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2651208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19270845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bower P, Gilbody S. Managing common mental health disorders in primary care: conceptual models and evidence base. Bmj. 2005;330(7495):839–42. doi: 10.1136/bmj.330.7495.839</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.330.7495.839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC556082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15817554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bower P, Gilbody S, Richards D, Fletcher J, Sutton A. Collaborative care for depression in primary care: making sense of a complex intervention: systematic review and meta-regression. The British Journal of Psychiatry. 2006;189(6):484–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17139031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bower P, Sibbald B. Systematic review of the effect of on-site mental health professionals on the clinical behaviour of general practitioners. Bmj. 2000;320(7235):614–7. doi: 10.1136/bmj.320.7235.614</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.320.7235.614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC27305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10698881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarvet B, Gold J, Bostic JQ, Masek BJ, Prince JB, Jeffers-Terry M, et al.. Improving Access to Mental Health Care for Children: The Massachusetts Child Psychiatry Access Project. Pediatrics. 2010;126(6):1191. doi: 10.1542/peds.2009-1340</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2009-1340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21059722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Thielke R, Payne J, Gonzalez N, Conde JG. A metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. J Biomed Inform. 2009;42(2):377–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2700030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18929686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Minor BL, Elliott V, Fernandez M, O’Neal L, et al.. The REDCap consortium: building an international community of software platform partners. Journal of biomedical informatics. 2019;95:103208. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103208</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7254481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31078660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiscock H O’Loughlin R Pelly R, Laird C, Holman J, Dalziel K, et al.. Strengthening care for children: pilot of an integrated general practitioner–paediatrician model of primary care in Victoria, Australia. Australian Health Review. 2020;44(4):569–75. doi: 10.1071/AH19177</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1071/AH19177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32045563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gale NK, Heath G, Cameron E, Rashid S, Redwood S. Using the framework method for the analysis of qualitative data in multi-disciplinary health research. BMC Medical Research Methodology. 2013;13(1):117. doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-13-117</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2288-13-117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3848812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24047204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Successful Qualitative Research: A Practical Guide for Beginners: SAGE Publications; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Straus JH, Sarvet B. Behavioral health care for children: the Massachusetts child psychiatry access project. Health Affairs. 2014;33(12):2153–61. doi: 10.1377/hlthaff.2014.0896</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2014.0896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25489033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gadomski AM, Wissow LS, Palinkas L, Hoagwood KE, Daly JM, Kaye DL. Encouraging and sustaining integration of child mental health into primary care: interviews with primary care providers participating in Project TEACH (CAPES and CAP PC) in NY. General Hospital Psychiatry. 2014;36(6):555–62. doi: 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2014.05.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2014.05.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4240770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24973125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walter HJ, Kackloudis G, Trudell EK, Vernacchio L, Bromberg J, DeMaso DR, et al.. Enhancing Pediatricians’ Behavioral Health Competencies Through Child Psychiatry Consultation and Education. Clinical Pediatrics. 2018;57(8):958–69. doi: 10.1177/0009922817738330</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0009922817738330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29082768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walter HJ, Vernacchio L, Trudell EK, Bromberg J, Goodman E, Barton J, et al.. Five-Year Outcomes of Behavioral Health Integration in Pediatric Primary Care. Pediatrics. 2019;144(1):07. doi: 10.1542/peds.2018-3243</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2018-3243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31186366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The National Children’s Mental Health and Wellbeing Strategy: Australian Government 2020 [1–109]. Available from: https://www.mentalhealthcommission.gov.au/mental-health-reform/childrens-mental-health-and-wellbeing-strategy.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>