<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39327668</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1864-0648</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of biophotonics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Biophotonics</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Blood Plasma Film Multifractal Scanning in COVID-19 Consequences Diagnostics.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e202400356</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e202400356</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jbio.202400356</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A 3D phase scanning method was applied to study blood plasma facies, generating layered polarization maps of the object field. The most sensitive parameters to changes in birefringence distribution were identified. Multifractal analysis using wavelet transforms and fractal dimension spectra provided specific insights into the scale self-similarity of the polarization maps. The multifractal spectra of ellipticity distributions were algorithmically derived, revealing that the third- and fourth-order statistical moments were most sensitive to changes in the supramolecular networks of the facies. These findings were successfully applied to differentiate post-COVID-19 effects with high accuracy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ushenko</LastName><ForeName>Alexander</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Electro-Optical &amp; Information Center, Taizhou Institute of Zhejiang University, Taizhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Optics and Publishing Department, Chernivtsi National University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pavlyukovich</LastName><ForeName>Natalia</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Clinical Pharmacology and Occupational Diseases, Bukovinian State Medical University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khukhlina</LastName><ForeName>Oksana</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Clinical Pharmacology and Occupational Diseases, Bukovinian State Medical University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pavlyukovich</LastName><ForeName>Olexander</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Forensic Medicine and Medical Law, Bukovinian State Medical University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soltys</LastName><ForeName>Iryna</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Optics and Publishing Department, Chernivtsi National University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dubolazov</LastName><ForeName>Alexander</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1051-2811</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Optics and Publishing Department, Chernivtsi National University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ushenko</LastName><ForeName>Yurii</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Shaoxing University, Shaoxing, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Computer Science Department, Chernivtsi National University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gordey</LastName><ForeName>Ivan</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Computer Science Department, Chernivtsi National University, Chernivtsi, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Electro-Optical &amp; Information Center, Taizhou Institute of Zhejiang University, Taizhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Zhebo</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Electro-Optical &amp; Information Center, Taizhou Institute of Zhejiang University, Taizhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bin</LastName><ForeName>Lin</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Optoelectronics, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2022.01/0034</GrantID><Agency>National Research Foundation of Ukraine</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2023.01/0174</GrantID><Agency>National Research Foundation of Ukraine</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>J Biophotonics</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101318567</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1864-063X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood plasma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diagnostics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polarization</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39327668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jbio.202400356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>V. Shankaran, J. T. Walsh, Jr., and D. J. Maitland, “Comparative Study of Polarized Light Propagation in Biological Tissues,” Journal of Biomedical Optics 7, no. 3 (2002): 300–306.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. V. Tuchin, L. Wang, and D. A. Zimnyakov, “Optical Polarization in Biomedical Applications,” in Biological and Medical Physics, Biomedical Engineering (Berlin Heidelberg: Springer‐Verlag, 2006), 281.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. V. Tuchin, Tissue Optics: Light Scattering Methods and Instruments for Medical Diagnosis, 3rd ed. (Bellingham, WA: Society of Photo‐Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE), 2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Ghosh, “Tissue Polarimetry: Concepts, Challenges, Applications, and Outlook,” Journal of Biomedical Optics 16 (2011): 110801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. L. Jacques, “Polarized Light Imaging of Biological Tissues,” in Handbook of Biomedical Optics2, eds. D. Boas, C. Pitris, and N. Ramanujam (Hoboken: CRC Press, 2011), 649–669.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Layden, N. Ghosh, and I. A. Vitkin, “Quantitative Polarimetry for Tissue Characterization and Diagnosis,” in Advanced Biophotonics: Tissue Optical Sectioning, eds. R. K. Wang and V. Tuchin (Boca Raton: CRC Press, 2013), 73–108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Vitkin, N. Ghosh, and A. de Martino, “Tissue Polarimetry,” in Photonics: Scientific Foundations, Technology and Applications, ed. D. L. Andrews (Hoboken: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd., 2015), 239–321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. L. Jacques, R. J. Roman, and K. Lee, “Imaging Superficial Tissues With Polarized Light,” Lasers in Surgery and Medicine 26 (2000): 119–129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. V. Wang, G. L. Coté, and S. L. Jacques, “Special Section Guest Editorial: Tissue Polarimetry,” Journal of Biomedical Optics 7 (2002): 278.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. R. Lee, C. Lotz, F. Kai Groeber Becker, S. Dembski, and T. Novikova, “Digital Histology With Mueller Polarimetry and Fast DBSCAN,” Applied Optics 61, no. 32 (2022): 9616–9624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Kim, H. R. Lee, R. Ossikovski, A. Malfait‐Jobart, D. Lamarque, and T. Novikova, “Optical Diagnosis of Gastric Tissue Biopsies With Mueller Microscopy and Statistical Analysis,” Journal of the European Optical Society Rapid Publications 18, no. 2 (2022): 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. R. Lee, C. Lotz, F. K. G. Becker, S. Dembski, and T. Novikova, “Digital Histology With Mueller Microscopy: How to Mitigate an Impact of Tissue Cut Thickness Fluctuations,” Journal of Biomedical Optics 24, no. 7 (2019): 076004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Li, H. R. Lee, S. Chandel, et al., “Analysis of Tissue Microstructure With Mueller Microscopy: Logarithmic Decomposition and Monte Carlo Modeling,” Journal of Biomedical Optics 25, no. 1 (2020): 015002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. R. Lee, T. S. H. Yoo, P. Li, et al., “Mueller Microscopy of Anisotropic Scattering Media: Theory and Experiments,” Proceedings of the SPIE 10677 (2018): 1067718.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Ma, H. He, and J. C. Ramella‐Roman, “Mueller Matrix Microscopy,” in Polarized Light in Biomedical Imaging and Sensing, eds. J. C. Ramella‐Roman and T. Novikova (Cham: Springer, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. I. Zabolotna, S. V. Pavlov, A. G. Ushenko, and A. O. Karachevtsev, “System of the Phase Tomography of Optically Anisotropic Polycrystalline Films of Biological Fluids,” Proceedings of the SPIE 9166 (2014): 916616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. K. Wang and V. V. Tuchin, eds., Advanced Biophotonics: Tissue Optical Sectioning (London: CRC Press, Taylor &amp; Francis Group, 2013), 681.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Vitkin, N. Ghosh, and A. de Martino, “Tissue Polarimetry” in Photonics: Scientific Foundations, Technology and Applications, vol. IV, ed. D. L. Andrews (Hoboken, New Jersey: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc, 2015), 239–321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. A. Ushenko, V. A. Ushenko, A. V. Dubolazov, V. O. Balanetskaya, and N. I. Zabolotna, “Mueller‐Matrix Diagnostics of Optical Properties of Polycrystalline Networks of Human Blood Plasma,” Optics and Spectroscopy 112, no. 6 (2012): 884–892.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. V. Dubolazov, N. V. Pashkovskaya, Y. A. Ushenko, Y. F. Marchuk, V. A. Ushenko, and O. Y. Novakovskaya, “Birefringence Images of Polycrystalline Films of Human Urine in Early Diagnostics of Kidney Pathology,” Applied Optics 55 (2016): B85–B90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. G. Ushenko, N. V. Pashkovskaya, O. V. Dubolazov, Y. A. Ushenko, Y. F. Marchuk, and V. O. Ushenko, “Mueller Matrix Images of Polycrystalline Films of Human Biological Fluids,” Romanian Reports in Physics 67, no. 4 (2015): 1467–1479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. Garazdyuk, V. T. Bachinskyi, and O. Y. Vanchulyak, “Polarization‐Phase Images of Liquor Polycrystalline Films in Determining Time of Death,” Applied Optics 55, no. 12 (2016): B67–B71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Ushenko, A. Sdobnov, and A. Dubolazov, “Stokes‐Correlometry Analysis of Biological Tissues With Polycrystalline Structure,” IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Quantum Electronics 25, no. 12 (2018): 1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. A. Ushenko, T. M. Boychuk, V. T. Bachynsky, and O. P. Mincer, “Diagnostics of Structure and Physiological State of Birefringent Biological Tissues: Statistical, Correlation and Topological Approaches,” in Handbook of Coherent‐Domain Optical Methods: Biomedical Diagnostics, Environmental Monitoring, and Materials Science, ed. V. V. Tuchin (New York: Springer, 2013), 107–148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Ushenko, V. Balanetcka, N. I. Piddubna, and B. P. Olyinichenko, “Statistical, Fractal, and Singular Processing of Phase Images of Hominal Blood Plasma During the Diagnostics of Breast Cancer,” Journal of Flow Visualization and Image Processing 18, no. 3 (2011): 185–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. O. Ushenko, Y. Ya, O. G. Tomka, and A. V. Pridiy, “Wavelet Analysis for Mueller Matrix Images of Biological Crystal Networks,” Semiconductor Physics Quantum Electronics &amp; Optoelectronics 12 (2009): 391–398.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Ushenko, Y. Tomka, O. Dubolazov, V. O. Balanetska, A. V. Karachevtsev, and A.‐P. Angelsky, “Wavelet‐Analysis for Laser Images of Blood Plasma,” Advances in Electrical and Computer Engineering 11, no. 2 (2011): 55–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. O. Ushenko, “Spatial‐Frequency Polarization Phasometry of Biological Polycrystalline Networks,” Optical Memory and Neural Networks 22, no. 1 (2013): 56–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. A. Ushenko, N. D. Pavlyukovich, and L. Trifonyuk, “Spatial‐Frequency Azimuthally Stable Cartography of Biological Polycrystalline Networks,” International Journal of Optics 2013 (2013): 683174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. A. Ushenko, A. Y. Sdobnov, W. D. Mishalov, and A. V. Dubolazov, “Biomedical Applications of Jones‐Matrix Tomography to Polycrystalline Films of Biological Fluids,” Journal of Innovative Optical Health Sciences 12, no. 6 (2019): 1950017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. G. Ushenko, O. V. Dubolazov, V. O. Ushenko, and O. Y. Novakovskaya, “Fourier Polarimetry of Human Skin in the Tasks of Differentiation of Benign and Malignant Formations,” Applied Optics 55, no. 12 (2016): B56–B60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. Volodimir, A. Sdobnov, A. Syvokorovskaya, and A. Dubolazov, “3D Mueller‐Matrix Diffusive Tomography of Polycrystalline Blood Films for Cancer Diagnosis,” Photonics 5, no. 4 (2018): 54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Peyvasteh, L. Tryfonyuk, V. Ushenko, and A.‐V. Syvokorovskaya, “3D Mueller‐Matrix‐Based Azimuthal Invariant Tomography of Polycrystalline Structure Within Benign and Malignant Soft‐Tissue Tumours,” Laser Physics Letters 17, no. 11 (2020): 115606.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. A. Ushenko, B. T. Hogan, A. Dubolazov, et al., “3D Mueller Matrix Mapping of Layered Distributions of Depolarization Degree for Analysis of Prostate Adenoma and Carcinoma Diffuse Tissues,” Scientific Reports 11, no. 1 (2021): 5162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Ushenko, J. Zheng, M. Gorsky, et al., “3D Digital Holographic Polarimetry of Diffuse Optically Anisotropic Biological Tissue Object Fields,” Frontiers in Physics 11 (2023): 1288935.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Ushenko, J. Zheng, A. Litvinenko, et al., “3D Digital Polarization‐Holographic Wavelet Histology in Determining the Duration of Mechanical Damage to the Myocardium,” Journal of Biophotonics 17, no. 3 (2024): e202300372.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Sdobnov, V. A. Ushenko, L. Trifonyuk, et al., “Mueller‐Matrix Imaging Polarimetry Elevated by Wavelet Decomposition and Polarization‐Singular Processing for Analysis of Specific Cancerous Tissue Pathology,” Journal of Biomedical Optics 28, no. 10 (2023): 102903.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. G. Ushenko, A. Sdobnov, I. V. Soltys, et al., “Insights Into Polycrystalline Microstructure of Blood Films With 3D Mueller Matrix Imaging Approach,” Scientific Reports 14, no. 1 (2024): 13679.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. B. Mandelbrot, Fractals and Multifractals: Noise, Turbulence and Galaxies (New York: Springer+Verlag, 1989).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. V. Angelsky, A. Ushenko, Y. A. Ushenko, V. P. Pishak, and A. P. Peresunko, “Statistical, Correlation, and Topological Approaches in Diagnostics of the Structure and Physiological State of Birefringent Biological Tissues,” in Handbook of Photonics for Biomedical Science, ed. V. V. Tuchin (London: CRC Press, Taylor and Francis Publishing, 2010), 283–322.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. F. Muzy, E. Bacry, and A. Arneodo, “The Multifractal Formalism Revisited With Wavelets,” International Journal of Bifurcation and Chaos 4 (1994): 245–302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Grassberger and I. Procaccia, “Measuring The Strangeness of Strange Attractors,” Physica 9D 9 (1983): 189–230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. G. E. Hentschel and I. Procaccia, “The Infinite Number of Generalized Dimensions of Fractals and Strange Attractors,” Applied Mathematics 8 (1983): 435–444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. R. Jones, “New Calculus for the Treatment of Optical Systems. VII. Properties of the N‐Matrices,” Journal of the Optical Society of America 38 (1948): 671–685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. M. A. Azzam, “Propagation of Partially Depolarized Light Through Anisotropic Media With or Without Depolarization. A Differential 4 × 4 Matrix Calculus,” Journal of the Optical Society of America 68 (1978): 1756–1767.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Arteaga and A. Canillas, “Analytic Inversion of the Mueller‐Jones Polarization Matrices for Homogeneous Media,” Optics Letters 35 (2010): 559–561.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Daubechies, Wavelets on the Interval, in Progress in Wavelet Analysis and Applications: Proceedings of the International Conference Wavelets and Applications, eds. Y. Meyer and S. Roques (Toulouse, France: Atlantica Seguier Frontieres, 1992), 95–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Farge, “Wavelet Transforms and Their Applications to Turbulence,” Annual Review of Fluid Mechanics 24, no. 1 (1992): 395–458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Vladimir, J. B. Wang, and X. H. Yan, “Human Blood Plasma Crystal and Molecular Biocolloid Textures – Dismetabolism and Genetic Breaches,” Natural Science Journal – Xiangtan University 23 (2001): 118–127.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. A. Killeen, N. Ossina, R. C. McGlennen, et al., “Protein Self‐Organization Patterns in Dried Serum Reveal Changes in B‐Cell Disorders,” Molecular Diagnosis &amp; Therapy 10 (2006): 371–380.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Marchesini, A. Bertoni, S. Andreola, E. Melloni, and A. E. Sichirollo, “Extinction and Absorption Coefficients and Scattering Phase Functions of Human Tissues In Vitro,” Applied Optics 28, no. 12 (1989): 2318–2324.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. K. Edwards, J. T. Gier, K. E. Nelson, and R. D. Roddick, “Integrating Sphere for Imperfectly Diffuse Samples,” Journal of the Optical Society of America 51 (1961): 1279–1288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. Goodman, “Statistical Properties of Laser Speckle Patterns,” in Statistical Properties of Laser Speckle Patterns (Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer, 1975).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. P. Robinson, Principles of Forensic Medicine (Hong Kong, China: Oxford University Press, 1996).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Bahraini and A. Dorgalaleh, “The Impact of SARS‐CoV‐2 Infection on Blood Coagulation and Fibrinolytic Pathways: A Review of Prothrombotic Changes Caused by COVID‐19,” Seminars in Thrombosis and Hemostasis 48, no. 1 (2022): 19–30.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>