<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39325238</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2150-5551</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>17</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nano-micro letters</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nanomicro Lett</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Tailoring Light-Matter Interactions in Overcoupled Resonator for Biomolecule Recognition and Detection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>10</StartPage><MedlinePgn>10</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">10</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40820-024-01520-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Plasmonic nanoantennas provide unique opportunities for precise control of light-matter coupling in surface-enhanced infrared absorption (SEIRA) spectroscopy, but most of the resonant systems realized so far suffer from the obstacles of low sensitivity, narrow bandwidth, and asymmetric Fano resonance perturbations. Here, we demonstrated an overcoupled resonator with a high plasmon-molecule coupling coefficient (μ) (OC-Hμ resonator) by precisely controlling the radiation loss channel, the resonator-oscillator coupling channel, and the frequency detuning channel. We observed a strong dependence of the sensing performance on the coupling state, and demonstrated that OC-Hμ resonator has excellent sensing properties of ultra-sensitive (7.25% nm<sup>-1</sup>), ultra-broadband (3-10 μm), and immune asymmetric Fano lineshapes. These characteristics represent a breakthrough in SEIRA technology and lay the foundation for specific recognition of biomolecules, trace detection, and protein secondary structure analysis using a single array (array size is 100 × 100 µm<sup>2</sup>). In addition, with the assistance of machine learning, mixture classification, concentration prediction and spectral reconstruction were achieved with the highest accuracy of 100%. Finally, we demonstrated the potential of OC-Hμ resonator for SARS-CoV-2 detection. These findings will promote the wider application of SEIRA technology, while providing new ideas for other enhanced spectroscopy technologies, quantum photonics and studying light-matter interactions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Dongxiao</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117583, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Intelligent Sensors and MEMS (CISM), National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117608, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Hong</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117583, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Intelligent Sensors and MEMS (CISM), National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117608, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Zhihao</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117583, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Intelligent Sensors and MEMS (CISM), National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117608, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Cheng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117583, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Intelligent Sensors and MEMS (CISM), National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117608, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Chengkuo</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117583, Singapore. elelc@nus.edu.sg.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Intelligent Sensors and MEMS (CISM), National University of Singapore, Singapore, 117608, Singapore. elelc@nus.edu.sg.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Nanomicro Lett</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101727940</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2150-5551</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biosensing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Light-matter interaction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Overcoupled</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Plasmonic nanoantennas</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Surface-enhanced infrared absorption</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no interest confict. They have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39325238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11427657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40820-024-01520-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s40820-024-01520-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>T. Weber, L. Kühner, L. Sortino, A. BenMhenni, N.P. Wilson et al., Intrinsic strong light–matter coupling with self-hybridized bound states in the continuum in van der Waals metasurfaces. Nat. Mater. 22, 970–976 (2023). 10.1038/s41563-023-01580-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10390334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37349392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A.H. Dorrah, F. Capasso, Tunable structured light with flat optics. Science 376, eabi6860 (2022). 10.1126/science.abi6860</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35446661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Neubrech, C. Huck, K. Weber, A. Pucci, H. Giessen, Surface-enhanced infrared spectroscopy using resonant nanoantennas. Chem. Rev. 117, 5110–5145 (2017). 10.1021/acs.chemrev.6b00743</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28358482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Xu, Z. Ren, H. Zhou, J. Zhou, C.P. Ho et al., Expanding chiral metamaterials for retrieving fingerprints via vibrational circular dichroism. Light Sci. Appl. 12, 154 (2023). 10.1038/s41377-023-01186-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10290984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37357238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Xu, Z. Ren, H. Zhou, J. Zhou, D. Li et al., Near-field coupling induced less chiral responses in chiral metamaterials for surface-enhanced vibrational circular dichroism. Adv. Funct. Mater. 34, 2314482 (2024). 10.1002/adfm.202314482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Li, S. Zhang, T. Zentgraf, Nonlinear photonic metasurfaces. Nat. Rev. Mater. 2, 17010 (2017). 10.1038/natrevmats.2017.10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. Aslam, V.G. Rao, S. Chavez, S. Linic, Catalytic conversion of solar to chemical energy on plasmonic metal nanostructures. Nat. Catal. 1, 656–665 (2018). 10.1038/s41929-018-0138-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Santiago-Cruz, S.D. Gennaro, O. Mitrofanov, S. Addamane, J. Reno et al., Resonant metasurfaces for generating complex quantum states. Science 377, 991–995 (2022). 10.1126/science.abq8684</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36007052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Wang, M. Ramezani, A.I. Väkeväinen, P. Törmä, J.G. Rivas et al., The rich photonic world of plasmonic nanoparticle arrays. Mater. Today 21, 303–314 (2018). 10.1016/j.mattod.2017.09.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Kozuch, K. Ataka, J. Heberle, Surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy. Nat. Rev. Meth. Primers 3, 70 (2023). 10.1038/s43586-023-00253-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Li, C. Xu, J. Xie, C. Lee, Research progress in surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy: from performance optimization, sensing applications, to system integration. Nanomaterials 13, 2377 (2023). 10.3390/nano13162377</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10458771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37630962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Dregely, F. Neubrech, H. Duan, R. Vogelgesang, H. Giessen, Vibrational near-field mapping of planar and buried three-dimensional plasmonic nanostructures. Nat. Commun. 4, 2237 (2013). 10.1038/ncomms3237</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3731659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23892519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. John-Herpin, A. Tittl, L. Kühner, F. Richter, S.H. Huang et al., Metasurface-enhanced infrared spectroscopy: an abundance of materials and functionalities. Adv. Mater. 35, e2110163 (2023). 10.1002/adma.202110163</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35638248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Altug, S.H. Oh, S.A. Maier, J. Homola, Advances and applications of nanophotonic biosensors. Nat. Nanotechnol. 17(1), 5–16 (2022). 10.1038/s41565-021-01045-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35046571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Hui, C. Yang, D. Li, X. He, H. Huang et al., Infrared plasmonic biosensor with tetrahedral DNA nanostructure as carriers for label-free and ultrasensitive detection of miR-155. Adv. Sci. 8, e2100583 (2021). 10.1002/advs.202100583</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8373097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34155822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. John-Herpin, D. Kavungal, L. von Mücke, H. Altug, Infrared metasurface augmented by deep learning for monitoring dynamics between all major classes of biomolecules. Adv. Mater. 33, e2006054 (2021). 10.1002/adma.202006054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33615570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Rodrigo, A. Tittl, N. Ait-Bouziad, A. John-Herpin, O. Limaj et al., Resolving molecule-specific information in dynamic lipid membrane processes with multi-resonant infrared metasurfaces. Nat. Commun. 9, 2160 (2018). 10.1038/s41467-018-04594-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5986821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29867181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Adato, H. Altug, In-situ ultra-sensitive infrared absorption spectroscopy of biomolecule interactions in real time with plasmonic nanoantennas. Nat. Commun. 4, 2154 (2013). 10.1038/ncomms3154</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3759039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23877168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Paggi, A. Fabas, H. El Ouazzani, J.P. Hugonin, N. Fayard et al., Over-coupled resonator for broadband surface enhanced infrared absorption (SEIRA). Nat. Commun. 14, 4814 (2023). 10.1038/s41467-023-40511-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10412556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37558692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Tittl, A. Leitis, M. Liu, F. Yesilkoy, D.-Y. Choi et al., Imaging-based molecular barcoding with pixelated dielectric metasurfaces. Science 360, 1105–1109 (2018). 10.1126/science.aas9768</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29880685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Yesilkoy, E.R. Arvelo, Y. Jahani, M. Liu, A. Tittl et al., Ultrasensitive hyperspectral imaging and biodetection enabled by dielectric metasurfaces. Nat. Photonics 13, 390–396 (2019). 10.1038/s41566-019-0394-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Aigner, A. Tittl, J. Wang, T. Weber, Y. Kivshar et al., Plasmonic bound states in the continuum to tailor light–matter coupling. Sci. Adv. 8, eadd4816 (2022). 10.1126/sciadv.add4816</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9733921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36490330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Rosas, K.A. Schoeller, E. Chang, H. Mei, M.A. Kats et al., Metasurface-enhanced mid-infrared spectrochemical imaging of tissues. Adv. Mater. 35, 2301208 (2023). 10.1002/adma.202301208</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10524888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37186328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhou, D. Li, Z. Ren, C. Xu, L.-F. Wang et al., Surface plasmons-phonons for mid-infrared hyperspectral imaging. Sci. Adv. 10, eado3179 (2024). 10.1126/sciadv.ado3179</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11135386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38809968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Rodrigo, O. Limaj, D. Janner, D. Etezadi, F.J. García de Abajo et al., Mid-infrared plasmonic biosensing with graphene. Science 349, 165–168 (2015). 10.1126/science.aab2051</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26160941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Wu, A.B. Khanikaev, R. Adato, N. Arju, A. Ali Yanik et al., Fano-resonant asymmetric metamaterials for ultrasensitive spectroscopy and identification ofmolecular monolayers. Nat. Mater. 11, 69–75 (2012). 10.1038/nmat3161</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22081082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhou, X. Hui, D. Li, D. Hu, X. Chen et al., Metal-organic framework-surface-enhanced infrared absorption platform enables simultaneous on-chip sensing of greenhouse gases. Adv. Sci. 7, 2001173 (2020). 10.1002/advs.202001173</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7578855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33101855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Miao, T.S. Luk, P.Q. Liu, Liquid-metal-based nanophotonic structures for high-performance SEIRA sensing. Adv. Mater. 34, e2107950 (2022). 10.1002/adma.202107950</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34991178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Hwang, M. Kim, J. Yu, J. Lee, J.H. Choi et al., Ultrasensitive molecule detection based on infrared metamaterial absorber with vertical nanogap. Small Methods 5, e2100277 (2021). 10.1002/smtd.202100277</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34927875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Yi, E.-M. You, S.-Y. Ding, Z.-Q. Tian, Unveiling the molecule-plasmon interactions in surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy. Natl. Sci. Rev. 7, 1228–1238 (2020). 10.1093/nsr/nwaa054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8288858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34692147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Ren, Z. Zhang, J. Wei, B. Dong, C. Lee, Wavelength-multiplexed hook nanoantennas for machine learning enabled mid-infrared spectroscopy. Nat. Commun. 13, 3859 (2022). 10.1038/s41467-022-31520-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9256719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35790752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Dong, X. Yang, C. Zhang, B. Cerjan, L. Zhou et al., Nanogapped Au antennas for ultrasensitive surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy. Nano Lett. 17, 5768–5774 (2017). 10.1021/acs.nanolett.7b02736</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28787169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Yoo, F. de León-Pérez, M. Pelton, I.-H. Lee, D.A. Mohr et al., Ultrastrong plasmon–phonon coupling via epsilon-near-zero nanocavities. Nat. Photonics 15, 125–130 (2021). 10.1038/s41566-020-00731-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Li, A. Yadav, H. Zhou, K. Roy, P. Thanasekaran et al., Advances and applications of metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) in emerging technologies: a comprehensive review. Glob. Chall. 8, 2300244 (2023). 10.1002/gch2.202300244</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10862192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38356684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Li, H. Zhou, X. Hui, X. He, H. Huang et al., Multifunctional chemical sensing platform based on dual-resonant infrared plasmonic perfect absorber for on-chip detection of poly(ethyl cyanoacrylate). Adv. Sci. 8, e2101879 (2021). 10.1002/advs.202101879</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8529490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34423591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Chen, R. Adato, H. Altug, Dual-band perfect absorber for multispectral plasmon-enhanced infrared spectroscopy. ACS Nano 6, 7998–8006 (2012). 10.1021/nn3026468</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22920565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R.A. Maniyara, D. Rodrigo, R. Yu, J. Canet-Ferrer, D.S. Ghosh et al., Tunable plasmons in ultrathin metal films. Nat. Photonics 13, 328–333 (2019). 10.1038/s41566-019-0366-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Jangid, F.U. Richter, M.L. Tseng, I. Sinev, S. Kruk et al., Spectral tuning of high-harmonic generation with resonance-gradient metasurfaces. Adv. Mater. 36, e2307494 (2024). 10.1002/adma.202307494</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37933748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>F.U. Richter, I. Sinev, S. Zhou, A. Leitis, S.H. Oh et al., Gradient high-Q dielectric metasurfaces for broadband sensing and control of vibrational light–matter coupling. Adv. Mater. 36, e2314279 (2024). 10.1002/adma.202314279</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38511549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Leitis, A. Tittl, M. Liu, B.H. Lee, M.B. Gu et al., Angle-multiplexed all-dielectric metasurfaces for broadband molecular fingerprint retrieval. Sci. Adv. 5, eaaw2871 (2019). 10.1126/sciadv.aaw2871</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6527437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31123705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Wang, T. Weber, A. Aigner, S.A. Maier, A. Tittl, Mirror-coupled plasmonic bound states in the continuum for tunable perfect absorption. Laser Photonics Rev. 17, 2300294 (2023). 10.1002/lpor.202300294</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Chen, D. Li, H. Zhou, T. Liu, X. Mu, A hybrid graphene metamaterial absorber for enhanced modulation and molecular fingerprint retrieval. Nanoscale 15, 14100–14108 (2023). 10.1039/d3nr02830e</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37581407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Vogt, C. Huck, F. Neubrech, A. Toma, D. Gerbert et al., Impact of the plasmonic near- and far-field resonance-energy shift on the enhancement of infrared vibrational signals. Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys. 17, 21169–21175 (2015). 10.1039/c4cp04851b</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25516198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J.-H. Park, A. Ndao, W. Cai, L. Hsu, A. Kodigala et al., Symmetry-breaking-induced plasmonic exceptional points and nanoscale sensing. Nat. Phys. 16, 462–468 (2020). 10.1038/s41567-020-0796-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Adato, A. Artar, S. Erramilli, H. Altug, Engineered absorption enhancement and induced transparency in coupled molecular and plasmonic resonator systems. Nano Lett. 13, 2584–2591 (2013). 10.1021/nl400689q</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23647070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhou, Z. Ren, C. Xu, L. Xu, C. Lee, MOF/polymer-integrated multi-hotspot mid-infrared nanoantennas for sensitive detection of CO2 gas. Nano-Micro Lett. 14, 207 (2022). 10.1007/s40820-022-00950-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9588146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36271989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Wei, Y. Li, Y. Chang, D.M.N. Hasan, B. Dong et al., Ultrasensitive transmissive infrared spectroscopy via loss engineering of metallic nanoantennas for compact devices. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 11, 47270–47278 (2019). 10.1021/acsami.9b18002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31769956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Li, H. Zhou, Z. Chen, Z. Ren, C. Xu et al., Ultrasensitive molecular fingerprint retrieval using strongly detuned overcoupled plasmonic nanoantennas. Adv. Mater. 35, e2301787 (2023). 10.1002/adma.202301787</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37204145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhou, D. Li, Z. Ren, X. Mu, C. Lee, Loss-induced phase transition in mid-infrared plasmonic metamaterials for ultrasensitive vibrational spectroscopy. InfoMat 4, e12349 (2022). 10.1002/inf2.12349</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Xu, Z. Ren, B. Dong, X. Liu, C. Wang et al., Nanometer-scale heterogeneous interfacial sapphire wafer bonding for enabling plasmonic-enhanced nanofluidic mid-infrared spectroscopy. ACS Nano 14, 12159–12172 (2020). 10.1021/acsnano.0c05794</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32812748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhou, Z. Ren, D. Li, C. Xu, X. Mu et al., Dynamic construction of refractive index-dependent vibrations using surface plasmon-phonon polaritons. Nat. Commun. 14, 7316 (2023). 10.1038/s41467-023-43127-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10640644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37952033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Cerjan, X. Yang, P. Nordlander, N.J. Halas, Asymmetric aluminum antennas for self-calibrating surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy. ACS Photonics 3, 354–360 (2016). 10.1021/acsphotonics.6b00024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Chen, T.D. Dao, S. Ishii, M. Aono, T. Nagao, Infrared aluminum metamaterial perfect absorbers for plasmon-enhanced infrared spectroscopy. Adv. Funct. Mater. 25, 6637–6643 (2015). 10.1002/adfm.201501151</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Neubrech, A. Pucci, T.W. Cornelius, S. Karim, A. García-Etxarri et al., Resonant plasmonic and vibrational coupling in a tailored nanoantenna for infrared detection. Phys. Rev. Lett. 101, 157403 (2008). 10.1103/PhysRevLett.101.157403</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18999639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Bertolotti, Waves and fields in optoelectronics. Opt. Acta Int. J. Opt. 32, 748 (1985). 10.1080/716099690</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P.A. Thomas, W.J. Tan, H.A. Fernandez, W.L. Barnes, A new signature for strong light–matter coupling using spectroscopic ellipsometry. Nano Lett. 20, 6412–6419 (2020). 10.1021/acs.nanolett.0c01963</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7608940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32709208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>M.F. Limonov, M.V. Rybin, A.N. Poddubny, Y.S. Kivshar, Fano resonances in photonics. Nat. Photonics 11(9), 543–554 (2017). 10.1038/nphoton.2017.142</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Dolado, C. Maciel-Escudero, E. Nikulina, E. Modin, F. Calavalle et al., Remote near-field spectroscopy of vibrational strong coupling between organic molecules and phononic nanoresonators. Nat. Commun. 13, 6850 (2022). 10.1038/s41467-022-34393-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9652397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36369225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Durmaz, Y. Li, A.E. Cetin, A multiple-band perfect absorber for SEIRA applications. Sens. Actuat. B Chem. 275, 174–179 (2018). 10.1016/j.snb.2018.08.053</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Liu, S. Iketani, Y. Guo, J.F.-W. Chan, M. Wang et al., Striking antibody evasion manifested by the Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2. Nature 602, 676–681 (2022). 10.1038/s41586-021-04388-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35016198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Zhu, C. Zhuang, K. Chu, L. Zhang, H. Zhao et al., Safety and immunogenicity of a live-attenuated influenza virus vector-based intranasal SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in adults: randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 1 and 2 trials. Lancet Respir. Med. 10, 749–760 (2022). 10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00131-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9135375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35644168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Cheong, H. Yu, C.Y. Lee, J.U. Lee, H.J. Choi et al., Fast detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA via the integration of plasmonic thermocycling and fluorescence detection in a portable device. Nat. Biomed. Eng. 4, 1159–1167 (2020). 10.1038/s41551-020-00654-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8202505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33273713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Wu, M. Guo, C. Gu et al., Rapid and ultrasensitive electromechanical detection of ions, biomolecules and SARS-CoV-2 RNA in unamplified samples. Nat. Biomed. Eng. 6, 276–285 (2022). 10.1038/s41551-021-00833-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35132229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Li, H. Zhou, X. Hui, X. He, X. Mu, Plasmonic biosensor augmented by a genetic algorithm for ultra-rapid, label-free, and multi-functional detection of COVID-19. Anal. Chem. 93, 9437–9444 (2021). 10.1021/acs.analchem.1c01078</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8262173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34170680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>S.X. Leong, Y.X. Leong, E.X. Tan, H.Y.F. Sim, C.S.L. Koh et al., Noninvasive and point-of-care surface-enhanced Raman scattering (SERS)-based Breathalyzer for mass screening of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) under 5 min. ACS Nano 16, 2629–2639 (2022). 10.1021/acsnano.1c09371</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35040314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Yao, Y. Song, Y. Chen, N. Wu, J. Xu et al., Molecular architecture of the SARS-CoV-2 virus. Cell 183, 730-738.e13 (2020). 10.1016/j.cell.2020.09.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7474903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32979942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>X.X. Han, R.S. Rodriguez, C.L. Haynes, Y. Ozaki, B. Zhao, Surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy. Nat. Rev. Meth. Primers 1, 87 (2022). 10.1038/s43586-021-00083-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Liu, Z. Zhang, J. Zhou, W. Liu, G. Zhou et al., Artificial intelligence-enhanced waveguide “photonic nose”-augmented sensing platform for VOC gases in mid-infrared. Small 20, e2400035 (2024). 10.1002/smll.202400035</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38576121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Liu, Y. Ma, X. Liu, J. Zhou, C. Xu et al., Larger-than-unity external optical field confinement enabled by metamaterial-assisted comb waveguide for ultrasensitive long-wave infrared gas spectroscopy. Nano Lett. 22, 6112–6120 (2022). 10.1021/acs.nanolett.2c01198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35759415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhou, Z. Zhang, B. Dong, Z. Ren, W. Liu et al., Midinfrared spectroscopic analysis of aqueous mixtures using artificial-intelligence-enhanced metamaterial waveguide sensing platform. ACS Nano 17, 711–724 (2023). 10.1021/acsnano.2c10163</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36576121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Hu, D. Mengu, D.C. Tzarouchis, B. Edwards, N. Engheta et al., Diffractive optical computing in free space. Nat. Commun. 15, 1525 (2024). 10.1038/s41467-024-45982-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10879514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38378715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Zhang, X. Liu, H. Zhou, S. Xu, C. Lee, Advances in machine-learning enhanced nanosensors: from cloud artificial intelligence toward future edge computing at chip level. Small Struct. 5, 2300325 (2024). 10.1002/sstr.202300325</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Bylinkin, M. Schnell, M. Autore, F. Calavalle, P. Li et al., Real-space observation of vibrational strong coupling between propagating phonon polaritons and organic molecules. Nat. Photonics 15, 197–202 (2021). 10.1038/s41566-020-00725-3</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>