<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39324558</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1520-6300</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>American journal of human biology : the official journal of the Human Biology Council</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Am J Hum Biol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on the Sex Ratio at Birth in Ireland.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e24159</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e24159</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ajhb.24159</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The sex ratio at birth (SRB), calculated as male divided by total live births, is an important indicator of population health. Typically, male live births slightly outnumber female live births. Population events, including pandemics, can alter the SRB, with effects sometimes evident 9 months post-event, potentially due to changes in sexual behavior and/or stress levels. This study investigates the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the SRB in the Republic of Ireland.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Publicly available monthly live birth data for Ireland were obtained from the Central Statistics Office for the period 2015 to 2021. Time series analysis predicted the SRB for 2020 using data from 2015 to 2019, with comparisons made between observed and predicted values.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In December 2020, 9 months after the March 2020 COVID-19 declaration, the observed SRB sharply fell to 49.44% (97.80 males for every 100 females), below the 95% prediction interval of 50.31% to 52.15%, significantly deviating from the expected male predominance. December 2020 also recorded the lowest average daily number of births (n = 145) in the study period.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The sharp decline in the SRB in December 2020, alongside the lowest birth count, suggests reduced sexual intercourse at the population level, particularly in March 2020, aligning with recommendations from Ireland's Health Service Executive (HSE). The HSE advocated precautionary measures such as limiting partnered sex in March 2020 to mitigate the spread of COVID-19. These findings highlight the pandemic's potential impact on population dynamics and stress the importance of SRB monitoring as a low-cost and readily available health indicator, especially during national crises.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). American Journal of Human Biology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Masukume</LastName><ForeName>Gwinyai</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9251-0264</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, Physiotherapy and Sports Science, University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Non</LastName><ForeName>Amy L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9781-2985</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anthropology, University of California San Diego, La Jolla, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cleaver</LastName><ForeName>Peyton</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anthropology, University of California San Diego, La Jolla, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grech</LastName><ForeName>Victor</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3373-0478</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academic Department of Paediatrics, Medical School, Mater Dei Hospital, Msida, Malta.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Am J Hum Biol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8915029</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1042-0533</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ireland</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sex ratio at birth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sexual intercourse</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">stress</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39324558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ajhb.24159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdoli, A. 2020. “The COVID‐19 Stress May Influence on the Sex Ratio at Birth.” Journal of Maternal‐Fetal &amp; Neonatal Medicine 1–6: 4043–4048. https://doi.org/10.1080/14767058.2020.1846181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arima, H. 2023. “Seasonal Variation in Air Pollutant Levels and Its Effects on the Sex Ratio at Birth on Fukue Island, Japan.” BMC Public Health 23, no. 1: 2471. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889‐023‐17418‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Björk, J., K. Modig, F. Kahn, and A. Ahlbom. 2021. “Revival of Ecological Studies During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” European Journal of Epidemiology 36, no. 12: 1225–1229. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10654‐021‐00830‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruckner, T. A., B. Bustos, C. Margerison, A. Gemmill, J. Casey, and R. Catalano. 2023. “Selection in Utero Against Male Twins in the United States Early in the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” American Journal of Human Biology 35, no. 3: e23830. https://doi.org/10.1002/ajhb.23830.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calleja, T. 2020. “The Assassinations of Investigative Journalists Daphne Caruana Galizia and Veronica Guerin and the Male‐to‐Female Birth Ratio.” Early Human Development 141, no. 104: 950. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2019.104950.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catalano, R., T. Bruckner, E. Anderson, and J. B. Gould. 2005. “Fetal Death Sex Ratios: A Test of the Economic Stress Hypothesis.” International Journal of Epidemiology 34, no. 4: 944–948. https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyi081.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catalano, R., T. Bruckner, J. A. Casey, A. Gemmill, C. Margerison, and T. Hartig. 2021. “Twinning During the Pandemic: Evidence of Selection in Utero.” Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health 9, no. 1: 374–382. https://doi.org/10.1093/emph/eoab033.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chao, F., P. Gerland, A. R. Cook, and L. Alkema. 2019. “Systematic Assessment of the Sex Ratio at Birth for all Countries and Estimation of National Imbalances and Regional Reference Levels.” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 116, no. 19: 9303–9311. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1812593116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID‐19 Excess Mortality Collaborators. 2022. “Estimating Excess Mortality due to the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Systematic Analysis of COVID‐19‐Related Mortality, 2020‐21.” Lancet 399, no. 10334: 1513–1536. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140‐6736(21)02796‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dáil Éireann. 2020. Emergency Measures in the Public Interest (Covid‐19) Act 2020. https://www.oireachtas.ie/en/bills/bill/2020/4/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis, D. L., M. B. Gottlieb, and J. R. Stampnitzky. 1998. “Reduced Ratio of Male to Female Births in Several Industrial Countries: A Sentinel Health Indicator?” JAMA 279, no. 13: 1018–1023. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.279.13.1018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desjardins, A., N. McCarthy, D. Hollingsworth, P. Garvey, K. O'Donnell, and D. Igoe. 2023. “The Impact of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on the Notification of Sexually Transmitted Infections in Ireland [Scientific Poster].” STI Surveillance Reports. https://web.archive.org/web/20240315183242/https://www.hpsc.ie/a‐z/sexuallytransmittedinfections/publications/stireports/The%20Impact%20of%20the%20COVID19%20Pandemic%20on%20the%20Notification%20of%20Sexually%20Transmitted%20Infections%20in%20Ireland.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elsmén, E., M. Steen, and L. Hellström‐Westas. 2004. “Sex and Gender Differences in Newborn Infants: Why Are Boys at Increased Risk?” Journal of Men's Health and Gender 1, no. 4: 303–311. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmhg.2004.09.010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>General Register Office. 2021. “Annual Report of an tArd‐Chláraitheoir to the Minister for Social Protection on the Operation of the Civil Registration Acts for 2020.” https://www.gov.ie/pdf/?file=https://assets.gov.ie/205846/67de407d‐3ff5‐4aad‐8029‐4527d7620f0e.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghaznavi, C., T. Kawashima, Y. Tanoue, et al. 2022. “Changes in Marriage, Divorce and Births During the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Japan.” BMJ Global Health 7, no. 5: e007866. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh‐2021‐007866.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graunt, J. 1676. Natural and Political Observations Mentioned in a Following Index, and Made Upon the Bills of Mortality. London: John Martyn. https://wellcomecollection.org/works/jt43sbkc.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grech, V., and H. Scherb. 2021. “No Local Birth Sex Ratio Changes Following the August 2019 Shootings in Montgomery County, Ohio and in El Paso County, Texas.” Medical Principles and Practice 31: 83–87. https://doi.org/10.1159/000521338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerrero, R. 1974. “Association of the Type and Time of Insemination Within the Menstrual Cycle With the Human Sex Ratio at Birth.” New England Journal of Medicine 291, no. 20: 1056–1059. https://doi.org/10.1056/nejm197411142912004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Service Executive. 2020. Sex and Coronavirus (COVID‐19). https://web.archive.org/web/20200401192632/https://www.sexualwellbeing.ie/sexual‐health/sex‐and‐coronavirus/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Healthcare Pricing Office (HPO). 2021. Perinatal Statistics Report, 2019. Health Service Executive (HSE). https://www.hpo.ie/latest_hipe_nprs_reports/NPRS_2019/Perinatal_Statistics_Report_2019.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Healthcare Pricing Office (HPO). 2022. Perinatal Statistics Report, 2020. Health Service Executive (HSE). https://www.hpo.ie/latest_hipe_nprs_reports/NPRS_2020/Perinatal_Statistics_Report_2020.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyland, P., M. Shevlin, O. McBride, et al. 2020. “Anxiety and Depression in the Republic of Ireland During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica 142, no. 3: 249–256. https://doi.org/10.1111/acps.13219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyndman, R. J., and G. Athanasopoulos. 2018. Forecasting: Principles and Practice. Melbourne, Australia: OTexts.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inoue, Y., and T. Mizoue. 2022. “A Preliminary Analysis of the Secondary Sex Ratio Decline After the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Japan.” American Journal of Human Biology 34: e23750. https://doi.org/10.1002/ajhb.23750.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>James, W. H. 2003. “Sex Ratios of Births Conceived During Wartime.” Human Reproduction 18, no. 5: 1133–1134. https://doi.org/10.1093/humrep/deg220.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jukic, A. M., D. D. Baird, C. R. Weinberg, D. R. McConnaughey, and A. J. Wilcox. 2013. “Length of Human Pregnancy and Contributors to Its Natural Variation.” Human Reproduction 28, no. 10: 2848–2855. https://doi.org/10.1093/humrep/det297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennelly, B., M. O'Callaghan, D. Coughlan, et al. 2020. “The COVID‐19 Pandemic in Ireland: An Overview of the Health Service and Economic Policy Response.” Health Policy and Technology 9, no. 4: 419–429. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.hlpt.2020.08.021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitamura, K., R. Ae, and M. Kosami. 2021. “Survey of Pregnancy and Contraceptive Awareness and Behavior During the COVID‐19 Pandemic and Efforts to Raise Awareness and Create Educational Material for Youth.” [COVID‐19 no ryuukouka ni okeru, ninshin, hinin nitaisuru ishikitokoudou no jittaichousa oyobi jakunensha heno keihatsu/kyouzaisakusei no torikumi, in Japanese.] The Effect of Self‐Restraint During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Survey of Unexpected Pregnancies and a Study for the Establishment of Appropriate Support and Provision Systems for Women's Health: 78–171. https://mhlw‐grants.niph.go.jp/system/files/report_pdf/20CA2062‐buntan4‐1_1.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lerchl, A. 1998. “Seasonality of Sex Ratio in Germany.” Human Reproduction 13, no. 5: 1401–1402. https://doi.org/10.1093/humrep/13.5.1401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macfarlane, A., N. Dattani, R. Gibson, et al. 2019. “Births and Their Outcomes by Time, Day and Year: A Retrospective Birth Cohort Data Linkage Study.” Health Services and Delivery Research 7, no. 18: 1–268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masukume, G., S. M. O'Neill, A. S. Khashan, L. C. Kenny, and V. Grech. 2017. “The Terrorist Attacks and the Human Live Birth Sex Ratio: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Acta Medica (Hradec Králové) 60, no. 2: 59–65. https://doi.org/10.14712/18059694.2017.94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masukume, G., M. Ryan, R. Masukume, D. Zammit, V. Grech, and W. Mapanga. 2022. “COVID‐19 Onset Reduced the Sex Ratio at Birth in South Africa.” PeerJ 10: e13985. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.13985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masukume, G., M. Ryan, R. Masukume, et al. 2023. “COVID‐19 Induced Birth Sex Ratio Changes in England and Wales.” PeerJ 11: e14618. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.14618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercer, C. H., S. Clifton, J. Riddell, et al. 2021. “Impacts of COVID‐19 on Sexual Behaviour in Britain: Findings From a Large, Quasi‐Representative Survey (Natsal‐COVID).” Sexually Transmitted Infections 98: 469–477. https://doi.org/10.1136/sextrans‐2021‐055210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikulec, A., I. Rosset, and E. Żądzińska. 2023. “Economic Stress Affects the Human Sex Ratio: A Retest of the Trivers–Willard Hypothesis in Poland.” Anthropological Review 86, no. 3: 87–108. https://doi.org/10.18778/1898‐6773.86.3.06.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Msemburi, W., A. Karlinsky, V. Knutson, S. Aleshin‐Guendel, S. Chatterji, and J. Wakefield. 2023. “The WHO Estimates of Excess Mortality Associated With the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Nature 613, no. 7942: 130–137. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586‐022‐05522‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng, R., T. Y. J. Chow, and W. Yang. 2021. “News Media Narratives of Covid‐19 Across 20 Countries: Early Global Convergence and Later Regional Divergence.” PLoS One 16, no. 9: e0256358. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0256358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obel, C., T. B. Henriksen, N. J. Secher, B. Eskenazi, and M. Hedegaard. 2007. “Psychological Distress During Early Gestation and Offspring Sex Ratio.” Human Reproduction 22, no. 11: 3009–3012. https://doi.org/10.1093/humrep/dem274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onyeaka, H., C. K. Anumudu, Z. T. Al‐Sharify, E. Egele‐Godswill, and P. Mbaegbu. 2021. “COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Review of the Global Lockdown and Its Far‐Reaching Effects.” Science Progress 104, no. 2: 368504211019854. https://doi.org/10.1177/00368504211019854.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavić, D. 2024. “Sex Ratio at Birth After Concurrent Events of Earthquakes and the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Croatia.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 21, no. 5: 572. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph21050572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearce, N. 2011. “Epidemiology in a Changing World: Variation, Causation and Ubiquitous Risk Factors.” International Journal of Epidemiology 40, no. 2: 503–512. https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyq257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philip, R. K., H. Purtill, E. Reidy, et al. 2020. “Unprecedented Reduction in Births of Very Low Birthweight (VLBW) and Extremely Low Birthweight (ELBW) Infants During the COVID‐19 Lockdown in Ireland: A ‘Natural Experiment’ Allowing Analysis of Data From the Prior Two Decades.” BMJ Global Health 5, no. 9: e003075. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh‐2020‐003075.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafter, K. 2022. “Taoisigh and Addressing the Nation.” Administration 70, no. 3: 127–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Retnakaran, R., and C. Ye. 2020. “Outcome of the 2016 United States Presidential Election and the Subsequent Sex Ratio at Birth in Canada: An Ecological Study.” BMJ Open 10, no. 2: e031208. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen‐2019‐031208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saadat, M. 2021. “Sex Ratio at Birth in COVID‐19 Era: A Report From Iran.” EXCLI Journal 20: 1499–1501. https://doi.org/10.17179/excli2021‐4257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tkachenko, A. V., A. Khalil, and I. Tepla. 2021. “Multiple Pregnancy.” In The EBCOG Postgraduate Textbook of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology, vol. 1, 147–158. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trivers, R. L., and D. E. Willard. 1973. “Natural Selection of Parental Ability to Vary the Sex Ratio of Offspring.” Science 179, no. 4068: 90–92. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.179.4068.90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wignall, L., E. Portch, M. McCormack, et al. 2021. “Changes in Sexual Desire and Behaviors Among UK Young Adults During Social Lockdown due to COVID‐19.” Journal of Sex Research 58, no. 8: 976–985. https://doi.org/10.1080/00224499.2021.1897067.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, Z., and J. M. McGoogan. 2020. “Characteristics of and Important Lessons From the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Outbreak in China: Summary of a Report of 72 314 Cases From the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention.” JAMA 323, no. 13: 1239–1242. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2020.2648.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>