<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39327265</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-198X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pediatric nephrology (Berlin, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Nephrol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Seroprevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in children with nephrotic syndrome and chronic kidney disease: a cross-sectional study from India.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00467-024-06534-y</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">There is a paucity of literature on the seroprevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies among pediatric patients with underlying kidney disorders; few serosurveys among healthy children have shown seropositivity of 20-65% after different waves of infections.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study had a cross-sectional design and was conducted between January 2023 and July 2023; 163 children and adolescents (1-18 years) with nephrotic syndrome and chronic kidney disease (CKD) were screened for Anti-Spike SARS-COV-2 IgG antibodies as detected by a quantitative chemiluminescence immunoassay. Children with nephrotic syndrome, both steroid sensitive (SSNS) and steroid resistant (SRNS) were enrolled during disease remission. Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 seropositivity status was done with age, gender, disease type, treatment duration, immunosuppressants, previous SARS-CoV-2 infection, and immunization status.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Of 163 children (63.8% boys) with median age of 9 years; 101 (62%) had underlying nephrotic syndrome (61 SSNS and 40 SRNS), and 62 (38%) children had CKD. Seroprotective titers for SARS-COV2 antibodies were present in 100 (61.3%) children. The median titers for all patients were 37.1 BAU/mL; for nephrotic syndrome they were 27.1 BAU/mL and for CKD they were 76.7 BAU/mL (p = 0.0033). A total of 43 (26.4%) children had high positive antibody levels (&gt; 200 BAU/ml). Among those with nephrotic syndrome 60.7% with SSNS and 43.5% SRNS had seropositive titers. Only 4 (2.5%) children had a history of previous COVID infection and 6 (3.7%) were vaccinated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In a largely unvaccinated population of children with nephrotic syndrome and CKD, 61.3% were seropositive for SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibody indicating a past asymptomatic infection; titers were significantly higher in CKD compared to nephrotic syndrome.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to International Pediatric Nephrology Association.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Richa</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pediatric Nephrology, Department of Pediatrics, Maulana Azad Medical College and Lok Nayak Hospital, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mantan</LastName><ForeName>Mukta</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6922-6548</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pediatric Nephrology, Department of Pediatrics, Maulana Azad Medical College and Lok Nayak Hospital, New Delhi, India. muktamantan@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahajan</LastName><ForeName>Akanksha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pediatric Nephrology, Department of Pediatrics, Maulana Azad Medical College and Lok Nayak Hospital, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tyagi</LastName><ForeName>Vernika</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pediatric Nephrology, Department of Pediatrics, Maulana Azad Medical College and Lok Nayak Hospital, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goswami</LastName><ForeName>Binita</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Maulana Azad Medical College and Lok Nayak Hospital, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Nephrol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8708728</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0931-041X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CKD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-COV2 antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Serosurvey</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Steroid resistant nephrotic syndrome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Steroid sensitive nephrotic syndrome</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39327265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00467-024-06534-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00467-024-06534-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>National Disaster Management Authority. Government of India (2021) Guidelines on operationalization of covid care service for children and adolescents. https://ndma.gov.in/covid/MoHFW-Medical-Health</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morello W, Vianello FA, Proverbio E, Peruzzi L, Pasini A, Montini G (2022) COVID-19 and idiopathic nephrotic syndrome in children: systematic review of the literature and recommendations from a highly affected area. Pediatr Nephrol 37:757–764</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00467-021-05330-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34687377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artborg A, Caldinelli A, Wijkström J, Nowak A, Fored M, Stendahl M et al (2023) Risk factors for COVID-19 hospitalization and mortality in patients with chronic kidney disease: a nationwide cohort study. Clin Kidney J 17:sfad283</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ckj/sfad283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38186903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10768790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhinder OS, Swarnim S, Mantan M, Dabas A, Ahlawat RS (2022) Chronic Kidney Disease and COVID-19: Outcomes of hospitalised adults from a tertiary care centre in North India. Med J Armed Forces India 79:S68–S74</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mjafi.2021.12.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35169379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8830751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winterberg PD, Ford ML (2017) The effect of chronic kidney disease on T cell alloimmunity. Curr Opin Organ Transplant 22:22–28</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MOT.0000000000000375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27926546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5412080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kemper MJ, Altrogge H, Ganeshow R, Wiefel DE (2002) Serum levels of immunoglobulins and IgG subclasses in steroid sensitive nephrotic syndrome. Pediatr Nephrol 17:413–417</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00467-001-0817-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12107805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han JW, Lee KY, Hwang JY, Koh DK, Lee J (2010) Antibody status in children with steroid sensitive nephrotic syndrome. Yonsei Med J 51:239–243</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3349/ymj.2010.51.2.239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20191016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2824870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahan N, Brahma A, Kumar MS, Bagepally BS, Ponnaiah M, Bhatnagar T et al (2022) Seroprevalence of IgG antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 in India, March 2020 to August 2021: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Infect Dis 116:59–67</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.12.353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34968773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>George CE, Inbaraj LR, Rajukutty S, Joan RF, Suseeladevi AK, Muthuraj S et al (2022) Seroprevalence of COVID-19 infection among vaccine naïve population after the second surge (June 2020) in a rural district of South India: A community-based cross-sectional study. PLoS One 17:e0265236</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0265236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35271669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8912234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajagopal PM, Sil S, Dinesh P, Shiju S, Arunkumar DP, Ramaiah SS et al (2024) Assessing the burden of COVID-19 among children aged 6–14 years in Karnataka, India: A cross-sectional survey. Indian J Community Med 49:110–114</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/ijcm.ijcm_60_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38425984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10900468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misra P, Kant S, Guleria R, Rai SK, Kishore S, Baidya S et al (2022) Serological prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibody among children and young age group (between 2 and 17 years) in India: an interim result from a large multicentric population-based seroepidemiological study. J Family Med Prim Care 11:2816–2823</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_2274_21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36119298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9480647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boey L, Roelants M, Merckx J, Hens N, Desombere I, Duysburgh L (2022) Age-dependent seroprevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in school-aged children from areas with low and high community transmission. Eur J Pediatr 181:571–578</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-021-04222-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34455523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mastrangelo A, Morello W, Vidal E, Guzzo I, AnnicchiaricoPetruzzelli L, Benetti E et al (2021) Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic in Children with CKD or Immunosuppression. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol 16:449–451</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2215/CJN.13120820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33318026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinha A, Bagga A, Banerjee S, Mishra K, Mehta A, Agarwal I et al (2021) Expert group of indian society of pediatric nephrology. steroid sensitive nephrotic syndrome: revised guidelines. Indian Pediatr 58:461–481</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13312-021-2217-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33742610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8139225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) CKD Work Group (2024) KDIGO 2024 Clinical Practice Guideline for the Evaluation and Management of Chronic Kidney Disease. Kidney Int 105:S117–S314</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.kint.2023.10.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khadilkar V, Yadav S, Agrawal KK, Tamboli S, Banerjee M, Cherian A, Goyal JP, Khadilkar A, Kumaravel V, Mohan V, Narayanappa D (2015) Revised IAP growth charts for height, weight and body mass index for 5-to 18-year-old Indian children. Indian Pediatr 52:47–55</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13312-015-0566-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25638185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (2006) WHO Child Growth Standards: Length/Height-for-Age, Weight-for-Age, Weight-for-Length, Weight-for-Height and Body Mass Index-for-Age: Methods and Development. World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murhekar MV, Bhatnagar T, Thangaraj JWV, Saravanakumar V, Kumar MS, Selvaraju S et al (2021) SARS-CoV-2 sero-prevalence among general population and healthcare workers in India, June 2020-July 2021. PLoS Med 18:e1003877</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34890407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8726494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Family Welfare. Government of India (2022) Guidelines for Covid-19 vaccination of children between 12–14 years of age. https://covid19.india.gov.in/document-category/ministry-of-health-and-family-welfare/page/25/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JM, Kronbichler A, Shin JI, Oh J (2021) Current understandings in treating children with steroid-resistant nephrotic syndrome. Pediatr Nephrol 36:747–761</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00467-020-04476-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32086590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chanchlani R, Parekh RS (2016) Ethnic Differences in Childhood Nephrotic Syndrome. Front Pediatr 4:39</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fped.2016.00039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27148508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4835686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantan M, Pandharikar N, Yadav S, Chakravarti A, Sethi GR (2013) Seroprotection for hepatitis B in children with nephrotic syndrome. Pediatr Nephrol 28:2125–2130</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00467-013-2538-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23800800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasudevan A, Mantan M, Krishnamurthy S et al (2020) Managing Children With Renal Diseases During the COVID-19 Pandemic. Indian Pediatr 57:641–651</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13312-020-1893-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32727941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7387253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith BK, Janowski AB, Danis JE, Harvey IB, Zhao H, Dai YN et al (2021) Seroprevalence of SARS-CoV-2 Antibodies in Children and Adults in St. Louis, Missouri, USA. mSphere 6:e01207-e1220</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murhekar MV, Bhatnagar T, Thangaraj JW, Saravanakumar V, Kumar MS, Selvaraju S et al (2021) SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence among the general population and healthcare workers in India, December 2020–January 2021. Int J Infect Dis 108:145–155</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.05.040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34022338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8132496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alshami A, Al Attas R, Azzam A, Mohammed A, Al-Quhaidan N (2021) Detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in pediatric kidney transplant patients. BMC Nephrol 22:123</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12882-021-02325-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33827461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8025893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nailescu C, Khalid M, Wilson AC, Amanat F, Arregui S, Canas J et al (2020) Assessment of Seroconversion to SARS-CoV-2 in a Cohort of Pediatric Kidney Transplant Recipients. Front Pediatr 8:601327</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fped.2020.601327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33194930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7661782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia X, Gesualdo P, Geno Rasmussen C, Alkanani AA, He L, Dong F et al (2021) Prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 Antibodies in Children and Adults with Type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes Technol Ther 23:517–521</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/dia.2020.0609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33544017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8252893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messaaoui A, Hajselova L, Tenoutasse S (2021) Anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in new-onset type 1 diabetes in children during pandemic in Belgium. J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab 34:1319–1322</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/jpem-2021-0289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34280962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walters HM, Mian Z, Thomas L, Cerise J, Eberhard BA, Pagano E et al (2022) Seroprevalence and clinical outcomes of SARS-CoV-2 in paediatric patients with rheumatic disease. Rheumatology (Oxford) 61:SI112-SI119</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waterfield T, Watson C, Moore R, Ferris K, Tonry C, Watt A et al (2021) Seroprevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in children: a prospective multicentre cohort study. Arch Dis Child 106:680–686</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2020-320558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33172887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamei K, Ogura M, Sato M, Nishi K, Shoji K, Funaki T et al (2023) Immunogenicity and safety of SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine in patients with nephrotic syndrome receiving immunosuppressive agents. Pediatr Nephrol 38:1099–1106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00467-022-05633-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35913562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Alós L, Hansen CB, AlmagroArmenteros JJ, Madsen JR, Heftdal LD, Hasselbalch RB et al (2023) Previous immunity shapes immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 booster vaccination and Omicron breakthrough infection risk. Nat Commun 14:5624</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-41342-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37699890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10497567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>