<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39332819</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1520-4812</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>35</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bioconjugate chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bioconjug Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Tyrosinase-Mediated Conjugation for Antigen Display on Ferritin Nanoparticles.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1608</StartPage><EndPage>1617</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1608-17</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.4c00387</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Ferritin (Ft) nanoparticles have become versatile platforms for displaying antigens, being a promising technology for vaccine development. While genetic fusion has traditionally been the preferred method for antigen display, concerns about improper folding and steric hindrance that may compromise vaccine efficacy or stability have prompted alternative approaches. Bioconjugation offers the advantage of preserving native protein structure and function, with recent advancements improving efficiency and specificity. In this study, we used tyrosinase (TYR) to bioconjugate the receptor binding domain of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, tagged with a tyrosine (RBD-Y), to native cysteines on Ft, resulting in RBD-Y-Ft nanoparticles. We quantified available cysteines on ferritin using Ellman's assay and monitored their reduction during the reactions. Denaturing analytics (via SDS-PAGE, Western blot, and LC-TOF-MS) confirmed the formation of RBD-Y-Ft monomers with an expected molecular weight of 46 kDa. Mass photometry and HPLC estimated a molecular weight of RBD-Y-Ft nanoparticles of 680 kDa, which was higher than that of nonfunctionalized ferritin (480 kDa), indicating successful binding of up to eight RBD-Y antigens per 24-mer Ft nanoparticle. This work enhances our understanding of how Ft nanoparticles can be engineered to present antigens, leveraging them as a robust scaffold for producing tailored-made candidate vaccines in a timely manner.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rodrigues</LastName><ForeName>Margarida Q</ForeName><Initials>MQ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6584-8331</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>iBET, Instituto de Biologia Experimental e Tecnológica, Apartado 12, 2781-901 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ITQB NOVA, Instituto de Tecnologia Química e Biológica António Xavier, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Av. da República, 2780-157 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patão</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>iBET, Instituto de Biologia Experimental e Tecnológica, Apartado 12, 2781-901 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ITQB NOVA, Instituto de Tecnologia Química e Biológica António Xavier, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Av. da República, 2780-157 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thomaz</LastName><ForeName>Mónica</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>iBET, Instituto de Biologia Experimental e Tecnológica, Apartado 12, 2781-901 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ITQB NOVA, Instituto de Tecnologia Química e Biológica António Xavier, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Av. da República, 2780-157 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nunes</LastName><ForeName>Tiago</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>iBET, Instituto de Biologia Experimental e Tecnológica, Apartado 12, 2781-901 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ITQB NOVA, Instituto de Tecnologia Química e Biológica António Xavier, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Av. da República, 2780-157 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alves</LastName><ForeName>Paula M</ForeName><Initials>PM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1445-3556</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>iBET, Instituto de Biologia Experimental e Tecnológica, Apartado 12, 2781-901 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ITQB NOVA, Instituto de Tecnologia Química e Biológica António Xavier, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Av. da República, 2780-157 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roldão</LastName><ForeName>António</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>iBET, Instituto de Biologia Experimental e Tecnológica, Apartado 12, 2781-901 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ITQB NOVA, Instituto de Tecnologia Química e Biológica António Xavier, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Av. da República, 2780-157 Oeiras, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P41 GM103311</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Bioconjug Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9010319</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1043-1802</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors
declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39332819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11487507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.4c00387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Smith D. M.; Simon J. K.; Baker J. R. Jr. Applications of Nanotechnology for Immunology. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2013, 13 (8), 592–605. 10.1038/nri3488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nri3488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7097370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23883969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He D.; Marles-Wright J. Ferritin Family Proteins and Their Use in Bionanotechnology. New Biotechnol. 2015, 32 (6), 651–657. 10.1016/j.nbt.2014.12.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nbt.2014.12.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4571993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25573765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoshnejad M.; Parhiz H.; Shuvaev V. V.; Dmochowski I. J.; Muzykantov V. R. Ferritin-Based Drug Delivery Systems: Hybrid Nanocarriers for Vascular Immunotargeting. J. Controlled Release 2018, 282, 13–24. 10.1016/j.jconrel.2018.02.042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jconrel.2018.02.042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6008199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29522833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigues M. Q.; Alves P. M.; Roldão A. Functionalizing Ferritin Nanoparticles for Vaccine Development. Pharmaceutics 2021, 13 (10), 1621.10.3390/pharmaceutics13101621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics13101621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8540537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34683914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houser K. V.; Chen G. L.; Carter C.; Crank M. C.; Nguyen T. A.; Burgos Florez M. C.; Berkowitz N. M.; Mendoza F.; Hendel C. S.; Gordon I. J.; Coates E. E.; Vazquez S.; Stein J.; Case C. L.; Lawlor H.; Carlton K.; Gaudinski M. R.; Strom L.; Hofstetter A. R.; Liang C. J.; Narpala S.; Hatcher C.; Gillespie R. A.; Creanga A.; Kanekiyo M.; Raab J. E.; Andrews S. F.; Zhang Y.; Yang E. S.; Wang L.; Leung K.; Kong W.-P.; Freyn A. W.; Nachbagauer R.; Palese P.; Bailer R. T.; McDermott A. B.; Koup R. A.; Gall J. G.; Arnold F.; Mascola J. R.; Graham B. S.; Ledgerwood J. E.; Casazza J.; Holman L.; Ola A. O.; Costner P.; Cunningham J.; Larkin B.; Novik L.; Saunders J.; Whalen W.; Wang X.; Eshun A. M.; Taylor A.; Cheng K. C.; Laurencot C.; Cox J. H.; Sitar S.; Le L.; Pittman I.; Vasilenko O.; Rothwell R. S.; Yamshchikov G.; Burch E.; Hickman S.; Trofymenko O.; Boyd C.; Apte P.; Cartagena C. T.; Hicks R.; Williams P.; Blaku Z.; Tran C. Safety and Immunogenicity of a Ferritin Nanoparticle H2 Influenza Vaccine in Healthy Adults: A Phase 1 Trial. Nat. Med. 2022, 28 (2), 383–391. 10.1038/s41591-021-01660-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01660-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10588819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35115706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanekiyo M.; Wei C.-J.; Yassine H. M.; McTamney P. M.; Boyington J. C.; Whittle J. R. R.; Rao S. S.; Kong W.-P.; Wang L.; Nabel G. J. Self-Assembling Influenza Nanoparticle Vaccines Elicit Broadly Neutralizing H1N1 Antibodies. Nature 2013, 499 (7456), 102–106. 10.1038/nature12202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature12202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8312026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23698367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yassine H. M.; Boyington J. C.; McTamney P. M.; Wei C.-J.; Kanekiyo M.; Kong W.-P.; Gallagher J. R.; Wang L.; Zhang Y.; Joyce M. G.; Lingwood D.; Moin S. M.; Andersen H.; Okuno Y.; Rao S. S.; Harris A. K.; Kwong P. D.; Mascola J. R.; Nabel G. J.; Graham B. S. Hemagglutinin-Stem Nanoparticles Generate Heterosubtypic Influenza Protection. Nat. Med. 2015, 21 (9), 1065–1070. 10.1038/nm.3927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nm.3927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26301691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanekiyo M.; Bu W.; Joyce M. G.; Meng G.; Whittle J. R. R.; Baxa U.; Yamamoto T.; Narpala S.; Todd J.-P.; Rao S. S.; McDermott A. B.; Koup R. A.; Rossmann M. G.; Mascola J. R.; Graham B. S.; Cohen J. I.; Nabel G. J. Rational Design of an Epstein-Barr Virus Vaccine Targeting the Receptor-Binding Site. Cell 2015, 162 (5), 1090–1100. 10.1016/j.cell.2015.07.043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.07.043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4757492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26279189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joyce M. G.; Chen W.-H.; Sankhala R. S.; Hajduczki A.; Thomas P. V.; Choe M.; Martinez E. J.; Chang W. C.; Peterson C. E.; Morrison E. B.; Smith C.; Chen R. E.; Ahmed A.; Wieczorek L.; Anderson A.; Case J. B.; Li Y.; Oertel T.; Rosado L.; Ganesh A.; Whalen C.; Carmen J. M.; Mendez-Rivera L.; Karch C. P.; Gohain N.; Villar Z.; McCurdy D.; Beck Z.; Kim J.; Shrivastava S.; Jobe O.; Dussupt V.; Molnar S.; Tran U.; Kannadka C. B.; Soman S.; Kuklis C.; Zemil M.; Khanh H.; Wu W.; Cole M. A.; Duso D. K.; Kummer L. W.; Lang T. J.; Muncil S. E.; Currier J. R.; Krebs S. J.; Polonis V. R.; Rajan S.; McTamney P. M.; Esser M. T.; Reiley W. W.; Rolland M.; de Val N.; Diamond M. S.; Gromowski G. D.; Matyas G. R.; Rao M.; Michael N. L.; Modjarrad K. SARS-CoV-2 Ferritin Nanoparticle Vaccines Elicit Broad SARS Coronavirus Immunogenicity. Cell Rep. 2021, 37 (12), 110143.10.1016/j.celrep.2021.110143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2021.110143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8651551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34919799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saunders K. O.; Wiehe K.; Tian M.; Acharya P.; Bradley T.; Alam S. M.; Go E. P.; Scearce R.; Sutherland L.; Henderson R.; Hsu A. L.; Borgnia M. J.; Chen H.; Lu X.; Wu N. R.; Watts B.; Jiang C.; Easterhoff D.; Cheng H.-L.; McGovern K.; Waddicor P.; Chapdelaine-Williams A.; Eaton A.; Zhang J.; Rountree W.; Verkoczy L.; Tomai M.; Lewis M. G.; Desaire H. R.; Edwards R. J.; Cain D. W.; Bonsignori M.; Montefiori D.; Alt F. W.; Haynes B. F. Targeted Selection of HIV-Specific Antibody Mutations by Engineering B Cell Maturation. Science 2019, 366 (6470), eaay719910.1126/science.aay7199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.aay7199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7168753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31806786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falvo E.; Tremante E.; Fraioli R.; Leonetti C.; Zamparelli C.; Boffi A.; Morea V.; Ceci P.; Giacomini P. Antibody-Drug Conjugates: Targeting Melanoma with Cisplatin Encapsulated in Protein-Cage Nanoparticles Based on Human Ferritin. Nanoscale 2013, 5 (24), 12278–12285. 10.1039/c3nr04268e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c3nr04268e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24150593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei J.; Li Z.; Yang Y.; Ma G.; Su Z.; Zhang S. An Apoferritin-Hemagglutinin Conjugate Vaccine with Encapsulated Nucleoprotein Antigen Peptide from Influenza Virus Confers Enhanced Cross Protection. Bioconjugate Chem. 2020, 31 (8), 1948–1959. 10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.0c00308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.0c00308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32678574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zakeri B.; Fierer J. O.; Celik E.; Chittock E. C.; Schwarz-Linek U.; Moy V. T.; Howarth M. Peptide Tag Forming a Rapid Covalent Bond to a Protein, through Engineering a Bacterial Adhesin. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 2012, 109 (12), E690-E69710.1073/pnas.1115485109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1115485109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3311370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22366317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma X.; Zou F.; Yu F.; Li R.; Yuan Y.; Zhang Y.; Zhang X.; Deng J.; Chen T.; Song Z.; Qiao Y.; Zhan Y.; Liu J.; Zhang J.; Zhang X.; Peng Z.; Li Y.; Lin Y.; Liang L.; Wang G.; Chen Y.; Chen Q.; Pan T.; He X.; Zhang H. Nanoparticle Vaccines Based on the Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) and Heptad Repeat (HR) of SARS-CoV-2 Elicit Robust Protective Immune Responses. Immunity 2020, 53 (6), 1315–1330. e910.1016/j.immuni.2020.11.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2020.11.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7687490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33275896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W.; Huang B.; Zhu Y.; Tan W.; Zhu M. Ferritin Nanoparticle-Based SARS-CoV-2 RBD Vaccine Induces a Persistent Antibody Response and Long-Term Memory in Mice. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 2021, 18 (3), 749–751. 10.1038/s41423-021-00643-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41423-021-00643-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7880661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33580169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W.; Liu Z.; Zhou X.; Guo Z.; Zhang J.; Zhu P.; Yao S.; Zhu M. Ferritin Nanoparticle-Based SpyTag/SpyCatcher-Enabled Click Vaccine for Tumor Immunotherapy. Nanomedicine Nanotechnol. Biol. Med. 2019, 16, 69–78. 10.1016/j.nano.2018.11.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nano.2018.11.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30529790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W.; Zhou X.; Bian Y.; Wang S.; Chai Q.; Guo Z.; Wang Z.; Zhu P.; Peng H.; Yan X.; Li W.; Fu Y.-X.; Zhu M. Dual-Targeting Nanoparticle Vaccine Elicits a Therapeutic Antibody Response against Chronic Hepatitis B. Nat. Nanotechnol. 2020, 15 (5), 406–416. 10.1038/s41565-020-0648-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41565-020-0648-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7223715</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32123380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He L.; Lin X.; Wang Y.; Abraham C.; Sou C.; Ngo T.; Zhang Y.; Wilson I. A.; Zhu J. Single-Component, Self-Assembling, Protein Nanoparticles Presenting the Receptor Binding Domain and Stabilized Spike as SARS-CoV-2 Vaccine Candidates. Sci. Adv. 2021, 7 (12), eabf159110.1126/sciadv.abf1591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abf1591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7978432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33741598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kolb H. C.; Finn M. G.; Sharpless K. B. Click Chemistry: Diverse Chemical Function from a Few Good Reactions. Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2001, 40 (11), 2004–2021. 10.1002/1521-3773(20010601)40:11&lt;2004::AID-ANIE2004&gt;3.0.CO;2-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/1521-3773(20010601)40:11&lt;2004::AID-ANIE2004&gt;3.0.CO;2-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11433435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoshnejad M.; Greineder C. F.; Pulsipher K. W.; Villa C. H.; Altun B.; Pan D. C.; Tsourkas A.; Dmochowski I. J.; Muzykantov V. R. Ferritin Nanocages with Biologically Orthogonal Conjugation for Vascular Targeting and Imaging. Bioconjugate Chem. 2018, 29 (4), 1209–1218. 10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.8b00004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.8b00004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6686135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29429330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao H.; Hart S. A.; Schink A.; Pollok B. A. Sortase-Mediated Protein Ligation: A New Method for Protein Engineering. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2004, 126 (9), 2670–2671. 10.1021/ja039915e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ja039915e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14995162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strop P. Versatility of Microbial Transglutaminase. Bioconjugate Chem. 2014, 25 (5), 855–862. 10.1021/bc500099v.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/bc500099v</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24694238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M.; Zhu Y.; Wu T.; Cheng J.; Liu Y. Nanobody-Ferritin Conjugate for Targeted Photodynamic Therapy. Chem. - Eur. J. 2020, 26 (33), 7442–7450. 10.1002/chem.202000075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/chem.202000075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32166771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krüger T.; Dierks T.; Sewald N. Formylglycine-Generating Enzymes for Site-Specific Bioconjugation. Biol. Chem. 2019, 400 (3), 289–297. 10.1515/hsz-2018-0358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/hsz-2018-0358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30291781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ito S.; Sugumaran M.; Wakamatsu K. Chemical Reactivities of Ortho-Quinones Produced in Living Organisms: Fate of Quinonoid Products Formed by Tyrosinase and Phenoloxidase Action on Phenols and Catechols. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2020, 21 (17), 6080.10.3390/ijms21176080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms21176080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7504153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32846902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bittner S. When Quinones Meet Amino Acids: Chemical, Physical and Biological Consequences. Amino Acids 2006, 30 (3), 205–224. 10.1007/s00726-005-0298-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00726-005-0298-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16601927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maza J. C.; Bader D. L. V.; Xiao L.; Marmelstein A. M.; Brauer D. D.; ElSohly A. M.; Smith M. J.; Krska S. W.; Parish C. A.; Francis M. B. Enzymatic Modification of N-Terminal Proline Residues Using Phenol Derivatives. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2019, 141 (9), 3885–3892. 10.1021/jacs.8b10845.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jacs.8b10845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30726077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marmelstein A. M.; Lobba M. J.; Mogilevsky C. S.; Maza J. C.; Brauer D. D.; Francis M. B. Tyrosinase-Mediated Oxidative Coupling of Tyrosine Tags on Peptides and Proteins. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2020, 142 (11), 5078–5086. 10.1021/jacs.9b12002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jacs.9b12002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32093466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lobba M. J.; Fellmann C.; Marmelstein A. M.; Maza J. C.; Kissman E. N.; Robinson S. A.; Staahl B. T.; Urnes C.; Lew R. J.; Mogilevsky C. S.; Doudna J. A.; Francis M. B. Site-Specific Bioconjugation through Enzyme-Catalyzed Tyrosine-Cysteine Bond Formation. ACS Cent. Sci. 2020, 6 (9), 1564–1571. 10.1021/acscentsci.0c00940.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acscentsci.0c00940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7517114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32999931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mogilevsky C. S.; Lobba M. J.; Brauer D. D.; Marmelstein A. M.; Maza J. C.; Gleason J. M.; Doudna J. A.; Francis M. B. Synthesis of Multi-Protein Complexes through Charge-Directed Sequential Activation of Tyrosine Residues. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2021, 143 (34), 13538–13547. 10.1021/jacs.1c03079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jacs.1c03079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9274618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34382787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao W.; Maza J. C.; Chernyak N.; Flygare J. A.; Krska S. W.; Toste F. D.; Francis M. B. Modification of Cysteine-Substituted Antibodies Using Enzymatic Oxidative Coupling Reactions. Bioconjugate Chem. 2023, 34 (3), 510–517. 10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.2c00576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.2c00576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36787347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismaya W. T.; Rozeboom H. J.; Weijn A.; Mes J. J.; Fusetti F.; Wichers H. J.; Dijkstra B. W. Crystal Structure of Agaricus Bisporus Mushroom Tyrosinase: Identity of the Tetramer Subunits and Interaction with Tropolone. Biochemistry 2011, 50 (24), 5477–5486. 10.1021/bi200395t.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/bi200395t</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21598903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaidi K. U.; Ali A. S.; Ali S. A. Purification and Characterization of Melanogenic Enzyme Tyrosinase from Button Mushroom. Enzyme Res. 2014, 2014, 120739.10.1155/2014/120739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2014/120739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4150416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25197562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison P. M.; Arosio P. The Ferritins: Molecular Properties, Iron Storage Function and Cellular Regulation. Biochim. Biophys. Acta BBA - Bioenerg. 1996, 1275 (3), 161–203. 10.1016/0005-2728(96)00022-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0005-2728(96)00022-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8695634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filippov S. K.; Khusnutdinov R.; Murmiliuk A.; Inam W.; Zakharova L. Y.; Zhang H.; Khutoryanskiy V. V. Dynamic Light Scattering and Transmission Electron Microscopy in Drug Delivery: A Roadmap for Correct Characterization of Nanoparticles and Interpretation of Results. Mater. Horiz. 2023, 10 (12), 5354–5370. 10.1039/D3MH00717K.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D3MH00717K</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37814922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huo J.; Zhao Y.; Ren J.; Zhou D.; Duyvesteyn H. M. E.; Ginn H. M.; Carrique L.; Malinauskas T.; Ruza R. R.; Shah P. N. M.; Tan T. K.; Rijal P.; Coombes N.; Bewley K. R.; Tree J. A.; Radecke J.; Paterson N. G.; Supasa P.; Mongkolsapaya J.; Screaton G. R.; Carroll M.; Townsend A.; Fry E. E.; Owens R. J.; Stuart D. I. Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 by Destruction of the Prefusion Spike. Cell Host Microbe 2020, 28 (3), 445–454. 10.1016/j.chom.2020.06.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2020.06.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7303615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32585135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S.; Zhou Q.; Chen X.; Luo R.-H.; Li Y.; Liu X.; Yang L.-M.; Zheng Y.-T.; Wang P. Modification of N-Terminal α-Amine of Proteins via Biomimetic Ortho-Quinone-Mediated Oxidation. Nat. Commun. 2021, 12 (1), 2257.10.1038/s41467-021-22654-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-22654-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8050078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33859198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X.; Zaro J.; Shen W.-C. Fusion Protein Linkers: Property, Design and Functionality. Adv. Drug Delivery Rev. 2013, 65 (10), 1357–1369. 10.1016/j.addr.2012.09.039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addr.2012.09.039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3726540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23026637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hempstead P. D.; Yewdall S. J.; Fernie A. R.; Lawson D. M.; Artymiuk P. J.; Rice D. W.; Ford G. C.; Harrison P. M. Comparison of the Three-Dimensional Structures of Recombinant Human H and Horse L Ferritins at High resolution11Edited by R. Huber. J. Mol. Biol. 1997, 268 (2), 424–448. 10.1006/jmbi.1997.0970.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1997.0970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9159481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calisti L.; Benni I.; Cardoso Trabuco M.; Baiocco P.; Ruzicka B.; Boffi A.; Falvo E.; Malatesta F.; Bonamore A. Probing Bulky Ligand Entry in Engineered Archaeal Ferritins. Biochim. Biophys. Acta BBA - Gen. Subj. 2017, 1861 (2), 450–456. 10.1016/j.bbagen.2016.10.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2016.10.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27755975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandebriel R. J.; Hoefnagel M. H. N. Dendritic Cell-Based in Vitro Assays for Vaccine Immunogenicity. Hum. Vaccines Immunother. 2012, 8 (9), 1323–1325. 10.4161/hv.21350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4161/hv.21350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3579917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22951585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>