<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39345040</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2013-6463</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>26</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>May-Aug</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Revista espanola de sanidad penitenciaria</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Esp Sanid Penit</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of dental emergency during the COVID-19 pandemic in the Social Rehabilitation Centre of San Francisco Kobén (Campeche, Mexico).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>65</StartPage><EndPage>71</EndPage><MedlinePgn>65-71</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.18176/resp.00089</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">During the COVID-19 pandemic, access to dental treatment by persons deprived of their liberty (PPL) was affected due to dentist-patient proximity and the risk of generation of aerosols in dental procedures and treatments. The risks of infection for oral health personnel are considered high, mainly from cross-infection between patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Differentiate between a true and false dental consultation emergency during the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak for a better and effective screening of inmates of the Social Rehabilitation Center (CERESO) of San Francisco Kobén (Campeche, Mexico).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIAL AND METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">An observational, cross-sectional, descriptive, and prospective study was designed for a sample of 100 inmates of the CERESO San Francisco Kobén, the data was collected in the prison's dental office, the participants signed a letter of informed consent to be voluntarily included in the study during the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak. The questionnaire "Assessment of a true Dental Emergency" previously validated for the Mexican population was applied, the personnel was standardized and an intra- examiner and inter-examiner reliability of k = 0.98 was obtained. To prepare the database and the analysis of the information collected, the Statistical Package for Social Science v. 21 (SPSS v.21) was used.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">When evaluating emergencies at the dental clinic, 84% were determined according to the instrument as a false emergency and 16% were a true emergency.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In the population of CERESO of San Francisco Kobén, the figures for medical-dental care show that inmates face a proportionally low dental morbidity-mortality.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gamboa Orozco</LastName><ForeName>Pedro Miguel</ForeName><Initials>PM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Secretary of Health for Campeche. Head of the Seconded Dental Unit of the San Francisco Kobén Social Rehabilitation Centre (CERESO), Campeche. Mexico. Institute for Training, Research and Postgraduate Studies of Campeche, Mexico. Master in Sciences. Candidate for PhD in Education.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Herrera López</LastName><ForeName>Luis Fernando</ForeName><Initials>LF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Training, Research and Postgraduate Studies of Campeche. Master in Medicine. Director General of the Institute for Training, Research and Postgraduate Studies of Campeche, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zazueta Hernández</LastName><ForeName>María Alejandra</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Training, Research and Postgraduate Studies of Campeche. PhD in Education. Academic Director of the Institute for Training, Research and Postgraduate Studies of Campeche, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D064888">Observational Study</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Spain</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Esp Sanid Penit</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101284897</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1575-0620</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008800" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Mexico</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011446" MajorTopicYN="N">Prospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003729" MajorTopicYN="N">Dental Care</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004630" MajorTopicYN="N">Emergencies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012047" MajorTopicYN="N">Rehabilitation Centers</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCCIÓN:">Durante la pandemia de enfermedad del coronavirus de 2019 (COVID-19), el acceso al tratamiento odontológico por parte de personas privadas de la libertad (PPL) se vio afectado, debido a la proximidad odontólogo-paciente como consecuencia de la generación de aerosoles en los procedimientos y tratamientos dentales. Los riesgos de infección para el personal de salud bucal se consideran altos, principalmente la infección cruzada entre los pacientes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJETIVOS:">Diferenciar entre una verdadera y falsa emergencia de consulta dental durante el brote de coronavirus de tipo 2 causante del síndrome respiratorio agudo severo (SARS-CoV-2) para un mejor y efectivo tamizaje en PPL del Centro de Reinserción Social (CERESO) San Francisco Kobén, en Campeche, México.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIAL Y MÉTODO:">Se diseñó un estudio observacional, transversal, descriptivo y prospectivo para una muestra de 100 PPL del CERESO San Francisco Kobén, los datos se recolectaron en el consultorio dental del centro de reclusión, las mujeres y hombres participantes, firmaron una carta de consentimiento informado para ser incluidos voluntariamente en el estudio durante el brote del SARS-CoV-2. Se aplicó el cuestionario <i>Assessment of a true Dental Emergency</i> (evaluación de una verdadera emergencia dental) previamente validado en la población mexicana, se estandarizó al personal y se obtuvo una confiabilidad intraexaminador e interexaminador con el coeficiente kappa de Cohen con una confiabilidad de <i>k</i> = 0,98. Para elaborar la base de datos y el análisis de la información recopilada, se utilizó el Statistical Package for Social Science en su versión 21 (SPSS v. 21).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTADOS:">Al evaluar la emergencia de la consulta dental, el 84% se determinaron de acuerdo con el instrumento como una falsa emergencia y el 16% resultaron una verdadera emergencia, 4% fueron del sexo femenino y 96% masculino.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSIÓN:">En la población del CERESO San Francisco Kobén, la atención médico-odontológica evidencia que las PPL enfrentan una morbimortalidad dental proporcionalmente baja.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><CoiStatement><b>Conflicts of interest:</b> The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39345040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11474841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18176/resp.00089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  . La OMS destaca que el descuido de la salud bucodental afecta a casi la mitad de la población mundial. WHO; Nov 18, 2022.  [22/06/2020].  Disponible en:  https://www.who.int/es/news/item/18-11-2022-who-highlights-oral-health-neglect-affecting-nearly-half-of-the-world-s-population
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gobierno del México  Programa Sectorial de Salud 2020-2024.  [22/06/2020].  Disponible en:  https://www.gob.mx/salud/documentos/programa-sectorial-de-salud-2020-2024
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinzón O, Meza S. Prestación de Servicios de Salud de las Personas Privadas de la Libertad. Archivos de Medicina. 2018;14(2):1–6. doi: 10.3823/1388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3823/1388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bermúdez-Jiménez C, Gaitán-Fonseca C, Aguilera-Galaviz L. Manejo del paciente en atención odontológica y bioseguridad del personal durante el brote de coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) Rev ADM. 2020;77(2):88–95. doi: 10.35366/93101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.35366/93101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ge ZY, Yang LM, Xia JJ, Fu XH, Zhang YZ. Possible aerosol transmission of COVID-19 and special precautions in dentistry. J Zhejiang Univ Sci B. 2020;21(5):361–368. doi: 10.1631/jzus.B2010010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1631/jzus.B2010010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7089481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32425001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohn WG, Collins AS, Cleveland JL, Harte JA, Eklund KJ, Malvitz DM, et al. Guidelines for infection control in dental health-care settings--2003. MMWR Recomm Rep. 2003;52(RR-17):1–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14685139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estados Unidos Mexicanos. Secretaría de Salud  . NORMA Oficial Mexicana NOM-004-SSA3-2012, Del expediente clínico. México: Secretaría de Salud; 2012. https://dof.gob.mx/nota_detalle_popup.php?codigo=5272787</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comisión Nacional de Arbitraje Médico . Consentimiento válidamente informado. CONAMED; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ather A, Patel B, Ruparel NB, Diogenes A, Hargreaves KM. Coronavirus Disease 19 (COVID-19): Implications for Clinical Dental Care. J Endod. 2020;46(5):584–595. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2020.03.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2020.03.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32273156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J. A coefficient of agreement for nominal scales. Educ Psychol Meas. 1960;20(1):37–46. doi: 10.1177/001316446002000104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/001316446002000104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sigua-Rodriguez EA, Bernal-Pérez JL, Lanata-Flores AG, Sánchez-Romero C, Rodíguez-Chessa J, Haidar ZS, et al.  COVID-19 y la Odontología: una Revisión de las recomendaciones y perspectivas para Latinoamérica. Int. J. Odontostomat. 2020;14(3):299–309. https://www.scielo.cl/pdf/ijodontos/v14n3/0718-381X-ijodontos-14-03-299.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards SP, Kasten S, Nelson C, Elner V, McKean E. Maxillofacial Trauma Management During COVID-19: Multidisciplinary Recommendations. Facial Plast Surg Aesthet Med. 2020;22(3):157–159. doi: 10.1089/fpsam.2020.0158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/fpsam.2020.0158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32255713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benadof D, Torche I, Zamora P. Medidas de bioseguridad en la atención odontológica durante la pandemia COVID-19. Odontología Vital. 2021;34:73–84. https://www.scielo.sa.cr/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1659-07752021000100073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai Y, Yao L, Wei T, Tian F, Jin D-Y, Chen L, et al. Presumed asymptomatic carrier transmission of COVID-19. JAMA. 2020;323(14):1406–1407. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.2565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.2565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7042844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32083643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothe C, Schunk M, Sothmann P, Bretzel G, Froeschl G, Wallrauch C, et al. Transmission of 2019-nCoV infection from an Asymptomatic Contact in Germany. N Engl J Med. 2020;382(10):970–971. doi: 10.1056/nejmc2001468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/nejmc2001468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7120970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32003551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng X, Xu X, Li Y, Cheng L, Zhou X, Ren B. Transmission routes of 2019-nCoV and controls in dental practice. Int J Oral Sci. 2020;12(1):9–9. doi: 10.1038/s41368-020-0075-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41368-020-0075-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7054527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32127517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez R. Odontología: rol en la transmisión del SARS-CoV-2 a través de bioaerosoles. ODOVTOS-Int. J. Dental Sc. 2020;22(3):103–112. https://www.scielo.sa.cr/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S2215-34112020000300103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrel SK, Molinari J. Aerosols and splatter in dentistry: a brief review of the literature and infection control implications. J Am Dent Assoc. 2004;135(4):429–437. doi: 10.14219/jada.archive.2004.0207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14219/jada.archive.2004.0207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7093851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15127864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Labor  . Guidance on preparing workplaces for COVID-19 (OSHA 3990-02) Occupational Safety and Health Act (OSHA); 2020. https://www.osha.gov/Publications/OSHA3990.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng L, Hua F, Bian Z. Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19): Emerging and future challenges for dental and oral medicine. J Dent Res. 2020;99(5):481–487. doi: 10.11777/0022034520914246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11777/0022034520914246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7140973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32162995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Health Service (NHS) England, NHS Improvement  . COVID-19 guidance and standard operating procedure: Urgent dental care systems in the context of the coronavirus. NHS; 2020. https://www.england.nhs.uk/coronavirus/wpcontent/uploads/sites/52/2020/06/C0581-covid-19-urgent-dental-care-sop-update-16-june-20-.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benzian H, Niederman R. A Dental Response to the COVID-19 Pandemic-Safer Aerosol-Free Emergent (SAFER) Dentistry. Front. Med. 2020;7:520–520. doi: 10.3389/fmed.2020.00520. https://alliancefororalhealthacrossborders.org/wpcontent/uploads/2020/11/Benzian-Niederman-2020-697.pdf</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2020.00520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7434942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32903453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borisconti HD.  Frecuencia de enfermedades en población carcelaria de hombres Unidad Penitenciaria N°3 de la ciudad de Rosario durante el periodo 2015-2016. Facultad de Ciencias Médicas, Universidad Nacional del Litoral; Santa Fe: 2019. https://bibliotecavirtual.unl.edu.ar:8443/bitstream/handle/11185/5151/TFI.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y Tesis doctoral.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>