<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39340152</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1542-0086</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biophysical journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biophys J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>An integrative characterization of proline cis and trans conformers in a disordered peptide.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0006-3495(24)00655-6</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.bpj.2024.09.028</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs) often contain proline residues that undergo cis/trans isomerization. While molecular dynamics (MD) simulations have the potential to fully characterize the proline cis and trans subensembles, they are limited by the slow timescales of isomerization and force field inaccuracies. NMR spectroscopy can report on ensemble-averaged observables for both the cis-proline and trans-proline states, but a full atomistic characterization of these conformers is challenging. Given the importance of proline cis/trans isomerization for influencing the conformational sampling of disordered proteins, we employed a combination of all-atom MD simulations with enhanced sampling (metadynamics), NMR, and small-angle x-ray scattering (SAXS) to characterize the two subensembles of the ORF6 C-terminal region (ORF6<sub>CTR</sub>) from SARS-CoV-2 corresponding to the proline-57 (P57) cis and trans states. We performed MD simulations in three distinct force fields: AMBER03ws, AMBER99SB-disp, and CHARMM36m, which are all optimized for disordered proteins. Each simulation was run for an accumulated time of 180-220 μs until convergence was reached, as assessed by blocking analysis. A good agreement between the cis-P57 populations predicted from metadynamic simulations in AMBER03ws was observed with populations obtained from experimental NMR data. Moreover, we observed good agreement between the radius of gyration predicted from the metadynamic simulations in AMBER03ws and that measured using SAXS. Our findings suggest that both the cis-P57 and trans-P57 conformations of ORF6<sub>CTR</sub> are extremely dynamic and that interdisciplinary approaches combining both multiscale computations and experiments offer avenues to explore highly dynamic states that cannot be reliably characterized by either approach in isolation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pettitt</LastName><ForeName>Alice J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Structural and Molecular Biology, Division of Biosciences, London, United Kingdom; Department of Engineering, Faculty of Natural, Mathematical and Engineering Sciences, King's College London, London, United Kingdom; The Francis Crick Institute, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shukla</LastName><ForeName>Vaibhav Kumar</ForeName><Initials>VK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Structural and Molecular Biology, Division of Biosciences, London, United Kingdom; The Francis Crick Institute, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Figueiredo</LastName><ForeName>Angelo Miguel</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Structural and Molecular Biology, Division of Biosciences, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Newton</LastName><ForeName>Lydia S</ForeName><Initials>LS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Structural and Molecular Biology, Division of Biosciences, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McCarthy</LastName><ForeName>Stephen</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Mathematical and Physical Sciences, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tabor</LastName><ForeName>Alethea B</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Mathematical and Physical Sciences, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heller</LastName><ForeName>Gabriella T</ForeName><Initials>GT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Structural and Molecular Biology, Division of Biosciences, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lorenz</LastName><ForeName>Christian D</ForeName><Initials>CD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Engineering, Faculty of Natural, Mathematical and Engineering Sciences, King's College London, London, United Kingdom. Electronic address: chris.lorenz@kcl.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hansen</LastName><ForeName>D Flemming</ForeName><Initials>DF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Structural and Molecular Biology, Division of Biosciences, London, United Kingdom; The Francis Crick Institute, London, United Kingdom. Electronic address: d.hansen@ucl.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Biophys J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370626</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0006-3495</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39340152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2024.09.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0006-3495(24)00655-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>