<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39345919</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1664-0640</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in psychiatry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Psychiatry</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Drug overdose deaths during prison riots and mental states of prisoners: a case study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1377995</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1377995</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1377995</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1377995</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Prison riots, though often sensationalized in the media, have profound consequences, with a significant death toll. Prison populations, historically plagued by psychiatric disorders, witness high rates of suicide, particularly linked to turbulent events like riots. This study examines three drug overdose deaths resulting from a prison riot during the initial wave of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic in Italy. To ascertain the nature of these deaths, a comprehensive toxicological analysis was conducted. Immunochemical screening and gas chromatography-mass spectrometry were employed to detect a spectrum of drugs, including MDMA, methadone, morphine, cannabis derivatives, benzodiazepines, and others. The toxicological findings revealed high concentrations of various substances in the biological fluids of the deceased inmates. Tramadol and mirtazapine were implicated in one case, while methadone was a common factor in the deaths of two inmates, one of whom also ingested diazepam. The synergistic effects of substances were explored, with methadone identified as a leading cause of death in two cases. Prison riots exacerbate drug abuse issues within prisons, leading to mass intoxication and overdose, as witnessed in historic incidents globally. The study underscores the challenges in determining whether such deaths are accidental, intentional (suicidal), or a consequence of uncontrollable drug consumption during a riot. The prison environment also amplifies pre-existing psychiatric disorders, and incidents like riots can trigger a cascade of uncontrollable psychological reactions. The three potential scenarios are drug dependence, accidental overdose in recreational drug use, and suicide attempts through substance ingestion.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Tomassini, Giuli, Bottoni, David and Scendoni.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tomassini</LastName><ForeName>Luca</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International School of Advanced Studies, University of Camerino, Camerino, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giuli</LastName><ForeName>Gianni</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathological Addictions, Territorial Health Authority of Macerata, Macerata, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bottoni</LastName><ForeName>Edoardo</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anatomical, Histological, Forensic Medicine and Orthopaedic Sciences, Section of Legal Medicine, Sapienza University of Rome, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>David</LastName><ForeName>Maria Chiara</ForeName><Initials>MC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Security, Central Health Directorate, Forensic Toxicology Research and Laboratory Center, Ministry of the Interior, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Scendoni</LastName><ForeName>Roberto</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Law, Institute of Legal Medicine, University of Macerata, Macerata, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Psychiatry</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101545006</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1664-0640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">crowd effect</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">impulse control disorders</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">overdose</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prison environment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prison riots</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">recreational drug use</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">suicide</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39345919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11427281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1377995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Graeve CM, DeLisi M, Hochstetler A. Prison rioters: exploring infraction characteristics, risk factors, social correlates, and criminal careers. Psychol Rep. (2007) 100:407–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17564215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miguel-Arias D, Pereiro-Gómez C, Bermejo-Barrera AM, Vázquez-Ventoso C, Rodríguez-Barca T. Deaths from acute drug reactions in Galician (Spain) Prisons (2001–2010). Rev Espanola Sanid Penit. (2017) 19:49–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28748984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felthous AR. Suicide behind bars: trends, inconsistencies, and practical implications. J Forensic Sci. (2011) 56:1541–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21827457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartoli C, Berland-Benhaim C, Tuchtan-Torrents L, Kintz P, Leonetti G, Pelissier-Alicot AL. Suicide by medication overdose in prison: A study of three cases. J Forensic Sci. (2018) 63:1316–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29059715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsson MO, Bradvik L, Öjehagen A, Hakansson A. Risk factors for unnatural death: Fatal accidental intoxication, undetermined intent and suicide: Register follow-up in a criminal justice population with substance use problems. Drug Alcohol Depend. (2016) 162:176–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27020324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caputo F, Gratteri S, Sacco MA, Scalise C, Cacciatore G, Bonetta F, et al. . Covid-19 emergency in prison: Current management and forensic perspectives. Med Leg J. (2020) 88:185–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
COSA INSEGNA LA RIVOLTA IN CARCERE (2021). Available online at: http://www.formatrieti.it/cosa-insegna-la-rivolta-carcere.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Coronavirus, carceri, ancora proteste. Tre detenuti morti a Rieti, le vittime salgono a dodici - la Repubblica (2021). Available online at: https://www.repubblica.it/cronaca/2020/03/10/news/coronavirus_carceri_ancora_proteste_tre_detenuti_morti_a_rieti-250829816/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Prison and drugs in Europe: current and future challenges. Avalibale online at: https://www.politicheantidroga.gov.it/media/3064/tdxd21001enn.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpentier C, Royuela L, Montanari L, Davis P. “The global epidemiology of drug use in prison”. In: Kinner SA, Rich JDJ, editors. Drug use in prisoners: epidemiology, implications, and policy responses. Oxford: Oxford University Press; (2018) pp.17–41. doi: 10.1093/med/9780199374847.003.0002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/med/9780199374847.003.0002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singleton N, Farrell M, Meltzer H. Substance misuse among prisoners in England and Wales. Int Rev Psychiatry Abingdon Engl. (2003) 15:150–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12745325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durand L, Keenan E, O’Reilly D, Bennett K, O’Hara A, Cousins G. Prescription drugs with potential for misuse in Irish prisons: analysis of national prison prescribing trends, by gender and history of opioid use disorder, 2012 to 2020. BMC Psychiatry. (2023) 23:725.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10559424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37803285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hockenhull J, Black JC, Haynes CM, Rockhill K, Dargan PI, Dart RC, et al. . Nonmedical use of benzodiazepines and Z-drugs in the UK. Br J Clin Pharmacol. (2021) 87:1676–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32472941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cremers S, Wright DFB. Nonmedical use of prescription drugs. Br J Clin Pharmacol. (2021) 87:1635–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33710669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fazel S, Yoon IA, Hayes AJ. Substance use disorders in prisoners: an updated systematic review and meta-regression analysis in recently incarcerated men and women. Addiction. (2017) 112:1725–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5589068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28543749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kabealo TB, Dinitz S. [Prison riots in U.S.A. 1951–1971]. Quad Criminol Clin. (1973) 15:305–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4778177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lapham SC, Weber SF, Burkhart MJ, Hoffman RE, Kreiss K. Risk factors for victimization during the 1980 riot at the Penitentiary of New Mexico. Am J Epidemiol. (1984) 119:218–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6695901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Report of the Attorney General on the February 2 and 3, 1980 Riot at the Penitentiary of New Mexico. Available online at: https://www.ojp.gov/pdffiles1/Digitization/72933NCJRS.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Venezuelan prisoners die of drug overdose following riots | Euronews. Available online at: https://www.euronews.com/2014/11/29/Venezuelan-prisoners-die-of-drug-overdose-following-riots.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Venezuela jail drug overdose kills 35 inmates in Uribana - BBC News. Available online at: https://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-30253935.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Droghe e dipendenze [Internet]. XV rapporto sulle condizioni di detenzione (2019). Available online at: https://www.antigone.it/quindicesimo-rapporto-sulle-condizioni-di-detenzione/droghe-e-dipendenze/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clua-García R, Bañuls-Oncina E, Imbernón-Casas M, Jiménez-Vinaja R. The discourses of risk of drug users in prison. Rev Esp Sanid Penit. (2019) 21:28–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6788205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31498857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baltieri DA. Predictors of drug use in prison among women convicted of violent crimes. Crim Behav Ment Health CBMH. (2014) 24:113–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24038391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamani S, Farnia M, Torknejad A, Alaei BA, Gholizadeh M, Kasraee F, et al. . Patterns of drug use and HIV-related risk behaviors among incarcerated people in a prison in Iran. J Urban Health Bull N Y Acad Med. (2010) 87:603–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2900562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20390391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price D, Billowitz E, Lieberman R, Fleming T, Dunn M, Sklar DP. Medical consequences of the New Mexico State Penitentiary riot. Ann Emerg Med. (1983) 12:361–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6859632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Psychiatric Association. American Psychiatric Association . Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM-5. 5th ed. Washington, D.C: American Psychiatric Association; (2013). p. 947.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Decker K, Cordonnier J, Jacobs W, Coucke V, Schepens P, Jorens PG. Fatal intoxication due to tramadol alone: case report and review of the literature. Forensic Sci Int. (2008) 175:79–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17875377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction . New psychoactive substances in prison: results from an EMCDDA trendspotter study. LU: Publications Office; (2018). doi: 10.2810/7247</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2810/7247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
EMCDDA home page. Available online at: https://www.emcdda.europa.eu/index_en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccaro G, Massariol A, Guirguis A, Kirton SB, Stair JL. NPS detection in prison: A systematic literature review of use, drug form, and analytical approaches. Drug Test Anal. (2022) 14:1350–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9545023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35355411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ralphs R, Williams L, Askew R, Norton A. Adding Spice to the Porridge1: The development of a synthetic cannabinoid market in an English prison. Int J Drug Policy. (2017) 40:57–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27955961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Synthetic cannabinoids: What are they? What are their effects? | HSB | NCEH (2022). Available online at: https://www.cdc.gov/nceh/hsb/chemicals/sc/default.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norman C, Halter S, Haschimi B, Acreman D, Smith J, Krotulski AJ, et al. . A transnational perspective on the evolution of the synthetic cannabinoid receptor agonists market: Comparing prison and general populations. Drug Test Anal. (2021) 13:841–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33463894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivlin A, Hawton K, Marzano L, Fazel S. Psychosocial characteristics and social networks of suicidal prisoners: towards a model of suicidal behaviour in detention. PloS One. (2013) 8:e68944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3726684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23922671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butterfield M, Al-Abri S, Huntington S, Carlson T, Geller RJ, Olson KR. Symptomatic exposures among california inmates 2011–2013. J Med Toxicol. (2015) 11:309–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4547960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25526949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCance-Katz EF, Sullivan L, Nallani S. Drug Interactions of Clinical Importance among the Opioids, Methadone and Buprenorphine, and other Frequently Prescribed Medications: A Review. Am J Addict. (2010) 19:4–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3334287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20132117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berling I, Isbister GK. Mirtazapine overdose is unlikely to cause major toxicity. Clin Toxicol Phila Pa. (2014) 52:20–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3894718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24228948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein MG, Krantz MJ, Fatima N, Watters A, Colon-Sanchez D, Geiger RM, et al. . Methadone blockade of cardiac inward rectifier K+ Current augments membrane instability and amplifies U waves on surface ECGs: A translational study. J Am Heart Assoc Cardiovasc Cerebrovasc Dis. (2022) 11:e023482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9238736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35658478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandanwale AS, Sundar S, Latchoumibady K, Biswas S, Gabhane M, Naik M, et al. . Efficacy and safety profile of combination of tramadol-diclofenac versus tramadol-paracetamol in patients with acute musculoskeletal conditions, postoperative pain, and acute flare of osteoarthritis and rheumatoid arthritis: a Phase III, 5-day open-label study. J Pain Res. (2014) 7:455–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4140236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25152629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sonis J. Tramadol for acute pain: a review of the evidence. Am Fam Physician. (2005) 72:1964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16342825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawton K, Ferrey A, Casey D, Wells C, Fuller A, Bankhead C, et al. . Relative toxicity of analgesics commonly used for intentional self-poisoning: A study of case fatality based on fatal and non-fatal overdoses. J Affect Disord. (2019) 246:814–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30634113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan NM, Isbister GK. Tramadol overdose causes seizures and respiratory depression but serotonin toxicity appears unlikely. Clin Toxicol Phila Pa. (2015) 53:545–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25901965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spiller HA, Gorman SE, Villalobos D, Benson BE, Ruskosky DR, Stancavage MM, et al. . Prospective multicenter evaluation of tramadol exposure. J Toxicol Clin Toxicol. (1997) 35:361–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9204095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neale J. Methadone, methadone treatment and non-fatal overdose. Drug Alcohol Depend. (2000) 58:117–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10669062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellenhorn JD, Hirsch R, Schreiber H, Bluestone JA. In vivo administration of anti-CD3 prevents Malignant progressor tumor growth. Science. (1988) 242:569–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2902689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alinejad S, Kazemi T, Zamani N, Hoffman RS, Mehrpour O. A systematic review of the cardiotoxicity of methadone. EXCLI J. (2015) 14:577–600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4747000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26869865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruciani RA. Methadone: to ECG or not to ECG … That is still the question. J Pain Symptom Manage. (2008) 36:545–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18440771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chugh SS, Socoteanu C, Reinier K, Waltz J, Jui J, Gunson K. A community-based evaluation of sudden death associated with therapeutic levels of methadone. Am J Med. (2008) 121:66–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2735350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18187075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikolaenko I, Robinson CA, Davis GG. A review of methadone deaths in Jefferson County, Alabama. Am J Forensic Med Pathol. (2002) 23:299–304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12198363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karch SB, Stephens BG. Toxicology and pathology of deaths related to methadone: retrospective review. West J Med. (2000) 172:11–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1070708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10695434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrett DH, Luk AJ, Parrish RG, Jones TS. An investigation of medical examiner cases in which methadone was detected, Harris County, Texas, 1987–1992. J Forensic Sci. (1996) 41:442–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8656185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caplehorn JRM, Drummer OH. Fatal methadone toxicity: signs and circumstances, and the role of benzodiazepines. Aust N Z J Public Health. (2002) 26:358–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12233958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sastre C, Bartoli C, Baillif-Couniou V, Leonetti G, Pelissier-Alicot AL. Post mortem redistribution of drugs: current state of knowledge. Curr Pharm Des. (2017) 23:5530–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28641544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelissier-Alicot AL, Coste N, Bartoli C, Piercecchi-Marti MD, Sanvoisin A, Gouvernet J, et al. . Comparison of ethanol concentrations in right cardiac blood, left cardiac blood and peripheral blood in a series of 30 cases. Forensic Sci Int. (2006) 156:35–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16410151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sastre C, Baillif-Couniou V, Musarella F, Bartoli C, Mancini J, Piercecchi-Marti MD, et al. . Can subclavian blood be equated with a peripheral blood sample? A series of 50 cases. Int J Legal Med. (2013) 127:379–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22773273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fazel S, Grann M. Older criminals: a descriptive study of psychiatrically examined offenders in Sweden. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry. (2002) 17:907–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12325049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baranyi G, Fazel S, Langerfeldt SD, Mundt AP. The prevalence of comorbid serious mental illnesses and substance use disorders in prison populations: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Public Health. (2022) 7:e557–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9178214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35660217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biondi M. DSM-5. Manuale diagnostico e statistico dei disturbi mentali. Milano: Raffaello Cortina Editore; (2014). p. 1092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Ginneken J. Crowds, psychology, and politics, 1871–1899. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; (1992). p. 300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahoda G. A history of social psychology: From the eighteenth-century Enlightenment to the Second World War. New York, NY, US: Cambridge University Press; (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reta Y, Getachew R, Bahiru M, Kale B, Workie K, Gebreegziabhere Y. Depressive symptoms and its associated factors among prisoners in Debre Berhan prison, Ethiopia. PloS One. (2020) 15:e0220267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7067449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32163419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Mizio G, Bolcato M, Rivellini G, Di Nunzio M, Falvo V, Nuti M, et al. . Protection of prisoners with mental health disorders in Italy: lights and shadows after the abolition of judicial psychiatric hospitals. Int J Environ Res Public Health. (2022) 19:9984.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9408278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36011618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mestria S, Odoardi S, Biosa G, Valentini V, Strano Rossi S. Hair analysis: Assessment of homemade hair treatment effects on drug concentrations in the keratin matrix. Drug Test Anal. (2023). doi: 10.1002/dta.3541</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/dta.3541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37419869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>