<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39355714</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1937-8688</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>48</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pan African medical journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pan Afr Med J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>[Refusal and hesitation regarding vaccination against COVID-19 in Douala, Cameroon].</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>61</StartPage><MedlinePgn>61</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">61</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.11604/pamj.2024.48.61.39880</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">vaccination is one of the strategies the World Health Organization recommends to reduce the burden of COVID-19. However, many African countries like Cameroon have low COVID-19 vaccination coverage. The purpose of this study was to investigate the reasons for the refusal of the population of the city of Douala to be vaccinated against COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">we conducted a cross-sectional and analytical study in Douala from February 10 to May 31, 2022. Participants, aged at least 21 years and residing in the city of Douala, were interviewed. Associations between the variables of interest were measured using Chi-square and Fisher tests, with a 95% confidence interval.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">a total of 1555 people were included in the study. Only 168 (11%) had been vaccinated. The proportion of vaccine refusal was high, with 711 (45.7%) refusing, 640 participants (41.1%) hesitating, and 204 people (13.2%) being in favor of COVID-19 vaccination. The main reasons for refusing anti-COVID-19 vaccination were fear of adverse effects (406; 44.8%), lack of information about vaccines (331; 36.5%), and lack of confidence (302; 33.3%). Factors associated with vaccine refusal were religion (p=0.026) and level of education (p=0.002).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">this study revealed low COVID-19 vaccination coverage in Douala, with a significant proportion of refusal and hesitation towards vaccination. Communication strategies should take into account the reasons and factors associated with refusal.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: André Arsène Bita Fouda et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fouda</LastName><ForeName>André Arsène Bita</ForeName><Initials>AAB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculté de Médecine et de Sciences Pharmaceutiques de Douala, Douala, Cameroun.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kengne</LastName><ForeName>Verdiane Félécité Metagne</ForeName><Initials>VFM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculté de Médecine et de Sciences Pharmaceutiques de Douala, Douala, Cameroun.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adiogo</LastName><ForeName>Dieudonné</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculté de Médecine et de Sciences Pharmaceutiques de Douala, Douala, Cameroun.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manga</LastName><ForeName>Léon Jules Owona</ForeName><Initials>LJO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculté de Médecine et de Sciences Pharmaceutiques de Douala, Douala, Cameroun.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>fre</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D004740">English Abstract</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Refus et hésitation vis-à-vis de la vaccination anti-COVID-19 à Douala, Cameroun.</VernacularTitle><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Uganda</Country><MedlineTA>Pan Afr Med J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101517926</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002163" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Cameroon</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014611" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vaccination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000072758" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vaccination Refusal</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000088823" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vaccination Hesitancy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073887" MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination Coverage</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005239" MajorTopicYN="N">Fear</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION">la vaccination est l'une des stratégies recommandées par l'Organisation mondiale de la Santé pour réduire le poids de la COVID-19. Cependant, de nombreux pays africains comme le Cameroun présentent de faibles couvertures vaccinales anti-COVID-19. Cette étude avait pour objectif d'étudier les raisons de refus de la population de la ville de Douala vis-à-vis de la vaccination contre la COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MÉTHODES">l'étude était transversale et analytique et conduite dans la ville de Douala du 10 février au 31 mai 2022. Les participants étaient âgés d'au moins 21 ans résidant dans la ville de Douala étaient interviewés. Les mesures d'association entre les variables d'intérêt ont été effectuées à l'aide des tests de Chi-deux et de Fisher avec un intervalle de confiance à 95%.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RÉSULTATS">au total, 1555 personnes avaient été incluses dans l'étude. Seulement 168 (11%) étaient vaccinées. La proportion de refus vaccinal était importante 711 (45,7%), 640 participants soit 41,1% hésitaient alors que 204 personnes soit 13,2% étaient favorable à la vaccination anti-COVID-19. Les raisons principales de refus de vaccination anti-COVID-19 étaient la crainte des effets indésirables 406 (44,8%), le manque d'information sur les vaccins 331 (36,5%) et le manque de confiance 302 (33,3%). Les facteurs associés au refus vaccinal étaient la religion (p=0,026) et le niveau d'étude (p=0,002).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">cette étude avait révélé la faible couverture vaccinale anti-COVID-19 à Douala avec une proportion importante de refus et hésitation vaccinale. Les stratégies de communication devraient tenir compte des raisons et facteurs associés au refus.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: André Arsène Bita Fouda et al.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cameroon</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Douala</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine refusal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine hesitation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Les auteurs ne déclarent aucun conflit d'intérêts.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39355714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11444086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11604/pamj.2024.48.61.39880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PAMJ-48-61</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Organisation Mondiale de la Santé . Genève: 2022. WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard. Visité le 31 mai 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohrabi C, Alsafi Z, O'Neill N, Khan M, Kerwan A, Al-Jabir A, et al. World Health Organization declares global emergency: A review of the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19) Int J Surg. 2020 Apr;76(2020):71–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7105032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32112977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sodki M, Marih L. COVID-19: épidémiologie et pathophysiologie. Batna J Med Sci. 2020 Aug;7(S1):S3–S8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation Mondiale de la Santé COVID-19 WHO Africa update. Brazzaville. 2022. Visité le 31 mai 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lapierre A, Fontaine G, Tremblay PL, Maheu-Cadotte MA, Desjardins M. La maladie à coronavirus (COVID-19): portrait des connaissances actuelles. Soins d'urgence. 2020 Printemps;1(1):13–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sodqi M. Vaccination contre la Covid-19: un énorme défi. Revue Marocaine de Santé Publique. 2021;8(12):2–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen R, Gemini GRC, Stahl JP, Levy C, Le Sage FV, Launay O, et al. Comprendre le développement des vaccins contre le SARS-CoV-2. Médecine &amp; enfance. 2020 Nov-Dec;1(1):1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation mondiale de la Santé Le déploiement de la vaccination contre la COVID-19 stagne en Afrique. Brazzaville. 2022. Visité le 31 mai 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlJamaan F, Temsah MH, Alhasan K, Alenezi S, Alhaboob A, Alrabiaah A, et al. SARS-CoV-2 variants and the global pandemic challenged by vaccine uptake during the emergence of the Delta variant: A national survey seeking vaccine hesitancy causes. J Infect Public Health. 2022 Jul;15(7):773–780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9212873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35728424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desclaux A, Bila B, Khoudia S, Varloteaux M, Houngnihinet RA. Les populations d'Afrique sont-elles prêtes à accepter le vaccin anti-COVID-19? Visité le 21 octobre 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mondal S, Stalteri R, Goel V, Horton S, Puchalski R. L, Muhajarine N, et al. Déterminants de l'hésitation 7à la vaccination contre la COVID-19 et moyens d'améliorer l'acceptation et la confiance dans le vaccin. 2021. Visité le 22 octobre 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harapan H, Anwar S, Yufika A, Sharun K, Gachabayov M, Fahriani M, et al. Vaccine hesitancy among communities in ten countries in Asia, Africa, and South America during the COVID-19 pandemic. Pathog Glob Health. 2022 Jun;116(4):236–243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9132408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34928187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhama K, Sharun K, Tiwari R, Dhawan M, Emran TB, Rabaan AA, et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy-reasons and solutions to achieve a successful global vaccination campaign to tackle the ongoing pandemic. Hum Vacin Immunother. 2021;17(10):3495–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8437517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34191680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaseen MO, Saif A, Khan TM, Yaseen M, Saif A, Bukhsh A, et al. A qualitative insight into the perceptions and COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy among Pakistani pharmacists. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2022 Dec;18(1):2031455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9009959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35192781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menezes NP, Iimuzingili M, Debebe ZY, Pivodic F, Massiah E. Comprendre les freins à la vaccination contre la COVID-19 en Afrique subsaharienne. Africa Can End Poverty. Visité le 23 mars 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fojnica A, Osmanovic A, Ðuzic N, Fejzic A, Mekic E, Gromilic Z, et al. COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and rejection in an adult population in Bosnia and Herzegovina. PLoS One. 2022 Feb 28;17(2):e0264754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8884480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35226708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fieselmann J, Annac K, Fabian Erdsiek F, Yilmaz-Aslan, Brzoska P. What are the reasons for refusing a COVID-19 vaccine? A qualitative analysis of social media in Germany. BMC Public Health. 2022 Apr;22(1):846.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9046705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35484619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soysal G, Durukan E, Akdur R. The Evaluation of Vaccine Hesitancy and Refusal for Childhood Vaccines and the COVID-19 Vaccine in Individuals Aged Between 18 and 25 Years 18-25. Turk J Immunol. 2021;9(3):120–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerda AA, Garcia LY. Hesitation and Refusal Factors in Individuals' Decision-Making Processes Regarding a Coronavirus Disease 2019 Vaccination. Frontiers in Public Health. 2021 Apr;9:626852. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2021.626852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.626852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8096991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33968880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montiel-Jarolin D, Samudio M. Vaccination against COVID-19 and causes of rejection of the vaccine in Paraguay. Rev. salud publica Parag. 2022 Jun;12(1):5–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcau F-C, Purec S, Niculescu G. Study on the Refusal of Vaccination against COVID-19 in Romania. Vaccines. 2022 Feb;10(2):261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8879492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35214719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carcelen AC, Prosperi C, Mutembo S, Chongwe G, Mwansa FD, Ndubani P, et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Zambia: a glimpse at the possible challenges ahead for COVID-19 vaccination rollout in sub-Saharan Africa. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2022 Dec;18(1):1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8920139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34227914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministère de la santé publique du Cameroun Etude sur l'acceptabilité et les logiques des populations à l'introduction d'un vaccin anti-covid au Cameroun. Rapport final. 2021 mars 25;:74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayle F. Évaluation des Connaissances. Attitudes et Pratiques des habitants de Oremu. Vaiare et Rimatara concernant la vaccination contre la COVID-19. 2021. Visité le 27 septembre 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salam AF, Soufianou M, Rokhaya C, Ndèye SC, Ouleye TF. L'acceptabilité des vaccins contre la COVID-19 au sein des communautés au Sénégal. Lartes. 2021. Visité le 23 septembre 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agbé B, Traoré Y, Diarrassouba M, Serigne N, Messou E, Aby-Davous A. P066 - Défis de la vaccination contre la COVID-19 en Côte d'Ivoire: connaissances, perception et confiance des populations vis-à-vis des vaccins anti-COVID. Rev Epidemiol Sante Publique. 2023 May;71:101708.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation Mondiale de la Santé . 2022. Nouveau coronavirus (2019-ncoV): flambée de la maladie à coronavirus (COVID-19) Visité le 31 mai 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministère de la Santé Publique du Cameroun-Coordination des Opérations d'Urgences de Santé Publique Rapport de situation COVID-19. N°130 du 19 au 25 Mai 2022 Yaoundé. 2022. Visité le 25 mai 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation Mondiale de la Santé Naming the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) and the virus that causes it. Genève. 2022. Visité le 23 mars 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Interim recommendations for an extended primary series with an additional vaccine dose for COVID-19 vaccination in immunocompromised persons. 2021. Visité le 12 mai 2022.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>