<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39365048</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-5336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>90</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied and environmental microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Environ Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A realistic approach for evaluating antimicrobial surfaces for dry surface exposure scenarios.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0115024</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0115024</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e01150-24</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/aem.01150-24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 pandemic has raised public awareness about the importance of hygiene, leading to an increased demand for antimicrobial surfaces to minimize microbial contamination on high-touch surfaces. This is particularly relevant in public and private transportation settings, where surfaces frequently touched by individuals pose a significant, yet preventable, risk of infection transmission. Typically, the antimicrobial activity of surfaces is tested using test methods of the International Standards Organization, American Society for Testing and Materials, or Japanese Industrial Standards, which involve complete submersion in liquid, elevated temperature (37°C), and prolonged (24 h) contact periods. However, these conditions do not accurately represent real-world scenarios where surfaces are exposed to air. In this study, we propose a modified test method designed to better reflect real-life conditions in the intended end-use setting. The modifications included using deionized water instead of nutrient broth while preparing bacterial inoculum, applying a small test inoculum to the surface and allowing it to dry, maintaining ambient temperature and relative humidity throughout the contact period, and reducing the contact period to 4 h. With this modified approach, the antimicrobial activity of 20 samples was reassessed. This screening revealed that out of 20 samples, only 2 samples were effective against all species, while 8 samples demonstrated partial effectiveness against selected species, and 10 samples showed no significant effect. These findings highlight the inadequacy of the current test standard and emphasize the urgent necessity for revised and adapted testing method to ensure a reliable and accurate evaluation.IMPORTANCEThe recent severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 pandemic has sparked increased demand for antimicrobial surfaces to mitigate the risk of fomites-transmitted infection in both indoors and confined spaces. Commonly, the antimicrobial activity of these surfaces is assessed using test standards established by national standards bodies, which do not distinguish between different application scenarios. While these test standards are suitable for surfaces intended for submerged application, they are inappropriate for antimicrobial surfaces designed for dry surface exposure. The usage of these standards can lead to an overestimation of antimicrobial efficacy. Thus, this study introduces a modified dry exposure test method aimed at better reflecting real-life conditions in the intended end-use setting. Our results revealed the subpar antimicrobial performance of numerous samples, highlighting the necessity to revise and tailor the universal test standard to real-world scenarios in order to ensure a reliable and accurate evaluation.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheong</LastName><ForeName>Yi Enn</ForeName><Initials>YE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0005-6793-6182</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Volkswagen AG, Group Innovation, Wolfsburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weyandt</LastName><ForeName>Ralph</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bioservices Department, SGS Institut Fresenius GmbH, Taunusstein, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dewald</LastName><ForeName>Wilma</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Volkswagen AG, Group Innovation, Wolfsburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tolksdorf</LastName><ForeName>Timo</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Volkswagen AG, Group Innovation, Wolfsburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Müller</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Preclinical Pharmacology and Toxicology, Fraunhofer Institute for Toxicology and Experimental Medicine - Hannover (Germany), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease Hannover (BREATH) research network Hannover (Germany), Member of the Fraunhofer Excellence Cluster of Immune Mediated Diseases (CIMD) and Institute of Immunology, Medizinische Hochschule Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Braun</LastName><ForeName>Armin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Preclinical Pharmacology and Toxicology, Fraunhofer Institute for Toxicology and Experimental Medicine - Hannover (Germany), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease Hannover (BREATH) research network Hannover (Germany), Member of the Fraunhofer Excellence Cluster of Immune Mediated Diseases (CIMD) and Institute of Immunology, Medizinische Hochschule Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Volkswagen Aktiengesellschaft (Volkswagen AG)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Environ Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7605801</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0099-2240</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000890">Anti-Infective Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000890" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Infective Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001419" MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013499" MajorTopicYN="N">Surface Properties</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibacterial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial coating</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral agents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">efficacy testing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fomite-transmitted infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">real-life scenarios</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">realistic condition</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surface coating</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39365048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11497783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01150-24</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Stephens B, Azimi P, Thoemmes MS, Heidarinejad M, Allen JG, Gilbert JA. 2019. Microbial exchange via fomites and implications for human health. Curr Pollut Rep 5:198–213. doi:10.1007/s40726-019-00123-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40726-019-00123-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7149182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34171005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wißmann JE, Kirchhoff L, Brüggemann Y, Todt D, Steinmann J, Steinmann E. 2021. Persistence of pathogens on inanimate surfaces: a narrative review. Microorganisms 9:343. doi:10.3390/microorganisms9020343</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms9020343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7916105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33572303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moon J, Ryu B-H. 2021. Transmission risks of respiratory infectious diseases in various confined spaces: a meta-analysis for future pandemics. Environ Res 202:111679. doi:10.1016/j.envres.2021.111679</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2021.111679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8566017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34265349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y. 2021. Basic routes of transmission of respiratory pathogens-A new proposal for transmission categorization based on respiratory spray, inhalation, and touch. Indoor Air 31:3–6. doi:10.1111/ina.12786</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ina.12786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8013452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33474779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suleyman G, Alangaden G, Bardossy AC. 2018. The role of environmental contamination in the transmission of nosocomial pathogens and healthcare-associated infections. Curr Infect Dis Rep 20:12. doi:10.1007/s11908-018-0620-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11908-018-0620-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29704133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández AM, Vargas-Robles D, Alcaraz LD, Peimbert M. 2020. Station and train surface microbiomes of Mexico City’s metro (subway/underground). Sci Rep 10:8798. doi:10.1038/s41598-020-65643-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-65643-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7260218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32472074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roukouni A, Homem de Almeida Correia G. 2020. Evaluation methods for the impacts of shared mobility: Classification and critical review. Sustainability 12:10504. doi:10.3390/su122410504</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su122410504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machado CAS, De Salles Hue NPM, Berssaneti FT, Quintanilha JA. 2018. An overview of shared mobility. Sustainability 10:4342. doi:10.3390/su10124342</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su10124342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muro-Rodríguez AI, Perez-Jiménez IR, Gutiérrez-Broncano S. 2017. Consumer behavior in the choice of mode of transport: a case study in the toledo-madrid corridor. Front Psychol 8:1011. doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2017.01011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.01011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5476976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28676776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garaus M, Garaus C. 2021. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on consumers' intention to use shared mobility services in German cities. Front Psychol 12:646593. doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2021.646593</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.646593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7956983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33732199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moges TK, Mitiku AG. 2023. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on the people’s choice of urban public transportation modes and mobility in Addis Ababa and Hawassa city, Ethiopia. Urban Plan Transp Res 11:14. doi:10.1080/21650020.2023.2193233</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21650020.2023.2193233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anke J, Francke A, Schaefer L-M, Petzoldt T. 2021. Impact of SARS-CoV-2 on the mobility behaviour in Germany. Eur Transp Res Rev 13:10. doi:10.1186/s12544-021-00469-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12544-021-00469-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7835317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38624595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das S, Boruah A, Banerjee A, Raoniar R, Nama S, Maurya AK. 2021. Impact of COVID-19: a radical modal shift from public to private transport mode. Transp Policy (Oxf) 109:1–11. doi:10.1016/j.tranpol.2021.05.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tranpol.2021.05.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9759716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36570699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasubramaniam B, Ranjan S, Saraf M, Kar P, Singh SP, Thakur VK, Singh A, Gupta RK. 2021. Antibacterial and antiviral functional materials: chemistry and biological activity toward tackling COVID-19-like pandemics. ACS Pharmacol Transl Sci 4:8–54. doi:10.1021/acsptsci.0c00174</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsptsci.0c00174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7784665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33615160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu L, Baghdachi J. 2015. Edited by Wu L and Baghdachi J. Functional polymer coatings. Principles, methods, and applications. Wiley, Hoboken, New Jersey.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molling JW, Seezink JW, Teunissen BE, Muijrers-Chen I, Borm PJ. 2014. Comparative performance of a panel of commercially available antimicrobial nanocoatings in Europe. Nanotechnol Sci Appl 7:97–104. doi:10.2147/NSA.S70782</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/NSA.S70782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4230231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25404853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenberg M, Ilić K, Juganson K, Ivask A, Ahonen M, Vinković Vrček I, Kahru A. 2019. Potential ecotoxicological effects of antimicrobial surface coatings: a literature survey backed up by analysis of market reports. PeerJ 7:e6315. doi:10.7717/peerj.6315</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.6315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6375256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30775167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bäumler W, Eckl D, Holzmann T, Schneider-Brachert W. 2022. Antimicrobial coatings for environmental surfaces in hospitals: a potential new pillar for prevention strategies in hygiene. Crit Rev Microbiol 48:531–564. doi:10.1080/1040841X.2021.1991271</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1040841X.2021.1991271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34699296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Organization for Standardization . 2019. Measurement of antiviral activity on plastics and other non-porous surfaces, 1st ed. 83.080.01</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Organization for Standardization . 2011. Measurement of antibacterial activity on plastics and other non-porous surfaces, 2nd ed. 83.080.01</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Organization for Standardization . 2019. Determination of antiviral activity of textile products, 2nd ed. 59.080.01</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Organization for Standardization . 2021. Determination of antibacterial activity of textile products, 3rd ed. 07.100.99</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campos MD, Zucchi PC, Phung A, Leonard SN, Hirsch EB. 2016. The activity of antimicrobial surfaces varies by testing protocol utilized. PLoS One 11:e0160728. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0160728</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0160728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4975443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27494336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owen L, Laird K. 2021. Development of a silver-based dual-function antimicrobial laundry additive and textile coating for the decontamination of healthcare laundry. J Appl Microbiol 130:1012–1022. doi:10.1111/jam.14850</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.14850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32916010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadeau E, Brunon C, Degraeve P, Leonard D, Grossiord C, Bessueille F, Cottaz A, Renaud F, Ferreira I, Darroux C, Simon F, Rimbault F, Oulahal N. 2012. Evaluation of antimicrobial activity of a polyhexamethylene biguanide-coated textile by monitoring both bacterial growth (ISO 20743/2005 standard) and viability (live/dead Baclight kit). J Food Saf 32:141–151. doi:10.1111/j.1745-4565.2011.00361.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4565.2011.00361.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali A, Hussain F, Attacha S, Kalsoom A, Qureshi WA, Shakeel M, Militky J, Tomkova B, Kremenakova D. 2021. Development of novel antimicrobial and antiviral green synthesized silver nanocomposites for the visual detection of Fe3+ ions. Nanomaterials (Basel) 11:2076. doi:10.3390/nano11082076</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11082076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8402186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34443906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assis M, Simoes LGP, Tremiliosi GC, Coelho D, Minozzi DT, Santos RI, Vilela DCB, Santos JR do, Ribeiro LK, Rosa ILV, Mascaro LH, Andrés J, Longo E. 2021. SiO2-Ag composite as a highly virucidal material: a roadmap that rapidly eliminates SARS-CoV-2. Nanomaterials (Basel) 11:638. doi:10.3390/nano11030638</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11030638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8001031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33806671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonald M, Wesgate R, Rubiano M, Holah J, Denyer SP, Jermann C, Maillard J-Y. 2020. Impact of a dry inoculum deposition on the efficacy of copper-based antimicrobial surfaces. J Hosp Infect 106:465–472. doi:10.1016/j.jhin.2020.08.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2020.08.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32810570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojeil M, Jermann C, Holah J, Denyer SP, Maillard J-Y. 2013. Evaluation of new in vitro efficacy test for antimicrobial surface activity reflecting UK hospital conditions. J Hosp Infect 85:274–281. doi:10.1016/j.jhin.2013.08.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2013.08.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24091310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knobloch J-M, Tofern S, Kunz W, Schütze S, Riecke M, Solbach W, Wuske T. 2017. “Life-like” assessment of antimicrobial surfaces by a new touch transfer assay displays strong superiority of a copper alloy compared to silver containing surfaces. PLoS One 12:e0187442. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0187442</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0187442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5685567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29135999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez-Gavilan A, de Castro JV, Arana A, Merino S, Retolaza A, Alves SA, Francone A, Kehagias N, Sotomayor-Torres CM, Cocina D, Mortera R, Crapanzano S, Pelegrín CJ, Garrigos MC, Jiménez A, Galindo B, Araque MC, Dykeman D, Neves NM, Marimón JM. 2021. Antibacterial activity testing methods for hydrophobic patterned surfaces. Sci Rep 11:6675. doi:10.1038/s41598-021-85995-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-85995-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7988007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33758227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valiei A, Okshevsky M, Lin N, Tufenkji N. 2018. Anodized aluminum with nanoholes impregnated with quaternary ammonium compounds can kill pathogenic bacteria within seconds of contact. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces 10:41207–41214. doi:10.1021/acsami.8b17634</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.8b17634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30395430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann EE, Manna D, Mettetal MR, May RM, Dannemiller EM, Chung KK, Brennan AB, Reddy ST. 2014. Surface micropattern limits bacterial contamination. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control 3:28. doi:10.1186/2047-2994-3-28</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/2047-2994-3-28</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4166016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25232470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McFARLAND J. 1907. The nephelometer. An instrument for estimating the number of bacteria in suspensions used for calculating the opsonic index and for vaccines. JAMA XLIX:1176. doi:10.1001/jama.1907.25320140022001f</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.1907.25320140022001f</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris RJC, ed. 1962. Techniques in experimental virology. Animal virus titration techniques. Academic press, London.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerba CP. 2015. Quaternary ammonium biocides: efficacy in application. Appl Environ Microbiol 81:464–469. doi:10.1089/fpd.2012.1155</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/fpd.2012.1155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4277564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25362069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardison RL, Ryan SP, Limmer RA, Crouse M, Nelson SW, Barriga D, Ghere JM, Stewart MJ, Lee SD, Taylor BM, James RR, Calfee MW, Howard MW. 2022. Residual antimicrobial coating efficacy against SARS-CoV-2. J Appl Microbiol 132:3375–3386. doi:10.1111/jam.15339</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.15339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9547327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34981882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aranega-Bou P, Brown N, Stigling A, D’Costa W, Verlander NQ, Pottage T, Bennett A, Moore G. 2023. Laboratory evaluation of a quaternary ammonium compound-based antimicrobial coating used in public transport during the COVID-19 pandemic. Appl Environ Microbiol 89:e0174422. doi:10.1128/aem.01744-22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01744-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10057021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36856438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artasensi A, Mazzotta S, Fumagalli L. 2021. Back to basics: choosing the appropriate surface disinfectant. Antibiotics (Basel) 10. doi:10.1016/j.copbio.2008.05.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2008.05.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8224088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34063833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daoud NN, Dickinson NA, Gilbert P. 1983. Antimicrobial activity and physico-chemical properties of some alkyldimethylbenzylammonium chlorides. Microbios 37:73–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6413825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wessels S, Ingmer H. 2013. Modes of action of three disinfectant active substances: a review. Regul Toxicol Pharmacol 67:456–467. doi:10.1016/j.yrtph.2013.09.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yrtph.2013.09.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24080225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asri LATW, Crismaru M, Roest S, Chen Y, Ivashenko O, Rudolf P, Tiller JC, van der Mei HC, Loontjens TJA, Busscher HJ. 2014. A shape-adaptive, antibacterial-coating of immobilized quaternary-ammonium compounds tethered on hyperbranched polyurea and its mechanism of action. Adv Funct Materials 24:346–355. doi:10.1002/adfm.201301686</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adfm.201301686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merkl P, Long S, McInerney GM, Sotiriou GA. 2021. Antiviral activity of silver, copper oxide and zinc oxide nanoparticle coatings against SARS-CoV-2. Nanomaterials (Basel) 11:1312. doi:10.3390/nano11051312</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11051312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8155969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34067553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh G, Joyce EM, Beddow J, Mason TJ. 2012. Evaluation of antibacterial activity of ZnO nanoparticles coated sonochemically onto textile fabrics. J Microbiol Biotechnol Food Sci 2:106–120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cyphert EL, von Recum HA. 2017. Emerging technologies for long-term antimicrobial device coatings: advantages and limitations. Exp Biol Med (Maywood) 242:788–798. doi:10.1177/1535370216688572</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1535370216688572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5407537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28110543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Redfern J, Tucker J, Simmons LM, Askew P, Stephan I, Verran J. 2018. Environmental and experimental factors affecting efficacy testing of nonporous plastic antimicrobial surfaces. Meth Protoc 1. doi:10.1111/lam.12714</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/lam.12714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6481088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31164576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fontecha-Umaña F, Ríos-Castillo AG, Ripolles-Avila C, Rodríguez-Jerez JJ. 2020. Antimicrobial activity and prevention of bacterial biofilm formation of silver and zinc oxide nanoparticle-containing polyester surfaces at various concentrations for use. Foods 9:442. doi:10.3390/foods9040442</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods9040442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7230149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32268566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michels HT, Noyce JO, Keevil CW. 2009. Effects of temperature and humidity on the efficacy of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus challenged antimicrobial materials containing silver and copper. Lett Appl Microbiol 49:191–195. doi:10.1111/j.1472-765X.2009.02637.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2009.02637.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2779462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19413757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salah I, Parkin IP, Allan E. 2021. Copper as an antimicrobial agent: recent advances. RSC Adv 11:18179–18186. doi:10.1039/d1ra02149d</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/d1ra02149d</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9033467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35480904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behzadinasab S, Hosseini M, Williams MD, Ivester HM, Allen IC, Falkinham JO, Ducker WA. 2022. Antimicrobial activity of cuprous oxide-coated and cupric oxide-coated surfaces. J Hosp Infect 129:58–64. doi:10.1016/j.jhin.2022.07.022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2022.07.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35940287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butot S, Baert L, Zuber S. 2021. Assessment of antiviral coatings for high-touch surfaces by using human coronaviruses HCoV-229E and SARS-CoV-2. Appl Environ Microbiol 87:e0109821. doi:10.1016/j.jinf.2020.06.059</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.06.059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8432523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34288707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munir MT, Pailhories H, Eveillard M, Irle M, Aviat F, Dubreil L, Federighi M, Belloncle C. 2020. Testing the antimicrobial characteristics of wood materials: a review of methods. Antibiotics (Basel) 9. doi:10.1007/s00107-018-1370-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00107-018-1370-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7277147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32370037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismaïl R, Le Bayon I, Michel V, Jequel M, Kutnik M, Aviat F, Fédérighi M. 2015. Comparative study of three methods for recovering microorganisms from wooden surfaces in the food industry. Food Anal Method 8:1238–1247. doi:10.1007/s12161-014-0008-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-014-0008-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares VM, Pereira JG, Viana C, Izidoro TB, Bersot L dos S, Pinto J de A. 2012. Transfer of Salmonella enteritidis to four types of surfaces after cleaning procedures and cross-contamination to tomatoes. Food Microbiol 30:453–456. doi:10.1016/j.fm.2011.12.028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2011.12.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22365360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Druvari D, Koromilas N, Bekiari V, Bokias G, Kallitsis J. 2018. Polymeric antimicrobial coatings based on quaternary ammonium compounds. Coatings 8:8. doi:10.3390/coatings8010008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/coatings8010008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gozzelino G, Tobar DER, Chaitiemwong N, Hazeleger W, Beumer R. 2011. Antibacterial activity of reactive quaternary ammonium compounds in solution and in nonleachable coatings. J Food Prot 74:2107–2112. doi:10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-11-220</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-11-220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22186051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullen DC, Wan X, Takala TM, Saris PE, Moreira VM. 2021. Precision design of antimicrobial surfaces. Front Med Technol 3:640929. doi:10.3389/fmedt.2021.640929</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmedt.2021.640929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8757849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35047910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhidime ID, Saubade F, Benson PS, Butler JA, Olivier S, Kelly P, Verran J, Whitehead KA. 2019. The antimicrobial effect of metal substrates on food pathogens. Food Bioprod Process 113:68–76. doi:10.1016/j.fbp.2018.09.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbp.2018.09.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie X, Li Y, Zhang T, Fang HHP. 2006. Bacterial survival in evaporating deposited droplets on a teflon-coated surface. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 73:703–712. doi:10.1007/s00253-006-0492-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-006-0492-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7080038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17053902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gładyszewska-Fiedoruk K, Teleszewski TJ. 2020. Modeling of humidity in passenger cars equipped with mechanical ventilation. Energ 13:2987. doi:10.3390/en13112987</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/en13112987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercer DK, Torres MDT, Duay SS, Lovie E, Simpson L, von Köckritz-Blickwede M, de la Fuente-Nunez C, O’Neil DA, Angeles-Boza AM. 2020. Antimicrobial susceptibility testing of antimicrobial peptides to better predict efficacy. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 10:326. doi:10.3389/fcimb.2020.00326</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2020.00326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7358464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32733816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van de Lagemaat M, Grotenhuis A, van de Belt-Gritter B, Roest S, Loontjens TJA, Busscher HJ, van der Mei HC, Ren Y. 2017. Comparison of methods to evaluate bacterial contact-killing materials. Acta Biomater 59:139–147. doi:10.1016/j.actbio.2017.06.042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2017.06.042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28666886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunliffe AJ, Askew PD, Stephan I, Iredale G, Cosemans P, Simmons LM, Verran J, Redfern J. 2021. How do we determine the efficacy of an antibacterial surface? A review of standardised antibacterial material testing methods. Antibiotics (Basel) 10:1069. doi:10.3390/antibiotics10091069</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics10091069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8472414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34572650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>