<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39363681</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2192-2659</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced healthcare materials</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Healthc Mater</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Oligonucleotide-Linked Lipid Nanoparticles as a Versatile mRNA Nanovaccine Platform.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2401868</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2401868</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/adhm.202401868</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>An effective delivery platform is crucial for the development of mRNA vaccines and therapeutics. Here, a versatile platform utilizing cholesterol-modified oligonucleotides (L-oligo) that bind to the mRNA within lipid nanoparticles (LNP), and enables the effective delivery of the mRNA into target cells is introduced. mRNA incorporated into LNPs via linkage with L-oligo, termed oligonucleotide-linked LNP (lnLNP), is superior in cellular uptake and transfection efficiency in target cells in vitro and in vivo, compared to the conventional LNP formulations. It is further applied lnLNP as an mRNA vaccine platform for SARS-CoV-2, demonstrating robust induction of neutralizing activity as well as polyfunctional SARS-CoV-2-specific T-cell response in vivo. The current strategy can be versatilely applied to different LNP platforms, for vaccine and therapeutic applications against various diseases, such as infections and cancers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Im</LastName><ForeName>San Hae</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon, 34141, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chung</LastName><ForeName>Youseung</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate School of Medical Science and Engineering, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon, 34141, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duskunovic</LastName><ForeName>Nevena</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon, 34141, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choi</LastName><ForeName>Heewon</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon, 34141, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Su-Hyung</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate School of Medical Science and Engineering, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon, 34141, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Center for Epidemic Preparedness, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon, 34141, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chung</LastName><ForeName>Hyun Jung</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5055-902X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon, 34141, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2022R1A4A5028131</GrantID><Agency>National Research Foundation of Korea</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>RS-2023-00222762</GrantID><Agency>National Research Foundation of Korea</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>RS-2024-00355464</GrantID><Agency>National Research Foundation of Korea</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Yuhan Corporation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Healthc Mater</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101581613</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2192-2640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">linker oligonucleotide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lipid nanoparticle</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mRNA delivery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39363681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adhm.202401868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>a) X. Hou, T. Zaks, R. Langer, Y. Dong, Nat. Rev. Mater. 2021, 6, 1078;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) E. Rohner, R. Yang, K. S. Foo, A. Goedel, K. R. Chien, Nat. Biotechnol. 2022, 40, 1586.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) P. Nordström, M. Ballin, A. Nordström, Lancet Reg. Health Eur. 2022, 21, 100466;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) L. R. Baden, H. M. E. Sahly, B. Essink, K. Kotloff, S. Frey, R. Novak, D. Diemert, S. A. Spector, N. Rouphael, C. B. Creech, J. McGettigan, S. Khetan, N. Segall, J. Solis, A. Brosz, C. Fierro, H. Schwartz, K. Neuzil, L. Corey, P. Gilbert, H. Janes, D. Follmann, M. Marovich, J. Mascola, L. Polakowski, J. Ledgerwood, B. S. Graham, H. Bennett, R. Pajon, C. Knightly, et al., N. Engl. J. Med. 2020, 384, 403;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) A. B. Vogel, I. Kanevsky, Y. Che, K. A. Swanson, A. Muik, M. Vormehr, L. M. Kranz, K. C. Walzer, S. Hein, A. Güler, J. Loschko, M. S. Maddur, A. Ota‐Setlik, K. Tompkins, J. Cole, B. G. Lui, T. Ziegenhals, A. Plaschke, D. Eisel, S. C. Dany, S. Fesser, S. Erbar, F. Bates, D. Schneider, B. Jesionek, B. Sänger, A.‐K. Wallisch, Y. Feuchter, H. Junginger, S. A. Krumm, et al., Nature 2021, 592, 283;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) K. S. Corbett, D. K. Edwards, S. R. Leist, O. M. Abiona, S. Boyoglu‐Barnum, R. A. Gillespie, S. Himansu, A. Schäfer, C. T. Ziwawo, A. T. DiPiazza, K. H. Dinnon, S. M. Elbashir, C. A. Shaw, A. Woods, E. J. Fritch, D. R. Martinez, K. W. Bock, M. Minai, B. M. Nagata, G. B. Hutchinson, K. Wu, C. Henry, K. Bahl, D. Garcia‐Dominguez, L. Ma, I. Renzi, W.‐P. Kong, S. D. Schmidt, L. Wang, Y. Zhang, et al., Nature 2020, 586, 567;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) J.‐L. Excler, M. Saville, S. Berkley, J. H. Kim, Nat. Med. 2021, 27, 591;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>f) E. Fang, X. Liu, M. Li, Z. Zhang, L. Song, B. Zhu, X. Wu, J. Liu, D. Zhao, Y. Li, Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022, 7, 94;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>g) G. T. Szabó, A. J. Mahiny, I. Vlatkovic, Mol. Ther. 2022, 30, 1850.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) U. Sahin, K. Karikó, Ö. Türeci, Nat. Rev. Drug Discovery 2014, 13, 759;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) J. D. Beck, D. Reidenbach, N. Salomon, U. Sahin, Ö. Türeci, M. Vormehr, L. M. Kranz, Mol. Cancer 2021, 20, 69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) N. Sa‐nguanmoo, K. Namdee, M. Khongkow, U. Ruktanonchai, Y. Zhao, X.‐J. Liang, Nano Res. 2022, 15, 2196;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) N. Pardi, M. J. Hogan, F. W. Porter, D. Weissman, Nat. Rev. Drug Discovery 2018, 17, 261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. Shahjin, M. Patel, J. Machhi, J. D. Cohen, M. U. Nayan, P. Yeapuri, C. Zhang, E. Waight, M. Hasan, M. M. Abdelmoaty, P. K. Dash, Y. Zhou, I. Andreu, H. E. Gendelman, B. D. Kevadiya, Acta Biomater. 2023, 158, 493;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) P. F. McKay, J. Zhou, R. Frise, A. K. Blakney, C. R. Bouton, Z. Wang, K. Hu, K. Samnuan, J. C. Brown, R. Kugathasan, J. Yeow, M. M. Stevens, W. S. Barclay, J. S. Tregoning, R. J. Shattock, Oxf. Open Immunol. 2022, 3, iqac004;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) P. Gu, A. Wusiman, Y. Zhang, Z. Liu, R. Bo, Y. Hu, J. Liu, D. Wang, Mol. Pharmaceutics 2019, 16, 5000;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) A. K. Patel, J. C. Kaczmarek, S. Bose, K. J. Kauffman, F. Mir, M. W. Heartlein, F. DeRosa, R. Langer, D. G. Anderson, Adv. Mater. 2019, 31, 1805116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) P. Daftarian, A. E. Kaifer, W. Li, B. B. Blomberg, D. Frasca, F. Roth, R. Chowdhury, E. A. Berg, J. B. Fishman, H. A. A. Sayegh, P. Blackwelder, L. Inverardi, V. L. Perez, V. Lemmon, P. Serafini, Cancer Res. 2011, 71, 7452;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) J. S. Chahal, O. F. Khan, C. L. Cooper, J. S. McPartlan, J. K. Tsosie, L. D. Tilley, S. M. Sidik, S. Lourido, R. Langer, S. Bavari, H. L. Ploegh, D. G. Anderson, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2016, 113, E4133;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) Q. Cheng, T. Wei, Y. Jia, L. Farbiak, K. Zhou, S. Zhang, Y. Wei, H. Zhu, D. J. Siegwart, Adv. Mater. 2018, 30, 1805308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) U. Elia, S. Rotem, E. Bar‐Haim, S. Ramishetti, G. S. Naidu, D. Gur, M. Aftalion, M. Israeli, A. Bercovich‐Kinori, R. Alcalay, E. Makdasi, T. Chitlaru, R. Rosenfeld, T. Israely, S. Melamed, I. A. Ionita, D. Danino, D. Peer, O. Cohen, Nano Lett. 2021, 21, 4774;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) N. Veiga, M. Goldsmith, Y. Granot, D. Rosenblum, N. Dammes, R. Kedmi, S. Ramishetti, D. Peer, Nat. Commun. 2018, 9, 4493;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) N. Duskunovic, S. H. Im, J. Lee, H. J. Chung, Mol. Pharmaceutics 2023, 20, 3088;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) L. Miao, J. Lin, Y. Huang, L. Li, D. Delcassian, Y. Ge, Y. Shi, D. G. Anderson, Nat. Commun. 2020, 11, 2424;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) J. Qin, L. Xue, N. Gong, H. Zhang, S. J. Shepherd, R. M. Haley, K. L. Swingle, M. J. Mitchell, RSC Adv. 2022, 12, 25397.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. M. Lee, Q. Cheng, X. Yu, S. Liu, L. T. Johnson, D. J. Siegwart, Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2021, 60, 5848;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Q. Cheng, T. Wei, L. Farbiak, L. T. Johnson, S. A. Dilliard, D. J. Siegwart, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2020, 15, 313;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) E. Álvarez‐Benedicto, L. Farbiak, M. M. Ramírez, X. Wang, L. T. Johnson, O. Mian, E. D. Guerrero, D. J. Siegwart, Biomater. Sci. 2021, 10, 549.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) S. Liu, Q. Cheng, T. Wei, X. Yu, L. T. Johnson, L. Farbiak, D. J. Siegwart, Nat. Mater. 2021, 20, 701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Ndeupen, Z. Qin, S. Jacobsen, A. Bouteau, H. Estanbouli, B. Z. Igyártó, iScience 2021, 24, 103479;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) R. Kedmi, N. Ben‐Arie, D. Peer, Biomaterials 2010, 31, 6867;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) D. Peer, Adv. Drug Delivery Rev. 2012, 64, 1738.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) H. Huo, X. Cheng, J. Xu, J. Lin, N. Chen, X. Lu, J. Mater. Chem. B 2023, 11, 4171;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. P. Lokugamage, D. Vanover, J. Beyersdorf, M. Z. C. Hatit, L. Rotolo, E. S. Echeverri, H. E. Peck, H. Ni, J.‐K. Yoon, Y. Kim, P. J. Santangelo, J. E. Dahlman, Nat. Biomed. Eng. 2021, 5, 1059;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) K. Hashiba, Y. Sato, M. Taguchi, S. Sakamoto, A. Otsu, Y. Maeda, T. Shishido, M. Murakawa, A. Okazaki, H. Harashima, Small Sci. 2023, 3, 2200071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Q. Wang, X. Ma, J. Jia, H. Fei, J. Mater. Chem. B 2016, 4, 1535;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. N. Endsley, R. J. Y. Ho, AAPS J. 2012, 14, 225;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) J. Chen, Z. Ye, C. Huang, M. Qiu, D. Song, Y. Li, Q. Xu, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2022, 119, e2207841119;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) R. Goswami, D. Chatzikleanthous, G. Lou, F. Giusti, A. Bonci, M. Taccone, M. Brazzoli, S. Gallorini, I. Ferlenghi, F. Berti, D. T. O'Hagan, C. Pergola, B. C. Baudner, R. Adamo, ACS Infect. Dis. 2019, 5, 1546.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Han, H. Zhang, K. Butowska, K. L. Swingle, M.‐G. Alameh, D. Weissman, M. J. Mitchell, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 7233.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Lee, S. Amirthalingam, C. Lee, A. K. Rajendran, Y.‐H. Ahn, N. S. Hwang, Nanoscale Adv. 2023, 5, 3834.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) N. Yoshinaga, S. Uchida, A. Dirisala, M. Naito, K. Osada, H. Cabral, K. Kataoka, J. Controlled Release 2021, 330, 317;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) N. Yoshinaga, S. Uchida, M. Naito, K. Osada, H. Cabral, K. Kataoka, Biomaterials 2019, 197, 255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) R. A. Haraszti, R. Miller, M.‐C. Didiot, A. Biscans, J. F. Alterman, M. R. Hassler, L. Roux, D. Echeverria, E. Sapp, M. DiFiglia, N. Aronin, A. Khvorova, Mol. Ther. 2018, 26, 1973;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. Biscans, R. A. Haraszti, D. Echeverria, R. Miller, M.‐C. Didiot, M. Nikan, L. Roux, N. Aronin, A. Khvorova, Mol. Ther. 2018, 26, 1520.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. Raouane, D. Desmaële, G. Urbinati, L. Massaad‐Massade, P. Couvreur, Bioconjug. Chem. 2012, 23, 1091;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Y. Zheng, W. Tai, Wiley Interdiscip. Rev.: Nanomed. Nanobiotechnol. 2020, 12, e1606;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) M. F. Osborn, A. Khvorova, Nucl. Acid Ther. 2018, 28, 128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) K. Lee, S. N. Cohen, J. Biol. Chem. 2001, 276, 23268;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) B. Li, X. Luo, Y. Dong, Bioconjugate Chem. 2016, 27, 849.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. H. Y. Cheng, J. Leung, Y. Zhang, C. Strong, G. Basha, A. Momeni, Y. Chen, E. Jan, A. Abdolahzadeh, X. Wang, J. A. Kulkarni, D. Witzigmann, P. R. Cullis, Adv. Mater. 2023, 35, 2303370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) H. Zhang, L. Zhang, A. Lin, C. Xu, Z. Li, K. Liu, B. Liu, X. Ma, F. Zhao, H. Jiang, C. Chen, H. Shen, H. Li, D. H. Mathews, Y. Zhang, L. Huang, Nature 2023, 621, 396;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) S. Mikkola, U. Kaukinen, H. Lönnberg, Cell Biochem. Biophys. 2001, 34, 95;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) H. K. Wayment‐Steele, D. S. Kim, C. A. Choe, J. J. Nicol, R. Wellington‐Oguri, A. M. Watkins, R. A. Parra Sperberg, P.‐S. Huang, E. Participants, R. Das, Nucl. Acids Res. 2021, 49, gkab764.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. D. Nance, J. L. Meier, ACS Cent. Sci. 2021, 7, 748.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Boyd, J. R. Almeida, P. A. Darrah, D. Sauce, R. A. Seder, V. Appay, G. Gorochov, M. Larsen, PLoS One 2015, 10, e0128714.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>