<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39367655</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-1492</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>NMR in biomedicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>NMR Biomed</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Influence of echo time on pulmonary ventilation and perfusion derived by phase-resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI using multi-echo ultrashort echo time acquisition.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e5270</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e5270</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/nbm.5270</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Non-contrast enhanced <sup>1</sup>H magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is promising for ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) assessment of the lung but the influence of the echo time (TE) on V/Q parameters is lacking. Therefore, the purpose of this study was to investigate the influence of different TEs on pulmonary V/Q parameters derived by phase-resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI using a multi-echo ultrashort TE (UTE) acquisition. A 2D multi-echo UTE sequence with radial center out readout and tiny golden angle increment was developed. Forty-eight participants were enrolled in this study: 25 healthy subjects, six patients with asthma, and 17 patients with pulmonary fibrosis. Participants underwent two acquisitions of 2D multi-echo UTE MRI with three TEs per acquisition (TE<sub>1-6</sub>: 0.07, 0.82, 1.72, 2.47, 3.37, and 4.12 ms). Regional ventilation (RVent), flow-volume loop cross-correlation metric (FVL-CM), and normalized perfusion-weighted signal (QN) maps were calculated. V/Q defect percentages (VDP/QDP) were determined. To assess repeatability, the measurement was repeated in healthy subjects. Median and interquartile range of RVent, FVL-CM, QN, VDP, and QDP were calculated. To assess significant differences between parameters obtained at different TEs, Friedman's test and Dunnett's test were performed. Pearson correlation coefficients between RVent derived at TE<sub>1</sub> and the difference in RVent between TE<sub>2,3</sub> and TE<sub>1</sub> were calculated. For repeatability assessment, coefficient of variation (CoV) and intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) were determined. Significant differences were found comparing V/Q parameters obtained at TE<sub>3-6</sub> compared to TE<sub>1</sub>. CoV increased with TE. For ICC, values between 0.35 (QDP at TE<sub>1</sub>) and 0.83 (VDP<sub>RVent</sub> at TE<sub>2</sub>) were obtained for T<sub>1,2</sub>. Statistically significant differences for ventilation and perfusion parameters derived by PREFUL were found for TE<sub>3-6</sub> compared to TE<sub>1</sub>. All V/Q parameters were well repeatable for TE<sub>1-2</sub>. With increasing TE and respiratory volume, RVent shows a T2*-dependency leading to biased ventilation assessment compared to TE<sub>1</sub>.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). NMR in Biomedicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Behrendt</LastName><ForeName>Lea</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8851-1849</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gutberlet</LastName><ForeName>Marcel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Voskrebenzev</LastName><ForeName>Andreas</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Klimeš</LastName><ForeName>Filip</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2715-0757</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Obert</LastName><ForeName>Arnd J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiation Oncology, University Hospital Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kern</LastName><ForeName>Agilo L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Horstmann</LastName><ForeName>Dominik</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wernz</LastName><ForeName>Marius M</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Müller</LastName><ForeName>Robin A</ForeName><Initials>RA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wacker</LastName><ForeName>Frank</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vogel-Claussen</LastName><ForeName>Jens</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research in Endstage and Obstructive Lung Disease (BREATH), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Hannover Medical School</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>NMR Biomed</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8915233</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0952-3480</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PREFUL</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UTE</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lung</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multi‐echo</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">perfusion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ventilation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39367655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/nbm.5270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Galiè N, Humbert M, Vachiery JL, et al. 2015 ESC/ERS guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary hypertension: The Joint Task Force for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Pulmonary Hypertension of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Respiratory Society (ERS): Endor. Eur Respir J. 2015;46(4):903‐975. doi:10.1183/13993003.01032‐2015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerrero T, Sanders K, Castillo E, et al. Dynamic ventilation imaging from four‐dimensional computed tomography. Phys Med Biol. 2006;51(4):777‐791. doi:10.1088/0031‐9155/51/4/002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scharm SC, Schaefer‐Prokop C, Winther HB, et al. Regional pulmonary morphology and function: photon‐counting CT assessment. Radiology. 2023;308(1):e230318. doi:10.1148/RADIOL.230318</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galbán CJ, Han MK, Boes JL, et al. Computed tomography–based biomarker provides unique signature for diagnosis of COPD phenotypes and disease progression. Nat Med. 2012;18(11):1711‐1715. doi:10.1038/nm.2971</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Connell OJ, McWilliams S, McGarrigle AM, et al. Radiologic imaging in cystic fibrosis: cumulative effective dose and changing trends over 2 decades. Chest. 2012;141(6):1575‐1583. doi:10.1378/chest.11‐1972</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo W, Ciet P, Tiddens HAWM, Zhang W, Guillerman RP, Van Straten M. Monitoring cystic fibrosis lung disease by computed tomography: radiation risk in perspective. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2014;189(11):1328‐1336. doi:10.1164/rccm.201311‐2099CI</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theilmann RJ, Arai TJ, Samiee A, et al. Quantitative MRI measurement of lung density must account for the change in T*2 with lung inflation. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2009;30(3):527‐534. doi:10.1002/jmri.21866</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu J, Xue Y, Song HK. Comparison of lung T2* during free‐breathing at 1.5T and 3.0T with ultrashort echo time (UTE) imaging. Magn Reson Med. 2011;66(1):248. doi:10.1002/MRM.22829</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wild JM, Marshall H, Bock M, et al. MRI of the lung (1/3): methods. Insights Imaging. 2012;3(4):345‐353. doi:10.1007/S13244‐012‐0176‐X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasch A, Metze P, Stumpf K, et al. 2D ultrashort echo‐time functional lung imaging. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2020;52(6):1637‐1644. doi:10.1002/jmri.27269</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendes Pereira L, Wech T, Weng AM, et al. UTE‐SENCEFUL: first results for 3D high‐resolution lung ventilation imaging. Magn Reson Med. 2019;81(4):2464‐2473. doi:10.1002/MRM.27576</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triphan SMF, Weinheimer O, Gutberlet M, et al. Echo time‐dependent observed lung T1 in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in correlation with quantitative imaging and clinical indices. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2021;54(5):1562‐1571. doi:10.1002/JMRI.27746</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triphan SMF, Stahl M, Jobst BJ, et al. Echo time‐dependence of observed lung T1 in patients with cystic fibrosis and correlation with clinical metrics. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2020;52(6):1645‐1654. doi:10.1002/JMRI.27271</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher Alsady T, Voskrebenzev A, Greer M, et al. MRI‐derived regional flow‐volume loop parameters detect early‐stage chronic lung allograft dysfunction. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2019;50(6):1873‐1882. doi:10.1002/JMRI.26799</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauman G, Puderbach M, Deimling M, et al. Non‐contrast‐enhanced perfusion and ventilation assessment of the human lung by means of Fourier decomposition in proton MRI. Magn Reson Med. 2009;62(3):656‐664. doi:10.1002/mrm.22031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glandorf J, Klimeš F, Voskrebenzev A, et al. Comparison of phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI derived perfusion and ventilation parameters at 1.5T and 3T in healthy volunteers. Baltzer PAT, ed. PLoS One. 2020;15(12):e0244638. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0244638</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voskrebenzev A, Gutberlet M, Klimeš F, et al. Feasibility of quantitative regional ventilation and perfusion mapping with phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI in healthy volunteers and COPD, CTEPH, and CF patients. Magn Reson Med. 2018;79(4):2306‐2314. doi:10.1002/mrm.26893</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klimeš F, Voskrebenzev A, Gutberlet M, et al. 3D phase‐resolved functional lung ventilation MR imaging in healthy volunteers and patients with chronic pulmonary disease. Magn Reson Med. 2021;85(2):912‐925. doi:10.1002/mrm.28482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pöhler GH, Klimeš F, Behrendt L, et al. Repeatability of phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL)‐MRI ventilation and perfusion parameters in healthy subjects and COPD patients. J Magn Reson Imaging Published online. 2020;53(3):915‐927. doi:10.1002/jmri.27385</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel‐Claussen J, Kaireit TF, Voskrebenzev A, et al. Phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI–derived ventilation and perfusion parameters predict future lung transplant loss. Radiology. 2023;307(4):e221958. doi:10.1148/RADIOL.221958/ASSET/IMAGES/LARGE/RADIOL.221958.TBL4.JPEG</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behrendt L, Voskrebenzev A, Klimeš F, et al. Validation of automated perfusion‐weighted phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL)‐MRI in patients with pulmonary diseases. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2020;52(1):103‐114. doi:10.1002/jmri.27027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behrendt L, Smith LJ, Voskrebenzev A, et al. A dual center and dual vendor comparison study of automated perfusion‐weighted phase‐resolved functional lung magnetic resonance imaging with dynamic contrast‐enhanced magnetic resonance imaging in patients with cystic fibrosis. Pulm Circ. 2022;12(2):e12054. doi:10.1002/pul2.12054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Couch MJ, Munidasa S, Rayment JH, et al. Comparison of functional free‐breathing pulmonary 1H and hyperpolarized 129Xe magnetic resonance imaging in pediatric cystic fibrosis. Acad Radiol. 2020;0(8):e209‐e218. doi:10.1016/j.acra.2020.05.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaireit TF, Kern A, Voskrebenzev A, et al. Flow volume loop and regional ventilation assessment using phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI: comparison with 129Xenon ventilation MRI and lung function testing. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2021;53(4):1092‐1105. doi:10.1002/JMRI.27452</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pöhler GH, Löffler F, Klimeš F, et al. Validation of phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) magnetic resonance imaging pulse wave transit time compared to echocardiography in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2022;56(2):605‐615. doi:10.1002/JMRI.28016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klimeš F, Obert AJ, Scheller J, et al. Comparison of free‐breathing 3D phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI with dynamic 19 F ventilation MRI in patients with obstructive lung disease and healthy volunteers. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2024; 60:1416‐1431. doi:10.1002/JMRI.29221</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klimeš F, Voskrebenzev A, Gutberlet M, et al. Repeatability of dynamic 3D phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) ventilation MR imaging in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and healthy volunteers. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2021;54(2):618‐629. doi:10.1002/JMRI.27543</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher Alsady T, Voskrebenzev A, Behrendt L, et al. Multicenter standardization of phase‐resolved functional lung MRI in patients with suspected chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension. J Magn Reson Imaging. Published online. 2023;59(6):1953‐1964. doi:10.1002/JMRI.28995</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munidasa S, Couch MJ, Rayment JH, et al. Free‐breathing MRI for monitoring ventilation changes following antibiotic treatment of pulmonary exacerbations in paediatric cystic fibrosis. Eur Respir J. 2021;57(4):2003104. doi:10.1183/13993003.03104‐2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaireit TF, Gutberlet M, Voskrebenzev A, et al. Comparison of quantitative regional ventilation‐weighted fourier decomposition MRI with dynamic fluorinated gas washout MRI and lung function testing in COPD patients. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2018;47(6):1534‐1541. doi:10.1002/JMRI.25902</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holguin F, Cardet JC, Chung KF, et al. Management of severe asthma: a European Respiratory Society/American Thoracic Society guideline. Eur Respir J. 2020;55(1):1900588. doi:10.1183/13993003.00588‐2019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triphan SMF, Breuer FA, Gensler D, Kauczor HU, Jakob PM. Oxygen enhanced lung MRI by simultaneous measurement of T1 and T2* during free breathing using ultrashort TE. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2015;41(6):1708‐1714. doi:10.1002/jmri.24692</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wundrak S, Paul J, Ulrici J, Hell E, Rasche V. A small surrogate for the golden angle in time‐resolved radial MRI based on generalized fibonacci sequences. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2015;34(6):1262‐1269. doi:10.1109/TMI.2014.2382572</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pauly J, Conolly S, Nishimura D, Macovski A. Slice‐selective excitation for very short T2 species. In: 8th Annual Meeting of the Society of Magnetic Resonance in Medicin. 1989:28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodsky EK, Samsonov AA, Block WF. Characterizing and correcting gradient errors in non‐Cartesian imaging: are gradient errors linear‐time‐invariant? Magn Reson Med. 2009;62(6):1466‐1476. doi:10.1002/MRM.22100</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodsky EK, Klaers JL, Samsonov AA, Kijowski R, Block WF. Rapid measurement and correction of phase errors from B0 Eddy currents: impact on image quality for non‐Cartesian imaging. Magn Reson Med. 2013;69(2):509‐515. doi:10.1002/MRM.24264</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uecker M, Ong F, Tamir J, et al. Berkeley advanced reconstruction toolbox. Proc Intl Soc Mag Reson Med. 2015;23:2486. doi:10.1002/mrm.25176</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avants BB, Tustison NJ, Song G, Cook PA, Klein A, Gee JC. A reproducible evaluation of ANTs similarity metric performance in brain image registration. Neuroimage. 2011;54(3):2033‐2044. doi:10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.09.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voskrebenzev A, Gutberlet M, Kaireit TF, Wacker F, Vogel‐Claussen J. Low‐pass imaging of dynamic acquisitions (LIDA) with a group‐oriented registration (GOREG) for proton MR imaging of lung ventilation. Magn Reson Med. 2017;78(4):1496‐1505. doi:10.1002/mrm.26526</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isensee F, Jaeger PF, Kohl SAA, Petersen J, Maier‐Hein KH. nnU‐Net: a self‐configuring method for deep learning‐based biomedical image segmentation. Nat Methods. 2020;18(2):203‐211. doi:10.1038/s41592‐020‐01008‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klimeš F, Voskrebenzev A, Gutberlet M, et al. Free‐breathing quantification of regional ventilation derived by phase‐resolved functional lung (PREFUL) MRI. NMR Biomed. 2019;32(6):e4088. doi:10.1002/NBM.4088</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGraw KO, Wong SP. Forming inferences about some Intraclass correlation coefficients. Psychol Methods. 1996;1(1):30‐46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koo TK, Li MY. A guideline of selecting and reporting Intraclass correlation coefficients for reliability research. J Chiropr Med. 2016;15(2):155‐163. doi:10.1016/J.JCM.2016.02.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang B, Metze P, Balasch A, et al. Reproducibility of functional lung parameters derived from free‐breathing non‐contrast‐enhanced 2D ultrashort echo‐time. Quant Imaging Med Surg. 2022;12(10):4720733‐4724733. doi:10.21037/QIMS‐22‐92</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun C, Manavaki R, Tarkin J, et al. Hybrid bias correction of thoracic zero echo time (ZTE) images. Proc Intl Soc Mag Reson Med. 2021;29:2631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wundrak S, Paul J, Ulrici J, et al. A self‐gating method for time‐resolved imaging of nonuniform motion. Magn Reson Med. 2016;76(3):919‐925. doi:10.1002/MRM.26000</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metze P, Frantz H, Straubmüller F, et al. Non‐uniform self‐gating in 2D lung imaging. Front Phys. 2022;10:836178. doi:10.3389/FPHY.2022.836178/BIBTEX</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>