<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39370655</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1520-6300</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>American journal of human biology : the official journal of the Human Biology Council</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Am J Hum Biol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sedentary Behavior and Ultra-Processed Food Consumption Associated to BMI Changes in Brazilian Students During COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e24165</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e24165</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ajhb.24165</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION">University students experienced significant changes in their routines with the implementation of remote learning during Covid-19 pandemic, including increase in sedentary behavior (SB) time and ultra-processed foods (UPF's) consumption, which may have influenced changes in body mass index (BMI).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE">To evaluate the association between the variation in SB time and UPF's consumption with the variation in BMI, before and during the pandemic, in university students.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">This is a cross-sectional study, conducted between November 2020 and February 2021, with students from a public university of Southeast of Brazil, who answered an online questionnaire with questions regarding to the period before and during the pandemic. SB was assessed through questions about time spent on TV and electronic devices. A score of the frequency of UPF's consumption was estimated based on the Brazilian Food Guide. Self-reported information on height and body mass was used to calculate BMI.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">The sample comprised 3390 university students, with an average age of 28.7 (± 10.0) years. Among them, 65.4% were undergraduates, and 66.9% were women. SB time, UPF score, and BMI increased significantly during the pandemic, compared to the previous period. In this population, there was a significant association between increased SB time (β = 0.06; SE = 0.01; p &lt; 0.001) and UPF score (β = 0.08; SE = 0.01; p &lt; 0.001) with an increase in BMI.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">Changes in SB time and UPF score were associated with an increase in BMI before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in students from a Brazilian University.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alves</LastName><ForeName>Lucas de Oliveira</ForeName><Initials>LO</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6249-725X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Activity Biosciences, School of Physical Education and Sports, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Institute of Social Medicine, State University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paravidino</LastName><ForeName>Vitor Barreto</ForeName><Initials>VB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Institute of Social Medicine, State University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Education and Sports, Naval Academy-Brazilian Navy, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gonçalves</LastName><ForeName>Tatiana Rehder</ForeName><Initials>TR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Collective Health Studies, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferreira</LastName><ForeName>Ana Lorena Lima</ForeName><Initials>ALL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Applied Nutrition, National Institute Josué de Castro, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gomes</LastName><ForeName>Diego Viana</ForeName><Initials>DV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Activity Biosciences, School of Physical Education and Sports, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dutra-Malvar</LastName><ForeName>Sabrina Graziani Veloso</ForeName><Initials>SGV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Activity Biosciences, School of Physical Education and Sports, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cocate</LastName><ForeName>Paula Guedes</ForeName><Initials>PG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Activity Biosciences, School of Physical Education and Sports, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Am J Hum Biol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8915029</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1042-0533</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covid‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">body mass index</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sedentary behavior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ultra‐processed foods</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">university students</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39370655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ajhb.24165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Alves, A. G., A. G. Dourado, P. C. Oliveira, et al. 2023. “Effects of the Covid‐19 Pandemic on Food Intake, Physical Activity and Anthropometry of Brazilian Undergraduate Students.” Revista Foco 16, no. 9: e2966. https://doi.org/10.54751/revistafoco.v16n9‐013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Askari, M., J. Heshmati, H. Shahinfar, N. Tripathi, and E. Daneshzad. 2020. “Ultra‐Processed Food and the Risk of Overweight and Obesity: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of Observational Studies.” International Journal of Obesity 44, no. 10: 2080–2091. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41366‐020‐00650‐z.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balducci, S., V. D'Errico, J. Haxhi, et al. 2017. “Level and Correlates of Physical Activity and Sedentary Behavior in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes: A Cross‐Sectional Analysis of the Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study_2.” PLoS One 12, no. 3: e0173337. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0173337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertolazi, A. N., S. C. Fagondes, L. S. Hoff, et al. 2011. “Validation of the Brazilian Portuguese Version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.” Sleep Medicine 12, no. 1: 70–75. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sleep.2010.04.020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertrand, L., K. Shaw, J. Ko, D. Deprez, P. D. Chilibeck, and G. A. Zello. 2021. “The Impact of the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Pandemic on University students' Dietary Intake, Physical Activity, and Sedentary Behaviour.” Applied Physiology, Nutrition, and Metabolism 46, no. 3: 265–272. https://doi.org/10.1139/apnm‐2020‐0990.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biddle, S. J. H., E. Bengoechea García, Z. Pedisic, J. Bennie, I. Vergeer, and G. Wiesner. 2017. “Screen Time, Other Sedentary Behaviours, and Obesity Risk in Adults: A Review of Reviews.” Current Obesity Reports 6, no. 2: 134–147. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13679‐017‐0256‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolesławska, I., P. Jagielski, E. Błaszczyk‐Bębenek, A. Jagielska, and J. Przysławski. 2023. “Lifestyle Changes During the SARS‐CoV‐2 Pandemic as Predictors of BMI Changes Among Men and Women in Poland.” Nutrients 15, no. 11: 2427. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu15112427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasil. Ministério Da Saúde. 2014. “Secretaria de Atenção Básica. Departamento de Atenção Básica. Guia alimentar para a população brasileira (2nd ed.) Ministério Da Saúde.” https://bvsms.saude.gov.br/bvs/publicacoes/guia_alimentar_populacao_brasileira_2ed.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brazil. 2020. “Ministry of Education. Ordinance No. 343, of March 17, 2020. Provides for the Replacement of Face‐to‐Face Classes With Digital Classes While the New Coronavirus Pandemic Situation Lasts.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bull, F. C., S. S. Al‐Ansari, S. Biddle, et al. 2020. “World Health Organization 2020 Guidelines on Physical Activity and Sedentary Behaviour.” British Journal of Sports Medicine 54, no. 24: 1451–1462. https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports‐2020‐102955.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell, S. D. I., B. J. Brosnan, A. K. Y. Chu, et al. 2017. “Sedentary Behavior and Body Weight and Composition in Adults: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of Prospective Studies.” Sports Medicine 48, no. 3: 585–595. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40279‐017‐0828‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chau, J. Y., H. P. van der Ploeg, D. Merom, T. Chey, and A. E. Bauman. 2012. “Cross‐Sectional Associations Between Occupational and Leisure‐Time Sitting, Physical Activity and Obesity in Working Adults.” Preventive Medicine 54, no. 3–4: 195–200. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2011.12.020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cotten, E., and H. Prapavessis. 2016. “Increasing Nonsedentary Behaviors in University Students Using Text Messages: Randomized Controlled Trial.” Journal of Medical Internet Research mHealth and uHealth 4, no. 3: e99. https://doi.org/10.2196/mhealth.5411.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Santana, J. M., M. P. Milagres, C. Silva dos Santos, J. M. Brazil, E. R. Lima, and M. Pereira. 2021. “Dietary Intake of University Students During COVID‐19 Social Distancing in the Northeast of Brazil and Associated Factors.” Appetite 162: 105172. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2021.105172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, Y., Y. Lv, W. Zha, N. Zhou, and X. Hong. 2021. “Association of Body Mass Index (BMI) With Critical COVID‐19 and In‐Hospital Mortality: A Dose‐Response Meta‐Analysis.” Metabolism 117: 154373. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.metabol.2020.154373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dziewior, J., L. J. Carr, G. L. Pierce, and K. Whitaker. 2022. “College Students Report Less Physical Activity and More Sedentary Behavior During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Journal of American College Health 1–9: 2022–2030. https://doi.org/10.1080/07448481.2022.2100708.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallè, F., E. A. Sabella, S. Ferracuti, et al. 2020. “Sedentary Behaviors and Physical Activity of Italian Undergraduate Students During Lockdown at the Time of COVID−19 Pandemic.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 17, no. 17: 6171. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17176171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcês, C. P., L. Oliveira e Silva, S. M. Nunes, and N. C. Cheik. 2022. “Effects of Social Distancing Caused by the COVID‐19 Pandemic on Physical Activity Level, Sitting Time, and Binge Eating: A Comparison Between Overweight/Obese and Normal‐Weight Adults.” Sport Sciences for Health 18, no. 4: 1505–1512. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11332‐022‐00974‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gestsdottir, S., T. Gisladottir, R. Stefansdottir, E. Johannsson, G. Jakobsdottir, and V. Rognvaldsdottir. 2021. “Health and Well‐Being of University Students Before and During COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Gender Comparison.” PLoS One 16, no. 12: e0261346. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0261346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenland, S., J. Pearl, and J. M. Robins. 1999. “Causal Diagrams for Epidemiologic Research.” Epidemiology 10, no. 1: 37–48. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9888278/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, C., Q. Zhou, D. Zhang, et al. 2020. “Association of Total Sedentary Behaviour and Television Viewing With Risk of Overweight/Obesity, Type 2 Diabetes and Hypertension: A Dose–Response Meta‐Analysis.” Diabetes, Obesity and Metabolism 22, no. 1: 79–90. https://doi.org/10.1111/dom.13867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guth, M. C. A., and F. S. Adami. 2023. “Comportamento alimentar e estado nutricional de universitários da área da saúde no período da pandemia de covid‐19.” RBONE—Revista Brasileira de Obesidade, Nutrição E Emagrecimento 17, no. 107: 233–244. Retrieved from https://www.rbone.com.br/index.php/rbone/article/view/2231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermassi, S., L. D. Hayes, A. Salman, et al. 2021. “Physical Activity, Sedentary Behavior, and Satisfaction With Life of University Students in Qatar: Changes During Confinement Due to the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Frontiers in Psychology 12: 704562. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.704562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoong, C. W. S., I. Hussain, V. M. Aravamudan, E. E. Phyu, J. H. X. Lin, and H. Koh. 2021. “Obesity Is Associated With Poor Covid‐19 Outcomes: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Hormone and Metabolic Research 53, no. 2: 85–93. https://doi.org/10.1055/a‐1326‐2125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain, M. J., F. Ahmmed, M. R. Khan, et al. 2022. “Impact of Prolonged COVID‐19 Lockdown on Body Mass Index, Eating Habits, and Physical Activity of University Students in Bangladesh: A Web‐Based Cross‐Sectional Study.” Frontiers in Nutrition 9: 873105. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.873105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalal, S. M., M. R. M. Beth, H. J. M. Al‐Hassan, and N. M. J. Alshealah. 2021. “Body Mass Index, Practice of Physical Activity and Lifestyle of Students During COVID‐19 Lockdown.” Journal of Multidisciplinary Healthcare 14: 1901–1910. https://doi.org/10.2147/JMDH.S325269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinoshita, K., N. Ozato, T. Yamaguchi, et al. 2023. “Association of the COVID‐19 Pandemic With Changes in Objectively Measured Sedentary Behaviour and Adiposity.” International Journal of Obesity 47, no. 5: 375–381. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41366‐023‐01274‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, E., and Y. Kim. 2018. “Effect of University students' Sedentary Behavior on Stress, Anxiety, and Depression.” Perspectives in Psychiatric Care 55, no. 2: 164–169. https://doi.org/10.1111/ppc.12296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima, E. R., T. B. Matos, L. A. de Anjos, et al. 2022. “Dietary Changes of Brazilian University Students During the COVID‐19.” Research, Society and Development 11, no. 7: e10411729733. https://doi.org/10.33448/rsd‐v11i7.29733.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lobstein, T., H. Brinsden, and M. Neveux. 2022. “World Obesity Atlas.” World Obesity Federation. https://s3‐eu‐west‐1.amazonaws.com/wof‐files/World_Obesity_Atlas_2022.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez Steele, E., F. Juul, D. Neri, F. Rauber, and C. A. Monteiro. 2019. “Dietary Share of Ultra‐Processed Foods and Metabolic Syndrome in the US Adult Population.” Preventive Medicine 125: 40–48. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2019.05.004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsudo, S., T. Araújo, V. Matsudo, et al. 2001. “International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ): Study of Valitidy and Realibity in Brazil.” Revista Brasileira de Atividade Física &amp; Saúde 6, no. 2: 5–18. https://doi.org/10.12820/rbafs.v.6n2p5‐18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melo, B., L. Rezende, P. Machado, N. Gouveia, and R. Levy. 2018. “Associations of Ultra‐Processed Food and Drink Products With Asthma and Wheezing Among Brazilian Adolescents.” Pediatric Allergy and Immunology 29, no. 5: 504–511. https://doi.org/10.1111/pai.12911.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendonça, R. D., A. M. Pimenta, A. Gea, et al. 2016. “Ultraprocessed Food Consumption and Risk of Overweight and Obesity: The University of Navarra Follow‐Up (SUN) Cohort Study.” American Journal of Clinical Nutrition 104, no. 5: 1433–1440. https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.116.135004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monteiro, C. A. 2019. “Ultra‐Processed Foods: What They Are and How to Identify Them.” Public Health Nutrition 22, no. 5: 936–941. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980018003762.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarro‐Cruz, A. R., A. Kammar‐García, J. Mancilla‐Galindo, et al. 2021. “Association of Differences in Dietary Behaviours and Lifestyle With Self‐Reported Weight Gain During the COVID‐19 Lockdown in a University Community From Chile: A Cross‐Sectional Study.” Nutrients 13, no. 9: 3213. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13093213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafique, N. 2022. “Body Mass Index, Eating Habits, and Various Lifestyle Changes in Young Adults During the Two Years of the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Pandemic.” Journal of Family &amp; Community Medicine 29, no. 3: 189–195. https://doi.org/10.4103/jfcm.jfcm_74_22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes‐Olavarría, D., P. Á. Latorre‐Román, I. P. Guzmán‐Guzmán, D. Jerez‐Mayorga, F. Caamaño‐Navarrete, and P. Delgado‐Floody. 2020. “Positive and Negative Changes in Food Habits, Physical Activity Patterns, and Weight Status during COVID‐19 Confinement: Associated Factors in the Chilean Population.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 17, no. 15: 5431. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17155431.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rocha, J. S. B., A. A. Fonseca, R. F. Freitas, et al. 2020. “Fatores associados ao aumento do consumo de alimentos ultraprocessados em universitários durante o isolamento social—pandemia covid‐19.” RBONE—Revista Brasileira de Obesidade, Nutrição E Emagrecimento 14, no. 90: 1222–1230. https://www.rbone.com.br/index.php/rbone/article/view/1542.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero‐Blanco, C., J. Rodríguez‐Almagro, M. D. Onieva‐Zafra, M. L. Parra‐Fernández, M. C. del Prado‐Laguna, and A. Hernández‐Martínez. 2020. “Physical Activity and Sedentary Lifestyle in University Students: Changes During Confinement Due to the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 17, no. 18: 6567. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17186567.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz‐Roso, M. B., P. de Carvalho Padilha, D. C. Mantilla‐Escalante, et al. 2020. “Covid‐19 Confinement and Changes of Adolescent's Dietary Trends in Italy, Spain, Chile, Colombia and Brazil.” Nutrients 12, no. 6: 1807. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12061807.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silveira, E. A., C. R. Mendonça, F. M. Delpino, et al. 2022. “Sedentary Behavior, Physical Inactivity, Abdominal Obesity and Obesity in Adults and Older Adults: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Clinical Nutrition ESPEN 50: 63–73. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clnesp.2022.06.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srour, B., L. K. Fezeu, E. Kesse‐Guyot, et al. 2019. “Ultra‐Processed Food Intake and Risk of Cardiovascular Disease: Prospective Cohort Study (NutriNet‐Santé).” British Medical Journal 365, no. 8201: l1451. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.l1451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, X., A. F. Yan, Z. Shi, et al. 2022. “Health Consequences of Obesity and Projected Future Obesity Health Burden in China.” Obesity (Silver Spring, Md) 30, no. 9: 1724–1751. https://doi.org/10.1002/oby.23472.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Textor, J., B. Van der Zander, M. S. Gilthorpe, M. Liśkiewicz, and G. T. Ellison. 2016. “Robust Causal Inference Using Directed Acyclic Graphs: The R Package ‘Dagitty’.” International Journal of Epidemiology 45, no. 6: 1887–1894. https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyw341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tirado‐Aguilar, R. D., J. A. Valdés‐Velázquez, H. U. Segovia‐Hernández, J. H. Martínez‐Quintanilla, E. Pérez‐García, and M. Pierdant‐Pérez. 2023. “Efecto del confinamiento durante la pandemia de Covid‐19 en los niveles séricos de lípidos y composición corporal de estudiantes universitarios.” Salud Pública de México 65, no. 1, ene‐feb: 103–105. https://doi.org/10.21149/14180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, C., R. Pan, X. Wan, et al. 2020. “Immediate Psychological Responses and Associated Factors During the Initial Stage of the 2019 Coronavirus Disease (COVID‐19) Epidemic Among the General Population in China.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 17, no. 5: 1729. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17051729.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2000. “Obesity: Preventing and Managing the Global Epidemic. Report of a WHO Consultation.” World Health Organization Technical Report Series 894: 1–253. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11234459/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2020. “WHO COVID‐19 Dashboard.” Retrieved from World Health Organization website: https://covid19.who.int.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, J., C. Tian, Y. Chen, C. Zhu, H. Chi, and J. Li. 2020. “Obesity Aggravates COVID‐19: An Updated Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Journal of Medical Virology 93, no. 5: 2662–2674. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.26677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X., A. M. Lewis, J. R. Moley, and J. R. Brestoff. 2021. “A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of Obesity and COVID‐19 Outcomes.” Scientific Reports 11, no. 1: 7193. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐021‐86694‐1.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>