<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39377494</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Functional evaluation of TMEM176B and its predictive role for severe respiratory viral infection through integrated analysis of single-cell and bulk RNA-sequencing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29954</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29954</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29954</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Transmembrane protein 176B (TMEM176B), localized mainly on the endosomal membrane, has been reported as an immune regulatory factor in malignant diseases. However, the biological function of this molecule remains undetermined during respiratory viral infections. To investigate the functions and prognostic value of this gene, six gene sets were selected from the Gene Expression Omnibus database for research. First, the function of TMEM176B and its co-expressed genes were evaluated at different levels (cell, peripheral blood, lung tissue). Afterwards, a machine learning algorithm was utilized to analyze the relationship between TMEM176B and its interacting genes with prognosis. After importance evaluation and variable screening, a prognostic model was established. Finally, the reliability of the model was further verified through external data sets. In vitro experiments were conducted to validate the function of TMEM176B. TMEM176B and its co-expressed genes are involved in multiple processes such as inflammasome activation, myeloid immune cell development, and immune cell infiltration. Machine learning further screened 27 interacting gene modules including TMEM176B as prognostic models for severe respiratory viral infections, with the area under the ROC curve (AUCs) of 0.986 and 0.905 in derivation and external validation sets, respectively. We further confirmed that viral load as well as NLRP3 activation and cell death were significantly enhanced in TMEM176B<sup>-/-</sup> THP-1-differentiated macrophages via in vitro experiments. Our study revealed that TMEM176B is involved in a wide range of biological functions in respiratory viral infections and has potential prognostic value, which is expected to bring new insights into the clinical management of severe respiratory viral infection hosts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shang</LastName><ForeName>Congcong</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate School of Peking Union Medical College, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences ＆ Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Respiratory Medicine; State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Health and Multimorbidity; National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Diseases; Institute of Respiratory Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences; Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Center of Respiratory Medicine, China-Japan Friendship Hospital, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Jiapei</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Respiratory Medicine; State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Health and Multimorbidity; National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Diseases; Institute of Respiratory Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences; Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Center of Respiratory Medicine, China-Japan Friendship Hospital, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zou</LastName><ForeName>Shumei</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Collaborative Innovation Center for Diagnosis and Treatment of Infectious Diseases, Key Laboratory for Medical Virology, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Hui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Respiratory Medicine; State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Health and Multimorbidity; National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Diseases; Institute of Respiratory Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences; Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Center of Respiratory Medicine, China-Japan Friendship Hospital, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cao</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate School of Peking Union Medical College, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences ＆ Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Respiratory Medicine; State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Health and Multimorbidity; National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Diseases; Institute of Respiratory Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences; Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Center of Respiratory Medicine, China-Japan Friendship Hospital, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tsinghua University-Peking University Joint Center for Life Sciences, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Clinical Center for Pulmonary Infections, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>CAP‐China network</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>82030002/H0104</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D008565">Membrane Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008565" MajorTopicYN="Y">Membrane Proteins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011379" MajorTopicYN="N">Prognosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059010" MajorTopicYN="Y">Single-Cell Analysis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069550" MajorTopicYN="N">Machine Learning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017423" MajorTopicYN="N">Sequence Analysis, RNA</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020869" MajorTopicYN="N">Gene Expression Profiling</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TMEM176B</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">monocytes/macrophages</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prognostic model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">severe influenza and SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39377494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Wei X, Narasimhan H, Zhu B, Sun J. Host recovery from respiratory viral infection. Annu Rev Immunol. 2023;41:277‐300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flerlage T, Boyd DF, Meliopoulos V, Thomas PG, Schultz‐Cherry S. Influenza virus and SARS‐CoV‐2: pathogenesis and host responses in the respiratory tract. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2021;19(7):425‐441.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GBD 2021 Demographics Collaborators. Global age‐sex‐specific mortality, life expectancy, and population estimates in 204 countries and territories and 811 subnational locations, 1950‐2021, and the impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic: a comprehensive demographic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2021. The Lancet. 2024;403(10440):1989‐2056.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas PG, Dash P, Aldridge JR, et al. The intracellular sensor NLRP3 mediates key innate and healing responses to influenza A virus via the regulation of caspase‐1. Immunity. 2009;30(4):566‐575.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Major J, Crotta S, Llorian M, et al. Type I and III interferons disrupt lung epithelial repair during recovery from viral infection. Science. 2020;369(6504):712‐717.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Louvet C, Chiffoleau E, Heslan M, et al. Identification of a new member of the CD20/FcεRIβ family overexpressed in tolerated allografts. Am J Transplant. 2005;5(9):2143‐2153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Condamine T, Le Texier L, Howie D, et al. Tmem176B and Tmem176A are associated with the immature state of dendritic cells. J Leukoc Biol. 2010;88(3):507‐515.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segovia M, Louvet C, Charnet P, et al. Autologous dendritic cells prolong allograft survival through Tmem176b‐dependent antigen cross‐presentation. Am J Trans. 2014;14(5):1021‐1031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu SH, Kim KH, Kim HB, et al. Oncogenic ras‐mediated downregulation of Clast1/LR8 is involved in ras‐mediated neoplastic transformation and tumorigenesis in NIH3T3 cells. Cancer Sci. 2010;101(9):1990‐1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Feng Q, Hu K, Cheng F. Using CRISPRa and CRISPRi technologies to study the biological functions of ITGB5, TIMP1, and TMEM176B in prostate cancer cells. Front Mol Biosci. 2021;8:676021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang C, Rostoker R, Ben‐Shumel S, et al. TMEM176B regulates AKT/mTOR signaling and tumor growth in triple‐negative breast cancer. Cells. 2021;10(12):3430.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jing L, An Y, Cai T, et al. A subpopulation of CD146(+) macrophages enhances antitumor immunity by activating the NLRP3 inflammasome. Cell Mol Immunol. 2023;20(8):908‐923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segovia M, Russo S, Jeldres M, et al. Targeting TMEM176B enhances antitumor immunity and augments the efficacy of immune checkpoint blockers by unleashing inflammasome activation. Cancer Cell. 2019;35(5):767‐781.e6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Zhou B, Zhu X, et al. Differentiation‐related genes in tumor‐associated macrophages as potential prognostic biomarkers in non‐small cell lung cancer. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1123840.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Zhang D, Sun G, et al. RNA‐sequencing study of peripheral blood mononuclear cells in sporadic ménière's disease patients: possible contribution of immunologic dysfunction to the development of this disorder. Clin Exp Immunol. 2018;192(1):33‐45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seki T, Sato M, Kibe Y, et al. Lysosomal dysfunction and early glial activation are involved in the pathogenesis of spinocerebellar ataxia type 21 caused by mutant transmembrane protein 240. Neurobiol Dis. 2018;120:34‐50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao S, Li H, Xin J, et al. Identification of genetic profile and biomarkers involved in acute respiratory distress syndrome. Intensive Care Med. 2024;50(1):46‐55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pekayvaz K, Leunig A, Kaiser R, et al. Protective immune trajectories in early viral containment of non‐pneumonic SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Nat Commun. 2022;13(1):1018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steel J, Lowen AC, Pena L, et al. Live attenuated influenza viruses containing NS1 truncations as vaccine candidates against H5N1 highly pathogenic avian influenza. J Virol. 2009;83(4):1742‐1753.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alfi O, Yakirevitch A, Wald O, et al. Human nasal and lung tissues infected ex vivo with SARS‐CoV‐2 provide insights into differential tissue‐specific and virus‐specific innate immune responses in the upper and lower respiratory tract. J Virol. 2021;95(14):e0013021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JS, Park S, Jeong HW, et al. Immunophenotyping of COVID‐19 and influenza highlights the role of type I interferons in development of severe COVID‐19. Sci Immunol. 2020;5(49):eabd1554.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li F, Piattini F, Pohlmeier L, Feng Q, Rehrauer H, Kopf M. Monocyte‐Derived alveolar macrophages autonomously determine severe outcome of respiratory viral infection. Science Immunology. 2022;7(73):eabj5761.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bost P, De Sanctis F, Canè S, et al. Deciphering the state of immune silence in fatal COVID‐19 patients. Nat Commun. 2021;12(1):1428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao M, Liu Y, Yuan J, et al. Single‐cell landscape of bronchoalveolar immune cells in patients with COVID‐19. Nature Med. 2020;26(6):842‐844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu A, Shen L, Li N, Shen L, Li Z. Pan‐cancer analyses of pyroptosis with functional implications for prognosis and immunotherapy in cancer. J Transl Med. 2022;20(1):109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou Y, Xie J, Zheng S, et al. Leveraging diverse cell‐death patterns to predict the prognosis and drug sensitivity of triple‐negative breast cancer patients after surgery. Int J Surg. 2022;107:106936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu J, Schroder K, Wu H. Mechanistic insights from inflammasome structures. Nat Rev Immunol. 2024;24(7):518‐535.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergen V, Lange M, Peidli S, Wolf FA, Theis FJ. Generalizing RNA velocity to transient cell states through dynamical modeling. Nature Biotechnol. 2020;38(12):1408‐1414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szabo PA, Dogra P, Gray JI, et al. Longitudinal profiling of respiratory and systemic immune responses reveals myeloid cell‐driven lung inflammation in severe COVID‐19. Immunity. 2021;54(4):797‐814.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vora SM, Lieberman J, Wu H. Inflammasome activation at the crux of severe COVID‐19. Nat Rev Immunol. 2021;21(11):694‐703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris G, Bortolasci CC, Puri BK, et al. The cytokine storms of COVID‐19, H1N1 influenza, CRS and MAS compared. Can one sized treatment fit all? Cytokine. 2021;144:155593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fajgenbaum DC, June CH. Cytokine storm. N Engl J Med. 2020;383(23):2255‐2273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia X, Liu B, Bao L, et al. Delayed oseltamivir plus sirolimus treatment attenuates H1N1 virus‐induced severe lung injury correlated with repressed NLRP3 inflammasome activation and inflammatory cell infiltration. PLoS Pathog. 2018;14(11):e1007428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu B, Bao L, Wang L, et al. Anti‐IFN‐γ therapy alleviates acute lung injury induced by severe influenza a (H1N1) Pdm09 infection in mice. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2021;54(3):396‐403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnett KC, Li S, Liang K, Ting JPY. A 360° view of the inflammasome: mechanisms of activation, cell death, and diseases. Cell. 2023;186(11):2288‐2312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Núñez G. The NLRP3 inflammasome: activation and regulation. Trends Biochem Sci. 2023;48(4):331‐344.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kagan JC. Excess lipids on endosomes dictate NLRP3 localization and inflammasome activation. Nature Immunol. 2023;24(1):3‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Venditti R, Ran L, et al. Distinct changes in endosomal composition promote NLRP3 inflammasome activation. Nature Immunol. 2023;24(1):30‐41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee B, Hoyle C, Wellens R, et al. Disruptions in endocytic traffic contribute to the activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome. Sci Signaling. 2023;16(773):eabm7134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman RE, Munro S. Retrieval of TGN proteins from the cell surface requires endosomal acidification. EMBO J. 1994;13(10):2305‐2312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reaves B, Banting G. Vacuolar ATPase inactivation blocks recycling to the trans‐Golgi network from the plasma membrane. FEBS Lett. 1994;345(1):61‐66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sefik E, Qu R, Junqueira C, et al. Inflammasome activation in infected macrophages drives COVID‐19 pathology. Nature. 2022;606(7914):585‐593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu G, Qi F, Li H, et al. The differential immune responses to COVID‐19 in peripheral and lung revealed by single‐cell RNA sequencing. Cell Discov. 2020;6:73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon S, Taylor PR. Monocyte and macrophage heterogeneity. Nat Rev Immunol. 2005;5(12):953‐964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wauters E, Van Mol P, Garg AD, et al. Discriminating mild from critical COVID‐19 by innate and adaptive immune single‐cell profiling of bronchoalveolar lavages. Cell Res. 2021;31(3):272‐290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao D, Bao L, Li F, et al. H1N1 influenza virus dose dependent induction of dysregulated innate immune responses and STAT1/3 activation are associated with pulmonary immunopathological damage. Virulence. 2022;13(1):1558‐1572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Li S, Huang B. Alveolar macrophages: Achilles' heel of SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022;7(1):242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv J, Wang Z, Qu Y, et al. Distinct uptake, amplification, and release of SARS‐CoV‐2 by M1 and M2 alveolar macrophages. Cell Discov. 2021;7(1):24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann JP, Liu JA, Seddu K, Klein SL. Sex hormone signaling and regulation of immune function. Immunity. 2023;56(11):2472‐2491.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>