<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39371275</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1679-4435</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>22</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Apr-Jun</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Revista brasileira de medicina do trabalho : publicacao oficial da Associacao Nacional de Medicina do Trabalho-ANAMT</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Bras Med Trab</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Burnout syndrome among health care professionals in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e20231134</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e20231134</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e20231134</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.47626/1679-4435-2023-1134</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Burnout syndrome, a mental illness caused by stressful work conditions, is prevalent among health professionals. In addition to existing risk factors, the COVID-19 pandemic introduced new ones, such as fear of infection and concern about the availability of personal protective equipment.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study's purpose was to verify the prevalence and correlates of burnout syndrome among health professionals in the context of the pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This quantitative study was conducted between April and June 2021 using the Google Forms platform. A semi-structured questionnaire and the <i>Questionário para la Evaluación del Syndrome de Quemarse por el Trabajo</i> were applied.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 93 health professionals participated. Those who fought on the frontline against COVID-19 were younger and had less professional experience, longer work hours, daily contact with a greater number of patients, lower scores in the disillusionment dimension, and higher scores in the emotional exhaustion dimension. Significant correlations were found between age and disillusionment, emotional exhaustion, and indolence. Less professional experience was also correlated with psychological distress.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Age and length of experience were significantly associated with burnout, given that younger and less experienced professionals generally worked on the frontline against COVID-19.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Oliveira</LastName><ForeName>Letícia Menezes</ForeName><Initials>LM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6200-4854</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enfermagem, Universidade Federal da Paraíba (UFPB), João Pessoa, PB, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vasconcelos</LastName><ForeName>Selene Cordeiro</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8828-1251</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programa de Pós-Graduação em Enfermagem (UFPB), João Pessoa, PB, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fernandes</LastName><ForeName>Fernando Lannes</ForeName><Initials>FL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4377-4597</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Geografia, University of Dundee, Dundee, Scotland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Araújo</LastName><ForeName>Ana Lúcia Belarmino</ForeName><Initials>ALB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3390-2118</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programa de Pós-Graduação em Enfermagem (UFPB), João Pessoa, PB, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Abrantes</LastName><ForeName>Gesualdo Gonçalves</ForeName><Initials>GG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7074-9995</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programa de Pós-Graduação em Enfermagem (UFPB), João Pessoa, PB, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pinheiro</LastName><ForeName>Ana Karina Bezerra</ForeName><Initials>AKB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3837-4131</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enfermagem, Universidade Federal do Ceará (UFC), Fortaleza, CE, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Brazil</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Bras Med Trab</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101214718</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1679-4435</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="por"><AbstractText Label="INTRODUÇÃO" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A síndrome de <i>burnout</i> é uma doença psíquica ocasionada por situações desgastantes de trabalho, sendo prevalente entre os profissionais de saúde. Além dos fatores de risco já existentes para o seu desenvolvimento, a pandemia de covid-19 apresentou novos fatores de risco, como o medo de adquirir a doença e a preocupação com a disponibilidade de equipamentos de proteção individual.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJETIVOS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Verificar a prevalência da síndrome de <i>burnout</i> em profissionais de saúde no contexto da covid-19 e suas correlações.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MÉTODOS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Trata-se de um estudo quantitativo, realizado em 2021 por meio da plataforma Google Forms. Foram utilizados um questionário semiestruturado e o Cuestionario para la Evaluación del Síndrome de Quemarse por el Trabajo.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTADOS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Participaram da pesquisa 93 profissionais de saúde. Os profissionais que participaram do enfrentamento à covid-19 possuíam menor idade, menor tempo de atuação profissional, maior carga horária semanal de trabalho, contato com maior número de pacientes diariamente, menor pontuação na dimensão ilusão pelo trabalho e maior pontuação na dimensão desgaste psíquico. Correlações significantes foram encontradas entre idade e ilusão pelo trabalho, desgaste psíquico e indolência. Além disso, menor tempo de atuação profissional foi correlacionado com desgaste psíquico.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSÕES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A idade e o tempo de atuação foram as variáveis que apresentaram significância nos testes estatísticos realizados, em que profissionais mais jovens e com menor tempo de atuação estavam em maioria no enfrentamento à covid-19, além de estarem associados ao <i>burnout,</i> corroborando para que fossem os profissionais mais susceptíveis a desenvolver a síndrome de <i>burnout.</i></AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Professional burnout</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health personnel</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interest: None</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39371275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11452128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47626/1679-4435-2023-1134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Silva SM. A dialética do trabalho: escritos de Marx e Engels. Rev Pegada Eletronica (Online) 2018;19(1):216–228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasil. Ministério da Saúde  . Síndrome de burnout. Brasília: Ministério da Saúde; 2020.  [12 mar 2022].  Disponível:  https://www.gov.br/saude/pt-br/assuntos/saude-de-a-a-z/s7sindrome-de-burnout.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soldera LLO, Martins LG. Síndrome de burnout: conceitos e observações para os gestores de recursos humanos. Leopoldianum. 2017;43(119-20):143–153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munhoz OL, Arrial TS, Barlem ELD, Dalmolin GL, Andolhe R, Magnago TSBS. Estresse ocupacional e burnout em profissionais de saúde de unidades de perioperatório. Acta Paul Enferm. 2020;33:eAPE20190261</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira SS, Fornés-Vives J, Preto VA, Pereira Junior GAP, Juruena MF, Cardoso L. Variáveis interventoras do burnout em profissionais de saúde dos serviços emergenciais. Texto Contexto Enferm. 2021;30:e20190245</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perniciotti P, Serrano Júnior CV, Guarita RV, Morales RJ, Romano BW. Síndrome de burnout nos profissionais de saúde: atualização sobre definições, fatores de risco e estratégias de prevenção. Rev SBPH. 2020;23(1):35–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nascimento AKF, Barbosa YMM, Camargo SRV, Souza TA, Gomes SM, Galvão MHR, et al. Impactos da pandemia de COVID-19sobre a saúde mental de profissionais de enfermagem. Rev Port Enferm Saude Mental. 2021;(26):169–186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, Gøtzsche PC, Vandenbroucke JP, et al. The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. J Clin Epidemiol. 2008;61(4):344–349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18313558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gil-Monte PR, Carlotto MS, Câmara SG. Validação da versão brasileira do “Cuestionario para la Evaluación del Síndrome de Quemarse por el Trabajo” em professores. Rev Saude Publica. 2010;44(1):140–147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasil. Conselho Nacional de Saúde  . Resolução nº 466, de 12 de dezembro de 2012. Brasília: Conselho Nacional de Saúde; 2012.  [28 mai 2022].  Disponível:  https://conselho.saude.gov.br/resolucoes/2012/Reso466.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conselho Federal de Enfermagem  . Resolução COFEN 564/2017. Brasília: COFEN; 2017.  [mai 2022].  Disponível:  http://www.cofen.gov.br/resolucao-cofen-no-5642017_59145.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutra HS, Gomes PAL, Garcia RN, Oliveira HC, Freitas SCD, Guirardello EDB. Burnout entre profissionais de enfermagem em hospitais no Brasil. Rev Cuidarte. 2018;10(1):e585–e585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Wang W, Laureys S, Di H. Burnout syndrome in healthcare professionals who care for patients with prolonged disorders of consciousness: a cross-sectional survey. BMC Health Serv Res. 2020;20(1):841–841.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7487695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32894132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandão MGSA, Ximenes MAM, Barros LM, Araújo TM, Veras VS. Constructs triggering the Burnout syndrome in nurses in front of COVID-19: an integrative review. Rev Port Enferm Saude Mental. 2022;(27):123–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribeiro BMSS, Scorsolini-Comin F, Souza SR. Burnout syndrome in intensive care unit nurses during the COVID-19 pandemic. Rev Bras Med Trab. 2021;19(3):363–371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9137873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35774761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>