<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39373693</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2198-3844</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced science (Weinheim, Baden-Wurttemberg, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Sci (Weinh)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Broad-Spectrum Engineered Multivalent Nanobodies Against SARS-CoV-1/2.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2402975</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2402975</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/advs.202402975</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>SARS-CoV-2 Omicron sublineages escape most preclinical/clinical neutralizing antibodies in development, suggesting that previously employed antibody screening strategies are not well suited to counteract the rapid mutation of SARS-CoV-2. Therefore, there is an urgent need to screen better broad-spectrum neutralizing antibody. In this study, a comprehensive approach to design broad-spectrum inhibitors against both SARS-CoV-1 and SARS-CoV-2 by leveraging the structural diversity of nanobodies is proposed. This includes the de novo design of a fully human nanobody library and the camel immunization-based nanobody library, both targeting conserved epitopes, as well as the development of multivalent nanobodies that bind nonoverlapping epitopes. The results show that trivale B11-E8-F3, three nanobodies joined tandemly in trivalent form, have the broadest spectrum and efficient neutralization activity, which spans from SARS-CoV-1 to SARS-CoV-2 variants. It is also demonstrated that B11-E8-F3 has a very prominent preventive and some therapeutic effect in animal models of three authentic viruses. Therefore, B11-E8-F3 has an outstanding advantage in preventing SARS-CoV-1/SARS-CoV-2 infections, especially in immunocompromised populations or elderly people with high-risk comorbidities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Advanced Science published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Zhihong</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Zhuangzhuang</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Jilin Province for Zoonosis Prevention and Control, Changchun Veterinary Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Changchun, 130122, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liao</LastName><ForeName>Xiaochen</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joint National Laboratory for Antibody Drug Engineering, the First Affiliated Hospital, Henan University, Kaifeng City, Henan, 475004, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Quan</LastName><ForeName>Guiqi</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hunan Normal University School of medicine, Changsha, Hunan, 410200, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dong</LastName><ForeName>Hui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joint National Laboratory for Antibody Drug Engineering, the First Affiliated Hospital, Henan University, Kaifeng City, Henan, 475004, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Pinnan</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Yangyihua</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joint National Laboratory for Antibody Drug Engineering, the First Affiliated Hospital, Henan University, Kaifeng City, Henan, 475004, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Ning</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Yahui</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hunan Normal University School of medicine, Changsha, Hunan, 410200, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qiao</LastName><ForeName>Chunxia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Xin Ying</ForeName><Initials>XY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Ran</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hunan Normal University School of medicine, Changsha, Hunan, 410200, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Zekun</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joint National Laboratory for Antibody Drug Engineering, the First Affiliated Hospital, Henan University, Kaifeng City, Henan, 475004, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Tiecheng</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Jilin Province for Zoonosis Prevention and Control, Changchun Veterinary Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Changchun, 130122, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Xiang</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Jiannan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Longlong</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8307-6478</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Toxicology and Medical Countermeasures, Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Beijing, 100850, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>82204262</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>31970166</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Z211100002121020</GrantID><Agency>Beijing Nova Program</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>20220484216</GrantID><Agency>Beijing Nova Program</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Sci (Weinh)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101664569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2198-3844</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibody engineering</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">de novo design</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multivalent nanobodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nanobody</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39373693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.202402975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO, Summary of probably SARS cases with onset of illness from 1 November 2002 to 31 July 2003, https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/summary‐of‐probable‐sars‐cases‐with‐onset‐of‐illness‐from‐1‐november‐2002‐to‐31‐july‐2003, accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID‐19 Epidemiological Update, 27 October 2023, https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/covid‐19‐epidemiological‐update, 27‐october‐2023, accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) D. Planas, N. Saunders, P. Maes, F. Guivel‐Benhassine, C. Planchais, J. Buchrieser, W. H. Bolland, F. Porrot, I. Staropoli, F. Lemoine, H. Péré, D. Veyer, J. Puech, J. Rodary, G. Baele, S. Dellicour, J. Raymenants, S. Gorissen, C. Geenen, B. Vanmechelen, T. Wawina‐Bokalanga, J. Martí‐Carreras, L. Cuypers, A. Sève, L. Hocqueloux, T. Prazuck, F. A. Rey, E. Simon‐Loriere, T. Bruel, H. Mouquet, et al., Nature 2022, 602, 671;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Q. Wang, Y. Guo, S. Iketani, M. S. Nair, Z. Li, H. Mohri, M. Wang, J. Yu, A. D. Bowen, J. Y. Chang, J. G. Shah, N. Nguyen, Z. Chen, K. Meyers, M. T. Yin, M. E. Sobieszczyk, Z. Sheng, Y. Huang, L. Liu, D. D. Ho, Nature 2022, 608, 603;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) Q. Wang, S. Iketani, Z. Li, L. Liu, Y. Guo, Y. Huang, A. D. Bowen, M. Liu, M. Wang, J. Yu, R. Valdez, A. S. Lauring, Z. Sheng, H. H. Wang, A. Gordon, L. Liu, D. D. Ho, Cell 2023, 186, 279.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) P. Qu, J. P. Evans, J. N. Faraone, Y. M. Zheng, C. Carlin, M. Anghelina, P. Stevens, S. Fernandez, D. Jones, G. Lozanski, A. Panchal, L. J. Saif, E. M. Oltz, K. Xu, R. J. Gumina, S. L. Liu, Cell Host Microbe 2023, 31, 9;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) ECDC, Update on SARS‐CoV‐2 variants: ECDC assessment of the XBB.1.5 sub‐lineage, https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/news‐events/update‐sars‐cov‐2‐variants‐ecdc‐assessment‐xbb15‐sub‐lineage, accessed: January 9, 2023;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) C. Yue, W. Song, L. Wang, F. Jian, X. Chen, F. Gao, Z. Shen, Y. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Cao, Lancet Infect. Dis. 2023, 23, 278;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) J. K. Singh, S. Anand, S. K. Srivastava, Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2023, 238, 124154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. Bhattacharya, S. Chatterjee, S. S. Lee, C. Chakraborty, Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2022, 229, 70;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) H. Aria, F. Mahmoodi, H. S. Ghaheh, M. Faranak, H. Zare, M. Heiat, H. Bakherad, Anal. Biochem. 2022, 640, 114546.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) C. B. Jackson, M. Farzan, B. Chen, H. Choe, Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 2022, 23, 3;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) J. Huo, A. Dijokaite‐Guraliuc, C. Liu, D. Zhou, H. M. Ginn, R. Das, P. Supasa, M. Selvaraj, R. Nutalai, A. Tuekprakhon, H. M. E. Duyvesteyn, A. J. Mentzer, D. Skelly, T. G. Ritter, A. Amini, S. Bibi, S. Adele, S. A. Johnson, N. G. Paterson, M. A. Williams, D. R. Hall, M. Plowright, T. A. H. Newman, H. Hornsby, T. I. de Silva, N. Temperton, P. Klenerman, E. Barnes, S. J. Dunachie, A. J. Pollard, et al., Cell Rep. 2023, 42, 111903.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) T. N. Starr, A. J. Greaney, A. S. Dingens, J. D. Bloom, bioRxiv 2021;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. Bhattacharya, S. Chatterjee, A. R. Sharma, G. Agoramoorthy, C. Chakraborty, Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2021, 105, 9035;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) Q. Li, J. Nie, J. Wu, L. Zhang, R. Ding, H. Wang, Y. Zhang, T. Li, S. Liu, M. Zhang, C. Zhao, H. Liu, L. Nie, H. Qin, M. Wang, Q. Lu, X. Li, J. Liu, H. Liang, Y. Shi, Y. Shen, L. Xie, L. Zhang, X. Qu, W. Xu, W. Huang, Y. Wang, Cell 2021, 184, 2362;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) A. Tuekprakhon, R. Nutalai, A. Dijokaite‐Guraliuc, D. Zhou, H. M. Ginn, M. Selvaraj, C. Liu, A. J. Mentzer, P. Supasa, H. M. E. Duyvesteyn, R. Das, D. Skelly, T. G. Ritter, A. Amini, S. Bibi, S. Adele, S. A. Johnson, B. Constantinides, H. Webster, N. Temperton, P. Klenerman, E. Barnes, S. J. Dunachie, D. Crook, A. J. Pollard, T. Lambe, P. Goulder, N. G. Paterson, M. A. Williams, D. R. Hall, et al., Cell 2022, 185, 2422;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) B. Ju, Q. Zheng, H. Guo, Q. Fan, T. Li, S. Song, H. Sun, S. Shen, X. Zhou, W. Xue, L. Cui, B. Zhou, S. Li, N. Xia, Z. Zhang, Cell Res. 2022, 32, 491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. R. Suresh, P. K. Bhatnagar, D. Das, J. Pharm. Pharm. Sci 2008, 11, 1;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) K. M. Hastie, H. Li, D. Bedinger, S. L. Schendel, S. M. Dennison, K. Li, V. Rayaprolu, X. Yu, C. Mann, M. Zandonatti, R. Diaz Avalos, D. Zyla, T. Buck, S. Hui, K. Shaffer, C. Hariharan, J. Yin, E. Olmedillas, A. Enriquez, D. Parekh, M. Abraha, E. Feeney, G. Q. Horn, Y. Aldon, H. Ali, S. Aracic, R. R. Cobb, R. S. Federman, J. M. Fernandez, J. Glanville, et al., Science 2021, 374, 472;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) M. Yuan, N. C. Wu, X. Zhu, C. D. Lee, R. T. Y. So, H. Lv, C. K. P. Mok, I. A. Wilson, Science 2020, 368, 630;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) E. Seydoux, L. J. Homad, A. J. MacCamy, K. R. Parks, N. K. Hurlburt, M. F. Jennewein, N. R. Akins, A. B. Stuart, Y. H. Wan, J. Feng, R. E. Whaley, S. Singh, M. Boeckh, K. W. Cohen, M. J. McElrath, J. A. Englund, H. Y. Chu, M. Pancera, A. T. McGuire, L. Stamatatos, Immunity 2020, 53, 98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Chi, R. Yan, J. Zhang, G. Zhang, Y. Zhang, M. Hao, Z. Zhang, P. Fan, Y. Dong, Y. Yang, Z. Chen, Y. Guo, J. Zhang, Y. Li, X. Song, Y. Chen, L. Xia, L. Fu, L. Hou, J. Xu, C. Yu, J. Li, Q. Zhou, W. Chen, Science 2020, 369, 650.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) E. C. Wall, M. Wu, R. Harvey, G. Kelly, S. Warchal, C. Sawyer, R. Daniels, P. Hobson, E. Hatipoglu, Y. Ngai, S. Hussain, J. Nicod, R. Goldstone, K. Ambrose, S. Hindmarsh, R. Beale, A. Riddell, S. Gamblin, M. Howell, G. Kassiotis, V. Libri, B. Williams, C. Swanton, S. Gandhi, D. L. Bauer, Lancet 2021, 397, 2331;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) B. Feng, Z. Chen, J. Sun, T. Xu, Q. Wang, H. Yi, X. Niu, J. Zhu, M. Fan, R. Hou, Y. Shao, S. Huang, C. Li, P. Hu, P. Zheng, P. He, J. Luo, Q. Yan, X. Xiong, J. Liu, J. Zhao, L. Chen, Small Methods 2022, 6, e2200387;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) S. Maurya, S. Kumar, A. K. Padhi, ChemistrySelect 2023, 8, 202302906.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Y. Cao, J. Wang, F. Jian, T. Xiao, W. Song, A. Yisimayi, W. Huang, Q. Li, P. Wang, R. An, J. Wang, Y. Wang, X. Niu, S. Yang, H. Liang, H. Sun, T. Li, Y. Yu, Q. Cui, S. Liu, X. Yang, S. Du, Z. Zhang, X. Hao, F. Shao, R. Jin, X. Wang, J. Xiao, Y. Wang, X. S. Xie, Nature 2022, 602, 657;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) E. Cameroni, J. E. Bowen, L. E. Rosen, C. Saliba, S. K. Zepeda, K. Culap, D. Pinto, L. A. VanBlargan, A. De Marco, J. di Iulio, F. Zatta, H. Kaiser, J. Noack, N. Farhat, N. Czudnochowski, C. Havenar‐Daughton, K. R. Sprouse, J. R. Dillen, A. E. Powell, A. Chen, C. Maher, L. Yin, D. Sun, L. Soriaga, J. Bassi, C. Silacci‐Fregni, C. Gustafsson, N. M. Franko, J. Logue, N. T. Iqbal, et al., Nature 2022, 602, 664;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) S. Cele, L. Jackson, D. S. Khoury, K. Khan, T. Moyo‐Gwete, H. Tegally, J. E. San, D. Cromer, C. Scheepers, D. G. Amoako, F. Karim, M. Bernstein, G. Lustig, D. Archary, M. Smith, Y. Ganga, Z. Jule, K. Reedoy, S. H. Hwa, J. Giandhari, J. M. Blackburn, B. I. Gosnell, S. S. Abdool Karim, W. Hanekom, A. von Gottberg, J. N. Bhiman, R. J. Lessells, M. S. Moosa, M. P. Davenport, T. de Oliveira, et al., Nature 2022, 602, 654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. P. O'Brien, E. Forleo‐Neto, B. J. Musser, F. Isa, K. C. Chan, N. Sarkar, K. J. Bar, R. V. Barnabas, D. H. Barouch, M. S. Cohen, C. B. Hurt, D. R. Burwen, M. A. Marovich, P. Hou, I. Heirman, J. D. Davis, K. C. Turner, D. Ramesh, A. Mahmood, A. T. Hooper, J. D. Hamilton, Y. Kim, L. A. Purcell, A. Baum, C. A. Kyratsous, J. Krainson, R. Perez‐Perez, R. Mohseni, B. Kowal, A. T. DiCioccio, et al., N. Engl. J. Med. 2021, 385, 1184;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) H. B. Gershengorn, S. Patel, T. Ferreira, S. Das, D. J. Parekh, B. Shukla, PLoS One 2022, 17, e0278770;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) P. Chen, A. Nirula, B. Heller, R. L. Gottlieb, J. Boscia, J. Morris, G. Huhn, J. Cardona, B. Mocherla, V. Stosor, I. Shawa, A. C. Adams, J. Van Naarden, K. L. Custer, L. Shen, M. Durante, G. Oakley, A. E. Schade, J. Sabo, D. R. Patel, P. Klekotka, D. M. Skovronsky, N. Engl. J. Med. 2021, 384, 229;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) A. Gupta, Y. Gonzalez‐Rojas, E. Juarez, M. Crespo Casal, J. Moya, D. Rodrigues Falci, E. Sarkis, J. Solis, H. Zheng, N. Scott, A. L. Cathcart, S. Parra, J. E. Sager, D. Austin, A. Peppercorn, E. Alexander, W. W. Yeh, C. Brinson, M. Aldinger, A. E. Shapiro, JAMA, J. Am. Med. Assoc. 2022, 327, 1236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) J. Bukh, Gastroenterology 2022, 162, 396;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. Yasuhara, S. Yamayoshi, M. Kiso, Y. Sakai‐Tagawa, M. Okuda, Y. Kawaoka, Nat. Commun. 2022, 13, 6602;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) L. L. Hammitt, R. Dagan, Y. Yuan, M. Baca Cots, M. Bosheva, S. A. Madhi, W. J. Muller, H. J. Zar, D. Brooks, A. Grenham, U. Wählby Hamrén, V. S. Mankad, P. Ren, T. Takas, M. E. Abram, A. Leach, M. P. Griffin, T. Villafana, N. Engl. J. Med. 2022, 386, 837;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Muyldermans, Annu. Rev. Biochem. 2013, 82, 775;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) X. Feng, H. Wang, ACS Pharmacol. Transl. Sci. 2023, 6, 925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Pinto, Y. J. Park, M. Beltramello, A. C. Walls, M. A. Tortorici, S. Bianchi, S. Jaconi, K. Culap, F. Zatta, A. De Marco, A. Peter, B. Guarino, R. Spreafico, E. Cameroni, J. B. Case, R. E. Chen, C. Havenar‐Daughton, G. Snell, A. Telenti, H. W. Virgin, A. Lanzavecchia, M. S. Diamond, K. Fink, D. Veesler, D. Corti, Nature 2020, 583, 290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Li, Y. Pan, Q. Yin, Z. Wang, S. Shan, L. Zhang, J. Yu, Y. Qu, L. Sun, F. Gui, J. Lu, Z. Jing, W. Wu, T. Huang, X. Shi, J. Li, X. Li, D. Li, S. Wang, M. Yang, L. Zhang, K. Duan, M. Liang, X. Yang, X. Wang, Cell Discov. 2022, 8, 87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Song, G. Zeng, J. Yu, X. Meng, X. Chen, J. Li, X. Xie, X. Lian, Z. Zhang, Y. Cao, W. Yin, R. Jin, Emerg. Microbes Infect. 2023, 12, 2212806.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Steeland, R. E. Vandenbroucke, C. Libert, Drug Discov. Today 2016, 21, 1076;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) K. B. Vu, M. A. Ghahroudi, L. Wyns, S. Muyldermans, Mol. Immunol. 1997, 34, 1121;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. M. Griffin, J. R. Snowden, A. D. Lawson, U. Wernery, J. Kinne, T. S. Baker, J. Immunol. Methods 2014, 405, 35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) R. Divine, H. V. Dang, G. Ueda, J. A. Fallas, I. Vulovic, W. Sheffler, S. Saini, Y. T. Zhao, I. X. Raj, P. A. Morawski, M. F. Jennewein, L. J. Homad, Y. H. Wan, M. R. Tooley, F. Seeger, A. Etemadi, M. L. Fahning, J. Lazarovits, A. Roederer, A. C. Walls, L. Stewart, M. Mazloomi, N. P. King, D. J. Campbell, A. T. McGuire, L. Stamatatos, H. Ruohola‐Baker, J. Mathieu, D. Veesler, D. Baker, Science 2021, 372;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) T. M. Chidyausiku, S. R. Mendes, J. C. Klima, M. Nadal, U. Eckhard, J. Roel‐Touris, S. Houliston, T. Guevara, H. K. Haddox, A. Moyer, C. H. Arrowsmith, F. X. Gomis‐Rüth, D. Baker, E. Marcos, Nat. Commun. 2022, 13, 5661;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) V. S. Boorla, R. Chowdhury, R. Ramasubramanian, B. Ameglio, R. Frick, J. J. Gray, C. D. Maranas, Proteins 2023, 91, 196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Kang, Y. Jiao, K. Jin, L. Pan, bioRxiv 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. R. Bennett, J. L. Watson, R. J. Ragotte, A. J. Borst, D. L. See, C. Weidle, R. Biswas, E. L. Shrock, P. J. Y. Leung, B. Huang, I. Goreshnik, R. Ault, K. D. Carr, B. Singer, C. Criswell, D. Vafeados, M. Garcia Sanchez, H. M. Kim, S. Vázquez Torres, S. Chan, D. Baker, bioRxiv 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Kunz, M. Durandy, L. Seguin, C. C. Feral, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2023, 24, 13229;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Y. Wu, C. Li, S. Xia, X. Tian, Y. Kong, Z. Wang, C. Gu, R. Zhang, C. Tu, Y. Xie, Z. Yang, L. Lu, S. Jiang, T. Ying, Cell Host Microbe 2020, 27, 891.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Cunningham, P. A. Piedra, F. Martinon‐Torres, H. Szymanski, B. Brackeva, E. Dombrecht, L. Detalle, C. Fleurinck, Lancet Respir. Med. 2021, 9, 21;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. I. Schriek, M. M. van Haaren, M. Poniman, G. Dekkers, A. E. H. Bentlage, M. Grobben, G. Vidarsson, R. W. Sanders, T. Verrips, T. B. H. Geijtenbeek, R. Heukers, N. A. Kootstra, S. W. de Taeye, M. J. van Gils, Front. Immunol. 2022, 13, 893648;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) A. Xiong, W. Li, X. Li, Y. Fan, Z. Ma, J. Fang, Q. Xie, W. Zhuang, M. Kang, J. Wang, T. Xu, M. Xu, L. Zhi, Q. Liu, N. Wang, C. Zhou, Eur. J. Cancer 2023, 190, 112936;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) Y. Ma, J. Xue, Y. Zhao, Y. Zhang, Y. Huang, Y. Yang, W. Fang, Y. Guo, Q. Li, X. Ge, J. Sun, B. Zhang, Y. Zhang, J. Xiao, L. Zhang, H. Zhao, J. Immunother. Cancer 2023, 11, e006654;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) L. Ding, C. Tian, S. Feng, G. Fida, C. Zhang, Y. Ma, G. Ai, S. Achilefu, Y. Gu, Theranostics 2015, 5, 378;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>f) M. Scully, S. R. Cataland, F. Peyvandi, P. Coppo, P. Knöbl, J. A. Kremer Hovinga, A. Metjian, J. de la Rubia, K. Pavenski, F. Callewaert, D. Biswas, H. De Winter, R. K. Zeldin, N. Engl. J. Med. 2019, 380, 335;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. M. Jeworowski, B. Mühlemann, F. Walper, M. L. Schmidt, J. Jansen, A. Krumbholz, E. Simon‐Lorière, T. C. Jones, V. M. Corman, C. Drosten, Euro Surveill. 2024, 29;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Z. Liu, J. Zhou, W. Wang, G. Zhang, L. Xing, K. Zhang, Y. Wang, W. Xu, Q. Wang, Q. Man, Q. Wang, T. Ying, Y. Zhu, S. Jiang, L. Lu, Cell Rep. Med. 2024, 5, 101445;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) C. Li, W. Zhan, Z. Yang, C. Tu, G. Hu, X. Zhang, W. Song, S. Du, Y. Zhu, K. Huang, Y. Kong, M. Zhang, Q. Mao, X. Gu, Y. Zhang, Y. Xie, Q. Deng, Y. Song, Z. Chen, L. Lu, S. Jiang, Y. Wu, L. Sun, T. Ying, Cell 2022, 185, 1389;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Luo, J. Zhang, A. J. B. Kreutzberger, A. Eaton, R. J. Edwards, C. Jing, H. Q. Dai, G. D. Sempowski, K. Cronin, R. Parks, A. Y. Ye, K. Mansouri, M. Barr, N. Pishesha, A. C. Williams, L. Vieira Francisco, A. Saminathan, H. Peng, H. Batra, L. Bellusci, S. Khurana, S. M. Alam, D. C. Montefiori, K. O. Saunders, M. Tian, H. Ploegh, T. Kirchhausen, B. Chen, B. F. Haynes, F. W. Alt, Sci. Immunol. 2022, 7, eadd5446.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. N. Starr, A. J. Greaney, S. K. Hilton, D. Ellis, K. H. D. Crawford, A. S. Dingens, M. J. Navarro, J. E. Bowen, M. A. Tortorici, A. C. Walls, N. P. King, D. Veesler, J. D. Bloom, Cell 2020, 182, 1295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. S. Brown, D. Safronetz, A. Marzi, H. Ebihara, H. Feldmann, J. Virol. 2011, 85, 12781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Yan, E. Li, T. Wang, Y. Li, J. Liu, W. Wang, T. Qin, R. Su, H. Pei, S. Wang, N. Feng, Y. Zhao, S. Yang, X. Xia, Y. Gao, Front. Immunol. 2022, 13, 821664.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Xu, K. Xu, S. Jung, A. Conte, J. Lieberman, F. Muecksch, J. C. C. Lorenzi, S. Park, F. Schmidt, Z. Wang, Y. Huang, Y. Luo, M. S. Nair, P. Wang, J. E. Schulz, L. Tessarollo, T. Bylund, G. Y. Chuang, A. S. Olia, T. Stephens, I. T. Teng, Y. Tsybovsky, T. Zhou, V. Munster, D. D. Ho, T. Hatziioannou, P. D. Bieniasz, M. C. Nussenzweig, P. D. Kwong, R. Casellas, Nature 2021, 595, 278.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>