<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39382352</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2648</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>09</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of advanced nursing</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Adv Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19's Impact in Long-Term Care Facilities: The Health and Coping Strategies of Older Adults and Their Families.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jan.16530</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Describe the stressors that long-term care facility (LTCF) residents and their family members were exposed to during the COVID-19 pandemic, the resources they mobilised to cope with them, and the strategies used by professionals to support them.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">A descriptive qualitative design study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">Between March 2021 and February 2022, we carried out semi-structured interviews with 8 LTCF residents, 11 family members, and 6 focus groups made up of healthcare and support staff from 8 LTCFs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Three themes emerged: (1) residents and family members: separated and suffering, (2) residents and family members: reinventing themselves, and (3) staff: attempts to maintain residents' well-being.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">LTCF Residents' and their family members' exposure to the various stressors linked to the COVID-19 pandemic generated suffering. Healthcare and support staff implemented strategies to support them, notably to maintain links between them. Some deep reflection must occur on the concepts of LTCF residents' autonomy and self-determination when implementing protective measures in future pandemic situations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPLICATIONS FOR THE PROFESSION AND PATIENT CARE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study has provided new insights into the nature of the stressors faced by LTCF residents and their families, and the measures implemented by professionals to support them. The role of the families of LTCF residents needs to be better recognised. Our results indicate the importance of involving nurses in discussions on patient autonomy and self-determination when implementing protective measures (in a pandemic situation).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPACT" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Exploring the nature of the stressors experienced by LTCF residents and their families enables professionals to tailor strategies to support them. Maintaining residents' self-determination is essential when implementing protective measures. Families involved with residents must be recognised and included in the assessment of stressors and the personalisation and implementation of strategies to support LTCF residents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PATIENT OR PUBLIC CONTRIBUTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">No Patient or Public Contribution.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Advanced Nursing published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cohen</LastName><ForeName>Christine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8681-0933</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>La Source School of Nursing, HES-SO University of Applied Sciences and Arts Western Switzerland, Lausanne, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abt</LastName><ForeName>Maryline</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8867-9518</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>La Source School of Nursing, HES-SO University of Applied Sciences and Arts Western Switzerland, Lausanne, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bélanger</LastName><ForeName>Louise</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0911-7788</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Département Sciences infirmières, Université du Québec en Outaouais, Gatineau, QC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ortoleva Bucher</LastName><ForeName>Claudia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8411-4181</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>La Source School of Nursing, HES-SO University of Applied Sciences and Arts Western Switzerland, Lausanne, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>SAGEX 105907</GrantID><Agency>University of Applied Sciences and Arts Western Switzerland</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Adv Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7609811</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0309-2402</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coping strategies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">family member</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">long‐term care facilities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">resident</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">staff strategies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">stressors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">support</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39382352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jan.16530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Auxéméry, Y., and C. Tarquinio. 2020. “Le confinement généralisé pendant l'épidémie de Coronavirus: Conséquences médico‐psychologiques en populations générales, soignantes, et de sujets souffrant antérieurement de troubles psychiques (Rétrospective concernant les répercussions des risques létaux de masse, modèles scientifiques du confinement collectif, premières observations cliniques, mise en place de contre‐mesures et de stratégies thérapeutiques innovantes).” Annales Médico‐Psychologiques, Revue Psychiatrique 178, no. 7: 699–710. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amp.2020.06.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayalon, L., A. Chasteen, M. Diehl, et al. 2021. “Aging in Times of the COVID‐19 Pandemic: Avoiding Ageism and Fostering Intergenerational Solidarity.” Journals of Gerontology: Series B 76, no. 2: e49–e52. https://doi.org/10.1093/geronb/gbaa051.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, C., W. M. Wong, and K. W. Tsang. 2006. “Perception of Benefits and Costs During SARS Outbreak: An 18‐Month Prospective Study.” Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology 74, no. 5: 870–879. https://doi.org/10.1037/0022‐006x.74.5.870.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, S. K. W., G. H. C. Chong, S. S. Y. Chang, et al. 2006. “Adjustment to Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS): Roles of Appraisal and Post‐Traumatic Growth.” Psychology &amp; Health 21, no. 3: 301–317. https://doi.org/10.1080/14768320500286450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiang, H. H., M. B. Chen, and I. L. Sue. 2007. “Self‐State of Nurses in Caring for SARS Survivors.” Nursing Ethics 14, no. 1: 18–26. https://doi.org/10.1177/0969733007071353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu, C. H., A. V. Yee, and V. Stamatopoulos. 2022. ““It's the Worst Thing I've Ever Been Put Through in My Life”: The Trauma Experienced by Essential Family Caregivers of Loved Ones in Long‐Term Care During the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Canada.” International Journal of Qualitative Studies on Health and Well‐Being 17, no. 1: 2075532. https://doi.org/10.1080/17482631.2022.2075532.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crespo‐Martín, A., D. Palacios‐Ceña, E. Huertas‐Hoyas, J. Güeita‐Rodríguez, G. Fernández‐Gómez, and J. Pérez‐Corrales. 2022. “Emotional Impact and Perception of Support in Nursing Home Residents During the COVID‐19 Lockdown: A Qualitative Study.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 19, no. 23: 15712. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph192315712.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danilovich, M. K., C. R. Norrick, K. C. Hill, and D. E. Conroy. 2020. “Nursing Home Resident Weight Loss During Coronavirus Disease 2019 Restrictions.” Journal of the American Medical Directors Association 21, no. 11: 1568–1569. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jamda.2020.08.032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DSAS. 2020. “Directive concernant les mesures d'accompagnement des EMS et les modalités d'admissions en EMS pendant la phase de lutte contre le coronavirus COVID‐19.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duhamel, F. 2007. “La santé et la famille: Une approche systémique en soins infirmiers (2e éd). G. Morin.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fontannaz, C. 2020. “Inquiétude dans les EMS romands qui paient un lourd tribut au Covid‐19.” https://www.rts.ch/info/regions/11220799‐inquietude‐dans‐les‐ems‐romands‐qui‐paient‐un‐lourd‐tribut‐au‐covid‐19.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fortin, M.‐F., and J. Gagnon. 2016. “Fondements et étapes du processus de recherche: Méthodes quantitatives et qualitatives. (3e ed.). Chenelière Education.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fortin, M.‐F., and J. Gagnon. 2022. “Fondements et étapes du processus de recherche: Méthodes quantitatives et qualitatives (4e édition). Chenelière éducation.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freedman, A., and J. Nicolle. 2020. “Social Isolation and Loneliness: The New Geriatric Giants.” Canadian Family Physician 66, no. 3: 176–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner, W., D. States, and N. Bagley. 2020. “The Coronavirus and the Risks to the Elderly in Long‐Term Care.” Journal of Aging &amp; Social Policy 32, no. 4–5: 310–315. https://doi.org/10.1080/08959420.2020.1750543.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giri, S., L. M. Chenn, and R. Romero‐Ortuno. 2021. “Nursing Homes During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Scoping Review of Challenges and Responses.” European Geriatric Medicine 12, no. 6: 1127–1136. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41999‐021‐00531‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hindmarch, W., G. McGhan, K. Flemons, and D. McCaughey. 2021. “COVID‐19 and Long‐Term Care: The Essential Role of Family Caregivers.” Canadian Geriatrics Journal 24, no. 3: 195–199. https://doi.org/10.5770/cgj.24.508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huber, A., and A. Seifert. 2022. “Retrospective Feelings of Loneliness During the COVID‐19 Pandemic Among Residents of Long‐Term Care Facilities.” Aging and Health Research 2, no. 1: 100053. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ahr.2022.100053.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ickert, C., R. Stefaniuk, and J. Leask. 2021. “Experiences of Long‐Term Care and Supportive Living Residents and Families During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: “It's a Lot Different for Us Than It Is for the Average Joe”.” Geriatric Nursing 42, no. 6: 1547–1555. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gerinurse.2021.10.012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>James, P. B., J. Wardle, A. Steel, and J. Adams. 2019. “Post‐Ebola Psychosocial Experiences and Coping Mechanisms Among Ebola Survivors: A Systematic Review.” Tropical Medicine &amp; International Health 24, no. 6: 671–691. https://doi.org/10.1111/tmi.13226.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaelen, S., W. van den Boogaard, U. Pellecchia, et al. 2021. “How to Bring residents' Psychosocial Well‐Being to the Heart of the Fight Against Covid‐19 in Belgian Nursing Homes—A Qualitative Study.” PLoS One 16, no. 3: e0249098. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0249098.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kusmaul, N., V. J. Miller, and J. H. Cheon. 2022. ““They Just Took Him out of My Life”: Nursing Home Care Partner Experiences During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Journal of Gerontological Nursing 48, no. 2: 7–11. https://doi.org/10.3928/00989134‐20220111‐02.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larivière, N., and M. Corbière. 2014. “Méthodes qualitatives, quantitatives et mixtes: Dans la recherche en sciences humaines dans la recherche en sciences humaines, sociales et de la santé. Presses de l'Université du Québec.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, T. M., I. Chi, L. W. Chung, and K. L. Chou. 2006. “Ageing and Psychological Response During the Post‐SARS Period.” Aging &amp; Mental Health 10, no. 3: 303–311. https://doi.org/10.1080/13607860600638545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lum, L. H. W., and P. A. Tambyah. 2020. “Outbreak of COVID‐19—An Urgent Need for Good Science to Silence Our Fears?” Singapore Medical Journal 61, no. 2: 55–57. https://doi.org/10.11622/smedj.2020018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matua, G. A., and D. M. Wal. 2015. “Living Under the Constant Threat of Ebola: A Phenomenological Study of Survivors and Family Caregivers During an Ebola Outbreak.” Journal of Nursing Research 23, no. 3: 217–224. https://doi.org/10.1097/jnr.0000000000000116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell, L. L., E. A. Albers, R. W. Birkeland, et al. 2022. “Caring for a Relative With Dementia in Long‐Term Care During COVID‐19.” Journal of the American Medical Directors Association 23, no. 3: 428–433.e1. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jamda.2021.11.026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mok, E., B. P. Chung, J. W. Chung, and T. K. Wong. 2005. “An Exploratory Study of Nurses Suffering From Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS).” International Journal of Nursing Practice 11, no. 4: 150–160. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1440‐172X.2005.00520.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nabarrot, J., S. Piazza, and A. Chandon‐Piazza. 2022. “Le Syndrome de glissement à l'aune d'un placement en EHPAD: Acte ultime de résistance?” Topique 154, no. 1: 77–89. https://doi.org/10.3917/top.154.0079.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuman, B., and J. Fawcett. 2011. The Neuman Systems Model. 5th ed. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Pearson.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noten, S., A. Stoop, J. De Witte, et al. 2022. ““Precious Time Together Was Taken Away”: Impact of COVID‐19 Restrictive Measures on Social Needs and Loneliness From the Perspective of Residents of Nursing Homes, Close Relatives, and Volunteers.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 19, no. 6: 3468. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19063468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paananen, J., J. Rannikko, M. Harju, and J. Pirhonen. 2021. “The Impact of Covid‐19‐Related Distancing on the Well‐Being of Nursing Home Residents and Their Family Members: A Qualitative Study.” International Journal of Nursing Studies Advances 3: 100031. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnsa.2021.100031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paillé, P., and A. Mucchielli. 2008. L'analyse qualitative en sciences humaines et sociales. Paris: Armand Colin.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paque, K., H. Bastiaens, P. Van Bogaert, and T. Dilles. 2018. “Living in a Nursing Home: A Phenomenological Study Exploring residents' Loneliness and Other Feelings.” Scandinavian Journal of Caring Sciences 32, no. 4: 1477–1484. https://doi.org/10.1111/scs.12599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez‐Rodríguez, P., M. Díaz de Bustamante, S. Aparicio Mollá, et al. 2021. “Functional, Cognitive, and Nutritional Decline in 435 Elderly Nursing Home Residents After the First Wave of the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” European Geriatric Medicine 12, no. 6: 1137–1145. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41999‐021‐00524‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polit, D., and C. Beck. 2020. Essentials of Nursing Research: Appraising Evidence for Nursing Practice. Philadephia, USA: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabelo, I., V. Lee, M. P. Fallah, et al. 2016. “Psychological Distress Among Ebola Survivors Discharged From an Ebola Treatment Unit in Monrovia, Liberia–A Qualitative Study.” Frontiers in Public Health 4: 142. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2016.00142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saad, A., O. Magwood, J. Benjamen, et al. 2022. “Health Equity Implications of the COVID‐19 Lockdown and Visitation Strategies in Long‐Term Care Homes in Ontario: A Mixed Method Study.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 19, no. 7: 4275. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19074275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santini, Z. I., P. E. Jose, E. York Cornwell, et al. 2020. “Social Disconnectedness, Perceived Isolation, and Symptoms of Depression and Anxiety Among Older Americans (NSHAP): A Longitudinal Mediation Analysis.” Lancet Public Health 5, no. 1: e62–e70. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2468‐2667(19)30230‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider, P., M. Abt, C. Cohen, N. Marmier, and C. Ortoleva Bucher. 2023. “The Impact of Protective Measures Against COVID‐19 on the Wellbeing of Residents in Nursing Homes and Their Relatives: A Rapid Review.” BMC Geriatrics 23, no. 1: 649. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12877‐023‐04300‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwerdtle, P. M., V. De Clerck, and V. Plummer. 2017. “Experiences of Ebola Survivors: Causes of Distress and Sources of Resilience.” Prehospital and Disaster Medicine 32, no. 3: 234–239. https://doi.org/10.1017/s1049023x17000073.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sim, K., Y. Huak Chan, P. N. Chong, H. C. Chua, and S. Wen Soon. 2010. “Psychosocial and Coping Responses Within the Community Health Care Setting Towards a National Outbreak of an Infectious Disease.” Journal of Psychosomatic Research 68, no. 2: 195–202. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychores.2009.04.004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smaling, H. J. A., B. Tilburgs, W. P. Achterberg, and M. Visser. 2022. “The Impact of Social Distancing Due to the COVID‐19 Pandemic on People With Dementia, Family Carers and Healthcare Professionals: A Qualitative Study.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 19, no. 1: 519. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19010519.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taha, S., K. Matheson, T. Cronin, and H. Anisman. 2014. “Intolerance of Uncertainty, Appraisals, Coping, and Anxiety: The Case of the 2009 H1N1 Pandemic.” British Journal of Health Psychology 19, no. 3: 592–605. https://doi.org/10.1111/bjhp.12058.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tana, C., L. Moffa, K. Falasca, et al. 2023. “Approach to COVID‐19 in Older Adults and Indications for Improving the Outcomes.” Annals of Medicine 55, no. 2: 2265298. https://doi.org/10.1080/07853890.2023.2265298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van der Roest, H. G., M. Prins, C. van der Velden, et al. 2020. “The Impact of COVID‐19 Measures on Well‐Being of Older Long‐Term Care Facility Residents in The Netherlands.” Journal of the American Medical Directors Association 21, no. 11: 1569–1570. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jamda.2020.09.007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veiga‐Seijo, R., M. d. C. Miranda‐Duro, and S. Veiga‐Seijo. 2022. “Strategies and Actions to Enable Meaningful Family Connections in Nursing Homes During the COVID‐19: A Scoping Review.” Clinical Gerontologist 45, no. 1: 20–30. https://doi.org/10.1080/07317115.2021.1937424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vickery, A., P. Willis, J. Powell, et al. 2023. “The Impact of COVID‐19 Lockdown Measures on Older residents' Social Connections and Everyday Wellbeing Within Housing Schemes That Provide Care and Support in England and Wales.” Journal of Aging Studies 65: 101126. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaging.2023.101126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiersma, E. C. 2012. “‘You Can't Turn Back the Clock’: Conceptualizing Time After Institutionalization.” Canadian Journal on Aging/La Revue Canadienne Du Vieillissement 31, no. 1: 73–85. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0714980811000572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2020. “Coronavirus Disease (COVID‐19) Pandemic 2020.”</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>