<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39386680</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2692-8205</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>bioRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>BETACORONAVIRUSES DIFFERENTIALLY ACTIVATE THE INTEGRATED STRESS RESPONSE TO OPTIMIZE VIRAL REPLICATION IN LUNG DERIVED CELL LINES.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.09.25.614975</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.09.25.614975</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">The betacoronavirus genus contains five of the seven human viruses, making it a particularly critical area of research to prepare for future viral emergence. We utilized three human betacoronaviruses, one from each subgenus- HCoV-OC43 (embecovirus), SARS-CoV-2 (sarbecovirus) and MERS-CoV (merbecovirus)- to study betacoronavirus interaction with the PKR-like ER kinase (PERK) pathway of the integrated stress response (ISR)/unfolded protein response (UPR). The PERK pathway becomes activated by an abundance of unfolded proteins within the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), leading to phosphorylation of eIF2α and translational attenuation in lung derived cell lines. We demonstrate that MERS-CoV, HCoV-OC43, and SARS-CoV-2 all activate PERK and induce responses downstream of p-eIF2α, while only SARS-CoV-2 induces detectable p-eIF2α during infection. Using a small molecule inhibitor of eIF2α dephosphorylation, we provide evidence that MERS-CoV and HCoV-OC43 maximize replication through p-eIF2α dephosphorylation. Interestingly, genetic ablation of GADD34 expression, an inducible phosphatase 1 (PP1)-interacting partner targeting eIF2α for dephosphorylation, did not significantly alter HCoV-OC43 or SARS-CoV-2 replication, while siRNA knockdown of the constitutive PP1 partner, CReP, dramatically reduced HCoV-OC43 replication. Combining growth arrest and DNA damage-inducible protein (GADD34) knockout with peripheral ER membrane-targeted protein (CReP) knockdown had the maximum impact on HCoV-OC43 replication, while SARS-CoV-2 replication was unaffected. Overall, we conclude that eIF2α dephosphorylation is critical for efficient protein production and replication during MERS-CoV and HCoV-OC43 infection. SARS-CoV-2, however, appears to be insensitive to p-eIF2α and, during infection, may even downregulate dephosphorylation to limit host translation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPORTANCE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Lethal human betacoronaviruses have emerged three times in the last two decades, causing two epidemics and a pandemic. Here, we demonstrate differences in how these viruses interact with cellular translational control mechanisms. Utilizing inhibitory compounds and genetic ablation, we demonstrate that MERS-CoV and HCoV-OC43 benefit from keeping p-eIF2α levels low to maintain high rates of virus translation while SARS-CoV-2 tolerates high levels of p-eIF2α. We utilized a PP1:GADD34/CReP inhibitor, GADD34 KO cells, and CReP-targeting siRNA to investigate the therapeutic potential of these pathways. While ineffective for SARS-CoV-2, we found that HCoV-OC43 seems to primarily utilize CReP to limit p-eIF2a accumulation. This work highlights the need to consider differences amongst these viruses, which may inform the development of host-directed pan-coronavirus therapeutics.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Renner</LastName><ForeName>David M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0548-3876</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Microbiology, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA 19104-6076.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Penn Center for Research on Coronaviruses and Other Emerging Pathogens, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA 19104-6076.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parenti</LastName><ForeName>Nicholas A</ForeName><Initials>NA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3673-1027</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Microbiology, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA 19104-6076.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Penn Center for Research on Coronaviruses and Other Emerging Pathogens, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA 19104-6076.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weiss</LastName><ForeName>Susan R</ForeName><Initials>SR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8155-4528</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Microbiology, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA 19104-6076.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Penn Center for Research on Coronaviruses and Other Emerging Pathogens, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA 19104-6076.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI140442</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>T32 AI055400</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>bioRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101680187</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2692-8205</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MERS-CoV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">OC43</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PERK pathway</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PKR pathway</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">integrated stress response</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39386680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11463420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.09.25.614975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.09.25.614975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Costa-Mattioli M., Walter P., The integrated stress response: From mechanism to disease. Science 368 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8997189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32327570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C. C., Peterson A., Zinshteyn B., Regot S., Green R., Ribosome Collisions Trigger General Stress Responses to Regulate Cell Fate. Cell 182, 404–416.e414 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7384957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32610081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo X. et al., Mitochondrial stress is relayed to the cytosol by an OMA1–DELE1–HRI pathway. Nature 579, 427–432 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7147832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32132707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platanias L. C., Mechanisms of type-I- and type-II-interferon-mediated signalling. Nature Reviews Immunology 5, 375–386 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15864272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hetz C., Zhang K., Kaufman R. J., Mechanisms, regulation and functions of the unfolded protein response. Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology 21, 421–438 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8867924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32457508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidrauski C. et al., Pharmacological dimerization and activation of the exchange factor eIF2B antagonizes the integrated stress response. Elife 4, e07314 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4426669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25875391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vattem K. M., Wek R. C., Reinitiation involving upstream ORFs regulates ATF4 mRNA translation in mammalian cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 101, 11269–11274 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC509193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15277680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hetz C., The unfolded protein response: controlling cell fate decisions under ER stress and beyond. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 13, 89–102 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22251901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu H., Tian M., Ding C., Yu S., The C/EBP Homologous Protein (CHOP) Transcription Factor Functions in Endoplasmic Reticulum Stress-Induced Apoptosis and Microbial Infection. Frontiers in immunology 9, 3083–3083 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6328441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30662442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reid D. W. et al., Complementary Roles of GADD34- and CReP-Containing Eukaryotic Initiation Factor 2α Phosphatases during the Unfolded Protein Response. Mol Cell Biol 36, 1868–1880 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4911741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27161320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jousse C. et al., Inhibition of a constitutive translation initiation factor 2alpha phosphatase, CReP, promotes survival of stressed cells. J Cell Biol 163, 767–775 (2003).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2173671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14638860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee Y. Y., Cevallos R. C., Jan E., An upstream open reading frame regulates translation of GADD34 during cellular stresses that induce eIF2alpha phosphorylation. J Biol Chem 284, 6661–6673 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2652341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19131336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novoa I., Zeng H., Harding H. P., Ron D., Feedback inhibition of the unfolded protein response by GADD34-mediated dephosphorylation of eIF2alpha. J Cell Biol 153, 1011–1022 (2001).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2174339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11381086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Grunewald M., Perlman S., Coronaviruses: An Updated Overview of Their Replication and Pathogenesis. Methods in molecular biology (Clifton, N.J.) 2203, 1–29 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7682345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32833200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knoops K. et al., SARS-coronavirus replication is supported by a reticulovesicular network of modified endoplasmic reticulum. PLoS Biol 6, 1957–1974 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2535663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18798692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malone B., Urakova N., Snijder E. J., Campbell E. A., Structures and functions of coronavirus replication-transcription complexes and their relevance for SARS-CoV-2 drug design. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 23, 21–39 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8613731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34824452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cortese M. et al., Integrative Imaging Reveals SARS-CoV-2-Induced Reshaping of Subcellular Morphologies. Cell Host Microbe 28, 853–866.e855 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7670925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33245857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y. et al., SARS-CoV-2 induces double-stranded RNA-mediated innate immune responses in respiratory epithelial-derived cells and cardiomyocytes. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 118 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8072330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33811184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comar C. E. et al., Antagonism of dsRNA-Induced Innate Immune Pathways by NS4a and NS4b Accessory Proteins during MERS Coronavirus Infection. mBio 10 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6437052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30914508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comar C. E. et al., MERS-CoV endoribonuclease and accessory proteins jointly evade host innate immunity during infection of lung and nasal epithelial cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 119, e2123208119 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9173776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35594398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price A. M. et al., Adenovirus prevents dsRNA formation by promoting efficient splicing of viral RNA. Nucleic Acids Res 50, 1201–1220 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8860579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34671803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habjan M. et al., NSs protein of rift valley fever virus induces the specific degradation of the double-stranded RNA-dependent protein kinase. J Virol 83, 4365–4375 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2668506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19211744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gale M. J. Jr., Korth M. J., Katze M. G., Repression of the PKR protein kinase by the hepatitis C virus NS5A protein: a potential mechanism of interferon resistance. Clin Diagn Virol 10, 157–162 (1998).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9741641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawagishi-Kobayashi M., Silverman J. B., Ung T. L., Dever T. E., Regulation of the protein kinase PKR by the vaccinia virus pseudosubstrate inhibitor K3L is dependent on residues conserved between the K3L protein and the PKR substrate eIF2alpha. Mol Cell Biol 17, 4146–4158 (1997).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC232268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9199350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao P. et al., Viral evasion of PKR restriction by reprogramming cellular stress granules. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 119, e2201169119 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9303852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35858300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnamoorthy J., Mounir Z., Raven J. F., Koromilas A. E., The eIF2alpha kinases inhibit vesicular stomatitis virus replication independently of eIF2alpha phosphorylation. Cell Cycle 7, 2346–2351 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18677106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berlanga J. J. et al., Antiviral effect of the mammalian translation initiation factor 2alpha kinase GCN2 against RNA viruses. Embo j 25, 1730–1740 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1440839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16601681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz J. L. et al., Coronavirus gene 7 counteracts host defenses and modulates virus virulence. PLoS Pathog 7, e1002090 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3111541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21695242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He B., Gross M., Roizman B., The gamma(1)34.5 protein of herpes simplex virus 1 complexes with protein phosphatase 1alpha to dephosphorylate the alpha subunit of the eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2 and preclude the shutoff of protein synthesis by double-stranded RNA-activated protein kinase. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 94, 843–848 (1997).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC19601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9023344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang F., Moon A., Childs K., Goodbourn S., Dixon L. K., The African swine fever virus DP71L protein recruits the protein phosphatase 1 catalytic subunit to dephosphorylate eIF2alpha and inhibits CHOP induction but is dispensable for these activities during virus infection. J Virol 84, 10681–10689 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2950568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20702639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Z., Qiu Y., Ge X., The taxonomy, host range and pathogenicity of coronaviruses and other viruses in the Nidovirales order. Animal Diseases 1, 5 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8062217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34778878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyce M. et al., A selective inhibitor of eIF2alpha dephosphorylation protects cells from ER stress. Science 307, 935–939 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15705855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan Y., Harding H. P., Ron D., Higher-order phosphatase-substrate contacts terminate the integrated stress response. Nat Struct Mol Biol 28, 835–846 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34625748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen L. C. et al., SARS-CoV-2 Diverges from Other Betacoronaviruses in Only Partially Activating the IRE1alpha/XBP1 Endoplasmic Reticulum Stress Pathway in Human Lung-Derived Cells. mBio 13, e0241522 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9600248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36125275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang H.-Y. et al., Activating transcription factor 3 is integral to the eukaryotic initiation factor 2 kinase stress response. Molecular and cellular biology 24, 1365–1377 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC321431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14729979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen T. B., Lopez C. Q., Manczak T., Martinez K., Simonsen H. T., Thapsigargin--from Thapsia L. to mipsagargin. Molecules 20, 6113–6127 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6272310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25856061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Echavarria-Consuegra L. et al., Manipulation of the unfolded protein response: A pharmacological strategy against coronavirus infection. PLoS Pathog 17, e1009644 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8211288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34138976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaban M. S. et al., Inhibiting coronavirus replication in cultured cells by chemical ER stress. bioRxiv 10.1101/2020.08.26.266304, 2020.2008.2026.266304 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2020.08.26.266304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sims A. C. et al., Unfolded Protein Response Inhibition Reduces Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-Induced Acute Lung Injury. mBio 12, e0157221 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8406233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34372702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu H. et al., Targeting highly pathogenic coronavirus-induced apoptosis reduces viral pathogenesis and disease severity. Science advances 7, eabf8577 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8208716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34134991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das I. et al., Preventing proteostasis diseases by selective inhibition of a phosphatase regulatory subunit. Science 348, 239–242 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4490275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25859045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marciniak S. J., Chambers J. E., Ron D., Pharmacological targeting of endoplasmic reticulum stress in disease. Nat Rev Drug Discov 21, 115–140 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34702991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa-Mattioli M. et al., eIF2alpha phosphorylation bidirectionally regulates the switch from short- to long-term synaptic plasticity and memory. Cell 129, 195–206 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4149214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17418795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert F. et al., Initiation of protein synthesis by hepatitis C virus is refractory to reduced eIF2.GTP.Met-tRNA(i)(Met) ternary complex availability. Mol Biol Cell 17, 4632–4644 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1635388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16928960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrara M., Sigurdardottir A., Bertolotti A., Decoding the selectivity of eIF2alpha holophosphatases and PPP1R15A inhibitors. Nat Struct Mol Biol 24, 708–716 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5591645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28759048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clavarino G. et al., Protein phosphatase 1 subunit Ppp1r15a/GADD34 regulates cytokine production in polyinosinic:polycytidylic acid-stimulated dendritic cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 109, 3006–3011 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3286954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22315398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan C. P. et al., Modulation of the unfolded protein response by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus spike protein. J Virol 80, 9279–9287 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1563899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16940539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fusade-Boyer M. et al., Evaluation of the Antiviral Activity of Sephin1 Treatment and Its Consequences on eIF2alpha Phosphorylation in Response to Viral Infections. Front Immunol 10, 134 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6379315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30809223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu T. et al., GADD34-mediated dephosphorylation of eIF2alpha facilitates pseudorabies virus replication by maintaining de novo protein synthesis. Vet Res 52, 148 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8686791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34930429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rojas M., Vasconcelos G., Dever T. E., An eIF2alpha-binding motif in protein phosphatase 1 subunit GADD34 and its viral orthologs is required to promote dephosphorylation of eIF2alpha. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 112, E3466–3475 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4500263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26100893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher T. et al., Parsing the role of NSP1 in SARS-CoV-2 infection. Cell Rep 39, 110954 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9133101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35671758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamitani W., Huang C., Narayanan K., Lokugamage K. G., Makino S., A two-pronged strategy to suppress host protein synthesis by SARS coronavirus Nsp1 protein. Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology 16, 1134–1140 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2784181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19838190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagawa K. et al., The Endonucleolytic RNA Cleavage Function of nsp1 of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus Promotes the Production of Infectious Virus Particles in Specific Human Cell Lines. Journal of virology 92, e01157–01118 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6189501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30111568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narayanan K., Ramirez S. I., Lokugamage K. G., Makino S., Coronavirus nonstructural protein 1: Common and distinct functions in the regulation of host and viral gene expression. Virus research 202, 89–100 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4444399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25432065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zust R. et al., Coronavirus non-structural protein 1 is a major pathogenicity factor: implications for the rational design of coronavirus vaccines. PLoS Pathog 3, e109 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1941747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17696607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolliver S. M., Galbraith C., Khaperskyy D. A., Human Betacoronavirus OC43 Interferes with the Integrated Stress Response Pathway in Infected Cells. Viruses 16 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10893100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38399988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kastan J. P., Dobrikova E. Y., Bryant J. D., Gromeier M., CReP mediates selective translation initiation at the endoplasmic reticulum. Sci Adv 6, eaba0745 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7269655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32537501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aviner R. et al., SARS-CoV-2 Nsp1 cooperates with initiation factors EIF1 and 1A to selectively enhance translation of viral RNA. PLoS Pathog 20, e1011535 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10903962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38335237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krzyzosiak A. et al., Target-Based Discovery of an Inhibitor of the Regulatory Phosphatase PPP1R15B. Cell 174, 1216–1228 e1219 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6108835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30057111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>So J. S., Cho S., Min S. H., Kimball S. R., Lee A. H., IRE1alpha-Dependent Decay of CReP/Ppp1r15b mRNA Increases Eukaryotic Initiation Factor 2alpha Phosphorylation and Suppresses Protein Synthesis. Mol Cell Biol 35, 2761–2770 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4508316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26031337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan R. et al., Circulatory miR-98–5p levels are deregulated during diabetes and it inhibits proliferation and promotes apoptosis by targeting PPP1R15B in keratinocytes. RNA Biol 17, 188–201 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6973307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31615341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan R., Verma A. K., Datta M., mir-98–5p regulates gluconeogenesis and lipogenesis by targeting PPP1R15B in hepatocytes. J Cell Commun Signal 17, 881–895 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10409962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36917438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu H. et al., Targeting highly pathogenic coronavirus-induced apoptosis reduces viral pathogenesis and disease severity. Sci Adv 7 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8208716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34134991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casas-Sanchez A. et al., Inhibition of Protein N-Glycosylation Blocks SARS-CoV-2 Infection. mBio 13, e0371821 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8844921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35164559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White K. M. et al., Plitidepsin has potent preclinical efficacy against SARS-CoV-2 by targeting the host protein eEF1A. Science (New York, N.Y.) 371, 926–931 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7963220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33495306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bojkova D. et al., Proteomics of SARS-CoV-2-infected host cells reveals therapy targets. Nature 583, 469–472 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32408336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van den Worm S. H. E. et al., Development and RNA-synthesizing activity of coronavirus replication structures in the absence of protein synthesis. Journal of virology 85, 5669–5673 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3094996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21430047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews S., FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data. (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. B. (2014) BBTools software package.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patro R., Duggal G., Love M. I., Irizarry R. A., Kingsford C., Salmon provides fast and bias-aware quantification of transcript expression. Nat Methods 14, 417–419 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5600148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28263959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Love M. I., Huber W., Anders S., Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2. Genome Biol 15, 550 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4302049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25516281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blighe K., Rana S., Lewis M. (2023) EnhancedVolcano: publication-ready volcano plots with enhanced colouring and labeling.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gennady K. et al., Fast gene set enrichment analysis. bioRxiv 10.1101/060012, 060012 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/060012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>