<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39387981</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2730-7174</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Research on child and adolescent psychopathology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Res Child Adolesc Psychopathol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Effect of Screen Time and Positive School Factors in the Pathway to Child and Youth Mental Health Outcomes.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10802-024-01252-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Beyond achievement, educational settings offer informal supports that may be critical for child and youth mental health. However, children's educational environments have experienced significant disruption with the coronavirus pandemic. School settings offer unique opportunities to support children's mental health, but research must identify powerful points of intervention. This study examined school factors (aspirations, perceived competence, sense of belonging, and emotional engagement) as predictors of children's mental health, and the potential consequences of increasing screen time in and outside of school. Participants (N = 707) were parents and their children (6-18 years) from community and clinical settings who completed prospective surveys about children's school experiences and mental health symptoms (November 2020-May 2022). Standardized measures of depression, anxiety, irritability, inattention, and hyperactivity were collected. Structural equation modelling tested longitudinal associations between screen time, school factors, and mental health outcomes. Positive associations between each of the school factors (B = 0.14 [SE = 0.04] to B = 0.43 [SE = 0.04]) suggested they may reinforce one another. Longitudinally, sense of belonging and emotional engagement at school predicted lower severity for symptoms of depression, anxiety, irritability, and inattention (B=-0.14 [SE = 0.07] to B =-0.33 [SE = 0.10]). Greater screen time was associated with lower aspirations and perceived competence (B = - 0.08 [SE = 0.04] to B = - 0.13 [SE = 0.06]). Results suggest that school factors beyond achievement may be key correlates of child and youth mental health. While curriculum expectations emphasize academic achievement, an investment in supporting positive attitudes and aspirations at school is also warranted.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsujimoto</LastName><ForeName>Kimberley C</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anagnostou</LastName><ForeName>Evdokia</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Holland Bloorview Research Institute, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Birken</LastName><ForeName>Catherine S</ForeName><Initials>CS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Child Health Evaluative Sciences, Peter Gilgan Centre for Research and Learning, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Charach</LastName><ForeName>Alice</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cost</LastName><ForeName>Katherine Tombeau</ForeName><Initials>KT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kelley</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Queens University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monga</LastName><ForeName>Suneeta</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nicolson</LastName><ForeName>Rob</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, University of Western Ontario, London, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Georgiades</LastName><ForeName>Stelios</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioural Neurosciences, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Nicole</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hamilton-Wentworth District School Board, Hamilton, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Osokin</LastName><ForeName>Konstantin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Toronto District School Board, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burton</LastName><ForeName>Christie L</ForeName><Initials>CL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Crosbie</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Korczak</LastName><ForeName>Daphne J</ForeName><Initials>DJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada. daphne.korczak@sickkids.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada. daphne.korczak@sickkids.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>173092</GrantID><Agency>Canadian Institutes for Health Research</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>PJT-159462</GrantID><Agency>Canadian Institutes for Health Research</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>700</GrantID><Agency>Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Garry Hurvitz Centre for Brain and Mental Health</GrantID><Agency>Garry Hurvitz Centre for Brain and Mental Health</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Leong Centre for Healthy Children, SickKids</GrantID><Agency>Leong Centre for Healthy Children, SickKids</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Miner's Lamp Innovation Fund in Prevention and Early Detection of Severe Mental Illness, University of Toronto</GrantID><Agency>Miner's Lamp Innovation Fund in Prevention and Early Detection of Severe Mental Illness, University of Toronto</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Ontario Brain Institute</GrantID><Agency>Ontario Brain Institute</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Res Child Adolesc Psychopathol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101773609</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2730-7166</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Child development</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Child mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Longitudinal studies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">School</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Screen time</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39387981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10802-024-01252-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10802-024-01252-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aishworiya, R., Magiati, I., Phua, D., Daniel, L. M., Shek, L. P., Chong, Y. S., Gluckman, P. D., Meaney, M. J., &amp; Law, E. C. (2022). Are there bidirectional influences between screen time exposure and social behavioral traits in young children? Journal of Developmental &amp; Behavioral Pediatrics, 43(6), 362–369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen, K. A., &amp; Boyle, C. (2022). School belonging and student engagement: The critical overlaps, similarities, and implications for student outcomes. Handbook of research on student engagement (pp. 133–154). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen, K., Kern, M. L., Vella-Brodrick, D., Hattie, J., &amp; Waters, L. (2018). What schools need to know about fostering school belonging: A Meta-analysis. Educational Psychology Review, 30(1), 1–34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen, K. A., Jamshidi, N., Berger, E., Reupert, A., Wurf, G., &amp; May, F. (2022). Impact of school-based interventions for building school belonging in adolescence: A systematic review. Educational Psychology Review, 34(1), 229–257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appleton, J. J., Christenson, S. L., Kim, D., &amp; Reschly, A. L. (2006). Measuring cognitive and psychological engagement: Validation of the student engagement instrument. Journal of School Psychology, 44(5), 427–445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arslan, G. (2019). School belonging in adolescents: Exploring the associations with school achievement and internalising and externalising problems. Educational and Child Psychology, 36(4), 22–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arslan, G., &amp; Coşkun, M. (2023). School belongingness in academically at-risk adolescents: Addressing psychosocial functioning and psychological well-being. Journal of Happiness and Health, 3(1), 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arslan, G., Allen, K. A., &amp; Ryan, T. (2020). Exploring the impacts of school belonging on youth wellbeing and mental health among Turkish adolescents. Child Indicators Research, 13(5), 1619–1635.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakadorova, O., Lazarides, R., &amp; Raufelder, D. (2020). Effects of social and individual school self-concepts on school engagement during adolescence. European Journal of Psychology of Education, 35(1), 73–91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birmaher, B., Khetarpal, S., Brent, D., Cully, M., Balach, L., Kaufman, J., &amp; Neer, S. M. (1997). The screen for child anxiety related emotional disorders (SCARED): Scale construction and psychometric characteristics. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, 36(4), 545–553.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cadman, T., Hughes, A., Wright, C., Lopez-Lopez, J. A., Morris, T., Rice, F., Smith, G. D., &amp; Howe, L. D. (2021). The role of school enjoyment and connectedness in the association between depressive and externalising symptoms and academic attainment: Findings from a UK prospective cohort study. Journal of Affective Disorders, 295, 974–980.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34706471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8572763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerniglia, L., Cimino, S., &amp; Ammaniti, M. (2021). What are the effects of screen time on emotion regulation and academic achievements? A three-wave longitudinal study on children from 4 to 8 years of age. Journal of Early Childhood Research, 19(2), 145–160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cost, K. T., Crosbie, J., Anagnostou, E., Birken, C. S., Charach, A., Monga, S., Kelley, E., Nicolson, R., Maguire, J. L., &amp; Burton, C. L. (2021). Mostly worse, occasionally better: Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on the mental health of Canadian children and adolescents. European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, 31, 671–684.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Los Reyes, A., Augenstein, T. M., Wang, M., Thomas, S. A., Drabick, D. A., Burgers, D. E., &amp; Rabinowitz, J. (2015). The validity of the multi-informant approach to assessing child and adolescent mental health. Psychological Bulletin, 141(4), 858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4486608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dekkers, T. J., &amp; Luman, M. (2024). Editorial: The need for more effective school-based youth mental health interventions. Child Adolesc Ment Health, 29(1), 1–3. https://doi.org/10.1111/camh.12688</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/camh.12688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38140899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dissanayake, A. S., Dupuis, A., Arnold, P. D., Burton, C. L., Crosbie, J., Schachar, R. J., &amp; Levy, T. (2024). Is irritability multidimensional: Psychometrics of The Irritability and Dysregulation of Emotion Scale (TIDES-13). European child &amp; adolescent psychiatry, 1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong, Y., &amp; Peng, C. Y. J. (2013). Principled missing data methods for researchers. SpringerPlus, 2, 1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebesutani, C., Korathu-Larson, P., Nakamura, B. J., Higa-McMillan, C., &amp; Chorpita, B. (2017). The revised child anxiety and depression scale 25–parent version: Scale development and validation in a school-based and clinical sample. Assessment, 24(6), 712–728.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26834091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EQAO (2022). Student Demographic Data and Questionnarie Responses. https://www.eqao.com/student-demographic-responses/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faught, E., Qian, W., Carson, V., Storey, K., Faulkner, G., Veugelers, P., &amp; Leatherdale, S. (2019). The longitudinal impact of diet, physical activity, sleep, and screen time on Canadian adolescents’ academic achievement: An analysis from the COMPASS study. Preventive Medicine, 125, 24–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31108133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzpatrick, C., &amp; Boers, E. (2022). Developmental associations between media use and adolescent prosocial behavior. Health Education &amp; Behavior, 49(2), 265–271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fong, C. J. (2022). Academic motivation in a pandemic context: A conceptual review of prominent theories and an integrative model. Educational Psychology, 42(10), 1204–1222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francés, L., Quintero, J., Fernández, A., Ruiz, A., Caules, J., Fillon, G., Hervás, A., &amp; Soler, C. V. (2022). Current state of knowledge on the prevalence of neurodevelopmental disorders in childhood according to the DSM-5: A systematic review in accordance with the PRISMA criteria. Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Mental Health, 16(1), 27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35361232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8973738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fredricks, J. A., Blumenfeld, P., Friedel, J., &amp; Paris, A. (2005). School engagement. What do children need to flourish? Conceptualizing and measuring indicators of positive development, 305–321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green, J., Liem, G. A. D., Martin, A. J., Colmar, S., Marsh, H. W., &amp; McInerney, D. (2012). Academic motivation, self-concept, engagement, and performance in high school: Key processes from a longitudinal perspective. Journal of Adolescence, 35(5), 1111–1122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22460236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green, C. D., Thornton, K., Fredrick, J. W., Wiggs, K. K., Smith, Z. R., Langberg, J. M., &amp; Becker, S. P. (2023). Longitudinal Evaluation of School Climate in Predicting Mood and Academic Functioning in Adolescence: The role of academic motivation. School Mental Health, 15(4), 1033–1048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, J., Tang, X., Marsh, H. W., Parker, P., Basarkod, G., Sahdra, B., Ranta, M., &amp; Salmela-Aro, K. (2022). The roles of social–emotional skills in students’ academic and life success: A multi-informant and multicohort perspective. Journal of personality and social psychology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris, P. A., Taylor, R., Thielke, R., Payne, J., Gonzalez, N., &amp; Conde, J. G. (2009). Research electronic data capture (REDCap)—a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. Journal of Biomedical Informatics, 42(2), 377–381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18929686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedderson, M. M., Bekelman, T. A., Li, M., Knapp, E. A., Palmore, M., Dong, Y., Elliott, A. J., Friedman, C., Galarce, M., &amp; Gilbert-Diamond, D. (2023). Trends in screen time use among children during the COVID-19 pandemic, July 2019 through August 2021. JAMA Network open, 6(2), e2256157–e2256157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36790805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9932850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendren, R. L., Haft, S. L., Black, J. M., White, N. C., &amp; Hoeft, F. (2018). Recognizing psychiatric comorbidity with reading disorders. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 9, 101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, L., &amp; Bentler, P. M. (1999). Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives. Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal, 6(1), 1–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, A., Lee, E. Y., &amp; Horwood, S. (2022). Adolescent screen time: Associations with school stress and school satisfaction across 38 countries. European Journal of Pediatrics, 181(6), 2273–2281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35211815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8869349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klootwijk, C. L., Koele, I. J., van Hoorn, J., Güroğlu, B., &amp; van Duijvenvoorde, A. C. (2021). Parental support and positive mood buffer adolescents’ academic motivation during the COVID-19 pandemic. Journal of Research on Adolescence, 31(3), 780–795.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34448292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8456955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korczak, D. J., Cost, K. T., LaForge-MacKenzie, K., Anagnostou, E., Birken, C. S., Charach, A.,... &amp; Crosbie, J. (2022). Ontario COVID-19 and Kids Mental Health Study: A study protocol for the longitudinal prospective evaluation of the impact of emergency measures on child and adolescent mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMJ Open, 12(3), e057248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korpershoek, H., Canrinus, E. T., Fokkens-Bruinsma, M., &amp; de Boer, H. (2020). The relationships between school belonging and students’ motivational, social-emotional, behavioural, and academic outcomes in secondary education: A meta-analytic review. Research Papers in Education, 35(6), 641–680.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LaForge-MacKenzie, K., Cost, K. T., Tsujimoto, K. C., Crosbie, J., Charach, A., Anagnostou, E., Birken, C. S., Monga, S., Kelley, E., &amp; Burton, C. L. (2022). Participating in extracurricular activities and school sports during the COVID-19 pandemic: Associations with child and youth mental health. Frontiers in Sports and Active Living, 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewin, A., Brondeel, R., Benmarhnia, T., Thomas, F., &amp; Chaix, B. (2018). Attrition bias related to missing outcome data: A longitudinal simulation study. Epidemiology (Cambridge, Mass.), 29(1), 87–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28926372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, C. H. (2021). Statistical estimation of structural equation models with a mixture of continuous and categorical observed variables. Behavior Research Methods, 53(5), 2191–2213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33791955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Vanderloo, L. M., Keown-Stoneman, C. D., Cost, K. T., Charach, A., Maguire, J. L., Monga, S., Crosbie, J., Burton, C., &amp; Anagnostou, E. (2021). Screen use and mental health symptoms in Canadian children and youth during the CoViD-19 pandemic. JAMA Network open, 4(12), e2140875–e2140875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34962557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8715351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim, A. J. M., &amp; Cheung, M. W. L. (2022). Evaluating FIML and multiple imputation in joint ordinal-continuous measurements models with missing data. Behavior Research Methods, 54(3), 1063–1077.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loades, M. E., Chatburn, E., Higson-Sweeney, N., Reynolds, S., Shafran, R., Brigden, A., Linney, C., McManus, M. N., Borwick, C., &amp; Crawley, E. (2020). Rapid systematic review: The impact of social isolation and loneliness on the mental health of children and adolescents in the context of COVID-19. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, 59(11), 1218–1239. e1213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madigan, S., McArthur, B. A., Anhorn, C., Eirich, R., &amp; Christakis, D. A. (2020). Associations between screen use and child language skills: A systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatrics, 174(7), 665–675.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32202633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madigan, S., Eirich, R., Pador, P., McArthur, B. A., &amp; Neville, R. D. (2022). Assessment of changes in child and adolescent screen time during the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatrics. 176(12), 1188–1198. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2022.4116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madley-Dowd, P., Hughes, R., Tilling, K., &amp; Heron, J. (2019). The proportion of missing data should not be used to guide decisions on multiple imputation. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology, 110, 63–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30878639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6547017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin, F., Xie, K., &amp; Bolliger, D. U. (2022). Engaging learners in the emergency transition to online learning during the COVID-19 pandemic (Vol. 54, pp. S1–S). Taylor &amp; Francis. 13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBreen, M., &amp; Savage, R. (2021). The impact of motivational reading instruction on the reading achievement and motivation of students: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Educational Psychology Review, 33, 1125–1163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra, S., &amp; Khare, D. (2014). On comparative performance of multiple imputation methods for moderate to large proportions of missing data in clinical trials: A simulation study. J Med Stat Inform, 2(1), 9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muthén, B. (2005). Negative Residual Variance. http://www.statmodel.com/discussion/messages/11/555.html?1358188287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muthén, L. K., &amp; Muthén, B. O. (1998–2017). Mplus User’s Guide (Eigth Edition ed.). Muthén &amp; Muthén.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neel, C. G. O., &amp; Fuligni, A. (2013). A longitudinal study of school belonging and academic motivation across high school. Child Development, 84(2), 678–692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23002809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikolaidis, A., Paksarian, D., Alexander, L., Derosa, J., Dunn, J., Nielson, D. M., Droney, I., Kang, M., Douka, I., &amp; Bromet, E. (2021). The Coronavirus Health and Impact Survey (CRISIS) reveals reproducible correlates of pandemic-related mood states across the Atlantic. Scientific Reports, 11(1), 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Reilly, M., Svirydzenka, N., Adams, S., &amp; Dogra, N. (2018). Review of mental health promotion interventions in schools. Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology, 53, 647–662.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29752493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6003977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberle, E., Ji, X. R., Guhn, M., Schonert-Reichl, K. A., &amp; Gadermann, A. M. (2019). Benefits of extracurricular participation in early adolescence: Associations with peer belonging and mental health. Journal of Youth and Adolescence, 48(11), 2255–2270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31440881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberle, E., Ji, X. R., Kerai, S., Guhn, M., Schonert-Reichl, K. A., &amp; Gadermann, A. M. (2020). Screen time and extracurricular activities as risk and protective factors for mental health in adolescence: A population-level study. Preventive Medicine, 141, 106291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, C., Tsujimoto, K. C., Tombeau-Cost, K., Anagnostou, E., Birken, C. S., Charach, A., Monga, S., Kelley, E., Nicolson, R., Georgiadis, S., Burton, C. L., Crosbie, J., &amp; Korczak, D. J. (2023). The distinction between social connectedness and support when examining depression among children and youth during the COVID-19 pandemic. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10578-023-01616-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patalay, P., &amp; Fitzsimons, E. (2018). Development and predictors of mental ill-health and wellbeing from childhood to adolescence. Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology, 53(12), 1311–1323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30259056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rombach, I., Gray, A. M., Jenkinson, C., Murray, D. W., &amp; Rivero-Arias, O. (2018). Multiple imputation for patient reported outcome measures in randomised controlled trials: Advantages and disadvantages of imputing at the item, subscale or composite score level. BMC Medical Research Methodology, 18, 1–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roulin, N., &amp; Bangerter, A. (2013). Extracurricular activities in young applicants’ résumés: What are the motives behind their involvement? International Journal of Psychology, 48(5), 871–880.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22823060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salway, R., Walker, R., Sansum, K., House, D., Emm-Collison, L., Reid, T.,... &amp; Jago, R. (2023). Screen-viewing behaviours of children before and after the 2020–21 COVID-19 lockdowns in the UK: a mixed methods study. BMC Public Health, 23(1), 116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, R. M. S., Mendes, C. G., Miranda, M., D., &amp; Romano-Silva, M. A. (2022). The association between screen time and attention in children: A systematic review. Developmental Neuropsychology, 47(4), 175–192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35430923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selwyn, N., &amp; Aagaard, J. (2021). Banning mobile phones from classrooms—An opportunity to advance understandings of technology addiction, distraction and cyberbullying. British Journal of Educational Technology, 52(1), 8–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shochet, I. M., Dadds, M. R., Ham, D., &amp; Montague, R. (2006). School connectedness is an underemphasized parameter in adolescent mental health: Results of a community prediction study. Journal of Clinical Child &amp; Adolescent Psychology, 35(2), 170–179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skinner, E. A., &amp; Belmont, M. J. (1993). Motivation in the classroom: Reciprocal effects of teacher behavior and student engagement across the school year. Journal of Educational Psychology, 85(4), 571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, M. L., Mann, M. J., Georgieva, Z., Curtis, R., &amp; Schimmel, C. J. (2016). What counts when it comes to school enjoyment and aspiration in the middle grades. RMLE Online, 39(8), 1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29098057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5663305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, J., Guimond, F. A., Bergeron, J., St-Amand, J., Fitzpatrick, C., &amp; Gagnon, M. (2021). Changes in students’ achievement motivation in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic: A function of extraversion/introversion? Education Sciences, 11(1), 30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steenweg, E. M., Dekkers, T., Doffer, D. P. A., van den Hoofdakker, B., Groenman, A., &amp; Luman, M. (2024). School-based interventions for children with behavioral difficulties. The Lack of an Evidence-Base.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stewart, S. L., Klassen, J., &amp; Hamza, C. (2016). Emerging mental health diagnoses and school disruption: An examination among clinically referred children and youth. Exceptionality Education International, 26(2).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swanson, J. M., Schuck, S., Porter, M. M., Carlson, C., Hartman, C. A., Sergeant, J. A., Clevenger, W., Wasdell, M., McCleary, R., &amp; Lakes, K. (2012). Categorical and dimensional definitions and evaluations of symptoms of ADHD: History of the SNAP and the SWAN rating scales. The International Journal of Educational and Psychological Assessment, 10(1), 51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26504617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4618695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsujimoto, K. C., Cost, K. T., LaForge-MacKenzie, K., Anagnostou, E., Birken, C. S., Charach, A., Monga, S., Kelley, E., Nicolson, R., Georgiadis, S., Lee, N., Osokin, K., Arnold, P., Schachar, R., Burton, C., Crosbie, J., &amp; Korczak, D. J. (2022). School and learning contexts during the COVID-19 pandemic: Implications for child and youth mental health. Current Psychology. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12144-022-03941-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12144-022-03941-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36468159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsujimoto, K. C., Cost, K. T., Laforge-Mackenzie, K., Anagnostou, E., Birken, C. S., Charach, A., Monga, S., Kelley, E., Nicolson, R., &amp; Georgiadis, S. (2023). Disruption to Education during COVID-19: School nonacademic factors are Associated with Children’s Mental Health. Journal of Developmental &amp; Behavioral Pediatrics, 44(2), e95–e103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaillancourt, T., McDougall, P., Comeau, J., &amp; Finn, C. (2021). COVID-19 school closures and social isolation in children and youth: Prioritizing relationships in education. In (Vol. 6, pp. 1795–1813): Canadian Science Publishing 1840 Woodward Drive, Suite 1, Ottawa, ON K2C 0P7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Ryzin, M. J., Gravely, A. A., &amp; Roseth, C. J. (2009). Autonomy, belongingness, and engagement in school as contributors to adolescent psychological well-being. Journal of Youth and Adolescence, 38, 1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19636787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Simson, K., Brekke, I., &amp; Hardoy, I. (2022). The impact of mental health problems in adolescence on educational attainment. Scandinavian Journal of Educational Research, 66(2), 306–320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M. T., &amp; Peck, S. C. (2013). Adolescent educational success and mental health vary across school engagement profiles. Developmental Psychology, 49(7), 1266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23066673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whiting, E. F., Everson, K. C., &amp; Feinauer, E. (2018). The simple school belonging scale: Working toward a unidimensional measure of student belonging. Measurement and Evaluation in Counseling and Development, 51(3), 163–178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaccoletti, S., Camacho, A., Correia, N., Aguiar, C., Mason, L., Alves, R. A., &amp; Daniel, J. R. (2020). Parents’ perceptions of student academic motivation during the COVID-19 lockdown: A cross-country comparison. Frontiers in Psychology, 11, 592670.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33391114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7775314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zendarski, N., Mensah, F., Hiscock, H., &amp; Sciberras, E. (2021). Trajectories of emotional and conduct problems and their association with early high school achievement and engagement for adolescents with ADHD. Journal of Attention Disorders, 25(5), 623–635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30832528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>