<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39387558</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-5336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied and environmental microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Environ Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multisite community-scale monitoring of respiratory and enteric viruses in the effluent of a nursing home and in the inlet of the local wastewater treatment plant.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0115824</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0115824</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/aem.01158-24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The aim of this study was to evaluate whether community-level monitoring of respiratory and enteric viruses in wastewater can provide a comprehensive picture of local virus circulation. Wastewater samples were collected weekly at the wastewater treatment plant (WWTP) inlet and at the outlet of a nearby nursing home (NH) in Burgundy, France, during the winter period of 2022/2023. We searched for the pepper mild mottle virus as an indicator of fecal content as well as for the main respiratory viruses [severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), influenza, and respiratory syncytial virus] and enteric viruses (rotavirus, sapovirus, norovirus, astrovirus, and adenovirus). Samples were analyzed using real-time reverse transcription PCR-based methods. SARS-CoV-2 was the most frequently detected respiratory virus, with 66.7% of positive samples from the WWTP and 28.6% from the NH. Peaks of SARS-CoV-2 were consistent with the chronological incidence of infections recorded in the sentinel surveillance and the nearby hospital databases. The number of positive samples was lower in the NH than in WWTP for the three respiratory viruses. Enteric viruses were frequently detected, most often sapovirus and norovirus genogroup II, accounting both for 77.8% of positive samples in the WWTP and 57.1% and 37%, respectively, in the NH. The large circulation of sapovirus was unexpected in particular in the NH. Combined wastewater surveillance using simple optimized methods can be a valuable tool for monitoring viral circulation and may serve as a suitable early warning system for identifying both local outbreaks and the onset of epidemics. These results encourage the application of wastewater-based surveillance (WBS) to SARS-CoV2, norovirus, and sapovirus.IMPORTANCEWBS provides valuable information on the spread of epidemic viruses in the environment using appropriate and sensitive detection methods. By monitoring the circulation of viruses using reverse transcription PCR methods in wastewater from the inlet of a wastewater treatment plant and the outlet of a nearby retirement home (connected to the same collective sewer network), we aimed to demonstrate that implementing combined WBS at key community sites allows effective detection of the occurrence of respiratory (influenza, respiratory syncytial virus, and SARS-CoV-2) and enteric (norovirus, rotavirus, and sapovirus) virus infections within a given population. This analysis on a localized scale provided new information on the viral circulation in the two different sites. Implementing WBS to monitor the circulation or the emergence of infectious diseases is an important means of alerting the authorities and improving public health management. WBS could participate actively to the health of humans, animals, and the environment.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manoha</LastName><ForeName>Catherine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3934-6132</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology, University Hospital of Dijon Bourgogne, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dequiedt</LastName><ForeName>Anne-Laure</ForeName><Initials>A-L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departmental Laboratory of Côte d'Or, Departmental Council of Côte-d'Or, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thery</LastName><ForeName>Lucie</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Reference Centre for Gastroenteritis Viruses, University Hospital of Dijon Bourgogne, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marotel</LastName><ForeName>Marina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departmental Laboratory of Côte d'Or, Departmental Council of Côte-d'Or, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pez</LastName><ForeName>Floriane</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>BioSellal S.A., Dardilly, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vouillon</LastName><ForeName>Bruno</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departmental Laboratory of Côte d'Or, Departmental Council of Côte-d'Or, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gueneau</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departmental Laboratory of Côte d'Or, Departmental Council of Côte-d'Or, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Rougemont</LastName><ForeName>Alexis</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3084-9414</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology, University Hospital of Dijon Bourgogne, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Reference Centre for Gastroenteritis Viruses, University Hospital of Dijon Bourgogne, Dijon, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Environ Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7605801</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0099-2240</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">monitoring</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">norovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nursing home</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sapovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">wastewater treatment plant</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">wastewater-based surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39387558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01158-24</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>