<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39380309</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1478-5153</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nursing in critical care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nurs Crit Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prone position applied to COVID-19 patients: Systematic review-meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/nicc.13185</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Position change and interventions to increase lung capacity should be considered in mechanically ventilated patients. The most effective of these is the prone position.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This systematic review and meta-analysis aimed to determine the effects of the prone position on respiratory parameters and outcomes and to guide nurses working in the intensive care unit.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY DESIGN AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This systematic review-meta-analysis was conducted in accordance with the Preferred Reporting in Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses guideline. ScienceDirect, CINAHL, Academic Search Complete (EBSCOhost), MEDLINE, EMBASE, Web of Science, Cochrane and PubMed databases were searched between January 2022 and January 2023 to access studies related to prone position in COVID-19 patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Twenty-three studies were included. This meta-analysis shows that a prone position is feasible and can achieve improvements in gas exchange. Prone position increases PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> in the majority of patients followed with a diagnosis of COVID-19 and severe hypoxemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The study has shown that the prone position is effective in improving patients' respiratory function and oxygenation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RELEVANCE TO CLINICAL PRACTICE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The results presented in this article support the notion that the prone position can be an effective strategy in the clinical management of COVID-19 patients.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 British Association of Critical Care Nurses.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tülüce</LastName><ForeName>Derya</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1340-013X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, Faculty of Health Sciences, Osmaniye Korkut Ata University, Osmaniye, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaplan Serin</LastName><ForeName>Emine</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7327-9167</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine Nursing, Faculty of Nursing, Mersin University, Mersin, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yıldız Karadeniz</LastName><ForeName>Ebru</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9327-0653</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Fundamentals of Nursing, Faculty of Nursing, Mersin University, Mersin, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Nurs Crit Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9808649</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1362-1017</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ICU nurse</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intensive care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mechanical ventilation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">patient outcomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prone</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39380309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nicc.13185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Keşkek Ş, Erdoğan H. COVID‐19: a current brief review. Acta Medica Alanya. 2020;4(2):197‐202. doi:10.30565/medalanya.747238</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Accessed 05 June 2023. 2020 https://www.who.int/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-similarities-and-differences-with-influenza</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID‐19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72 314 cases from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. JAMA. 2020;323(13):1239‐1242. doi:10.1001/jama.2020.2648</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayoğlu H. Intensive care approach in COVID‐19 patients. Turk J Diab Obes. 2020;2:183‐193. doi:10.25048/tudod.767999</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özbilen F, Altunkan AA. COVID‐19 ve Uyanık Pron Pozisyon. Turk J Intensive Care. 2020;18:50‐56. doi:10.4274/tybd.galenos.2020.51422</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yalçın A. COVID‐19 Sürecinde Yoğun Bakım Yönetimi. Med Res Rep. 2020;3(Özel Sayı):66‐85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gattinoni L, Coppola S, Cressoni M, Busana M, Rossi S, Chiumello D. COVID‐19 does not lead to a “typical” acute respiratory distress syndrome. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2020;201(10):1299‐1300. doi:10.1164/rccm.202003‐0817LE</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çelik S. Mekanik ventilasyonda prone pozisyonunun yönetimi. Yoğun Bakım Hemşireliği Dergisi. 2018;22(2):80‐87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiruvoipati R, Bangash M, Manktelow B, Peek GJ. Efficacy of prone ventilation in adult patients with acute respiratory failure: a meta‐analysis. J Crit Care. 2008;23(1):101‐110. doi:10.1016/j.jcrc.2007.09.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venet C, Guyomarc'h S, Pingat J, et al. Prognostic factors in acute respiratory distress syndrome: a retrospective multivariate analysis including prone positioning in management strategy. Intensive Care Med. 2003;29(9):1435‐1441. doi:10.1007/s00134‐003‐1856‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coppadoro A, Foti G. Prone positioning in severe acute respiratory distress syndrome. 50 Studies every Intensivist Should Know. Oxford University Press; 2018:129‐134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taccone P, Pesenti A, Latini R, et al. Prone positioning in patients with moderate and severe acute respiratory distress syndrome: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2009;302(18):1977‐1984. doi:10.1001/jama.2009.1614</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koulouras V, Papathanakos G, Papathanasiou A, Nakos G. Efficacy of prone position in acute respiratory distress syndrome patients: a pathophysiology‐based review. World J Crit Care Med. 2016;5(2):121‐136. doi:10.5492/wjccm.v5.i2.121</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JM, Bae W, Lee YJ, Cho YJ. The efficacy and safety of prone positional ventilation in acute respiratory distress syndrome: updated study‐level meta‐analysis of 11 randomized controlled trials. Crit Care Med. 2014;42(5):1252‐1262. doi:10.1097/CCM.0000000000000122</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munshi L, Del Sorbo L, Adhikari NK, et al. Prone position for acute respiratory distress syndrome. A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2017;14(Supplement 4):S280‐S288. doi:10.1513/AnnalsATS.201704‐343OT</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kopterides P, Siempos II, Armaganidis A. Prone positioning in hypoxemic respiratory failure: meta‐analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Crit Care. 2009;24(1):89‐100. doi:10.1016/j.jcrc.2007.12.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong Sze LR. Evidence based guideline of prone positioning for adult patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome in ıntensive care unit. [Unpublished Master Thesis], Hong Kong:The University of Hong Kong. 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sud S, Sud M, Friedrich JO, Adhikari NK. Effect of mechanical ventilation in the prone position on clinical outcomes in patients with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. CMAJ. 2008;178(9):1153‐1161. doi:10.1503/cmaj.071802</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D, Jeon B, Son JS, Lee JR, Ko S, Lim H. The changes of endotracheal tube cuff pressure by the position changes from supine to prone and the flexion and extension of head. Korean J Anesthesiol. 2015;68(1):27‐31. doi:10.4097/kjae.2015.68.1.27</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. Int J Surg. 2021;88:105906.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Astua AJ, Michaels EK, Michaels AJ. Proning during pandemic: the rapid institution of a safe, transferable, and effective prone positioning program at Nychhc/Elmhurst hospital, a situationally resource limited facility, during the peak of the COVID 19 surge. Research Square. 2020. doi:10.21203/rs.3.rs‐29653/v1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berrill M. Evaluation of oxygenation in 129 proning sessions in 34 mechanically ventilated COVID‐19 patients. J Intensive Care Med. 2021;36(2):229‐232. doi:10.1177/08850666209551</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boselli E, Fatah A, Ledochowski S, Allaouchiche B. ANI and BIS variations in supine and prone position during closed‐tracheal suction in sedated and myorelaxed ICU patients with severe COVID‐19: a retrospective study. J Clin Monit Comput. 2021;35(6):1403‐1409. doi:10.1007/s10877‐020‐00612‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burton‐Papp HC, Jackson AIR, Beecham R, et al. Conscious prone positioning during non‐invasive ventilation in COVID‐19 patients: experience from a single centre. F1000Research. 2020;31(9):859. doi:10.12688/f1000research.25384.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caputo ND, Strayer RJ, Levitan R. Early self‐proning in awake, non‐intubated patients in the emergency department: a single ED's experience during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Acad Emerg Med. 2020;27(5):375‐378. doi:10.1111/acem.13994</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coppo A, Bellani G, Winterton D, et al. Feasibility and physiological effects of prone positioning in non‐intubated patients with acute respiratory failure due to COVID‐19 (PRON‐COVID): a prospective cohort study. Lancet Respir Med. 2020;8(8):765‐774. doi:10.1016/S2213‐2600(20)30268‐X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubosh NM, Wong ML, Grossestreuer AV, et al. Early, awake proning in emergency department patients with COVID‐19. Am J Emerg Med. 2021;46:640‐645. doi:10.1016/j.ajem.2020.11.074</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrando C, Mellado‐Artigas R, Gea A, et al. Awake prone positioning does not reduce the risk of intubation in COVID‐19 treated with high‐flow nasal oxygen therapy: a multicenter, adjusted cohort study. Crit Care. 2020;24:1‐11. doi:10.1186/s13054‐020‐03314‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gleissman H, Forsgren A, Andersson E, et al. Prone positioning in mechanically ventilated patients with severe acute respiratory distress syndrome and coronavirus disease 2019. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2021;65(3):360‐363. doi:10.1111/aas.13741</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hallifax RJ, Porter BM, Elder PJ, et al. Successful awake proning is associated with improved clinical outcomes in patients with COVID‐19: single‐centre high‐dependency unit experience. BMJ Open Respir Res. 2020;7(1):e000678. doi:10.1136/bmjresp‐2020‐000678</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagan N, Morrow LE, Walters RW, et al. The positioned study: prone positioning in nonventilated coronavirus disease 2019 patients—a retrospective analysis. Crit Care Explor. 2020;2(10):e0229. doi:10.1097/CCE.0000000000000229</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly NL, Curtis A, Douthwaite S, et al. Effect of awake prone positioning in hypoxaemic adult patients with COVID‐19.J Intensive Care Soc. 2023;24:32‐34. doi:10.1177/1751143720961244</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kharat A, Dupuis‐Lozeron E, Cantero C, et al. Self‐proning in COVID‐19 patients on low‐flow oxygen therapy: a cluster randomised controlled trial. ERJ Open Res. 2021;7(1):00692‐2020. doi:10.1183/23120541.00692‐2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu K, Zhang W, Yang Y, Zhang J, Li Y, Chen Y. Respiratory rehabilitation in elderly patients with COVID‐19: a randomized controlled study. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2020;39:101166. doi:10.1016/j.ctcp.2020.101166</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mittermaier M, Pickerodt P, Kurth F, et al. Evaluation of PEEP and prone positioning in early COVID‐19 ARDS. EClinicalMedicine. 2020;28:100579. doi:10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100579</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padrao EM, Valente FS, Besen BA, et al. Awake prone positioning in COVID‐19 hypoxemic respiratory failure: exploratory findings in a single‐center retrospective cohort study. Acad Emerg Med. 2020;27(12):1249‐1259. doi:10.1111/acem.14160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perier F, Tuffet S, Maraffi T, et al. Effect of positive end‐expiratory pressure and proning on ventilation and perfusion in COVID‐19 acute respiratory distress syndrome. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2020;202(12):1713‐1717. doi:10.1164/rccm.202008‐3058LE</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Şan İ, Yıldırım Ç, Bekgöz B, Gemcioğlu E. Transport of awake hypoxemic probable COVID 19 patients in the prone position. Am J Emerg Med. 2021;46:420‐423. doi:10.1016/j.ajem.2020.10.036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimazu H, Yoshiya K, Maruyama S, et al. The efficacy of combination therapies including antiviral drugs, methylprednisolone and daily proning in 20 patients with COVID‐19 requiring invasive mechanical ventilation‐case series in a single critical care center in Osaka, Japan. Arch Clin Med Case Rep. 2020;4(5):867‐882. doi:10.26502/acmcr.96550274</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solverson K, Weatherald J, Parhar KKS. Tolerability and safety of awake prone positioning COVID‐19 patients with severe hypoxemic respiratory failure. Can J Anaesth. 2021;68(1):64‐70. doi:10.1007/s12630‐020‐01787‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss TT, Cerda F, Scott JB, et al. Prone positioning for patients intubated for severe acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) secondary to COVID‐19: a retrospective observational cohort study. Br J Anaesth. 2021;126(1):48‐55. doi:10.1016/j.bja.2020.09.042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wormser J, Romanet C, Philippart F. Prone position in wards for spontaneous breathing COVID‐19 patients: a retrospective study. Ir J Med Sci. 2021;190(4):1519‐1522. doi:10.1007/s11845‐020‐02479‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winearls S, Swingwood EL, Hardaker CL, et al. Early conscious prone positioning in patients with COVID‐19 receiving continuous positive airway pressure: a retrospective analysis. BMJ Open Respir Res. 2020;7(1):e000711. doi:10.1136/bmjresp‐2020‐000711</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins JP, Thomas J, Chandler J, et al., eds. Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions. John Wiley &amp; Sons; 2019. doi:10.1002/9781119536604</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thalheimer W, Cook S. How to calculate effect sizes from published research: a simplified methodology. Work‐Learn Res. 2002;1(9):1‐9. www.work-learning.com/effect_sizes.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen N, Zhou M, Dong X, et al. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a descriptive study. Lancet. 2020;395(10223):507‐513. doi:10.1016/S0140‐6736(20)30211‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghelichkhani P, Esmaeili M. Prone position in management of COVID‐19 patients; a commentary. Arch Acad Emerg Med. 2020;8(1):e48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua EX, Zahir SMISM, Ng KT, et al. Effect of prone versus supine position in COVID‐19 patients: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. J Clin Anesth. 2021;74:110406. doi:10.1016/j.jclinane.2021.110406</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarantonello F, Andreatta G, Sella N, Navalesi P. Prone position and lung ventilation and perfusion matching in acute respiratory failure due to COVID‐19. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2020;202(2):278‐279. doi:10.1164/rccm.202003‐0775IM</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kallet RH. A comprehensive review of prone position in ARDS. Respir Care. 2015;60(11):1660‐1687. doi:10.4187/respcare.04271</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heldeweg MLA, Mousa A, Van Ekeren J, et al. Lung ultrasound to predict gas‐exchange response to prone positioning in COVID‐19 patients: a prospective study in pilot and confirmation cohorts. J Crit Care. 2023;73:154173. doi:10.1016/j.jcrc.2022.154173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zang X, Wang Q, Zhou H, et al. Efficacy of early prone positionfor COVID‐19 patients with severe hypoxia: a single‐centerprospective cohort study. Intensive Care Med. 2020;46:1927‐1929. doi:10.1007/s00134‐020‐06182‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gattinoni L, Tognoni G, Pesenti A, et al. Effect of prone positioning on the survival of patients with acute respiratory failure. N Engl J Med. 2001;345(8):568‐573. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa010043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okin D, Huang CY, Alba GA, et al. Prolonged prone position ventilation is associated with reduced mortality in intubated COVID‐19 patients. Chest. 2023;163(3):533‐542. doi:10.1016/j.chest.2022.10.034</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavlov I, He H, McNicholas B, et al. Awake prone positioning in non‐intubated patients with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure due to COVID‐19. Respir Care. 2022;67(1):102‐114. doi:10.4187/respcare.09191</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>