<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39388246</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2563-3570</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>5</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JMIR bioinformatics and biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JMIR Bioinform Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of the Neutralization Power of Sotrovimab Against SARS-CoV-2 Variants: Development of a Rapid Computational Method.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e58018</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e58018</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e58018</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2196/58018</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The rapid evolution of SARS-CoV-2 imposed a huge challenge on disease control. Immune evasion caused by genetic variations of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein's immunogenic epitopes affects the efficiency of monoclonal antibody-based therapy of COVID-19. Therefore, a rapid method is needed to evaluate the efficacy of the available monoclonal antibodies against the new emerging variants or potential novel variants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The aim of this study is to develop a rapid computational method to evaluate the neutralization power of anti-SARS-CoV-2 monoclonal antibodies against new SARS-CoV-2 variants and other potential new mutations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The amino acid sequence of the extracellular domain of the spike proteins of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (GenBank accession number YP_009825051.1) and SARS-CoV-2 (GenBank accession number YP_009724390.1) were used to create computational 3D models for the native spike proteins. Specific mutations were introduced to the curated sequence to generate the different variant spike models. The neutralization potential of sotrovimab (S309) against these variants was evaluated based on its molecular interactions and Gibbs free energy in comparison to a reference model after molecular replacement of the reference receptor-binding domain with the variant's receptor-binding domain.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Our results show a loss in the binding affinity of the neutralizing antibody S309 with both SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2. The binding affinity of S309 was greater to the Alpha, Beta, Gamma, and Kappa variants than to the original Wuhan strain of SARS-CoV-2. However, S309 showed a substantially decreased binding affinity to the Delta and Omicron variants. Based on the mutational profile of Omicron subvariants, our data describe the effect of the G339H and G339D mutations and their role in escaping antibody neutralization, which is in line with published clinical reports.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This method is rapid, applicable, and of interest to adapt the use of therapeutic antibodies to the treatment of emerging variants. It could be applied to antibody-based treatment of other viral infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©Dana Ashoor, Maryam Marzouq, M-Dahmani Fathallah. Originally published in JMIR Bioinformatics and Biotechnology (https://bioinform.jmir.org), 10.10.2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashoor</LastName><ForeName>Dana</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0376-6859</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, Health Biotechnology Program - King Fahad Chair for Health Biotechnology, College of Graduate Studies, Arabian Gulf University, Manama, Bahrain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marzouq</LastName><ForeName>Maryam</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9881-0412</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, Health Biotechnology Program - King Fahad Chair for Health Biotechnology, College of Graduate Studies, Arabian Gulf University, Manama, Bahrain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fathallah</LastName><ForeName>M-Dahmani</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8834-7460</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, Health Biotechnology Program - King Fahad Chair for Health Biotechnology, College of Graduate Studies, Arabian Gulf University, Manama, Bahrain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Canada</Country><MedlineTA>JMIR Bioinform Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101769661</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2563-3570</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Omicron</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">S309</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sotrovimab</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">amino acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anti–SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">computational method</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">in silico</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">monoclonal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mutation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neutralizing antibody</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">protein</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">subvariants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">variants</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of Interest: None declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39388246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11502979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/58018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">v5i1e58018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>van Dorp L, Acman M, Richard D, Shaw LP, Ford CE, Ormond L, Owen CJ, Pang J, Tan CC, Boshier FA, Ortiz AT, Balloux F. Emergence of genomic diversity and recurrent mutations in SARS-CoV-2. Infect Genet Evol. 2020 Sep;83:104351. doi: 10.1016/j.meegid.2020.104351. 
 
S1567-1348(20)30182-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2020.104351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7199730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32387564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amicone M, Borges Vítor, Alves Maria João, Isidro Joana, Zé-Zé Líbia, Duarte Sílvia, Vieira Luís, Guiomar Raquel, Gomes João Paulo, Gordo Isabel. Mutation rate of SARS-CoV-2 and emergence of mutators during experimental evolution. Evol Med Public Health. 2022;10(1):142–155. doi: 10.1093/emph/eoac010. 
 
eoac010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/emph/eoac010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8996265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35419205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Focosi D, Quiroga R, McConnell S, Johnson MC, Casadevall A. Convergent evolution in SARS-CoV-2 spike creates a variant soup from which new COVID-19 waves emerge. Int J Mol Sci. 2023 Jan 23;24(3):2264. doi: 10.3390/ijms24032264. 
 
ijms24032264</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms24032264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9917121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36768588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emergency Use Authorization. Food and Drug Administration.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/mcm-legal-regulatory-and-policy-framework/emergency-use-authorization#coviddrugs
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 medicines. European Medicines Agency.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/human-regulatory/overview/public-health-threats/coronavirus-disease-covid-19/treatments-vaccines/covid-19-treatments
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hastie KM, Li H, Bedinger D, Schendel SL, Dennison SM, Li K, Rayaprolu V, Yu X, Mann C, Zandonatti M, Diaz Avalos R, Zyla D, Buck T, Hui S, Shaffer K, Hariharan C, Yin J, Olmedillas E, Enriquez A, Parekh D, Abraha M, Feeney E, Horn GQ, CoVIC-DB team1. Aldon Yoann, Ali Hanif, Aracic Sanja, Cobb Ronald R, Federman Ross S, Fernandez Joseph M, Glanville Jacob, Green Robin, Grigoryan Gevorg, Lujan Hernandez Ana G, Ho David D, Huang Kuan-Ying A, Ingraham John, Jiang Weidong, Kellam Paul, Kim M, Kim HM, Kim Hyeong Mi, Kong Chao, Krebs Shelly J, Lan Fei, Lang Guojun, Lee Sooyoung, Leung Cheuk Lun, Liu Junli, Lu Yanan, MacCamy Anna, McGuire Andrew T, Palser Anne L, Rabbitts Terence H, Rikhtegaran Tehrani Zahra, Sajadi Mohammad M, Sanders Rogier W, Sato Aaron K, Schweizer Liang, Seo Jimin, Shen Bingqing, Snitselaar Jonne L, Stamatatos Leonidas, Tan Yongcong, Tomic Milan T, van Gils Marit J, Youssef Sawsan, Yu Jian, Yuan Tom Z, Zhang Qian, Peters Bjoern, Tomaras Georgia D, Germann Timothy, Saphire Erica Ollmann. Defining variant-resistant epitopes targeted by SARS-CoV-2 antibodies: a global consortium study. Science. 2021 Oct 22;374(6566):472–478. doi: 10.1126/science.abh2315. 
 
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abh2315?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub0pubmed</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abh2315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9302186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34554826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mittal A, Khattri A, Verma V. Structural and antigenic variations in the spike protein of emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants. PLoS Pathog. 2022 Feb 17;18(2):e1010260. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1010260. 
 
PPATHOGENS-D-21-02162</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1010260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1010260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8853550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35176090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnes CO, Jette CA, Abernathy ME, Dam KA, Esswein SR, Gristick HB, Malyutin AG, Sharaf NG, Huey-Tubman KE, Lee YE, Robbiani DF, Nussenzweig MC, West AP, Bjorkman PJ. SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody structures inform therapeutic strategies. Nature. 2020 Dec 12;588(7839):682–687. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2852-1. 
 
10.1038/s41586-020-2852-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2852-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8092461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33045718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piccoli L, Park Young-Jun, Tortorici M Alejandra, Czudnochowski Nadine, Walls Alexandra C, Beltramello Martina, Silacci-Fregni Chiara, Pinto Dora, Rosen Laura E, Bowen John E, Acton Oliver J, Jaconi Stefano, Guarino Barbara, Minola Andrea, Zatta Fabrizia, Sprugasci Nicole, Bassi Jessica, Peter Alessia, De Marco Anna, Nix Jay C, Mele Federico, Jovic Sandra, Rodriguez Blanca Fernandez, Gupta Sneha V, Jin Feng, Piumatti Giovanni, Lo Presti Giorgia, Pellanda Alessandra Franzetti, Biggiogero Maira, Tarkowski Maciej, Pizzuto Matteo S, Cameroni Elisabetta, Havenar-Daughton Colin, Smithey Megan, Hong David, Lepori Valentino, Albanese Emiliano, Ceschi Alessandro, Bernasconi Enos, Elzi Luigia, Ferrari Paolo, Garzoni Christian, Riva Agostino, Snell Gyorgy, Sallusto Federica, Fink Katja, Virgin Herbert W, Lanzavecchia Antonio, Corti Davide, Veesler David. Mapping neutralizing and immunodominant sites on the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain by structure-guided high-resolution serology. Cell. 2020 Nov 12;183(4):1024–1042.e21. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2020.09.037. 
 
S0092-8674(20)31234-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.09.037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7494283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32991844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto D, Park Y, Beltramello M, Walls AC, Tortorici MA, Bianchi S, Jaconi S, Culap K, Zatta F, De Marco A, Peter A, Guarino B, Spreafico R, Cameroni E, Case JB, Chen RE, Havenar-Daughton C, Snell G, Telenti A, Virgin HW, Lanzavecchia A, Diamond MS, Fink K, Veesler D, Corti D. Cross-neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 by a human monoclonal SARS-CoV antibody. Nature. 2020 Jul 18;583(7815):290–295. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2349-y.10.1038/s41586-020-2349-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2349-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32422645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Karuppanan K, Subramaniam G. Omicron (BA.1) and sub-variants (BA.1.1, BA.2, and BA.3) of SARS-CoV-2 spike infectivity and pathogenicity: a comparative sequence and structural-based computational assessment. J Med Virol. 2022 Oct;94(10):4780–4791. doi: 10.1002/jmv.27927. 
 
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9347785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35680610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCallum M, Czudnochowski N, Rosen LE, Zepeda SK, Bowen JE, Walls AC, Hauser K, Joshi A, Stewart C, Dillen JR, Powell AE, Croll TI, Nix J, Virgin HW, Corti D, Snell G, Veesler D. Structural basis of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron immune evasion and receptor engagement. Science. 2022 Feb 25;375(6583):864–868. doi: 10.1126/science.abn8652. 
 
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abn8652?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub0pubmed</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abn8652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9427005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35076256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heo Y. Sotrovimab: first approval. Drugs. 2022 Mar 14;82(4):477–484. doi: 10.1007/s40265-022-01690-7. 
 
10.1007/s40265-022-01690-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40265-022-01690-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8919156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35286623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashoor D, Ben Khalaf N, Marzouq M, Jarjanazi H, Chlif S, Fathallah MD. A computational approach to evaluate the combined effect of SARS-CoV-2 RBD mutations and ACE2 receptor genetic variants on infectivity: the COVID-19 host-pathogen nexus. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2021 Aug 9;11:707194. doi: 10.3389/fcimb.2021.707194. 
 
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.707194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8381355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34434902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Z, Zhou J, Tian M, Huang M, Liu S, Xie Y, Han P, Bai C, Han P, Zheng A, Fu L, Gao Y, Peng Q, Li Y, Chai Y, Zhang Z, Zhao X, Song H, Qi J, Wang Q, Wang P, Gao GF. Omicron SARS-CoV-2 mutations stabilize spike up-RBD conformation and lead to a non-RBM-binding monoclonal antibody escape. Nat Commun. 2022 Aug 24;13(1):4958. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-32665-7. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-32665-7.10.1038/s41467-022-32665-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-32665-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-32665-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9399999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36002453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv Z, Deng Y, Ye Q, Cao L, Sun C, Fan C, Huang W, Sun S, Sun Y, Zhu L, Chen Q, Wang N, Nie J, Cui Z, Zhu D, Shaw N, Li X, Li Q, Xie L, Wang Y, Rao Z, Qin C, Wang X. Structural basis for neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV by a potent therapeutic antibody. Science. 2020 Sep 18;369(6510):1505–1509. doi: 10.1126/science.abc5881. 
 
science.abc5881</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abc5881?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub0pubmed</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abc5881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7402622</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32703908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta A, Gonzalez-Rojas Y, Juarez E, Crespo Casal M, Moya J, Falci DR, Sarkis E, Solis J, Zheng H, Scott N, Cathcart AL, Hebner CM, Sager J, Mogalian E, Tipple C, Peppercorn A, Alexander E, Pang PS, Free A, Brinson C, Aldinger M, Shapiro AE. Early treatment for Covid-19 with SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody sotrovimab. N Engl J Med. 2021 Nov 18;385(21):1941–1950. doi: 10.1056/nejmoa2107934.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/nejmoa2107934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34706189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta A, Gonzalez-Rojas Y, Juarez E, Crespo Casal M, Moya J, Rodrigues Falci D, Sarkis E, Solis J, Zheng H, Scott N, Cathcart AL, Parra S, Sager JE, Austin D, Peppercorn A, Alexander E, Yeh WW, Brinson C, Aldinger M, Shapiro AE, COMET-ICE Investigators  Effect of sotrovimab on hospitalization or death among high-risk patients with mild to moderate COVID-19: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2022 Apr 05;327(13):1236–1246. doi: 10.1001/jama.2022.2832. 
 
2790246</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.2832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8922199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35285853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashoor D, Marzouq M, Trabelsi K, Chlif S, Abotalib N, Khalaf NB, Ramadan AR, Fathallah M. How concerning is a SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern? Computational predictions and the variants labeling system. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2022 Aug 10;12:868205. doi: 10.3389/fcimb.2022.868205. 
 
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2022.868205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9399656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36034694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Protein Data Bank. RCSB.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://www.rcsb.org/
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hodcroft E. CoVariants. CoVariants.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://covariants.org/
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SARS-CoV-2 Variants. Stanford University: Coronavirus Antiviral &amp; Resistance Database.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://covdb.stanford.edu/variants/omicron_ba_1_3/
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waterhouse A, Bertoni Martino, Bienert Stefan, Studer Gabriel, Tauriello Gerardo, Gumienny Rafal, Heer Florian T, de Beer Tjaart A P, Rempfer Christine, Bordoli Lorenza, Lepore Rosalba, Schwede Torsten. SWISS-MODEL: homology modelling of protein structures and complexes. Nucleic Acids Res. 2018 Jul 02;46(W1):W296–W303. doi: 10.1093/nar/gky427. 
 
5000024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gky427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6030848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29788355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeLano W. The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System. PyMOL. 2002.  [2024-09-17].  
 http://www.pymol.org/
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song W, Gui M, Wang X, Xiang Y. Cryo-EM structure of the SARS coronavirus spike glycoprotein in complex with its host cell receptor ACE2. PLoS Pathog. 2018 Aug 13;14(8):e1007236. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1007236. 
 
PPATHOGENS-D-18-00336</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6107290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30102747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dejnirattisai W, Zhou D, Ginn HM, Duyvesteyn HME, Supasa P, Case JB, Zhao Y, Walter TS, Mentzer AJ, Liu C, Wang B, Paesen GC, Slon-Campos J, López-Camacho César, Kafai NM, Bailey AL, Chen RE, Ying B, Thompson C, Bolton J, Fyfe A, Gupta S, Tan TK, Gilbert-Jaramillo J, James W, Knight M, Carroll MW, Skelly D, Dold C, Peng Y, Levin R, Dong T, Pollard AJ, Knight JC, Klenerman P, Temperton N, Hall DR, Williams MA, Paterson NG, Bertram FKR, Siebert CA, Clare DK, Howe A, Radecke J, Song Y, Townsend AR, Huang KA, Fry EE, Mongkolsapaya J, Diamond MS, Ren J, Stuart DI, Screaton GR. The antigenic anatomy of SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain. Cell. 2021 Apr 15;184(8):2183–2200.e22. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.032. 
 
S0092-8674(21)00221-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7891125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33756110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mannar D, Saville JW, Sun Z, Zhu X, Marti MM, Srivastava SS, Berezuk AM, Zhou S, Tuttle KS, Sobolewski MD, Kim A, Treat BR, Da Silva Castanha PM, Jacobs JL, Barratt-Boyes SM, Mellors JW, Dimitrov DS, Li W, Subramaniam S. SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern: spike protein mutational analysis and epitope for broad neutralization. Nat Commun. 2022 Aug 18;13(1):4696. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-32262-8. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-32262-8.10.1038/s41467-022-32262-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-32262-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-32262-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9388680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35982054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Liu C, Zhang C, Wang Y, Hong Q, Xu S, Li Z, Yang Y, Huang Z, Cong Y. Structural basis for SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant recognition of ACE2 receptor and broadly neutralizing antibodies. Nat Commun. 2022 Feb 15;13(1):871. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-28528-w. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-28528-w.10.1038/s41467-022-28528-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-28528-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-28528-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8847413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35169135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saville JW, Mannar D, Zhu X, Srivastava SS, Berezuk AM, Demers J, Zhou S, Tuttle KS, Sekirov I, Kim A, Li W, Dimitrov DS, Subramaniam S. Structural and biochemical rationale for enhanced spike protein fitness in delta and kappa SARS-CoV-2 variants. Nat Commun. 2022 Feb 08;13(1):742. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-28324-6. doi: 10.1038/s41467-022-28324-6.10.1038/s41467-022-28324-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-28324-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-28324-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8826856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35136050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The GROMOS Software for (Bio)Molecular Simulation. Volume 1: About the GROMOS package: Overview. The GROMOS Software for (Bio)Molecular Simulation. Volume 1: About the GROMOS package: Overview. 2023.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://www.gromos.net/gromos11_pdf_manuals/vol1.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guex N, Peitsch MC. SWISS-MODEL and the Swiss-PdbViewer: an environment for comparative protein modeling. Electrophoresis. 1997 Dec 14;18(15):2714–2723. doi: 10.1002/elps.1150181505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/elps.1150181505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9504803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laskowski RA, Swindells MB. LigPlot+: multiple ligand-protein interaction diagrams for drug discovery. J Chem Inf Model. 2011 Oct 24;51(10):2778–2786. doi: 10.1021/ci200227u.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ci200227u</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21919503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myung Y, Pires Douglas E V, Ascher David B. CSM-AB: graph-based antibody-antigen binding affinity prediction and docking scoring function. Bioinformatics. 2022 Jan 27;38(4):1141–1143. doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btab762.6420700</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34734992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manjunath R, Gaonkar Santosh L, Saleh Ebraheem Abdu Musad, Husain Kakul. A comprehensive review on Covid-19 Omicron (B.1.1.529) variant. Saudi J Biol Sci. 2022 Sep;29(9):103372. doi: 10.1016/j.sjbs.2022.103372. 
 
S1319-562X(22)00288-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2022.103372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9284530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35855306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Xiong J, Sun Z, Hu J, Thilakavathy K, Chen M, Zhao Q, Feng Y, Jiang Q, Xiong C. Omicron: a chimera of two early SARS-CoV-2 lineages. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022 Mar 17;7(1):90. doi: 10.1038/s41392-022-00949-5. doi: 10.1038/s41392-022-00949-5.10.1038/s41392-022-00949-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-00949-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-00949-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8927754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35301279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins M, do Nascimento GM, Nooruzzaman M, Yuan F, Chen C, Caserta LC, Miller AD, Whittaker GR, Fang Y, Diel DG. The omicron variant BA.1.1 presents a lower pathogenicity than B.1 D614G and delta variants in a feline model of SARS-CoV-2 infection. J Virol. 2022 Sep 14;96(17):e0096122. doi: 10.1128/jvi.00961-22. 
 
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jvi.00961-22?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub0pubmed</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jvi.00961-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9472624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36000850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue C, Song W, Wang L, Jian F, Chen X, Gao F, Shen Z, Wang Y, Wang X, Cao Y. Enhanced transmissibility of XBB.1.5 is contributed by both strong ACE2 binding and antibody evasion. bioRxiv. doi: 10.1101/2023.01.03.522427. Preprint posted online January 5, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2023.01.03.522427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9897732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36746173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neher R. Variant report 2022-12-22. GitHub.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://github.com/neherlab/SARS-CoV-2_variant-reports/blob/d2d531c6deb12e52e5a6fde9af25f2cce023302b/reports/variant_report_2022-12-22.md
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu P, Evans JP, Faraone JN, Zheng Y, Carlin C, Anghelina M, Stevens P, Fernandez S, Jones D, Lozanski G, Panchal A, Saif LJ, Oltz EM, Xu K, Gumina RJ, Liu S. Enhanced neutralization resistance of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron subvariants BQ.1, BQ.1.1, BA.4.6, BF.7, and BA.2.75.2. Cell Host Microbe. 2023 Jan 11;31(1):9–17.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2022.11.012. 
 
S1931-3128(22)00568-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2022.11.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9678813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36476380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magnus CL, Hiergeist A, Schuster P, Rohrhofer A, Medenbach J, Gessner A, Peterhoff D, Schmidt B. Targeted escape of SARS-CoV-2 from monoclonal antibody S309, the precursor of sotrovimab. Front Immunol. 2022 Aug 24;13:966236. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2022.966236. 
 
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.966236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9449809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36090991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao Y, Wang J, Jian F, Xiao T, Song W, Yisimayi A, Huang W, Li Q, Wang P, An R, Wang J, Wang Y, Niu X, Yang S, Liang H, Sun H, Li T, Yu Y, Cui Q, Liu S, Yang X, Du S, Zhang Z, Hao X, Shao F, Jin R, Wang X, Xiao J, Wang Y, Xie XS. Omicron escapes the majority of existing SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies. Nature. 2022 Feb 23;602(7898):657–663. doi: 10.1038/s41586-021-04385-3.10.1038/s41586-021-04385-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-04385-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8866119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35016194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benkert P, Biasini Marco, Schwede Torsten. Toward the estimation of the absolute quality of individual protein structure models. Bioinformatics. 2011 Feb 01;27(3):343–350. doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btq662. 
 
btq662</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3031035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21134891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Studer G, Rempfer Christine, Waterhouse Andrew M, Gumienny Rafal, Haas Juergen, Schwede Torsten. QMEANDisCo-distance constraints applied on model quality estimation. Bioinformatics. 2020 Mar 01;36(6):1765–1771. doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btz828. 
 
5614424</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz828</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7075525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31697312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asif A, Ilyas I, Abdullah M, Sarfraz S, Mustafa M, Mahmood A. The comparison of mutational progression in SARS-CoV-2: a short updated overview. JMP. 2022 Oct 06;3(4):201–218. doi: 10.3390/jmp3040018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jmp3040018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang M, Wu L, Zheng A, Xie Y, He Q, Rong X, Han P, Du P, Han P, Zhang Z, Zhao R, Jia Y, Li L, Bai B, Hu Z, Hu S, Niu S, Hu Y, Liu H, Liu B, Cui K, Li W, Zhao X, Liu K, Qi J, Wang Q, Gao GF. Atlas of currently available human neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 and escape by Omicron sub-variants BA.1/BA.1.1/BA.2/BA.3. Immunity. 2022 Aug 09;55(8):1501–1514.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2022.06.005. 
 
S1074-7613(22)00265-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2022.06.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9197780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35777362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van de Veerdonk FL, Giamarellos-Bourboulis E, Pickkers P, Derde L, Leavis H, van Crevel R, Engel JJ, Wiersinga WJ, Vlaar APJ, Shankar-Hari M, van der Poll T, Bonten M, Angus DC, van der Meer JWM, Netea MG. A guide to immunotherapy for COVID-19. Nat Med. 2022 Jan 21;28(1):39–50. doi: 10.1038/s41591-021-01643-9.10.1038/s41591-021-01643-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01643-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35064248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng ZJ, Li B, Zhan Z, Zhao Z, Xue M, Zheng P, Lyu J, Hu C, He J, Chen R, Sun B. Clinical application of antibody immunity against SARS-CoV-2: comprehensive review on immunoassay and immunotherapy. Clin Rev Allergy Immunol. 2023 Feb 15;64(1):17–32. doi: 10.1007/s12016-021-08912-y. 
 
10.1007/s12016-021-08912-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12016-021-08912-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8760112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35031959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aggarwal NR, Beaty LE, Bennett TD, Carlson NE, Mayer DA, Molina KC, Peers JL, Russell S, Wynia MK, Ginde AA. Change in effectiveness of sotrovimab for preventing hospitalization and mortality for at-risk COVID-19 outpatients during an Omicron BA.1 and BA.1.1-predominant phase. Int J Infect Dis. 2023 Mar;128:310–317. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2022.10.002. 
 
S1201-9712(22)00540-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2022.10.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9549713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36229005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora P, Kempf A, Nehlmeier I, Schulz SR, Cossmann A, Stankov MV, Jäck H, Behrens GMN, Pöhlmann S, Hoffmann M. Augmented neutralisation resistance of emerging omicron subvariants BA.2.12.1, BA.4, and BA.5. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022 Aug;22(8):1117–1118. doi: 10.1016/s1473-3099(22)00422-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s1473-3099(22)00422-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9239574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35777385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imai M, Ito M, Kiso M, Yamayoshi S, Uraki R, Fukushi S, Watanabe S, Suzuki T, Maeda K, Sakai-Tagawa Y, Iwatsuki-Horimoto K, Halfmann PJ, Kawaoka Y. Efficacy of antiviral agents against omicron subvariants BQ.1.1 and XBB. N Engl J Med. 2023 Jan 05;388(1):89–91. doi: 10.1056/nejmc2214302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/nejmc2214302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9749618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36476720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox M, Peacock TP, Harvey WT, Hughes J, Wright DW, COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium. Willett Brian J, Thomson Emma, Gupta Ravindra K, Peacock Sharon J, Robertson David L, Carabelli Alessandro M. SARS-CoV-2 variant evasion of monoclonal antibodies based on in vitro studies. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023 Feb 28;21(2):112–124. doi: 10.1038/s41579-022-00809-7. 
 
10.1038/s41579-022-00809-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00809-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9616429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36307535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 weekly epidemiological update, edition 119, 23 November 2022. World Health Organization. 2022.  [2024-09-17].  
 https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/364724
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willett BJ, Grove J, MacLean OA, Wilkie C, De Lorenzo G, Furnon W, Cantoni D, Scott S, Logan N, Ashraf S, Manali M, Szemiel A, Cowton V, Vink E, Harvey WT, Davis C, Asamaphan P, Smollett K, Tong L, Orton R, Hughes J, Holland P, Silva V, Pascall DJ, Puxty K, da Silva Filipe A, Yebra G, Shaaban S, Holden MTG, Pinto RM, Gunson R, Templeton K, Murcia PR, Patel AH, Klenerman P, Dunachie S, PITCH Consortium. COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium. Haughney J, Robertson DL, Palmarini M, Ray S, Thomson EC. SARS-CoV-2 Omicron is an immune escape variant with an altered cell entry pathway. Nat Microbiol. 2022 Aug;7(8):1161–1179. doi: 10.1038/s41564-022-01143-7.10.1038/s41564-022-01143-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41564-022-01143-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9352574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35798890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohapatra RK, Mahal A, Kutikuppala LS, Pal M, Kandi V, Sarangi AK, Obaidullah AJ, Mishra S. Renewed global threat by the novel SARS-CoV-2 variants ‘XBB, BF.7, BQ.1, BA.2.75, BA.4.6’: a discussion. Front Virol. 2022 Dec 23;2:104. doi: 10.3389/fviro.2022.1077155.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fviro.2022.1077155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>