<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39407069</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1920-7476</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Canadian journal of public health = Revue canadienne de sante publique</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Can J Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Isolation to stabilization: A Housing First approach to address homelessness in Kingston, Ontario.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.17269/s41997-024-00936-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="METHODS">Homelessness is a significant and growing public health concern across Canada. In Kingston, Ontario, the number of people experiencing chronic homelessness has more than doubled from 136 people in 2020 to 296 in 2023.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERVENTION" NlmCategory="METHODS">An emergency shelter-in-place hotel program was established in April 2020 to provide non-congregate shelter to people experiencing homelessness and vulnerable to SARS-CoV-2 infections. Beyond preventing COVID transmission, the unintentional consequence was that a population that experienced chronic homelessness reduced drug consumption and became stable. In 2022, with increased funding from the Ministry of Health and the City of Kingston, a new Housing First program was implemented to transition individuals from homelessness to long-term stable housing.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OUTCOMES" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Between November 2022 and June 2023, a total of 34 clients initiated the program. Of these clients, 10 completed the program and were successfully housed, 10 remained active participants, and 14 were discharged before completion. Strengths and challenges were identified. Diverse services provided to meet the population's needs and strong collaborations with various community partners were facilitating factors. Inadequate external resources, a lack of evening and prosocial activities, and outside peers (not part of the program) who influenced recovery plans were identified as challenges.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPLICATIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This program illustrates that simultaneously integrating housing, community building, mental health, and addiction services is possible and provides an innovative way to stabilize this vulnerable population of people experiencing homelessness. Results from this program and the knowledge generated through implementation are being used to further scale up the program.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tan</LastName><ForeName>Yvonne</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4281-1835</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Queen's University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Revell</LastName><ForeName>Zack</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Addiction and Mental Health Services - Kingston, Frontenac and Lennox &amp; Addington (AMHS-KFLA), Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wilson</LastName><ForeName>Victoria</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>City of Kingston, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guan</LastName><ForeName>T Hugh</ForeName><Initials>TH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kingston, Frontenac and Lennox &amp; Addington Public Health (KFL&amp;A), Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lambert</LastName><ForeName>Julie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Addiction and Mental Health Services - Kingston, Frontenac and Lennox &amp; Addington (AMHS-KFLA), Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saeed</LastName><ForeName>Sahar</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0224-379X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON, Canada. sahar.saeed@queensu.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>Research Initiaition Grant</GrantID><Agency>Faculty of Health Sciences, Queen's University</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Can J Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0372714</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0008-4263</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText>RéSUMé: LIEU: Le sans-abrisme est un problème de santé publique important et en croissance au Canada. À Kingston, en Ontario, le nombre de personnes aux prises avec le sans-abrisme chronique a plus que doublé entre 2020 et 2023, passant de 136 à 296 personnes. INTERVENTION: Un programme d’abri d’urgence à l’hôtel mis en place en avril 2020 fournit un abri non collectif aux personnes aux prises avec le sans-abrisme vulnérables aux infections par le SRAS-CoV-2. En plus de prévenir la transmission de la COVID, ce programme a eu un effet inattendu : la population aux prises avec le sans-abrisme chronique a réduit sa consommation de drogue et s’est stabilisée. En 2022, grâce à un financement accru du ministère de la Santé et de la Ville de Kingston, un nouveau programme (Logement d’abord) a été mis en œuvre pour faciliter la transition des personnes sans abri vers un logement stable à long terme. RéSULTATS: Entre novembre 2022 et juin 2023, 34 personnes se sont inscrites à Logement d’abord. Dix d’entre elles ont terminé le programme et ont été logées avec succès, 10 y participent encore activement, et 14 en sont sorties avant la fin. Nous avons cerné les forces et les limites du programme. Les facteurs favorables ont été la gamme de services fournis en réponse aux besoins de la population et les liens de collaboration solides avec divers partenaires associatifs. Les limites du programme ont été le manque de ressources externes, l’absence d’activités prosociales et en soirée et l’influence des pairs de l’extérieur (non inscrits au programme) sur les plans de rétablissement des usagères et des usagers. CONSéQUENCES: Ce programme montre qu’il est possible d’intégrer simultanément le logement, la solidarité sociale, la santé mentale et les services en toxicomanie, et que c’est un moyen novateur de stabiliser cette population vulnérable aux prises avec le sans-abrisme. Les résultats du programme et les connaissances apportées par sa réalisation serviront à le reproduire à plus grande échelle.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emergency shelter</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Homelessness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Housing First</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Substance-related disorders</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>39</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39407069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17269/s41997-024-00936-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.17269/s41997-024-00936-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abbs, E., Schoenfeld, N., Lai, M., Satterwhite, S., Zhou, S., Bamberger, J., &amp; Zevin, B. (2023). Care and complexity in emergency housing: An examination of the COVID-19 Shelter-in-Place (SIP) hotel program to house people experiencing homelessness in San Francisco. Journal of Urban Health, 100(2), 303–313. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11524-022-00705-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11524-022-00705-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36652157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9848030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baral, S., Bond, A., Boozary, A., Bruketa, E., Elmi, N., Freiheit, D., Ghosh, S. M., Goyer, M. E., Orkin, A. M., Patel, J., Richter, T., Robertson, A., Sutherland, C., Svoboda, T., Turnbull, J., Wong, A., &amp; Zhu, A. (2021). Seeking shelter: Homelessness and COVID-19. FACETS, 6, 925–958. https://doi.org/10.1139/facets-2021-0004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/facets-2021-0004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baxter, A. J., Tweed, E. J., Katikireddi, S. V., &amp; Thomson, H. (2019). Effects of Housing First approaches on health and well-being of adults who are homeless or at risk of homelessness: Systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health, 73(5), 379–387. https://doi.org/10.1136/jech-2018-210981</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jech-2018-210981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30777888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brickner, P. W. (1972). A clinic for male derelicts: A welfare hotel project. Annals of Internal Medicine, 77(4), 565. https://doi.org/10.7326/0003-4819-77-4-565</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-77-4-565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4642737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colburn, G., Fyall, R., McHugh, C., Moraras, P., Ewing, V., Thompson, S., Dean, T., &amp; Argodale, S. (2022). Hotels as noncongregate emergency shelters: An analysis of investments in hotels as emergency shelter in King County, Washington during the COVID-19 pandemic. Housing Policy Debate, 32(6), 853–875. https://doi.org/10.1080/10511482.2022.2075027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10511482.2022.2075027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37860162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10586465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummings, C., Lei, Q., Hochberg, L., Hones, V., &amp; Brown, M. (2022). Social support and networks among people experiencing chronic homelessness: A systematic review. American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 92(3), 349–363. https://doi.org/10.1037/ort0000616</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/ort0000616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35266727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ecker, J., Aubry, T., Cherner, R., &amp; Jetté, J. (2014). Implementation evaluation of a Housing First program in a small Canadian city. Canadian Journal of Community Mental Health, 33(4), 23–40. https://doi.org/10.7870/cjcmh-2014-028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7870/cjcmh-2014-028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleming, M. D., Evans, J. L., Graham-Squire, D., Cawley, C., Kanzaria, H. K., Kushel, M. B., &amp; Raven, M. C. (2022). Association of shelter-in-place hotels with health services use among people experiencing homelessness during the COVID-19 pandemic. JAMA Network Open, 5(7), e2223891. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.23891</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.23891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35895061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9331083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fowler, P. J., Hovmand, P. S., Marcal, K. E., &amp; Das, S. (2019). Solving homelessness from a complex systems perspective: Insights for prevention responses. Annual Review of Public Health, 40(1), 465–486. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-040617-013553</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-040617-013553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30601718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6445694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuchs, J. D., Carter, H. C., Evans, J., Graham-Squire, D., Imbert, E., Bloome, J., Fann, C., Skotnes, T., Sears, J., Pfeifer-Rosenblum, R., Moughamian, A., Eveland, J., Reed, A., Borne, D., Lee, M., Rosenthal, M., Jain, V., Bobba, N., Kushel, M., &amp; Kanzaria, H. K. (2021). Assessment of a hotel-based COVID-19 isolation and quarantine strategy for persons experiencing homelessness. JAMA Network Open, 4(3), e210490. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.0490</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.0490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33651111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7926291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goering, P., Veldhuizen, S., Watson, A., Adair, C., Kopp, B., Latimer, E., Nelson, G., MacNaughton, E., Streiner, E., &amp; Aubry, E. (2014). National At Home/Chez Soi Final Report. Mental Health Commission of Canada. https://homelesshub.ca/sites/default/files/attachments/mhcc_at_home_report_national_cross-site_eng_2.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Canada. (2013, February 11). Institutional profiles: Ontario region. https://www.csc-scc.gc.ca/institutions/001002-3000-en.shtml</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant, R. (1991). The special needs of homeless children: Early intervention at a welfare hotel. Topics in Early Childhood Special Education, 10(4), 76–91. https://doi.org/10.1177/027112149101000407</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/027112149101000407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulcur, L., Stefancic, A., Shinn, M., Tsemberis, S., &amp; Fischer, S. N. (2003). Housing, hospitalization, and cost outcomes for homeless individuals with psychiatric disabilities participating in continuum of care and housing first programmes. Journal of Community &amp; Applied Social Psychology, 13(2), 171–186. https://doi.org/10.1002/casp.723</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/casp.723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Homelessness Registry By-Name List. (2023). https://opendatakingston.cityofkingston.ca/explore/dataset/homelessness-registry-by-name-list/table/?dataChart=eyJxdWVyaWVzIjpbeyJjb25maWciOnsiZGF0YXNldCI6ImhvbWVsZXNzbmVzcy1yZWdpc3RyeS1ieS1uYW1lLWxpc3QiLCJvcHRpb25zIjp7fX0sImNoYXJ0cyI6W3siYWxpZ25Nb250aCI6dHJ1ZSwidHlwZSI6ImxpbmUiLCJmdW5jIjoiQVZHIiwieUF4aXMiOiJpbmRpdmlkdWFsc19vbl90aGVfYnlfbmFtZV9saXN0Iiwic2NpZW50aWZpY0Rpc3BsYXkiOnRydWUsImNvbG9yIjoiIzY2YzJhNSJ9XSwieEF4aXMiOiJkYXRlIiwibWF4cG9pbnRzIjoiIiwidGltZXNjYWxlIjoieWVhciIsInNvcnQiOiIifV0sImRpc3BsYXlMZWdlbmQiOnRydWUsImFsaWduTW9udGgiOnRydWV9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huggett, T. D., Tung, E. L., Cunningham, M., Ghinai, I., Duncan, H. L., McCauley, M. E., &amp; Detmer, W. M. (2021). Assessment of a hotel-based protective housing program for incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection and management of chronic illness among persons experiencing homelessness. JAMA Network Open, 4(12), e2138464. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.38464</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.38464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34902035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8669521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang, S. W. (2001). Homelessness and health. CMAJ: Canadian Medical Association Journal = Journal de l’Association Medicale Canadienne, 164(2), 229–233.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kneebone, R., &amp; Jadidzadeh, A. (2022). An evaluation of housing first programs in Calgary. The School of Public Policy Publications, 15(1). https://doi.org/10.11575/SPPP.V15I1.75034</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mares, A. S., &amp; Rosenheck, R. A. (2011). A comparison of treatment outcomes among chronically homelessness adults receiving comprehensive housing and health care services versus usual local care. Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research, 38(6), 459–475. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-011-0333-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10488-011-0333-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21259068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGraw, S. A., Larson, M. J., Foster, S. E., Kresky-Wolff, M., Botelho, E. M., Elstad, E. A., Stefancic, A., &amp; Tsemberis, S. (2010). Adopting best practices: Lessons learned in the Collaborative Initiative to Help End Chronic Homelessness (CICH). The Journal of Behavioral Health Services &amp; Research, 37(2), 197–212. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11414-009-9173-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11414-009-9173-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montgomery, M. P., Paulin, H. N., Morris, A., Cotton, A., Speers, A., Boyd, A. T., Buff, A. M., Mathews, D., Wells, A., Marchman, C., Gaffga, N., Bamrah Morris, S., &amp; Cavanaugh, S. S. (2021). Establishment of isolation and noncongregate hotels during COVID-19 and symptom evolution among people experiencing homelessness—Atlanta, Georgia, 2020. Journal of Public Health Management and Practice, 27(3), 285–294. https://doi.org/10.1097/PHH.0000000000001349</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PHH.0000000000001349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33762544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10878749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nilsson, S. F., Nordentoft, M., &amp; Hjorthøj, C. (2019). Individual-level predictors for becoming homeless and exiting homelessness: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Journal of Urban Health, 96(5), 741–750. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11524-019-00377-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11524-019-00377-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31388823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6814700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padgett, D. K., Bond, L., &amp; Wusinich, C. (2022). From the streets to a hotel: A qualitative study of the experiences of homeless persons in the pandemic era. Journal of Social Distress and Homelessness, 1–7. https://doi.org/10.1080/10530789.2021.2021362</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plutchik, R., McCarthy, M., &amp; Hall, B. H. (1975). Changes in elderly welfare hotel residents during a one-year period†. Journal of the American Geriatrics Society, 23(6), 265–270. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1532-5415.1975.tb00316.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.1975.tb00316.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1127200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponce, A. N., Brown, M., Cunningham, A., &amp; Rowe, M. (2018). Stakeholder perspectives on integrated services for people who experience chronic homelessness. Journal of Social Distress and the Homeless, 27(2), 126–134. https://doi.org/10.1080/10530789.2018.1501947</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10530789.2018.1501947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson, L., Schlesinger, P., &amp; Keene, D. E. (2022). “You have a place to rest your head in peace”: Use of hotels for adults experiencing homelessness during the COVID-19 pandemic. Housing Policy Debate, 32(6), 837–852. https://doi.org/10.1080/10511482.2022.2113816</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10511482.2022.2113816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, A., &amp; Kopec, A. (2023). Mapping homelessness research in Canada. American Review of Canadian Studies, 53(1), 42–62. https://doi.org/10.1080/02722011.2023.2170155</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/02722011.2023.2170155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics Canada. (2017). Census Profile, 2016. https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2016/dp-pd/prof/index.cfm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stergiopoulos, V., Gozdzik, A., O’Campo, P., Holtby, A. R., Jeyaratnam, J., &amp; Tsemberis, S. (2014). Housing First: Exploring participants’ early support needs. BMC Health Services Research, 14(1), 167. https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6963-14-167</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1472-6963-14-167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24725374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4021373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stona, A., Berrang, C., Santerre, H., Georges, N., Chimenti, R., Kneip, R., &amp; Fond-Harmant, L. (2016). Homelessness and stakeholders’ involvement in the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg: A qualitative study. Health Expectations, 19(1), 138–151. https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.12336</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/hex.12336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25601355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson, R. G., Wall, M. M., Greenstein, E., Grant, B. F., &amp; Hasin, D. S. (2013). Substance-use disorders and poverty as prospective predictors of first-time homelessness in the United States. American Journal of Public Health, 103(S2), S282–S288. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2013.301302</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2013.301302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24148043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3865876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsemberis, S., Gulcur, L., &amp; Nakae, M. (2004). Housing First, consumer choice, and harm reduction for homeless individuals with a dual diagnosis. American Journal of Public Health, 94(4), 651–656. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.94.4.651</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.94.4.651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15054020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">1448313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Way – Kingston, Frontenac Lennox and Addington. (2021). Results of the Urban Kingston Point-in-Time Count. United Way of KFL&amp;A. https://www.unitedwaykfla.ca/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/2021-Kingston-PiT-Count-Results.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitzman, C. (2006). At the intersection of invisibilities: Canadian women, homelessness and health outside the ‘big city.’ Gender, Place &amp; Culture, 13(4), 383–399. https://doi.org/10.1080/09663690600808502</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09663690600808502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Worton, S. K., Hasford, J., Macnaughton, E., Nelson, G., MacLeod, T., Tsemberis, S., Stergiopoulos, V., Goering, P., Aubry, T., Distasio, J., &amp; Richter, T. (2018). Understanding systems change in early implementation of Housing First in Canadian communities: An examination of facilitators/barriers, training/technical assistance, and points of leverage. American Journal of Community Psychology, 61(1–2), 118–130. https://doi.org/10.1002/ajcp.12219</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ajcp.12219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29251344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>