<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39400220</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1938-4351</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>68</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Avian diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Avian Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Antiviral Effect of Different Essential Oils on Avian Coronavirus.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>254</StartPage><EndPage>258</EndPage><MedlinePgn>254-258</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1637/aviandiseases-D-24-00015</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Plant essential oils (EOs) possess established antimicrobial properties; however, research on their antiviral activity, particularly against avian coronaviruses, remains limited. EOs offer a promising plant-based alternative for viral control, especially in scenarios where conventional chemical use is restricted. This study aimed to evaluate the antiviral effects of six different essential oils derived from <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i>, <i>Origanum vulgare</i>, <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i>, <i>Cymbopogon citratus</i>, <i>Mentha piperita</i>, and <i>Mentha spicata</i> against avian coronavirus (AvCov) at 0.1% and 1% dilutions. The antiviral effects of the EOs were assessed via virus isolation from embryonated chicken eggs, and the ability of the EOs to inhibit AvCoV replication was evaluated. The EOs from <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i>, <i>Origanum vulgare</i>, <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i>, and <i>Cymbopogon citratus</i> completely inhibited AvCov replication at a 1% dilution. Conversely, absent to partial inhibitory effect was observed at the 0.1% dilution for all tested EOs, with <i>O. vulgare</i> derived EO exhibiting the greatest inhibitory effect (over 70%). Notably, EOs from <i>Mentha piperita</i> and <i>Mentha spicata</i> were unable to completely inhibit AvCov at either concentration. Our findings highlight the potent antiviral activity of the EOs from <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i>, <i>Origanum vulgare</i>, <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i>, and <i>Cymbopogon citratus</i> against AvCov at a 1% dilution. The complete inhibition observed for these EOs suggests their potential for AvCov control. However, further research is necessary to elucidate the mechanisms of action, optimize formulations, and evaluate the efficacy against other coronaviruses, including those relevant to human health.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okino</LastName><ForeName>Cintia Hiromi</ForeName><Initials>CH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brazilian Agricultural Research Corporation, Embrapa Pecuária Sudeste, Rodovia Washington Luiz, Fazenda Canchim, 13560-970, São Carlos, SP, Brazil, cintia.okino@embrapa.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Melito</LastName><ForeName>Gláucia Roberta</ForeName><Initials>GR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brazilian Agricultural Research Corporation, Embrapa Pecuária Sudeste, Rodovia Washington Luiz, Fazenda Canchim, 13560-970, São Carlos, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Astolfo</LastName><ForeName>Maria Eduarda de Almeida</ForeName><Initials>MEA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of São Paulo (USP), São Carlos Institute of Chemistry (IQSC), 13566-590, São Carlos, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martins</LastName><ForeName>Maria Eduarda Da Mata</ForeName><Initials>MEDM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Postgraduate Program in Food Science and Engineering, IBILCE, São Paulo State University "Julio de Mesquita Filho," UNESP, São José do Rio Preto, SP, 15054-000, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Junior</LastName><ForeName>Stanislau Bogusz</ForeName><Initials>SB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of São Paulo (USP), São Carlos Institute of Chemistry (IQSC), 13566-590, São Carlos, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferreira</LastName><ForeName>Marcos David</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brazilian Agricultural Research Corporation, Embrapa Instrumentation, São Carlos 13561-206, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Avian Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370617</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0005-2086</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D009822">Oils, Volatile</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000998">Antiviral Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010938">Plant Oils</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009822" MajorTopicYN="Y">Oils, Volatile</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000998" MajorTopicYN="Y">Antiviral Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011201" MajorTopicYN="N">Poultry Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002642" MajorTopicYN="N">Chick Embryo</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010938" MajorTopicYN="N">Plant Oils</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018352" MajorTopicYN="N">Coronavirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014779" MajorTopicYN="N">Virus Replication</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D031743" MajorTopicYN="N">Cymbopogon</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText><i>Nota de investigación-</i> Efecto antiviral de diferentes aceites esenciales sobre el coronavirus aviar. Los aceites esenciales vegetales poseen propiedades antimicrobianas establecidas; sin embargo, la investigación sobre su actividad antiviral, particularmente contra los coronavirus aviares, sigue siendo limitada. Los aceites esenciales ofrecen una alternativa vegetal prometedora para el control viral, especialmente en escenarios donde el uso de químicos convencionales está restringido. Este estudio tuvo como objetivo evaluar los efectos antivirales de seis aceites esenciales diferentes derivados de <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i>, <i>Origanum vulgare</i>, <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i>, <i>Cymbopogon citratus</i>, <i>Mentha piperita</i> y <i>Mentha spicata</i> contra el coronavirus aviar (AvCov) en diluciones de 0.1% y 1%. Los efectos antivirales de los aceites esenciales se evaluaron mediante el aislamiento del virus a partir de huevos embrionados de pollo y se evaluó la capacidad de los aceites esenciales para inhibir la replicación del coronavirus aviar. Los aceites esenciales de <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i>, <i>Origanum vulgare</i>, <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i> y <i>Cymbopogon citratus</i> inhibieron completamente la replicación del coronavirus aviar en una dilución del 1%. Por el contrario, se observó un efecto inhibidor nulo o parcial con la dilución del 0.1% para todos los aceites esenciales analizados, siendo el aceite esencial derivado de <i>O. vulgare</i> el que exhibió el mayor efecto inhibidor (más del 70%). En particular, los aceites esenciales de <i>Mentha piperita</i> y <i>Mentha spicata</i> no pudieron inhibir completamente al coronavirus aviar en ninguna de las concentraciones. Nuestros hallazgos resaltan la potente actividad antiviral de los aceites esenciales de <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i>, <i>Origanum vulgare</i>, <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i> y <i>Cymbopogon citratus</i> contra coronavirus en una dilución del 1%. La inhibición completa observada para estos aceites esenciales sugiere su potencial para el control de coronavirus. Sin embargo, se necesitan más investigaciones para dilucidar los mecanismos de acción, optimizar las formulaciones y evaluar la eficacia contra otros coronavirus, incluidos los relevantes para la salud humana.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RTqPCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chicken</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious bronchitis virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral load</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39400220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1637/aviandiseases-D-24-00015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wani AR, Yadav K, Khursheed A, Rather MA. An updated and comprehensive review of the antiviral potential of essential oils and their chemical constituents with special focus on their mechanism of action against various influenza and coronaviruses. <i>Microb PAthog</i>, 152, 104620; 2021. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2020.104620.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackwood MW, Rosenbloom R, Petteruti M, Hilt DA, McCall AW, Williams SM. Avian coronavirus infectious bronchitis virus susceptibility to botanical oleoresins and essential oils in vitro and in vivo. <i>Virus Res</i>. 149; 2010. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virusres.2010.01.006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catella C, Camero M, Lucente MS, Fracchiolla G, Sblano S, Tempesta M, Martella V, Buonavoglia C, Lanave G. Virucidal and antiviral effects of <i>Thymus vulgaris</i> essential oil on feline coronavirus. <i>Res Vet Sci</i>. 137; 2021. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rvsc.2021.04.024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Li XY, Zhang BS, Ren LN, Lu YP, Tang JW, et al. In vivo antiviral effect of plant essential oils against avian infectious bronchitis virus. <i>BMC Vet Res</i>. 18; 2022. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12917-022-03183-x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin J, Li G, Li J, Yang Q, Ren X. In vitro and in vivo effects of <i>Houttuynia cordata</i> on infectious bronchitis virus. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 2011;40. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079457.2011.605107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C, Zuckerman DM, Brantley S, Sharpe M, Childress K, Hoiczyk E, et al. Sambucus nigra extracts inhibit infectious bronchitis virus at an early point during replication. <i>BMC Vet Res</i>. 10; 2014. https://doi.org/10.1186/1746-6148-10-24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shojai TM, Langeroudi AG, Karimi V, Barin A, Sadri N. The effect of <i>Allium sativum</i> (garlic) extract on infectious bronchitis virus in specific pathogen free embryonic egg. <i>Avicenna J Phytomed</i>. 6:458–467; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Liu X, Liu H, Wang W, Liu X, Li X, et al. Astragalus polysaccharides inhibit avian infectious bronchitis virus infection by regulating viral replication. <i>Microb Pathog</i>. 114; 2018. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2017.11.026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lelešius R, Karpovaite A, Mickiene R, Drevinskas T, Tiso N, Ragažinskiene O, et al. In vitro antiviral activity of fifteen plant extracts against avian infectious bronchitis virus. <i>BMC Vet Res</i>. 15; 2019. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12917-019-1925-6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soltani S, Shakeri A, Iranshahi M, Boozari M. A review of the phytochemistry and antimicrobial properties of <i>Origanum vulgare</i> L. and subspecies. <i>Iran J Pharm Res</i>. 20<i>;</i> 2021. https://doi.org/10.22037/ijpr.2020.113874.14539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mediouni S, Jablonski JA, Tsuda S, Barsamian A, Kessing C, Richard A, et al. Oregano oil and its principal component, carvacrol, inhibit HIV-1 fusion into target cells. <i>J Virol</i>. 94; 2020. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.00147-20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Picoli T, Waller SB, Hoffmann JF, Peter CM, Barcelos L da S, Lopes MG, et al. Antiviral and virucidal potential of <i>Origanum vulgare</i> Linn. (oregano) extracts against Bovine alphaherpesvirus 1 (BoHV-1). <i>Res Soc Dev</i>. 10; 2021. https://doi.org/10.33448/rsd-v10i5.14979.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiki MJ. In vitro antiviral potential, antioxidant, and chemical composition of clove (<i>Syzygium aromaticum</i>) essential oil. <i>Molecules</i> 28; 2023. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules28062421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batiha GES, Alkazmi LM, Wasef LG, Beshbishy AM, Nadwa EH, Rashwan EK. <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i> L. (myrtaceae): Traditional uses, bioactive chemical constituents, pharmacological and toxicological activities. <i>Bio-molecules</i> 10; 2020. https://doi.org/10.3390/biom10020202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem HN, Batool F, Mansoor HJ, Shahzad-Ul-Hussan S, Saeed M. Inhibition of dengue virus protease by eugeniin, isobiflorin, and biflorin isolated from the flower buds of <i>Syzygium aromaticum</i> (cloves). <i>ACS Omega</i> 4; 2019. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.8b02861.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vicidomini C, Roviello V, Roviello GN. Molecular basis of the therapeutical potential of clove (<i>Syzygium aromaticum</i> L.) and clues to its anti-COVID-19 utility. <i>Molecules</i> 26; 2021. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26071880.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marinković J, Ćulafić DM, Nikolić B, Đukanović S, Marković T, Tasić G, et al. Antimicrobial potential of irrigants based on essential oils of <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i> and <i>Thymus zygis</i> towards in vitro multispecies biofilm cultured in ex vivo root canals. <i>Arch Oral Biol</i>. 117; 2020. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.archoralbio.2020.104842.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devi MA, Sahoo D, Singh TB, Rajashekar Y. Antifungal activity and volatile organic compounds analysis of essential oils from <i>Cymbopogon</i> species using solid-phase microextraction-gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. <i>J Agric Food Res</i>. 3; 2021. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jafr.2021.100110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin L, Chen S, Xia W, Li T, Dong L, Zhang Y, et al. A new strategy: inhibitory effect and mechanism of <i>Cymbopogon martinii</i> essential oil on <i>Aspergillus</i> fl<i>avus</i>. <i>Food Biosci</i>. 51; 2023. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2022.102315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalise PP, Pudasaini R, Dawadi S, Khanal A. Efficacy of plant essential oils on black bean aphid (<i>Aphis fabae</i>) and cabbage aphid (<i>Brevicoryne brassicae</i>) under laboratory condition. <i>J Entomol Zool Stud</i><i>.</i>7; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha P, Nath PS, De BK, Das S. Effect of different botanical oils on the control of aphid (<i>Aphis craccivora</i>) population and incidence of leaf crinckle virus of mungbean (<i>Vigna radiata</i> L.). <i>J Mycopathol Res</i>. 50:325–327; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukarram M, Choudhary S, Khan MA, Poltronieri P, Khan MMA, Ali J, et al. Lemongrass essential oil components with antimicrobial and anticancer activities. <i>Antioxidants</i> 11; 2022. https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox11010020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao H, Ren S, Yang H, Tang S, Guo C, Liu M, et al. Peppermint essential oil: its phytochemistry, biological activity, pharmacological effect and application. <i>Biomed Pharmacother</i>. 154; 2022. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2022.113559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gelb J Jr, Jackwood MW. Infectious bronchitis. In: Dufour-Zavala L, Swayne DE, Glisson JR, Jackwood MW, Pearson JE, Reed WM, et al., editors. <i>A laboratory manual for the isolation</i>, <i>identi</i>fi<i>cation</i>, <i>and characterization of avian pathogens</i>. 5th ed. Athens (GA): American Association of Avian Pathologists. p. 146–149; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed LJ, Muench H. A simple method of estimating fifty per cent end points. <i>Am J Hyg</i>. 27:493–497; 1938.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linstrom PJ, Mallard WG. <i>NIST Chemistry webbook</i>. NIST Standard Reference Database Number 69. National Institute of Standards and Technology. 20899; 2014, (http://webbook.nist.gov).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chousalkar KK, Cheetham BF, Roberts JR. LNA probe-based real-time RT-PCR for the detection of infectious bronchitis virus from the oviduct of unvaccinated and vaccinated laying hens. <i>J Virol Methods</i> 155; 2009. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2008.09.028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz-Villalba A, Ruijter JM, van den Hoff MJB. Use and misuse of C<sub>q</sub> in qPCR data analysis and reporting. <i>Life</i> 11; 2021. https://doi.org/10.3390/life11060496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook JKA, Orbell SJ, Woods MA, Huggins MB. Breadth of protection of the respiratory tract provided by different live-attenuated infectious bronchitis vaccines against challenge with infectious bronchitis viruses of heterologous serotypes. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 28; 1999. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079459994506.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burt S. Essential oils: Their antibacterial properties and potential applications in foods—a review. <i>Int J Food Microbiol</i>. 94; 2004. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2004.03.022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres Neto L, Monteiro MLG, Fernández-Romero J, Teleshova N, Sailer J, Conte Junior CA. Essential oils block cellular entry of SARS-CoV-2 delta variant. <i>Sci Rep</i>. 12; 2022. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-25342-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawat SS, Viard M, Gallo SA, Rein A, Blumenthal R, Puri A. Modulation of entry of enveloped viruses by cholesterol and sphingolipids. <i>Mol Membr Biol</i>. 20; 2003. https://doi.org/10.1080/0968768031000104944.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai J, Wang H, Liao Y, Tan L, Sun Y, Song C, et al. Coronavirus infection and cholesterol metabolism. <i>Front Immunol</i>. 13; 2022. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.791267.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>