<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39402851</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1475-6773</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Health services research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Health Serv Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effects of the continuous Medicaid coverage provision of the family first coronavirus response act on postpartum Medicaid coverage, depression symptoms, and birth control use.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1475-6773.14395</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The 2020 Family First Coronavirus Response Act (FFCRA) extended Medicaid coverage for enrollees without rechecking eligibility. Before that, women were eligible for Medicaid coverage up to 60 days postpartum. We examine the FFCRA's effect on Medicaid postpartum coverage, depression symptoms, and birth control use beyond 60 days after delivery.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA SOURCES AND SETTING" NlmCategory="METHODS">We use data from the 2016-2021 Pregnancy Risk Assessment Monitoring System (PRAMS). The primary sample includes 56,828 women who were income eligible up to 60 days postpartum or beyond in their state.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">We employ a difference-in-differences design comparing outcomes before and after the FFCRA between women who were not income eligible for Medicaid coverage beyond 60 days postpartum in their state and those who were income eligible. We estimate models without and with controlling for state-specific trends in outcomes over time.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA COLLECTION/EXTRACTION METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">N/A.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PRINCIPAL FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">There is an 8.1 percentage-point increase in the likelihood of having Medicaid coverage without controlling for state-specific trends, and 5.4 percentage-points when controlling for state-specific trends (both p &lt; 0.05). There is a decline in likelihood of being uninsured by 3 percentage-points (p &lt; 0.05) without state-specific trends and a smaller and non-significant decline when including state-specific trends. Estimated effects on depression symptoms and birth control use are small and statistically non-significant.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Following the FFCRA, there was an increase in Medicaid coverage beyond 60 days postpartum among women who would have been income ineligible for Medicaid after 60 days. However, there is a less pronounced effect on likelihood of being uninsured, which might be partly due to some switching from private to Medicaid coverage. There were no discernable effects on depression symptoms and birth control use. Examining additional health and health care utilization measures over a longer postpartum period is needed to further understand the FCCRA effects on these outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Health Services Research published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Health Research and Educational Trust.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ejughemre</LastName><ForeName>Ufuoma</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Management and Policy, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lyu</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7441-9961</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Services Administration, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wehby</LastName><ForeName>George L</ForeName><Initials>GL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7784-9908</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Management and Policy, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Policy Center, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Bureau of Economic Research, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Health Serv Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0053006</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0017-9124</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medicaid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PRAMS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health insurance continuity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">maternal health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">postpartum</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39402851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.14395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Ko JY, Rockhill KM, Tong VT, Morrow B, Farr SL. Trends in Postpartum Depressive Symptoms—27 States, 2004, 2008, and 2012. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017;66(6):153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauman BL. Vital signs: postpartum depressive symptoms and provider discussions about perinatal depression—United States, 2018. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020;69:69‐581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahrens KA, Thoma ME, Copen CE, Frederiksen BN, Decker EJ, Moskosky S. Unintended pregnancy and interpregnancy interval by maternal age, National Survey of Family Growth. Contraception. 2018;98(1):52‐55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creanga AA, Syverson C, Seed K, Callaghan WM. Pregnancy‐related mortality in the United States, 2011–2013. Obstet Gynecol. 2017;130(2):366‐373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myerson R, Crawford S, Wherry LR. Medicaid expansion increased preconception health counseling, folic acid intake, and postpartum contraception: study examines the impact of ACA Medicaid expansion on health behaviors including birth control use and pregnancy intention, and receipt of preconception health services. Health Aff. 2020;39(11):1883‐1890.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunlop AL, Joski P, Strahan AE, Sierra E, Adams EK. Postpartum Medicaid coverage and contraceptive use before and after Ohio's Medicaid expansion under the Affordable Care Act. Womens Health Issues. 2020;30(6):426‐435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zephyrin L, Coleman A, Nuzum R, Getachew Y. Increasing postpartum medicaid coverage could reduce maternal deaths and improve outcomes. Accessed March 28, 2024. https://www.commonwealthfund.org/blog/2019/increasing-postpartum-medicaid-coverage</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saldanha IJ, Adam GP, Kanaan G, et al. Health insurance coverage and postpartum outcomes in the US: a systematic review. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(6):e2316536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corallo B, Tolbert J, Saunders H, Frederiksen B. Medicaid enrollment patterns during the postpartum year. Accessed March 28, 2024. https://www.kff.org/medicaid/issue‐brief/medicaid‐enrollment‐patterns‐during‐the‐postpartum‐year/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boozang P, Serafi K, O'Connor K. Protecting coverage for postpartum individuals at the end of the public health emergency. Accessed March 28, 2024. https://www.shvs.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Protecting-Coverage-for-Postpartum-Individuals-at-the-End-of-the-PHE.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation. Medicaid income eligibility limits for adults as a percent of the federal poverty level. https://www.kff.org/health‐reform/state‐indicator/medicaid‐income‐eligibility‐limits‐for‐adults‐as‐a‐percent‐of‐the‐federal‐poverty‐level/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daw JR, MacCallum‐Bridges CL, Kozhimannil KB, Admon LK. Continuous Medicaid Eligibility during the COVID‐19 Pandemic and Postpartum Coverage, Health Care, and Outcomes. American Medical Association; 2024:e240004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. The Pregnancy Risk Assessment Monitoring System (PRAMS): Overview of Design and Methodology. Accessed November 3, 2023. https://www.cdc.gov/prams/methodology.htm#methodology</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eliason EL, Spishak‐Thomas A, Steenland MW. Association of the affordable care act Medicaid expansions with postpartum contraceptive use and early postpartum pregnancy. Contraception. 2022;113:42‐48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clapp MA, James KE, Kaimal AJ, Daw JR. Preconception coverage before and after the affordable care act Medicaid expansions. Obstet Gynecol. 2018;132(6):1394‐1400. doi:10.1097/aog.0000000000002972</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eliason EL, Daw JR, Allen HL. Association of Medicaid vs marketplace eligibility with maternal coverage and access to prenatal and postpartum care. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(12):e2137383. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.37383</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon J, Harvey SM, Luck J. Improved depression screening and treatment among low‐income pregnant and postpartum women following Medicaid expansion in the US. Front Health Serv. 2022;2:942476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Austin AE, Sokol RL, Rowland C. Medicaid expansion and postpartum depressive symptoms: evidence from the 2009–2018 pregnancy risk assessment monitoring system survey. Ann Epidemiol. 2022;68:9‐15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nidey N, Tabb KM, Carter KD, et al. Rurality and risk of perinatal depression among women in the United States. J Rural Health. 2020;36(1):9‐16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranji U, Gomez I, Salganicoff A, Rosenzweig C, Kellenberg R, Gifford K. Medicaid Coverage of Family Planning Benefits: Findings from a 2021 State Survey. https://www.kff.org/womens‐health‐policy/report/medicaid‐coverage‐of‐family‐planning‐benefits‐findings‐from‐a‐2021‐state‐survey/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnston EM, McMorrow S, Thomas TW, Kenney GM. ACA Medicaid expansion and insurance coverage among new mothers living in poverty. Pediatrics. 2020;145(5):e20193178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daw JR, Winkelman TN, Dalton VK, Kozhimannil KB, Admon LK. Medicaid expansion improved perinatal insurance continuity for low‐income women: study examines the impact of state Medicaid expansions on continuity of insurance coverage for low‐income women across three time points: preconception, delivery, and postpartum. Health Aff. 2020;39(9):1531‐1539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bullinger LR, Simon K, Edmonds BT. Coverage effects of the ACA's Medicaid expansion on adult reproductive‐aged women, postpartum mothers, and mothers with older children. Matern Child Health J. 2022;26(5):1104‐1114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyu W, Wehby GL. Heterogeneous effects of affordable care act Medicaid expansions among women with dependent children by state‐level pre‐expansion eligibility. J Womens Health. 2021;30:1278‐1287.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wehby GL, Lyu W. The impact of the ACA Medicaid expansions on health insurance coverage through 2015 and coverage disparities by age, race/ethnicity, and gender. Health Serv Res. 2017;53:1248‐1271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaestner R, Garrett B, Gangopadhyaya A, Fleming C. Effects of ACA Medicaid expansions on health insurance coverage and labor supply. 2015. http://www.nber.org/papers/w21836</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Pengetnze YM, Eckert E, Keever G, Chowdhry V. Extending postpartum Medicaid beyond 60 days improves care access and uncovers unmet needs in a Texas Medicaid health maintenance organization. Front Public Health. 2022;10:841832.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaiser Family Foundation. Medicaid postpartum coverage extension tracker. Accessed March 28, 2024. https://www.kff.org/medicaid/issue-brief/medicaid-postpartum-coverage-extension-tracker/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert Hest EL, Blewett L. Medicaid Undercount Doubles, Likely Tied to Enrollee Misreporting of Coverage. State Health Access Data Assistance Center; 2022. Accessed December 13, 2023. https://www.shadac.org/publications/medicaid-undercount-doubles-20-21</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>