<PubmedArticle xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39401269</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2473-4209</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medical physics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Med Phys</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sinogram-characteristic-informed network for efficient restoration of low-dose SPECT projection data.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/mp.17459</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography (SPECT) sinogram restoration for low-dose imaging is a critical challenge in medical imaging. Existing methods often overlook the characteristics of the sinograms, necessitating innovative approaches.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">In this study, we introduce the Sinogram-characteristic-informed network (SCI-Net) to address the restoration of low-dose SPECT sinograms. Our aim is to build and train a model based on the characteristics of sinograms, including continuity, periodicity, multi-scale properties of lines in sinograms, and others, to enhance the model's understanding of the restoration process.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">SCI-Net incorporates several novel mechanisms tailored to exploit the inherent characteristics of sinograms. We implement a channel attention module with a decay mechanism to leverage continuity across adjacent sinograms, while a position attention module captures global correlations within individual sinograms. Additionally, we propose a multi-stage progressive integration mechanism to balance local detail and overall structure. Multiple regularization terms, customized to sinogram image characteristics, are embedded into the loss function for model training.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The experimental evaluations are divided into two parts: simulation data evaluation and clinical evaluation. The simulation data evaluation is conducted on a dataset comprising ten organ types, generated by the SIMIND Monte Carlo program from extended cardiac-torso (XCAT) anatomical phantoms. The dataset includes a total of SPECT sinograms with low-dose as input data and normal-dose as ground truth, consisting of 3881 sinograms in the training dataset and 849 sinograms in the testing set. When comparing the restoration of low-dose sinograms to normal-dose references, SCI-Net effectively improves performance. Specifically, the peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR) and the structural similarity (SSIM) on sinograms increase from 15.72 to 34.66 ( <ns0:math> <ns0:semantics><ns0:mrow><ns0:mi>p</ns0:mi> <ns0:mo>&lt;</ns0:mo></ns0:mrow> <ns0:annotation>$\text{p}&amp;lt; $</ns0:annotation></ns0:semantics> </ns0:math> 0.001) and 0.6297 to 0.9834 ( <ns0:math> <ns0:semantics><ns0:mrow><ns0:mi>p</ns0:mi> <ns0:mo>&lt;</ns0:mo></ns0:mrow> <ns0:annotation>$\text{p}&amp;lt;$</ns0:annotation></ns0:semantics> </ns0:math> 0.001), respectively, and on reconstructed images, reconstructed by maximum likelihood-expectation maximization (ML-EM), the PSNR and the SSIM improve from 21.95 to 33.14 ( <ns0:math> <ns0:semantics><ns0:mrow><ns0:mi>p</ns0:mi> <ns0:mo>&lt;</ns0:mo></ns0:mrow> <ns0:annotation>$\text{p}&amp;lt;$</ns0:annotation></ns0:semantics> </ns0:math> 0.001) and 0.9084 to 0.9866 ( <ns0:math> <ns0:semantics><ns0:mrow><ns0:mi>p</ns0:mi> <ns0:mo>&lt;</ns0:mo></ns0:mrow> <ns0:annotation>$\text{p}&amp;lt;$</ns0:annotation></ns0:semantics> </ns0:math> 0.001), respectively. We compared SCI-Net with existing methods, including baseline models, traditional reconstruction algorithms, end-to-end methods, sinogram restoration methods, and image post-processing methods. The experimental results and visual examples demonstrate that SCI-Net surpasses these existing methods in SPECT sinogram restoration. The clinical evaluation is conducted on clinical data of low-dose SPECT sinograms for spleen, thyroid, skull, and bone. These SPECT projection data are obtained from Discovery NM/CT670 scans. We compare the reconstructed images from the SCI-Net restored sinograms, the reconstructed images from the original low-dose sinograms, and the reconstructed images using the built-in algorithm of the Discovery NM/CT670. The results show that our method effectively reduces the coefficient of variation (COV) in the regions of interest (ROI) of the reconstructed images, thereby enhancing the quality of the reconstructed images through SPECT sinogram restoration.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our proposed SCI-Net exhibits promising performance in the restoration of low-dose SPECT projection data. In the SCI-Net, we have implemented three mechanisms based on distinct forms, which are advantageous for the model to more effectively leverage the characteristics of sinograms and achieve commendable restoration outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 American Association of Physicists in Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Ruifan</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computer Science and Engineering, and Guangdong Province Key Lab of Computational Science, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Haotian</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computer Science and Engineering, and Guangdong Province Key Lab of Computational Science, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lai</LastName><ForeName>Peng</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computer Science and Engineering, and Guangdong Province Key Lab of Computational Science, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Woliang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Haiying</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Ying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computer Science and Engineering, and Guangdong Province Key Lab of Computational Science, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2023YFB3001704</GrantID><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021B0101190003</GrantID><Agency>Special Project for Research and Development in Key areas of Guangdong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2022A1515010831</GrantID><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Med Phys</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0425746</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0094-2405</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">deep learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">low‐dose restoration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">projection data</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">single photon emission computed tomography</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sinogram‐characteristic</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39401269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mp.17459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. White paper: Initiative to Reduce Unnecessary Radiation Exposure from Medical Imaging. 2010. https://www.fda.gov/radiation‐emitting‐products/initiative‐reduce‐unnecessary‐radiation‐exposure‐medical‐imaging/white‐paper‐initiative‐reduce‐unnecessary‐radiation‐exposure‐medical‐imaging</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jerome SD, Tilkemeier PL, Farrell MB, Shaw LJ. Nationwide laboratory adherence to myocardial perfusion imaging radiation dose reduction practices: a report from the intersocietal accreditation commission data repository. JACC Card Imag. 2015;8(10):1170‐1176. doi:10.1016/j.jcmg.2015.07.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Liu C. Recent advances in cardiac SPECT instrumentation and imaging methods. Phys Med Biol. 2019;64(6):1361‐6560. doi:10.1088/1361‐6560/ab04de</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henzlova MJ, Duvall WL, Einstein AJ, Travin MI, Verberne HJ. ASNC imaging guidelines for SPECT nuclear cardiology procedures: Stress, protocols, and tracers. J Nucl Cardiol. 2016;23:606‐639. doi:10.1007/s12350‐015‐0387‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scabbio C, Malaspina S, Capozza A, et al. Impact of low‐dose SPECT imaging on normal databases and myocardial perfusion scores. Phys Med. 2019;59:163‐169. doi:10.1016/j.ejmp.2019.03.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shinohara H, Hasebe S, Uchiyama K. Quality control of SPECT on the basis of analytical SPECT reconstruction methods. Japanese Journal of Medical Physics. 1997;17(1):18‐36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Floyd CE, Bowsher JE, Munley MT, et al. Artificial neural networks for SPECT image reconstruction with optimized weighted backprojection. In: Conf Rec Nucl Sci Symp Med Imag Conf. 1991;(3):2184‐2188. doi:10.1109/NSSMIC.1991.259306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desai MD, Jenkins WK. Convolution backprojection image reconstruction for spotlight mode synthetic aperture radar. IEEE Trans Image Process. 1992;1(4):505‐517. doi:10.1109/83.199920</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruyant PP. Analytic and iterative reconstruction algorithms in SPECT. J Nucl Med Off Publ Soc Nucl Med. 2002;43(10):1343‐1358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsui BMW, Zhao X, Frey EC, Gullberg GT. Comparison between ML‐EM and WLS‐CG algorithms for SPECT image reconstruction. IEEE Trans Med Imag. 1991;38(6):1766‐1772. doi:10.1109/23.124174</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallis JW, Miller TR, Dai GM. Comparison of the convergence properties of the It‐W and OS‐EM algorithms in SPECT. IEEE Trans Nucl Sci. 1998;45(3):1317‐1323. doi:10.1109/23.682023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krol A, Li S, Shen L, Xu Y. Preconditioned alternating projection algorithms for maximum a posteriori ECT reconstruction. Inverse Probl. 2012;28(11):115005. doi:10.1088/0266‐5611/28/11/115005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Li S, Xu Y, et al. SPECT reconstruction using DCT‐induced tight framelet regularization. Med Imag Phys Med Imag. 2015;9412:94123H. doi:10.1117/12.2082118</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Y, Li S, Xu Y. A higher‐order polynomial method for SPECT reconstruction. IEEE Trans Med Imag. 2019;38(5):1271‐1283. doi:10.1109/TMI.2018.2881919</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Huang J, Li S, Lu Y, Xu Y. A content‐adaptive unstructured grid based integral equation method with the TV regularization for SPECT reconstruction. Inverse Probl &amp; Imag. 2020;14(1):27‐52. doi:10.3934/ipi.2019062</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Benabdallah N, Abou DS, et al. A projection‐domain low‐count quantitative SPECT method for α$\alpha$‐particle‐emitting radiopharmaceutical therapy. IEEE Trans Radiat Plasma Med Sci. 2023;7(1):62‐74. doi:10.1109/TRPMS.2022.3175435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apostolopoulos ID, Papandrianos NI, Feleki A, Moustakidis S, Papageorgiou EI. Deep learning‐enhanced nuclear medicine SPECT imaging applied to cardiac studies. EJNMMI Phys. 2023;10(1):6. doi:10.1186/s40658‐022‐00522‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Dewaraja YK, Fessler JA. Training end‐to‐end unrolled iterative neural networks for SPECT image reconstruction. IEEE Trans Radiat Plasma Med Sci. 2023;7(4):410‐420. doi:10.1109/TRPMS.2023.3240934</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao W, Pomper MG, Du Y. A learned reconstruction network for SPECT imaging. IEEE Trans Radiat Plasma Med Sci. 2021;5(1):26‐34. doi:10.1109/trpms.2020.2994041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Zhou B, Guo X, et al. DuDoCFNet: Dual‐domain coarse‐to‐fine progressive network for simultaneous denoising, limited‐view reconstruction, and attenuation correction of cardiac spect. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2024;43:3110‐3125. doi:10.1109/TMI.2024.3385650</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Li CY, Du Y, et al. Low dose myocardial perfusion spect denoising using an attention‐based generative adversarial network. In: IEEE Nucl Sci Symp Med Imag Conf. 2022:1‐3. doi:10.1109/NSS/MIC44845.2022.10399080</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Li Z, Ge R, Zhao J, Si H, Zhang D. Low‐Dose CT denoising via sinogram inner‐structure transformer. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2023;42(4):910‐921. doi:10.1109/TMI.2022.3219856</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Xia XG, He C, et al. An end‐to‐end deep network for reconstructing CT images directly from sparse sinograms. IEEE Trans Comput Imag. 2020;6:1548‐1560. doi:10.1109/TCI.2020.3039385</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C, Xing Y, Gao H, Zhang L, Chen Z. Sam's Net: A self‐augmented multistage deep‐learning network for end‐to‐end reconstruction of limited angle CT. IEEE Trans Med Imag. 2022;41(10):2912‐2924. doi:10.1109/TMI.2022.3175529</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Gao Q, Wu Y, et al. Quad‐Net: Quad‐domain network for CT metal artifact reduction. IEEE Trans Med Imag. 2024;1‐1. doi:10.1109/TMI.2024.3351722</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui J, Zeng P, Zeng X, et al. TriDo‐Former: A triple‐domain transformer for direct PET reconstruction from low‐dose sinograms. In: Proc Med Image Comput Comput Assist Interv ‐ MICCAI 2023. 2023:184‐194. doi:10.1007/978‐3‐031‐43999‐5_18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Li J, Liu H. A deep ADMM‐net for iterative low‐count PET reconstruction. In: Opt Health Care Biomed Opt X. SPIE/COS Photonics Asia. 2020;183‐189. doi:10.1117/12.2573412</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiang J, Dong Y, Yang Y. FISTA‐Net: Learning a fast iterative shrinkage thresholding network for inverse problems in imaging. IEEE Trans Med Imag. 2021;40(5):1329‐1339. doi:10.1109/TMI.2021.3054167</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohlberg A, Kangasmaa T, Constable C, Tikkakoski A. Comparison of deep learning‐based denoising methods in cardiac SPECT. EJNMMI phys. 2023;10(1):9. doi:10.1186/s40658‐023‐00531‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Zhang Y, Kalra MK, et al. Low‐dose CT with a residual encoder‐decoder convolutional neural network. IEEE Trans Med Imag. 2017;36(12):2524‐2535. doi:10.1109/TMI.2017.2715284</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Zhang Qi, Du Y,, et al. Dual gating myocardial perfusion SPECT denoising using a conditional generative adversarial network. Med Phys. 2022;49:5093‐5106. doi:10.1002/mp.15707</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramon AJ, Yang Y, Pretorius PH, et al. Improving diagnostic accuracy in Low‐Dose SPECT myocardial perfusion imaging with convolutional denoising networks. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2020;39:2893‐2903. doi:10.1109/TMI.2020.2979940</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Z, Rahman MA, Laforest R, et al. Need for objective task‐based evaluation of deep learning‐based denoising methods: A study in the context of myocardial perfusion SPECT. Med Phys. 2023;50(7):4122‐4137. doi:10.1002/mp.16407</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ronneberger O, Fischer P, Brox T. U‐Net: convolutional networks for biomedical image segmentation. In: Proc Med Image Comput Comput Assist Interv ‐ MICCAI 2015. 2015;9351:234‐241. doi:10.1007/978‐3‐319‐24574‐4_28</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Yang Y, Wernick MN, et al. Deep learning with noise‐to‐noise training for denoising in SPECT myocardial perfusion imaging. Med Phys. 2021;48:156‐168. doi:10.1002/mp.14577</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian C, Xu Y, Li Z, Zuo W, Fei L, Liu H. Attention‐guided CNN for image denoising. Neural Netw. 2020;124:117‐129. doi:10.1016/j.neunet.2019.12.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Zhang Y, Kalra MK, et al. Low‐dose CT with a residual encoder‐decoder convolutional neural network. IEEE Trans Med Imag. 2017;36(12):2524‐2535. doi:10.1109/TMI.2017.2715284</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chrysostomou C. Sinogram denoise based on generative adversarial networks. In: IEEE Nucl Sci Symp Med Imag Conf. 2020:1‐4. doi:10.1109/NSS/MIC42677.2020.9507945</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olia NA, Kamali‐Asi A, Tabrizi SH, et al. Deep learning‐based denoising of low‐dose SPECT myocardial perfusion images: quantitative assessment and clinical performance. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imag. 2021;49:1508‐1522. doi:10.1007/s00259‐021‐05614‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiri I, AmirMozafari Sabet K, Arabi H, et al. Standard SPECT myocardial perfusion estimation from half‐time acquisitions using deep convolutional residual neural networks. J Nucl Cardiol. 2021;28(6):2761‐2779. doi:10.1007/s12350‐020‐02119‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Zhou B, Xie H, et al. DuDoSS: “Deep‐learning‐based dual‐domain sinogram synthesis from sparsely sampled projections of cardiac SPECT.” Med Phys. 2023;50(1):89‐103. doi:10.1002/mp.15958</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiang H, Lim H, Fessler JA, Dewaraja YK. A deep neural network for fast and accurate scatter estimation in quantitative SPECT/CT under challenging scatter conditions. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imag. 2020;1‐12. doi:10.1007/s00259‐020‐04840‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helgason S. Integral Geometry and Radon Transforms. In: Proc. International Congress of Mathematicians (ICM); 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raissi M, Perdikaris P, Karniadakis GE. Physics‐informed neural networks: A deep learning framework for solving forward and inverse problems involving nonlinear partial differential equations. J Comput Phys. 2019;378:686‐707. doi:10.1016/j.jcp.2018.10.045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu J, Liu J, Tian HJ, et al. Dual attention network for scene segmentation. In: Proc. IEEE Conf Comput Vis Pattern Recognit ‐ CVPR 2019. 2019;3146‐3154. doi:10.1109/CVPR.2019.00326</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toossi M, Islamian JP, Momennezhad M, Ljungberg M, Naseri SH. Simind monte carlo simulation of a single photon emission CT. J Med Phys. 2010;35(1):42‐47. doi:10.4103/0971‐6203.55967</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segars WP, Sturgeon G, Mendonca S, Grimes J, Tsui BMW. 4D XCAT phantom for multimodality imaging research. Med Phys. 2010;37(9):4902‐4915. doi:10.1118/1.3480985</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islamian J, Toossi MT, Momennezhad M, et al. Monte carlo study of the effect of collimator thickness on T‐99m source response in single photon emission computed tomography. World J Nucl Med. 2012;11(2):70‐74. doi:10.4103/1450‐1147.103419</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darami M, Mahmoudian B, Ljungberg M, et al. Impact of wolfmet tungsten alloys as parallel‐hole collimator material on single‐photon emission computed tomography image quality and functional parameters: a simulating medical imaging nuclear detectors monte carlo study. World J Nucl Med. 2023;22(3):217‐225. doi:10.1055/s‐0043‐1771287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Girshick R, Gupta A, He K. Non‐local neural networks. In: Proc. IEEE Conf Comput Vis Pattern Recognit. ‐ CVPR 2018. 2018;7794‐7803. doi:10.1109/CVPR.2018.00813</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy AG, Navab N, Wachinger C. Concurrent spatial and channel 'squeeze &amp; excitation’ in fully convolutional networks. In: Proc Med Image Comput Comput Assist Interv ‐ MICCAI 2018. 2018;11070:421‐429. doi:10.1007/978‐3‐030‐00928‐1_48</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Liu T, Zhang J, et al. CT‐free attenuation correction for dedicated cardiac SPECT using a 3D dual squeeze‐and‐excitation residual dense network. J Nucl Cardiol. 2022;29(5):2235‐2250. doi:10.1007/s12350‐021‐02672‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Hsu W, Xie X, Cong J, Gao W. SACNN: Self‐attention convolutional neural network for low‐dose CT denoising with self‐supervised perceptual loss network. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2020;39:2289‐2301. doi:10.1109/TMI.2020.2970323</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang NE, Shen Z, Long SR, et al. The empirical mode decomposition and the Hilbert spectrum for nonlinear and non‐stationary time series analysis. Proc R Soc Lond A Math Phys Eng Sci. 1998;454:903‐995. doi:10.1098/rspa.1998.0193</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>