<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39405084</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2291-9279</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JMIR serious games</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JMIR Serious Games</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Serious Game Development for Public Health: Participatory Design Approach to COVID-19 Quarantine Policy Education.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e54968</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e54968</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e54968</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2196/54968</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Public health education plays a crucial role in effectively addressing infectious diseases such as COVID-19. However, existing educational materials often provide only foundational information, and traditional group education faces challenges due to social distancing policies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Addressing these gaps, our study introduces a serious game called "Flattening the Curve." This interactive experience immerses learners in the role of quarantine policy managers, offering unique insights into the effects and challenges of social distancing policies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The development of the game adhered to the SERES framework, ensuring a scientifically designed foundation. To achieve its learning objectives, the game incorporated learning and game mechanics including an agent-based infection model, a social distancing policy model, and an economic model, which were developed based on previous literature. After defining a broad concept of scientific and design foundations, we used a participatory design process. This study included 16 undergraduates and took place over one semester. Participants played the game, gave feedback, and answered surveys. The game was improved based on participants' feedback throughout the process. Participants' feedback was analyzed based on the Design, Play, and Experience framework. Surveys were conducted before and after the activity and analyzed to assess participants' evaluation of and satisfaction with the game.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The game successfully achieved its learning objectives, encompassing a comprehensive understanding of infectious disease characteristics; the disease transmission process; the necessity and efficacy of quarantine policies and their delicate balance with economic factors; and the concept of flattening the curve. To achieve this, the game includes the following: (1) an agent-based infection model based on the modified Susceptible-Exposed-Infectious-Hospitalized-Recovered (SEIHR) model with five infectious disease scenarios; (2) a quarantine policy model with social distancing, travel control, and intensive care unit management; and (3) an economic model that allows users to consider the impact of quarantine policies on a community's economy. In response to participatory design feedback, the game underwent meticulous modifications, including refining game systems, parameters, design elements, the user interface, and interactions. Key feedback included requests for more scenarios and engaging yet simple game elements, as well as suggestions for improving the scoring system and design features. Notably, concerns about the fairness of the outcome evaluation system (star rating system), which could incentivize prioritizing economic activity over minimizing casualties, were raised and addressed by replacing the star rating system with a progress-based vaccine development system. Quantitative evaluation results reflect participants' positive assessments of the game through the learner-centric approach.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The serious game "Flattening the Curve," developed through a participatory design approach, emerges as a valuable tool for public health education, particularly concerning social distancing policies. The game and its source code are openly accessible online, enabling widespread use for research and educational purposes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Myunghwan Kwak, Byeong-Je Kim, Ji-Bum Chung. Originally published in JMIR Serious Games (https://games.jmir.org).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kwak</LastName><ForeName>Myunghwan</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7164-5645</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil Urban Earth and Environmental Engineering, Ulsan National Institute of Science and Technology, 50, UNIST-gil, Ulsan, 44919, Republic of Korea, 82 010-2488-1506.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Byeong-Je</ForeName><Initials>BJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9149-0708</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Social Data Science, Pohang University of Science and Technology, Pohang-si, Gyeongsangbuk-do, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Advanced Nuclear Engineering, Pohang University of Science and Technology, Pohang-si, Gyeongsangbuk-do, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chung</LastName><ForeName>Ji-Bum</ForeName><Initials>JB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2388-9917</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil Urban Earth and Environmental Engineering, Ulsan National Institute of Science and Technology, 50, UNIST-gil, Ulsan, 44919, Republic of Korea, 82 010-2488-1506.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Canada</Country><MedlineTA>JMIR Serious Games</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101645255</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">game</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">learner-centric</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">online learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">quarantine policy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">serious game</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">simulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social distancing policy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>None declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39405084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/54968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">v12i1e54968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Williams SN, Armitage CJ, Tampe T, Dienes K. Public perceptions and experiences of social distancing and social isolation during the COVID-19 pandemic: a UK-based focus group study. BMJ Open. 2020 Jul 20;10(7):e039334. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2020-039334. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-039334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7387310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32690752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baum NM, Jacobson PD, Goold SD. “Listen to the people”: public deliberation about social distancing measures in a pandemic. Am J Bioeth. 2009 Nov;9(11):4–14. doi: 10.1080/15265160903197531. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15265160903197531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19882444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor S, Asmundson GJG. Negative attitudes about facemasks during the COVID-19 pandemic: The dual importance of perceived ineffectiveness and psychological reactance. PLoS One. 2021;16(2):e0246317. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0246317. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7888611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33596207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhajarine N, Adeyinka DA, McCutcheon J, Green KL, Fahlman M, Kallio N. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and refusal and associated factors in an adult population in Saskatchewan, Canada: evidence from predictive modelling. PLoS One. 2021;16(11):e0259513. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0259513. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0259513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8589208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34767603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bui LN, Berkowitz RL, Jilek W, et al. Public protests and the risk of novel coronavirus disease hospitalizations: a county-level analysis from California. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021 Sep 8;18(18):9481. doi: 10.3390/ijerph18189481. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18189481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8467497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34574407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gisondi MA, Barber R, Faust JS, et al. A deadly infodemic: social media and the power of COVID-19 misinformation. J Med Internet Res. 2022 Feb 1;24(2):e35552. doi: 10.2196/35552. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/35552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8812140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35007204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JJ, Kang KA, Wang MP, et al. Associations between COVID-19 misinformation exposure and belief with COVID-19 knowledge and preventive behaviors: cross-sectional online study. J Med Internet Res. 2020 Nov 13;22(11):e22205. doi: 10.2196/22205. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/22205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7669362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33048825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman D, Waite F, Rosebrock L, et al. Coronavirus conspiracy beliefs, mistrust, and compliance with government guidelines in England. Psychol Med. 2022 Jan;52(2):251–263. doi: 10.1017/S0033291720001890. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0033291720001890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32436485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, López Seguí F, Vidal-Alaball J, Katz MS. COVID-19 and the “Film Your Hospital” conspiracy theory: social network analysis of Twitter data. J Med Internet Res. 2020 Oct 5;22(10):e22374. doi: 10.2196/22374. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/22374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7537721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32936771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calik A, Cakmak B, Kapucu S, Inkaya B. The effectiveness of serious games designed for infection prevention and promotion of safe behaviors of senior nursing students during the COVID-19 pandemic. Am J Infect Control. 2022 Dec;50(12):1360–1367. doi: 10.1016/j.ajic.2022.02.025. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2022.02.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8881815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35231565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>All A, Plovie B, Castellar EPN, Van Looy J. Pre-test influences on the effectiveness of digital-game based learning: a case study of a fire safety game. Comput Educ. 2017 Nov;114:24–37. doi: 10.1016/j.compedu.2017.05.018. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.compedu.2017.05.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahed BT, White G, Quarles J. Play it safe: an educational cyber safety game for children in elementary school. 2019 11th International Conference on Virtual Worlds and Games for Serious Applications (VS-Games); Sep 4-6, 2019; Vienna, Austria. Presented at. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/VS-Games.2019.8864594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chettoor Jayakrishnan G, Banahatti V, Lodha S. GOVID: repurposing serious game for enterprise COVID-19 awareness. India HCI 2021; Nov 19-21, 2021; Virtual event India. Presented at. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1145/3506469.3506471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu H, Xiao Y, Li H. The effectiveness of a serious game versus online lectures for improving medical students’ coronavirus disease 2019 knowledge. Games Health J. 2021 Apr;10(2):139–144. doi: 10.1089/g4h.2020.0140. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/g4h.2020.0140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33434099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kao D, Joshi A, Mousas C, et al. Fighting COVID-19 at Purdue University: design and evaluation of a game for teaching COVID-19 hygienic best practices. FDG’21: The 16th International Conference on the Foundations of Digital Games 2021; Aug 3-6, 2021; Montreal, Canada. Presented at. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1145/3472538.3472552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill J, Corke E, Salawu M, Cotterell E, Russell M. Point of contact: investigating change in perception through a serious game for COVID-19 preventive measures. Proc ACM Hum Comput Interact. 2021 doi: 10.1145/3474701. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1145/3474701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suppan M, Catho G, Robalo Nunes T, et al. A serious game designed to promote safe behaviors among health care workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: development of “Escape COVID-19.”. JMIR Serious Games. 2020 Dec 3;8(4):e24986. doi: 10.2196/24986. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/24986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7717924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33242312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suppan M, Stuby L, Harbarth S, et al. Nationwide deployment of a serious game designed to improve COVID-19 infection prevention practices in Switzerland: prospective web-based study. JMIR Serious Games. 2021 Nov 25;9(4):e33003. doi: 10.2196/33003. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/33003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8623323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34635472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartikainen H, Iivari N, Kinnula M. Children’s design recommendations for online safety education. Int J Child Comput Interact. 2019 Dec;22:100146. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcci.2019.100146. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijcci.2019.100146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viitaharju P, Yliniemi K, Nieminen M, Karttunen AJ. Learning experiences from digital laboratory safety training. Educ Chem Eng. 2021 Jan;34:87–93. doi: 10.1016/j.ece.2020.11.009. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ece.2020.11.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhute VJ, Inguva P, Shah U, Brechtelsbauer C. Transforming traditional teaching laboratories for effective remote delivery—a review. Educ Chem Eng. 2021 Apr;35:96–104. doi: 10.1016/j.ece.2021.01.008. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ece.2021.01.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiradkar S, Rabelo L, Alasim F, Nagadi K. Virtual world as an interactive safety training platform. Inf. 2021;12(6):219. doi: 10.3390/info12060219. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/info12060219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dzeng RJ, Hsueh HH, Chang RN. 3D game-based training system for hazard identification on construction site. 2015 12th International Conference on Fuzzy Systems and Knowledge Discovery (FSKD); Aug 15-17, 2015; Zhangjiajie, China. Presented at. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/FSKD.2015.7382339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu WH, Hsiao HC, Wu PL, Lin CH, Huang SH. Investigating the learning‐theory foundations of game‐based learning: a meta‐analysis. Comp Assisted Learn. 2012 Jun;28(3):265–279. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2729.2011.00437.x. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2729.2011.00437.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verschueren S, Buffel C, Vander Stichele G. Developing theory-driven, evidence-based serious games for health: framework based on research community insights. JMIR Serious Games. 2019 May 2;7(2):e11565. doi: 10.2196/11565. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/11565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6521217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31045496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeSmet A, Thompson D, Baranowski T, Palmeira A, Verloigne M, De Bourdeaudhuij I. Is participatory design associated with the effectiveness of serious digital games for healthy lifestyle promotion? A meta-analysis. J Med Internet Res. 2016 Apr 29;18(4):e94. doi: 10.2196/jmir.4444. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.4444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4867751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27129447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismail R, Ibrahim R, Yaacob S. Participatory design method to unfold educational game design issues: a systematic review of trends and outcome. 2019 5th International Conference on Information Management (ICIM); Mar 24-27, 2019; Cambridge, United Kingdom. Presented at. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/INFOMAN.2019.8714678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spinuzzi C. The methodology of participatory design.  [24-09-2024];Tech Commun. 2005 52(2):163–174. https://www.ingentaconnect.com/contentone/stc/tc/2005/00000052/00000002/art00005 URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nunes EPS, Luz AR, Lemos EM, Nunes C. Approaches of Participatory Design in the Design Process of a Serious Game to Assist in the Learning of Hospitalized Children. Springer International Publishing; 2016. pp. 406–416. ISBN.9783319395135</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen EIK, Iversen OS. You are the real experts! - studying teenagers’ motivation in participatory design. IDC '13: Interaction Design and Children 2013; Jun 24-27, 2013; New York, USA. Presented at. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1145/2485760.2485826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falcão TP, de Andrade e Peres FM, de Morais DCS, da Silva Oliveira G. Participatory methodologies to promote student engagement in the development of educational digital games. Comput Educ. 2018 Jan;116:161–175. doi: 10.1016/j.compedu.2017.09.006. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.compedu.2017.09.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tekinbas KS, Zimmerman E. Rules of Play: Game Design Fundamentals. MIT Press; 2003. ISBN.0262240459</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winn BM. In: Handbook of Research on Effective Electronic Gaming in Education. Ferdig RE, editor. Information Science Reference; 2009. The design, play, and experience framework; pp. 1010–1024. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4018/978-1-59904-808-6.ch058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medeiros LC, Hillers VN, Chen G, Bergmann V, Kendall P, Schroeder M. Design and development of food safety knowledge and attitude scales for consumer food safety education. J Am Diet Assoc. 2004 Nov;104(11):1671–1677. doi: 10.1016/j.jada.2004.08.030. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jada.2004.08.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15499353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dragutinovic N, Twisk D.  SWOV Institute for Road Safety Research; 2006.  [24-09-2024]. The effectiveness of road safety education: a literature review.https://swov.nl/en/publicatie/effectiveness-road-safety-education-literature-review URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schafer RB, Schafer E, Bultena GL, Hoiberg EO. Food safety: an application of the health belief model. J Nutr Educ. 1993 Jan;25(1):17–24. doi: 10.1016/S0022-3182(12)80183-X. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0022-3182(12)80183-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covid-19 is now in 50 countries, and things will get worse. The Economist. Feb 29, 2020.  [22-09-2024]. https://www.economist.com/briefing/2020/02/29/covid-19-is-now-in-50-countries-and-things-will-get-worse? URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gourinchas PO. In: Mitigating the COVID Economic Crisis: Act Fast and Do Whatever. Baldwin R, Weder di B, editors. CEPR Press; 2020. Flattening the pandemic and recession curves; pp. 31–40. ISBN.9781912179299</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dias S, Queiroz K, Araujo A. Introduction to group-structured-epidemic model. J Control Autom Electr Syst. 2022 Feb;33(1):23–37. doi: 10.1007/s40313-021-00841-7. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40313-021-00841-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrante M, Ferraris E, Rovira C. On a stochastic epidemic SEIHR model and its diffusion approximation. TEST (Madr) 2016 Sep;25(3):482–502. doi: 10.1007/s11749-015-0465-z. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11749-015-0465-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang P, Qi J, Zhang S, et al. Feasibility study of mitigation and suppression strategies for controlling COVID-19 outbreaks in London and Wuhan. PLoS One. 2020;15(8):e0236857. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0236857. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0236857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7410247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32760081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kermack WO, McKendrick AG. A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics. Proc R Soc Lond A. 1927 Aug;115(772):700–721. doi: 10.1098/rspa.1927.0118. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rspa.1927.0118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, May RM. Directly transmitted infections diseases: control by vaccination. Science. 1982 Feb 26;215(4536):1053–1060. doi: 10.1126/science.7063839. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.7063839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7063839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren SY, Wang WB, Gao RD, Zhou AM. Omicron variant (B.1.1.529) of SARS-CoV-2: mutation, infectivity, transmission, and vaccine resistance. World J Clin Cases. 2022 Jan 7;10(1):1–11. doi: 10.12998/wjcc.v10.i1.1. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v10.i1.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8727245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35071500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolter N, Jassat W, Walaza S, et al. Early assessment of the clinical severity of the SARS-CoV-2 omicron variant in South Africa: a data linkage study. Lancet. 2022 Jan 29;399(10323):437–446. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00017-4. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00017-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8769664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35065011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chovatiya R, Silverberg JI. Inpatient morbidity and mortality of measles in the United States. PLoS One. 2020;15(4):e0231329. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0231329. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0231329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7188204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32343688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francis MR.  Popular Science; 2020.  [22-09-2024]. Just how contagious is COVID-19? This chart puts it in perspective.https://www.popsci.com/story/health/how-diseases-spread/ URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebola virus disease. PAHO.  [30-03-2022]. https://www.paho.org/en/topics/ebola-virus-disease URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>What you need to know about Ebola. CDC.  [23-09-2024]. https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/25845 URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gastanaduy P, Haber P, Rota PA, Patel M.  Epidemiology and Prevention of Vaccine-Preventable Diseases. CDC; 2021.  [30-09-2024]. Measles.https://www.cdc.gov/pinkbook/hcp/table-of-contents/chapter-13-measles.html URL. Accessed. ISBN.9780990449133</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Current status of COVID-19 [Website in Korean] Korea Disease Control and Prevention Agency. 2024.  [23-09-2024]. https://ncov.kdca.go.kr/pot/cv/trend/dmstc/selectMntrgSttus.do URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qualls N, Levitt A, Kanade N, et al. Community mitigation guidelines to prevent pandemic influenza - United States, 2017. MMWR Recomm Rep. 2017 Apr 21;66(1):1–34. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.rr6601a1. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.rr6601a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5837128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28426646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miksch F, Urach C, Einzinger P, Zauner G. Information and Communication Technology. Springer Berlin Heidelberg; 2014. A flexible agent-based framework for infectious disease modeling; pp. 36–45. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-55032-4_4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maharaj S, Kleczkowski A. Controlling epidemic spread by social distancing: do it well or not at all. BMC Public Health. 2012 Aug 20;12:679. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-12-679. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3563464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22905965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal A, Alomar A, Sarker A, Shah D, Shen D, Yang C. Two burning questions on COVID-19: did shutting down the economy help? can we (partially) reopen the economy without risking the second wave? arXiv. 2020 May 10; doi: 10.48550/arXiv.2005.00072. Preprint posted online on. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2005.00072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kristjanpoller W, Michell K, Minutolo MC. A causal framework to determine the effectiveness of dynamic quarantine policy to mitigate COVID-19. Appl Soft Comput. 2021 Jun;104:107241. doi: 10.1016/j.asoc.2021.107241. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.asoc.2021.107241</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7920818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33679272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer L, Broady K, Edelberg W, O’Donnell J.  Brookings Institute; 2020.  [30-09-2024]. Ten facts about COVID-19 and the US economy.https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/FutureShutdowns_Facts_LO_Final.pdf URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnab S, Lim T, Carvalho MB, et al. Mapping learning and game mechanics for serious games analysis. Brit J Educ Tech. 2015 Mar;46(2):391–411. doi: 10.1111/bjet.12113. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjet.12113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lameras P, Arnab S, Dunwell I, Stewart C, Clarke S, Petridis P. Essential features of serious games design in higher education: linking learning attributes to game mechanics. Brit J Educ Tech. 2017 Jun;48(4):972–994. doi: 10.1111/bjet.12467. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjet.12467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva FGM. Practical methodology for the design of educational serious games. Inf. 2019;11(1):14. doi: 10.3390/info11010014. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/info11010014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almala AH. A constructivist conceptual framework for a quality e-learning environment.  [24-09-2024];Dist Learn. 2005 2(5):9–12. https://www.proquest.com/docview/230696773?sourcetype=Scholarly%20Journals URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang CY, Tsai YS, Wen TH. Simulations for epidemiology and public health education. Operational Research for Emergency Planning in Healthcare. 2016;2:176–202. doi: 10.1007/978-1-137-57328-5_9. Vol. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-137-57328-5_9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hale T, Angrist N, Goldszmidt R, et al. A global panel database of pandemic policies (Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker) Nat Hum Behav. 2021 Apr;5(4):529–538. doi: 10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33686204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barclay E, Scott D, Animashaun C. The US doesn’t just need to flatten the curve. It needs to “raise the line.”. Vox. 2020.  [22-09-2024]. https://www.vox.com/2020/4/7/21201260/coronavirus-usa-chart-mask-shortage-ventilators-flatten-the-curve URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laine TH, Lindberg RSN. Designing engaging games for education: a systematic literature review on game motivators and design principles. IEEE Trans Learn Technol. 2020;13(4):804–821. doi: 10.1109/TLT.2020.3018503. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2020.3018503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarasmita MA, Larasanty LPF, Kuo LN, Cheng KJ, Chen HY. A computer-based interactive narrative and a serious game for children with asthma: development and content validity analysis. J Med Internet Res. 2021 Sep 13;23(9):e28796. doi: 10.2196/28796. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/28796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8477291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34515641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim BJ, Chung JB. Is safety education in the e-learning environment effective? Factors affecting the learning outcomes of online laboratory safety education. Saf Sci. 2023 Dec;168:106306. doi: 10.1016/j.ssci.2023.106306. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2023.106306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollio A, Magee L, Salazar JF. The making of Antarctic futures: participatory game design at the interface between science and policy. Futures. 2021 Jan;125:102662. doi: 10.1016/j.futures.2020.102662. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.futures.2020.102662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khaled R, Vasalou A. Bridging serious games and participatory design. Int J Child Comput Interact. 2014 May;2(2):93–100. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcci.2014.03.001. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijcci.2014.03.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen A, Larsen KB, Nielsen HH, Sokolov MK, Kraus M. Augmented Reality, Virtual Reality, and Computer Graphics. Springer International Publishing; 2020. Asymmetrical multiplayer versus single player: effects on game experience in a virtual reality edutainment game; pp. 22–33. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-58465-8_2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwak MH, Kim BJ, Chung JB. Flattening the Curve. GitHub. 2022.  [22-09-2024]. https://brad9704.github.io/COVID_Simulation/en-us/covid_game.html URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwak MH, Kim BJ, Chung JB. Flattening the Curve (source file) GitHub. 2022.  [22-09-2024]. https://github.com/brad9704/COVID_Simulation/releases/tag/v1.0.0 URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>