<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39405551</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-987X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of computational chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Comput Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>High-throughput molecular simulations of SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain mutants quantify correlations between dynamic fluctuations and protein expression.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jcc.27512</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Prediction of protein fitness from computational modeling is an area of active research in rational protein design. Here, we investigated whether protein fluctuations computed from molecular dynamics simulations can be used to predict the expression levels of SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain (RBD) mutants determined in the deep mutational scanning experiment of Starr et al. [Science (New York, N.Y.) 2022, 377, 420] Specifically, we performed more than 0.7 milliseconds of molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of 557 mutant RBDs in triplicate to achieve statistical significance under various simulation conditions. Our results show modest but significant anticorrelation in the range [-0.4, -0.3] between expression and RBD protein flexibility. A simple linear regression machine learning model achieved correlation coefficients in the range [0.7, 0.8], thus outperforming MD-based models, but required about 25 mutations at each residue position for training.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ovchinnikov</LastName><ForeName>Victor</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0008-7913-9633</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Karplus</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Chimie Biophysique, ISIS, Université de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>OPP1214161</GrantID><Agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>CHARMM Development Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Comput Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9878362</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0192-8651</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">deep mutational scanning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">linear regression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecular dynamics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39405551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcc.27512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>N. Andrews, J. Stowe, F. Kirsebom, S. Toffa, T. Rickeard, E. Gallagher, C. Gower, M. Kall, N. Groves, A.‐M. O'Connell, D. Simons, P. B. Blomquist, A. Zaidi, S. Nash, N. I. B. A. Aziz, S. Thelwall, G. Dabrera, R. Myers, G. Amirthalingam, S. Gharbia, J. C. Barrett, R. Elson, S. N. Ladhani, N. Ferguson, M. Zambon, C. N. Campbell, K. Brown, S. Hopkins, M. Chand, M. Ramsay, J. L. Bernal, N. Engl. J. Med. 2022, 386, 1532. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa2119451</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Shaman, M. Galanti, Science (New York, N.Y.) 2020, 370, 527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Byrne, J. McLellan, Curr. Opin. Immunol. 2022, 77, 102209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. N. Starr, A. J. Greaney, S. K. Hilton, D. Ellis, K. H. Crawford, A. S. Dingens, M. J. Navarro, J. E. Bowen, M. A. Tortorici, A. C. Walls, N. P. King, D. Veesler, J. D. Bloom, Cell 2020, 182, 1295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Ovchinnikov, S. Conti, E. Lau, F. Lightstone, M. Karplus, J. Chem. Theor. Comput. 2020, 16, 1866.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Heo, M. Feig, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2018, 115, 13276.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Raval, S. Piana, M. Eastwood, R. Dror, D. Shaw, Proteins 2012, 80, 2071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Lan, J. Ge, J. Yu, S. Shan, H. Zhou, S. Fan, Q. Zhang, X. Shi, Q. Wang, L. Zhang, X. Wang, Nature 2020, 581, 215.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Brooks, D. Janežič, M. Karplus, J. Comput. Chem. 1995, 16, 1522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Andricioaei, M. Karplus, J. Chem. Phys. 2001, 115, 6289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Tyka, A. Clarke, R. Sessions, J. Phys. Chem. B 2007, 111, 9571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Fu, W. Cai, J. H'enin, B. Roux, C. Chipot, J. Chem. Theor. Comput. 2017, 13, 5173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Huang, S. Rauscher, G. Nawrocki, T. Ran, M. Feig, B. de Groot, H. Grubmüller, A. MacKerell, Nature Methods 2017, 14, 71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. A. Pearlman, D. A. Case, J. W. Caldwell, W. S. Ross, T. E. Cheatham, S. DeBolt, D. Ferguson, G. Seibel, P. Kollman, Comput. Phys. Commun. 1995, 91, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Shivakumar, E. Harder, W. Damm, R. A. Friesner, W. Sherman, J. Chem. Theory Computat. 2012, 8, 2553.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Hess, C. Kutzner, D. van der Spoel, E. Lindahl, J. Chem. Theory Computat. 2008, 4, 435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Conti, V. Ovchinnikov, M. Karplus, J. Comput. Chem. 2022, 43, 1747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Ryan, G. Henehan, Current protocols in protein science, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Hoobken, New Jersey, 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Romero, E. Stone, C. Lamb, L. Chantranupong, A. Krause, A. Miklos, R. Hughes, B. Fechtel, A. Ellington, F. Arnold, G. Georgiou, ACS Synth. Biol. 2012, 1, 221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Jumper, R. Evans, A. Pritzel, T. Green, M. Figurnov, O. Ronneberger, K. Tunyasuvunakool, R. Bates, A. židek, A. Potapenko, A. Bridgland, C. Meyer, S. Kohl, A. Ballard, A. Cowie, B. Romera‐Paredes, S. Nikolov, R. Jain, J. Adler, T. Back, S. Petersen, D. Reiman, E. Clancy, M. Zielinski, M. Steinegger, M. Pacholska, T. Berghammer, D. Silver, O. Vinyals, A. Senior, K. Kavukcuoglu, P. Kohli, D. Hassabis, Proteins 2021, 89, 1711.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Hie, E. Zhong, B. Berger, B. Bryson, Science (New York, N.Y.) 2021, 371, 284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Biswas, G. Khimulya, E. Alley, K. Esvelt, G. Church, Nature Methods 2021, 18, 389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Starr, A. Greaney, W. Hannon, A. Loes, K. Hauser, J. Dillen, E. Ferri, A. Farrell, B. Dadonaite, M. McCallum, K. Matreyek, D. Corti, D. Veesler, G. Snell, J. Bloom, Science (New York, N.Y.) 2022, 377, 420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Louie, K. Kaczorowski, J. Barton, A. Chakraborty, M. McKay, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2018, 115, E564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Levy, A. Haldane, W. Flynn, Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol. 2017, 43, 55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Bhardwaj, V. Mulligan, C. Bahl, J. Gilmore, P. Harvey, O. Cheneval, G. Buchko, S. Pulavarti, Q. Kaas, A. Eletsky, P. Huang, W. Johnsen, P. Greisen, G. Rocklin, Y. Song, T. Linsky, A. Watkins, S. Rettie, X. Xu, L. Carter, R. Bonneau, J. Olson, E. Coutsias, C. Correnti, T. Szyperski, D. Craik, D. Baker, Nature 2016, 538, 329.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Radom, A. Plückthun, E. Paci, PLoS Comput. Biol. 2018, 14, e1006182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. W. Buchko, S. Pulavarti, V. Ovchinnikov, E. A. Shaw, S. A. Rettie, P. J. Myler, M. Karplus, T. S. D. Baker, C. D. Bahl, Prot. Sci. 2018, 27, 1611.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Gray, S. Moughon, C. Wang, O. Schueler‐Furman, B. Kuhlman, C. Rohl, D. Baker, J. Mol. Biol. 2003, 331, 281.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Conti, E. Lau, V. Ovchinnikov, Antibodies 2022, 11, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Brooks, C. Brooks, A. Mackerell, L. Nilsson, R. Petrella, B. Roux, Y. Won, G. Archontis, C. Bartels, S. Boresch, A. Caflisch, L. Caves, Q. Cui, A. R. Dinner, M. Feig, S. Fischer, J. Gao, M. Hodoscek, W. Im, K. Kuczera, T. Lazaridis, J. Ma, V. Ovchinnikov, E. Paci, R. W. Pastor, C. B. Post, J. Z. Pu, M. Schaefer, B. Tidor, R. M. Venable, H. L. Woodcock, X. Wu, W. Yang, D. M. York, M. Karplus, J. Comput. Chem. 2009, 30, 1545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Noé, F. Ille, J. Smith, S. Fischer, Proteins 2005, 59, 534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Friedrichs, P. Eastman, V. Vaidyanathan, M. Houston, S. Legrand, A. Beberg, D. Ensign, C. Bruns, V. Pande, J. Comput. Chem. 2009, 30, 864.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Ovchinnikov, M. Karplus, J. Phys. Chem. B 2023, 127, 8565.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Guvench, S. Mallajosyula, E. Raman, E. Hatcher, K. Vanommeslaeghe, T. Foster, F. Jamison, A. Mackerell, J. Chem. Theor. Comput. 2011, 7, 3162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Jorgensen, J. Tirado‐Rives, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2005, 102, 6665.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Humphrey, A. Dalke, K. Schulten, J. Mol. Graphics 1996, 14, 33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MATLAB, Version 7.10.0 (R2010a), The MathWorks Inc., Natick, Massachusetts 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Nanni, A. Lumini, Expert Syst. Appl. 2011, 38, 3185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Grantham, Science (New York, N.Y.) 1974, 185, 862.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Atchley, J. Zhao, A. Fernandes, T. Drüke, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2005, 102, 6395.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Mei, Z. Liao, Y. Zhou, S. Li, Biopolymers 2005, 80, 775.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Liu, H. Zeng, J. Mueller, B. Carter, Z. Wang, J. Schilz, G. Horny, M. Birnbaum, S. Ewert, D. Gifford, Bioinformatics (Oxford, England) 2020, 36, 2126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. J. Chorin, O. H. Hald, Stochastic Tools in Mathematics and Science, 3rd ed., Springer, New York, NY, 2013.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>