<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39405211</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1082-6742</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>38</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of avian medicine and surgery</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Avian Med Surg</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Molecular Detection of Infectious Bronchitis Virus in Captive-Bred Houbara Bustards (<i>Chlamydotis undulata</i>).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>129</StartPage><EndPage>132</EndPage><MedlinePgn>129-132</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1647/AVIANMS-D-24-00020</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This article describes the first reported case of infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) in houbara bustards (<i>Chlamydotis undulata</i>) from Saudi Arabia. Infectious bronchitis virus is a highly infectious virus that leads to major economic losses in the poultry industry. It is prevalent globally and causes severe respiratory and reproductive diseases in chickens. Although a wealth of information exists about IBV prevalence and transmission in domestic birds, similar information is lacking for houbara bustards. The major objectives of this research were to investigate whether IBV infections exist among houbara bustards at the National Wildlife Research Center in Taif, Saudi Arabia, and to determine the prevalence of this virus in this bird population. Fifty-eight oropharyngeal and cloacal swabs were gathered from 29 unvaccinated birds without clinical signs between 2017 and 2023. Extraction of complete RNA from the swab samples and reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction testing were used to identify IBV. The prevalence of IBV in this population was 37.9% (11 of 29; 95% confidence interval, 20.2-55.5%), indicating transmission asymptomatically among captive houbara bustards. This research identified for the first time that houbara bustards were exposed to IBV, and that this exposure is not uncommon. To counter IBV in Saudi Arabia, recommendations include continuous monitoring of the virus, isolation of infected birds, phylogenetic analysis, genotypic identification of the virus in houbara bustard, and development of an effective vaccination.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Rasheed</LastName><ForeName>Mohammed</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Science Department, College of Veterinary Medicine, and the Avian Research Center, King Faisal University, Al-Hofuf, Al-Ahsa 31982, Saudi Arabia, malrasheed@kfu.edu.sa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Avian Med Surg</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9512497</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1082-6742</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001351" MajorTopicYN="Y">Infectious bronchitis virus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018352" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coronavirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001715" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bird Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012529" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Saudi Arabia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001717" MajorTopicYN="Y">Birds</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chlamydotis macqueenii</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RT-PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">avian</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">avian coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">houbara bustard</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious bronchitis virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">virus detection</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39405211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1647/AVIANMS-D-24-00020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Dolz R, Vergara-Alert J, Pérez M, et al. New insights on infectious bronchitis virus pathogenesis: characterization of Italy 02 serotype in chicks and adult hens. <i>Vet Microbiol</i>. 2012;156:256–264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackwood MW, de Wit S. Infectious bronchitis. In: Swayne DE, ed. <i>Diseases of Poultry</i>. 13th ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons Inc; 2013:139–159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Rasheed M, Ball C, Manswr B, et al. Infectious bronchitis virus infection in chicken: viral load and immune responses in Harderian gland, choanal cleft and turbinate tissues compared to trachea. <i>Br Poult Sci</i>. 2022;63:484–492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beach JR, Schalm OW. A filterable virus, distinct from that of laryngotracheitis, the cause of a respiratory disease of chicks. <i>Poult Sci</i>. 1936;15:199–206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh D. Coronavirus avian infectious bronchitis virus. <i>Vet Res</i>. 2007;38:281–297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramakrishnan S, Kappala D. Avian infectious bronchitis virus. In: Malik Y, Singh R, Yadav M, eds. <i>Recent Advances in Animal Virology</i>. Springer; 2019;301–319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kariithi HM, Volkening JD, Goraichuk IV, et al. Unique variants of avian coronaviruses from indigenous chickens in Kenya. <i>Viruses</i>. 2023;15:264–264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bande F, Arshad SS, Omar, AR, et al. Pathogenesis and diagnostic approaches of avian infectious bronchitis. <i>Adv Virol</i>. 2016;2016:4621659.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Wit JJ, Cook JK, Van der Heijden HM. Infectious bronchitis virus variants: a review of the history, current situation and control measures. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 2011; 40:223–235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackwood MW. Review of infectious bronchitis virus around the world. <i>Avian Dis</i>. 2012;56:634–641.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awad F, Chhabra R, Baylis M, et al. An overview of infectious bronchitis virus in chickens. <i>Worlds Poult Sci J</i>. 2014;70:375–384.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carstens EB. Ratification vote on taxonomic proposals to the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (2009). <i>Arch Virol</i>. 2009;155:133–146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Wit JJ, Cook JKA. Spotlight on avian coronaviruses. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 2020;49:313–316.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Rasheed M, Shawky, M, El-Sabagh I, et al. Circulation of infectious bronchitis virus among guineafowls in Al-Ahsa province, Saudi Arabia. <i>Braz J Poult Sci</i>. 2023;25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goriup PD. The world status of the houbara bustard <i>Chlamydotis undulata</i>. <i>Bird Conserv Int</i>. 1997;7:373–397.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailey TA, ed. <i>Diseases and Medical Management of Houbara Bustards and Other Otididae</i>. National Avian Research Centre; 2008;225–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolman PM, Scotland KM, Burnside RJ, et al. Sustainable hunting and the conservation of the threatened houbara bustards. <i>J Nat Conserv</i>. 2021;61:126000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shobrak MY, Hassan SA, Stiévenart C, et al. Prevalence and antibiotic resistance profile of intestinal bacteria isolated from captive adult houbara bustards (<i>Chlamydotis macqueenii</i>) exposed to natural weather conditions in Saudi Arabia. <i>Glob Vet</i>. 2013;10:276–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones RM, Ellis RJ, Cox WJ, et al. Development and validation of RT-PCR tests for the detection and S1 genotyping of infectious bronchitis virus and other closely related gammacoronaviruses within clinical samples. <i>Transbound Emerg Dis</i>. 2011;58:411–420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Handberg K, Nielsen OL, Pedersen MW, et al. Detection and strain differentiation of infectious bronchitis virus in tracheal tissues from experimentally infected chickens by reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction: comparison with an immunohistochemical technique. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 1999;28:327–335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh D. Coronaviruses in poultry and other birds. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 2005;34:439–448.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suryaman GK, Soejoedono RD, Setiyono A, et al. Isolation and characterization of avian coronavirus from healthy Eclectus parrots (<i>Eclectus roratus</i>) from Indonesia. <i>Vet World</i>. 2019;12:1797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Besar SA, Arshad SS, Ramanoon SZ, et al. Isolation and characterization of avian coronavirus from diagnostic cases of selected bird species in Malaysia. <i>Pertanika J Trop Agric Sci</i>. 2023;46:503–516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh D, Mawditt K, Welchman D, et al. Coronaviruses from pheasants (<i>Phasianus colchicus</i>) are genetically closely related to coronaviruses of domestic fowl (infectious bronchitis virus) and turkeys. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 2002;31:81–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Promkuntod N. Dynamics of avian coronavirus circulation in commercial and non-commercial birds in Asia—a review. <i>Vet Q</i>. 2015;36:30–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebiyi AI, Fagbohun AF. Infectious bronchitis virus in captured free-living, free-range and intensively reared birds in Southwest Nigeria. <i>Folia Vet</i>. 2017;61:23–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guy JS. Turkey coronavirus is more closely related to avian infectious bronchitis virus than to mammalian coronaviruses: a review. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 2000;29:207–212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismail MH, Tang Y, Saif YM. Pathogenicity of turkey coronavirus in turkeys and chickens. <i>Avian Dis</i>. 2003; 47:515–522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bitrus I, Shittu I, Meseko CA, et al. Occurrence and molecular detection of avian coronavirus in selected live bird markets, northwestern, Nigeria. <i>Sokoto J Vet Sci</i>. 2021;18:226–229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Wit JJ, Cook JK. Factors influencing the outcome of infectious bronchitis vaccination and challenge experiments. <i>Avian Pathol</i>. 2014;43:485–497.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>