<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39417099</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>medRxiv : the preprint server for health sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>medRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association of COVID-19 risk factors with systemic fungal infections in hospitalized patients.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.10.10.24315254</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.10.10.24315254</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A new category of systemic co-infections that emerged with the COVID-19 pandemic is known as COVID-19-associated (CA) fungal infections, which include pulmonary aspergillosis (CAPA), candidiasis (CAC), and mucormycosis (CAM). We aimed to study the association between patient characteristics of hospitalized COVID-19 patients, COVID-19 comorbidities, and COVID-19 therapies with secondary non-superficial fungal infections.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We performed descriptive and regression analyses of data from 4,999 hospitalized COVID-19 patients from the University of Kentucky Healthcare (UKHC) system.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The patients with secondary systemic fungal infections had a 6-fold higher risk of death than those without such infections. Generally, the risk factors for severe COVID-19 (age, obesity, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and lack of COVID-19 vaccination) were strong predictors of a secondary fungal infection. However, several characteristics had much higher risks, suggesting that a causative link may be at play: ICU admission, mechanical ventilation, length of hospital stay, and steroid use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In sum, this study found that the known risk factors for severe COVID-19 disease, age, diabetes, cardiovascular disease, obesity, ventilation, and high steroid doses were all predictors of a secondary fungal infection. Steroid therapy may need to be modified to account for a risk or a presence of a fungal infection in vulnerable patients.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wilbourn</LastName><ForeName>Abbygail C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0008-2658-0695</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Kentucky, College of Pharmacy, 789 South Limestone St., Lexington, KY, 40536-0596, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsodikov</LastName><ForeName>Oleg V</ForeName><Initials>OV</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7094-4216</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Kentucky, College of Pharmacy, 789 South Limestone St., Lexington, KY, 40536-0596, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garneau-Tsodikova</LastName><ForeName>Sylvie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7961-5555</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Kentucky, College of Pharmacy, 789 South Limestone St., Lexington, KY, 40536-0596, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>UL1 TR001998</GrantID><Acronym>TR</Acronym><Agency>NCATS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>medRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101767986</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aspergillosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Candidiasis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mortality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ventilator</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Viral pneumonia</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest/Competing interests The authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39417099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11482998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.10.10.24315254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.10.10.24315254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>https://www.niaid.nih.gov/diseases-conditions/coronaviruses.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, Yu Y, Xu J, Shu H, Xia J, Liu H, et al. Clinical course and outcomes of critically ill patients with SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia in Wuhan, China: A single-centered, retrospective, observational study. Lancet Respir Med. 2020;8(5):475–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32105632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim SH, Hong JY, Bae S, Lee H, Wi YM, Ko JH, et al. Risk factors for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)-associated pulmonary aspergillosis in critically ill patients: A nationwide, multicenter, retrospective cohort study. J Korean Med Sci. 2022;37(18):e134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9091428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35535369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leistner R, Schroeter L, Adam T, Poddubnyy D, Stegemann M, Siegmund B, et al. Corticosteroids as risk factor for COVID-19-associated pulmonary aspergillosis in intensive care patients. Crit Care. 2022;26(1):30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8796178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35090528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewi IM, Janssen NA, Rosati D, Bruno M, Netea MG, Bruggemann RJ, et al. Invasive pulmonary aspergillosis associated with viral pneumonitis. Curr Opin Microbiol. 2021;62:21–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34034082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muthu V, Rudramurthy SM, Chakrabarti A, Agarwal R. Epidemiology and pathophysiology of COVID-19-associated mucormycosis: India versus the rest of the world. Mycopathologia. 2021;186(6):739–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8375614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34414555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoenigl M, Seidel D, Sprute R, Cunha C, Oliverio M, Goldman GH, et al. COVID-19-associated fungal infections. Nat Microbiol. 2022;7(8):1127–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9362108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35918423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morton CO, Griffiths JS, Loeffler J, Orr S, White PL. Defective antifungal immunity in patients with COVID-19. Front Immunol. 2022;13:1080822.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9750792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36531987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borczuk AC, Yantiss RK. The pathogenesis of coronavirus-19 disease. J Biomed Sci. 2022;29(1):87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9597981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36289507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim YM, Shin EC. Type I and III interferon responses in SARS-CoV-2 infection. Exp Mol Med. 2021;53(5):750–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8099704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33953323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park A, Iwasaki A. Type I and type III interferons - Induction, signaling, evasion, and application to combat COVID-19. Cell Host Microbe. 2020;27(6):870–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7255347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32464097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galani IE, Rovina N, Lampropoulou V, Triantafyllia V, Manioudaki M, Pavlos E, et al. Untuned antiviral immunity in COVID-19 revealed by temporal type I/III interferon patterns and flu comparison. Nat Immunol. 2021;22(1):32–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33277638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruetsch C, Brglez V, Cremoni M, Zorzi K, Fernandez C, Boyer-Suavet S, et al. Functional exhaustion of type I and II interferons production in severe COVID-19 patients. Front Med (Lausanne). 2020;7:603961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7873370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33585507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grifoni A, Weiskopf D, Ramirez SI, Mateus J, Dan JM, Moderbacher CR, et al. Targets of T cell responses to SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus in humans with COVID-19 disease and unexposed individuals. Cell. 2020;181(7):1489–501 e15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7237901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32473127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wildner NH, Ahmadi P, Schulte S, Brauneck F, Kohsar M, Lutgehetmann M, et al. B cell analysis in SARS-CoV-2 versus malaria: Increased frequencies of plasmablasts and atypical memory B cells in COVID-19. J Leukoc Biol. 2021;109(1):77–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10016889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33617048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/management/clinical-management/hospitalized-adults--therapeutic-management/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Therapeutic management of hospitalized adults with COVID-19. NIH A, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malaska J, Stasek J, Duska F, Balik M, Maca J, Hruda J, et al. Effect of dexamethasone in patients with ARDS and COVID-19 - prospective, multi-centre, open-label, parallel-group, randomised controlled trial (REMED trial): A structured summary of a study protocol for a randomised controlled trial. Trials. 2021;22(1):172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7917377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33648568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taboada M, Rodriguez N, Varela PM, Rodriguez MT, Abelleira R, Gonzalez A, et al. Effect of high versus low dose of dexamethasone on clinical worsening in patients hospitalised with moderate or severe COVID-19 pneumonia: an open-label, randomised clinical trial. Eur Respir J. 2022;60(2).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8678498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34916266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angus DC, Berry S, Lewis RJ, Al-Beidh F, Arabi Y, van Bentum-Puijk W, et al. The REMAP-CAP (Randomized Embedded Multifactorial Adaptive Platform for Community-acquired Pneumonia) study. Rationale and design. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2020;17(7):879–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7328186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32267771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tocilizumab [package insert]. Genentech ISF, CA; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prattes J, Wauters J, Giacobbe DR, Salmanton-Garcia J, Maertens J, Bourgeois M, et al. Risk factors and outcome of pulmonary aspergillosis in critically ill coronavirus disease 2019 patients-a multinational observational study by the European Confederation of Medical Mycology. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2022;28(4):580–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8387556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34454093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezeokoli OT, Gcilitshana O, Pohl CH. Risk factors for fungal co-infections in critically ill COVID-19 patients, with a focus on immunosuppressants. J Fungi (Basel). 2021;7(7).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8304654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34356924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song G, Liang G, Liu W. Fungal co-infections associated with global COVID-19 pandemic: A clinical and diagnostic perspective from China. Mycopathologia. 2020;185(4):599–606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7394275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32737747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdalla S, Almaslamani MA, Hashim SM, Ibrahim AS, Omrani AS. Fatal coronavirus disease 2019-associated pulmonary aspergillosis; A report of two cases and review of the literature. IDCases. 2020;22:e00935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7443053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32864340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Almeida JN Jr., Francisco EC, Hagen F, Brandao IB, Pereira FM, Presta Dias PH, et al. Emergence of Candida auris in Brazil in a COVID-19 intensive care unit. J Fungi (Basel). 2021;7(3):220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8002986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33803060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang CC, Senining R, Kim J, Goyal R. An acute pulmonary coccidioidomycosis coinfection in a patient presenting with multifocal pneumonia with COVID-19. J Investig Med High Impact Case Rep. 2020;8:2324709620972244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7658503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33167717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen N, Zhou M, Dong X, Qu J, Gong F, Han Y, et al. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: A descriptive study. Lancet. 2020;395(10223):507–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7135076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32007143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benedetti MF, de Abreu MS, Cadena RC, Arias MC, Posse G, Capece P, et al. Invasive pulmonary aspergillosis and candidiasis in a critically ill patient with COVID-19. J Mycol Med. 2022;32(2):101251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8801853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35123158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meikle AW, Tyler FH. Potency and duration of action of glucocorticoids. Effects of hydrocortisone, prednisone and dexamethasone on human pituitary-adrenal function. Am J Med. 1977;63(2):200–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">888843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu D, Ahmet A, Ward L, Krishnamoorthy P, Mandelcorn ED, Leigh R, et al. A practical guide to the monitoring and management of the complications of systemic corticosteroid therapy. Allergy Asthma Clin Immunol. 2013;9(1):30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3765115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23947590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenthal N, Cao Z, Gundrum J, Sianis J, Safo S. Risk factors associated with in-hospital mortality in a US national sample of patients with COVID-19. JAMA Netw Open. 2020;3(12):e2029058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7729428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko JY, Danielson ML, Town M, Derado G, Greenlund KJ, Kirley PD, et al. Risk factors for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)-associated hospitalization: COVID-19-associated hospitalization surveillance network and behavioral risk factor surveillance system. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;72(11):e695–e703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7543371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32945846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salazar F, Bignell E, Brown GD, Cook PC, Warris A. Pathogenesis of respiratory viral and fungal coinfections. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2022;35(1):e0009421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8597983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34788127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shieh WJ, Blau DM, Denison AM, Deleon-Carnes M, Adem P, Bhatnagar J, et al. 2009 pandemic influenza A (H1N1): Pathology and pathogenesis of 100 fatal cases in the United States. Am J Pathol. 2010;177(1):166–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2893660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20508031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seyedjavadi SS, Bagheri P, Nasiri MJ, Razzaghi-Abyaneh M, Goudarzi M. Fungal infection in co-infected patients with COVID-19: An overview of case reports/case series and systematic review. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:888452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9298665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35875562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng J, Wang Q, Mei H, Zheng H, Liang G, She X, et al. Fungal co-infection in COVID-19 patients: Evidence from a systematic review and meta-analysis. Aging (Albany NY). 2021;13(6):7745–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8034918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33744863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio-Rivas M, Forero CG, Mora-Lujan JM, Montero A, Formiga F, Homs NA, et al. Beneficial and harmful outcomes of tocilizumab in severe COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Pharmacotherapy. 2021;41(11):884–906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8661749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34558742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborti A, Jaiswal A, Verma PK, Singhal R. A prospective study of fungal colonization and invasive fungal disease in long-term mechanically ventilated patients in a respiratory intensive care unit. Indian J Crit Care Med. 2018;22(8):597–601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6108304</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30186011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Group RC, Horby P, Lim WS, Emberson JR, Mafham M, Bell JL, et al. Dexamethasone in hospitalized patients with Covid-19. N Engl J Med. 2021;384(8):693–704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7383595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32678530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chimote AA, Alshwimi AO, Chirra M, Gawali VS, Powers-Fletcher MV, Hudock KM, et al. Immune and ionic mechanisms mediating the effect of dexamethasone in severe COVID-19. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1143350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10080085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37033961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najeeb H, Siddiqui SA, Anas Z, Ali SH, Usmani SUR, Jawed F, et al. The menace of Candida auris epidemic amidst the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review. Diseases. 2022;10(3):58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9497911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36135214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>