<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39412115</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2842</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of oral rehabilitation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Oral Rehabil</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Oral Health Related Factors Predicting Severe COVID-19 Disease in Elderly Swedes.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/joor.13879</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To analyse different background factors that may serve as predictors for acquiring symptoms of severe COVID-19 disease.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A postal questionnaire was sent to the total population of individuals born between 1942 (80 years, n = 6299) and 1932 (90 years, n = 1904) living in the Örebro and Östergötland counties, Sweden, in 2017 and repeated in 2022. Tentative predictive factors for self-reported severe COVID-19 disease were based on the responses from the 2017 questionnaire related to general and oral health and prior to the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Response rate to the main questionnaire in 2022 was 66% (5375/8203), and 577 reported having been sick with COVID-19 out of which 359 agreed to answer a separate questionnaire on COVID-19. This questionnaire was returned by 278/359 of the participants corresponding to a response rate of 77%. Information gleaned from the 2017 pre-COVID-19 survey revealed a relatively large number of associations between severity of subsequently self-reported COVID-19 disease and several diverse tentative related factors found in unadjusted regression analyses. Based on statistically significant correlations in the adjusted regression analysis, significant predictive factors (based on self-reports from 2017) for contracting severe COVID-19 were in decreasing order of odds ratios (OR): reported removable partial or complete denture usage (OR 6.2, CI 2.2-17.2); reported periodontal problems in the past year (OR 3.4, CI 1.1-10.4); and reported daytime dry mouth (OR 2.5, CI 1.2-5.2).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Removable dentures, periodontal problems and daytime dry mouth were predictors for developing symptoms of severe COVID-19 disease.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Oral Rehabilitation published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johansson</LastName><ForeName>Ann-Katrin</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9478-6435</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Dentistry-Cariology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Omar</LastName><ForeName>Ridwaan</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Dentistry, Kuwait University, Safat, Kuwait.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lehmann</LastName><ForeName>Sverre</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Science, Faculty of Medicine, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Thoracic Medicine, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sannevik</LastName><ForeName>Josefin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dentistry, Örebro County Council, Örebro, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mastrovito</LastName><ForeName>Berit</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dental Commissioning Unit, Östergötland County Council, Linköping, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johansson</LastName><ForeName>Anders</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7933-1624</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Thoracic Medicine, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Dentistry-Prosthodontics, Faculty of Medicine, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Oral Rehabil</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0433604</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0305-182X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ageing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">corona</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">denture</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dry mouth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">periodontitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">questionnaire</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39412115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joor.13879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, “WHO COVID‐19 Dashboard. COVID‐19 deaths | WHO COVID‐19 dashboard,” accessed July 30, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Harris, “Most COVID‐19 Deaths Worldwide Were Among Older People,” Journal of the American Medical Association 329 (2023): 704, https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2023.1554.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sweden Statstics, “Statistik‐Covid19‐Avlidna,” accessed July 30, 2024, statistik‐covid19‐avlidna.xlsx (live.com).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Ciarambino, P. Crispino, G. Minervini, and M. Giordano, “COVID‐19 and Frailty,” Vaccine 11 (2023): 606, https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines11030606.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. G. Dessie and T. Zewotir, “Mortality‐Related Risk Factors of COVID‐19: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of 42 Studies and 423,117 Patients,” BMC Infectious Diseases 21 (2021): 855, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879‐021‐06536‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Oboza, N. Ogarek, M. Olszanecka‐Glinianowicz, and P. Kocelak, “The Main Causes of Death in Patients With COVID‐19,” European Review for Medical and Pharmacological Sciences 27 (2023): 2165–2172, https://doi.org/10.26355/eurrev_202303_31589.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. G. Kim, A. Zhang, A. M. Rauseo, et al., “The Salivary and Nasopharyngeal Microbiomes Are Associated With SARS‐CoV‐2 Infection and Disease Severity,” Journal of Medical Virology 95 (2023): e28445, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.28445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Dyrhovden, T. M. Eagan, Ø. Fløtten, et al., “Pleural Empyema Caused by Streptococcus intermedius and Fusobacterium nucleatum: A Distinct Entity of Pleural Infections,” Clinical Infectious Diseases 77 (2023): 1361–1371, https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/ciad378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Tan, M. M. Zhong, Q. Liu, et al., “Potential Interaction Between the Oral Microbiota and COVID‐19: A Meta‐Analysis and Bioinformatics Prediction,” Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology 13 (2023): 1193340, https://doi.org/10.3389/fcimb.2023.1193340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Hajishengallis, T. Chavakis, and J. D. Lambris, “Current Understanding of Periodontal Disease Pathogenesis and Targets for Host‐Modulation Therapy,” Periodontology 2000 2020, no. 84 (2000): 14–34, https://doi.org/10.1111/prd.12331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. A. Al‐Maweri, M. N. Alhajj, E. Halboub, et al., “The Impact of Periodontal Disease on the Clinical Outcomes of COVID‐19: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis,” BMC Oral Health 23 (2023): 658, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12903‐023‐03378‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Johansson, R. Omar, B. Mastrovito, J. Sannevik, G. E. Carlsson, and A. Johansson, “Xerostomia in 75–85‐Year‐Olds: A Longitudinal Population Study,” Journal of Oral Rehabilitation 50 (2023): 812–821, https://doi.org/10.1111/joor.13512.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. AlmståhI, M. Wikström, I. Stenberg, A. Jakobsson, and B. Fagerberg‐Mohlin, “Oral Microbiota Associated With Hyposalivation of Different Origins,” Oral Microbiology and Immunology 18 (2003): 1–8, https://doi.org/10.1034/j.1399‐302x.2003.180101.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Alzamil, T. T. Wu, E. van Wijngaarden, et al., “Removable Denture Wearing as a Risk Predictor for Pneumonia Incidence and Time to Event in Older Adults,” JDR Clinical &amp; Translational Research 23 (2021): 66–75, https://doi.org/10.1177/23800844211049406.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. A. Twigg, A. Smith, C. Haury, et al., “Compositional Shifts Within the Denture‐Associated Bacteriome in Pneumonia—An Analytical Cross‐Sectional Study,” Journal of Medical Microbiology 72: (2023): 1–10, https://doi.org/10.1099/jmm.0.001702.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. T. Awatade, P. A. B. Wark, A. S. L. Chan, et al., “The Complex Association Between COPD and COVID‐19,” Journal of Clinical Medicine 12 (2023): 3791, https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm12113791.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Przybyłowska, R. Rubinsztajn, R. Chazan, E. Swoboda‐Kopeć, J. Kostrzewa‐Janicka, and E. Mierzwińska‐Nastalska, “The Prevalence of Oral Inflammation Among Denture Wearing Patients With Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease,” Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology 858 (2015): 87–91, https://doi.org/10.1007/5584_2015_128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. S. Jerônimo, R. P. Esteves Lima, T. Y. U. Suzuki, J. A. C. Discacciati, and C. L. B. Bhering, “Oral Candidiasis and COVID‐19 in Users of Removable Dentures: Is Special Oral Care Needed?,” Gerontology 68 (2022): 80–85, https://doi.org/10.1159/000515214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Johansson, R. Omar, S. Lehmann, J. Sannevik, B. Mastrovito, and A. Johansson, “General and Orofacial Symptoms Associated With Acute and Long COVID in 80‐ and 90‐Year‐Old Swedish COVID‐19 Survivors,” Journal of Dentistry 141 (2024): 104824, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jdent.2023.104824.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, “Vaccinating Older Adults Against COVID‐19 2023,” accessed July 30, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. K. Gazdeck, S. R. Fruscione, G. R. Adami, Y. Zhou, L. F. Cooper, and J. L. Schwartz, “Diversity of the Oral Microbiome Between Dentate and Edentulous Individuals,” Oral Diseases 25 (2019): 911–918, https://doi.org/10.1111/odi.13039.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. A. Costa, A. C. S. Vilela, S. A. Oliveira, et al., “Poor Oral Health Status and Adverse COVID‐19 Outcomes: A Preliminary Study in Hospitalized Patients,” Journal of Periodontology 93 (2022): 1889–1901, https://doi.org/10.1002/JPER.21‐0624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Qi, M. E. Northridge, M. Hu, and B. Wu, “Oral Health Conditions and COVID‐19: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of the Current Evidence,” Aging and Health Research 2 (2022): 100064, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ahr.2022.100064.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Lynge Pedersen and D. Belstrøm, “The Role of Natural Salivary Defences in Maintaining a Healthy Oral Microbiota,” Journal of Dentistry 80, no. Suppl 1 (2019): S3–S12, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jdent.2018.08.010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, “Oral Health,” accessed July 30, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statista, “U.S. Population: Usage of Dentures From 2012 to 2024. U.S: Usage of Dentures 2012‐2024 | Statista,” accessed July 30, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public Health England, “National Dental Epidemiology Programme for England,” in Oral Health Survey of Adults Attending General Dental Practices. Government Digital Service, London; (2018), accessed July 30, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Trindade, R. Carvalho, V. Machado, L. Chambrone, J. J. Mendes, and J. Botelho, “Prevalence of Periodontitis in Dentate People Between 2011 and 2020: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of Epidemiological Studies,” Journal of Clinical Periodontology 50 (2023): 604–626, https://doi.org/10.1111/jcpe.13769.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>