<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39411688</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9175</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced biomedical research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Biomed Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Autonomic Response Latency Revisited: Assessment of Repeatability in Healthy Subjects.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>60</StartPage><MedlinePgn>60</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">60</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/abr.abr_409_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Autonomic function assessment provides valuable information regarding the status of the autonomic nervous system. The time lag between the onset of orthostasis and the peak/nadir of heart rate response is a surrogate of the integrity of underlying autonomic neural pathways. Autonomic response latency (ARL) is a relatively novel yet underreported parameter in this context. Test-retest repeatability of this parameter has not been evaluated previously.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We recruited 31 healthy adults (17 males and 14 females; 29.00 ± 5.44 years) and subjected them to postural challenge tests on five instances - forenoon and afternoon of day 1, the next day, 1 week later, and 1 month later. Tachycardia and bradycardia latencies (TL and BL) were computed using heart rate derived from digital ECG data. Repeatability was assessed using the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) and coefficient of variation (CoV).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">ICCs for TL and BL were 0.69 (0.56, 0.82) and 0.77 (0.66, 0.87), respectively. The CoVs for TL and BL were 14.8% and 12.4%, respectively. Sex-based subgroup analysis revealed ICCs for TL and BL in males to be 0.71 (0.53, 0.86) and 0.74 (0.57, 0.88) and in females to be 0.68 (0.64, 0.86) and 0.82 (0.66, 0.93), respectively. CoVs for TL and BL were 14.4% and 13.8% in male subjects and 15.4% and 10.7% in female subjects, respectively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">ARL to orthostatic challenge demonstrated moderate to good test-retest repeatability. Based on our observations, we propose that ARL has potential as a consistent and repeatable index for the assessment of the integrity of autonomic neural pathways and therefore can help in the diagnosis of autonomic neuropathy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Advanced Biomedical Research.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jose</LastName><ForeName>Annie S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srivastav</LastName><ForeName>Shival</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mehta</LastName><ForeName>Bharati</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Biomed Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101586897</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9175</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Autonomic denervation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">autonomic nervous system</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">heart rate</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neurophysiology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors do not declare any conflict of interest, financial or otherwise.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39411688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11478735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/abr.abr_409_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ABR-13-60</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tewari HK, Gadia R, Kumar D, Venkatesh P, Garg SP. Sympathetic-parasympathetic activity and reactivity in central serous chorioretinopathy: A case-control study. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2006;47:3474–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16877418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jyotsna VP, Singh AK, Deepak KK, Sreenivas V. Progression of cardiac autonomic dysfunction in newly detected type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2010;90:e5–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20452081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khandelwal E, Jaryal AK, Deepak KK. Pattern and prevalence of cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy in diabetics visiting a tertiary care referral center in India. Indian J Physiol Pharmacol. 2011;55:119–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22319892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heart rate variability. Standards of measurement, physiological interpretation, and clinical use. Task force of the European Society of cardiology and the North American society of pacing and electrophysiology. Eur Heart J. 1996;17:354–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8737210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham T, Lau ZJ, Chen SHA, Makowski D. Heart rate variability in psychology: A review of HRV indices and an analysis tutorial. Sensors (Basel) 2021;21:3998.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8230044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34207927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos-de-Araújo AD, Shida-Marinho R, Pontes-Silva A. Heart rate variability (HRV): Checklist for observational and experimental studies. Autoimmun Rev. 2022;21:103190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36103963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewing DJ, Campbell IW, Murray A, Neilson JM, Clarke BF. Immediate heart-rate response to standing: Simple test for autonomic neuropathy in diabetes. Br Med J. 1978;1:145–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1602825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">620228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewing DJ. Testing for autonomic neuropathy. Lancet. 1981;1:224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6109894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewing DJ, Clarke BF. Diagnosis and management of diabetic autonomic neuropathy. Br Med J (Clin Res Ed) 1982;285:916–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1500018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6811067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewing DJ, Martyn CN, Young RJ, Clarke BF. The value of cardiovascular autonomic function tests: 10 years experience in diabetes. Diabetes Care. 1985;8:491–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4053936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ueda T, Yoshimura N, Yoshida O. Diabetic cystopathy: Relationship to autonomic neuropathy detected by sympathetic skin response. J Urol. 1997;157:580–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8996363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazhel B, Yetkin I, Irkeç C, Koçer B. Sympathetic skin response in diabetic neuropathy. Electromyogr Clin Neurophysiol. 2002;42:181–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11977432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Lieshout JJ, Harms MP, Pott F, Jenstrup M, Secher NH. Stroke volume of the heart and thoracic fluid content during head-up and head-down tilt in humans. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2005;49:1287–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16146465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laitinen T, Niskanen L, Geelen G, Länsimies E, Hartikainen J. Age dependency of cardiovascular autonomic responses to head-up tilt in healthy subjects. J Appl Physiol (1985) 2004;96:2333–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14766788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiner BC. Valsalva maneuver. Clin Med Res. 2005;3:55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1183428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16012118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Looga R. The Valsalva manoeuvre--cardiovascular effects and performance technique: A critical review. Respir Physiol Neurobiol. 2005;147:39–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15848122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pstras L, Thomaseth K, Waniewski J, Balzani I, Bellavere F. The Valsalva manoeuvre: Physiology and clinical examples. Acta Physiol (Oxf) 2016;217:103–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26662857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastav S, Jamil RT, Zeltser R.  StatPearls. StatPearls publishing; Treasure island (FL): 2023. Valsalva maneuver. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK537248/ . [Last accessed on 3 Jun 2023]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30725933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstein DS, Cheshire WP., Jr Beat-to-beat blood pressure and heart rate responses to the Valsalva maneuver. Clin Auton Res. 2017;27:361–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8897824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29052077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastav S, Chandran DS, Jaryal AK, Deepak KK. Comparison of baroreflex responses to lower body negative pressure and Valsalva maneuver in healthy subjects. Indian Journal of Physiology and Pharmacology. 2018;62:278–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma RK, Deepak KK, Bijlani RL, Rao PS. Short-term physical training alters cardiovascular autonomic response amplitude and latencies. Indian J Physiol Pharmacol. 2004;48:165–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15521555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, Gøtzsche PC, Vandenbroucke JP, et al. The strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement: Guidelines for reporting observational studies. J Clin Epidemiol. 2008;61:344–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18313558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartlett JW, Frost C. Reliability, repeatability and reproducibility: Analysis of measurement errors in continuous variables. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2008;31:466–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18306169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ravichandran S, Srivastav S, Kamble PH, Chambial S, Shukla R, Sharma P, et al. VEGF-A and cardiac autonomic function in newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes mellitus: A cross-sectional study at a tertiary care center. J Family Med Prim Care. 2019;8:3185–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6857358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31742140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoonjans F, Zalata A, Depuydt CE, Comhaire FH. MedCalc: A new computer program for medical statistics. Comput Methods Programs Biomed. 1995;48:257–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8925653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoonjans F, Zalata A, Depuydt CE, Comhaire FH. MedCalc: a new computer program for medical statistics. Comput Methods Programs Biomed. 1995;48:257–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8925653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomasi J, Zai CC, Pouget JG, Tiwari AK, Kennedy JL. Heart rate variability: Evaluating a potential biomarker of anxiety disorders. Psychophysiology. 2024;61:e14481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37990619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roche F, Pichot V, Mouhli-Gasmi L, Monier M, Barthélémy JC, Berger M, Celle S, Chouchou F. Anatomy and physiology of the autonomic nervous system: Implication on the choice of diagnostic/monitoring tools in 2023. Rev Neurol (Paris) 2024;180:42–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38176987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prokhorov MD, Karavaev AS, Ishbulatov YM, Ponomarenko VI, Kiselev AR, Kurths J. Interbeat interval variability versus frequency modulation of heart rate. Phys Rev E. 2021;103:042404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34005986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ravits JM. AAEM minimonograph #48: Autonomic nervous system testing. Muscle Nerve. 1997;20:919–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9236782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low PA. Testing the autonomic nervous system. Semin Neurol. 2003;23:407–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15088262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low PA. Laboratory evaluation of autonomic function. Suppl Clin Neurophysiol. 2004;57:358–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16106634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borst C, Wieling W, van Brederode JF, Hond A, de Rijk LG, Dunning AJ. Mechanisms of initial heart rate response to postural change. Am J Physiol. 1982;243:H676–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7137360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borst C, van Brederode JF, Wieling W, van Montfrans GA, Dunning AJ. Mechanisms of initial blood pressure response to postural change. Clin Sci (Lond) 1984;67:321–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6467836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieling W, Borst C, Karemaker JM, Dunning AJ. Testing for autonomic neuropathy: Initial heart rate response to active and passive changes of posture. Clin Physiol. 1985;5(Suppl 5):23–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3914385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieling W, Borst C, van Brederode JF, van Dongen Torman MA, van Montfrans GA, Dunning AJ. Testing for autonomic neuropathy: Heart rate changes after orthostatic manoeuvres and static muscle contractions. Clin Sci (Lond) 1983;64:581–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6839664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman R. Assessment of cardiovascular autonomic function. Clin Neurophysiol. 2006;117:716–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16464634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman R, Chapleau MW. Testing the autonomic nervous system. Handb Clin Neurol. 2013;115:115–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23931777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartko JJ. The intraclass correlation coefficient as a measure of reliability. Psychol Rep. 1966;19:3–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5942109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koo TK, Li MY. A guideline of selecting and reporting intraclass correlation coefficients for reliability research. J Chiropr Med. 2016;15:155–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4913118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27330520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Figueroa JJ, Cheshire WP, Claydon VE, Norcliffe-Kaufmann L, Peltier A, Singer W, et al. Autonomic function testing in the COVID-19 pandemic: An American autonomic society position statement. Clin Auton Res. 2020;30:295–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7287407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32529405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arvind A, Srivastav S. Cardiac autonomic function evaluation during the COVID-19 pandemic: A frugal innovation for Valsalva manoeuvre. Indian Journal of Physiology and Pharmacology. 2021;65:66–8.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>