<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429404</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Epidemiological Study and Seropositivity in Viral Panel Testing Among Corneal Tissue Donors.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69728</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69728</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69728</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69728</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Corneal tissue is a critical component for vision restoration through transplantation, yet the availability of suitable corneal tissue is limited. This limitation results in long waiting lists and high demand, especially in countries with lower donation rates compared to global benchmarks. In Mexico, the corneal donation rate remains significantly behind other Latin American countries and leading nations such as Spain. Understanding the characteristics of corneal tissue donors is essential for improving donation practices and addressing the shortage of available tissues.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This descriptive retrospective study analyzed electronic medical records of cadaveric corneal donors at the General Regional Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute of Querétaro from January 2022 to December 2023. Donors were included based on criteria such as age (2-85 years) and known cause of death. Exclusion criteria included age outside the specified range, neoplastic diseases, active systemic infections, and prior ocular surgeries. Serological testing for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Venereal Disease Research Laboratory (VDRL), coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), hepatitis B virus (HBV), and hepatitis C virus (HCV was performed to assess viral reactivity. Statistical analyses were conducted using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 25 (Released 2017; IBM Corp., Armonk, New York, United States), summarizing data with descriptive statistics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study included 185 corneal donors with a mean age of 56.34 years. The majority were male (109; 58.9%), and the leading causes of death were cardiogenic shock (34; 18.4%), hypovolemic shock (31; 16.8%), and acute respiratory failure (30; 16.2%). Exclusion due to positive serological tests included seven donors (3.8%) for HIV and seven (3.8%) for SARS-CoV-2. A total of 16 donors (8.6%) were excluded due to positive results in the viral serological panel. The most common comorbidities were chronic kidney disease (36; 19.5%), type 2 diabetes mellitus (28; 15.1%), and systemic hypertension (31; 16.8%).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The study highlights a predominantly male donor profile with a mean age of 56.34 years and emphasizes cardiogenic shock as a leading cause of death. The notably higher seropositivity rate of 8.6% for various viral infections compared to international reports indicates a need for improved health interventions and screening processes. The focus on cardiovascular and respiratory causes of death underscores regional health issues affecting donation patterns. To address the organ and tissue donation shortfall, it is crucial to enhance coordination within donation teams and increase public awareness, given the significant gap in donation rates compared to leading countries.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Pérez Peña et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pérez Peña</LastName><ForeName>Nemi Isabel</ForeName><Initials>NI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant and Donation Department, Regional General Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sanchez García</LastName><ForeName>Luis Enrique</ForeName><Initials>LE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant and Donation Department, Regional General Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García Romero</LastName><ForeName>José Manuel</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant and Donation Department, Regional General Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Montoya Vázquez</LastName><ForeName>Alberto</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant and Donation Department, Regional General Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alonso Aguiñiga</LastName><ForeName>Karen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant and Donation Department, Regional General Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Villegas Amador</LastName><ForeName>Floricel O</ForeName><Initials>FO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant and Donation Department, Regional General Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tolentino Pérez</LastName><ForeName>Daniela Esperanza</ForeName><Initials>DE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>General Practice, Autonomous University of Querétaro, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ochoa Cisneros</LastName><ForeName>Lilia Yolanda</ForeName><Initials>LY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>General Practice, Autonomous University of Querétaro, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diaz Ugalde</LastName><ForeName>Jesus A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>General Practice, Autonomous University of Querétaro, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García Hernández</LastName><ForeName>Irene</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant and Donation Department, Regional General Hospital 1 of the Mexican Social Security Institute, Querétaro, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">comorbidities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cornea</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">corneal procurement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">donors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tissue donor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral panel</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11490291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Deceased donation and organ transplantation in Mexico: analysis of 12 years and seven strategic proposals. Argüero-Sánchez R, Sánchez-Ramírez O, Olivares-Durán EM. Cir Cir. 2020;88:254–262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32538984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>OPTN/SRTR 2015 annual data report: early effects of the new kidney allocation system. Hart A, Gustafson SK, Skeans MA, Stock P, Stewart D, Kasiske BL, Israni AK. Am J Transplant. 2017;17:543–564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5523515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28052605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centro Nacional de Trasplantes (CENATRA) https://www.gob.mx/cenatra/documentos/estadisticas-50060 Sistema Informático del Registro Nacional de Trasplantes (SIRNT) 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centro Nacional de Trasplantes (CENATRA): Reporte de Actividades y Establecimientos Autorizados para la Procuración de Tejido Corneal. 2020. https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/415055/CENATRA._Establecimientos_Autorizados.pdf https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/415055/CENATRA._Establecimientos_Autorizados.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obstacles to donor eye procurement and their solutions at the University of Iowa. Mack RJ, Mason P, Mathers WD. Cornea. 1995;14:249–252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7600807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Differences in the procurement of organs and tissues by health care professionals. Siminoff LA, Arnold R, Miller DS. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/7819612/ Clin Transplant. 1994;8:460–465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7819612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trasplante de córnea. Rojas DJ. https://www.medigraphic.com/pdfs/juarez/ju-2000/ju003h.pdf Rev Hosp Jua Mex. 2000;67:139–143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trasplante de córnea: aspectos bioéticos. Hurtado-Sarrió M, Duch-Hurtado M, Tudela J. Acta Bioethica. 2019;25:73–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Procuración de córneas por donación. Querevalú-Murillo WA. https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/4577/457745508001.pdf. Rev Med Inst Mex Seguro Soc. 2010;48:233–236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21192893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Causes of blindness and vision impairment in 2020 and trends over 30 years, and prevalence of avoidable blindness in relation to VISION 2020: the right to sight: an analysis for the global burden of disease study. Adelson JD, Bourne RRA, Briant PS, Flaxman SR, Taylor HRB, Jonas JB, Abu-Gharbieh EG. https://www.thelancet.com/JOURNALS/LANGLO/ARTICLE/PIIS2214-109X(20)30489-7/FULLTEXT Lancet Glob Health. 2020;9:0–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7820391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33275949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perfil epidemiológico del donante de tejido corneal en el Hospital General de Cholula. Merino-Cabrera G, Monter-Valera DB, Tejeda-Mondragón M, Barrientos-Núñez ME. Rev Mex Traspl. 2021;10:23–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perfil epidemiológico del donante y del receptor en trasplante de córnea en el Instituto Cubano de Oftalmología 'Ramón Pando Ferrer'. Escalona LET, Pérez PZ, Castillo PA, Jareño OM, López HSM. http://scielo.sld.cu/pdf/oft/v27n4/oft06414.pdf Rev Cubana Oftalmol. 2014;27:558–568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparison of seropositivity of human immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis B virus, hepatitis C virus, and syphilis among Hospital Cornea Retrieval Programme-donors versus voluntary cornea donors at a large eye bank in Eastern India. Basak S, Basak SK, Biswas B. Indian J Ophthalmol. 2017;65:1138–1142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5700581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29133639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donor and tissue profile of a community eye bank in Eastern India. Ranjan A, Das S, Sahu SK. Indian J Ophthalmol. 2014;62:935–937.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4244740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25370396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thirty years of cornea cultivation: long-term experience in a single eye bank. Linke SJ, Eddy MT, Bednarz J, et al. Acta Ophthalmol. 2013;91:571–578.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22863151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comprehensive retrospective analysis of corneal donor characteristics at the National Institute of Traumatology and Orthopedics Eye Bank (2013-2021) Neno JO, Da Silva DM, Prinz RA, Barbosa IG, Bonfadini G, Roisman V, Couto A. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.transproceed.2023.04.009. Transplant Proc. 2023;55:1362–1365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37246130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The New Zealand National Eye Bank study: trends in the acquisition and storage of corneal tissue over the decade 2000 to 2009. Cunningham WJ, Moffatt SL, Brookes NH, Twohill HC, Pendergrast DG, Stewart JM, McGhee CN. Cornea. 2012;31:538–545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22314820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Semiquantitative criteria in the eye bank that correlate with cornea guttata in donor corneas. Safi T, Daas L, Kiefer GL, et al. Klin Monbl Augenheilkd. 2021;238:680–687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34157770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seroprevalence of HIV, HBV, HCV &amp; RPR among cornea donor in the regional institute of ophthalmology. Patel MH, Patel AM, Shah AM. J Integr Health Sci. 2017;5:39–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Consideraciones para la donación y trasplante de tejido ocular en México durante la pandemia de COVID-19. Tello-Medina RI, Verdiguel-Sotelo K. Rev Mex Traspl. 2020;9:216–221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical utility of COVID-19 real time-polymerase chain reaction testing of ocular tissues of non-COVID-19 cornea donors deemed suitable for corneal retrieval and transplantation. Chaurasia S, Rudraprasad D, Senagari JR, et al. Cornea. 2022;41:238–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34852410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donor risk factors for graft failure in the cornea donor study. Sugar J, Montoya M, Dontchev M, et al. Cornea. 2009;28:981–985.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3124710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19724216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>