<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39427267</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-3017</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Ecotoxicology (London, England)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ecotoxicology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Gut microbiome as biomarker for triclosan toxicity in Labeo rohita: bioconcentration, immunotoxicity and metagenomic profiling.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10646-024-02817-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Triclosan (TCS) is a lipophilic, broad spectrum antimicrobial agent commonly used in personal care products with a projected continuous escalation in aquatic environments in the post COVID 19 era. There is rich documentation in the literature on the alteration of physiological responses in fish due to TCS exposure; however, studies on gut associated bacteria of fish are still scarce. This is the first attempt to determine changes in bacterial community structure due to exposure of TCS on Labeo rohita, a commercially essential freshwater species, using 16S V3-V4 region ribosomal RNA (rRNA) next-generation sequencing (NGS). Chronic exposure of TCS at environmentally realistic concentrations viz. 1/5th (T<sub>1</sub>: 0.129 mg/L) and 1/10th (T<sub>2</sub>: 0.065 mg/L) of LC<sub>50</sub> for 28 days resulted in the dose dependent bioconcentration of TCS in the fish gut. Prolonged exposure to TCS leads to disruption of gut bacteria evidenced by down regulation of the host immune system. Additionally, high-throughput sequencing analysis showed alternation in the abundance and diversity of microbial communities in the gut, signifying Proteobacteria and Verrucomicrobia as dominant phyla. Significant changes were also observed in the relative abundance of Chloroflexi and Gammatimonadetes phyla in TCS exposed groups. The study revealed that gut microbiome can be used as a biomarker in assessing the degree of TCS toxicity in commercially important fish species.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Angom Baleshwor</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ICAR-Central Institute of Fisheries Education, Mumbai, Maharashtra, 400061, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paul</LastName><ForeName>Tapas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Fisheries, Bihar Animal Sciences University, Kishanganj, Bihar, 855107, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shukla</LastName><ForeName>S P</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ICAR-Central Institute of Fisheries Education, Mumbai, Maharashtra, 400061, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Saurav</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ICAR-Central Institute of Fisheries Education, Mumbai, Maharashtra, 400061, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Sanath</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ICAR-Central Institute of Fisheries Education, Mumbai, Maharashtra, 400061, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Ganesh</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Rani Lakshmi Bai Central Agricultural University, Jhansi, Uttar Pradesh, 284003, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Kundan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ICAR-Central Institute of Fisheries Education, Mumbai, Maharashtra, 400061, India. kundankumar@cife.edu.in.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>DST/TMD-EWO-WTI/2K19/EWFH/2019/214</GrantID><Agency>Department of Science and Technology, Ministry of Science and Technology, India</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Ecotoxicology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9885956</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0963-9292</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Labeo rohita</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioconcentration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gut microbiota</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Next-generation sequencing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Triclosan</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39427267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10646-024-02817-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10646-024-02817-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahn KC, Zhao B, Chen J, Cherednichenko G, Sanmarti E, Denison MS, Lasley B, Pessah IN, Kültz D, Chang DP, Gee SJ (2008) In vitro biologic activities of the antimicrobials triclocarban, its analogs, and triclosan in bioassay screens: receptor-based bioassay screens. Environ Health Perspect 116:1203–10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.11200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amend DF (1981) Potency testing of fish vaccines. Dev Biol Stand 49:447–454</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belkaid Y, Hand TW (2014) Role of the microbiota in immunity and inflammation. Cell 157:121–41</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.03.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bera KK, Kumar S, Paul T, Prasad KP, Shukla SP, Kumar K (2020) Triclosan induces immunosuppression and reduces survivability of striped catfish Pangasianodon hypophthalmus during the challenge to a fish pathogenic bacterium Edwardsiella tarda. Environ Res 186:109575</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.109575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beveridge MC, Sikdar PK, Frerichs GN, Millar S (1991) The ingestion of bacteria in suspension by the common carp Cyprinus carpio L. J Fish Biol 39:825–31</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8649.1991.tb04412.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas P, Vellanki BP (2021) Occurrence of emerging contaminants in highly anthropogenically influenced river Yamuna in India. Sci Total Environ 782:146741</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown K, DeCoffe D, Molcan E, Gibson DL (2012) Diet-induced dysbiosis of the intestinal microbiota and the effects on immunity and disease. Nutrients 4:1095–119</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu4081095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caporaso JG, Lauber CL, Walters WA, Berg-Lyons D, Huntley J, Fierer N, Owens SM, Betley J, Fraser L, Bauer M, Gormley N (2012) Ultra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platforms. ISME J 6:1621–4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ismej.2012.8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carey DE, McNamara PJ (2015) The impact of triclosan on the spread of antibiotic resistance in the environment. Front Microbiol 5:780</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2014.00780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Claus SP, Guillou H, Ellero-Simatos S (2016) The gut microbiota: a major player in the toxicity of environmental pollutants? Npj Biofilms Microbiomes 2:1–1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/npjbiofilms.2016.3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das KM, Tripathi SD (1991) Studies on the digestive enzymes of grass carp, Ctenopharyngodon idella (Val.). Aquaculture 92:21–32</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0044-8486(91)90005-R</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwyer FJ, Hardesty DK, Henke CE, Ingersoll CG, Whites DW, Augspurger T, Canfield TJ, Mount DR, Mayer FL (2005) Assessing contaminant sensitivity of endangered and threatened aquatic species: Part III. Effluent toxicity tests. Arch Environ Contam Toxicol 48:174–83</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00244-004-0104-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eaton DL, Gilbert SG (2008) Principles of toxicology. In: Klaassen CD (ed) Casarett &amp; Doull’s Toxicology. The Basic Science of Poisons. 11–34 Macmillan Publishing Company, New York</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebele AJ, Abdallah MA, Harrad S (2017) Pharmaceuticals and personal care products (PPCPs) in the freshwater aquatic environment. Emerg Contam 3:1–6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.emcon.2016.12.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) (2002). Methods for measuring the acute toxicity of effluents and receiving waters to freshwater and marine organisms, 5th edn. 275. https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/acute-freshwater-and-marine-wet-manual_2002.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evariste L, Barret M, Mottier A, Mouchet F, Gauthier L, Pinelli E (2019) Gut microbiota of aquatic organisms: a key endpoint for ecotoxicological studies. Environ Pollut 248:989–99</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.02.101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang JL, Vanlandingham M, da Costa GG, Beland FA (2016) Absorption and metabolism of triclosan after application to the skin of B 6 C 3 F 1 mice. Environ Toxicol 31:609–23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/tox.22074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finney DJ (1971) Probit analysis. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gavrilescu M, Demnerová K, Aamand J, Agathos S, Fava F (2015) Emerging pollutants in the environment: present and future challenges in biomonitoring, ecological risks and bioremediation. N. Biotechnol 32:147–56</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nbt.2014.01.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaulke CA, Barton CL, Proffitt S, Tanguay RL, Sharpton TJ (2016) Triclosan exposure is associated with rapid restructuring of the microbiome in adult zebrafish. PloS one 11:e0154632</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Godon JJ, Zumstein E, Dabert P, Habouzit F, Moletta R (1997) Microbial 16S rDNA diversity in an anaerobic digester. Water Sci Technol 36:49–55</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wst.1997.0574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalo-Lumbreras R, Sanz-Landaluze J, Guinea J, Cámara C (2012) Miniaturized extraction methods of triclosan from aqueous and fish roe samples. Bioconcentration studies in zebrafish larvae (Danio rerio). Anal Bioanal Chem 403:927–37</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-012-5713-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gradel KO, Schønheyder HC, Pedersen L, Thomsen RW, Nørgaard M, Nielsen H (2006) Incidence and prognosis of nontyphoid Salmonella bacteraemia in Denmark: a 10-year county-based follow-up study. Eur J Clin Microbiol 25:151–8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10096-006-0110-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hemalatha D, Nataraj B, Rangasamy B, Shobana C, Ramesh M (2019) DNA damage and physiological responses in an Indian major carp Labeo rohita exposed to an antimicrobial agent triclosan. Fish Physiol Biochem 45:1463–84</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10695-019-00661-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins MJ, Macfarlane GT (2002) Changes in predominant bacterial populations in human faeces with age and with Clostridium difficile infection. 51(5):448–54</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keerthisinghe TP, Yang Q, Chow A, Fang M (2021) Feeding state greatly modulates the effect of xenobiotics on gut microbiome metabolism: A case study of tetracycline. J Hazard Mater 413:125441</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.125441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly JR, Kennedy PJ, Cryan JF, Dinan TG, Clarke G, Hyland NP (2015). Breaking down the barriers: the gut microbiome, intestinal permeability and stress-related psychiatric disorders. Front Cell Neurosci 9:392</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim DH, Brunt J, Austin B (2007) Microbial diversity of intestinal contents and mucus in rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss). J Appl Microbiol 102:1654–64</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2006.03185.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Paul T, Shukla SP, Kumar K, Karmakar S, Bera KK (2021) Biomarkers-based assessment of triclosan toxicity in aquatic environment: A mechanistic review. Environ Pollut 286:117569</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nag SK, Das Sarkar S, Manna SK (2018) Triclosan–an antibacterial compound in water, sediment and fish of River Gomti, India. Int J Environ Health Res 28:461–70</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09603123.2018.1487044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narrowe AB, Albuthi-Lantz M, Smith EP, Bower KJ, Roane TM, Vajda AM, Miller CS (2015) Perturbation and restoration of the fathead minnow gut microbiome after low-level triclosan exposure. Microbiome 3:1–8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40168-015-0069-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarrete P, Mardones P, Opazo R, Espejo R, Romero J (2008) Oxytetracycline treatment reduces bacterial diversity of intestinal microbiota of Atlantic salmon. J Aquat Anim Health 20:177–83</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1577/H07-043.1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak SK (2010) Role of gastrointestinal microbiota in fish. Aquac Res 41:1553–1573</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2109.2010.02546.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orvos DR, Versteeg DJ, Inauen J, Capdevielle M, Rothenstein A, Cunningham V (2002) Aquatic toxicity of triclosan. Environ Toxicol Chem 21:1338–49</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/etc.5620210703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul T, Shukla SP, Kumar K, Poojary N, Kumar S (2019) Effect of temperature on triclosan toxicity in Pangasianodon hypophthalmus (Sauvage, 1878): Hematology, biochemistry and genotoxicity evaluation. Sci Total Environ 668:104–14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul T, Kumar S, Shukla SP, Pal P, Kumar K, Poojary N, Biswal A, Mishra A (2020) A multi-biomarker approach using integrated biomarker response to assess the effect of pH on triclosan toxicity in Pangasianodon hypophthalmus (Sauvage, 1878). Environ Pollut 260:114001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price MN, Dehal PS, Arkin AP (2010) FastTree 2–approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments. PloS one 5(3):e9490</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quade MJ, Roth JA (1997) A rapid, direct assay to measure degranulation of bovine neutrophil primary granules. Vet Immunol Immunopathol 58:239–48</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0165-2427(97)00048-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasal KD, Dixit S, Swain PP, Siriyappagouder P, Kumar R, Iquebal MA, Vasam M, Debbarma J, Jaiswal S, Angadi UB, Rai A (2023) Identification of host-specific skin-mucus and gut microbiota in snakehead murrel (Channa striata) (Bloch, 1793) using metagenomics approach. J Appl Biol Biotechnol X:1–11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasheed T, Bilal M, Hassan AA, Nabeel F, Bharagava RN, Ferreira LF, Tran HN, Iqbal HM (2020) Environmental threatening concern and efficient removal of pharmaceutically active compounds using metal-organic frameworks as adsorbents. Environ Res 185:109436</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.109436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roeselers G, Mittge EK, Stephens WZ, Parichy DM, Cavanaugh CM, Guillemin K, Rawls JF (2011) Evidence for a core gut microbiota in the zebrafish. Multi J Microb Ecol 5:1595–1608</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowland I, Gibson G, Heinken A, Scott K, Swann J, Thiele I, Tuohy K (2018) Gut microbiota functions: metabolism of nutrients and other food components. Eur J Nutr 57:1–24</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00394-017-1445-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha S, Roy RN, Sen SK, Ray AK (2006) Characterization of cellulase‐producing bacteria from the digestive tract of tilapia, Oreochromis mossambica (Peters) and grass carp, Ctenopharyngodon idella (Valenciennes). Aquac Res 37:380–8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2109.2006.01442.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahoo PK, Kumari J, Mishra BK (2005) Non‐specific immune responses in juveniles of Indian major carps. J Appl Ichthyol 21:151–5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0426.2004.00606.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahu VK, Karmakar S, Kumar S, Shukla SP, Kumar K (2018) Triclosan toxicity alters behavioral and hematological parameters and vital antioxidant and neurological enzymes in Pangasianodon hypophthalmus (Sauvage, 1878). Aquat Toxicol 202:145–52</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aquatox.2018.07.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanidad KZ, Xiao H, Zhang G (2019) Triclosan, a common antimicrobial ingredient, on gut microbiota and gut health. Gut microbes 10:434–7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2018.1546521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt B, Mulder IE, Musk CC, Aminov RI, Lewis M, Stokes CR, Bailey M, Prosser JI, Gill BP, Pluske JR, Kelly D (2011) Establishment of normal gut microbiota is compromised under excessive hygiene conditions. PloS one 6:e28284</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Secombes CJ (1990) Isolation of salmonid macrophages and analysis of their killing activity. Tech Fish Immunol 1:137–163</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singer H, Müller S, Tixier C, Pillonel L (2002) Triclosan: occurrence and fate of a widely used biocide in the aquatic environment: field measurements in wastewater treatment plants, surface waters, and lake sediments. Environ Sci Technol 36:4998–5004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es025750i</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh V, Suthar S (2021) Occurrence, seasonal variations, and ecological risk of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in River Ganges at two holy cities of India. Chemosphere 268:129331</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.129331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith KW, Souter I, Dimitriadis I, Ehrlich S, Williams PL, Calafat AM, Hauser R (2013) Urinary paraben concentrations and ovarian aging among women from a fertility center. Environ Health Perspect 121:1299–305</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.1205350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stasiack AS, Bauman CP (1996) Netrophil activity as a potential indicator immunomodulator Ecteinascida turbinata extract on Edwardsiella ictaluri infection of channel catfish. J Aquat Anim Health 7:141–6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka S, Kobayashi T, Songjinda P, Tateyama A, Tsubouchi M, Kiyohara C, Shirakawa T, Sonomoto K, Nakayama J (2009) Influence of antibiotic exposure in the early postnatal period on the development of intestinal microbiota. FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol 56:80–7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2009.00553.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyagi A, Singh B (2017) Microbial diversity in Rohu fish gut and inland saline aquaculture sediment and variations associated with next-generation sequencing of 16S rRNA gene. J Fish Life Sci. 2:1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q, Garrity GM, Tiedje JM, Cole JR (2007) Naive Bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomy. Appl Environ Microbiol 73:5261–7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00062-07</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Sheng HF, He Y, Wu JY, Jiang YX, Tam NF, Zhou HW (2012) Comparison of the levels of bacterial diversity in freshwater, intertidal wetland, and marine sediments by using millions of illumina tags. Appl Environ Microbiol 78:8264–71</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01821-12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Liu X, Yu W, Zhang Y, Shi C, Ni S, Liu Q, Li X, Sun Y, Zheng C, Sun H (2016) Effects of human vascular endothelial growth factor on reparative dentin formation. Mol Med Rep. 13:705–12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3892/mmr.2015.4608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>