<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39424242</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-8406</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Journal of arthroplasty</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Arthroplasty</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Hospital and Patient Factors Associated with Length of Hospitalization in Patients Who Have Osteoarthritis Undergoing Primary Total Knee Arthroplasty: An Analysis of National Data.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0883-5403(24)01029-5</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.arth.2024.10.016</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">/Objective: By 2040, an estimated 3.5 million primary total knee arthroplasties (TKAs) will be performed each year in the United States (U.S.) osteoarthritis (OA) is the most common indication for primary TKA. We examined the association of hospital, regional, and patient-level factors with extended lengths of hospital stay (eLOS).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Patients who have OA who underwent primary TKA from 2016 to 2019 were queried using a national inpatient database. We used the International Classification of Disease (ICD-10) codes to identify diagnoses and procedures. There were 2,592,469 patients who had OA who underwent primary TKA from 2016 to 2019. We used univariate and multivariable-adjusted logistic regression analyses to assess whether patient, payer, hospital, and geographic factors were associated with an eLOS. Predictive probabilities from multivariable analyses were used in the Area Under the Curve (AUC) analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Patient race and ethnicity, Medicaid or Medicare payer status, income, age/sex, and nearly all regional and hospital characteristics were independently associated with eLOS (&gt; 3 days; ROC C-statistic = 0.74). Sensitivity analyses that used the most recent years of data from 2020 to 2021 (COVID-19 pandemic years), or adjusted for individual organ system complications reproduced the main results without much attenuation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Age, sex, race, ethnicity, hospital location and teaching status, elective procedure designation, perioperative complications, and insurance payer status significantly influenced the length of hospital stay (LOS) for primary total knee arthroplasty (TKA) hospitalizations in the US. Recognized disparities were linked to longer hospital stays after primary TKA in patients who had osteoarthritis (OA). Implementing policies and interventions that target these factors could help shorten hospital stays for high-risk patients after primary TKA.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Published by Elsevier Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rumalla</LastName><ForeName>Kranti C</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Feinberg School of Medicine, Northwestern University, Chicago, IL, 60611.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chandrupatla</LastName><ForeName>Sumanth R</ForeName><Initials>SR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Immunology and Rheumatology, Department of Medicine, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, 35294.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Jasvinder A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Immunology and Rheumatology, Department of Medicine, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, 35294; Medicine Service, VA Medical Center, Birmingham, AL 35233; Department of Epidemiology, University of Alabama at Birmingham School of Public Health, Birmingham, AL 35294. Electronic address: Jasvinder.md@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Arthroplasty</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8703515</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0883-5403</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">geographic disparities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">knee</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">osteoarthritis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">total knee arthroplasty</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39424242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2024.10.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0883-5403(24)01029-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>