<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39421845</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1664-1078</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in psychology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Psychol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Psychological mediators between risk perception and psychological wellbeing in emergency healthcare workers.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1435189</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1435189</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1435189</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1435189</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Healthcare workers are subjected to numerous work-related stress factors, which have negative consequences on their physical and mental health, making them a vulnerable group. The recent pandemic caused by the new coronavirus created a high demand for attention from healthcare workers, which put their mental health at risk. This study aimed to test a mediation model in which resilience and the satisfaction of psychological needs play a mediating role in risk perception, the attitude toward the management carried out by the administration, emotional intelligence on psychological wellbeing, and depressive symptoms of frontline professionals. The sample consisted of 405 healthcare professionals aged between 22 and 65 years, belonging to critical care units in southern Spain. Linear correlation and mediation analyses were performed. The results showed that psychological wellbeing had positive correlations with resilience and negative correlations with the discrepancy in the satisfaction of psychological needs. Depressive symptoms had negative correlations with resilience and positive correlations with the satisfaction of psychological needs. To explore these results further, a mediation analysis was conducted, and a large set of significant indirect effects was found.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Badía, Alarcón, Trillo and Miranda-Páez.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Badía</LastName><ForeName>Maria Del Carmen</ForeName><Initials>MDC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Malaga, Málaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Comarcal Santa Ana, Granada, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alarcón</LastName><ForeName>Rafael</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Malaga, Málaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychobiology and Behavioral Sciences Methodology, University of Malaga, Málaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Trillo</LastName><ForeName>Javier</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Malaga, Málaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Strategic Chair of Security, Emergencies and Disasters. University of Malaga, Málaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miranda-Páez</LastName><ForeName>Jesús</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Malaga, Málaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Strategic Chair of Security, Emergencies and Disasters. University of Malaga, Málaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Psychol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101550902</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1664-1078</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare professionals</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mediation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychological wellbeing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk perception</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39421845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11484491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1435189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aradilla H. A. (2013). Inteligencia Emocional y variables relacionadas en Enfermería: Universitat de Barcelona.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arenas Sanchez A., Pinzon-Amaya A. (2021). Asociación entre los rasgos de personalidad y la ocurrencia de accidentes de trabajo de riesgo biológico del personal de enfermería en el Hospital Universitario de Santander (HUS): estudio de casos y controles. Medunab 24, 220–232. doi: 10.29375/01237047.3981</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.29375/01237047.3981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arias Molina Y., Herrero Solano Y., Hernández C., Guyat C., Mederos G. (2020). Manifestaciones psicológicas frente a la situación epidemiológica causada por la COVID-19. Revista Habanera Ciencias Médicas 19, 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arrogante Ó. (2014a). Estudio del bienestar en personal sanitario. Dialnet.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arrogante Ó. (2014b). Mediación de la resiliencia entre burnout y salud en el personal de EnfermeríaEfecto mediador de la resiliencia entre burnout y salud en personal de enfermería. Enfermeria Clínica 24, 283–289. doi: 10.1016/j.enfcli.2014.06.003, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.enfcli.2014.06.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25126983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arrogante Ó. (2015). Resiliencia en Enfermería: definición, evidencia empírica e intervenciones. Index Enfermería. 24, 232–235. doi: 10.4321/S1132-12962015000300009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4321/S1132-12962015000300009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arrogante O., Pérez García P. M., Zaldiar E. G. (2016). Recursos personales relevantes para el bienestar psicológico en el personal de enfermería. Enferm. Intensiva 27, 22–30. doi: 10.1016/j.enfi.2015.07.002, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.enfi.2015.07.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26342700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ato M., Vallejo G. (2011). Los efectos de terceras variables en la investigación psicológica. Anal. Psicol.:27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballesteros B. P., Medina A., Caycedo C. (2006). El bienestar psicológico definido por asistentes a un servicio de consulta psicológica en Bogotá, Colombia Universidad. Psicológica 5, 239–258.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bentler P. M. (1990). Comparative fit indexes in structural models. Psychol. Bull. 107, 238–246. doi: 10.1037/0033-2909.107.2.238, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.107.2.238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2320703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bentler P. M., Bonett D. G. (1980). Significance tests and goodness of fit in the analysis of covariance structures. Psychol. Bull. 88, 588–606. doi: 10.1037/0033-2909.88.3.588</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.88.3.588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bermudez M. P., Teva Alvarez I., Sanchez A. (2013). Análisis de la relación entre inteligencia emocional, estabilidad emocional ybienestar psicológico. Univ. Psychol. 2, 27–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biggs A., Brough P., Drummond S. (2017). La teoría del estrés psicológico y el afrontamiento de Lazarus y Folkman: Wiley Online Library, 21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brito Pons G. (2022). Programa de reducción del estrés basado en la atención plena (mindfulness): sistematización de una experiencia de su aplicación en un hospital público semi-rural del sur de Chile. Psicoperspectivas 10, 221–242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Browne M. W., Cudeck R. (1993). Alternative ways of assessing model fit. Sociol. Methods Res. 21, 230–258. doi: 10.1177/0049124192021002005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0049124192021002005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bueno Ferrán M., Barrientos-Trigo S. (2021). Cuidar al que cuida: el impacto emocional de la epidemia de coronavirus en las enfermeras y otros profesionales de la salud. Enferm. Clin. 31, 35–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7229967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32425487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capone V., Donizzetti A. R., Sang-Ah P. M. (2021). Validación y evaluación psicométrica de la escala de percepción de riesgo COVID-19 (CoRP): una nueva escala breve para medir la percepción de riesgo de los individuos. Revist. Inter. Salud Mental Adicciones 21, 170–178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caro Alonso P. Á., Rodriguez M. B. (2018). Potencialidades de la resiliencia para los profesionales de Enfermería. Index Enfermería:27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carol D. R. (1989). Happiness is everything, or is it? Explorations on the meaning of psychological well-being. J. Personal. Soc. Psychol. 56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrillo-García C., Ríos-Rísquez M. I., Martínez-Hurtado R., Noguera-Villaescusa P. (2016). Nivel de estrés del personal de enfermería de la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos de un hospital clínico universitario. Enfermeria Intensiva 27, 89–95. doi: 10.1016/j.enfi.2016.03.001, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.enfi.2016.03.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27267958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casales J. C. (2022). Percepción de riesgo durante la COVID-19: UNA mirada desde la psicología social. Revist Cubana Psicol. 2, 1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceberio M. R., Cócola F., Benedicto G., Jones G., Daiana Agostinelli J., Florencia-Daverio R. (2021). Evaluación del grado de percepción de riesgo al contagio. Revist Caribeña Psicol. 6, 1–9. doi: 10.37226/rcp.v6i1.6051</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.37226/rcp.v6i1.6051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceberio M. R., Cócola F., Benedicto G., Jones G., Daiana Agostinelli J., Florencia-Daverio R. (2022). Evaluación del Grado de Percepción de Riesgo al Contagio. Revista Caribeña Psicol 6, 1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celis-Herrero P. d., Concepción M. d. l., Judith C.-A. (2021). Percepción del riesgo de COVID-19 y medidas preventivas en México. Rev. Med. Inst. Mex. Seguro Soc. 59, 377–386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34914344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cénat J. M., Mahdi Moshirian Farahi S. M., Dalexis R. D., Darius W. P., Bekarkhanechi F. M., Poisson H. (2022). The global evolution of mental health problems during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review and meta-analysis of longitudinal studies. J. Affect. Disord. 315, 70–95. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2022.07.011, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.07.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9278995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35842064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho H. C., Abe S. (2013). Is two-tailed testing for directional research hypotheses tests legitimate? J. Business Res. 66, 1261–1266.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J. (1988). Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences. 2nd Edn. New York: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cori L., Bianchi F., Cadum E., Anthonj C. (2020). Risk perception and COVID-19. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 17, 1–6. doi: 10.3390/ijerph17093114, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17093114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7246460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32365710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Caneva F., García Gómez M., Baura B. (2020). Salud emocional del personal sanitario del Área de Urgencias durante la pandemia COVID-19. Natl Library Med. 155, 366–370.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7318973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32674888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Juan P. A. (2021). Revisión sistemática y metaanálisis sobre la prevalencia de depresión, ansiedad e insomnio en trabajadores sanitarios durante la pandemia de COVID-19. Archivos Preven Riesgos Laborales 24, 310–315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Díaz D., Rodriguez Carvajal R., Blanco A., Moreno Jimenez B., Gallardo I., Valle C., et al. . (2006). Adaptación española de las escalas de bienestar psicológico de Ryff. Psicothema. 18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17296089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dierendonck D. V. (2004). The construct validity of Ryff’s scales of psychological well-being and its extension with spiritual well-being. Personal. Individ. Differ. 36, 629–643. doi: 10.1016/S0191-8869(03)00122-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0191-8869(03)00122-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diez-Quevedo C., Rangil T., Sánchez Planell L., Kroenke K., Spitzer R. L. (2001). Validation and utility of the patient health questionnaire in diagnosing mental disorders in 1003 general hospital Spanish inpatients. Psychosom. Med. 63, 679–686. doi: 10.1097/00006842-200107000-00021, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00006842-200107000-00021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11485122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>dos Santos M. R., Carvalho Saraiva F. J., Rocha S. L. (2019). Estrés, burnout y depresión en los profesionales de enfermería de las unidades de cuidados intensivos. Enfermeria Global 18, 79–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dosil Santamarría M., Ozamiz-Etxebarria R. R., Jaureguizar Alboniga-Mayor J., Picaza G. M. (2021). Impacto psicológico de la COVID-19 en una muestra de profesionales sanitarios españoles. Rev. Psiquiatr. Salud Ment. 14, 106–112. doi: 10.1016/j.rpsm.2020.05.004, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.rpsm.2020.05.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32622882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunn L., Iglewicz A., Moutier C. (2014). Un modelo conceptual del bienestar del estudiante de medicina: promover la resiliencia y prevenir el agotamiento. Psiquiatria Acad.:32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erquicia J., Valls L., Barja A., Gil S., Joan M., Leal-Blanquet J., et al. . (2020). Emotional impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on healthcare workers in one of the most important infection outbreaks in Europe. Med. Clin. 155, 434–440. doi: 10.1016/j.medcli.2020.07.006, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.medcli.2020.07.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7604105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33163628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estrada Araoz E. G., Mamani Uchasara H. J. (2020). Bienestar psicológico y resiliencia en estudiantes de educación superior pedagógica. Apuntes Universitarios. 10, 56–68. doi: 10.17162/au.v10i4.491</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17162/au.v10i4.491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang-Huerta Mdl Á., Meléndez-Méndez M. C., Garza-Hernández R., Aguilera-Pérez P., Aguilera-Pérez O.-L. R. M. (2015). Percepción del personal de enfermería sobre los riesgos biológicos. Revista Conamed 1, 12–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrer R. (2020). Pandemia por COVID-19: el mayor reto de la historia del intensivismo. Med. Intensiva 44, 323–324. doi: 10.1016/j.medin.2020.04.002, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.medin.2020.04.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7151426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32376091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Figueroa Pico C., Castillo Morocho S., Carranza Gómez F. J. (2021). Riesgos psicosociales ante la amenaza infecciosa en personal de enfermería en un centro de salud de Ecuador 2020. Boletín Malariología Salud Ambiental 61, 54–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fletcher D., Sarkar M. (2013). Resiliencia psicológica Una revisión y crítica de definiciones, conceptos y teoría. Eur. Psychol. 18, 19–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forner-Puntonet M., Fidel-Kinoria S. G., Beneria A., Delgado-Arroyo M., Perea-Ortueta M., Closa-Castells H., et al. . (2021). La atención a las necesidades en salud mental de los profesionales sanitarios durante la COVID-19. Clín Salud. 32, 119–128. doi: 10.5093/clysa2021a13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5093/clysa2021a13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García A. J. (2013). Bienestar psicológico, edad y género en universitarios españoles. Salud. Sociedad 4, 48–58. doi: 10.22199/S07187475.2013.0001.00004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22199/S07187475.2013.0001.00004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerhold (2020). Risk perception and coping strategies. Results from a survey in Germany. Psy ArXiv. 1, 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glasser W. (1999). Choice theory: a new psychology of personal freedom.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González Gacel J. F., Soler Sánchez Y. M., Pérez Rosabali E. (2021). Percepción de riesgo ante la COVID-19 en pobladores del municipio Manzanillo. Multimed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayes A. F. (2018). Introduction to mediation, moderation, and conditional process analysis: a regression-based approach (Methodology in the Social Sciences). 2nd Edn. New York: The Guilford Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández G. L. (2020). Recomendaciones para el cuidado de la salud mental del personal sanitario cubano ante la COVID-19. Inform. Direct. Salud 32, 1–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández Rodriguez J. (2020). Impacto de la COVID 19 sobre la salud mental de las personas. Medicentro Electrónica 24, 578–594.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu L. T., Bentler P. M. (1999). Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: conventional criteria versus new alternatives. Struct. Equ. Model. Multidiscip. J. 6, 1–55. doi: 10.1080/10705519909540118, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10705519909540118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huarcaya-Victoria J. (2020). Consideraciones sobre la salud mental en la pandemia de COVID-19. Rev. Peru Med. Exp. Salud Publica 37, 327–334. doi: 10.17843/rpmesp.2020.372.5419, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17843/rpmesp.2020.372.5419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32876225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juárez-García A., Garcia Rivas J., Arias Galicia L. F., Merino S. C. (2024). Percepción de riesgo, efectos psicológicos y apoyo social en trabajadores sanitarios con pacientes con COVID-19 en México. Rev. Bras. Saúde Ocup. 49:49. doi: 10.1590/2317-6369/15722es2024v49e7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/2317-6369/15722es2024v49e7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lastre-Amell G., Gaviria-García G., Herazo-Beltrán Y., Mendinueta-Martínez M. (2018). Estresores laborales en el personal de enfermería de unidades de cuidados intensivos. Revist. Latinoam. Hipertensión. 13, 323–334.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozano-Vargas A. (2020). Impacto de la epidemia del Coronavirus (COVID-19) en la salud mental del personal de salud y en la población general de China. Rev. Neuropsiquiatr. 83, 51–56. doi: 10.20453/rnp.v83i1.3687</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20453/rnp.v83i1.3687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lugo-González I. V., Vega-Valero C. Z., González-Betanzos F., Robles-Montijo S., Fernández-Vega M. (2022). Relación entre percepción de enfermedad, tratamiento, adherencia y control del asma: un análisis de mediación. NCT 81, 157–164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maguiña Vargas C., Gastelo Acosta R., Tequen B. A. (2020). El nuevo Coronavirus y la pandemia del Covid-19. Revist. Med. Herediana. 31, 125–131. doi: 10.20453/rmh.v31i2.3776, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20453/rmh.v31i2.3776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez Arriaga R. J., González Ramirez L. P., Navarro Ruiz N. E., De la Roca Chiapas J. M., Reynoso González O. U. (2021). Resilience associated to mental health and sociodemographic factors in Mexican nurses during Covid19. Enfermería Global. 20, 1–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayordomo T., Sales A., Satorres E., Meléndez J. C. (2016). Bienestar psicológico en función de la etapa de vida, el sexo y su interacción. Pensamiento Psicol. 14, 101–112. doi: 10.11144/Javerianacali.PPSI14-2.bpfe</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11144/Javerianacali.PPSI14-2.bpfe</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mejillo A., Suárez Ojeda E. N., Rodriguez D., Munist M., Galli A. (2004). Módulo de enseñanza de resiliencia en enfermería. Bibliotec. Responsável.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meléndez Chávez S., Santes Bastian M. C., Ángel Salazar E. M. (2013). Inteligencia emocional en los profesionales enfermeros / emotional intelligence in nursing professionals. Metas Enfermería 16, 64–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mingote Adán J. C., Nuñez L. C. (2011). Importancia de la consideración de la salud mental en la gestión de la salud laboral: una responsabilidad compartida. Med. Segur. Trab. 57, 239–262.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miranda J., Martinez R., Alarcón R. (2002). Fiabilidad y validez de un inventario de imágenes para la satisfacción de necesidades básicas psicológicas. Metodol. Ciencias Comportamiento 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muñoz Fernández S. I., Molina Valdespino D., Ochoa Palacios R., Sánchez Guerrero O., Esquivel-Acevedo J. A. (2020). Stress, emotional responses, risk factors, psychopathology and management of healthcare workers during (COVID-19) pandemic. Acta Pediátrica México 41:127. doi: 10.18233/APM41No4S1ppS127-S1362104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18233/APM41No4S1ppS127-S1362104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nespereira-Campuzano T., Vázquez-Campo M. (2017). Emotional intelligence and stress management in nursing professionals in a hospital emergency department. Enferm. Clin. 27, 172–178. doi: 10.1016/j.enfcli.2017.02.007, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.enfcli.2017.02.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28499753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ordoñez-Rufat P., Polit-Martínez M. V., Martínez-Estalella G., Videla-Ces S. (2021). Inteligencia emocional de las enfermeras de cuidados intensivos en un hospital terciario. Enferm. Intensiva 32, 125–132. doi: 10.1016/j.enfie.2020.05.001, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.enfie.2020.05.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34332933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel M. S. J. S., Oh M. E., Rand K. L., Wu W., Cyders M. A., Kroenke K., et al. . (2019). Measurement invariance of the patient health questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) depression screener in U.S. adults across sex, race/ethnicity, and education level: NHANES 2005–2016. Depress. Anxiety 36, 813–823. doi: 10.1002/da.22940, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/da.22940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6736700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31356710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peñafiel-León J. E., Ramírez-Coronel A. A., Mesa-Cano I. C., Martínez-Suárez P. C. (2021). Impacto psicológico, resiliencia y afrontamiento del personal de salud durante la pandemia por COVID 19. Archivos Venezolanos Farmacol Terapéutica. 40, 1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porras-Povedano M., Santacruz-Hamer O.-R. (2014). Occupational risks perception in professional nursing practitioners at health care center. Enferm. Clin. 24, 191–195. doi: 10.1016/j.enfcli.2013.11.002, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.enfcli.2013.11.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24529895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preacher K. J., Zyphur M. J., Zhang Z. (2010). A general multilevel SEM framework for assessing multilevel mediation. Psychol Methods. 15, 209–233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20822249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puerta Cortés D. X. (2020). Percepción de riesgo frente al COVID 19: nuevos retos. Pasicol Desde Caribe 37, 7–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real R. E., Dávalos J. C., Molina S. C. (2021). Conocimientos, percepción de riesgo y prácticas del personal de salud acerca de la enfermedad por nuevo coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19). Anal. Facult. Ciencias Méd. 54, 17–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Restrepo J. E. (2016). El concepto de riesgo: avances hacia un modelo de percepción de riesgo en salud. Psicoespacios. Revista. 10, 174–200. doi: 10.25057/21452776.718</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.25057/21452776.718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez Zambrano J. E. (2020). Impacto de la pandemia COVID −19 en la salud mental de la población y del personal sanitario: Revisión Sistemática: Universidad César Vallejo, Repositorio digital institucional.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosseel (2012). Lavaan: an R package for structural equation modeling. J. Stat. Softw.:48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santamaría M., Ozamiz-Etxebarria N., Redondo Rodríguez I., Jaureguizar Alboniga-Mayor J., Picaza G. M. (2021). Impacto psicológico de la COVID-19 en una muestra de profesionales sanitarios españoles Impacto psicológico de laCOVID-19 en una muestra de profesionales sanitarios españoles. Revista de Psiquiatría y. Salud Mental. 14, 106–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32622882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salguero J. M., Fernández Berrocal P., Balluerka A. A. (2009). Medición de la inteligencia emocional percibida en la población adolescente: propiedades psicométricas de la escala Trait Meta-Mood. Comport. Soc. Personal. Revista Int. 38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salovery P., Mayer J. D., Goldman S. L., Turvey C., Palfais y Tibor P. (1995). Emotional attention, clarity, and repair: Exploring emotional intelligence using the Trait Meta-Mood Scale. Emot Discov. Health, 125–154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez Herrero H., Capella D. M., Revuelta Zamorano M., Santano Margariño A., Cazallo N. P. (2022). Percepción del riesgo, información recibida y participación laboral de los trabajadores de un hospital universitario ante la pandemia de la COVID-19. Rev. Esp. Salud Publica 96, 1–20., PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36263885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandin B., Chorot P., García-Escalera J., Valiente R. M. (2021). Emotional impact of the COVID-19 pandemic during the Spanish National Lockdown: protective and risk/vulnerability factors. Revista Acción Psicol. 18, 27–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebri V., Pizzoli S., Pravetton G. (2024). Cómo se ve mi ansiedad? Un análisis temático del impacto de una técnica de imágenes de una sola sesión en cuestiones emocionales. J. Ration. Emot. Cogn. Behav. Ther., 1–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seckman C. (2023). The impact of COVID-19 on the psychosocial well-being of older adults: a literature review. J. Nurs. Scholarsh. 55, 97–111. doi: 10.1111/jnu.12824, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jnu.12824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9874600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36218196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shechter A., Díaz M. N., Anstey E., Siqin Y., Agarwal S. (2020). Psychological distress, coping behaviors, and preferences for support among New York healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic. Gen. Hosp. Psychiatry 66, 1–8. doi: 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2020.06.007, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2020.06.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7297159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32590254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Short J. F. (1984). The social fabric at risk: toward the social transformation of risk analysis. Am. Sociol. Rev. 49, 711–735. doi: 10.2307/2095526, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2095526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slovic P., Weber E. U. (2013). Perception of risk posed by extreme events. SSRN.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong J., Zhang J., Zhu N., Pei Y., Weiqing L., Wei Y., et al. . (2022). Efectos de la pandemia de COVID-19 en la salud mental entre los trabajadores sanitarios de primera línea: una revisión sistemática y un metanálisis. Psicól Frontal:13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaishnavi C., Davidson J. R. T. (2007). An abbreviated version of the Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale (CD-RISC), the CD-RISC2: psychometric properties and applications in psychopharmacological trials. Psychres 25: 152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2041449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17459488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veliz Burgos A. L., Dörner Paris A. P., Soto Salcedo A., Reyes Lobos J. L., Ganga C. F. (2018). Inteligencia emocional y bienestar psicológico en profesionales de enfermería del sur de Chile. Medisur 16, 259–266.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong J., Lipsitz O., Nasri F., Gill H., Phan L., Chen-Li D., et al. . (2020). Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on mental health in the general population: a systematic review. J Affect Disord. 277, 55–64. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2020.08.001, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.08.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7413844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32799105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>