<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429967</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2297-7775</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in sociology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Sociol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Mask of the Warrior: unraveling deep-seated health vulnerabilities in veteran identities.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1389924</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1389924</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1389924</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fsoc.2024.1389924</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>As service members transition from deployment to civilian life, they are also expected to reintegrate into society. An important part of this process is to "soften up" veteran or warrior identities and open up the self for both existing and new identities, mindsets, and ways of life. Past research has shown that the warrior mindset, in particular, can have negative health implications in the long run. The mindset can be costly, not only for the individual and their loved ones, but also for the healthcare services and other agencies. This article draws from a recent interview study with 24 deployed Swedish veterans suffering from deteriorating mental health without receiving a clinical diagnosis. Purposeful sampling was conducted with the support of the medical staff at the Veterans' Clinic at Uppsala University Hospital. Participants had been screened for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) but had not received a clinical diagnosis. This constitutes a large and understudied patient group in the clinic. The medical staff selected patients based on the following criteria: deteriorating mental health, increased suffering related to PTSD symptoms, and issues related to moral issues, existential concerns, and identity. The sample included veterans from both the Swedish Armed Forces and other deploying agencies. Of the 24 interviewees, 19 were from the Swedish Armed Forces (16 men and three women), and five (four women and one man) were deployed by other agencies. The number of overseas deployments varied widely, with some interviewees having completed 1-2 deployments, while others had completed 3-8. Additionally, some interviewees had interrupted planned or ongoing deployments for various reasons. At the time of the interviews, none were serving full-time in the armed forces; all were veterans. The interviews took place during an intense wave of COVID-19 infections in Sweden in early 2022, so the majority were conducted via videoconference. The participants' veteran identities were abductively analyzed through the mask of secrecy, the stoic mask, and the mask of denial, which are elements of the "Mask of the Warrior." This mask functions to safeguard mission focus, to endure, to execute tasks in extremely stressful situations, and to solve operational tasks during deployments and combat operations. The analysis of the interviews suggests that certain elements in these powerful veteran identities can serve as breeding grounds for suffering later in life. The veterans in the study tended to be stoic about their deteriorating mental health, kept the suffering to themselves, and denied the harmful aspects of their deployments. Thus, the Mask of the Warrior played a counterproductive role for the individual, their friends and family, and life in the aftermath of deployments. Another implication of secrecy and denial occurred on the societal or macro and system levels due to the absence of sufficient insight, knowledge, and understanding of veterans among personnel within the healthcare system and other agencies. This made it difficult for the healthcare system, and other relevant agencies, to offer adequate care and to understand the participants' health issues during sick leave. The perceived absence of societal and organizational rewards and benefits for veterans who risk their mental health and lives during deployment can be seen as a failing implicit work contract. This lack of recognition may lead to the corrosion of character.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Grimell.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grimell</LastName><ForeName>Jan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Faculty of Social Sciences, Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Sociol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101777459</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2297-7775</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Me (a concept for a group’s values and behaviors that constitute a particular “Me”)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">deteriorating mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mask</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">suffering</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">veteran</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">warrior</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author declares that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11487641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsoc.2024.1389924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abrahamsson B. (2010). Kärnvärden och den militära framgångsformeln: Huset som Clausewitz byggde. Stockholm: Försvarshögskolan.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrell W. (2013). Ett krig här och nu: Sveriges väg till väpnad konflikt i Afghanistan. Stockholm: Bokförlaget Atlantis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amdur D., Batres A., Belisle J., Brown J. H., Cornis-Pop M., Mathewson-Chapman M., et al. . (2012). “VA integrated post-combat care” in Advances in social work practice with the military. ed. Beder J. (New York: Routledge, Taylor &amp; Francis Group; ), 253–263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atuel H. R., Castro C. A. (2019). “Military transition process and veteran identity” in American military life in the 21st century. eds. Weiss E., Castro C. A., vol. 2 (Denver, Colorado: ABC-CLIO; ), 485–496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bélanger S. A. H., Moore M. (2013). “Public opinion and soldier identity: tensions and resolutions” in Beyond the line: Military and veteran health research. eds. Aiken A. B., Bélanger S. A. H. (Montreal and Kingston: McGill-Queen’s University Press; ), 103–113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackburn D. (2017). Transitioning from military to civilian life: examining the final step in a military career. Can. Milit. J. 3, 62–69. doi: 10.3138/jmvfh.4160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3138/jmvfh.4160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradby H. (2016). Research agenda in medical sociology. Front. Sociol. 1:14. doi: 10.3389/fsoc.2016.00014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsoc.2016.00014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bragin M. (2010). Can anyone here know who I am? Co-constructing meaningful narratives with combat veterans. Clin. Soc. Work. J. 38, 316–326. doi: 10.1007/s10615-010-0267-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10615-010-0267-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brotz H., Wilson E. (1946). Characteristics of military society. Am. J. Sociol. 51, 371–375. doi: 10.1086/219845</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/219845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21014483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryan C. J., Morrow C. E. (2011). Circumventing mental health stigma by embracing the warrior culture: lessons learned from the defender’s edge program. Prof. Psychol. Res. Pract. 42, 16–23. doi: 10.1037/a0022290</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/a0022290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro C. A., Dursun S. (2019). Military veteran reintegration: approach, management, and assessment of military veterans transitioning to civilian life. London, United Kingdom: Academic Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clandinin J. D. (2013). Engaging in narrative inquiry. Walnut Creek, CA: Left Coast Press, Inc.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clandinin J. D., Connelly M. F. (2000). Narrative inquiry: experience and story in qualitative research. San Francisco: A Wiley Imprint.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coll J. E., Weiss E. L., Yarvis J. S. (2012). “No one leaves unchanged - insights for civilian mental health care: professionals into the military experience and culture” in Advances in social work practice with the military. ed. Beder J. (New York: Routledge, Taylor &amp; Francis Group; ), 18–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21846250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickstein B. D., Vogt D. S., Handa S., Litz B. T. (2010). Targeting self-stigma in returning military personnel and veterans: a review of intervention strategies. Mil. Psychol. 22, 224–236. doi: 10.1080/08995600903417399</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08995600903417399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duel J., Godier-McBard L., MacLean M. B., Fossey M. (2019). “Challenging missions: vulnerable veterans leaving the armed forces and promising avenues to support them” in Military veteran reintegration: Approach, management, and assessment of military veterans transitioning to civilian life. eds. Castro C. A., Dursun S. (London, United Kingdom: Academic Press; ), 95–134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edström E., Lunde N. T., Haaland Matlary J. (2009). “På jakt etter den militære profesjon [in the search of the military profession]” in Krigerkultur i en fredsnasjon [warrior culture in a peace nation]. eds. Edström E., Lunde N. T., Matlary J. H. (Oslo, Norge: Abstrakt Förlag; ), 17–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>English A., Dale-McGrath S. (2013). “Overcoming systemic obstacles to veteran transition to civilian life” in Beyond the line: Military and veteran health research. eds. Aiken A. B., Bélanger S. A. H. (Montreal and Kingston: McGill-Queen’s University Press; ), 249–264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fossey M., Lazier R., Lewis N. M., Williamson N., Caddick N. (2019). “Military-to-civilian transition policies, processes, and program efforts” in Military veteran reintegration: Approach, management, and assessment of military veterans transitioning to civilian life. eds. Castro C. A., Dursun S. (London, United Kingdom: Academic Press; ), 51–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franks T. (2004). American soldier: General Tommy Franks. New York: ReganBooks.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>French S. E. (2005). The code of the warrior: Exploring warrior values past and present. Maryland: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganzevoort R. (1998). Reading by the lines: proposal for a narrative analytical technique in empirical theology. J. Empir. Theol. 11, 23–40. doi: 10.1163/157092598X00112</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1163/157092598X00112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganzevoort R. R. (2008). Scars and stigmata: trauma, identity and theology. Pract. Theol. 1, 19–31. doi: 10.1558/prth.v1i1.19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1558/prth.v1i1.19</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goffman E. (1952). The presentation of self in everyday life. New York: Anchor books.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goffman E. (1986). Stigma: Notes on the management of spoiled identity. New York: Touchstone.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstein J. S. (2001). War and gender: How gender shapes the war system and vice versa. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorman G. E., Clayton P. (2005). Qualitative research for the information professional: a practical handbook (2nd ed). London: Facet Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2016). Existential spiritual life among Swedish service members in transition: marking out trends. Spiritual. Clin. Practice 3, 208–219. doi: 10.1037/scp0000103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/scp0000103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2017a). Making dialogue with an existential voice in transition from military to civilian life. Theory Psychol. 27, 832–850. doi: 10.1177/0959354317739164, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0959354317739164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5703081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29249868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2017b). A service member’s self in transition: a longitudinal case study analysis. J. Constr. Psychol. 30, 255–269. doi: 10.1080/10720537.2016.1187580</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10720537.2016.1187580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2018). Advancing an understanding of selves in transition: I-positions as an analytical tool. Cult. Psychol. 24, 190–211. doi: 10.1177/1354067X17707451, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1354067X17707451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5967103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29881325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2020). Aborted transition between two dichotomous cultures as seen through dialogical self theory. J. Constr. Psychol. 33, 188–206. doi: 10.1080/10720537.2019.1581999</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10720537.2019.1581999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2022a). The invisible wounded warriors in a nation at peace: an interview study on the lives of Swedish veterans of foreign conflicts and their experiences with PTSD, moral injuries, and military identities. Zürich: Lit Verlag.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2022b). After so much is invested in creating robust military identities, what about the construction of fulfilling civilian identities after service? I D. Schmitz Wortmeyer (red.), deep loyalties: Values in military lives (a volume in advances of cultural psychology: Constructing human development). Charlotte, NC: Information Age Publications, 191–210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2023a). A symbolic interactionist perspective on the divide within the veteran self. J. Veteran Stud. 9, 46–59. doi: 10.21061/jvs.v9i1.392</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21061/jvs.v9i1.392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2023b). Evil, constructed: a salient part of an emerging spiritual veteran identity. J. Pastoral Care Couns. 77, 148–157. doi: 10.1177/15423050231213418</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/15423050231213418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10704872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37946528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2023c). Veteranhälsans Limbo: En intervjustudie om försämrat mående och ökat lidande hos svenska utlandsveteraner. Skellefteå: Artos Academic.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimell J. (2023d). Moral injury: understanding Swedish veterans who are assessed but not diagnosed with PTSD. Front. Psych. 14, 1–13. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1200869</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1200869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10725915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38111618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haaland T. L. (2009). “Den norske militaere profesionsidentiteten; Kriger, hjemlandsforsvarer og statsansatt tjenstemann [The Norwegian military professional identity: Warriors, homeland defenders and governmental employees]” in Krigerkultur i en fredsnasjon [warrior culture in a peace nation]. eds. Edström E., Lunde N. T., Matlary J. H. (Olso, Norge: Abstrakt Förlag; ), 48–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall L. K. (2012a). “The importance of understanding military culture” in Advances in social work practice with the military. ed. Beder J. (New York: Routledge, Taylor &amp; Francis Group; ), 3–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall L. K. (2012b). “The military lifestyle and the relationship” in Handbook of counseling military couples. ed. Moore B. A. (New York: Routledge, Taylor and Francis Group; ), 137–156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermans H. J. M. (2001a). The dialogical self: toward a theory of personal and cultural positioning. Cult. Psychol. 7, 243–281. doi: 10.1177/1354067X0173001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1354067X0173001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermans H. J. M. (2001b). The construction of a personal position repertoire: method and practice. Cult. Psychol. 7, 323–365. doi: 10.1177/1354067X0173005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1354067X0173005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermans H. J. M. (2002). The dialogical self as a society of mind: introduction. Theory Psychol. 12, 147–160. doi: 10.1177/0959354302012002626</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0959354302012002626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermans H. J. M., Kempen H. J. G., van Loon R. J. P. (1992). The dialogical self:beyond individualism and rationalism. Am. Psychol. 47, 23–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huntington S. (1957). The soldier and the state: the theory and politics of civil-military relations. Cambridge, MA: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kvale S., Brinkmann S. (2009). Den kvalitativa forskningen (2.a upplagan). Lund, Sverige: Studentlitteratur AB.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsson G. (2019). Mental health problems following military missions: veterans’ experiences of the quality of care. Archi. Women Health Care 2, 1–2. doi: 10.31038/AWHC.2019252</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31038/AWHC.2019252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsson G., Nilsson S., Ohlsson A., Svensén S. (2024). Military veterans’ perception of quality of care following international operations. Cogent Psychol. 11, 1–8. doi: 10.1080/23311908.2024.2306770</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/23311908.2024.2306770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lifton R. J. (1992). Home from the war: Learning from Vietnam veterans (with a new preface and epilogue on the Gulf war). Boston: Beacon Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lunde N. T. (2009). “Profesjonsetiske strategier: Nasjonal konsensus, liberal tilpasning og konservativ avskjerming [Professional ethical strategies: national consensus, liberal adjustment and conservative shielding]” in Krigerkultur i en fredsnasjon [warrior culture in a peace nation]. eds. Edström E., Lunde N. T., Matlary J. H. (Oslo, Norge: Abstrakt Förlag; ), 156–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malmin M. (2013). Warrior culture, spirituality, and prayer. Journal of Religion &amp; Health 52, 740–758. doi: 10.1007/s10943-013-9690-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-013-9690-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23430532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mead G. H. (1934/2015). Mind, self &amp; society (the definite edition) [edited by C.W. Morris, commented by D.R. Huebner and H. Joas]. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merriam S. B. (2002). Qualitative research in practice: Examples for discussion and analysis. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishler E. G. (1986). “The analysis of interview-narratives” in Narrative psychology: the storied nature of human conduct. ed. Sarbin T. R. (Westport, CT: Praeger; ), 233–255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishler E. G. (1991). Research interviewing: Context and narrative. Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishler E. G. (2004). Storylines: craftartists’ narratives of identity. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moss P., Prince M. J. (2014). Weary warriors: power, knowledge, and the invisible wounds of soldiers. New York: Berghahn Books.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nash W. P. (2014). “The stressors of war” in Combat stress injury: theory, research, and management. eds. Figley C. R., Nash W. P. (New York: Routledge Taylor and Francis; ), 11–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polkinghorne D. E. (2005). Language and meaning: data collection in qualitative research. J. Couns. Psychol. 52, 137–145. doi: 10.1037/0022-0167.52.2.137</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0022-0167.52.2.137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarbin T. R. (1986). “The narrative as a root metaphor for psychology” in Narrative psychology: the storied nature of human conduct. ed. Sarbin T. R. (Westport, CT: Praeger; ), 3–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savion S. M. (2009). How do retired officers start anew in civilian society? A phenomenological study of life transition. (Doctoral dissertation). Washington, United States of America: The George Washington University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schok M. (2009). Meaning as a mission: making sense of war and peacekeeping. (Doctoral dissertation). Utrecht, The Netherlands: Utrecht University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sennett R. (1998). Corrosion of character: the personal consequences of work in the new capitalism. New York: W.W. Norton and Co.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shay J. (2002). Odysseus in America: Combat trauma and the trails of homecoming. New York: Scribner.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slocum-Bradley N. (2010). The positioning diamond: a trans-disciplinary framework for discourse analysis. J. Theory Soc. Behav. 40, 79–107. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-5914.2009.00418.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1468-5914.2009.00418.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sørensen H. (2011). “Core values of Danish expeditionary soldiers” in Core values and the expeditionary mindset: armed forces in metamorphosis. eds. Fürst H., Kümmel G. (Baden-Baden, Germany: Nomos Verlagsgesellschaft; ), 179–189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strachan H. (2006). Morale and modern war. J. Contemp. Hist. 41, 211–227. doi: 10.1177/0022009406062054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0022009406062054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajfel H. (1974). Social identity and intergroup behaviour. Soc. Sci. Inf. 13, 65–93. doi: 10.1177/053901847401300204</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/053901847401300204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajfel H., Turner J. C. (1979). “An integrative theory of intergroup conflict” in The social psychology of intergroup relations. eds. Austin W. G., Worchel S. (Monterey, California: Brooks/Cole; ), 33–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thornborrow T., Brown A. D. (2009). Being regimented: aspiration, discipline and identity work in the British parachute regiment. Organ. Stud. 30, 355–376. doi: 10.1177/0170840608101140</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0170840608101140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tick E. (2005). War and the soul. Wheaton, IL: Theosophical Publishing House.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verrips J. (2006). “Dehumanization as a double-edged sword” in Grammars of identity/alterity: a structural approach. eds. Baumann G., Gingrich A. (New York: Berghahn Books; ), 142–154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watson T. (2017). Sociology, work and organisation. 7th Edn. London: Routledge.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wertsch M. E. (1991). Military brats: Legacies of childhood inside the fortress. New York: Harmony Books.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson P. H. (2008). Defining military culture. J. Mil. Hist. 72, 11–41. doi: 10.1353/jmh.2008.0041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1353/jmh.2008.0041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodward R., Jenkings N. K. (2011). Military identities in the situated accounts of British military personnel. Sociology 45, 252–268. doi: 10.1177/0038038510394016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0038038510394016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanos R. C. (2004). Perceptions of transition to civilian life among recently retired air force officers. (Doctoral dissertation). College Park, United States of America: University of Maryland.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>