<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39426054</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1095-8673</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>303</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Journal of surgical research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Surg Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Piloting an Assessment Tool to Organize Surgical Care in Armed Conflicts: Findings From Cameroon.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>446</StartPage><EndPage>453</EndPage><MedlinePgn>446-453</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jss.2024.09.061</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0022-4804(24)00609-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Armed conflict is increasing globally and is dramatically disrupting surgical care more than ever before. To address this, the PIPESS (Personnel, Infrastructure, Procedures, Equipment, Supplies, and Standard) tool was designed to facilitate assessment of hospital capacity. It assesses 6 key categories at 3 timepoints: preconflict, during conflict, and postconflict. This tool was piloted to assess the impact of conflict and COVID-19 on surgical care delivery at the Buea Regional Hospital in Cameroon.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This was a cross-sectional, qualitative study combining in-depth interviews and on-site observations of the surgical care unit. The data collected during the interviews were then applied to the modified PIPESS tool to calculate a preconflict score based on recall and a during conflict score to quantify differences before and during conflict.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We interviewed 12 key informants: 6 patients, 3 doctors, and 3 other staff. The themes extracted from the preconflict period highlight major barriers including rudimentary prehospital care and referral limitations from remote areas, lack of funding and training, and a demand exceeding the supply of care. COVID-19 resulted in an influx of resources into the region and did not disrupt care to the extent of the conflict. Quantitatively, the PIPESS score for preconflict was 110, and the PIPESS score during conflict was 115, showing an increase in resources, specifically in personnel and infrastructure during conflict.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The conflict increased the burden on existing health centers and strained resources for trauma care. Paradoxically, surgical resources increased during the conflict likely because of increased international support along with local displacement of staff toward the hospital. Further data should be collected during the postconflict setting.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gianaris</LastName><ForeName>Kevin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, Indiana. Electronic address: kgianaris16@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Djeunang Dongho</LastName><ForeName>Ghyslaine Bruna</ForeName><Initials>GB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Health Policy and Research, Nkafu Policy Institute, Yaoundé, Cameroon.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fobellah</LastName><ForeName>Nkengafac Nyiawung</ForeName><Initials>NN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Health Policy and Research, Nkafu Policy Institute, Yaoundé, Cameroon; Bangem Health District, Bangem, Cameroon.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gobina</LastName><ForeName>Ronald M</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Health Policy and Research, Nkafu Policy Institute, Yaoundé, Cameroon; Buea Regional Hospital, Buea, Cameroon; Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Buea, Buea, Cameroon.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Foretia</LastName><ForeName>Denis A</ForeName><Initials>DA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Health Policy and Research, Nkafu Policy Institute, Yaoundé, Cameroon; Department of Surgery, Carilion Clinic - Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine, Roanoke, Virginia; Office of the Dean, Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine, Roanoke, Virginia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Surg Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376340</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-4804</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Armed conflict</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cameroon</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Global surgery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Low- and middle-income countries</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Surgical care</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39426054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2024.09.061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0022-4804(24)00609-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>