<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39425062</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>An exploration of community food pantries in Scotland: strategic and operational perspectives on addressing food insecurity and health inequalities.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2881</StartPage><MedlinePgn>2881</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2881</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-024-20421-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Food insecurity and health are inextricably linked. Since 2008, Scotland has witnessed a proliferation of both food insecurity and emergency food provision. There is a recognised commitment from Scottish Government to 'end the need for food banks', however, the food aid landscape was 'turbo-charged' during COVID-19 leading to intense expansion and diversification of food-based projects, including the development of community food pantries (CFPs). These 'new' models are relatively under-researched, meaning we do not adequately understand their potential or realised impacts on food insecurity and health. This study aims to fill that gap.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A qualitative methodology was used to collect and analyse data from in-depth interviews with 10 representatives from both operational and policy settings related to food insecurity in Scotland. In addition, we conducted an analysis of policy documentation from Scottish Government related to tackling food insecurity to understand how CFPs fit into its overall strategy to transition away from food bank use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We found there were variations in conceptualisations of CFPs and how they operate, challenges related to addressing food insecurity at a community level and varied narratives around the role of community level interventions in tackling health inequalities. Choice and access to services were viewed as central components to the pantry model. However, there were significant challenges faced by CFPs, including territorialism, funding and food supply. Articulations of health were often multi-layered and complicated with strong recognition of the social determinants as well as acknowledgement of the limitations of tackling food insecurity and health inequalities solely at the community level.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Despite a commitment to transition away from emergency food provision, CFPs in Scotland appear to face many of the same issues as food banks, particularly those which impact health. Urgent critique of their reliance on surplus food redistribution is required alongside investigation of how these 'new' models are experienced by the people who access them. Further expansion of these models should be viewed with caution and in the same vein as traditional emergency food provision: a symptom of, rather than a solution to, the problem of food insecurity.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baillie</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3760-7768</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC /CSO Social and Public Health Science Research Unit, School of Health and Wellbeing, University of Glasgow, 90 Byres Road, Glasgow, G12 8TB, UK. a.baillie.1@research.gla.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Skivington</LastName><ForeName>Kathryn</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC /CSO Social and Public Health Science Research Unit, School of Health and Wellbeing, University of Glasgow, 90 Byres Road, Glasgow, G12 8TB, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fergie</LastName><ForeName>Gillian</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC /CSO Social and Public Health Science Research Unit, School of Health and Wellbeing, University of Glasgow, 90 Byres Road, Glasgow, G12 8TB, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>MC_UU_00022/3</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>MC_UU_12017/11, MC_UU_00022/3</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>MC_ UU_00022/2</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SPHSU18</GrantID><Agency>Chief Scientist Office, Scottish Government Health and Social Care Directorate</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SPHSU18</GrantID><Agency>Chief Scientist Office, Scottish Government Health and Social Care Directorate</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SPHSU17</GrantID><Agency>Chief Scientist Office, Scottish Government Health and Social Care Directorate</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012606" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Scotland</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000084884" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Insecurity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D063105" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Assistance</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036301" MajorTopicYN="N">Qualitative Research</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054624" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Status Disparities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005523" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Supply</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000091682" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Inequities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007407" MajorTopicYN="N">Interviews as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Community level</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food insecurity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health inequalities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pantry</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Scotland</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11490137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-20421-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-024-20421-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Loopstra R. Interventions to address household food insecurity in high-income countries. Proc Nutr Soc. 2018;77(3):270–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29580316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollard CM, Booth S. Food insecurity and hunger in rich countries-it is time for action against inequality. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(10):1804.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6572174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31117216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spring C, Garthwaite K, Fisher A, Containing Hunger. Contesting injustice? Exploring the transnational growth of Foodbanking- and counter-responses- before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. Food Ethics. 2022;7(1):6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8934159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35340530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowler EA, O’Connor D. Rights-based approaches to addressing food poverty and food insecurity in Ireland and UK. Soc Sci Med. 2012;74(1):44–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22000764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis O, Geiger BB. Did food insecurity rise across Europe after the 2008 crisis? An analysis across welfare regimes. Social Policy Society: J Social Policy Association. 2017;16(3):343–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garthwaite KA, Collins PJ, Bambra C. Food for thought: an ethnographic study of negotiating ill health and food insecurity in a UK foodbank. Social science &amp; medicine (1982). 2015;132:38–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25792338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garratt E. Please sir, I want some more: an exploration of repeat foodbank use. BMC Public Health. 2017;17(1):828.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5697111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29157208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gundersen C, Ziliak JP. Food insecurity and health outcomes. Health affairs (Millwood, Va). 2015;34(11):1830-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26526240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loopstra R. Rising food bank use in the UK: sign of a new public health emergency? Nutr Bull. 2018;43(1):53–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riches G. Food banks and food security: welfare reform, human rights and social policy. Lessons from Canada? Social Policy Adm. 2002;36(6):648–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vozoris NT, Tarasuk VS. Household Food Insufficiency Is Associated with Poorer Health. J Nutr. 2003;133(1):120–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12514278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell Z, Scott S, Visram S, Rankin J, Bambra C, Heslehurst N. Experiences and perceptions of nutritional health and wellbeing amongst food insecure women in Europe: a qualitative meta-ethnography. Social science &amp; medicine (1982). 2022;311:115313-.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36087388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purdam K, Garratt EA, Esmail A. Hungry? Food Insecurity, Social Stigma and Embarrassment in the UK. Sociol (Oxford). 2016;50(6):1072–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson C, Smith D, Cummins S. Understanding the health and wellbeing challenges of the food banking system: a qualitative study of food bank users, providers and referrers in London. Soc Sci Med. 2018;211:95–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6079189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29933211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douglas F, Sapko J, Kiezebrink K, Kyle J, Resourcefulness. Desperation, shame, gratitude and powerlessness: common themes emerging from a study of food bank use in Northeast Scotland. AIMS Public Health. 2015;2(3):297–317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5690237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29546112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garthwaite K. Hunger pains: life inside foodbank Britain. Bristol: Policy; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacLeod MA. Found Wanting, understanding journeys into and out of food insecurity: a longitudinal study. Glasgow: A Menu for Change (Oxfam); 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Power M, Small N, Doherty B, Pickett KE. Hidden hunger? Experiences of food insecurity amongst Pakistani and white British women. British food journal (1966). 2018;120(11):2716-32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6290894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30581196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Horst H, Pascucci S, Bol W. The dark side of food banks? Exploring emotional responses of food bank receivers in the Netherlands. British food journal (1966). 2014;116(9):1506-20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambie-Mumford H. Every town should have one’: emergency food banking in the UK. J Social Policy. 2013;42(1):73–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douglas F, MacKenzie F, Ejebu O-Z, Whybrow S, Garcia AL, McKenzie L et al. A lot of people are struggling privately. They don’t know where to go or they’re not sure of what to do: frontline service provider perspectives of the nature of household food insecurity in Scotland. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2018;15(12).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6313537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30518162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goudie S, Hughes I. The broken plate. 2022. The State of the Nation’s Food System. London; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miall N, Fergie G, Pearce A. Health inequalities in Scotland: trends in deaths, health and wellbeing, health behaviours, and health services since 2000. Glasgow: University of Glasgow; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarasuk V, Dachner N, Hamelin A-M, Ostry A, Williams P, Bosckei E, et al. A survey of food bank operations in five Canadian cities. BMC Public Health. 2014;14(1):1234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4289166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25432209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papargyropoulou E, Fearnyough K, Spring C, Antal L. The future of surplus food redistribution in the UK: reimagining a ‘win-win’ scenario. Food Policy. 2022;108:102230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Healy AE. Measuring food poverty in Ireland: the importance of including exclusion. Ir J Sociology: IJS. 2019;27(2):105–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Human Rights Watch. Nothing left in the cupboards: austerity, welfare cuts and the right to food in the UK. 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Network TSP. FAQs Glasgow: the Scottish pantry network; 2024 [https://scottishpantrynetwork.org.uk/faq/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scottish Government. Dignity: ending hunger together in Scotland: the report of the Independent Working Group on Food Poverty. Edinburgh: Scottish Government; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scottish Government. Consultation analysis: draft plan on ending the need for food banks. Edinburgh: Scottish Government; 2022. Report No.: 1805250728;9781805250722; Contract No.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blaikie N, Priest J. Social research: paradigms in action. Polity; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creswell JW, Creswell JD. Research design: qualitative, quantitative, and mixed methods approaches. Fifth edition: Sage; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scottish Pantry Network. Find your nearest community pantry: Scottish pantry network. 2023 [https://scottishpantrynetwork.org.uk/locations/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammond C. Review of the fair food transformation fund for Scottish government. Edinburgh: Scottish Government Social Research; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scottish Government. Response to UN special rapporteur communication. Food Insecurity and Poverty - Human rights. February 2021. APS Group; 2021. Report No.: 9781800041554;1800041551; Contract No.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scottish Government. Investing in communities fund round 2: food insecurity fact sheet. Edinburgh; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V, Thematic Analysis. A Practical Guide: SAGE; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pool U, Dooris M. Prevalence of food security in the UK measured by the food insecurity experience scale. J Public Health. 2021;44(3):634–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8083270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33866365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodwin S, Marshall M. Building ‘cash first’ momentum while breaking the food bank paradox from the ground up. 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mead R, Thurston M, Bloyce D. From public issues to personal troubles: individualising social inequalities in health within local public health partnerships. Crit Public Health. 2022;32(2):168–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarasuk V. A critical examination of community-based responses to household food insecurity in Canada. Health Educ Behav. 2001;28(4):487–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11465158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizvi A, Wasfi R, Enns A, Kristjansson E. The impact of novel and traditional food bank approaches on food insecurity: a longitudinal study in Ottawa, Canada. BMC Public Health. 2021;21(1):771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8061005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33882881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>IFAN, Trussell Trust. A cash first future: case studies, presentations and next steps from our conference. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyler I. Stigma: the machinery of inequality. London: Bloomsbury Academic; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatzenbuehler ML, Phelan JC, Link BG. Stigma as a fundamental cause of population health inequalities. Am J Public Health (1971). 2013;103(5):813–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3682466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23488505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitehead M. A typology of actions to tackle social inequalities in health. J Epidemiol Commun Health. 2007;61(6):473–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2465710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17496254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douglas M. Beyond ‘health’: why don’t we tackle the cause of health inequalities. In: Smith KE, Hill S, Bambra C, editors. Health inequalities: critical perspectives. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2016.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>