<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429994</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Socio-Demographic Factors Influencing Monkeypox Vaccination Intentions Among Healthcare Workers and the General Population of Makurdi, Nigeria: A Cross-Sectional Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e71828</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e71828</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e71828</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.71828</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background Monkeypox, now known as mpox, is a viral zoonotic disease caused by the monkeypox virus (MPXV) and is endemic to parts of Central and West Africa. Historically considered a regional health issue, mpox has gained global attention due to recent outbreaks in non-endemic regions. In 2022, the World Health Organization (WHO) declared mpox a Public Health Emergency of International Concern (PHEIC) following widespread transmission in countries where the virus had not been previously reported. This declaration was renewed in August 2024 after a surge in cases, particularly across Africa, including the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) and neighboring countries, where a more transmissible strain (Clade 1b) has rapidly spread, complicating efforts to control its transmission. Objective This study evaluated the socio-demographic factors that influenced monkeypox vaccination intentions among healthcare workers and the general population in Benue State, Nigeria. The findings provide insights into key determinants of vaccine hesitancy and acceptance, aimed at informing future public health interventions to improve vaccine uptake. Methodology This cross-sectional study, conducted from July to September 2024 in Makurdi, Benue State, Nigeria, evaluated socio-demographic factors influencing monkeypox vaccination intentions among healthcare workers (HCWs) and high-risk populations. The study, prompted by the WHO's declaration of monkeypox as a PHEIC, surveyed 377+ participants including HCWs, people living with HIV, and men who have sex with men. Results Key findings revealed significant differences in vaccination intentions based on marital status (p-value = 0.02), with no significant variations by gender or age. COVID-19 vaccination status was associated with monkeypox vaccination intentions. The 30-60 age group demonstrated the highest monkeypox awareness (75.2%). Healthcare workers showed high vaccination intent (83%) and were identified as the most reliable information source (p-value = 0.03). Higher education levels correlated with greater vaccine trust (p-value = 0.003), while lower education was linked to reduced awareness and increased stigma perceptions. Conclusion The study recommends enhancing HCW training, addressing socioeconomic barriers to vaccination, implementing targeted education campaigns, and focusing on trust-building strategies. Limitations include the study's urban focus and potential language barriers. In conclusion, socio-demographic factors significantly influence monkeypox vaccination intentions, underscoring the need for targeted interventions and improved vaccine access to mitigate the impact of monkeypox in Nigeria and affected regions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Lawrence et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lawrence</LastName><ForeName>Adewale</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmaceutical Medicine, Bioluminux Clinical Research, Naperville, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare workers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">monkeypox</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nigeria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">socio-demographic factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination intentions</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Health Research Ethics Committee issued approval FMH/FMC/HREC/108/VOL.I. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11491129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.71828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Monkeypox virus: future role in human population. Farasani A. J Infect Public Health. 2022;15:1270–1275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9554154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36272392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiological trends of Lassa fever in Nigeria from 2015-2021: a review. Grace JA, Egoh IJ, Udensi N. Ther Adv Infect Dis. 2021;8:20499361211058252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8637796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34868582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronavirus outbreak in Nigeria: Burden and socio-medical response during the first 100 days. Amzat J, Aminu K, Kolo VI, Akinyele AA, Ogundairo JA, Danjibo MC. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;98:218–224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7307993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32585282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccine hesitancy: where we are and where we are going. McClure CC, Cataldi JR, O'Leary ST. Clin Ther. 2017;39:1550–1562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28774498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors responsible for the re-emergence of monkeypox and implications for global health. Oduoye MO, Faloye TO, Ubechu SC, et al. IJS Global Health. 2024;7:459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attitudes towards anti-SARS-CoV2 vaccination among healthcare workers: results from a national survey in Italy. Di Gennaro F, Murri R, Segala FV, et al. Viruses. 2021;13:371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7996832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33652829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Utilization of health services in a resource-limited rural area in Kenya: prevalence and associated household-level factors. Ngugi AK, Agoi F, Mahoney MR, et al. PLoS One. 2017;12:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5328402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28241032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Improving pro-environmental behaviours in Spain. The role of attitudes and socio-demographic and political factors. Sánchez M, López-Mosquera N, Lera-López F. J Environ Policy Plan. 2016;18:47–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attitudes towards receiving monkeypox vaccination: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Moawad MH, Taha AM, Nguyen D, et al.  https://doi.org/ Vaccines (Basel) 2023;11:1840.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10747893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38140243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Influence of socio-economic attributes on travel behaviour in the rural areas of Nigeria: towards a sustainable rural planning and development. Aderibigbe O-O, Gumbo T. Urban Plan Transp Res. 2022;10:181–199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multidimensional social and cultural norms influencing HPV vaccine hesitancy in Asia. Wong LP, Wong PF, Megat Hashim MM, et al. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2020;16:1611–1622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7482900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32429731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ncreasing vaccination: putting psychological science into action. Brewer NT, Chapman GB, Rothman AJ, Leask J, Kempe A. Psychol Sci Public Interest. 2017;18:149–207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29611455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Re-emergence of monkeypox virus outbreak in Nigeria: epidemic preparedness and response (Review-Commentary) Precious ND, Agboola P, Oluwatimilehin O, et al. Ann Med Surg (Lond) 2023;85:3990–3996.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10406091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37554898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global burden of disease in young people aged 10-24 years: a systematic analysis. Gore FM, Bloem PJ, Patton GC, et al. Lancet. 2011;377:2093–2102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21652063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The rural non-farm economy: prospects for growth and poverty reduction. Haggblade S, Hazell P, Reardon T. World Dev. 2010;38:1429–1441.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sample study protocol for adapting and translating the 5C scale to assess the psychological antecedents of vaccination. Betsch C, Bach Habersaat K, Deshevoi S, et al. BMJ Open. 2020;10:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7066639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32161160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barriers associated with care-seeking for institutional delivery among rural women in three provinces in Afghanistan. Higgins-Steele A, Burke J, Foshanji AI, Farewar F, Naziri M, Seddiqi S, Edmond KM. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2018;18:246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6006744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29914439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gender inequality and restrictive gender norms: framing the challenges to health. Heise L, Greene ME, Opper N, et al. Lancet. 2019;393:2440–2454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31155275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpox (monkeypox) risk and mortality associated with HIV infection: a national case-control study in Nigeria. Yinka-Ogunleye A, Dalhat M, Akinpelu A, et al. BMJ Glob Health. 2023;8:13126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10689363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38035733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ethical problems in nursing management - a cross-sectional survey about solving problems. Aitamaa E, Suhonen R, Puukka P, Leino-Kilpi H. BMC Health Serv Res. 2019;19:417.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6591814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31234855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The state of vaccine confidence 2016: global insights through a 67-country survey. Larson HJ, de Figueiredo A, Xiahong Z, et al. EBioMedicine. 2016;12:295–301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5078590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27658738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpox in people with advanced HIV infection: a global case series. Mitjà O, Alemany A, Marks M, et al. Lancet. 2023;401:939–949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36828001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors influencing pandemic influenza vaccination of healthcare workers - a systematic review. Prematunge C, Corace K, McCarthy A, Nair RC, Pugsley R, Garber G. Vaccine. 2012;30:4733–4743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22643216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strategic silences, eroded trust: the impact of divergent COVID-19 vaccine sentiments on healthcare workers' relations with peers and patients. Heyerdahl LW, Dielen S, Dodion H, et al. Vaccine. 2023;41:883–891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9606030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36319488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy of the modified vaccinia Ankara virus vaccine and the replication-competent vaccine ACAM2000 in monkeypox prevention. Kandeel M, Morsy MA, Abd El-Lateef HM, et al. Int Immunopharmacol. 2023;119:110206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10120163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37087871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>