<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39428518</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Model of driving factors for success in public health project management using structural equation modeling.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>24647</StartPage><MedlinePgn>24647</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">24647</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-75437-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In a context where pandemic crises and chronic conditions are a constant and increasing threat, the success of public health projects is absolutely critical. However, little is known about the factors that influence the success of projects that aim to provide conditions for people to be healthy and prolong the life of the population as a whole. A mixed-method study was carried out to fill the literature gap, resulting in a new model of success factors for public health projects. The research work theorizes the success factors that impact public health project success, providing relevant knowledge for project managers and contributing to the successful management of public health projects.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Santos</LastName><ForeName>Carolina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NOVA National School of Public Health, Public Health Research Centre, Comprehensive Health Research Center, NOVA University, Lisbon, Portugal. c.santos@ensp.unl.pt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Varajão</LastName><ForeName>João</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ALGORITMI Center/LASI, University of Minho, Guimarães, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Takagi</LastName><ForeName>Nilton</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ALGORITMI Center/LASI, University of Minho, Guimarães, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Computing, Federal University of Mato Grosso, Cuiabá, MT, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manuela Gonçalves</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre of Mathematics, University of Minho, Guimarães, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="Y">Public Health</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000077272" MajorTopicYN="N">Latent Class Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008962" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Theoretical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Project management</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Project success</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Success criteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Success factors</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39428518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11491464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-75437-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-75437-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Turnock, B. Public Health: What It Is and How It Works 5th edn (Jones &amp; Bartlett, 2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anomaly, J. What is public health? Public goods, publicized goods, and the conversion problem. Public. Choice, (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8174542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34103770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz, M. P. et al. COVID-19, a worldwide public health emergency. Revista Clínica Española. 221 (1), 55–61 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7173827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33998479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brownson, R. C. et al. Reimagining Public Health in the Aftermath of a pandemic. Am. J. Public Health. 110 (11), 1605–1610 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7542265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32816552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benjamin, G. C. What is Public Health? Telling our own story. Am. J. Public Health. 112 (4), 613–614 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8961827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35319949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kickbusch, I. The contribution of the World Health Organization to a New Public Health and Health Promotion. Am. J. Public Health. 93 (3), 383–388 (2003).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1447748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12604477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner, J. The Handbook of Project-based Management: Leading Strategic Change in Organizations 3th edn (McGraw-Hill Education, 2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Essential public health functions, health systems and health security: Developing conceptual clarity and a WHO roadmap for action. (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CCDF. CDC Foundation. (2024). https://www.cdcfoundation.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EC EU Health Programme: Project Management in Public Health in Europe (Publications Office, 2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ika, L. A. Opening the black box of project management: does World Bank project supervision influence project impact? Int. J. Project Manage. 33 (5), 1111–1123 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ika, L. A. &amp; Donnelly, J. Success conditions for international development capacity building projects. Int. J. Project Manage. 35 (1), 44–63 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto, J. K. &amp; Mantel, S. J. The causes of project failure. IEEE Trans. Eng. Manage. 37 (4), 269–276 (1990).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trigo, A. &amp; Varajão., J. IT Project Management Critical Success Factors. in International Conference on Computational Science and Its Applications. Cagliari, Italy: Springer International Publishing. (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, C. et al. Project Management in Public Health: a systematic literature review on Success Criteria and factors. Portuguese J. Public. Health. 38 (1), 37–48 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baier, M. S. et al. Success factors of process digitalization projects—insights from an exploratory study. Bus. Process. Manage. J. 28 (2), 325–347 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venczel, T. B., Berényi, L. &amp; Hriczó, K. Project Management Success Factors. Journal of Physics: Conference Series, 1935(2021): pp. 1–9. (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsoy, M. &amp; Staples, D. S. What are the critical success factors for Agile Analytics projects? Inform. Syst. Manage. 38 (4), 324–341 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iriarte, C. &amp; Bayona, S. IT projects success factors: a literature review. Int. J. Inform. Syst. Project Manage. 8 (2), 49–78 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radujković, M. &amp; Sjekavica, M. Project management success factors. in Creative Construction Conference. Primosten, Croatia. (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moura, I., Dominguez, C. &amp; Varajão, J. Information systems project team members: factors for high performance. TQM J. 33 (6), 1426–1446 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tam, C. et al. The factors influencing the success of on-going agile software development projects. Int. J. Project Manage. 38 (3), 165–176 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, C. et al. Project management success in health—the need of additional research in public health projects. Procedia Technol. 16 (2014), 1080–1085 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takagi, N. &amp; Varajão, J. ISO 21500 and success management: an integrated model for project management. Int. J. Qual. Reliab. Manage. 39 (2), 408–427 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varajão, J. et al. Success Management—from theory to practice. Int. J. Project Manage. 40 (5), 481–498 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varajão, J. A new process for success management bringing order to a typically ad-hoc area. J. Mod. Project Manage. 5 (3), 92–99 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takagi, N. &amp; Varajão, J. Success Management and Scrum for IS Projects – An Integrated Approach. in Pacific Asia Conference on Information Systems. Association for Information Systems. (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edelman, C. &amp; Kudzma, E. C. Health Promotion throughout the Life Span 10th edn (Elsevier Health Sciences, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cappellaro, G., Compagni, A. &amp; Dacin, M. T. Trajectories of Value Generation and capturing by public–private hybrids: mechanisms of multi-level governance in healthcare. Organ. Stud., : pp. 1–27. (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhodes, P. public health. [cited 2023 01/06/2023]; (2022). https://www.britannica.com/topic/public-health</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moberg, J. et al. The GRADE evidence to decision (EtD) framework for health system and public health decisions. Health Res. Policy Syst. 16 (1), 1–15 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5975536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29843743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunasekeran, D. V. et al. Applications of digital health for public health responses to COVID-19: a systematic scoping review of artificial intelligence, telehealth and related technologies. Npj Digit. Med. 4 (1), 40 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7910557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33637833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubé, È. et al. Vaccine hesitancy, acceptance, and anti-vaccination: trends and future prospects for public health. Annu. Rev. Public Health. 42 (1), 175–191 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33798403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul, E., Steptoe, A. &amp; Fancourt, D. Attitudes towards vaccines and intention to vaccinate against COVID-19: implications for public health communications. Lancet Reg. Health - Europe. 1 (2021), 1–10 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33954296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benham, J. L. et al. Attitudes, current behaviours and barriers to public health measures that reduce COVID-19 transmission: a qualitative study to inform public health messaging. PloS One. 16 (2), 1–14 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7895406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33606782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papke-Shields, K. E., Beise, C. &amp; Quan, J. Do project managers practice what they preach, and does it matter to project success? Int. J. Project Manage. 28 (7), 650–662 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner, J. &amp; Xue, Y. On the success of megaprojects. Int. J. Managing Projects Bus. 11 (3), 783–805 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Wit, A. Measurement of project success. Int. J. Project Manage. 6 (3), 164–170 (1988).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngereja, B. J., Hussein, B. &amp; Wolff, C. A comparison of soft factors in the implementation and adoption of digitalization projects: a systematic literature review. Int. J. Inform. Syst. Project Manage. 12 (2), 70–86 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shore, B. Systematic biases and culture in Project failures. Project Manage. J. 39 (4), 5–16 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirley, D. Project Management for Healthcare 2nd edn (CRC, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belout, A. &amp; Gauvreau, C. Factors influencing project success: the impact of human resource management. Int. J. Project Manage. 22 (1), 1–11 (2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mir, F. A. &amp; Pinnington, A. H. Exploring the value of project management: linking Project Management Performance and Project Success. Int. J. Project Manage. 32 (2), 202–217 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem, F. et al. Public Health and Project Management: do projects deliver? Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 17 10.3390/ijerph17197244 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7579134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33023044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milat, A. J., Bauman, A. &amp; Redman, S. Narrative review of models and success factors for scaling up public health interventions. Implement. Sci. 10 (1), 1–11 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4533941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26264351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barros, L., Tam, C. &amp; Varajão, J. Agile software development projects–Unveiling the human-related critical success factors. Information and Software Technology, 170(2024): pp. 1–12. (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cserháti, G. &amp; Szabó, L. The relationship between success criteria and success factors in organisational event projects. Int. J. Project Manage. 32 (4), 613–624 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takagi, N. &amp; Varajão, J. Integration of success management into project management guides and methodologies - position paper. Procedia Computer Science, 164(2019): pp. 366–372. (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takagi, N. et al. Managing success criteria and success factors in a BPM project: an approach using PRINCE2 and Success Management on the public sector. Cogent Bus. Manage. 11 (1), 1–20 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim, C. S. &amp; Mohamed, M. Z. Criteria of project success: an exploratory re-examination. Int. J. Project Manage. 17 (4), 243–248 (1999).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPMA, Individual Competence Baseline for Project, Programme and Portfolio Management. 4th ed. Amrsterdam, Netherlands: International Project Management Association. (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira, J., Varajão, J. &amp; Takagi, N. Evaluation of Information Systems Project success – insights from practitioners. Inform. Syst. Manage. 39 (2), 138–155 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shenhar, A. et al. Project Success: a Multidimensional Strategic Concept. Long Range Plann. 34 (6), 699–725 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baccarini, D. The logical framework method for defining project success. Project Manage. J. 30 (4), 25–32 (1999).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dille, T., Hernes, T. &amp; Vaagaasar, A. L. Stuck in temporal translation? Challenges of discrepant temporal structures in interorganizational project collaboration. Organ. Stud. 44 (6), 867–888 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berg, H. &amp; Ritschel, J. D. The characteristics of successful military IT projects: A cross-country empirical study. Int. J. Inform. Syst. Project Manage. 11 (2), 25–44 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen, E. S. Do project managers have different perspectives on project management? Int. J. Project Manage. 34 (1), 58–65 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen, E. S. Value creation using the mission breakdown structure. Int. J. Project Manage. 32 (5), 885–892 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Westerveld, E. The project excellence model: Linking success criteria and critical success factors. Int. J. Project Manage. 21 (6), 411–418 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryde, D. J. Modelling project management performance. Int. J. Qual. Reliab. Manage. 20 (2), 229–254 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qureshi, T. M., Warraich, A. S. &amp; Hijazi, S. T. Significance of project management performance assessment (PMPA) model. Int. J. Project Manage. 27 (4), 378–388 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winter, M. &amp; Szczepanek, T. Projects and programmes as value creation processes: A new perspective and some practical implications. Int. J. Project Manage. 26 (1), 95–103 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berssaneti, F. T. &amp; Carvalho, M. M. Identification of variables that impact project success in Brazilian companies. Int. J. Project Manage. 33 (3), 638–649 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis, K. An empirical investigation into different stakeholder groups perception of project success. Int. J. Project Manage. 35 (4), 604–617 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, P. et al. Relationship quality and satisfaction: Customer-perceived success factors for on-time projects. Int. J. Project Manage. 33 (8), 1836–1850 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serrador, P. &amp; Pinto, J. K. Does agile work?—A quantitative analysis of agile project success. Int. J. Project Manage. 33 (5), 1040–1051 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haverila, M. J. &amp; Fehr, K. The impact of product superiority on customer satisfaction in project management. Int. J. Project Manage. 34 (4), 570–583 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkinson, R. Project management: cost, time and quality, two best guesses and a phenomenon, its time to accept other success criteria. Int. J. Project Manage. 17 (6), 337–342 (1999).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takagi, N. &amp; Ventura, T. Artificial Intelligence Insights on Success Evaluation in Information Systems Government-to-Government Projects, in Mediterranean Conference on Information Systems. AIS: Porto, Portugal. (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyman, H. J. &amp; Öörni, A. Successful projects or success in project management-are projects dependent on a methodology? Int. J. Inform. Syst. Project Manage. 11 (4), 5–25 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis, K. Different stakeholder groups and their perceptions of project success. Int. J. Project Manage. 32 (2), 189–201 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooke-Davies, T. The real success factors on projects. Int. J. Project Manage. 20 (3), 185–190 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesh, V., Brown, S. A. &amp; Bala, H. Bridging the qualitative-quantitative divide: guidelines for conducting mixed methods research in information systems. MIS Q. 37 (1), 21–54 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdullah, A. A. et al. Literature mapping: a bird’s eye view on classification of factors influencing project success. Afr. J. Bus. Manage. 4 (19), 4174–4182 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheadle, A. et al. Involving local health departments in community health partnerships: Evaluation results from the Partnership for the public’s Health Initiative. J. Urb. Health. 85 (2), 162–177 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2430113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18259870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwyer, J., Stanton, P. &amp; Thiessen, V. Project Management in Health and Community Services: Getting good Ideas to work (Allen &amp; Unwin, 2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medlin, C. A. et al. Improving the Health of Populations: Lessons of Experience, in Disease Control Priorities in Developing Countries (The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The World Bank, 2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21250309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paré, G. &amp; Trudel, M. C. Knowledge barriers to PACS adoption and implementation in hospitals. Int. J. Med. Informatics. 76 (1), 22–33 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16478675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suhonen, M. &amp; Paasivaara, L. Nurse managers’ challenges in project management. J. Nurs. Adm. Manag. 19 (8), 1028–1036 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22074305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yazici, H. The role of project management maturity and organizational culture in perceived performance. Project Manage. J. 40 (3), 14–33 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isensee, C. et al. The relationship between organizational culture, sustainability, and digitalization in SMEs: A systematic review. J. Clean. Prod. 275 (2020), 1–19 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diallo, A. &amp; Thuillier, D. The success dimensions of international development projects: The perceptions of African project coordinators. Int. J. Project Manage. 22 (1), 19–31 (2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glaser, J. Management’s role in IT project failures, in Healthcare Financial Management. pp. 90–92. (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15524041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khang, D. B. &amp; Moe, T. L. Success Criteria and factors for International Development projects: A life-cycle-based Framework. Project Manage. J. 39 (1), 72–84 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ackermann, F. &amp; Eden, C. Strategic Management of stakeholders: Theory and practice. Long Range Plann. 44 (3), 179–196 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dvir, D., Raz, T. &amp; Shenhar, A. An empirical analysis of the relationship between project planning and project success. Int. J. Project Manage. 21 (2), 89–95 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tempfer, C. B. &amp; Nowak, P. Consumer participation and organizational development in health care: A systematic review. Wien. Klin. Wochenschr. 123 (13), 408–414 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21739200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irfan, M. et al. Role of project planning and project manager competencies on public sector project success. Sustainability. 13 (3), 1421 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Payne, J. M. et al. Researchers’ experience with project management in health and medical research: Results from a post-project review. BMC Public. Health. 11 (424), 1–11 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3135535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21635721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snowden, D. Complex acts of knowing: Paradox and descriptive self-awareness. J. Knowl. Manage. 6 (2), 100–111 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sampedro, F. et al. Developing a risk management framework to improve public health outcomes by enumerating Salmonella in ground Turkey – RETRACTION. Epidemiol. Infect. 147 (e69), 1–8 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6518596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30520390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>PMI. Process Groups: A Practical Guide (Project Management Institute, 2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, C. C., Liu, P. H. &amp; Tsai, Y. C. Resource-constrained project management using enhanced theory of constraint. Int. J. Project Manage. 20 (7), 561–567 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crawford, P. &amp; Bryce, P. Project monitoring and evaluation: a method for enhancing the efficiency and effectiveness of aid project implementation. Int. J. Project Manage. 21 (5), 363–373 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zulch, B. G. Communication: The Foundation of Project Management. Procedia Technol. 16 (2014), 1000–1009 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Söderlund, J. Pluralism in Project Management: Navigating the crossroads of specialization and fragmentation. Int. J. Manage. Reviews. 13 (2), 153–176 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, H. L. &amp; Lin, Y. L. Goal orientations, leader-leader exchange, trust, and the outcomes of project performance. Int. J. Project Manage. 36 (5), 716–729 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buvik, M. P. &amp; Rolfsen, M. Prior ties and trust development in project teams—a case study from the construction industry. Int. J. Project Manage. 33 (7), 1484–1494 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tansley, C. &amp; Newell, S. Project social capital, leadership and trust: A study of human resource information systems development. J. Managerial Psychol. 22 (4), 350–368 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edward, J., Kinlaw, C. S. &amp; Kinlaw, D. C. Developing superior project teams: a study of the characteristics of high performance in project teams. in PMI Research Conference. Paris, France: Project Management Institute. (2000).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paton, S., Hodgson, D. &amp; Cicmil, S. Who am I and what am I doing here? Becoming and being a project manager. J. Manage. Dev. 29 (2), 157–166 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takagi, N. et al. Implementing Success Management and PRINCE2 in a BPM Public Project. in Australasian Conference on Information Systems (ACIS). Sydney, Australia: Association for Information Systems. (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marnewick, C. A longitudinal analysis of ICT project success. in South African Institute for Computer Scientists and Information Technologists Conference. Centurion, South Africa: ACM. (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller, R. &amp; Jugdev, K. Critical success factors in projects: Pinto, Slevin, and Prescott – the elucidation of project success. Int. J. Managing Projects Bus. 5 (4), 757–775 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorman, K. &amp; Johnson, D. E. Quantitative analysis, in The Oxford Handbook of Sociolinguistics. Oxford University Press. 214–240. (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pallant, J. SPSS Survival Manual: A step by step Guide to data Analysis Using IBM SPSS 7th edn (Routledge, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cronbach, L. J. Coefficient alpha and the internal structure of tests. Psychometrika. 16 (3), 297–334 (1951).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nunnally, J. C. &amp; Bernstein, I. H. Psychometric Theory 3rd edn (McGraw-Hill, 1994).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bentler, P. M. On tests and indices for evaluating structural models. Pers. Indiv. Differ. 42 (5), 825–829 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen, J. A power primer. Psychol. Bull. 112 (1), 155–159 (1992).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19565683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPMA, Project Excellence Baseline - for Achieving Excellence in Projects and Programmes. Amrsterdam, Netherlands: International Project Management Association. (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>PMI A Guide to the Project Management Body of Knowledge: (PMBOK Guide) 7th edn (Project Management Institute, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munns, A. K. &amp; Bjeirmi, B. F. The role of project management in achieving project success. Int. J. Project Manage. 14 (2), 81–87 (1996).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varajão, J., Fernandes, G. &amp; Silva, H. Most used project management tools and techniques in information systems projects. J. Syst. Inform. Technol. 12 (3), 225–242 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engwall, M. No project is an island: linking projects to history and context. Res. Policy. 32 (5), 789–808 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundin, R. A. &amp; Steinthórsson, R. S. Studying organizations as temporary. Scand. J. Manag. 19 (2), 233–250 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johansson, S., Löfström, M. &amp; Ohlsson, Ö. Separation or integration? A dilemma when organizing development projects. Int. J. Project Manage. 25 (5), 457–464 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grabher, G. The Project Ecology of Advertising: Tasks, talents and teams. Reg. Stud. 36 (3), 245–262 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White, D. &amp; Fortune, J. Current practice in project management—an empirical study. Int. J. Project Manage. 20 (1), 1–11 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diallo, A. &amp; Thuillier, D. The success of international development projects, trust and communication: An African perspective. Int. J. Project Manage. 23 (3), 237–252 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X. &amp; Huang, J. The relationships between key stakeholders’ project performance and project success: perceptions of Chinese construction supervising engineers. Int. J. Project Manage. 24 (3), 253–260 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyväri, I. Success of projects in different organizational conditions. Project Manage. J. 37 (4), 31–41 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varajão, J. &amp; Trigo, A. Assessing IT Project success – perception vs. Reality (ACM Queue, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabachnick, B. G. &amp; Fidell, L. S. Using Multivariate Statistics 7th edn (Pearson, 2019).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>