<PubmedArticle xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39427025</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>SAPPNet: students' academic performance prediction during COVID-19 using neural network.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>24605</StartPage><MedlinePgn>24605</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">24605</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-75242-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A variety of reasons have made it more difficult for educators and tutors to anticipate students' performance. Numerous researchers have used various predictive models to identify students who may be at-risk of dropping out early. Additionally, these methods were used to forecast final semester grades based on various datasets. However, these prediction models still fall short of meeting educational management requirements. In this paper, we propose the deep learning (DL) based model named students academic performance prediction network (SAPPNet) to predict the students' grades. We consider the questionnaire-based Jordan University dataset which contains demographic information, usage of digital tools before and after COVID-19, sleep times before and after COVID-19, social interaction, psychological state, and academic performance. SAPPNet consists of spatial convolution modules which are designed to extract spatial dependencies includes categorical and numerical attributes that represent static features (gender, level/year, age, digital tools used before and after COVID-19, psychological condition using prolonged e-learning tools) and temporal module for temporal dependencies involves sequences that capture changes before and after COVID-19. Additionally, we also try to implement classical machine learning (ML) models including support vector machine, k nearest neighbor, decision tree, and random forest, and DL models named artificial neural network, convolutional neural network, long short-term memory, and students learning prediction network. Simulation results show that SAPPNet achieved the best performance compared to state-of-the-art methods, with an accuracy, precision, recall, and an F1-score of <ns0:math><ns0:mrow><ns0:mn>93</ns0:mn> <ns0:mo>%</ns0:mo></ns0:mrow> </ns0:math> . The proposed model with spatial and temporal modules improves the prediction performance, and it implies new aspect of the educational dataset.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Junejo</LastName><ForeName>Naveed Ur Rehman</ForeName><Initials>NUR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Physics and Electronic Engineering, Hanshan Normal University, Chaozhou, 521041, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Hanshan Normal University, Chaozhou, 521041, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Electronic and Information Engineering, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen, 518060, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Qingsheng</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Mathematics and Statistics, Hanshan Normal University, Chaozhou, 521041, China. huangqs@hstc.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dong</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoqing</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Physics and Electronic Engineering, Hanshan Normal University, Chaozhou, 521041, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Chang</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Physics and Electronic Engineering, Hanshan Normal University, Chaozhou, 521041, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeb</LastName><ForeName>Adnan</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Intelligent Manufacturing and Smart Transportation, Suzhou City University, Suzhou, 215000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Humayoo</LastName><ForeName>Mahammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Hanshan Normal University, Chaozhou, 521041, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Gengzhong</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Hanshan Normal University, Chaozhou, 521041, China. zhenggz@hstc.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2023KCXTD022</GrantID><Agency>The Innovation Teams of Ordinary Universities in Guangdong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021KCXTD038</GrantID><Agency>The Innovation Teams of Ordinary Universities in Guangdong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2022KSYS003</GrantID><Agency>Key Laboratory of Ordinary Universities in Guangdong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073978" MajorTopicYN="Y">Academic Performance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016571" MajorTopicYN="Y">Neural Networks, Computer</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007597" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Jordan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000077321" MajorTopicYN="N">Deep Learning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014495" MajorTopicYN="N">Universities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Deep learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">K-NN</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SVM</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Student performance prediction. machine learning</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39427025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11490531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-75242-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-75242-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Huang, Z. &amp; Wang, G. Student learning performance prediction based on online behavior: An empirical study during the covid-19 pandemic. PeerJ Comput. Sci.9, e1699 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10703107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38077563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pokhrel, S. &amp; Chhetri, R. A literature review on impact of covid-19 pandemic on teaching and learning. High. Educ. Future8, 133–141 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kloft, M., Stiehler, F., Zheng, Z. &amp; Pinkwart, N. Predicting mooc dropout over weeks using machine learning methods. In Proceedings of the EMNLP 2014 workshop on analysis of large scale social interaction in MOOCs, 60–65 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waheed, H. et al. Early prediction of learners at risk in self-paced education: A neural network approach. Expert Syst. Appl.213, 118868 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waheed, H. et al. Predicting academic performance of students from vle big data using deep learning models. Comput. Hum. Behav.104, 106189 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raj, N. S., Prasad, S., Harish, P., Boban, M. &amp; Cheriyedath, N. Early prediction of at-risk students in a virtual learning environment using deep learning techniques. In International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction, 110–120 (Springer, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousafzai, B. K. et al. Student-performulator: Student academic performance using hybrid deep neural network. Sustainability13, 9775 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, O. H. et al. Applying learning analytics for the early prediction of students’ academic performance in blended learning. J. Educ. Technol. Soc.21, 220–232 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydoğdu, Ş. Predicting student final performance using artificial neural networks in online learning environments. Educ. Inf. Technol.25, 1913–1927 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yağcı, M. Educational data mining: Prediction of students’ academic performance using machine learning algorithms. Smart Learn. Environ.9, 11 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., An, R., Liu, S., Cui, J. &amp; Shang, X. Predicting and understanding student learning performance using multi-source sparse attention convolutional neural networks. IEEE Trans. Big Data9, 118–132 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y. et al. Educational data mining techniques for student performance prediction: Method review and comparison analysis. Front. Psychol.12, 698490 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8688359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34950079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamoud, A., Hashim, A. S. &amp; Awadh, W. A. Predicting student performance in higher education institutions using decision tree analysis. Int. J. Interact. Multimed. Artif. Intell.5, 26–31 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, W., Ji, P. &amp; Hu, J. A survey on educational data mining methods used for predicting students’ performance. Eng. Rep.4, e12482 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mengash, H. A. Using data mining techniques to predict student performance to support decision making in university admission systems. IEEE Access8, 55462–55470 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, B., Zhang, R., Xu, G., Shi, C. &amp; Yang, L. Predicting students performance in educational data mining. In 2015 international symposium on educational technology (ISET), 125–128 (IEEE, 2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, B.-H., Vizitei, E. &amp; Ganapathi, V. Gritnet: Student performance prediction with deep learning. 2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Q. &amp; Rangwala, H. Reliable deep grade prediction with uncertainty estimation. In Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Learning Analytics &amp; Knowledge, 76–85 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LeCun, Y., Bengio, Y. &amp; Hinton, G. Deep learning. Nature521, 436–444 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26017442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan, S.-U. et al. Virtual learning environment to predict withdrawal by leveraging deep learning. Int. J. Intell. Syst.34, 1935–1952 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Q. &amp; Rangwala, H. Academic performance estimation with attention-based graph convolutional networks. (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernacki, M. L., Chavez, M. M. &amp; Uesbeck, P. M. Predicting achievement and providing support before stem majors begin to fail. Comput. Educ.158, 103999 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haider, A. S. &amp; Al-Salman, S. Dataset of Jordanian university students’ psychological health impacted by using e-learning tools during covid-19. Data Brief32, 106104 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32789158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, X. &amp; Li, J. Sequential engagement-based online learning analytics and prediction. In Intelligent Systems and Learning Data Analytics in Online Education, 71–89 (Elsevier, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal, Z., Qadir, J., Mian, A. N. &amp; Kamiran, F. Machine learning based student grade prediction: A case study. (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marbouti, F., Diefes-Dux, H. A. &amp; Madhavan, K. Models for early prediction of at-risk students in a course using standards-based grading. Comput. Educ.103, 1–15 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Shehri, H. et al. Student performance prediction using support vector machine and k-nearest neighbor. In 2017 IEEE 30th canadian conference on electrical and computer engineering (CCECE), 1–4 (IEEE, 2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaulac, C. &amp; Rosenthal, J. S. Predicting University students’ academic success and major using random forests. Res. High. Educ.60, 1048–1064 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hlioui, F., Aloui, N. &amp; Gargouri, F. Understanding learner engagement in a virtual learning environment. In Intelligent Systems Design and Applications: 18th International Conference on Intelligent Systems Design and Applications (ISDA 2018) held in Vellore, India, December 6-8, 2018, Volume 2, 709–719 (Springer, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chui, K. T., Fung, D. C. L., Lytras, M. D. &amp; Lam, T. M. Predicting at-risk university students in a virtual learning environment via a machine learning algorithm. Comput. Hum. Behav.107, 105584 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hew, K. F., Hu, X., Qiao, C. &amp; Tang, Y. What predicts student satisfaction with moocs: A gradient boosting trees supervised machine learning and sentiment analysis approach. Comput. Educ.145, 103724 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sood, S. &amp; Saini, M. Hybridization of cluster-based lda and ann for student performance prediction and comments evaluation. Educ. Inf. Technol.26, 2863–2878 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cazarez, R. L. U. Accuracy comparison between statistical and computational classifiers applied for predicting student performance in online higher education. Educ. Inf. Technol.27, 11565–11590 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9110636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35603317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abou Naaj, M., Mehdi, R., Mohamed, E. A. &amp; Nachouki, M. Analysis of the factors affecting student performance using a neuro-fuzzy approach. Educ. Sci.13, 313 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, C., Wang, H. &amp; Yuan, Z. A method for predicting the academic performances of college students based on education system data. Mathematics10, 3737 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed, E. Student performance prediction using machine learning algorithms. Appl. Comput. Intell. Soft Comput.2024, 4067721 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotsiantis, S. B. Use of machine learning techniques for educational proposes: A decision support system for forecasting students’ grades. Artif. Intell. Rev.37, 331–344 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nahar, K., Shova, B. I., Ria, T., Rashid, H. B. &amp; Islam, A. S. Mining educational data to predict students performance: A comparative study of data mining techniques. Educ. Inf. Technol.26, 6051–6067 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu, F. et al. Predicting students’ performance in e-learning using learning process and behaviour data. Sci. Rep.12, 453 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8748729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35013396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilal, M., Omar, M., Anwar, W., Bokhari, R. H. &amp; Choi, G. S. The role of demographic and academic features in a student performance prediction. Sci. Rep.12, 12508 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9307570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35869103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, Y. Student performance prediction via attention-based multi-layer long-short term memory. J. Comput. Commun.9, 61–79 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alnasyan, B., Basheri, M. &amp; Alassafi, M. The power of deep learning techniques for predicting student performance in virtual learning environments: A systematic literature review. Computers and Education: Artificial Intelligence 100231 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Junejo, N. et al. SLPNet: Student’s learning performance prediction during covid-19 using deep neural network. Unpublished.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>