<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39425220</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2397-0642</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Global health research and policy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Glob Health Res Policy</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Challenges associated with the implementation of institutional quarantine and isolation strategies during major multicountry viral outbreaks in Africa (2000-2023): a scoping review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>44</StartPage><MedlinePgn>44</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">44</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s41256-024-00385-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Quarantine and isolation (Q&amp;I) are interrelated but not mutually exclusive public health practices for disease control, which may face public resistance in the context of health emergencies due to associated challenges. Hence, it is often tough for most countries to implement Q&amp;I even in the context of health emergencies. Therefore, this scoping review examines the challenges associated with the implementation of institutional Q&amp;I strategies during major multicountry viral outbreaks (Ebola, Lassa and COVID-19) in Africa between 2000 and 2023.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This scoping review was designed based on Arksey and O'Malley's guidelines. A systematic literature search, using nine online research databases, was conducted with the aid of relevant search terms, Boolean operators and truncations. All articles obtained from the literature search were electronically imported into Rayyan web application for deduplication based on specific inclusion and exclusion criteria. From the included literature, relevant data were charted, summarized, collated, and presented.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">This review included 24 of the 787 retrieved articles. Sixteen of the 24 selected articles investigated issues related to COVID-19 prevention and control in Africa. Two assessed precautionary practices for Lassa fever, while five were on Ebola virus disease. However, one article explored knowledge, preventive practices, and general isolation precautions. The review identified various challenges that hindered the implementation of successful Q&amp;I practices during viral infection outbreaks in Africa. Essential healthcare infrastructure, equipment (medical supplies including personal protective equipment and testing kits) and facilities that are essential for Q&amp;I were deficient. Q&amp;I implementation was often threatened by low human resource capacity and inefficiencies in the healthcare system which portray Africa as unprepared to handle complex public health crises.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This review shows that Q&amp;I implementation in Africa is often threatened by low human resource capacity and inefficiencies in the healthcare system and also portrays Africa as unprepared to handle complex public health crises. Hence, Q&amp;I for major multicountry outbreaks in Africa is very challenging. Therefore, continuous efforts to address these identified challenges are crucial to enhancing health emergency preparedness in Africa.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amzat</LastName><ForeName>Jimoh</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9564-1190</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Usmanu Danfodiyo University, Sokoto, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, University of Johannesburg, Johannesburg, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health and Life Sciences, Teesside University, Middlesbrough, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oduwole</LastName><ForeName>Ebunoluwa</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Philosophy, Olabisi Onabanjo University, Ago-Iwoye, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lawal</LastName><ForeName>Saheed Akinmayowa</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Olabisi Onabanjo University, Ago-Iwoye, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aluko-Arowolo</LastName><ForeName>Olusola</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Olabisi Onabanjo University, Ago-Iwoye, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Afolabi</LastName><ForeName>Rotimi</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology and Medical Statistics, College of Medicine, University of Ibadan, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adedeji</LastName><ForeName>Isaac Akinkunmi</ForeName><Initials>IA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Olabisi Onabanjo University, Ago-Iwoye, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Temisan</LastName><ForeName>Ige Angela</ForeName><Initials>IA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Science and Technology Education, University of Ibadan, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oludiran</LastName><ForeName>Ayoyinka</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Olabisi Onabanjo University, Ago-Iwoye, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aminu</LastName><ForeName>Kafayat</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7438-2556</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Child and Adolescent Mental Health, University College Hospital, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salami</LastName><ForeName>Afeez Abolarinwa</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4544-0080</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Dentistry, University of Puthisastra, Phnom Penh, Cambodia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Dentistry, Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, University College Hospital, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanmodi</LastName><ForeName>Kehinde Kazeem</ForeName><Initials>KK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9906-3826</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Dentistry, University of Puthisastra, Phnom Penh, Cambodia. kanmodikehinde@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive and Community Dentistry, University of Rwanda, Kigali, Rwanda. kanmodikehinde@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NRF/HSS/GPL/00048</GrantID><Agency>TETFund</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Glob Health Res Policy</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101705789</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2397-0642</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011790" MajorTopicYN="Y">Quarantine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000349" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Africa</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019142" MajorTopicYN="N">Hemorrhagic Fever, Ebola</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007835" MajorTopicYN="N">Lassa Fever</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11489991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s41256-024-00385-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s41256-024-00385-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Amzat J, Kanmodi KK, Aminu K, Egbedina EA. School-based interventions on Mpox: a scoping review. Health Sci Rep. 2023;6(6):e1334. 10.1002/hsr2.1334</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10259520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37313531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amzat J, Razum O. Globalization, health and the Global South: a critical approach. London: Routledge; 2022. 10.4324/9781003247975.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbisch D, Koenig KL, Shih FY. Is there a case for quarantine? Perspectives from SARS to Ebola. Disaster Med Public Health Prep. 2015;9(5):547–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25797363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amzat J, Razum O. Healthcare emergencies in Africa: A case of Ebola in Nigeria. In: Amzat J, Razum O, editors. Towards a Sociology of Health Discourse in Africa. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2014. p. 143–55. 10.1007/978-3-319-61672-8_10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood R, Reinhardt GY, RezaeeDaryakenari B, Windsor LC. Resisting lockdown: the influence of COVID-19 restrictions on social unrest. Int Stud Q. 2022;66(2):sqac015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimoh A, Akor O. COVID-19: Our self-isolation policy has failed – FG. Daily Trust [Internet]. 2020 May 8 [cited 2024 Jan 10]; https://dailytrust.com/covid-19-our-self-isolation-policy-has-failed-fg/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onwuzoo A. Nigeria can’t beat COVID-19 with patients fleeing isolation centres. Healthwise [Internet]. 2020 May 12 [cited 2024 Jan 10]; https://healthwise.punchng.com/nigeria-cant-beat-covid-19-with-patients-fleeing-isolation-centres/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arksey H, O’Malley L. Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework. Int J Soc Res Methodol. 2005;8(1):19–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouzzani M, Hammady H, Fedorowicz Z, Elmagarmid A. Rayyan—a web and mobile app for systematic reviews. Syst Rev. 2016;5(1):210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5139140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27919275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ackah BBB, Woo M, Stallwood L, Fazal ZA, Okpani A, Ukah UV, et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Africa: a scoping review. Glob Health Res Policy. 2022;7(1):21. 10.1186/s41256-022-00255-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9294808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35850783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adu PA, Stallwood L, Adebola SO, Abah T, Okpani AI. The direct and indirect impact of COVID-19 pandemic on maternal and child health services in Africa: a scoping review. Glob Health Res Policy. 2022;7(1):20. 10.1186/s41256-022-00257-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9296365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35854345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tricco AC, Lillie E, Zarin W, O’Brien K, Colquhoun H, Kastner M, et al. A scoping review on the conduct and reporting of scoping reviews. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2016;16(1):15. 10.1186/s12874-016-0116-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4746911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26857112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol. 2006;3(2):77–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aidonojie PA, Okuonghae N, Ukhurebor KE. The Legal rights and challenges of COVID-19 patients accessing private Healthcare in Nigeria. BESTUUR. 2022;10(2):183–97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asare IT, Douglas M, Kye-Duodu G, Manu E. Challenges and opportunities for improved contact tracing in Ghana: experiences from coronavirus disease-2019-related contact tracing in the Bono region. BMC Infect Dis. 2023;23(1):335.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10193342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37202733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delamou A, Sow A, Fofana TO, Sidibé S, Kourouma K, Sandouno M, et al. A rapid assessment of health system preparedness and response to the COVID-19 pandemic in Guinea. J Public Health Afr. 2022;13(2):1475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9425928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36051518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desie Y, Habtamu K, Asnake M, Gina E, Mequanint T. Coping strategies among Ethiopian migrant returnees who were in quarantine in the time of COVID-19: a center-based cross-sectional study. BMC Psychol. 2021;9(1):192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8653623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34879855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fawole OI, Bello S, Adebowale AS, Bamgboye EA, Salawu MM, Afolabi RF, et al. COVID-19 surveillance in Democratic Republic of Congo, Nigeria, Senegal and Uganda: strengths, weaknesses and key lessons. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):835.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10165588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37158897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GebreEyesus FA, Geleta OT, Shiferaw BZ, Tarekegn TT, Amlak BT, Emeria MS, et al. Health care providers’ preparedness and health care protection against the third wave of COVID-19 pandemics in a resource-limited setting in Southwest Ethiopia: a multi-center cross-sectional study. Pan Afr Med J. 2023;44:53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10148170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37128615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habtamu K, Desie Y, Asnake M, Lera EG, Mequanint T. Psychological distress among Ethiopian migrant returnees who were in quarantine in the context of COVID-19: institution-based cross-sectional study. BMC Psychiatry. 2021;21(1):424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8385266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34433430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idrees MHD, Bashir MMI. The psychological impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the Sudanese healthcare workers in quarantine centers: a cross-sectional study 2020–2021. Middle East Curr Psychiatry Ain Shams Univ. 2023;30(1):19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joy Okwor T, Gatua J, Umeokonkwo CD, Abah S, Ike IF, Ogunniyi A, et al. An assessment of infection prevention and control preparedness of healthcare facilities in Nigeria in the early phase of the COVID-19 pandemic (February-May 2020). J Infect Prev. 2022;23(3):101–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8872810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35502165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kharroubi G, Cherif I, Amor SH, Zribi M, Atigue WB, Ouali U, et al. Mental health status of adults under institutional quarantine: a cross-sectional survey in Tunisia. Pan Afr Med J. 2021;40:197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8760296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35096224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misgana T, Tesfaye D, Tariku M, Ali T, Alemu D, Dessie Y. Psychological burden and associated factors of the COVID-19 pandemic on people in quarantine and isolation centers in Ethiopia: a cross-sectional study. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:753383.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8790141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35095590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndejjo R, Naggayi G, Tibiita R, Mugahi R, Kibira SPS. Experiences of persons in COVID-19 institutional quarantine in Uganda: a qualitative study. BMC Public Health. 2021;21(1):482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7947936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33706737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogoina D, Mahmood D, Oyeyemi AS, Okoye OC, Kwaghe V, Habib Z, et al. A national survey of hospital readiness during the COVID-19 pandemic in Nigeria. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(9):e0257567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8454967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34547038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olani AB, Degefa N, Aschalew Z, Kassa M, Feleke T, Gura G, et al. Exploring experiences of quarantined people during the early phase of COVID-19 outbreak in Southern Nations nationalities and peoples’ region of Ethiopia: a qualitative study. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(9):e0275248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9524644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36178945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanni UA, Offiong UM, Anigilaje EA, Airede KI, Imam A. A pre-COVID-19 assessment of aspects of the school health programme in some selected Nigerian primary schools: implications for school re-opening during the COVID-19 pandemic in developing country contexts. BMC Public Health. 2021;21(1):1214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8223233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34167515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ijarotimi IT, Ilesanmi OS, Aderinwale A, Abiodun-Adewusi O, Okon IM. Knowledge of Lassa fever and use of infection prevention and control facilities among health care workers during Lassa fever outbreak in Ondo State, Nigeria. Pan Afr Med J. 2018;30:56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6125309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30197747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obionu IM, Ochu CL, Ukponu W, Okwor T, Dan-Nwafor C, Ilori E, et al. Evaluation of infection prevention and control practices in Lassa fever treatment centers in north-central Nigeria during an ongoing Lassa fever outbreak. J Infect Prev. 2021;22(6):275–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8647645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34880950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adokiya MN, Awoonor-Williams JK. Ebola virus disease surveillance and response preparedness in Northern Ghana. Glob Health Action. 2016. 10.3402/gha.v9.29763.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4856840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27146443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awoonor-Williams JK, Moyer CA, Adokiya MN. Self-reported challenges to border screening of travelers for Ebola by district health workers in Northern Ghana: an observational study. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(1):e0245039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7785234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33400709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oji MO, Haile M, Baller A, Trembley N, Mahmoud N, Gasasira A et al. Implementing infection prevention and control capacity building strategies within the context of Ebola outbreak in a Hard-to-Reach area of Liberia. Pan Afr Med J [Internet]. 2018 Dec 10 [cited 2023 Aug 10];31(107). https://www.panafrican-med-journal.com/content/article/31/107/full</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6462381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31037168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedi D, Gillespie A, Bedson J, Jalloh MF, Jalloh MB, Kamara A, et al. The development of standard operating procedures for social mobilization and community engagement in sierra leone during the West Africa Ebola Outbreak of 2014–2015. J Health Commun. 2017;22(sup1):39–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28854137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellecchia U, Crestani R, Decroo T, Van den Bergh R, Al-Kourdi Y. Social consequences of ebola containment measures in liberia. PLoS ONE. 2015;10(12):e0143036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4674104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26650630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndoungué VF, Ngapagna AN, Kouadio SA, Djinguebey R, Gnigninanjouena O, Eyangoh S, et al. Assessing core capacities for addressing public health emergencies of international concern at designated points of entry in Cameroon during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1):2197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9702939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36443744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebimpe WO, Ibirongbe DO. Exploring the knowledge and preventive practices on isolation precaution and quarantine among health care workers in Ondo State, Nigeria. Ann Glob Health. 2019;85(1):72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6634389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31125195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. Guidelines Library | Infection Control | CDC [Internet]. 2022 [cited 2023 Aug 31]. https://www.cdc.gov/infectioncontrol/guidelines/index.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Infection prevention and control: Guidance to action tools. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. Quarantine and Isolation | Quarantine | CDC [Internet]. 2021 [cited 2023 Aug 31]. https://www.cdc.gov/quarantine/index.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Academies of Sciences, Division E H and, Practice M, on PH B, Policy PH, on HS B et al. Response C on EBP for PHEP and, Downey A,. Implementing Quarantine to Reduce or Stop the Spread of a Contagious Disease. In: Evidence-Based Practice for Public Health Emergency Preparedness and Response [Internet]. National Academies Press (US); 2020 [cited 2023 Aug 31]. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK563999/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iacobucci G. Covid-19: doctors sound alarm over hospital transmissions. BMJ. 2020;369:m2013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32430304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lessells R, Moosa Y, de Oliveira T. Report into a nosocomial outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) at Netcare St. Augustine’s Hospital [Internet]. South Africa: KwaZulu‐Natal Research Innovation and Sequencing Platform (KRISP); 2020 [cited 2023 Sep 1] p. 37. https://www.cebm.net/study/covid-19-hospital-outbreak-of-covid-in-south-africa/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mo Y, Eyre DW, Lumley SF, Walker TM, Shaw RH, O’Donnell D, et al. Transmission of community- and hospital-acquired SARS-CoV-2 in hospital settings in the UK: a cohort study. PLOS Med. 2021;18(10):e1003816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8509983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34637439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baller A, Padoveze MC, Mirindi P, Hazim CE, Lotemo J, Pfaffmann J, et al. Ebola virus disease nosocomial infections in the Democratic Republic of the Congo: a descriptive study of cases during the 2018–2020 outbreak. Int J Infect Dis IJID off Publ Int Soc Infect Dis. 2022;115:126–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8755545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34883237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shears P, O’Dempsey TJD. Ebola virus disease in Africa: epidemiology and nosocomial transmission. J Hosp Infect. 2015;90(1):1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25655197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dan-Nwafor CC, Ipadeola O, Smout E, Ilori E, Adeyemo A, Umeokonkwo C, et al. A cluster of nosocomial Lassa fever cases in a tertiary health facility in Nigeria: description and lessons learned, 2018. Int J Infect Dis. 2019;83:88–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30930184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tacconelli E, Buhl M, Humphreys H, Malek V, Presterl E, Rodriguez-Baño J, et al. Analysis of the challenges in implementing guidelines to prevent the spread of multidrug-resistant gram-negatives in Europe. BMJ Open. 2019;9(5):e027683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6530321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31110101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qureshi M, Chughtai A, Seale H. Supporting the delivery of infection prevention and control training to healthcare workers: insights from the sector. Healthcare. 2022;10(5):936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9141703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35628072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Infection prevention and control GLOBAL [Internet]. [cited 2023 Sep 1]. https://www.who.int/health-topics/infection-prevention-and-control</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonio E, Alobo M, Tufet Bayona M, Marsh K, Norton A. Funding and COVID-19 research priorities - are the research needs for Africa being met? AAS Open Res. 2020;3:56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7927206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33709054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ly BA, Ahmed MAA, Traore FB, Diarra NH, Dembele M, Diarra D, et al. Challenges and difficulties in implementing and adopting isolation and quarantine measures among internally displaced people during the COVID-19 pandemic in Mali (161/250). J Migr Health. 2022;5:100104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8994677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35434677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lohiniva AL, Dub T, Hagberg L, Nohynek H. Learning about COVID-19-related stigma, quarantine and isolation experiences in Finland. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(4):e0247962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8046198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33852581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Shi L, Que J, Lu Q, Liu L, Lu Z, et al. The impact of quarantine on mental health status among general population in China during the COVID-19 pandemic. Mol Psychiatry. 2021;26(9):4813–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7821451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33483692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cava MA, Fay KE, Beanlands HJ, McCay EA, Wignall R. The experience of quarantine for individuals affected by SARS in Toronto. Public Health Nurs. 2005;22(5):398–406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16229732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kołodziejczyk A, Misiak B, Szcześniak D, Maciaszek J, Ciułkowicz M, Łuc D, et al. Coping styles, Mental Health, and the COVID-19 Quarantine: a nationwide survey in Poland. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:625355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7991383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33776817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orgilés M, Morales A, Delvecchio E, Mazzeschi C, Espada JP. Immediate Psychological effects of the COVID-19 Quarantine in Youth from Italy and Spain. Front Psychol. 2020;11:579038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7677301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33240167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>