<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429254</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effects of N95 Masks Versus Surgical/Loop Masks on Arterial Blood Gases and Adverse Symptoms in Operating Room Staff During Prolonged Usage: A Pilot Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69655</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69655</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69655</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69655</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic continues to have a catastrophic impact on the global population. N95 masks are commonly used as filtering facepiece respirators for healthcare workers. At the end of long shifts, they have reported headaches, dizziness, fatigue, exhaustion, and physical and mental discomfort. There is a lack of data on the effects of N95 masks on blood gases in healthcare workers who wear masks for longer durations. We analyzed and compared the effects of continuously wearing N95 versus loop/surgical masks on various symptomology parameters and arterial blood gases for longer durations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This was a non-blinded, pilot, observational study at a single academic institution. Utilizing a survey, we collected information on operating room staff volunteers (demographics, mask use, and symptoms) and measured transcutaneous partial pressure carbon dioxide (tcPCO<sub>2</sub>) and oxygen saturation (SpO<sub>2</sub>) before and after the subject's shift to identify changes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Thirty-nine subjects enrolled in the study (N95 mask = 13, loop/surgical mask = 26). Overall, 69.2% of the subjects continuously wore a mask for five or more hours on their shift. There was a statistical difference with reported fatigue with exclusively wearing an N95 mask versus a loop/surgical mask (p=0.017). None of the other parameters showed a statistical difference between groups. The tcPCO<sub>2</sub> was not statistically different between mask types at the beginning of the shift (p=0.922) or at the end of the shift (p=0.188), although tcPCO<sub>2</sub> levels increased. The SpO<sub>2</sub> was not statistically different between the mask types at the beginning of the shift (p=0.883) or at the end of the shift (p=0.505) with SpO<sub>2</sub> decreasing.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Individuals exclusively wearing an N95 mask reported a statistically greater number of complaints of fatigue after their shift. No statistical differences were observed in arterial blood gas parameters measured for SpO<sub>2</sub> and tcPCO<sub>2</sub> between mask groups. No definitive conclusions can be made due to the small sample size.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Catanzaro et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Catanzaro</LastName><ForeName>Sandra</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Anesthesiology, State University of New York Upstate Medical University, Syracuse, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lavelle</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Orthopedic Surgery, State University of New York Upstate Medical University, Syracuse, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lavelle</LastName><ForeName>W Jacob</ForeName><Initials>WJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Colgate University, Hamilton, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Demers Lavelle</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth A</ForeName><Initials>EA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Anesthesiology, State University of New York Upstate Medical University, Syracuse, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood oxygen saturation (spo2)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">loop/surgical mask</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">n95 mask</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">partial pressure of carbon dioxide (pco2)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">partial pressure of oxygen (po2)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transcutaneous partial pressure carbon dioxide (tcpco2)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11488527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Number of COVID-19 Cases Reported to WHO.  [
Aug;
2024 
]. 2024. https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statement on the Fifteenth Meeting of the IHR (2005) Emergency Committee on the COVID-19 Pandemic.  [
Jan;
2024 
]. 2005. https://www.who.int/news/item/05-05-2023-statement-on-the-fifteenth-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations--pandemic https://www.who.int/news/item/05-05-2023-statement-on-the-fifteenth-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations--pandemic</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Health and Human Services. COVID-19 Public Health Emergency.  [
Jan;
2024 
]. 2023. https://www.hhs.gov/coronavirus/covid-19-public-health-emergency/index.html https://www.hhs.gov/coronavirus/covid-19-public-health-emergency/index.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Airborne transmission of respiratory viruses. Wang CC, Prather KA, Sznitman J, Jimenez JL, Lakdawala SS, Tufekci Z, Marr LC. Science. 2021;373:9149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8721651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34446582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy of face mask in preventing respiratory virus transmission: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Liang M, Gao L, Cheng C, Zhou Q, Uy JP, Heiner K, Sun C. Travel Med Infect Dis. 2020;36:101751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7253999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32473312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effectiveness of masks and respirators against respiratory infections in healthcare workers: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Offeddu V, Yung CF, Low MS, Tam CC. Clin Infect Dis. 2017;65:1934–1942.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29140516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparison of effects of N95 respirators and surgical masks to physiological and psychological health among healthcare workers: a randomized controlled trial. Su CY, Peng CY, Liu HL, Yeh IJ, Lee CW. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:13308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8705067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34948915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carbon dioxide rebreathing in respiratory protective devices: influence of speech and work rate in full-face masks. Smith CL, Whitelaw JL, Davies B. Ergonomics. 2013;56:781–790.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23514282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preliminary report on surgical mask induced deoxygenation during major surgery. Beder A, Buyukkocak H, Sabuncuoglu H, Keskil ZA, Keskil S. Neurocirugia. 2008;19:121–126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18500410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Surgical mask and N95 in healthcare workers of Covid-19 departments: clinical and social aspects. Gelardi M, Fiore V, Giancaspro R, et al. Acta Biomed. 2020;91:2020171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7927551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33525214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carbon dioxide re-breathing with close fitting face respirator masks. Fletcher SJ, Clark M, Stanley PJ. Anaesthesia. 2006;61:910.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16922771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Respirator masks protect health but impact performance: a review. Johnson AT. J Biol Eng. 2016;10:4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4748517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26865858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Respiratory consequences of N95-type Mask usage in pregnant healthcare workers-a controlled clinical study. Tong PS, Kale AS, Ng K, et al. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control. 2015;4:48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4647822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26579222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The effect of wearing an N95 mask on the blood gas values of healthcare providers. Nafisah SB, Susi A, Alsaif E, Alqasmi M, Mzahim B. https://www.ijmrhs.com/medical-research/the-effect-of-wearing-an-n95-mask-on-the-blood-gas-values-of-healthcare-providers-64731.html Inter J Med Res Health Sci. 2021;10:51–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effects of the use of N95 masks on the vital signs of healthy healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: a hospital-based cross-sectional study. Kumar P, Nath K, Prasad A, Tiwari LK, Chowdhry BK, Sinha AK, Chaudhary N. Cureus. 2023;15:40622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10355089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37476108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prolonged use of surgical masks and respirators affects the protection and comfort for healthcare workers. Guan X, Lin J, Han J, et al. Materials (Basel) 2022;15:7918.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9696921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36431403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Surgical masks affect the peripheral oxygen saturation and respiratory rate of Anesthesiologists. Yang S, Fang C, Liu X, Liu Y, Huang S, Wang R, Qi F. Front Med (Lausanne) 2022;9:844710.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9047907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35492371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transcutaneous PCO(2) monitoring in critically ill patients: update and perspectives. Mari A, Nougue H, Mateo J, Vallet B, Vallée F. J Thorac Dis. 2019;11:1558–1567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6642914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31388461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ABC of oxygen: assessing and interpreting arterial blood gases and acid-base balance. Williams AJ. BMJ. 1998;317:1213–1216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1114160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9794863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Physiologic and other effects and compliance with long-term respirator use among medical intensive care unit nurses. Rebmann T, Carrico R, Wang J. Am J Infect Control. 2013;41:1218–1223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7132714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23768438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biohazards of prolonged N95 use: effects on arterial blood gases, peak expiratory flow rate and general well-being of healthcare professionals during COVID-19 pandemic. Athar MH, Zubair UB, Zakir U. J Coll Physicians Surg Pak. 2020;30:134–135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33115589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oxygen saturation and perceived discomfort with face mask types, in the era of COVID-19: a hospital-based cross-sectional study. Nwosu AD, Ossai EN, Onwuasoigwe O, Ahaotu F. Pan Afr Med J. 2021;39:203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8464215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34603584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The tiny effects of respiratory masks on physiological, subjective, and behavioral measures under mental load in a randomized controlled trial. Spang RP, Pieper K. Sci Rep. 2021;11:19601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8486780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34599253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of long duration wearing of N95 masks on cardiorespiratory system and subjective sensations of health-care workers during COVID-19 era. Singla M, Soni RK, Chhina RS, Chhabra ST, Wander GS. J Anaesthesiol Clin Pharmacol. 2022;38:599–604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9912871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36778816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Headaches and the N95 face-mask amongst healthcare providers. Lim EC, Seet RC, Lee KH, Wilder-Smith EP, Chuah BY, Ong BK. Acta Neurol Scand. 2006;113:199–202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16441251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adverse effect of prolonged mask use among healthcare professionals during Covid-19. Rosner E. J Infect Dis Epidemiol. 2020;6:130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prolonged use of N95 mask a boon or bane to healthcare workers during COVID-19 pandemic. Kumar Shubhanshu, Singh A. Indian J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2022;74:2853–2856.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7831687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33520688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stress and health: psychological, behavioral, and biological determinants. Schneiderman N, Ironson G, Siegel SD. Annu Rev Clin Psychol. 2005;1:607–628.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2568977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17716101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stress and health: major findings and policy implications. Thoits PA. J Health Soc Behav. 2010;51:41–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20943582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>