<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39427164</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6963</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC health services research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Health Serv Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 vaccine implementation at a syringe services program: experiences of frontline staff.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1260</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1260</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1260</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12913-024-11691-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">While people with substance use disorders, including people who inject drugs (PWID), experience increased risk for COVID-19 infection and adverse outcomes, COVID-19 vaccination rates among PWID are consistently lower than those observed in the general population. Offering COVID-19 vaccines at syringe services programs (SSPs) has been proposed as a critical strategy to increase vaccine uptake among this population. We explored the experiences of frontline staff at an SSP in Miami, Florida implementing onsite COVID-19 vaccines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Between June and July 2022, we conducted in-depth semi-structured interviews with 17 staff members of an SSP in Miami, Florida. Data collection and codebook thematic analysis of transcribed interviews were guided by the Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research (CFIR).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Facilitators and barriers of COVID-19 vaccine implementation at the SSP aligned with all major CFIR domains. Key facilitators included the SSP's established partnership with the local health department for vaccine distribution, its existing funding sources which could be leveraged for vaccine-related expenses, consensus among staff about the need for new strategies to increase vaccine uptake among PWID, and PWID's trust in the SSP. Major-but largely modifiable-barriers included lack of participant compensation, limited internal collaboration and communication regarding the vaccine initiative beyond implementation leads and innovation deliverers due to competing priorities and segmented roles and responsibilities, and insufficient involvement of the most participant-facing staff (i.e., the SSP's peer navigators and outreach workers).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Implementing onsite COVID-19 vaccines was perceived as feasible and acceptable by frontline staff at the SSP, however contextual factors impeded optimal implementation. Multilevel strategies, such as participant compensation for vaccine completion and internal educational meetings with staff to improve vaccine implementation and reach, are required. As a trusted source of preventative services for PWID, SSPs are an underutilized venue for increasing vaccine uptake among this population, and findings from this study could inform the expansion of low-barrier vaccine services at SSPs nationwide.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Plesons</LastName><ForeName>Marina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Sciences, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, FL, USA. m.plesons@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, FL, USA. m.plesons@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soto Sugar</LastName><ForeName>Sabrina E</ForeName><Initials>SE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Sciences, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chimbaru</LastName><ForeName>Rutendo</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Miami School of Communication, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McDonald</LastName><ForeName>Giuliano</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Miami School of Communication, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Friedman</LastName><ForeName>Lily</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Sciences, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thompson</LastName><ForeName>Ernest</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Suffix>Jr</Suffix><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bazzi</LastName><ForeName>Angela R</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Herbert Wertheim School of Public Health, University of California San Diego, San Diego, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tookes</LastName><ForeName>Hansel E</ForeName><Initials>HE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bartholomew</LastName><ForeName>Tyler S</ForeName><Initials>TS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Sciences, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NU38OT000285</GrantID><Agency>Department of Health &amp; Human Services / NASTAD</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>NU38OT000285</GrantID><Agency>Department of Health &amp; Human Services / NASTAD</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Health Serv Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088677</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6963</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018671" MajorTopicYN="Y">Needle-Exchange Programs</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005431" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Florida</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015819" MajorTopicYN="N">Substance Abuse, Intravenous</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006282" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Personnel</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036301" MajorTopicYN="N">Qualitative Research</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007407" MajorTopicYN="N">Interviews as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">People who inject drugs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Syringe services programs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccines</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: TSB and HET receive research funding from Gilead Sciences.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39427164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11490171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-024-11691-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12913-024-11691-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO. WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard Geneva. World Health Organization; Available from: https://covid19.who.int/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang QQ, Kaelber DC, Xu R, Volkow ND. COVID-19 risk and outcomes in patients with substance use disorders: analyses from electronic health records in the United States. Mol Psychiatry. 2021;26(1):30–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7488216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32929211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strathdee SA, Abramovitz D, Harvey-Vera A, Vera CF, Rangel G, Artamonova I, et al. Prevalence and correlates of SARS-CoV-2 seropositivity among people who inject drugs in the San Diego-Tijuana border region. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(11):e0260286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8608290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34807963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim J, Pavalagantharajah S, Verschoor CP, Lentz E, Loeb M, Levine M, et al. Infectious diseases, comorbidities and outcomes in hospitalized people who inject drugs (PWID) infections in persons who inject drugs. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(4):e0266663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9020696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35443003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cioffi CC, Kosty D, Nachbar S, Capron CG, Mauricio AM, Tavalire HF. COVID-19 vaccine deliberation among people who inject drugs. Drug Alcohol Depend Rep. 2022;3:100046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8942572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35345466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iversen J, Wand H, Kemp R, Bevan J, Briggs M, Patten K, et al. Uptake of COVID-19 vaccination among people who inject drugs. Harm Reduct J. 2022;19(1):59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9162792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35655217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cepeda JA, Feder KA, Astemborski J, Schluth C, Kirk GD, Mehta SH, et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and vaccination status in a community-based cohort of people who inject drugs in Baltimore, Maryland, March-June 2021. Public Health Rep. 2022;137(5):1031–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9357826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35848111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aronson ID, Bennett AS, Ardouin-Guerrier MA, Rivera-Castellar G, Gibson B, Santoscoy S, et al. How Vaccine Ambivalence can lead people who inject drugs to decline COVID-19 vaccination and Ways this can be addressed: qualitative study. JMIR Form Res. 2022;6(3):e35066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8945077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35191841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dietze PM, Hall C, Price O, Stewart AC, Crawford S, Peacock A, et al. COVID-19 vaccine acceptability among people in Australia who inject drugs: implications for vaccine rollout. Drug Alcohol Rev. 2022;41(2):484–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8653113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34752659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price O, Dietze PM, Maher L, Crawford S, Peacock A. COVID-19 vaccine acceptability among people in Australia who inject drugs: update from the 2021 Illicit Drug Reporting System interviews. Drug Alcohol Rev. 2022;41(5):1025–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9111623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35184346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arcadepani FB, De Macedo M, Tardelli VS, Martins SS, Fidalgo TM. COVID-19 vaccination among socially vulnerable people who use drugs. Addiction. 2021;116(9):2590–1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33788354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valasek CJ, Streuli SA, Pines HA, Mittal ML, Strathdee SA, Vera CF, et al. COVID-19 vaccination acceptability and experiences among people who inject drugs in San Diego County. Prev Med Rep. 2022;30:101989.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9484100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36148319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strathdee SA, Abramovitz D, Vera CF, Artamonova I, Patterson TL, Smith DM, et al. Predictors of COVID-19 vaccine uptake among people who inject drugs. Vaccine. 2023;41(12):1916–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9868393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36697311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strathdee SA, Abramovitz D, Harvey-Vera A, Vera CF, Rangel G, Artamonova I et al. Correlates of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccine hesitancy among people who inject drugs in the San Diego-Tijuana Border Region. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;5(1):e726-33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8690110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35024825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stack E, Shin S, LaForge K, Pope J, Leichtling G, Larsen JE, et al. COVID-19 vaccination status and concerns among people who use drugs in Oregon. J Addict Med. 2022;16(6):695-701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9653059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35797436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iversen J, Peacock A, Price O, Byrne J, Dunlop A, Maher L. COVID-19 vaccination among people who inject drugs: leaving no one behind. Drug Alcohol Rev. 2021;40(4):517–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8013693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33650174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montgomery MP, Zhong Y, Roberts E, Asher A, Bixler D, Doshani M, et al. Vaccination barriers and opportunities at syringe services programs in the United States, June-August 2021-A cross-sectional survey. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2022;237:109540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11287426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35753280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heidari O, Meyer D, O’Conor KJ, Cargill V, Patch M, Farley JE. COVID-19 vaccination and Communicable Disease Testing Services’ Integration within a Syringe services Program: a program brief. J Assoc Nurses AIDS Care. 2022;33(3):348–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35025822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Des Jarlais DC, Behrends CN, Corcorran MA, Glick SN, Perlman DC, Kapadia SN, et al. Availability of and obstacles to providing COVID-19 vaccinations at Syringe Services Programs in the United States, 2021. Public Health Rep. 2022;137(6):1066–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9574299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36113105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carry M, Bixler D, Weng MK, Doshani M, Roberts E, Montgomery MP. Supporting syringe services programs in the initiation and scale-up of vaccine administration: findings from in-depth interviews. Harm Reduct J. 2022;19(1):100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9435406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36050735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heidari O, Meyer D, Lowensen K, Patil A, O’Conor KJ, LaRicci J, et al. Colocating Syringe Services, COVID-19 vaccination, and Infectious Disease Testing: Baltimore’s experience. Health Aff (Millwood). 2024;43(6):883–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38830163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corcorran MA, Austin EJ, Behrends CN, Briggs ES, Frost MC, Juarez AM, et al. Syringe Service Program perspectives on barriers, readiness, and programmatic needs to support rollout of the COVID-19 vaccine. J Addict Med. 2023;17(1):e36–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9892351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35916422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stancliff S, Salomon N, Perlman DC, Russell PC. Provision of influenza and pneumococcal vaccines to injection drug users at a syringe exchange. J Subst Abuse Treat. 2000;18(3):263–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10742640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss D, Stern EJ, Zimmerman C, Bregman B, Yeung A, Das D, et al. Epidemiologic investigation and targeted vaccination initiative in response to an outbreak of meningococcal disease among illicit drug users in Brooklyn, New York. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;48(7):894–901.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19231975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Update: syringe exchange programs–United States. 1998. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2001;50(19):384-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11465907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Des Jarlais DC, Fisher DG, Newman JC, Trubatch BN, Yancovitz M, Paone D, et al. Providing hepatitis B vaccination to injection drug users: referral to health clinics vs on-site vaccination at a syringe exchange program. Am J Public Health. 2001;91(11):1791–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1446878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11684603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altice FL, Bruce RD, Walton MR, Buitrago MI. Adherence to hepatitis B virus vaccination at syringe exchange sites. J Urban Health. 2005;82(1):151–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3456633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15746385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topp L, Day CA, Wand H, Deacon RM, van Beek I, Haber PS, et al. A randomised controlled trial of financial incentives to increase hepatitis B vaccination completion among people who inject drugs in Australia. Prev Med. 2013;57(4):297–303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23639625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowman S, Grau LE, Singer M, Scott G, Heimer R. Factors associated with hepatitis B vaccine series completion in a randomized trial for injection drug users reached through syringe exchange programs in three US cities. BMC Public Health. 2014;14:820.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4138371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25107530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tressler S, Bhandari R. Interventions to increase completion of Hepatitis B vaccination in people who inject drugs: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2019;6(12):ofz521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6929254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31890724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alanko Blomé M, Björkman P, Flamholc L, Jacobsson H, Widell A. Vaccination against hepatitis B virus among people who inject drugs - a 20 year experience from a Swedish needle exchange program. Vaccine. 2017;35(1):84–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27894721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Grau LE, Scott G, Seal KH, Marshall PA, Singer M, et al. Economic evaluation of delivering hepatitis B vaccine to injection drug users. Am J Prev Med. 2008;35(1):25–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2483306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18541174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell JV, Garfein RS, Thiede H, Hagan H, Ouellet LJ, Golub ET, et al. Convenience is the key to hepatitis A and B vaccination uptake among young adult injection drug users. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2007;91(Suppl 1):S64–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17276018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Des Jarlais DC, Friedman SR. HIV epidemiology and interventions among injecting drug users. Int J STD AIDS. 1996;7(Suppl 2):57–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8799797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Surveillance Report HIV. 2015. Atlanta: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. NCHHSTP AtlasPlus Atlanta: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 2023 [ https://www.cdc.gov/nchhstp/atlas/index.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartholomew TS, Nakamura N, Metsch LR, Tookes HE. Syringe services program (SSP) operational changes during the COVID-19 global outbreak. Int J Drug Policy. 2020;83:102821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7290194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32591222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Escudero DJ, Bennett B, Suarez S, Darrow WW, Mayer KH, Seage GR 3. Progress and challenges in getting to Zero New HIV infections in Miami, Florida. J Int Assoc Provid AIDS Care. 2019;18:2325958219852122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6573019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31131664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyengar S, Kravietz A, Bartholomew TS, Forrest D, Tookes HE. Baseline differences in characteristics and risk behaviors among people who inject drugs by syringe exchange program modality: an analysis of the Miami IDEA syringe exchange. Harm Reduct J. 2019;16(1):7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6343273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30674334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartholomew TS, Andraka-Cristou B, Totaram RK, Harris S, Doblecki-Lewis S, Ostrer L, et al. We want everything in a one-stop shop: acceptability and feasibility of PrEP and buprenorphine implementation with mobile syringe services for black people who inject drugs. Harm Reduct J. 2022;19(1):133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9719627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36463183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>University of Miami Miller School of Medicine. Miami-Dade County Sterile Needle and Syringe Exchange Program Annual Report. Miami: University of Miami Miller School of Medicine; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damschroder LJ, Reardon CM, Widerquist MAO, Lowery J. The updated Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research based on user feedback. Implement Sci. 2022;17(1):75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9617234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36309746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>APA handbook of research methods in psychology, Vol 2: Research designs: Quantitative, qualitative, neuropsychological, and biological. Cooper H, Camic PM, Long DL, Panter AT, Rindskopf D, Sher KJ, editors. Washington, DC, US: American Psychological Association. 2012. x, 701-x, p.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creswell JW, Báez JC. 30 Essential Skills for the Qualitative Researcher. 2nd Edition ed. London: SAGE Publications, Inc.; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Storer D, Lafferty L, Graham S, Murphy D, Rance J, Brener L et al. Perceptions of COVID-19 Vaccines: Lessons from Selected Populations Who Experience Discrimination in the Australian Healthcare System. Health &amp; Social Care in the Community. 2023;2023:5901128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardin B, Graboyes M, Kosty D, Cioffi C. Vaccine decision making among people who inject drugs: improving on the WHO’s 3 C model of vaccine hesitancy. Prev Med Rep. 2023;35:102341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10428103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37593355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey-Vera A, Munoz S, Artamonova I, Abramovitz D, Mittal ML, Rosales C, et al. COVID-19 vaccine uptake among people who inject drugs in Tijuana Mexico. Front Public Health. 2022;10:931306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9485825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36148330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>