<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429747</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2352-3409</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>57</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Data in brief</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Data Brief</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Analysis of data of COVID lockdown period: Comorbidity and fatality rates in a few districts of Assam, India.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>110974</StartPage><MedlinePgn>110974</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">110974</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.dib.2024.110974</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In many regions of the world, significant data collection, analysis, and availability on comorbidity and fatality incidents caused by COVID-19 during the lockdown period (2020-2022) is rare. This is especially true for hospitals and COVID treatment facilities in India. This lack of understanding impedes the development of appropriate treatment options, potentially resulting in inferior planning, patient recovery results, and a load on healthcare resources. This project intends to bridge the gap and enhance patient care in Assam, India, in light of the COVID pandemic. Furthermore, this study aims to determine baseline patient characteristics associated with an elevated risk of death among hospitalized COVID-19 patients in Assam. We employed machine learning (ML) and deep learning (DL) approaches to discover hidden patterns in patient data that could predict which individuals are more sensitive to severe consequences. This knowledge has the potential to transform patient care by allowing doctors to personalize treatment plans and prioritize resources for individuals who are most at risk. A retrospective observational analysis was performed using data from 5329 individuals hospitalized with SARS-CoV-2 illness between April and December 2021. ML and DL algorithms could be used to examine patient characteristics and identify risk factors for death (in this case, 554). We expect this to help us better understand the risk factors for in-hospital death among COVID19 patients in Assam. The findings could be useful in building risk assessment tools to guide patient care.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choudhury</LastName><ForeName>Atlanta</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering, Gauhati University, Guwahati, 781014, Assam, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarma</LastName><ForeName>Kandarpa Kumar</ForeName><Initials>KK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering, Gauhati University, Guwahati, 781014, Assam, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dutta</LastName><ForeName>Lachit</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering, Gauhati University, Guwahati, 781014, Assam, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Misra</LastName><ForeName>Debashis Dev</ForeName><Initials>DD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Faculty of Engineering and Technology, Assam Down Town University, Guwahati 781026, Assam, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choudhury</LastName><ForeName>Aakangkhita</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jorhat Medical College and Hospital, Jorhat 785001, Assam, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarma</LastName><ForeName>Rijusmita</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, LCB College, Guwahati 781011, Assam, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Data Brief</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101654995</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2352-3409</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Comorbidity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fatality rate</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">P- value</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11490760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dib.2024.110974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2352-3409(24)00936-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alsaleh M.M., Allery F., Choi J.W., Hama T., McQuillin A., Wu H., &amp;Thygesen J.H. Prediction of disease comorbidity using explainable artificial intelligence and machine learning techniques: a systematic review. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2023;175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37156169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterjee S., Nalla L.V., Sharma M., Sharma N., Singh A.A., Malim F.M., &amp;Khairnar A. Association of COVID-19 with comorbidities: an update. ACS Pharmacol. Transl. Sci. 2023;6(3):334–354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10000013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36923110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel R., Kooner J.S., Zhang W. Comorbidities associated with the severity of COVID-19, and differences across ethnic groups: a UK Biobank cohort study. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):1566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10436456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37592225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei Q., Mease P.J., Chiorean M., Iles-Shih L., Matos W.F., Baumgartner A., &amp;Hadlock J. Risk factors for severe COVID-19 outcomes: a study of immune-mediated inflammatory diseases, immunomodulatory medications, and comorbidities in a large US healthcare system. Medrxiv. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11069366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38670740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glancy M., Yeung A., McAuley A., Palmateer N., Bishop J., Taylor B., Hutchinson S. Factors associated with SARS-CoV-2 testing, diagnosis and COVID-19 disease among individuals prescribed opioid-agonist treatment: a nationwide retrospective cohort study. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38936544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan Z., Mlawa G., Islam S., Elshowaya S., &amp;Saleem M. A retrospective study on the outcome of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients admitted to a district general hospital and predictors of high mortality. Cureus. 2024;16(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10908435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38435221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanna N., Bharti S., Guralarasan G., Kumar T., Sinha R., &amp;Bhadani P.P. Evaluation of comorbidities in the SARS-CoV-2-related mortalities: a retrospective observation from a dedicated COVID-19 care hospital. J. Fam. Med. Prim. Care. 2024;13(2):585–588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11006050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38605758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright G., Senthil K., Zadeh-Kochek A., Heung-san Au., Zhang J., Huang J., J, Koduri G. Health-related quality of life after 12 months post discharge in patients hospitalised with COVID-19 related severe acute respiratory infection (SARI): a prospective analysis of SF-36 data and correlation with retrospective admission data on age, disease severity, and frailty. BMJ Open. 2024;14(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10961539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38508629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houston K.D., Hartnett J., Rose S.J. Investigating the association between the COVID-19 vaccination and incident gastrointestinal symptomology: a comprehensive dataset. Data Br. 2023;48</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10232932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37287691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jehangir Q., Lee Y., Latack K., Poisson L., Wang D.D., Song S., &amp;Sule A.A. Data of atrial arrhythmias in hospitalized COVID-19 and influenza patients. Data Br. 2022;42</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9008092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35449710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan W.J., Liang W.H., Zhao Y., Liang H.R., Chen Z.S., Li Y.M., He J.X. Comorbidity and its impact on 1590 patients with COVID-19 in China: a nationwide analysis. Eur. Respir. J. 2020;55(5):2000547.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7098485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djaharuddin I., Munawwarah S., Nurulita A., Ilyas M., Tabri N.A., Lihawa N. Comorbidities and mortality in COVID-19 patients. Gaceta Sanit. 2021;35:S530–S532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8677356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34929892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>