<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429835</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of education and health promotion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Educ Health Promot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Navigating the death attitudes and anxiety during COVID-19: Role of dispositional mindfulness and tranquil ego.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>304</StartPage><MedlinePgn>304</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">304</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jehp.jehp_1507_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Anecdotally, the concept of death consistently evokes profound unease. This study explores the intricate relationship between individuals' attitudes toward death and the associated anxiety, introducing a two-step model that posits dispositional mindfulness and tranquil ego as mediators.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We used a correlational design in this study and assessed 209 Indian adults (111 males and 98 females) who recovered from corona symptoms on self-report measures of attitudes toward death, death anxiety, dispositional mindfulness, and tranquil ego. Bivariate correlational analyses and path analysis were used to analyze the data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Findings revealed that attitudes toward death involving fear, avoidance, approach, and escape acceptance of death correlated positively with death anxiety. Dispositional mindfulness and tranquil ego correlated negatively with death anxiety. Path analyses with percentile bootstrapping supported our hypothesis and showed that dispositional mindfulness and tranquil ego sequentially mediated the relationship.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These findings indicate that various aspects of attitudes toward death differentially predict death anxiety. Moreover, the relationship between death attitudes and death anxiety is potentially mediated by dispositional mindfulness and a tranquil ego. The findings were discussed in light of existing literature.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Education and Health Promotion.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mandal</LastName><ForeName>Satchit Prasun</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Rajiv Gandhi University, Rono Hills, Itanagar, Arunachal Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pandey</LastName><ForeName>Vijyendra</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Central University of Karnataka, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bonal</LastName><ForeName>Raghavendra B</ForeName><Initials>RB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Central University of Karnataka, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Abhishek</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Sardar Patel University of Police, Security and Criminal Justice, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Astha</LastName><ForeName>Arora</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Central University of Karnataka, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rajesh</LastName><ForeName>Viju</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Behavioural Forensics, National Forensic Sciences University, Gandhinagar, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saha</LastName><ForeName>Proshanto Kr</ForeName><Initials>PK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Rajiv Gandhi University, Rono Hills, Itanagar, Arunachal Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Educ Health Promot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101593794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Death anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">death attitudes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dispositional mindfulness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tranquil ego</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11488761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_1507_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JEHP-13-304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Becker E. New York: The Free Press; 1973. The Denial of Death.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menzies RE, Menzies RG. Death anxiety in the time of COVID-19: Theoretical explanations and clinical implications. Cogn Behav Ther. 2020;13:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7308596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34191938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherman DW, Norman R, McSherry CB. A comparison of death anxiety and quality of life of patients with advanced cancer or AIDS and their family caregivers. J Assoc Nurses AIDS Care. 2010;21:99–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20006525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenberg J, Pyszczynski T, Solomon S, Simon L, Breus M. Role of consciousness and accessibility of death-related thoughts in mortality salience effects. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1994;67:627–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7965609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Khalek AM. Death anxiety in clinical and nonclinical groups. Death Stud. 2005;29:251–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15818874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleet RP, Beitman BD. Cardiovascular death from panic disorder and panic-like anxiety: A critical review of the literature. J Psychosom Res. 1998;44:71–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9483465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong PT, Reker GT, Gesser G. Death attitude profile – revised: A multidimensional measure of attitudes toward death (DAP-R) In: Neimeyer RA, editor. Death Anxiety Handbook: Research, Instrumentation, and Application. Washington DC: Taylor and Francis; 1994. pp. 121–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell NJ, Stuart S, Longley SL, Langbehn DR, Happel RL. Hypochondriasis and fear of death. J Nerv Ment. 2002;190:503–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12193834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoelter JW, Hoelter JA. On the interrelationships among exposure to death and dying, fear of death, and anxiety. Omega-J Death Dying. 1981;11:241–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Starcevic V. Pathological fear of death, panic attacks, and hypochondriasis. Am J Psychoanal. 1989;49:347–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2699164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gesser G, Wong PT, Reker GT. Death attitudes across the life-span: The development and validation of the Death Attitude Profile (DAP) Omega-J Death Dying. 1988;18:113–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cicirelli VG. Sibling death and death fear in relation to depressive symptomatology in older adults. J Gerontol -B Psychol Sci Soc Sci. 2009;64:24–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2654987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19181691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triplett G, Cohen D, Reimer W, Rinaldi S, Hill C, Roshdieh S, et al. Death discomfort differential. Omega-J Death Dying. 1995;31:295–304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aday RH. Belief in afterlife and death anxiety: Correlates and comparisons. Omega-J Death Dying. 1985;15:67–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beck AT, Kovacs M, Weissman A. Hopelessness and suicidal behavior: An overview. JAMA. 1975;234:1146–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1242427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenberg J. Terror management theory: From genesis to revelations. In: Shaver PR, Mikulincer M, editors. Meaning, Mortality, and Choice: The Social Psychology of Existential Concerns. Washington DC: American Psychological Association; 2012. pp. 17–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strachan E, Schimel J, Arndt J, Williams T, Solomon S, Pyszczynski T, et al. Terror mismanagement: Evidence that mortality salience exacerbates phobic and compulsive behaviors. Pers Soc Psychol Bull. 2007;33:1137–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17545415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker E. New York: Free Press; 1975. Escape from Evil.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao Q, Yue C, He W, Yu JY. The mindful self: A mindfulness-enlightened self-view. Front Psychol. 2017;8:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5645519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29081754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kabat-Zinn J. New York: Delta; 1990. Full catastrophe living: The program of the stress reduction clinic.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siegel DJ, Siegel MW, Parker SC. Internal education and the roots of resilience: Relationships and reflection as the new R’s of education. In: Schonert-Reichl KA, Roeser RW, editors. Handbook of Mindfulness in Education: Integrating Theory and Research into Practice. New York: Springer; 2016. pp. 47–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomlinson ER, Yousaf O, Vittersø AD, Jones L. Dispositional mindfulness and psychological health: A systematic review. Mindfulness. 2018;9:23–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5770488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29387263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bränström R, Duncan LG, Moskowitz JT. The association between dispositional mindfulness, psychological well‐being, and perceived health in a Swedish population‐based sample. Br J Health Psychol. 2011;16:300–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3762484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21489058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cash M, Whittingham K. What facets of mindfulness contribute to psychological well-being and depressive, anxious, and stress-related symptomatology? Mindfulness. 2010;1:177–82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McIntosh WD. East meets west: Parallels between Zen Buddhism and social psychology. Int J Psychol Relig. 1997;7:37–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heeren A, Philippot P. Changes in ruminative thinking mediate the clinical benefits of mindfulness: Preliminary findings. Mindfulness. 2011;2:8–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan WS. Psychological attachment, no-self and Chan Buddhist mind therapy. Contemp Buddhism. 2008;9:253–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wayment HA, Wiist B, Sullivan BM, Warren MA. Doing and being: Mindfulness, health, and quiet ego characteristics among Buddhist practitioners. J Happiness Stud. 2011;12:575–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wayment HA, Bauer JJ, Sylaska K. The quiet ego scale: Measuring the compassionate self-identity. J Happiness Stud. 2015;16:999–1033.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niemiec CP, Brown KW, Kashdan TB, Cozzolino PJ, Breen WE, Levesque-Bristol C, et al. Being present in the face of existential threat: The role of trait mindfulness in reducing defensive responses to mortality salience. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2010;99:344–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20658848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kesebir P. A quiet ego quiets death anxiety: Humility as an existential anxiety buffer. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2014;106:610–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24660992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Marne KM, Harris LM. Death anxiety, perfectionism and disordered eating. Behav Change. 2016;33:193–211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown KW, Ryan RM. The benefits of being present: Mindfulness and its role in psychological well-being. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2003;84:822–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12703651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Templer DI. The construction and validation of a death anxiety scale. J Gen Psychol. 1970;82:165–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4394812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavakoli MA, Mohammad A, Ahmadzadeh B. Investigation of validity and reliability of Templer death anxiety Scale. Thought Behav Clin Psychol. 2011;21:80–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoet G. PsyToolkit: A software package for programming psychological experiments using Linux. Behav Res Methods. 2010;42:1096–104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21139177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoet G. PsyToolkit: A novel web-based method for running online questionnaires and reaction-time experiments. Teach Psychol. 2017;44:24–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jöreskog KG, Sörbom D. Illinois: Scientific Software International; 1993. LISREL 8: Structural equation modeling with the SIMPLIS command language.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu LT, Bentler PM. Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives. Struct Equ Modeling. 1999;6:1–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baron RM, Kenny DA. The moderator–mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: Conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1986;51:1173–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3806354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray JJ, Najman J. Death anxiety and death acceptance: A preliminary approach. Omega-J Death Dying. 1975;5:311–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feifel H. Religious conviction and fear of death among the healthy and the terminally ill. J Sci Study Relig. 1974;13:353–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feifel H, Nagy VT. Another look at fear of death. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1981;49:278–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7217494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hooper T, Spilka B. Some meanings and correlates of future time and death among college students. Omega-J Death Dying. 1970;1:49–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett O. The manufacture of hope: Religion, eschatology and the culture of optimism. Int J Cult Policy. 2011;17:115–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehto RH, Stein KF. Death anxiety: An analysis of an evolving concept. Res theory Nurs Pract. 2009;23:23–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19418886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rank O. New York: Dover Publications; 1958. Beyond Psychology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bassett JF. Psychological defenses against death anxiety: Integrating terror management theory and Firestone’s separation theory. Death Stud. 2007;31:727–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17853526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin JB. New York: Plenum Press; 1996. Psychotherapy and Buddhism: Toward an integration.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalff M. The negation of ego in Tibetan Buddhism and Jungian psychology. J Transpers Psychol. 1983;15:103–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wayment HA, Bauer JJ. The quiet ego: Concept, measurement, and well-being. In: Robinson MD, Eid M, editors. The Happy Mind: Cognitive Contributions to Well-Being. New York: Springer; 2017. pp. 77–94.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>