<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39425976</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2191-0278</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of adolescent medicine and health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Adolesc Med Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Psychiatric hospitalizations among adolescents during the pandemic in Italy: a retrospective study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1515/ijamh-2024-0088</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The COVID-19 pandemic has negatively impacted child and adolescent mental health. The study outcome was the evaluation of the pandemic impact on adolescents' hospitalizations in an acute psychiatric ward.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">With an observational and retrospective design, we collected selected variables among adolescents hospitalized in an acute psychiatric ward from 01/07/2017 to 30/06/2022. Data were statistically processed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Our sample consisted of 118 minors with an average age of 15.7 ± 1.2 SD, mostly represented by females (61 %) and Italians (60.2 %), who made 204 hospitalizations in the study period. The admissions by years drastically decreased in 2020 concomitantly with the lockdown and increased in the first half of 2022. The admission rate was higher in winter and spring, except in 2020 when all admissions decreased (p=0.000). Females more frequently were hospitalized for suicidal behavior and acute anxiety (p=0.000) and were discharged with acute stress reactions, eating disorders, and mood disorder diagnoses (p=0.000). Differently, males more frequently were hospitalized for aggressive behavior (p=0.000) and discharged with ADHD diagnosis (p=0.000). At multiple linear regression, the duration of hospitalization (dependent variable) was negatively associated with "the pandemic period" (p=0.017) and "absent aggressive behavior" (p=0.003), and positively with "autism" diagnosis (p=0.000).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">We highlighted the more stressful impact of COVID-19 pandemic on female adolescents, who required more frequently psychiatric hospitalizations due to suicidal behavior, anxiety and mood disorders.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Walter de Gruyter GmbH, Berlin/Boston.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Di Lorenzo</LastName><ForeName>Rosaria</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9497-6837</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mental Health Department and Drug Abuse, AUSL-Modena, Modena, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cutino</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mental Health Department and Drug Abuse, ASP-Trapani, Trapani, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morgante</LastName><ForeName>Martina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mental Health Department and Drug Abuse, AUSL-Modena, Modena, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Panini</LastName><ForeName>Giulia</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mental Health Department and Drug Abuse, AUSL-Modena, Modena, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rovesti</LastName><ForeName>Sergio</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical, Metabolic and Neural Sciences, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Filippini</LastName><ForeName>Tommaso</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2100-0344</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical, Metabolic and Neural Sciences, Environmental, Genetic and Nutritional Epidemiology Research Center (CREAGEN), Section of Public Health, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, University of California Berkeley, Berkeley, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferri</LastName><ForeName>Paola</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7761-7226</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical, Metabolic and Neural Sciences, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Adolesc Med Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8506960</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0334-0139</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adolescents’ psychiatric hospitalization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">suicidal behavior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">the pre- and post-COVID-19 periods</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/ijamh-2024-0088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ijamh-2024-0088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . Mental health of adolescents ; 2021. Available from: https://www.who.int/newsroom/fact-sheets/detail/adolescent-mental-health .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mokdad, AH, Forouzanfar, MH, Daoud, F, Mokdad, AA, El Bcheraoui, C, Moradi-Lakeh, M, et al.. Global burden of diseases, injuries, and risk factors for young people’s health during 1990–2013: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2013. Lancet 2016;387:2383–401. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(16)00648-6 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)00648-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patton, GC, Sawyer, SM, Santelli, JS, Ross, DA, Afifi, R, Allen, NB, et al.. Our future: a Lancet commission on adolescent health and wellbeing. Lancet 2016;387:2423–278. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(16)00579-1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)00579-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mapelli, E, Black, T, Doan, Q. Trends in pediatric emergency department utilization for mental health-related visits. J Pediatr 2015;167:905–10. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpeds.2015.07.004 . Erratum in: J Pediatr. 2015;167(5):1176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2015.07.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Lorenzo, R, Cimino, N, Di Pietro, E, Pollutri, G, Neviani, V, Ferri, P. A 5-year retrospective study of demographic, anamnestic, and clinical factors related to psychiatric hospitalizations of adolescent patients. Neuropsychiatric Dis Treat 2016;12:191–201. https://doi.org/10.2147/NDT.S93874 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/NDT.S93874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guessoum, SB, Lachal, J, Radjack, R, Carretier, E, Minassian, S, Benoit, L, et al.. Adolescent psychiatric disorders during the COVID-19 pandemic and lockdown. Psychiatr Res 2020;291:113264. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113264 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fountoulakis, KN, Karakatsoulis, G, Abraham, S, Adorjan, K, Ahmed, HU, Alarcón, RD, et al.. Results of the COVID-19 mental health international for the general population (COMET-G) study. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 2022;54:21–40. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.euroneuro.2021.10.004 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2021.10.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Lorenzo, R, Pinelli, M, Bertani, D, Cutino, A, Dragone, D, Elia, C, et al.. The impact of COVID-19 pandemic on psychiatric emergencies in two different settings: emergency room and community mental health service. Front Psychiatr 2022;13:894939. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2022.894939 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.894939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sprang, G, Silman, M. Posttraumatic stress disorder in parents and youth after health-related disasters. Disaster Med Public Health Prep 2013;7:105–10. https://doi.org/10.1017/dmp.2013.22 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/dmp.2013.22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samji, H, Wu, J, Ladak, A, Vossen, C, Stewart, E, Dove, N, et al.. Review: mental health impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on children and youth – a systematic review. Child Adolesc Ment Health 2022;27:173–89. https://doi.org/10.1111/camh.12501 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/camh.12501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, SJ, Zhang, LG, Wang, LL, Guo, ZC, Wang, JQ, Chen, JC, et al.. Prevalence and socio-demographic correlates of psychological health problems in Chinese adolescents during the outbreak of COVID-19. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatr 2020;29:749–58. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-020-01541-4 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-020-01541-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanai, R, Bahrami, B, Duchaine, B, Janik, A, Banissy, MJ, Rees, G. Brain structure links loneliness to social perception. Curr Biol 2012;22:1975–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2012.08.045 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2012.08.045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamblin, M, Murawski, C, Whittle, S, Fornito, A. Social connectedness, mental health and the adolescent brain. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 2017;80:57–68. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.05.010 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.05.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill, J, Inder, T, Neil, J, Dierker, D, Harwell, J, Van Essen, D. Similar patterns of cortical expansion during human development and evolution. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2010;107:13135–40. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1001229107 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1001229107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whittle, S, Vijayakumar, N, Dennison, M, Schwartz, O, Simmons, JG, Sheeber, L, et al.. Observed measures of negative parenting predict brain development during adolescence. PLoS One 2016;11:e0147774. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0147774 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeon, KC, Goodson, P. US adolescents’ friendship networks and health risk behaviors: a systematic review of studies using social network analysis and Add Health data. PeerJ 2015;3:e1052. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.1052 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.1052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paluck, EL, Shepherd, H, Aronow, PM. Changing climates of conflict: a social network experiment in 56 schools. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2016;113:566–71. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1514483113 . Erratum in: Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2018; Erratum in: Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2019;116(3):1066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1514483113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mensi, MM, Capone, L, Rogantini, C, Orlandi, M, Ballante, E, Borgatti, R. COVID-19-related psychiatric impact on Italian adolescent population: a cross-sectional cohort study. J Community Psychol 2021;49:1457–69.  https://doi.org/10.1002/jcop.22563 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcop.22563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Youngminds . Coronavirus: impact on young people with mental health needs; 2020. Available from: https://www.youngminds.org.uk/media/xq2dnc0d/youngminds-coronavirus-report-march2020.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grigoletto, V, Cognigni, M, Occhipinti, AA, Abbracciavento, G, Carrozzi, M, Barbi, E, et al.. Rebound of severe alcoholic intoxications in adolescents and young adults after COVID-19 lockdown. J Adolesc Health 2020;67:727–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.08.017 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.08.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parsons, H, Murphy, B, Malone, D, Holme, I. Review of Ireland’s first year of the COVID-19 pandemic impact on people affected by eating disorders: ‘behind every screen there was a family supporting a person with an eating disorder’. J Clin Med 2021;10:3385. https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm10153385 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm10153385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill, RM, Rufino, K, Kurian, S, Saxena, J, Saxena, K, Williams, L. Suicide ideation and attempts in a pediatric emergency department before and during COVID-19. Pediatrics 2021;147:e2020029280. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2020-029280 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2020-029280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson, EC, Thomas, SA, Burke, TA, Nesi, J, MacPherson, HA, Bettis, AH, et al.. Suicidal thoughts and behaviors in psychiatrically hospitalized adolescents pre- and post-COVID-19: a historical chart review and examination of contextual correlates. J Affect Disord Rep 2021;4:100100. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jadr.2021.100100 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadr.2021.100100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yard, E, Radhakrishnan, L, Ballesteros, MF, Sheppard, M, Gates, A, Stein, Z, et al.. Emergency department visits for suspected suicide attempts among persons aged 12–25 years before and during the COVID-19 pandemic – United States, January 2019–May 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2021;70:888–94. https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm7024e1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7024e1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davico, C, Marcotulli, D, Lux, C, Calderoni, D, Cammisa, L, Bondone, C, et al.. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on child and adolescent psychiatric emergencies. J Clin Psychiatry 2021;82:20m13467. https://doi.org/10.4088/JCP.20m13467 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.20m13467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cloutier, RL, Marshaall, R. A dangerous pandemic pair: Covid19 and adolescent mental health emergencies. Am J Emerg Med 2021;46:776–7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajem.2020.09.008 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2020.09.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann, JA, Duffy, SJ. Supporting youth mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic. Acad Emerg Med 2021;28:1485–7. https://doi.org/10.1111/acem.14398 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/acem.14398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>So, P, Wierdsma, AI, Kasius, MC, Cornelis, J, Lommerse, M, Vermeiren, RRJM, et al.. Predictors of voluntary and compulsory admissions after psychiatric emergency consultation in youth. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatr 2021;30:747–56. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-020-01558-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-020-01558-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corrigall, R, Bhugra, D. The role of ethnicity and diagnosis in rates of adolescent psychiatric admission and compulsory detention: a longitudinal case-note study. J R Soc Med 2013;106:190–5. https://doi.org/10.1177/0141076813480995 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0141076813480995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grudnikoff, E, Soto, EC, Frederickson, A, Birnbaum, ML, Saito, E, Dicker, R, et al.. Suicidality and hospitalization as cause and outcome of pediatric psychiatric emergency room visits. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatr 2015;24:797–814. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-014-0624-x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-014-0624-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masters, KJ, Bellonci, C, Bernet, W, Arnold, V, Beitchman, J, Benson, RS, et al.. Practice parameter for the prevention and management of aggressive behavior in child and adolescent psychiatric institutions, with special reference to seclusion and restraint. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry 2002;41:4S–25S. https://doi.org/10.1097/00004583-200202001-00002 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00004583-200202001-00002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royal College of Psychiatrists . Acute in-patient psychiatric care for young people with severe mental illness. Recommendations for commissioners, child and adolescent psychiatrists and general psychiatrists. Council Report CR106 ; 2002. Available at: https://www.sciesocialcareonline.org.uk/acute-in-patient-psychiatric-care-for-young-people-with-severe-mentalillness-recommendations-for-commissioners-child-and-adolescent-psychiatrists-and-generalpsychiatrists/r/a11G00000017tCRIAY .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evensen, M, Hart, RK, Godøy, AA, Hauge, LJ, Lund, IO, Knudsen, AKS, et al.. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental healthcare consultations among children and adolescents in Norway: a nationwide registry study. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatr 2023;32:1025–35. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-022-02046-y .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-022-02046-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slaunwhite, AK, Ronis, ST, Peters, PA, Miller, D. Seasonal variations in psychiatric admissions to hospital. Can Psychol/Psychol Canad 2019;60:155–64. https://doi.org/10.1037/cap0000156 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/cap0000156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gracia, R, Pamias, M, Mortier, P, Alonso, J, Pérez, V, Palao, D. Is the COVID-19 pandemic a risk factor for suicide attempts in adolescent girls? J Affect Disord 2021;292:139–41. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2021.05.044 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.05.044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miranda-Mendizabal, A, Castellví, P, Parés-Badell, O, Alayo, I, Almenara, J, Alonso, I, et al.. Gender differences in suicidal behavior in adolescents and young adults: systematic review and meta-analysis of longitudinal studies. Int J Publ Health 2019;64:265–83. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00038-018-1196-1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00038-018-1196-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krass, P, Dalton, E, Doupnik, SK, Esposito, J. US pediatric emergency department visits for mental health conditions during the COVID-19 pandemic. JAMA Netw Open 2021;4:e218533. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.8533 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.8533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Simson, K, Brekke, I, Hardoy, I. The impact of mental health problems in adolescence on educational attainment. Scand J Educ Res 2022;66:306–20. https://doi.org/10.1080/00313831.2020.1869077 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00313831.2020.1869077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bera, L, Souchon, M, Ladsous, A, Colin, V, Lopez-Castroman, J. Emotional and behavioral impact of the COVID-19 epidemic in adolescents. Curr Psychiatr Rep 2022;24:37–46. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11920-022-01313-8 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11920-022-01313-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou, TY, Mao, XF, Dong, W, Cai, WP, Deng, GH. Prevalence of and factors associated with mental health problems and suicidality among senior high school students in rural China during the COVID-19 outbreak. Asian J Psychiatr 2020;54:102305. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajp.2020.102305 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajp.2020.102305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira, JMD, Butini, L, Pauletto, P, Lehmkuhl, KM, Stefani, CM, Bolan, M, et al.. Mental health effects prevalence in children and adolescents during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review. Worldviews Evidence-Based Nurs 2022;19:130–7. https://doi.org/10.1111/wvn.12566 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/wvn.12566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Luca, L, Giletta, M, Nocentini, A, Menesini, E. Non-suicidal self-injury in adolescence: the role of pre-existing vulnerabilities and COVID-19-related stress. J Youth Adolesc 2022;51:2383–95. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10964-022-01669-3 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10964-022-01669-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Souza, DC, Di Forti, M, Ganesh, S, George, TP, Hall, W, Hjorthøj, C, et al.. Consensus paper of the WFSBP task force on cannabis, cannabinoids and psychosis. World J Biol Psychiatr 2022;23:719–42. https://doi.org/10.1080/15622975.2022.2038797 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15622975.2022.2038797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moffitt, TE, Houts, R, Asherson, P, Belsky, DW, Corcoran, DL, Hammerle, M, et al.. Is adult ADHD a childhood-onset neurodevelopmental disorder? Evidence from a four-decade longitudinal cohort study. Am J Psychiatr 2015;172:967–77. https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.ajp.2015.14101266 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2015.14101266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smile, SC. Supporting children with autism spectrum disorder in the face of the COVID-19 pandemic. CMAJ (Can Med Assoc J) 2020;192:E587. https://doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.75399 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1503/cmaj.75399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cortese, S, Asherson, P, Sonuga-Barke, E, Banaschewski, T, Brandeis, D, Buitelaar, J, et al.. ADHD management during the COVID-19 pandemic: guidance from the European ADHD Guidelines Group. Lancet Child Adolesc Health 2020;4:412–14. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30110-3 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30110-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Lorenzo, R, Vecchi, L, Artoni, C, Mongelli, F, Ferri, P. Demographic and clinical characteristics of patients involuntarily hospitalized in an Italian psychiatric ward: a 1-year retrospective analysis. Acta Biomed 2018;89:17–28. https://doi.org/10.23750/abm.v89i6-S.7392 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.23750/abm.v89i6-S.7392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>