<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39423875</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-2742</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Journal of infection</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Infect</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessment of Neutralizing Antibody Response as a Correlate of Protection against Symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 Infections after Administration of two doses of the CoronaVac inactivated COVID-19 Vaccine: A Phase III Randomized Controlled Trial.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>106315</StartPage><MedlinePgn>106315</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jinf.2024.106315</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0163-4453(24)00249-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The emergence of variants of concerns of SARS-CoV-2 highlights the need for comprehensively elucidating the correlates of protection for different COVID-19 vaccine types. Inactivated COVID-19 vaccines are currently amongst the most widely administered vaccines globally. However, investigations into the correlates of protection for inactivated COVID-19 vaccines are relatively rare.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Data from a phase III double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial (NCT0445659) that evaluated the efficacy and safety of the CoronaVac vaccine in healthcare professionals were utilized in this secondary analysis. Additionally, the correlation between neutralizing antibody levels measured by micro-cytopathic effect (CPE) neutralization assay and the occurrence of laboratory-confirmed infections was assessed using neutralizing antibodies measured in blood samples collected on day 28 after receiving two doses of the vaccine. Finally, the protective threshold required to provide 50% protection against symptomatic illness and virus infections was estimated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The risk of infection was negatively correlated with the levels of post-vaccination neutralizing antibodies measured on day 28 after the second dose. A neutralization titer of 30 (95% CI: 2-56) was predicted to provide 50% efficacy against symptomatic infection, whilst a titer of 42 (95% CI: 24-62) was predicted to provide 50% efficacy against total infection. Lastly, a neutralization titer of 247 (95% CI: 139-506) or higher was required to achieve 80% or higher protection against symptomatic infections.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The results highlight the value of neutralizing antibody response as a correlate of protection, which can be used to inform future vaccine development and implementation. Further studies of immune correlates of protection for other vaccines are warranted.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Xinhua</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Institute of Infectious Disease and Biosecurity, School of Public Health, Fudan University, Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety, Ministry of Education, Shanghai, China; MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, School of Public Health, Imperial College, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meng</LastName><ForeName>Xing</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Qianhui</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Institute of Infectious Disease and Biosecurity, School of Public Health, Fudan University, Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety, Ministry of Education, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lim</LastName><ForeName>Wey Wen</ForeName><Initials>WW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Collaborating Centre for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Control, School of Public Health, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xin</LastName><ForeName>Qianqian</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cowling</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin J</ForeName><Initials>BJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Collaborating Centre for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Control, School of Public Health, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meng</LastName><ForeName>Weining</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Hongjie</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai Institute of Infectious Disease and Biosecurity, School of Public Health, Fudan University, Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety, Ministry of Education, Shanghai, China. Electronic address: yhj@fudan.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Covasa</LastName><ForeName>Dimas Tadeu</ForeName><Initials>DT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Butantan Institute, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Infect</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7908424</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0163-4453</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 inactivated vaccines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CoronaVac</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Correlates of protection</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. Declaration of interests H.Y. has received research funding from Sanofi Pasteur, GlaxoSmithKline, Yichang HEC Changjiang Pharmaceutical Company, Shanghai Roche Pharmaceutical Company, and SINOVAC Biotech Ltd. None of the research funding is related to this work. BJC has received consulting fees from AstraZeneca, Fosun Pharma, GSK, Haleon, Moderna, Novavax, Pfizer, Roche, and Sanofi Pasteur. All other authors report no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39423875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2024.106315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0163-4453(24)00249-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>