<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39425875</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2194-7899</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Health &amp; justice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Health Justice</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on the experiences of incarcerated pregnant people.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>40</StartPage><MedlinePgn>40</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">40</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s40352-024-00296-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic disproportionately impacted incarcerated populations, yet few studies have investigated the specific effects on incarcerated pregnant people. This study compares pregnant people's experiences of pregnancy and parenting in prison before and during the pandemic in order to explore the impacts of COVID-19 on this population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We conducted semi-structured interviews with pregnant people at a state prison as part of a larger study on pregnant people's experiences during incarceration. Interviews explored participants' experiences and decision-making related to pregnancy and parenting while incarcerated. This secondary analysis compared interviews conducted between June 2019 and March 2020 (pre-COVID-19) to interviews conducted between June and November 2020 (during COVID-19). Interviews conducted during the pandemic included questions about the impact of COVID-19 on participants' experiences. Brief three and six-month follow-up interviews were conducted when possible.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">COVID-19 introduced new stressors and exacerbated preexisting stressors around participants' reproductive and parenting experiences. Three major themes emerged: 1) incarceration causes mental, emotional, and physical distress during pregnancy and parenting; 2) COVID-19 worsened conditions of incarceration, contributing to participants' distress; and 3) the introduction of quarantine protocols during the pandemic felt uniquely punitive for pregnant and postpartum people.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The COVID-19 pandemic was characterized as a major crisis and primary threat to public health, particularly for incarcerated individuals. Yet just as COVID-19 exacerbated preexisting disparities for marginalized, non-incarcerated communities, incarcerated pregnant people similarly described a "worsening" of already-intolerable conditions. The indiscriminate application of quarantine protocols for pregnant people reflects broader carceral logics of control that do not account for the wellbeing of pregnant and postpartum people and their infants, as evidenced by current practices of infant separation, a lack of support, and physically taxing living conditions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marsh</LastName><ForeName>L Noël</ForeName><Initials>LN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anthropology, University of Pittsburgh, Behavioral and Community Health Sciences, Wesley W. Posvar Hall, #3302, 230 S. Bouquet Street, Pittsburgh, PA, 15213, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kramer</LastName><ForeName>Camille</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7033-3439</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Center for Medical Humanities and Social Medicine, 4940 Eastern Ave, Baltimore, MD, 21224, USA. ckramer@jhu.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shlafer</LastName><ForeName>Rebecca J</ForeName><Initials>RJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Minnesota, 717 Delaware Street SE, Room 382, Minneapolis, MN, 55414, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sufrin</LastName><ForeName>Carolyn B</ForeName><Initials>CB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Center for Medical Humanities and Social Medicine, 4940 Eastern Ave, Baltimore, MD, 21224, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Health Justice</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101626355</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2194-7899</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Incarceration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parenting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pregnancy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quarantine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>CBS serves on the Board of the National Commission on Correctional Health Care as the liaison for the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists. LNM, CK, and RJS declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11490136</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40352-024-00296-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s40352-024-00296-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>ACOG. (2021a). Committee Opinion: Reproductive Health Care for Incarcerated Pregnant, Postpartum, and Nonpregnant Individuals. Obstetrics and Gynecology,138(1), e1–e11. 10.1097/ACOG.0000000000004429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33906198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ACOG. (2023). COVID-19 Public Health Considerations for Pregnant and Postpartum People Who Are Incarcerated. ACOG Policy and Position Statements. https://www.acog.org/clinical-information/policy-and-position-statements/position-statements/2021/covid-19-public-health-considerations-for-pregnant-and-postpartum-people-who-are-incarcerated</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altibi, A. M., Pallavi, B., Liaqat, H., Slota, A. A., Sheth, R., Al Jebbawi, L., George, M. E., LeDuc, A., Abdallah, E., Russell, L. R., Jain, S., Shirvanian, N., Masri, A., &amp; Kak, V. (2021). Characteristics and comparative clinical outcomes of prisoner versus non-prisoner populations hospitalized with COVID-19. Scientific Reports,11(1), 6488. 10.1038/s41598-021-85916-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7985211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33753786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnert, E., Kwan, A., &amp; Williams, B. (2021). Ten Urgent Priorities Based on Lessons Learned From More Than a Half Million Known COVID-19 Cases in US Prisons. American Journal of Public Health,111(6), 1099–1105. 10.2105/ajph.2021.306221</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8101573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33856887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogel-Burroughs, N., &amp; Swales, V. (2020). Prisoner with Coronavirus Dies After Giving Birth While on Ventilator. The New York Times. https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/29/us/coronavirus-inmate-death-andrea-circle-bear.html?searchResultPositioN=2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun, V., &amp; Clarke, V. (2006). Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qualitative Research in Psychology,3(2), 77–101. 10.1191/1478088706qp063oa</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breuer, E., Remond, M., Lighton, S., Passalaqua, J., Galouzis, J., Stewart, K.-A., &amp; Sullivan, E. (2021). The needs and experiences of mothers while in prison and post-release: A rapid review and thematic synthesis. Health Justice,9(1), 31. 10.1186/s40352-021-00153-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8590213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34773158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caron, R. M., &amp; Adegboye, A. R. A. (2023). COVID-19: A Syndemic Requiring an Integrated Approach for Marginalized Populations. Frontiers in Public Health,9, 675280. 10.3389/fpubh.2021.675280</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8144466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34046392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carson, E. A. (2022). Prisoners in 2021 - Statistical Tables. (NCJ Publication No. 305125). U.S. Department of Justice, Bureau of Justice Statistics. https://bjs.ojp.gov/library/publications/prisoners-2021-statistical-tables</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carson, E. A., &amp; Kluckow, R. (2023). Correctional Populations in the United States, 2021 - Statistical Tables. (NCJ Publication No. 305542). U.S. Department of Justice, Bureau of Justice Statistics. https://bjs.ojp.gov/sites/g/files/xyckuh236/files/media/document/cpus21stB.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassarino, N., Dabbara, H., Monteiro, C. B., Bembury, A., Credle, L., Grandhi, U., Patil, A., White, S., &amp; Jiménez, M. C. (2023). Conditions of Confinement in U.S. Carceral Facilities During COVID-19: Individuals Speak-Incarcerated During the COVID-19 Epidemic. Health Equity, 7(1), 261–270. 10.1089/heq.2022.0017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10150723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37139167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh, A., Shamsheri, T., Shen, K., Gaber, J., Liauw, J., Vanstone, M., &amp; Kouyoumdjian, F. (2022). Lived experiences of pregnancy and prison through a reproductive justice lens: A qualitative meta-synthesis. Social Science &amp; Medicine,1982(307), 115179–115179. 10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.115179</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35809528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. (2023). Pregnancy Mortality Surveillance System. Division of Reproductive Health, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion. https://www.cdc.gov/reproductivehealth/maternal-mortality/pregnancy-mortality-surveillance-system.htm#race-ethnicity</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chambers, A. (2009). Impact of Forced Separation Policy on Incarcerated Postpartum Mothers. Policy, Politics, &amp; Nursing Practice,10(3), 204–211. 10.1177/1527154409351592</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20022914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cloud, D. H., Ahalt, C., Augustine, D., Sears, D., &amp; Williams, B. (2020). Medical Isolation and Solitary Confinement: Balancing Health and Humanity in US Jails and Prisons During COVID-19. Journal of General Internal Medicine,35(9), 2738–2742. 10.1007/s11606-020-05968-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7338113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32632787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahir, A. L. (2020). ‘Instead of Coronavirus, the Hunger Will Kill Us.’ A Global Food Crisis Looms. The New York TImes. https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/22/world/africa/coronavirus-hunger-crisis.html?searchResultPositioN=8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dallaire, D. H., Shlafer, R. J., Goshin, L. S., Hollihan, A., Poehlmann-Tynan, J., Eddy, J. M., &amp; Adalist-Estrin, A. (2021). COVID-19 and prison policies related to communication with family members. Psychology, Public Policy, and Law,27(2), 231–241. 10.1037/law0000297</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickerson, C. (2020). Sleeping Outside in a Pandemic: Vulnerable Renters Face Evictions. The New York Times. https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/04/us/coronavirus-evictions-renters-immigrants.html?searchResultPositioN=2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumont, D. M., Brockmann, B., Dickman, S., Alexander, N., &amp; Rich, J. D. (2012). Public Health and the Epidemic of Incarceration. Annual Review of Public Health,33, 325–339. 10.1146/annurev-publhealth-031811-124614</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3329888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22224880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eligon, J. (2021). ‘Likely a Death Sentence’: Officials Fear Cold Weather Is Greater Risk for Homeless Than Virus. The New York Times. https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/14/us/coronavirus-homeless-cold-weather.html?searchResultPositioN=14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferszt, G. G., &amp; Clarke, J. G. (2012). Health care of pregnant women in U.S. state prisons. J Health Care Poor Underserved, 23(2), 557–569. 10.1353/hpu.2012.0048</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22643607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher, M., &amp; Bubola, E. (2020). As Coronavirus Deepens Inequality, Inequality Worsens Its Spread. The New York Times. https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/15/world/europe/coronavirus-inequality.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fletcher, A. J. (2017). Applying critical realism in qualitative research: Methodology meets method. International Journal of Social Research Methodology,20(2), 181–194. 10.1080/13645579.2016.1144401</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson, B. (2020). COVID-19 in Correctional Facilities: Screening, Testing, Race and Ethnicity. National Commission on Correctional Healthcare. Retrieved 04/25/2023 from https://www.ncchc.org/covid-19-in-correctional-facilities/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayes, C. M., Sufrin, C., &amp; Perritt, J. B. (2020). Reproductive Justice Disrupted: Mass Incarceration as a Driver of Reproductive Oppression. American Journal of Public Health,110(S1), S21–S24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6987912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31967889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutchinson-Colas, J., &amp; Sachdev, D. (2021). COVID-19 and pregnancy care for incarcerated women [Editorial]. Case Reports in Women’s Health, 30(e00296). 10.1016/j.crwh.2021.e00296</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7880836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33614418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin, Y., &amp; Murray, L. (2023). Perinatal mental health and women’s lived experience of the COVID-19 pandemic: A scoping review of the qualitative literature 2020–2021. Midwifery,123, 103706. 10.1016/j.midw.2023.103706</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10150412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37167674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelsey, C. M., Medel, N., Mullins, C., Dallaire, D., &amp; Forestell, C. (2017). An Examination of Care Practices of Pregnant Women Incarcerated in Jail Facilities in the United States. Maternal and Child Health Journal,21, 1260–1266. 10.1007/s10995-016-2224-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28236159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer, C., Thomas, K., Patil, A., Hayes, C. M., &amp; Sufrin, C. B. (2023). Shackling and pregnancy care policies in US prisons and jails. Maternal and Child Health Journal,27(1), 186–196. 10.1007/s10995-022-03526-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9660187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36372806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer, C., Williamston, A.-D., Shlafer, R., &amp; Sufrin, C. (2022). COVID-19’s Effect on Pregnancy Care for Incarcerated People. Health Equity, 6(1). 10.1089/heq.2022.0035</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9257549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35801144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>LeMasters, K., Brinkley-Rubinstein, L., Maner, M., Peterson, M., Nowotny, K., &amp; Bailey, Z. D. (2022). Carceral epidemiology: Mass incarceration and structural racism during the COVID-19 pandemic. Lancet Public Health,7(3), e287–e290. 10.1016/s2468-2667(22)00005-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8890762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35247354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandavilli, A. (2020). Study Raises Concerns for Pregnant Women with the Coronavirus. The New York Times. https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/24/health/coronavirus-pregnancy.html?searchResultPositioN=21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyer, C. A., Compton, S. D., Kaselitz, E., &amp; Muzik, M. (2020). Pregnancy-related anxiety during COVID-19: A nationwide survey of 2740 pregnant women. Archives of Women’s Mental Health,23(6), 757–765. 10.1007/s00737-020-01073-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7522009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32989598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muñiz, J. O., Corcoran, F., Marzougui, J., Shlafer, R., Eddy, J. M., &amp; Dallaire, D. (2023). Towards Family Preservation: A Systematic Jurisdiction Analysis of Prison Visitation Policies During the COVID-19 Pandemic. Psychology, Public Policy, and Law.10.1037/law0000379</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair, S., McGreevy, J. E., Hutchinson-Colas, J., Turock, H., Chervenak, F., Bachmann, G., &amp; NJ on Women’s Reentry-Health Subcommittee. (2021). Pregnancy in incarcerated women: Need for national legislation to standardize care. Journal of Perinatal Medicine,49(7), 830–836. 10.1515/jpm-2021-0145</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34167182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NASEM. (2020). Decarcerating Correctional Facilities during COVID-19: Advancing Health, Equity, and Safety. Press.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33411438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NCCHC. (2016). NCCHC Position Statement: Solitary Confinement [Position Statement]. https://www.ncchc.org/position-statements/solitary-confinement-isolation-2016/</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27302711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pettus-Davis, C., Kennedy, S. C., &amp; Veeh, C. A. (2021). Incarcerated individuals’ experiences of COVID-19 in the United States. International Journal of Prisoner Health,17(3), 335–350. 10.1108/ijph-11-2020-0094</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33760428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poehlmann-Tynan, J., &amp; Turney, K. (2021). A Developmental Perspective on Children with Incarcerated Parents. Child Development Perspectives,15(1), 3–11. 10.1111/cdep.12392</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>QSR International. (2020). NVivo 13 (Version R1) [computer software]. https://lumivero.com/products/nvivo/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ransom, J., &amp; Feuer, A. (2020). ‘A Storm Is Coming’: Fears of an Inmate Epidemic as the Virus Spreads in the Jails. The New York Times. https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/20/nyregion/nyc-coronavirus-rikers-island.html?searchResultPositioN=13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reisdorf B. C. (2023). Locked In and Locked Out: How COVID-19 Is Making the Case for Digital Inclusion of Incarcerated Populations. The American Behavioral Scientist, 00027642231155369. 10.1177/00027642231155369</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts, S. C., Kimport, K., Kriz, R., Holl, J., Mark, K., &amp; Williams, V. (2019). Consideration of and Reasons for Not Obtaining Abortion Among Women Entering Prenatal Care in Southern Louisiana and Baltimore, Maryland. Sexuality Research and Social Policy,16, 476–487. 10.1007/s13178-018-0359-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romano, S. D., Blackstock, A. J., Taylor, E. V., Felix, S. E. B., Adjei, S., Singleton, C.-M., Fuld, J., Bruce, B. B., &amp; Boehmer, T. K. (2021). Trends in Racial and Ethnic Disparities in COVID-19 Hospitalizations, by Region — United States, March-December 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep, 70, 560–565. 10.15585/mmwr.mm7015e2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8344991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33857068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross, L., Roberts, L., Derkas, E., Peoples, W., &amp; Bridgewater, P. (Eds.). (2017). Radical Reproductive Justice: Foundation. Practice, Critique Feminist Press at the City University of New York.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saldaña, J. (2016). The Coding Manual for Qualitative Researchers (3rd ed.). Sage.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saloner, B., Parish, K., Ward, J. A., DiLaura, G., &amp; Dolovich, S. (2020). COVID-19 Cases and Deaths in Federal and State Prisons. JAMA,324(6), 602–603. 10.1001/jama.2020.12528</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7344796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32639537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scales, D., Gorman, J., &amp; Jamieson, K. H. (2021). The Covid-19 Infodemic — Applying the Epidemiological Model to Counter Misinformation. The New England Journal of Medicine,385(8), 678–681. 10.1056/NEJMp2103798</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33979506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shlafer, R. J., Hardeman, R. R., &amp; Carlson, E. A. (2019). Reproductive Justice for Incarcerated Mothers and Advocacy for their Infants and Young Children. Infant Mental Health Journal,40, 725–741. 10.1002/imhj.21810</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6973282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31323699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, M., Kramer, C. T., Sufrin, C. B., Eber, G. B., Rubenstein, L. S., Beyrer, C., &amp; Saloner, B. (2023). “It was like you were being literally punished for getting sick”: Formerly incarcerated people’s perspectives on liberty restrictions during COVID-19. AJOB Empirical Bioethics. 10.1080/23294515.2023.2180105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36811402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sufrin, C. (2017). Jailcare: Finding the Safety Net for Women Behind Bars. University of California Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sufrin, C., Beal, L., Clarke, J., Jones, R., &amp; Mosher, W. D. (2019). Pregnancy Outcomes in US Prisons, 2016–2017. American Journal of Public Health,109(5), 799–805. 10.2105/AJPH.2019.305006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6459671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30897003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sufrin, C., Jones, R. K., Mosher, W. D., &amp; Beal, L. (2020). Pregnancy Prevalence and Outcomes in U.S. Jails. Obstetrics and Gynecology, 135(5), 1177–1183. 10.1097/AOG.0000000000003834.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7183903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32282606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sufrin, C. B., Devon-Williamston, A., Beal, L., Hayes, C. M., &amp; Kramer, C. (2023). “I mean, I didn’t really have a choice of anything:” How incarceration influences abortion decision-making and precludes access in the United States. Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health. 10.1363/psrh.12235</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37394626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tai, D. B. G., Shah, A., Doubeni, C. A., Sia, I. G., &amp; Wieland, M. L. (2021). The Disproportionate Impact of COVID-19 on Racial and Ethnic Minorities in the United States. Clinical Infectious Diseases,72(4), 703–706. 10.1093/cid/ciaa815</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7337626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32562416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomfohr-Madsen, L. M., Racine, N., Giesbrechta, G. F., Lebel, C., &amp; Madigan, S. (2021). Depression and anxiety in pregnancy during COVID-19: A rapid review and meta-analysis. Psychiatry Research, 300(113912). 10.1016/j.psychres.2021.113912</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9755112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33836471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Towers, S., Wallace, D., Walker, J., Eason, J. M., Nelson, J. R., &amp; Grubesic, T. H. (2022). A study of SARS-COV-2 outbreaks in US federal prisons: The linkage between staff, incarcerated populations, and community transmission. BMC Public Health,22(1), 482. 10.1186/s12889-022-12813-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8916071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35277142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsuda-McCaie, F., &amp; Kotera, Y. (2022). A qualitative meta-synthesis of pregnant women’s experiences of accessing and receiving treatment for opioid use disorder. Drug and Alcohol Review,41(4), 851–862. 10.1111/dar.13421</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35038366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, T., Weiser, B., &amp; Rashbaum, W. K. (2020). ‘Jails Are Petri Dishes’: Inmates Freed as the Virus Spreads Behind Bars. The New York Times. https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/30/us/coronavirus-prisons-jails.html?actioN=click&amp;module=RelatedLinks&amp;pgtype=Article</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zambrano, L. D., Ellington, S., Strid, P., Galang, R. R., Oduyebo, T., Tong, V. T., Woodworth, K. R., Nahabedian III, J. F., Azziz-Baumgartner, E., Gilboa, S. M., Meaney-Delman, D., &amp; CDC COVID-19 Response Pregnancy and Infant Linked Outcomes Team. (2020). Update: Characteristics of Symptomatic Women of Reproductive Age with Laboratory-Confirmed SARS-CoV-2 Infection by Pregnancy Status — United States, January 22-October 3, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep, 69, 1641–1647. 10.15585/mmwr.mm6944e3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7643892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33151921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zielinski, M. J., Cowell, M., Bull, C. E., Veluvolu, M., Behne, M. F., Nowotny, K., &amp; Brinkley-Rubinstein, L. (2022). Policy and public communication methods among U.S. state prisons during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic. Health &amp; Justice,10, 27–40. 10.1186/s40352-022-00187-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9435413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36048251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>