<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39435321</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2328-8957</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Open forum infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Open Forum Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effects of Pitavastatin on COVID-19 Incidence and Seriousness Among a Global Cohort of People With HIV.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>ofae574</StartPage><MedlinePgn>ofae574</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">ofae574</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/ofid/ofae574</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Among people with HIV (PWH), COVID-19 is common and potentially severe. We leveraged REPRIEVE (Randomized Trial to Prevent Vascular Events in HIV) to assess the effects of statin therapy for cardiovascular disease prevention on COVID-19 outcomes (incidence and serious cases) among a global cohort of PWH.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">COVID-19 data collection was implemented April 2020 to capture events from January 2020. COVID-19 was defined by positive test result or clinical diagnosis and serious COVID-19 according to the International Conference on Harmonisation definition. Among participants in follow-up on 1 January 2020, Cox proportional hazards modeling was used to estimate the hazard ratio (HR) of COVID-19 (pitavastatin/placebo), stratified by Global Burden of Disease region. Modification of statin effect following COVID-19 vaccination was evaluated via interaction with time-updated vaccination status.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Among 6905 PWH, 32% were natal female and 41% were Black or African American. The median age was 53 years and the 10-year atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease risk score 4.5%. Statin therapy did not reduce COVID-19 incidence (HR, 1.05; 95% CI, .95-1.15) but appeared to reduce incidence of serious COVID-19 (HR, 0.75; 95% CI, .52-1.09). Among 1701 PWH with COVID-19, the relative risk (pitavastatin/placebo) for serious COVID-19 was 0.73 (95% CI, .52-1.03). The treatment effect size for serious COVID-19 fell within the hypothesized range, but the 95% CI crossed 1 given fewer-than-anticipated cases (117 vs 200). Furthermore, 83% reported COVID-19 vaccination by end of study, with a strong protective effect on serious COVID-19 (HR, 0.27; 95% CI, .14-.53; <i>P</i> &lt; .0001). A protective statin effect was observed prior to vaccination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Among PWH, statin therapy had no effect on COVID-19 incidence but showed potential to reduce risk of serious COVID-19 prior to COVID-19 vaccination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CLINICAL TRIALS REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">NCT02344290 (ClinicalTrials.gov).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Infectious Diseases Society of America.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zanni</LastName><ForeName>Markella V</ForeName><Initials>MV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolism Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Umbleja</LastName><ForeName>Triin</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7161-7743</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Biostatistics in AIDS Research, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Heath, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fichtenbaum</LastName><ForeName>Carl J</ForeName><Initials>CJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6778-7253</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, College of Medicine, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fitch</LastName><ForeName>Kathleen V</ForeName><Initials>KV</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0541-3707</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolism Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McCallum</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0289-1295</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolism Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aberg</LastName><ForeName>Judith A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Overton</LastName><ForeName>Edgar Turner</ForeName><Initials>ET</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malvestutto</LastName><ForeName>Carlos D</ForeName><Initials>CD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3156-2965</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Ohio State University Medical Center, Columbus, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bloomfield</LastName><ForeName>Gerald S</ForeName><Initials>GS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Duke Global Health Institute, and Duke Clinical Research Institute, School of Medicine, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Currier</LastName><ForeName>Judith S</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4279-4737</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schnittman</LastName><ForeName>Samuel R</ForeName><Initials>SR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolism Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Erlandson</LastName><ForeName>Kristine M</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0808-6729</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, University of Colorado-Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diggs</LastName><ForeName>Marissa R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolism Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Foldyna</LastName><ForeName>Borek</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2466-4827</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Imaging Research Center, Department of Radiology, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martinez</LastName><ForeName>Esteban</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Diseases Service, Hospital Clinic and University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Somboonwit</LastName><ForeName>Charurut</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Morsani College of Medicine, University of South Florida, Tampa, Florida, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Gary P</ForeName><Initials>GP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, School of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mushatt</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, School of Medicine, Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Connick</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0465-6248</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, College of Medicine, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Michael T</ForeName><Initials>MT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Imaging Research Center, Department of Radiology, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Douglas</LastName><ForeName>Pamela S</ForeName><Initials>PS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9876-4049</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Duke Clinical Research Institute, School of Medicine, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ribaudo</LastName><ForeName>Heather J</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Biostatistics in AIDS Research, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Heath, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grinspoon</LastName><ForeName>Steven K</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolism Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT02344290</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016430">Clinical Trial</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Open Forum Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101637045</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2328-8957</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HIV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PWH</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">REPRIEVE</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">statin</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Potential conflicts of interest. M. V. Z. reports grant support through her institution from the National Institutes of Health/National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIH/NIAID) and Gilead Sciences, Inc, relevant to the conduct of the study, as well as grants from NIH/NIAID and the NIH/National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI); support for attending the Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections and International Workshop for HIV and Women from conference organizing committee when abstract reviewer and/or speaker; and participation in a data and safety monitoring board for NIH funded studies, outside the submitted work. T. U. reports grants from NIH/NHLBI and Kowa Pharmaceuticals during the conduct of the study, as well as grants from NIH/NIAID and NIH/National Institute on Aging (NIA), outside the submitted work. C. J. F. reports research grants to his institution from Gilead Sciences, Merck, ViiV Healthcare and Moderna unrelated to this work. J. A. A. reports institutional research support for clinical trials from Emergent Biosolutions, Gilead Sciences, Glaxo Smith Kline, Janssen, Merck, Pfizer, Regeneron, and ViiV Healthcare; personal fees for advisory boards from Glaxo Smith Kline/ViiV and Merck; and participation on a data and safety monitoring board for Kintor Pharmaceuticals, all outside the submitted work. E. T. O. reports grant support from Gilead Sciences, ViiV Healthcare, and Janssen; consulting fees from ViiV Healthcare; and employment with ViiV Healthcare Medical Affairs, all outside the submitted work. C. D. M. reports institutional research support by Lilly and honoraria from ViiV Healthcare, Gilead Sciences, and Pfizer for advisory board membership, all outside the submitted work. J. S. C. reports consulting fees from Merck and Company and Resvirlogix, outside the submitted work. S. R. S. reports grant support through his institution from NIH/NIAID (T32 AI007387). K. M. E. reports grant support from NIH/NIA and Gilead Sciences, Inc; consulting fees paid to her institution from Gilead Sciences, Inc, ViiV Healthcare, and Janssen Therapeutics; and participation on an NIH data and safety monitoring board, all outside the submitted work. B. F. reports institutional research support from AstraZeneca, MedImmune, and MedTrace, as well as grants from NIH/NHLBI, all outside the submitted work. E. M. reports institutional research support from MSD and ViiV as well as honoraria for lectures or advisory boards from Gilead, Janssen, MDS, and ViiV. G. P. W. reports grant support through his institution from NIH/NIAID, NIH/National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, and Veterans Health Administration, all outside the submitted work. M. T. L. reports grant support through his institution from the NIH/NHLBI and Kowa Pharmaceuticals America for the conduct of the study. He also reports research support to his institution from the American Heart Association, AstraZeneca, Ionis, Johnson &amp; Johnson Innovation, MedImmune, the National Academy of Medicine, the NIH/NHLBI, and the Risk Management Foundation of the Harvard Medical Institutions Incorporated, outside the submitted work. H. J. R. reports grants from Kowa Pharmaceuticals during the conduct of the study, as well as grants from NIH/NIAID, NIH/NHLBI, NIH/National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, and NIH/NIA, outside the submitted work. S. K. G. reports grant support through his institution from NIH, Kowa Pharmaceuticals America, Inc, Gilead Sciences, Inc, and ViiV Healthcare for the conduct of the study; personal fees from Theratechnologies and ViiV; and service on the Scientific Advisory Board of Marathon Asset Management, all outside the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39435321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11493083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofae574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ofae574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wang  Y, Xie  Y, Hu  S, et al.  Systematic review and meta-analyses of the interaction between HIV infection and COVID-19: two years’ evidence summary. Front Immunol  2022; 13:864838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9128408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35619709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thornhill  J, Orkin  C, Cevik  M. Estimating the global impact of coronavirus disease 2019 on people living with HIV. Curr Opin Infect Dis  2023; 36:20–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36729763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertagnolio  S, Thwin  SS, Silva  R, et al.  Clinical features of, and risk factors for, severe or fatal COVID-19 among people living with HIV admitted to hospital: analysis of data from the WHO global clinical platform of COVID-19. Lancet HIV  2022; 9:e486–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9090268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35561704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniels  LB, Sitapati  AM, Zhang  J, et al.  Relation of statin use prior to admission to severity and recovery among COVID-19 inpatients. Am J Cardiol  2020; 136:149–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7492151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32946859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lohia  P, Kapur  S, Benjaram  S, Mir  T. Association between antecedent statin use and severe disease outcomes in COVID-19: a retrospective study with propensity score matching. J Clin Lipidol  2021; 15:451–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7936125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33726984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santosa  A, Franzen  S, Natman  J, Wettermark  B, Parmryd  I, Nyberg  F. Protective effects of statins on COVID-19 risk, severity and fatal outcome: a nationwide Swedish cohort study. Sci Rep  2022; 12:12047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9282150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35835835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouillon  K, Baricault  B, Semenzato  L, et al.  Association of statins for primary prevention of cardiovascular diseases with hospitalization for COVID-19: a nationwide matched population-based cohort study. J Am Heart Assoc  2022; 11:e023357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9238639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35699173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres-Pena  JD, Katsiki  N, Perez-Martinez  P. Could statin therapy be useful in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)?  Front Cardiovasc Med  2021; 8:775749.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8578478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34778421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grinspoon  SK, Fitch  KV, Overton  ET, et al.  Rationale and design of the Randomized Trial to Prevent Vascular Events in HIV (REPRIEVE). Am Heart J  2019; 212:23–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6535121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30928825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grinspoon  SK, Fitch  KV, Zanni  MV, et al.  Pitavastatin to prevent cardiovascular disease in HIV infection. N Engl J Med  2023; 389:687–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10564556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37486775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GBD 2019 Diseases and Injuries Collaborators . Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet  2020; 396:1204–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7567026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
International Conference on Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Registration of Pharmaceuticals for Human Use 
. ICH harmonised tripartite guideline. Clinical safety data management: definitions and standards for expedited reporting E2A. 1994. https://database.ich.org/sites/default/files/E2A_Guideline.pdf. Accessed 16 September 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douglas  PS, Umbleja  T, Bloomfield  GS, et al.  Cardiovascular risk and health among people with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) eligible for primary prevention: insights from the REPRIEVE trial. Clin Infect Dis  2021; 73:2009–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8664454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34134131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fulda  ES, Fitch  KV, Overton  ET, et al.  COVID-19 vaccination rates in a global HIV cohort. J Infect Dis  2022; 225:603–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8844595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34794178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butt  JH, Gerds  TA, Schou  M, et al.  Association between statin use and outcomes in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a nationwide cohort study. BMJ Open  2020; 10:e044421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7722358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33277291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitacchione  G, Schiavone  M, Curnis  A, et al.  Impact of prior statin use on clinical outcomes in COVID-19 patients: data from tertiary referral hospitals during COVID-19 pandemic in Italy. J Clin Lipidol  2021; 15:68–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33390341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yetmar  ZA, Chesdachai  S, Kashour  T, et al.  Prior statin use and risk of mortality and severe disease from coronavirus disease 2019: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Open Forum Infect Dis  2021; 8:ofab284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8244756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34258316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talasaz  AH, Sadeghipour  P, Aghakouchakzadeh  M, et al.  Investigating lipid-modulating agents for prevention or treatment of COVID-19: JACC state-of-the-art review. J Am Coll Cardiol  2021; 78:1635–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8504484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34649702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu  C, Yan  W, Shi  J, et al.  Biological actions, implications, and cautions of statins therapy in COVID-19. Front Nutr  2022; 9:927092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9257176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35811982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandermeer  ML, Thomas  AR, Kamimoto  L, et al.  Association between use of statins and mortality among patients hospitalized with laboratory-confirmed influenza virus infections: a multistate study. J Infect Dis  2012; 205:13–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22170954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frost  FJ, Petersen  H, Tollestrup  K, Skipper  B. Influenza and COPD mortality protection as pleiotropic, dose-dependent effects of statins. Chest  2007; 131:1006–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17426203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacobs  ET, Cordova-Marks  FM, Farland  LV, et al.  Understanding low COVID-19 booster uptake among US adults. Vaccine  2023; 41:6221–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37666694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah  A, Coiado  OC. COVID-19 vaccine and booster hesitation around the world: a literature review. Front Med (Lausanne)  2022; 9:1054557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9878297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36714110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsampasian  V, Elghazaly  H, Chattopadhyay  R, et al.  Risk factors associated with post-COVID-19 condition: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Intern Med  2023; 183:566–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10037203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36951832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talasaz  AH, Sadeghipour  P, Bakhshandeh  H, et al.  Atorvastatin versus placebo in ICU patients with COVID-19: ninety-day results of the INSPIRATION-S trial. Thromb Haemost  2023; 123:723–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36944357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>REMAP-CAP Investigators . Simvastatin in critically ill patients with COVID-19. N Engl J Med  2023; 389:2341–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10755839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37888913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>