<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39438522</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Topic modelling and sentiment analysis during COVID-19 revealed emotions changes for public health.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>24954</StartPage><MedlinePgn>24954</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">24954</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-75209-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Between 2020 and 2022, lockdown and restraining measures as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic led to changes in daily routines and also in language usage. At certain points during the pandemic, populations in some countries were unwilling or unlikely to respond to government messages, either because of the tone and analytic discourse used by leaders, or because they did not understand the messages. Linguistic markers and meanings were therefore linked to low levels of engagement, negative emotions and high levels of analytical thinking, especially in relation to the discourses of influential international leaders. We subjected sixteen speeches by eight country leaders to topic modelling and sentiment analysis in order to understand how the psychological functions of language were affected during two different periods of the COVID-19 pandemic. In this topic analysis we organize 39,073 words collected from sixteen authentic speeches delivered in two different periods of the acute phase of the pandemic. These were encoded in the Linguistic Inquiry Word Count program (LIWC), with the main aim being to identify differences between the periods. We examined the following aspects: (1) the emotional tone, analytical thinking and clout (empathy dimension); (2) the changes in these three dimensions or factors between periods 1 and 2 (February and May 2020). We observed a negative relationship between emotional tone and analytical thinking and a positive relationship between clout and emotional tone. When we considered the changes in pandemic circumstances, the psycholinguistic profiles of eight country leaders demonstrated fluctuations in language and emotions. Further reviews and research should focus on the current language and deficit wording of this population (leaders). We also note that psychologists and schoolteachers can play an important role in supporting language programmes with positive wording and by emphasising the collateral effects of face-to-face classes when teaching children to read and write.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Figueiredo</LastName><ForeName>S</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5152-4467</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Autonomous University of Lisbon, Palácio Dos Condes Do Redondo, R. de Santa Marta 56, Lisbon, 1169-023, Portugal. sfigueiredo@autonoma.pt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004644" MajorTopicYN="Y">Emotions</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="Y">Public Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007802" MajorTopicYN="N">Language</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004645" MajorTopicYN="N">Empathy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008037" MajorTopicYN="N">Linguistics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Analytical thinking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Democracy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emotion and empathy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Language fluctuation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sentiment analysis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39438522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11496542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-75209-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-75209-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lwin, M., Lu, J., Sheldenkar, A., Schulz, P., Shin, W., Gupta, R., Yang, Y. Global sentiments surrounding the COVID-19 pandemic on Twitter: Analysis of Twitter trends. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 6(2), e19447 (2020). 10.2196/19447</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7247466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32412418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, Y., Ren, Y. Language Change and morphological processes in contemporary Chinese: The case of 健康码 (Health QR Code). Languages. 8(2), 123 (2023). 10.3390/languages8020123</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ducasse, A. Oral reflection tasks: Advanced Spanish L2 Learner insights on Emergency Remote Teaching Assessment practices in a higher education context. Languages. 7(1), 26 (2020). 10.3390/languages7010026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joudry, R., Leonard, R. How sound therapy can help children recover from language deficits resulting from COVID-19 lock downs: A literature review. J. Alternative Med. Res.. 15(2), 209–223 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musyoka, M. Translanguaging in bilingual Deaf Education Teacher Preparation Programs. Languages. 8(1), 65 (2023). 10.3390/languages8010065</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barreneche, S.M. Somebody to blame: On the construction of the other in the context of the COVID-19 outbreak. Society Register. 4(2), 19–32 (2020). 10.14746/sr.2020.4.2.02</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanschmidt, F., Kersting, A. Emotions in COVID-19 Twitter discourse following the introduction of social contact restrictions in Central Europe. J. Public Health. 31(6), 933–946 (2023). 10.1007/s10389-021-01613-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8252989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34230875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kostruba, N. Text health messages in religious discourse: Psycholinguistic analysis. Psycholinguistics. 30(1), 59–82 (2021). 10.31470/2309-1797-2021-30-1-59-82</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borges, É., Koltermann, G., Minervino, C., de Salles, J. The role of Emergent Literacy Assessment in Brazilian Portuguese literacy Acquisition during COVID-19. Behav. Sci.. 13(6), 510. 10.3390/bs13060510</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10295449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37366762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdo, M.S., Alghonaim, A.S., Essam, B.A. Public perception of COVID-19’s global health crisis on Twitter until 14 weeks after the outbreak. Digital Scholarship Humanities. 37, 509–52. 10.1093/llc/fqaa037</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, T., Olivares, S., Myneni, S. Latent linguistic motifs in social media postings resisting COVID-19 misinformation. in MEDINFO: One World, One Health–Global Partnership for Digital Innovation, 557–561. (IOS Press, 2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11420648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35673078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volk, S. Political performances of control during COVID-19: Controlling and contesting democracy in Germany. Front. Political Sci.. 3, 654069 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cinelli, M., Quattrociocchi, W., Galeazzi, A. et al. The COVID-19 social media infodemic. Sci. Rep. 10, 16598 (2020). 10.1038/s41598-020-73510-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7538912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33024152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastani, P., Bahrami, M.A. COVID-19 related misinformation on Social Media: A qualitative study from Iran. J. Med. Internet Res. (2020). 10.2196/18932</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32250961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Figueiredo, S., João, R., Alho, L., Hipólito, J. Psychological research on sleep problems and Adjustment of working hours during teleworking in the COVID-19 pandemic: An exploratory study. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 19(21), 14305 (2020). 10.3390/ijerph192114305</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9656353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36361185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feldman, R. Development across the Life Span (10th). (Pearson Education International, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dworakowski, O., Meier, T., Mehl, M.R., Pennebaker, J.W., Boyd, R.L., Horn, A.B. Comparing the language style of heads of state in the US, UK, Germany and Switzerland during COVID-19. Sci. Rep.. 14(1), 1708 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10799077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38242954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitfield, C., Liu, Y., Anwar, M. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on Social Determinants of Health Issues of Marginalized Black and Asian communities: a social media analysis empowered by Natural Language Processing. J. Racial Ethnic Health Disparities. (2024). 10.1007/s40615-024-01996-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38625665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Figueiredo, S., Dierks, A., Ferreira, R. Mental health screening in refugees communities: Ukrainianrefugees and their post-traumatic stress disorder specificities. Eur. J. Trauma Dissociation.. 8(1), 100382 (2024). 10.1016/j.ejtd.2024.100382</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, V., Garg, L., Fomiceva, E., Pineda, S.V., Santos, A.N., Bawa, S. A framework for masked-image recognition system in COVID-19 era. in International Conference on Recent Trends in Image Processing and Pattern Recognition, 195–209. (Springer International Publishing, 2021). 10.1007/978-3-031-07005-1_18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calbi, M., Langiulli, N., Ferroni, F., Montalti, M., Kolesnikov, A., Gallese, V., Umiltà, M.A. The consequences of COVID-19 on social interactions: An online study on face covering. Sci. Rep.. 11(1), 2601 (2021). 10.1038/s41598-021-81780-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7844002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33510195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baiano, C., Raimo, G., Zappullo, I., Marra, M., Cecere, R., Trojano, L.,Conson, M. Empathy through the pandemic: Changes of different emphatic dimensions during the COVID-19 outbreak. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 19(4), 2435 (2022). 10.3390/ijerph19042435</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8872216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35206623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamble, R.S., Henry, J.D., Vanman, E.J. Empathy moderates the relationship between cognitive load and prosocial behaviour. Sci. Rep.. 13(1), 824 (2023). 10.1038/s41598-023-28098-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9841498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36646855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández-Pichel, M., Aragón, M.E., Saborido-Patiño, J., Losada, D.E. Personality trait analysis during the COVID-19 pandemic: A comparative study on social media. J. Intell. Inform. Syst. 62(1), 117–142 (2024). 10.1007/s10844-023-00810-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed, N.M., Kisa. Political leaders’ communication strategies during COVID-19 in highly infected countries: A scoping review. Healthcare. 12(6), 607 (2024). 10.3390/healthcare12060607</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10970693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38540571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crible, L &amp; Degand, L. Domains and functions: A two-dimensional account of discourse markers. Discours. Revue de Linguistique, Psycholinguistique et Informatique. A Journal of Linguistics, Psycholinguistics and Computational Linguistics. 24, 3–35 (2019). 10.4000/discours.9997</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dudău, D. &amp; Sava, F. Performing multilingual analysis with Linguistic Inquiry and Word Count 2015 (LIWC2015). An equivalence study of four languages. Front. Psychol. 12, 570568 (2020). 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.570568</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8311520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34322047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wortham, S. &amp; Reyes, A. Discourse Analysis Beyond the Speech Event. (Routledge, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morosanova, V., Bondarenko, I.N. &amp; Kondratyuk, N.G. Regulatory resources and emotional states in overcoming difficulties of self-organization during lockdown. Psychol. Studies. 66(3), 280–290 (2021). 10.1007/s12646-021-00611-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8286645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34305182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong, J.C., Cao, W., Liu, X., Tai, K.H., &amp; Zhao, L. Personality traits predict the effects of internet and academic self-efficacy on practical performance anxiety in online learning under the COVID-19 lockdown. J. Res. Technol. Education. 55(3), 426–440 (2023). 10.1080/15391523.2021.1967818</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hampshire, A., Hellyer, P.J. &amp; Soreq, E. et al. Associations between dimensions of behaviour, personality traits, and mental-health during the COVID-19 pandemic in the United Kingdom. Nat. Commun. 12, 4111 (2021). 10.1038/s41467-021-24365-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8285408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34272365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pennebaker, J.W., Booth, R.J., Boyd, R.L., &amp; Francis, M.E. Linguistic Inquiry and Word Count: LIWC2015. (Pennebaker Conglomerates, 2015).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>