<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39435115</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>19</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Expression of interferon-stimulated genes, but not polymorphisms in the interferon α/β receptor 2 gene, is associated with coronavirus disease 2019 mortality.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e39002</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e39002</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e39002</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e39002</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Excessive inflammatory response is a hallmark of severe COVID-19. This study investigated the associations between interferon-stimulated genes (ISGs) expression, genetic variation in the interferon α/β receptor 2 (IFNAR2) gene, and COVID-19 mortality. We investigated 67 patients with moderate-to-severe COVID-19. Of them, 22 patients (32.8 %) died because of COVID-19. We examined the expression of ISGs in total RNA of peripheral whole blood. We observed a significant increase in the expression of all ISGs examined in non-surviving patients, indicating a heightened interferon type I signaling activation in non-survived patients. Subsequently, we analyzed whether the increase in ISGs expression was correlated with polymorphism within the <i>IFNAR2</i> gene. Intriguingly, no significant association was observed between <i>IFNAR2</i> gene polymorphism and COVID-19 mortality. Similarly, no association was noted between the IFNAR2 and ISGs expression levels. Overall, our data showed that higher ISGs expression, which presumably indicates heightened interferon type I activation, is associated with COVID-19 mortality.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hamidah</LastName><ForeName>Berliana</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Science, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pakpahan</LastName><ForeName>Cennikon</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Science, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wulandari</LastName><ForeName>Laksmi</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonology and Respiratory Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Airlangga/Dr Soetomo General Academic Hospital, Surabaya, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tinduh</LastName><ForeName>Damayanti</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Airlangga/Dr Soetomo General Academic Hospital, Surabaya, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wibawa</LastName><ForeName>Tri</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Medicine, Public Health, and Nursing, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prakoeswa</LastName><ForeName>Cita Rosita Sigit</ForeName><Initials>CRS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Venerology and Aesthetics, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Airlangga / Dr. Soetomo General Academic Hospital, Surabaya, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oceandy</LastName><ForeName>Delvac</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Sciences, Faculty of Biology, Medicine and Health, University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">IFNAR2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immune response</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Interferon</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Interferon receptor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Interferon type I</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Interferon-stimulated genes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Polymorphism</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39435115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11492585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e39002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)15033-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Stanifer M.L., Guo C., Doldan P., Boulant S. Importance of type I and III interferons at respiratory and intestinal barrier surfaces. Front. Immunol. 2020;11 doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2020.608645.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.608645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7759678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33362795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platanias L.C. Mechanisms of type-I- and type-II-interferon-mediated signalling. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2005;5:375–386. doi: 10.1038/nri1604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nri1604</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15864272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoggins J.W. Interferon-stimulated genes: what do they all do? Annu Rev Virol. 2019;6:567–584. doi: 10.1146/annurev-virology-092818-015756.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-virology-092818-015756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31283436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Upasani V., Scagnolari C., Frasca F., Smith N., Bondet V., Vanderlinden A., Lay S., Auerswald H., Heng S., Laurent D., Ly S., Duong V., Antonelli G., Dussart P., Duffy D., Cantaert T. Decreased type I interferon production by plasmacytoid dendritic cells contributes to severe dengue. Front. Immunol. 2020;11 doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2020.605087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.605087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7773824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33391269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirasaki T., Honda M., Shimakami T., Murai K., Shiomoto T., Okada H., Takabatake R., Tokumaru A., Sakai Y., Yamashita T., Lemon S.M., Murakami S., Kaneko S. Impaired interferon signaling in chronic hepatitis C patients with advanced fibrosis via the transforming growth factor beta signaling pathway. Hepatology. 2014;60:1519–1530. doi: 10.1002/hep.27277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hep.27277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24962339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grajales-Reyes G.E., Colonna M. Interferon responses in viral pneumonias. Science. 2020;369:626–627. doi: 10.1126/science.abd2208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abd2208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32764056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Queiroz M.A.F., Brito W., Pereira K.A.S., Pereira L.M.S., Amoras E., Lima S.S., Santos E.F.D., Costa F.P.D., Sarges K.M.L., Cantanhede M.H.D., Brito M., Silva A., Leite M.M., Viana M., Rodrigues F.B.B., Silva R.D., Viana G.M.R., Chaves T., Verissimo A.O.L., Carvalho M.D.S., Henriques D.F., Silva C.P.D., Nunes J.A.L., Costa I.B., Cayres-Vallinoto I.M.V., Brasil-Costa I., Quaresma J.A.S., Falcao L.F.M., Santos E., Vallinoto A.C.R. Severe COVID-19 and long COVID are associated with high expression of STING, cGAS and IFN-alpha. Sci. Rep. 2024;14:4974. doi: 10.1038/s41598-024-55696-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-55696-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10904751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38424312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sposito B., Broggi A., Pandolfi L., Crotta S., Clementi N., Ferrarese R., Sisti S., Criscuolo E., Spreafico R., Long J.M., Ambrosi A., Liu E., Frangipane V., Saracino L., Bozzini S., Marongiu L., Facchini F.A., Bottazzi A., Fossali T., Colombo R., Clementi M., Tagliabue E., Chou J., Pontiroli A.E., Meloni F., Wack A., Mancini N., Zanoni I. The interferon landscape along the respiratory tract impacts the severity of COVID-19. Cell. 2021;184:4953–4968 e4916. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2021.08.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.08.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8373821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34492226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Valle D.M., Kim-Schulze S., Huang H.H., Beckmann N.D., Nirenberg S., Wang B., Lavin Y., Swartz T.H., Madduri D., Stock A., Marron T.U., Xie H., Patel M., Tuballes K., Van Oekelen O., Rahman A., Kovatch P., Aberg J.A., Schadt E., Jagannath S., Mazumdar M., Charney A.W., Firpo-Betancourt A., Mendu D.R., Jhang J., Reich D., Sigel K., Cordon-Cardo C., Feldmann M., Parekh S., Merad M., Gnjatic S. An inflammatory cytokine signature predicts COVID-19 severity and survival. Nat. Med. 2020;26:1636–1643. doi: 10.1038/s41591-020-1051-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-1051-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7869028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fajgenbaum D.C., June C.H. Cytokine storm. N. Engl. J. Med. 2020;383:2255–2273. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra2026131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMra2026131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7727315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33264547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tay M.Z., Poh C.M., Renia L., MacAry P.A., Ng L.F.P. The trinity of COVID-19: immunity, inflammation and intervention. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2020;20:363–374. doi: 10.1038/s41577-020-0311-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41577-020-0311-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7187672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32346093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanco-Melo D., Nilsson-Payant B.E., Liu W.C., Uhl S., Hoagland D., Moller R., Jordan T.X., Oishi K., Panis M., Sachs D., Wang T.T., Schwartz R.E., Lim J.K., Albrecht R.A., tenOever B.R. Imbalanced host response to SARS-CoV-2 drives development of COVID-19. Cell. 2020;181:1036–1045 e1039. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2020.04.026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.04.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7227586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32416070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broggi A., Ghosh S., Sposito B., Spreafico R., Balzarini F., Lo Cascio A., Clementi N., De Santis M., Mancini N., Granucci F., Zanoni I. Type III interferons disrupt the lung epithelial barrier upon viral recognition. Science. 2020;369:706–712. doi: 10.1126/science.abc3545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abc3545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32527925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King C., Sprent J. Dual nature of type I interferons in SARS-CoV-2-induced inflammation. Trends Immunol. 2021;42:312–322. doi: 10.1016/j.it.2021.02.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.it.2021.02.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7879020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33622601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pairo-Castineira E., Clohisey S., Klaric L., Bretherick A.D., Rawlik K., Pasko D., Walker S., Parkinson N., Fourman M.H., Russell C.D., Furniss J., Richmond A., Gountouna E., Wrobel N., Harrison D., Wang B., Wu Y., Meynert A., Griffiths F., Oosthuyzen W., Kousathanas A., Moutsianas L., Yang Z., Zhai R., Zheng C., Grimes G., Beale R., Millar J., Shih B., Keating S., Zechner M., Haley C., Porteous D.J., Hayward C., Yang J., Knight J., Summers C., Shankar-Hari M., Klenerman P., Turtle L., Ho A., Moore S.C., Hinds C., Horby P., Nichol A., Maslove D., Ling L., McAuley D., Montgomery H., Walsh T., Pereira A.C., Renieri A., Gen O.I., Investigators I.C., Initiative C.-H.G., andMe I., Investigators B., Gen C.I., Shen X., Ponting C.P., Fawkes A., Tenesa A., Caulfield M., Scott R., Rowan K., Murphy L., Openshaw P.J.M., Semple M.G., Law A., Vitart V., Wilson J.F., Baillie J.K. Genetic mechanisms of critical illness in COVID-19. Nature. 2021;591:92–98. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-03065-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-03065-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33307546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stark G.R., Kerr I.M., Williams B.R., Silverman R.H., Schreiber R.D. How cells respond to interferons. Annu. Rev. Biochem. 1998;67:227–264. doi: 10.1146/annurev.biochem.67.1.227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.67.1.227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9759489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q., Bastard P., Liu Z., Le Pen J., Moncada-Velez M., Chen J., Ogishi M., Sabli I.K.D., Hodeib S., Korol C., Rosain J., Bilguvar K., Ye J., Bolze A., Bigio B., Yang R., Arias A.A., Zhou Q., Zhang Y., Onodi F., Korniotis S., Karpf L., Philippot Q., Chbihi M., Bonnet-Madin L., Dorgham K., Smith N., Schneider W.M., Razooky B.S., Hoffmann H.H., Michailidis E., Moens L., Han J.E., Lorenzo L., Bizien L., Meade P., Neehus A.L., Ugurbil A.C., Corneau A., Kerner G., Zhang P., Rapaport F., Seeleuthner Y., Manry J., Masson C., Schmitt Y., Schluter A., Le Voyer T., Khan T., Li J., Fellay J., Roussel L., Shahrooei M., Alosaimi M.F., Mansouri D., Al-Saud H., Al-Mulla F., Almourfi F., Al-Muhsen S.Z., Alsohime F., Al Turki S., Hasanato R., van de Beek D., Biondi A., Bettini L.R., D'Angio M., Bonfanti P., Imberti L., Sottini A., Paghera S., Quiros-Roldan E., Rossi C., Oler A.J., Tompkins M.F., Alba C., Vandernoot I., Goffard J.C., Smits G., Migeotte I., Haerynck F., Soler-Palacin P., Martin-Nalda A., Colobran R., Morange P.E., Keles S., Colkesen F., Ozcelik T., Yasar K.K., Senoglu S., Karabela S.N., Rodriguez-Gallego C., Novelli G., Hraiech S., Tandjaoui-Lambiotte Y., Duval X., Laouenan C., Clinicians C.-S., Clinicians C., Imagine C.G., French C.C.S.G., Co V.C.C., Amsterdam U.M.C.C.-B., Effort C.H.G., Group N.-U.T.C.I., Snow A.L., Dalgard C.L., Milner J.D., Vinh D.C., Mogensen T.H., Marr N., Spaan A.N., Boisson B., Boisson-Dupuis S., Bustamante J., Puel A., Ciancanelli M.J., Meyts I., Maniatis T., Soumelis V., Amara A., Nussenzweig M., Garcia-Sastre A., Krammer F., Pujol A., Duffy D., Lifton R.P., Zhang S.Y., Gorochov G., Beziat V., Jouanguy E., Sancho-Shimizu V., Rice C.M., Abel L., Notarangelo L.D., Cobat A., Su H.C., Casanova J.L. Inborn errors of type I IFN immunity in patients with life-threatening COVID-19. Science. 2020;370 doi: 10.1126/science.abd4570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abd4570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7857407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32972995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soltani-Zangbar M.S., Parhizkar F., Ghaedi E., Tarbiat A., Motavalli R., Alizadegan A., Aghebati-Maleki L., Rostamzadeh D., Yousefzadeh Y., Jadideslam G., Farid S.S., Roshangar L., Mahmoodpoor A., Heris J.A., Miahipour A., Yousefi M. A comprehensive evaluation of the immune system response and type-I Interferon signaling pathway in hospitalized COVID-19 patients. Cell Commun. Signal. 2022;20:106. doi: 10.1186/s12964-022-00903-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12964-022-00903-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9287826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35842705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . World Health Organization; 2020. Clinical Management of COVID-19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wulandari L., Hamidah B., Pakpahan C., Damayanti N.S., Kurniati N.D., Adiatmaja C.O., Wigianita M.R., Soedarsono, Husada D., Tinduh D., Prakoeswa C.R.S., Endaryanto A., Puspaningsih N.N.T., Mori Y., Lusida M.I., Shimizu K., Oceandy D. Initial study on TMPRSS2 p.Val160Met genetic variant in COVID-19 patients. Hum. Genom. 2021;15:29. doi: 10.1186/s40246-021-00330-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40246-021-00330-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8127183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34001248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X., Spandidos A., Wang H., Seed B. PrimerBank: a PCR primer database for quantitative gene expression analysis, 2012 update. Nucleic Acids Res. 2012;40:D1144–D1149. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkr1013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr1013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3245149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22086960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen C.L., Jensen J.L., Orntoft T.F. Normalization of real-time quantitative reverse transcription-PCR data: a model-based variance estimation approach to identify genes suited for normalization, applied to bladder and colon cancer data sets. Cancer Res. 2004;64:5245–5250. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-0496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-0496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15289330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Livak K.J., Schmittgen T.D. Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method. Methods. 2001;25:402–408. doi: 10.1006/meth.2001.1262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11846609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Treatment Guidelines Panel  . National Institute of Health; 2020. Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Treatment Guidelines.https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/ Available at:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34003615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoggins J.W., Rice C.M. Interferon-stimulated genes and their antiviral effector functions. Curr Opin Virol. 2011;1:519–525. doi: 10.1016/j.coviro.2011.10.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2011.10.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3274382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22328912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho S.D., Shin H., Kim S., Kim H.J. Insights on interferon-independent induction of interferon-stimulated genes shaping the lung's response in early SARS-CoV-2 infection. Heliyon. 2023;9 doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10731229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38125412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider W.M., Chevillotte M.D., Rice C.M. Interferon-stimulated genes: a complex web of host defenses. Annu. Rev. Immunol. 2014;32:513–545. doi: 10.1146/annurev-immunol-032713-120231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-032713-120231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4313732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24555472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marigorta U.M., Navarro A. High trans-ethnic replicability of GWAS results implies common causal variants. PLoS Genet. 2013;9 doi: 10.1371/journal.pgen.1003566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3681663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23785302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelhafez M., Nasereddin A., Shamma O.A., Abed R., Sinnokrot R., Marof O., Heif T., Erekat Z., Al-Jawabreh A., Ereqat S. Association of IFNAR2 rs2236757 and OAS3 rs10735079 polymorphisms with susceptibility to COVID-19 infection and severity in Palestine. Interdiscip Perspect Infect Dis. 2023;2023 doi: 10.1155/2023/9551163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2023/9551163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10517872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37745867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dieter C., de Almeida Brondani L., Lemos N.E., Schaeffer A.F., Zanotto C., Ramos D.T., Girardi E., Pellenz F.M., Camargo J.L., Moresco K.S., da Silva L.L., Aubin M.R., de Oliveira M.S., Rech T.H., Canani L.H., Gerchman F., Leitao C.B., Crispim D. Polymorphisms in ACE1, TMPRSS2, IFIH1, IFNAR2, and TYK2 genes are associated with worse clinical outcomes in COVID-19. Genes. 2022;14 doi: 10.3390/genes14010029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/genes14010029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9858252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36672770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fricke-Galindo I., Martinez-Morales A., Chavez-Galan L., Ocana-Guzman R., Buendia-Roldan I., Perez-Rubio G., Hernandez-Zenteno R.J., Veronica-Aguilar A., Alarcon-Dionet A., Aguilar-Duran H., Gutierrez-Perez I.A., Zaragoza-Garcia O., Alanis-Ponce J., Camarena A., Bautista-Becerril B., Nava-Quiroz K.J., Mejia M., Guzman-Guzman I.P., Falfan-Valencia R. IFNAR2 relevance in the clinical outcome of individuals with severe COVID-19. Front. Immunol. 2022;13 doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2022.949413.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.949413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9374460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35967349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skerenova M., Cibulka M., Dankova Z., Holubekova V., Kolkova Z., Lucansky V., Dvorska D., Kapinova A., Krivosova M., Petras M., Baranovicova E., Baranova I., Novakova E., Liptak P., Banovcin P., Bobcakova A., Rosolanka R., Janickova M., Stanclova A., Gaspar L., Caprnda M., Prosecky R., Labudova M., Gabbasov Z., Rodrigo L., Kruzliak P., Lasabova Z., Matakova T., Halasova E. Host genetic variants associated with COVID-19 reconsidered in a Slovak cohort. Adv. Med. Sci. 2024;69:198–207. doi: 10.1016/j.advms.2024.03.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.advms.2024.03.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38555007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nhung V.P., Ton N.D., Ngoc T.T.B., Thuong M.T.H., Hai N.T.T., Oanh K.T.P., Hien L.T.T., Thach P.N., Hai N.V., Ha N.H. Host genetic risk factors associated with COVID-19 susceptibility and severity in Vietnamese. Genes. 2022;13 doi: 10.3390/genes13101884.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/genes13101884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9601961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36292769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalkanen J., Khan S., Elima K., Huttunen T., Wang N., Hollmen M., Elo L.L., Jalkanen S. Polymorphism in interferon alpha/beta receptor contributes to glucocorticoid response and outcome of ARDS and COVID-19. Crit. Care. 2023;27:112. doi: 10.1186/s13054-023-04388-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13054-023-04388-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10018638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36927455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J.S., Park S., Jeong H.W., Ahn J.Y., Choi S.J., Lee H., Choi B., Nam S.K., Sa M., Kwon J.S., Jeong S.J., Lee H.K., Park S.H., Park S.H., Choi J.Y., Kim S.H., Jung I., Shin E.C. Immunophenotyping of COVID-19 and influenza highlights the role of type I interferons in development of severe COVID-19. Sci Immunol. 2020;5 doi: 10.1126/sciimmunol.abd1554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciimmunol.abd1554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7402635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32651212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilk A.J., Rustagi A., Zhao N.Q., Roque J., Martinez-Colon G.J., McKechnie J.L., Ivison G.T., Ranganath T., Vergara R., Hollis T., Simpson L.J., Grant P., Subramanian A., Rogers A.J., Blish C.A. A single-cell atlas of the peripheral immune response in patients with severe COVID-19. Nat. Med. 2020;26:1070–1076. doi: 10.1038/s41591-020-0944-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-0944-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7382903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32514174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Z., Ren L., Zhang L., Zhong J., Xiao Y., Jia Z., Guo L., Yang J., Wang C., Jiang S., Yang D., Zhang G., Li H., Chen F., Xu Y., Chen M., Gao Z., Yang J., Dong J., Liu B., Zhang X., Wang W., He K., Jin Q., Li M., Wang J. Heightened innate immune responses in the respiratory tract of COVID-19 patients. Cell Host Microbe. 2020;27:883–890 e882. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2020.04.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2020.04.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7196896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32407669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalil A.C., Patterson T.F., Mehta A.K., Tomashek K.M., Wolfe C.R., Ghazaryan V., Marconi V.C., Ruiz-Palacios G.M., Hsieh L., Kline S., Tapson V., Iovine N.M., Jain M.K., Sweeney D.A., El Sahly H.M., Branche A.R., Regalado Pineda J., Lye D.C., Sandkovsky U., Luetkemeyer A.F., Cohen S.H., Finberg R.W., Jackson P.E.H., Taiwo B., Paules C.I., Arguinchona H., Erdmann N., Ahuja N., Frank M., Oh M.D., Kim E.S., Tan S.Y., Mularski R.A., Nielsen H., Ponce P.O., Taylor B.S., Larson L., Rouphael N.G., Saklawi Y., Cantos V.D., Ko E.R., Engemann J.J., Amin A.N., Watanabe M., Billings J., Elie M.C., Davey R.T., Burgess T.H., Ferreira J., Green M., Makowski M., Cardoso A., de Bono S., Bonnett T., Proschan M., Deye G.A., Dempsey W., Nayak S.U., Dodd L.E., Beigel J.H., Members A.-S.G. Baricitinib plus remdesivir for hospitalized adults with covid-19. N. Engl. J. Med. 2021;384:795–807. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2031994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2031994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7745180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33306283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marconi V.C., Ramanan A.V., de Bono S., Kartman C.E., Krishnan V., Liao R., Piruzeli M.L.B., Goldman J.D., Alatorre-Alexander J., de Cassia Pellegrini R., Estrada V., Som M., Cardoso A., Chakladar S., Crowe B., Reis P., Zhang X., Adams D.H., Ely E.W., Group C.-B.S. Efficacy and safety of baricitinib for the treatment of hospitalised adults with COVID-19 (COV-BARRIER): a randomised, double-blind, parallel-group, placebo-controlled phase 3 trial. Lancet Respir. Med. 2021;9:1407–1418. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00331-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00331-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8409066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34480861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu W., Liu Y., Xia L., Li M., Song Z., Hu H., Yang Z., Wang L., Cheng X., Wang M., Jiang R., Liu L., Mao X., Chen J., Ling Y., Zhang L., Yan J., Shan F., Steinhart C., Zhang X., Zhu T., Xu J., Lu H. A clinical pilot study on the safety and efficacy of aerosol inhalation treatment of IFN-kappa plus TFF2 in patients with moderate COVID-19. EClinicalMedicine. 2020;25 doi: 10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7388798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32838238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Docherty A.B., Harrison E.M., Green C.A., Hardwick H.E., Pius R., Norman L., Holden K.A., Read J.M., Dondelinger F., Carson G., Merson L., Lee J., Plotkin D., Sigfrid L., Halpin S., Jackson C., Gamble C., Horby P.W., Nguyen-Van-Tam J.S., Ho A., Russell C.D., Dunning J., Openshaw P.J., Baillie J.K., Semple M.G., investigators I.C. Features of 20 133 UK patients in hospital with covid-19 using the ISARIC WHO Clinical Characterisation Protocol: prospective observational cohort study. BMJ. 2020;369 doi: 10.1136/bmj.m1985.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7243036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32444460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>