<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439628</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 Recovery and Cardiovascular Health: The Interplay Between Fetuin-A and Blood Pressure.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69905</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69905</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69905</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69905</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">COVID-19 has been shown to impair cardiovascular function, and further studies have proven that this effect can be long-term on several cardiovascular biomarkers. Fetuin-A, a multifunctional protein involved in calcification and inflammation, has emerged as an important biomarker in this process. This study investigates the relationship between recovery from COVID-19, cardiovascular health, and concentrations of fetuin-A in patients with high blood pressure.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Seventy-nine men and 36 women were admitted to the Nasiriyah Heart Center in Iraq between March and August 2023, with ages ranging from 5 to 93 years. Clinical data were collected on admission along with blood samples, and serum levels of fetuin-A were measured using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). The results were analyzed using Python libraries Pandas and SciPy to perform independent sample t-tests to determine mean levels of fetuin-A in various patient subgroups. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study showed that patients who had survived COVID-19 had significantly higher levels of fetuin-A compared to healthy controls, with a mean concentration of 103.64 mg/L versus 19.199 mg/L (p &lt; 0.001). Additionally, it was found that patients with high blood pressure had increased levels of fetuin-A compared to those without high blood pressure, with a mean concentration of 109.01 mg/L versus 95.88 mg/L (p = 0.025). These results suggest that COVID-19 may alter the usual relationship between blood pressure and cardiovascular biomarkers.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study emphasizes the complex interaction between recovery from COVID-19 and cardiovascular health, primarily through the levels of fetuin-A. The increase in fetuin-A among hypertensive patients suggests that COVID-19 may enhance cardiovascular risk, highlighting the need for stricter monitoring and tailored treatment strategies. Further studies are needed to elucidate the underlying mechanisms, which will help develop effective clinical guidelines for managing cardiovascular health in COVID-19 survivors.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Ramadan et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramadan</LastName><ForeName>Montather F</ForeName><Initials>MF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Dentistry, Al-Ayen University, Thi-Qar, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine Ibn El Jazzar, University of Sousse, Sousse, TUN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Assadi</LastName><ForeName>Iqbal J</ForeName><Initials>IJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, College of Science, Basra University, Basra, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hadj Slama</LastName><ForeName>Foued B</ForeName><Initials>FB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine Ibn El Jazzar, University of Sousse, Sousse, TUN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood pressure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cardiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cardiovascular health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fetuin-a</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ministry of Health/Thi-Qar Health Directorate issued approval 43/2023. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Coronavirus seasonality, respiratory infections and weather. Nichols GL, Gillingham EL, Macintyre HL, et al. BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21:1101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8547307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34702177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A close look at the biology of SARS-CoV-2, and the potential influence of weather conditions and seasons on COVID-19 case spread. Adedokun KA, Olarinmoye AO, Mustapha JO, Kamorudeen RT. Infect Dis Poverty. 2020;9:77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7316581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32586369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19: prevention and control measures in community. Güner R, Hasanoğlu I, Aktaş F. Turk J Med Sci. 2020;50:571–577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32293835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Movement control as an effective measure against Covid-19 spread in Malaysia: an overview. Tang KH. Z Gesundh Wiss. 2022;30:583–586.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7293423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32837842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathophysiological, immunological, and inflammatory features of long COVID. Bohmwald K, Diethelm-Varela B, Rodríguez-Guilarte L, Rivera T, Riedel CA, González PA, Kalergis AM. Front Immunol. 2024;15:1341600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10932978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38482000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The role of immune activation and antigen persistence in acute and long COVID. Opsteen S, Files JK, Fram T, Erdmann N. J Investig Med. 2023;71:545–562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9996119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36879504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>6-month consequences of COVID-19 in patients discharged from hospital: a cohort study. Huang C, Huang L, Wang Y, et al. Lancet. 2021;397:220–232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33428867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Insight into the long-term psychological impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. Adorjan K, Stubbe HC. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2023;273:287–288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10040902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36971863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exploring the role of CD74 and D-dopachrome tautomerase in COVID-19: insights from transcriptomic and serum analyses. Ralchev Ralchev N, Lyubenova Bradyanova S, Valerieva Doneva Y, et al. J Clin Med. 2023;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10419634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37568438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The immunology of long COVID. Altmann DM, Whettlock EM, Liu S, Arachchillage DJ, Boyton RJ. Nat Rev Immunol. 2023;23:618–634.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37433988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The structure, biosynthesis, and biological roles of Fetuin-A: a review. Abebe EC, Muche ZT, Mariam ABT, et al. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2022;10:945287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9340150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35923855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical implications of fetuin-A. Jirak P, Stechemesser L, Moré E, et al. Adv Clin Chem. 2019;89:79–130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30797472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Role of fetuin-A in atherosclerosis associated with diabetic patients. Singh M, Sharma PK, Garg VK, Mondal SC, Singh AK, Kumar N. J Pharm Pharmacol. 2012;64:1703–1708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23146032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathophysiological Implication of Fetuin-A glycoprotein in the development of metabolic disorders: a concise review. Bourebaba L, Marycz K. J Clin Med. 2019;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6947209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31766373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Insulin signaling and its application. Le TK, Dao XD, Nguyen DV, et al. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 2023;14:1226655.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10469844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37664840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fetuin-A (α2HS-glycoprotein) is a serum chemo-attractant that also promotes invasion of tumor cells through Matrigel. Nangami GN, Watson K, Parker-Johnson K, et al. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2013;438:660–665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3833465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23933250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fetuin-A and risk of diabetes-related vascular complications: a prospective study. Birukov A, Polemiti E, Jäger S, Stefan N, Schulze MB. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2022;21:6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8742328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34998417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The relationship between serum fetuin-A levels and cardiovascular risk factors in hemodialysis patients. El-Shishtawy S, Sherif N, Mosbah O, Metwaly A, Mamdouh S, Abd Elazim IM, Ibrahim A. https://mattollijournal.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/The-Relationship-between-serum.pdf Acta Biomedica. 2023;94:0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Facilitatory effects of fetuin-A on atherosclerosis. Naito C, Hashimoto M, Watanabe K, et al. Atherosclerosis. 2016;246:344–351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26828753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serum fetuin-A levels are associated with the presence and severity of coronary artery disease in patients with type 2 diabetes. Zhao ZW, Lin CG, Wu LZ, Luo YK, Fan L, Dong XF, Zheng H. Biomarkers. 2013;18:160–164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23410047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fetuin-A, type 2 diabetes, and risk of cardiovascular disease in older adults: the cardiovascular health study. Jensen MK, Bartz TM, Mukamal KJ, et al. Diabetes Care. 2013;36:1222–1228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3631840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23250801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fetuin-A deficiency but not pentraxin 3, FGF-21, or irisin, predisposes to more serious COVID-19 course. Kukla M, Menżyk T, Dembiński M, et al. Biomolecules. 2021;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8533535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34680053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of fetuin-A on predicting aortic arch calcification: secondary analysis of a community-based survey. Lin YH, Lin MH, Shi CS, et al. Front Cardiovasc Med. 2024;11:1415438.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11260669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39040998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tissue chaperoning-the expanded functions of fetuin-A beyond inhibition of systemic calcification. Rudloff S, Jahnen-Dechent W, Huynh-Do U. Pflugers Arch. 2022;474:949–962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8995415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35403906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 on the cardiovascular system: a review of available reports. Soumya RS, Unni TG, Raghu KG. Cardiovasc Drugs Ther. 2021;35:411–425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7487338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32926272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 on cardiovascular disease. Vosko I, Zirlik A, Bugger H. Viruses. 2023;15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9962056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36851722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long-term cardiovascular effects of COVID-19: emerging data relevant to the cardiovascular clinician. Tobler DL, Pruzansky AJ, Naderi S, Ambrosy AP, Slade JJ. Curr Atheroscler Rep. 2022;24:563–570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9065238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35507278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The serum protein alpha 2-Heremans-Schmid glycoprotein/fetuin-A is a systemically acting inhibitor of ectopic calcification. Schafer C, Heiss A, Schwarz A, et al. J Clin Invest. 2003;112:357–366.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC166290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12897203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fetuin-A and incident diabetes mellitus in older persons. Ix JH, Wassel CL, Kanaya AM, et al. JAMA. 2008;300:182–188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2779582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18612115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The association between fetuin-A and testosterone levels and markers of arterial stiffness in Saudi subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Ali TM, El Askary A. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2018;12:1045–1050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30168427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>