<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439617</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Emergency Department Visits Among Adolescents for Intentional Assault, Firearm, Poison, and Self-Harm Injuries Before and During the COVID-19 Pandemic in the United States.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69884</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69884</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69884</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69884</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Purpose This study aimed to examine changes in adolescent emergency department (ED) visits for firearm, poison, self-harm, and intentional assault injuries before and during the COVID-19 pandemic and to identify sociodemographic factors influencing these variations. Methods Utilizing the Nationwide Emergency Department Sample (NEDS), the study analyzes data for intentional self-harm, poison-related, intentional assaults, and firearm injuries from 2019 to 2021 in adolescents aged 10 to 18 years. A difference-in-differences analysis was conducted to investigate the potential impacts of COVID-19 on injury-associated ED visits, accounting for adjustments related to year, patient factors, and hospital characteristics. Results There was a substantial decline in the number of all ED visits from pre-COVID to during the COVID, but we observed increases in the volume of ED visits for firearm-related injuries (13,248 to 20,611; p-value &lt; 0.0001), poison-related injuries (147,812 to 213,753; p-Value &lt; 0.0001), and intentional self-harm-related injuries (153,297 to 229,591; p-value &lt; 0.0001). Conversely, intentional assault-related injuries decreased (167,614 to 154,940; p-value &lt; 0.0001). During the COVID-19 pandemic, ED visits for intentional self-harm increased by 15% (95% CI = 1.09-1.21), intentional assault by 6% (95% CI = 1.02-1.09), and poison-related injuries by 17% (95% CI = 1.11-1.21) compared to pre-pandemic levels. Racial disparities were observed, with Black individuals having lower odds of self-harm (aOR = 0.63) and poison-related visits (aOR = 0.69) but higher odds of assault-related visits (aOR = 1.40) compared to Whites. Hispanic individuals had fewer ED visits across all injury types, while Native Americans had higher odds across all injury types. Disparities between Black and White individuals in assault-related visits narrowed during the pandemic (aOR = 1.40 to 0.94), but disparities for Native Americans in assault-related injuries widened. Insurance status influenced ED visits, with Medicaid recipients having higher odds of self-harm (aOR = 1.11) but lower odds of assault visits (aOR = 0.82) compared to those with private insurance. Uninsured adolescents had lower odds of self-harm (aOR = 0.85) and poison-related visits (aOR = 0.95), but higher odds of assault-related visits (aOR = 1.17). Gender disparities persisted, with females having higher odds of self-harm (aOR = 1.66) and poison-related visits (aOR = 1.42) but lower odds of assault-related visits (aOR = 0.91) compared to males, with these disparities widening for self-harm and poison-related visits during the pandemic. Conclusions The findings underscore the heightened vulnerability of adolescents to certain injuries during the COVID-19 pandemic. Targeted interventions and policies to support mental health, firearm safety measures, and strategies to prevent poisoning are recommended. Addressing socioeconomic disparities is necessary to mitigate the impact of intentional injuries among racially/ethnically diverse adolescents during future pandemics.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Kapukotuwa et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kapukotuwa</LastName><ForeName>Sidath C</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Behavioral Health, School of Public Health, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, Las Vegas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grigsby</LastName><ForeName>Timothy J</ForeName><Initials>TJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Behavioral Health, School of Public Health, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, Las Vegas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Jay J</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Healthcare Administration and Policy, Center for Health Disparities Research, School of Public Health, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, Las Vegas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adolescent</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">assault</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">emergency service</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">firearms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hospital</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poisoning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">self-injurious behavior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">socioeconomic factors</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>I10_INTENT_SELF_HARM - intent of injury: intentional self-harm. 2015. https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_intent_self_harm/nedsnote.jsp https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_intent_self_harm/nedsnote.jsp</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association between unintentional injuries and self-harm among adolescent emergency department patients. Phillips D, Lidón-Moyano C, Cerdá M, Gruenewald P, Goldman-Mellor S. Gen Hosp Psychiatry. 2020;64:87–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7211429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32304935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suicide and suicidal behavior. Nock MK, Borges G, Bromet EJ, Cha CB, Kessler RC, Lee S. Epidemiol Rev. 2008;30:133–154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2576496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18653727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The major causes of death in children and adolescents in the United States. Cunningham RM, Walton MA, Carter PM. N Engl J Med. 2018;379:2468–2475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6637963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30575483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sociodemographic factors and outcomes by intent of firearm injury. Patel SJ, Badolato GM, Parikh K, Iqbal SF, Goyal MK. Pediatrics. 2021;147</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparison of cost and resource utilization between firearm injuries and motor vehicle collisions at pediatric hospitals. Fraser Doh K, Sheline E, Wetzel M, Simon HK, Morris CR. Acad Emerg Med. 2021;28:630–638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33599028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Violent injury as a predictor of subsequent assault-related emergency department visits among adolescents. Fornari MJ, Badolato GM, Rao K, Goyal MK, McCarter R, Donnelly KA. J Adolesc Health. 2023;72:972–976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36737352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Recent increases in injury mortality among children and adolescents aged 10-19 years in the United States: 1999-2016. Curtin SC, Heron M, Miniño AM, Warner M. https://europepmc.org/article/med/29874162 Natl Vital Stat Rep. 2018;67:1–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29874162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sex-and age-specific increases in suicide attempts by self-poisoning in the United States among youth and young adults from 2000 to 2018. Spiller HA, Ackerman JP, Spiller NE, Casavant MJ. J Pediatr. 2019;210:201–208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31054768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incidence of suicide, hospital-presenting non-fatal self-harm, and community-occurring non-fatal self-harm in adolescents in England (the iceberg model of self-harm): a retrospective study. Geulayov G, Casey D, McDonald KC, et al. Lancet Psychiatry. 2018;5:167–174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29246453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Youth Risk Behavior Surveillance - United States, 2017. Kann L, McManus T, Harris WA, et al. MMWR Surveill Summ. 2018;67:1–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6002027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29902162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National trends in the prevalence and treatment of depression in adolescents and young adults. Mojtabai R, Olfson M, Han B. Pediatrics. 2016;138</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5127071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27940701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of COVID-19 lockdown on child and adolescent mental health: systematic review. Panchal U, Salazar de Pablo G, Franco M, Moreno C, Parellada M, Arango C, Fusar-Poli P. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2023;32:1151–1177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8371430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34406494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on child and adolescent mental health policy and practice implementation. Palinkas LA, De Leon J, Salinas E, et al. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8467758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34574547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 and adolescent depression and suicide risk screening outcomes. Mayne SL, Hannan C, Davis M, et al. Pediatrics. 2021;148</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34140393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence and psychosocial risk factors of nonsuicidal self-injury among adolescents during the COVID-19 outbreak. Tang WC, Lin MP, You J, Wu JY, Chen KC. Curr Psychol. 2021:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8167308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34092987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disparities in COVID-19 outcomes by race, ethnicity, and socioeconomic status: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Magesh S, John D, Li WT, et al. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8586903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34762110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racial and ethnic health disparities related to COVID-19. Lopez L 3rd, Hart LH 3rd, Katz MH. JAMA. 2021;325:719–720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33480972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pediatric emergency department visits before and during the COVID-19 pandemic—United States, January 2019-January. Radhakrishnan L, Carey K, Hartnett KP, et al. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:313–318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35202351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Injury-related pediatric emergency department visits in the first year of COVID-19. Wells JM, Rodean J, Cook L, et al. Pediatrics. 2022;150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35836331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Injury-related emergency department visits during the COVID-19 pandemic. Law RK, Wolkin AF, Patel N, et al. Am J Prev Med. 2022;63:43–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8858709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35292198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Introduction to the HCUP nationwide emergency department sample (NEDS), 2020. 2022. https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/neds/NEDS_Introduction_2020.jsp https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/neds/NEDS_Introduction_2020.jsp</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trends and seasonality of emergency department visits and hospitalizations for suicidality among children and adolescents in the US from 2016 to 2021. Kim Y, Krause TM, Lane SD. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10357341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37466942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NEDS description of data elements. 2024. https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/neds/nedsdde.jsp https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/neds/nedsdde.jsp</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Changes in pediatric trauma during COVID-19 stay-at-home epoch at a tertiary pediatric hospital. Sanford EL, Zagory J, Blackwell JM, Szmuk P, Ryan M, Ambardekar A. J Pediatr Surg. 2021;56:918–922.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7817462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33516579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The DISTANCE study: determining the impact of social distancing on trauma epidemiology during the COVID-19 epidemic-an interrupted time-series analysis. Matthay ZA, Kornblith AE, Matthay EC, et al. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2021;90:700–707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7979514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33252457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emergency department visits for self-inflicted injuries in adolescents. Cutler GJ, Flood A, Dreyfus J, Ortega HW, Kharbanda AB. Pediatrics. 2015;136:28–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26077475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barriers to mental health help seeking at school for Asian-and Latinx-American adolescents. Wang C, Barlis J, Do KA, Chen J, Alami S. School Mental Health. 2020;12:182–194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Indian and Alaska Native mental health: diverse perspectives on enduring disparities. Gone JP, Trimble JE. Annu Rev Clin Psychol. 2012;8:131–160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22149479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asian American mental health: a call to action. Sue S, Yan Cheng JK, Saad CS, Chu JP. Am Psychol. 2012;67:532–544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23046304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racism as a determinant of health: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Paradies Y, Ben J, Denson N, et al. PLoS One. 2015;10:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4580597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26398658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Self-harm among youth during the first 28 months of the COVID-19 pandemic in Ontario, Canada: a population-based study. Mitchell RH, Toulany A, Chung H, et al. CMAJ. 2023;195:0–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10506509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37722745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A cross-sectional study investigating Canadian and Australian adolescents’ perceived experiences of COVID- 19: gender differences and mental health implications. Marie R, Journault AA, Cernik R, et al. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8998759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35410086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adolescent well-being amid the COVID-19 pandemic: are girls struggling more than boys? Halldorsdottir T, Thorisdottir IE, Meyers CC, et al. JCPP Adv. 2021;1:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8420409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34514467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elevated depressive symptoms and adolescent injury: examining associations by injury frequency, injury type, and gender. Asbridge M, Azagba S, Langille DB, Rasic D. BMC Public Health. 2014;14:190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3975970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24555802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trends in pediatric poisoning-related emergency department visits: 2001-2011. Kline JN, Badolato GM, Goyal MK. Pediatr Emerg Care. 2021;37:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30973499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 cases, hospitalizations, and deaths among American Indian or Alaska Native persons—Alaska, 2020-2021. Ward LA, Black KP, Britton CL, Tompkins ML, Provost EM. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:730–733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9169521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35653289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Partners in fighting coronavirus among Native Americans. 2020. https://publichealth.jhu.edu/2020/partners-in-fighting-coronavirus-among-native-americans https://publichealth.jhu.edu/2020/partners-in-fighting-coronavirus-among-native-americans</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Native American deaths from COVID-19 highest among racial groups. 2021. https://spia.princeton.edu/news/native-american-deaths-covid-19-highest-among-racial-groups https://spia.princeton.edu/news/native-american-deaths-covid-19-highest-among-racial-groups</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors associated with retaliatory attitudes among African American adolescents who have been assaulted. Copeland-Linder N, Jones VC, Haynie DL, Simons-Morton BG, Wright JL, Cheng TL. J Pediatr Psychol. 2007;32:760–770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17403911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Youth Violence Prevention. 2024. https://www.cdc.gov/youth-violence/risk-factors/?CDC_AAref_Val=https://www.cdc.gov/violenceprevention/youthviolence/riskprotectivefactors.html https://www.cdc.gov/youth-violence/risk-factors/?CDC_AAref_Val=https://www.cdc.gov/violenceprevention/youthviolence/riskprotectivefactors.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Black adolescents' perceptions of COVID-19: challenges, coping, and connection to family, religious, and school support. Parker JS, Haskins N, Lee A, Hailemeskel R, Adepoju OA. Sch Psychol. 2021;36:303–312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34591585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Structural and social determinants of inequities in violence risk: A review of indicators. Armstead TL, Wilkins N, Nation M. J Community Psychol. 2021;49:878–906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7278040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31421656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A comparison of female and male adolescent victims of violence seen in the emergency department. Ranney ML, Mello MJ. J Emerg Med. 2011;41:701–706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21536402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>‘Shadow pandemic’ of domestic violence. 2022. https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2022/06/shadow-pandemic-of-domestic-violence/ https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2022/06/shadow-pandemic-of-domestic-violence/</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34521630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staying home, staying safe? A short-term analysis of COVID-19 on Dallas domestic violence. Piquero AR, Riddell JR, Bishopp SA, Narvey C, Reid JA, Piquero NL. Am J Crim Justice. 2020;45:601–635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7293590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32837161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>I10_INJURY_POISON - mechanism of injury: poisoning, including drugs and nondrugs.  [
Apr;
2024 
]. 2015. https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_injury_poison/nedsnote.jsp https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_injury_poison/nedsnote.jsp</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I10_INTENT_ASSAULT - intent of injury: assault.  [
Apr;
2024 
]. 2015. https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_intent_assault/nedsnote.jsp https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_intent_assault/nedsnote.jsp</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I10_INJURY_FIREARM - mechanism of injury: firearm.  [
Apr;
2024 
]. 2015. https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_injury_firearm/nedsnote.jsp https://hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/vars/i10_injury_firearm/nedsnote.jsp</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The International classification of diseases, 10th revision, clinical modification (ICD- 10-CM): external cause-of-injury framework for categorizing mechanism and intent of injury. Hedegaard H, Johnson RL, Garnett MF, Thomas KE. https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/83789 Natl Health Stat Report. 2019;1:22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32510317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>