<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39432586</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-5964</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>42</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Medicine (Baltimore)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sense of coherence in Spanish-speaking countries during the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e39907</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e39907</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e39907</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MD.0000000000039907</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The aim of this study was to assess the sense of coherence (SOC) in the Spanish-speaking population during the 2019 coronavirus disease pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A systematic review was conducted in accordance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses guidelines in the PubMed, Scopus, and Web of Science electronic databases in August 2024. The methodological quality of the included studies was evaluated using the critical appraisal tools developed by the Joanna Briggs Institute.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 25 studies were included in the review, which demonstrated that high SOC is associated with improved coping styles, a reduced incidence of mental disorders, and greater resilience to traumatic events. The findings indicated that SOC acts as a crucial protective factor in diverse population groups, including health professionals, university students, and older adults, particularly during the 2019 coronavirus disease pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The study concludes that there are significant benefits for the mental and physical health of the population, regardless of cultural context, to be gained from strengthening the SOC. It is therefore essential that interventions which enhance the SOC are implemented in order to improve public health in times of crisis. Furthermore, it is crucial that SOC measurement instruments are validated in different cultural contexts in order to ensure the reliability and validity of the results obtained.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Escobar-Segovia</LastName><ForeName>Kenny</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Engineering in Earth Sciences FICT, ESPOL Polytechnic University ESPOL, Guayaquil, Ecuador.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Domínguez-Salas</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5666-1487</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departamento de Psicología Experimental, Universidad de Sevilla, Sevilla, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García-Iglesias</LastName><ForeName>Juan Jesús</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4074-0399</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Social Work, and Public Health, Faculty of Labour Sciences, University of Huelva, Huelva, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>López-López</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9818-6290</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research, Health and Podiatry Group, Department of Health Sciences, Faculty of Nursing and Podiatry, Industrial Campus of Ferrol, University of A Coruña, Ferrol, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Allande-Cussó</LastName><ForeName>Regina</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8325-0838</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, University of Seville, Seville, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Romero</LastName><ForeName>Adolfo</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing and Podiatry, Instituto de Investigación Biomédica de Málaga (IBIMA), University of Malaga, Malaga, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gómez-Salgado</LastName><ForeName>Juan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9053-7730</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Social Work, and Public Health, Faculty of Labour Sciences, University of Huelva, Huelva, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Safety and Health Postgraduate Programme, Universidad Espíritu Santo, Guayaquil, Ecuador.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Medicine (Baltimore)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985248R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0025-7974</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060685" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sense of Coherence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000223" MajorTopicYN="N">Adaptation, Psychological</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008603" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055500" MajorTopicYN="N">Resilience, Psychological</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39432586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000039907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00005792-202410180-00002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Antonovsky A. The structure and properties of the coherence sense. Soc Sci Med. 1993;36:725–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8480217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonovsky A. The salutogenic model as a theory to guide health promotion. Health Promot Int. 1996;11:11–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eriksson M, Lindström B. Antonovsky’s sense of coherence scale and the relation with health: a systematic review. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2006;60:376–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2563977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16614325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Super S, Wagemakers MAE, Picavet HSJ, Verkooijen KT, Koelen MA. Strengthening sense of coherence: opportunities for theory building in health promotion. Health Promot Int. 2016;31:869–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26208654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arias-Ulloa CA, Gómez-Salgado J, Escobar-Segovia K, García-Iglesias JJ, Fagundo-Rivera J, Ruiz-Frutos C. Psychological distress in healthcare workers during COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review. J Safety Res. 2023;87:297–312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38081703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adanaqué-Bravo I, Escobar-Segovia K, Gómez-Salgado J, García-Iglesias JJ, Fagundo-Rivera J, Ruiz-Frutos C. Relationship between psychological distress, burnout and work engagement in workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review. Int J Public Health. 2023;67:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9849247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36686389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez-Brescia M. Factors affecting Hispanics’ access to healthcare during the COVID-19 pandemic: an integrative review. Online J Issues Nurs. 2022;19:1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mana A, Bauer GF, Meier Magistretti C, et al. . Order out of chaos: Sense of coherence and the mediating role of coping resources in explaining mental health during COVID-19 in 7 countries. SSM Ment Health. 2021;1:100001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8470743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34604824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagi HM, Soleimanpour M, Abdollahi F, Soleimanpour H. Evaluation of clinical outcomes of patients with mild symptoms of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) discharged from the emergency department. PLoS One. 2021;16:e0258697.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8530279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34673806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikniaz Z, Faghih Dinevari M, Mokhtari L. Association of cardiovascular disease, respiratory diseases, and diabetes treatment with COVID-19 mortality in hospitalized patients. Int J Drug Res Clin. 2023;1:e21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Salgado J, Domínguez-Salas S, Romero-Martín M, Ortega-Moreno M, García-Iglesias JJ, Ruiz-Frutos C. Sense of coherence and psychological distress among healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic in Spain. Sustainability. 2020;12:6855.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz-Frutos C, Ortega-Moreno M, Allande-Cussó R, Ayuso-Murillo D, Domínguez-Salas S, Gómez-Salgado J. Sense of coherence, engagement, and work environment as precursors of psychological distress among non-health workers during the COVID-19 pandemic in Spain. Saf Sci. 2021;133:105033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7539829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33046949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da-Silva-Domingues H, del-Pino-Casado R, Palomino-Moral PA, López Martínez C, Moreno-Cámara S, Frías-Osuna A. Relationship between sense of coherence and health-related behaviours in adolescents and young adults: a systematic review. BMC Public Health. 2022;22:1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8915532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35272648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Betancurth Loaiza DP, Sánchez Palacio N, Vélez Álvarez C. The sense of coherence among university students: a resource for care in times of pandemic. Rev Cuid. 2022;13:1–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulcar V, Kreh A, Juen B, Siller H. The role of sense of coherence during the COVID-19 crisis: does it exercise a moderating or a mediating effect on university students’ wellbeing? Sage Open. 2023;13:215824402311601–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10018232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36942126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bueno-Pacheco A, Satorres E, Delhom I, Meléndez JC. Ego-integrity and its relationship with sense of coherence, satisfaction, self-efficacy, and depression. Curr Psychol. 2023;42:6439–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolff AC, Ratner PA. Stress, social support, and sense of coherence. West J Nurs Res. 1999;21:182–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11512176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernabé E, Tsakos G, Watt RG, et al. . Structure of the sense of coherence scale in a nationally representative sample: The Finnish Health 2000 survey. Qual Life Res. 2009;18:629–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19326255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sardu C, Mereu A, Sotgiu A, Andrissi L, Jacobson MK, Contu P. Antonovsky’s sense of coherence scale: cultural validation of Soc questionnaire and socio-demographic patterns in an Italian Population. Clin Pract Epidemiol Ment Health. 2012;8:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3282882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22371812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, et al. . The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;372:n71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munn Z, Stern C, Aromataris E, Lockwood C, Jordan Z. What kind of systematic review should I conduct? A proposed typology and guidance for systematic reviewers in the medical and health sciences. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2018;18:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5761190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29316881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan Z, Lockwood C, Munn Z, Aromataris E. The updated Joanna Briggs Institute Model of evidence-based healthcare. Int J Evid Based Healthc. 2019;17:58–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30256247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez Palacio N, Vélez Álvarez C, Betancurth Loaiza DP. Validación de contenido y adaptación de la escala de sentido de coherencia 29 para la población colombiana. Rev Fac Nac Salud Pública. 2021;39:e342827.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mafla AC, Herrera-López M, España-Fuelagan K, Ramírez-Solarte I, Pino CG, Schwendicke F. Psychometric properties of the soc-13 scale in colombian adults. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8700993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34948627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cadena Buitrago GP, Diaz Quijano DM. Sense of coherence in medical students at a Colombian university, observational study. Gac Med Caracas. 2022;130:339–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortiz-Granja D, Jayo-Suquillo L, Ramos-Galarza C. Estructura factorial del sentido de coherencia y su Relación de Apego. Aval Psicol. 2020;19:298–309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpio-Arias TV, Piedra-Andrade JS, Nicolalde-Cifuentes TM, Padilla-Samaniego MV, Tapia-Veloz EC, Vinueza-Veloz MF. Mobility restrictions and mental health among young adults during the COVID-19 pandemic in Ecuador. Gac Sanit. 2022;36:512–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8823959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35339310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Salgado J, Arias-Ulloa CA, Ortega-Moreno M, García-Iglesias JJ, Escobar-Segovia K, Ruiz-Frutos C. Sense of coherence in healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic in Ecuador: association with work engagement, work environment and psychological distress factors. Int J Public Health. 2022;67:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9760665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36545403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Salgado J, Delgado-García D, Ortega-Moreno M, et al. . Work engagement and sense of coherence as predictors of psychological distress during the first phase of the COVID-19 pandemic in Chile. Heliyon. 2024;10:e31327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11128991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38803934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaccarini C, Simkin H, Bachem R, Azzollini S. Validation and adaptation into Spanish of the revised sense of coherence scale (Soc-R): a scale associated with life satisfaction. J Consum Satisf Dissatisfaction Complain Behav. 2022;35:146–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espina-Romero LC, Guerrero-Alcedo JM, Tananta JM. Psychological factors associated with lifestyle in Venezuelan university students. Rev Cienc Soc. 2023;29:41–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Salgado J, Ortega-Moreno M, Soriano G, Fagundo-Rivera J, Allande-Cussó R, Ruiz-Frutos C. History of contact with the SARS-COV-2 virus and the sense of coherence in the development of psychological distress in the occupational health professionals in Spain. Sci Prog. 2021;104:1–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10454955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34137643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins J, Green S. Cochrane handbook for systematic reviews of interventions. The Cochrane Collaboration, editor. 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colomer-Pérez N, Paredes-Carbonell JJ, Sarabia-Cobo C, Useche SA, Gea-Caballero V. Self-care and sense of coherence: a salutogenic model for health and care in nursing education. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:9482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9368734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35954838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantas-Jiménez S, Reig-García G, Roqueta-Vall-Llosera M, et al. . Positive mental health and sense of coherence among emergency medical service professionals. Front Public Health. 2024;12:1344872.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10912187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38444442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domínguez‐Salas S, Gómez‐Salgado J, Guillén‐Gestoso C, Romero‐Martín M, Ortega‐Moreno M, Ruiz‐Frutos C. Health care workers’ protection and psychological safety during the COVID‐19 pandemic in Spain. J Nurs Manag. 2021;29:1924–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33844359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso MS, Lima MCP, Dias A, et al. . Psychological distress among Brazilian workers during the initial stage of the COVID-19 pandemic: a descriptive study. Front Public Heal. 2024;12:1283310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10910103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38439755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarro Prados AB, Jiménez García‐Tizón S, Meléndez JC. Sense of coherence and burnout in nursing home workers during the COVID‐19 pandemic in Spain. Heal Soc Care Community. 2022;30:244–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33894094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarabia-Cobo CM, Delgado Uria A, García Lecue M, Izaguirre Palazuelos E, Martínez Ruiz C, Fernández-Rodríguez A. Predictive model of preventive behaviors against COVID-19 in the older adult: the PREASOC-COVID-19 study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:11067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8583025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34769587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Salgado J, Domínguez-Salas S, Rodríguez-Domínguez C, Allande-Cussó R, Romero-Martín M, Ruiz-Frutos C. Gender perspective of psychological discomfort during COVID-19 confinement among Spanish adult population: a cross-sectional study. BMJ Open. 2021;11:e051572.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8688733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34930733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griesi JM, Bernardes JM, Alonso M, et al. . Risk perception of healthcare workers in the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic in Brazil. Heliyon. 2024;10:e25297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10861974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38352759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aguilar-Latorre A, Serrano-Ripoll MJ, Oliván-Blázquez B, Gervilla E, Navarro C. Associations between severity of depression, lifestyle patterns, and personal factors related to health behavior: secondary data analysis from a randomized controlled trial. Front Psychol. 2022;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8971623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35369144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reverté‐Villarroya S, Ortega L, Lavedán A, et al. . The influence of COVID‐19 on the mental health of final‐year nursing students: comparing the situation before and during the pandemic. Int J Ment Health Nurs. 2021;30:694–702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33393201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarro-Prados AB, Jiménez García-Tizón S, Meléndez JC, López J. Predictors of stress among nursing home staff during COVID-19 pandemic. Curr Psychol. 2024;43:23404–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serrano-Gómez D, Velasco-González V, Alconero-Camarero AR, et al. . COVID-19 infection among nursing students in Spain: the risk perception, perceived risk factors, coping style, preventive knowledge of the disease and sense of coherence as psychological predictor variables: a cross sectional survey. Nurs Rep. 2022;12:661–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9505543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36135985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>