<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39430966</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2694-250X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ACS measurement science au</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ACS Meas Sci Au</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>E.Co.Tech Breathalyzer: A Pilot Study of a Non-invasive COVID-19 Diagnostic Tool for Light and Non-smokers.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>496</StartPage><EndPage>503</EndPage><MedlinePgn>496-503</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acsmeasuresciau.4c00020</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Analysis of exhaled breath offers a noninvasive approach to understanding the metabolic state of the body. This study focuses on the efficacy of an innovative Electrochemical Hand-held Breathalyzer COVID-19 Sensing Technology (E.Co.Tech) for predicting COVID-19 infection, specifically in populations of never or former light smokers. The electrochemical nose technology used in this device aims to discriminate changes in exhaled nitric oxide levels, which are associated with COVID-19-linked respiratory inflammation. The methodology combines the device with a machine learning-based algorithm trained on a diverse data set of breath profiles from both infected and noninfected individuals. A cohort of 46 participants, consisting of never or former light smokers, was recruited. Each participant was tested using the E.Co.Tech prototype device and an iHealth COVID-19 antigen rapid test. The performance of the device was assessed by calculating sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, and negative predictive value (NPV). The results demonstrated high specificity (91.11%) and NPV (97.62%) for the device in this demographic group. This case study underscores the potential of E.Co.Tech as a valuable tool for point-of-care COVID-19 diagnosis, particularly in populations with unique smoking histories. The technology's high sensitivity and specificity, along with its rapid results, make it a promising candidate for deployment in resource-limited settings and situations where timely detection is crucial for effective public health management. Further large-scale clinical trials and real-world validations are necessary to establish the device's utility across diverse population groups.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Banga</LastName><ForeName>Ivneet</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Texas at Dallas, 800 W Campbell Road, Richardson, Texas 75080, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>France</LastName><ForeName>Kordel</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, University of Texas at Dallas, 800 W Campbell Road, Richardson, Texas 75080, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paul</LastName><ForeName>Anirban</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Texas at Dallas, 800 W Campbell Road, Richardson, Texas 75080, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prasad</LastName><ForeName>Shalini</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2404-3801</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Texas at Dallas, 800 W Campbell Road, Richardson, Texas 75080, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ACS Meas Sci Au</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918232604306676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2694-250X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39430966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11487758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsmeasuresciau.4c00020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Davis H. E.; McCorkell L.; Vogel J. M.; Topol E. J. Long COVID: Major Findings, Mechanisms and Recommendations. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2023, 21 (3), 133–146. 10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00846-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9839201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36639608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballering A. V.; van Zon S. K. R.; olde Hartman T. C.; Rosmalen J. G. M. Persistence of Somatic Symptoms after COVID-19 in the Netherlands: An Observational Cohort Study. Lancet 2022, 400 (10350), 452–461. 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01214-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01214-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9352274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35934007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bull-Otterson L.; Baca S.; Saydah S. H.; Boehmer T. K.; Adjei S.; Gray S.; Harris A. M. Post–COVID Conditions Among Adult COVID-19 Survivors Aged 18–64 and ≥ 65 Years — United States, March 2020–November 2021. Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep. 2022, 71, 713–717. 10.15585/mmwr.mm7121e1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7121e1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartung T. J.; Neumann C.; Bahmer T.; Chaplinskaya-Sobol I.; Endres M.; Geritz J.; Haeusler K. G.; Heuschmann P. U.; Hildesheim H.; Hinz A.; Hopff S.; Horn A.; Krawczak M.; Krist L.; Kudelka J.; Lieb W.; Maetzler C.; Mehnert-Theuerkauf A.; Montellano F. A.; Morbach C.; Schmidt S.; Schreiber S.; Steigerwald F.; Störk S.; Maetzler W.; Finke C. Fatigue and Cognitive Impairment after COVID-19: A Prospective Multicentre Study. eClinicalMedicine 2022, 53, 101651.10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101651.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9482331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36133318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adatia A.; Wahab M.; Shahid I.; Moinuddin A.; Killian K. J.; Satia I. Effects of Cigarette Smoke Exposure on Pulmonary Physiology, Muscle Strength and Exercise Capacity in a Retrospective Cohort with 30,000 Subjects. PLoS One 2021, 16 (6), e025095710.1371/journal.pone.0250957.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0250957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8224924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34166381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maestrelli P.; Saetta M.; Mapp C. E.; Fabbri L. M. Remodeling in Response to Infection and Injury. Airway Inflammation and Hypersecretion of Mucus in Smoking Subjects with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 2001, 164, S76–S80. 10.1164/ajrccm.164.supplement_2.2106067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.164.supplement_2.2106067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11734472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullen J. B.; Wright J. L.; Wiggs B. R.; Pare P. D.; Hogg J. C. Structure of Central Airways in Current Smokers and Ex-Smokers with and without Mucus Hypersecretion: Relationship to Lung Function. Thorax 1987, 42 (11), 843–848. 10.1136/thx.42.11.843.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/thx.42.11.843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC461007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3424265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isajevs S.; Taivans I.; Strazda G.; Kopeika U.; Bukovskis M.; Gordjusina V.; Kratovska A. Decreased FOXP3 Expression in Small Airways of Smokers with COPD. Eur. Respir. J. 2009, 33 (1), 61–67. 10.1183/09031936.00145307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/09031936.00145307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18684844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tantisuwat A.; Thaveeratitham P. Effects of Smoking on Chest Expansion, Lung Function, and Respiratory Muscle Strength of Youths. J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 2014, 26 (2), 167–170. 10.1589/jpts.26.167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1589/jpts.26.167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3944281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24648624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Westen-Lagerweij N. A.; Meijer E.; Meeuwsen E. G.; Chavannes N. H.; Willemsen M. C.; Croes E. A. Are Smokers Protected against SARS-CoV-2 Infection (COVID-19)? The Origins of the Myth. npj Prim. Care Respir. Med. 2021, 31 (1), 10.10.1038/s41533-021-00223-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41533-021-00223-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7910565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33637750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korzeniowska A.; Ręka G.; Bilska M.; Piecewicz-Szczęsna H. The Smoker’s Paradox during the COVID-19 Pandemic? The Influence of Smoking and Vaping on the Incidence and Course of SARS-CoV-2 Virus Infection as Well as Possibility of Using Nicotine in the Treatment of COVID-19 – Review of the Literature. Przegl. Epidemiol. 2021, 75 (1), 27–44. 10.32394/pe.75.03.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.32394/pe.75.03</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34328284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Usman M. S.; Siddiqi T. J.; Khan M. S.; Patel U. K.; Shahid I.; Ahmed J.; Kalra A.; Michos E. D. Is There a Smoker’s Paradox in COVID-19?. BMJ Evid. Based Med. 2021, 26 (6), 279–284. 10.1136/bmjebm-2020-111492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjebm-2020-111492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32788164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boots A. W.; Bos L. D.; van der Schee M. P.; van Schooten F.-J.; Sterk P. J. Exhaled Molecular Fingerprinting in Diagnosis and Monitoring: Validating Volatile Promises. Trends Mol. Med. 2015, 21 (10), 633–644. 10.1016/j.molmed.2015.08.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.molmed.2015.08.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26432020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia Z.; Patra A.; Kutty V. K.; Venkatesan T. Critical Review of Volatile Organic Compound Analysis in Breath and In Vitro Cell Culture for Detection of Lung Cancer. Metabolites 2019, 9 (3), 52.10.3390/metabo9030052.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/metabo9030052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6468373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30889835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banga I.; Paul A.; Poudyal D. C.; Muthukumar S.; Prasad S. Recent Advances in Gas Detection Methodologies with a Special Focus on Environmental Sensing and Health Monitoring Applications–A Critical Review. ACS Sens. 2023, 8 (9), 3307–3319. 10.1021/acssensors.3c00959.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssensors.3c00959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37540230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor D. R.; Pijnenburg M. W.; Smith A. D.; De Jongste J. C. Exhaled Nitric Oxide Measurements: Clinical Application and Interpretation. Thorax 2006, 61 (9), 817–827. 10.1136/thx.2005.056093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/thx.2005.056093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2117092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16936238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Austin V.; Crack P. J.; Bozinovski S.; Miller A. A.; Vlahos R. COPD and Stroke: Are Systemic Inflammation and Oxidative Stress the Missing Links?. Clin. Sci. 2016, 130 (13), 1039–1050. 10.1042/CS20160043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/CS20160043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4876483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27215677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banga I.; Paul A.; Sardesai A. U.; Muthukumar S.; Prasad S. ZEUS (ZIF-Based Electrochemical Ultrasensitive Screening) Device for Isopentane Analytics with Focus on Lung Cancer Diagnosis. RSC Adv. 2021, 11 (33), 20519–20528. 10.1039/D1RA03093K.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1RA03093K</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9033977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35479925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banga I.; Paul A.; Churcher N. K. M.; Kumar R. M.; Muthukumar S.; Prasad S. Passive Breathomics for Ultrasensitive Characterization of Acute and Chronic Respiratory Diseases Using Electrochemical Transduction Mechanism. TrAC, Trends Anal. Chem. 2024, 170, 117455.10.1016/j.trac.2023.117455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trac.2023.117455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banga I.; Paul A.; Muthukumar S.; Prasad S. HELP (Hydrogen Peroxide Electrochemical Profiling): A Novel Biosensor for Measuring Hydrogen Peroxide Levels Expressed in Breath for Monitoring Airway Inflammation Using Electrochemical Methods. Biosens. Bioelectron.: X 2022, 10, 100139.10.1016/j.biosx.2022.100139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biosx.2022.100139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Violi F.; Oliva A.; Cangemi R.; Ceccarelli G.; Pignatelli P.; Carnevale R.; Cammisotto V.; Lichtner M.; Alessandri F.; De Angelis M.; Miele M. C.; D’Ettorre G.; Ruberto F.; Venditti M.; Pugliese F.; Mastroianni C. M. Nox2 Activation in Covid-19. Redox Biol. 2020, 36, 101655.10.1016/j.redox.2020.101655.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.redox.2020.101655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7381406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32738789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loffredo L.; Carnevale R.; Cangemi R.; Angelico F.; Augelletti T.; Di Santo S.; Calabrese C. M.; Della Volpe L.; Pignatelli P.; Perri L.; Basili S.; Violi F. NOX2 Up-Regulation Is Associated with Artery Dysfunction in Patients with Peripheral Artery Disease. Int. J. Cardiol. 2013, 165 (1), 184–192. 10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.01.069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.01.069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22336250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks C. R.; Brogan S.-B. M.; van Dalen C. J.; Lampshire P. K.; Crane J.; Douwes J. Measurement of Exhaled Nitric Oxide in a General Population Sample: A Comparison of the Medisoft HypAir FE NO and Aerocrine NIOX Analyzers. J. Asthma 2011, 48 (4), 324–328. 10.3109/02770903.2011.560322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/02770903.2011.560322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21385111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson J. K.; Bollinger M. J.; Birks J. W. Luminol/H2O2 Chemiluminescence Detector for the Analysis of Nitric Oxide in Exhaled Breath. Anal. Chem. 1999, 71 (22), 5131–5136. 10.1021/ac990646d.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac990646d</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10575964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horváth I.; Barnes P. J.; Loukides S.; Sterk P. J.; Högman M.; Olin A.-C.; Amann A.; Antus B.; Baraldi E.; Bikov A.; Boots A. W.; Bos L. D.; Brinkman P.; Bucca C.; Carpagnano G. E.; Corradi M.; Cristescu S.; de Jongste J. C.; Dinh-Xuan A.-T.; Dompeling E.; Fens N.; Fowler S.; Hohlfeld J. M.; Holz O.; Jöbsis Q.; Van De Kant K.; Knobel H. H.; Kostikas K.; Lehtimäki L.; Lundberg J. O.; Montuschi P.; Van Muylem A.; Pennazza G.; Reinhold P.; Ricciardolo F. L. M.; Rosias P.; Santonico M.; van der Schee M. P.; van Schooten F.-J.; Spanevello A.; Tonia T.; Vink T. J. A European Respiratory Society Technical Standard: Exhaled Biomarkers in Lung Disease. Eur. Respir. J. 2017, 49 (4), 1600965.10.1183/13993003.00965-2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/13993003.00965-2016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28446552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cristescu S. M.; Mandon J.; Harren F. J. M.; Meriläinen P.; Högman M. Methods of NO Detection in Exhaled Breath. J. Breath Res. 2013, 7 (1), 017104.10.1088/1752-7155/7/1/017104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1752-7155/7/1/017104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23445766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim W.; Carr L.; Cordell R.; Wilde M. J.; Salman D.; Monks P. S.; Thomas P.; Brightling C. E.; Siddiqui S.; Greening N. J. Breathomics for the Clinician: The Use of Volatile Organic Compounds in Respiratory Diseases. Thorax 2021, 76 (5), 514–521. 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-215667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-215667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7611078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33414240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carraro S.; Rezzi S.; Reniero F.; Héberger K.; Giordano G.; Zanconato S.; Guillou C.; Baraldi E. Metabolomics Applied to Exhaled Breath Condensate in Childhood Asthma. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 2007, 175 (10), 986–990. 10.1164/rccm.200606-769OC.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.200606-769OC</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17303796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banga I.; Paul A.; France K.; Micklich B.; Cardwell B.; Micklich C.; Prasad S. E.Co.Tech-electrochemical handheld breathalyzer COVID sensing technology. Sci. Rep. 2022, 12 (1), 4370.10.1038/s41598-022-08321-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-08321-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8919908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35288614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farquhar A. K.; Henshaw G. S.; Williams D. E. Understanding and Correcting Unwanted Influences on the Signal from Electrochemical Gas Sensors. ACS Sens. 2021, 6 (3), 1295–1304. 10.1021/acssensors.0c02589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssensors.0c02589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33544583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hitchman M. L.; Saffell J. R. Considerations of Thermodynamics and Kinetics for the Effects of Relative Humidity on the Electrolyte in Electrochemical Toxic Gas Sensors. ACS Sens. 2021, 6 (11), 3985–3993. 10.1021/acssensors.1c01339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssensors.1c01339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34672617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karvonen T.; Lehtimäki L. Effect of Exhalation Flow Rates and Level of Nitric Oxide Output on Accuracy of Linear Approximation of Pulmonary Nitric Oxide Dynamics. J. Breath Res. 2021, 15 (3), 036003.10.1088/1752-7163/abf3ab.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1752-7163/abf3ab</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33784646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hotelling H. Analysis of a Complex of Statistical Variables into Principal Components. J. Educ. Psychol. 1933, 24, 498–520. 10.1037/h0070888.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/h0070888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karl Pearson F. R. S. LIII. On Lines and Planes of Closest Fit to Systems of Points in Space. Philos. Mag Ser. 1901, 2, 559–572. 10.1080/14786440109462720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14786440109462720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karhunen K.; Selin I.. On Linear Methods in Probability Theory; RAND Corporation: Santa Monica, CA: Santa Monica, CA, 1960.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Maaten L.; Hinton G. Visualizing Data Using T-SNE. J. Mach. Learn. Res. 2008, 9, 2579–2605.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>