<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39431248</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2094-9278</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>58</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Acta medica Philippina</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acta Med Philipp</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Understanding Perceptions and Experiences on Acceptability of Oral Ivermectin, Topical Permethrin, and their Combination in the Treatment of Adult Filipino Patients with Scabies: A Multiple Case Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>24</StartPage><EndPage>41</EndPage><MedlinePgn>24-41</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.47895/amp.v58i17.9703</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Oral ivermectin, a broad-spectrum anti-parasitic drug, alone or in combination with permethrin, may be a cheaper and more convenient alternative drug to topical permethrin alone in the treatment of classic scabies. There are no previous studies on the treatment acceptability of the three interventions among individual patients with scabies in the Philippines.The purpose of this study was to understand the experiences and perceptions on treatment acceptability for oral ivermectin, topical permethrin or combination treatment among patients with scabies using the multiple-case study approach.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We conducted a qualitative multiple case study among adult Filipino patients with classic scabies who were prescribed oral ivermectin, topical permethrin or its combination at a government tertiary hospital dermatology outpatient clinic from December 2022 to September 2023. Semi-structured interviews were used as the primary source of data and analyzed together with chart reviews, Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) scores, and clinical images. Interviews were transcribed, coded, and triangulated with other secondary data. A three-person research team employed a reflexive and iterative process of familiarization, coding, and thematic analysis using a modified Theoretical Framework of Acceptability (TFA) to generate case descriptions, within-case analyses, and cross-case syntheses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The acceptability of scabies treatments (permethrin, ivermectin, and combination therapy) was generally positive. Permethrin, used in three patient cases, was generally perceived as effective but itch relief varied. The burden of whole-body application of permethrin was context-dependent, influenced by living arrangements and family support. Perceived affordability of permethrin was linked to socioeconomic status. Ivermectin, used by one patient case, was perceived as highly effective with no side effects. Its single dose use did not interfere with patient routine. Combination therapy was also considered effective but potential antagonistic effects and the cost of adding permethrin made it less preferred. Reluctance in taking oral pills was noted. All patients valued medical advice and deferred to their physicians for treatment decisions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION AND RECOMMENDATIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">All three treatment options were considered effective and safe. Patients generally preferred permethrin over oral ivermectin due to its topical nature and perceived lower side effects. However, affordability and logistical challenges, especially for large households and low-income families, were noted with permethrin. Oral ivermectin elicited hesitation due to its controversial role in COVID-19 and veterinary use. Concerns about added costs and potential antagonism in combination therapy were raised. Despite these considerations, patients ultimately relied on physicians for treatment decisions. This study underscores the importance of understanding patient perspectives, experiences, and the patient-physician relationship in choosing scabies interventions. Addressing patient concerns, providing education, and ensuring ease of use and affordability can enhance treatment acceptability and adherence for better outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Acta Medica Philippina.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Genuino</LastName><ForeName>Rowena F</ForeName><Initials>RF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anatomy, College of Medicine, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Batac</LastName><ForeName>Ma Christina Filomena R</ForeName><Initials>MCFR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, College of Medicine and Philippine General Hospital, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mariano</LastName><ForeName>Alena Marie B</ForeName><Initials>AMB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, East Avenue Medical Center, Quezon City, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Buenaflor</LastName><ForeName>Ma Carla E</ForeName><Initials>MCE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, College of Medicine and Philippine General Hospital, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arevalo</LastName><ForeName>Ma Veronica Pia N</ForeName><Initials>MVPN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, College of Medicine and Philippine General Hospital, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Capule</LastName><ForeName>Francis R</ForeName><Initials>FR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical, Social and Administrative Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garcia</LastName><ForeName>Fernando B</ForeName><Initials>FB</Initials><Suffix>Jr</Suffix><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Policy and Administration, College of Public Health, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ladia</LastName><ForeName>Mary Ann J</ForeName><Initials>MAJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Clinical Epidemiology, National Institutes of Health, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Santos</LastName><ForeName>Malaya P</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Sciences, Mapua University, Makati, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yabes</LastName><ForeName>Ailyn M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, College of Medicine, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cagayan</LastName><ForeName>Maria Stephanie Fay S</ForeName><Initials>MSFS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, College of Medicine, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, College of Medicine and Philippine General Hospital, University of the Philippines Manila, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Philippines</Country><MedlineTA>Acta Med Philipp</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0312677</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0001-6071</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acceptability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">case study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ivermectin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">permethrin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">qualitative research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">scabies</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>All authors declared no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39431248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11484571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47895/amp.v58i17.9703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">AMP-58-17-9703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Sekhon M, Cartwright M, Francis JJ. Acceptability of healthcare interventions: an overview of reviews and development of a theoretical framework. BMC Health Serv Res. 2017. Jan 26;17(1):88. doi: 10.1186/s12913-017-2031-8. PMID: 28126032 PMCID: .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-017-2031-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5267473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28126032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>La Vincente S, Kearns T, Connors C, Cameron S, Carapetis J, Andrews R. Community management of endemic scabies in remote Aboriginal communities of Northern Australia: low treatment uptake and high ongoing acquisition. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2009. May 26;3(5):e444. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0000444. PMID: 19478832; PMCID: .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2680947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19478832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amgarth-Duff I, Hendrickx D, Bowen A, Carapetis J, Chibawe R, Samson M, et al. . Talking skin: attitudes and practices around skin infections, treatment options, and their clinical management in a remote region in Western Australia. Rural Remote Health. 2019. Sep;19(3):5227. doi: 10.22605/RRH5227. PMID: 31540550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22605/RRH5227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31540550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien BC, Harris IB, Beckman TJ, Reed DA, Cook DA. Standards for reporting qualitative research: a synthesis of recommendations. Acad Med. 2014. Sep;89(9):1245-51. doi: 10.1097/ACM.0000000000000388. PMID: 24979285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24979285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardiff University . Dermatology Life Quality Index [Internet]. Cardiff University. 2019. 
[cited 2023 Nov 16]. Available from: https://www.cardiff.ac.uk/medicine/resources/quality-of-life-questionnaires/dermatology-life-quality-index</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krentel A, Basker N, de Rochars MB, Bogus J, Dilliott D, Direny AN, et al. . A multicenter, community-based, mixed methods assessment of the acceptability of a triple drug regimen for elimination of lymphatic filariasis. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2021. Mar 3;15(3):e0009002. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0009002. PMID: 33657090; PMCID: .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0009002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7928496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33657090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watkins JA, Ross JDC, Thandi S, Brittain C, Kai J, Griffiths F. Acceptability of and treatment preferences for recurrent bacterial vaginosis—Topical lactic acid gel or oral metronidazole antibiotic: qualitative findings from the VITA trial. PLoS One. 2019. Nov 15;14(11):e0224964. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0224964. PMID: 31730666; PMCID: .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0224964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6857901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31730666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekhon M, van der Straten A, MTN-041/MAMMA Study Team. Pregnant and breastfeeding women’s prospective acceptability of two biomedical HIV prevention approaches in Sub Saharan Africa: A multisite qualitative analysis using the Theoretical Framework of Acceptability. PLoS One. 2021. Nov 16;16(11):e0259779. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0259779. PMID: 34784355; PMCID: .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0259779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8594804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34784355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statista . Philippines: OOP payment share to current health expenditure 2021 [Internet]. [cited 2023 Aug 2]. Available from: https://www.statista.com/statistics/1173970/philippines-share-of-out-of-pocket-health-expenditure-on-the-current-health-expenditure/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statista . Household OOP payment share to current health expenditure Philippines 2014-2022 [Internet]. Statista. 2022. 
[cited 2023 Nov 27]. Available from: https://www.statista.com/statistics/1173970/philippines-share-of-out-of-pocket-health-expenditure-on-the-current-health-expenditure/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Labor and Employment – National Wages and Productivity Commission . Latest Wage Orders Issued by the Regional Boards (2018-2022 Issuances) (As of 08 June 2022) [Internet]. 2022. 
[cited 2023 Oct 23]. Available from: https://nwpc.dole.gov.ph/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Latest-Wage-Orders-Matrix-as-of-08-June-2022.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lasco G, Yu VG, David CC. The lived realities of health financing: A qualitative exploration of catastrophic health expenditure in the Philippines. Acta Med Philipp. 2022. Jun 29;56(11):5-15. doi: 10.47895/amp.vi0.2389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47895/amp.vi0.2389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philippine Health Insurance Corporation . ACR Policy No. 2. Implementing Guidelines on Medical and Procedure Case Rates (PhilHealth Circular 0035-2013 [Internet]. 2013. 
[cited 2023 Oct 23]. Available from: https://www.philhealth.gov.ph/circulars/2013/circ35_2013.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvarez-Moreno C, Cassell JA, Donkor CM, Head MG, Middleton J, Pomat W, et al. . Long-term consequences of the misuse of ivermectin data. Lancet Infect Dis. 2021. Dec;21(12):1624–6. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00630-7. PMID: 34672962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00630-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34672962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Republic of the Philippines, Food and Drug Administration . FDA Advisory No.2021-0526 || Public Health Warning on the Purchase and Use of Ivermectin Veterinary Products for COVID-19 [Internet]. 2021. 
[cited 2023 Dec 16]. Available from: https://www.fda.gov.ph/fda-advisory-no-2021-0526-public-health-warning-on-the-purchase-and-use-of-ivermectin-veterinary-products-for-covid-19/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philippine Dermatological Society . PDS Advisory on the Use of Ivermectin for COVID-19 [Internet]. 2021. 
[cited 2022 Jun 15]. Available from: www.pds.org.ph</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philippine 
COVID-19 Living CPG Reviewers of the UP-NIH ICE and Consensus, Panel Representatives of FDA-DOH, PMA, PCP, PAFP, POGS, PCEM, PSGIM, PCCP, PSPHP and PSMID. Statement on the Use of Ivermectin As Treatment for COVID-19 [Internet]. 2021. 
Mar
[cited 2023 Aug 25]. Available from: https://www.psmid.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Ivermectin-1.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazcano-Ponce E, Angeles-Llerenas A, Rodríguez-Valentín R, Salvador-Carulla L, Domínguez-Esponda R, Astudillo-García CI, et al. . Communication patterns in the doctor–patient relationship: evaluating determinants associated with low paternalism in Mexico. BMC Med Ethics. 2020. Dec 10;21(1):125. doi: 10.1186/s12910-020-00566-3. PMID: 33302932; PMCID: .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12910-020-00566-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7731770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33302932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawton BL, Mahoney M, Pelliccio L. A comparative study of the utility of new media technologies and power distance in doctor-patient communication in the Philippines and the United States. Journal of Intercultural Communication [Internet]. 2015. 
Jul
1
[cited 2023 Oct 23];(38). Available from: https://digitalcommons.wcupa.edu/comstudies_facpub/6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simbulan NP, Medical Action Group Inc. Perceptions, attitudes and practices of Metro Manila urban poor residents on patients’ rights. Acta Med Philipp. 2008. Dec 2;42(1):45–55. doi: 10.47895/amp.v42i1.2380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47895/amp.v42i1.2380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendoza MJ, Sacdalan DB, Palileo-Villanueva LA. Shared decision making at the General Internal Medicine Outpatient Clinic of the Philippine General Hospital: Patient’s perspective. J Participat Med. 2016. Nov 3;8:e14.r</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>