<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39433985</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2393</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC pregnancy and childbirth</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mothers' and caregivers' experiences of COVID-19 restrictions during postpartum hospitalisation: a cross-sectional survey in France.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>686</StartPage><MedlinePgn>686</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">686</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12884-024-06854-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 highlighting the importance of social distancing guidelines. Following a series of lockdowns and the widespread vaccination of the European population, many countries began to lift these restrictions. During this period, while some parents yearned for emotional support and family presence, others found that the solitude facilitated by the restrictions was beneficial for bonding and breastfeeding. In France, postnatal stays are generally longer than in other countries, and the limited availability of home-based follow-up care, combined with pandemic isolation measures, further complicated perspectives on visitation restrictions. Therefore, the objective of this study was to assess the satisfaction of mothers and caregivers regarding these visit restrictions in French maternity settings during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We conducted two multicentre descriptives surveys across five French maternity wards (three in Paris and two in Lyon) from June 1st to July 15th, 2021. Participants included mothers, selected based on criteria such as French-speaking, at-term birth (≥ 37 weeks), and hospitalisation with their newborn, as well as caregivers working in the postpartum units. Satisfaction with visitation restrictions was assessed using a four-point Likert scale, which was then dichotomised into "mostly satisfied" versus "mostly dissatisfied" for the analysis. Multivariable logistic regression models were used to identify factors associated with satisfaction.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We analysed complete responses from 430 of the 2,142 mothers (20.1%) and 221 of the 385 caregivers (57.4%) who participated during the study period. The majority of mothers (68.8%, n = 296/430) and caregivers (90.5%, n = 200/221) declare themselves satisfied with the policy of restricting visits to maternity wards. The main source of mother's satisfaction came from a quieter stay, but they regretted the absence of their other children.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Maternity visit restriction policies were largely supported by mothers and caregivers, especially when partners and siblings were allowed. Revisiting these policies, along with the postpartum stay length, may improve care, though further evaluation in non-pandemic settings is needed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Louis</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Obstetric Department, Foch Hospital, Suresnes, F-92150, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rousseau</LastName><ForeName>Anne</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Midwifery, Paris-Saclay University, Montigny-le-Bretonneux, F-78180, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Poissy-Saint Germain Hospital, Poissy, F-78300, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CESP, Epidémiologie Clinique, Versailles Saint Quentin University, Montigny-le-Bretonneux, F-78180, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mercier</LastName><ForeName>Louise</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Midwifery, Paris-Saclay University, Montigny-le-Bretonneux, F-78180, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Poissy-Saint Germain Hospital, Poissy, F-78300, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chamly</LastName><ForeName>Mireille</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospices Civils de Lyon, Lyon, F-69000, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gaucher</LastName><ForeName>Laurent</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospices Civils de Lyon, Lyon, F-69000, France. laurent.gaucher@hesge.ch.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research on Healthcare Performance (RESHAPE), INSERM U1290, Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1, Lyon, F-69008, France. laurent.gaucher@hesge.ch.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Geneva School of Health Sciences, HES-SO University of Applied Sciences and Arts, 47, av. de Champel Western Switzerland, Genève, GE-1206, Switzerland. laurent.gaucher@hesge.ch.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016448">Multicenter Study</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100967799</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2393</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005602" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">France</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009035" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mothers</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017028" MajorTopicYN="Y">Caregivers</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011247" MajorTopicYN="N">Pregnancy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006760" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hospitalization</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D049590" MajorTopicYN="Y">Postpartum Period</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011181" MajorTopicYN="N">Postnatal Care</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017060" MajorTopicYN="N">Patient Satisfaction</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health Service Research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Midwifery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and questionnaires, hospitals isolation.</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39433985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12884-024-06854-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12884-024-06854-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). WHO Director-General’s opening remarks at the media briefing on COVID-19. January. 2022;30:2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiersinga WJ, Rhodes A, Cheng AC, Peacock SJ, Prescott HC, Pathophysiology. Transmission, diagnosis, and treatment of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19): a review. JAMA. 2020;324:782.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32648899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statement by Mr Edouard Philippe. Prime Minister, on the new measures to deal with the COVID-19 epidemic caused by the SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus (closure of all places open to the public that are not essential to the life of the country, restaurants, cafés, cinemas… Paris, 14 March 2020. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sen S, Karaca-Mandic P, Georgiou A. Association of Stay-at-home orders with COVID-19 hospitalizations in 4 States. JAMA. 2020;323:2522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7254451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32459287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidelines for non. -pharmaceutical interventions to reduce the impact of COVID-19 in the EU/EEA and the UK. 24 September 2020. Volume ECDC. Stockholm; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreland A, Herlihy C, Tynan MA, Sunshine G, McCord RF, Hilton C, et al. Timing of state and territorial COVID-19 stay-at-home orders and changes in Population Movement — United States, March 1–May 31, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020;69:1198–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7470456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32881851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han E, Tan MMJ, Turk E, Sridhar D, Leung GM, Shibuya K, et al. Lessons learnt from easing COVID-19 restrictions: an analysis of countries and regions in Asia Pacific and Europe. Lancet. 2020;396:1525–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7515628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32979936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hale T, Angrist N, Goldszmidt R, Kira B, Petherick A, Phillips T, et al. A global panel database of pandemic policies (Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker). Nat Hum Behav. 2021;5:529–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33686204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Décret n°. 2021 – 699 du 1er juin 2021 prescrivant les mesures générales nécessaires à la gestion de la sortie de crise sanitaire. 2021. https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/eli/decret/2021/6/1/2021-699/jo/texte</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rousseau A, Gaucher L, Gautier S, Mahrez I, Baumann S. How midwives implemented teleconsultations during the COVID-19 health crisis: a mixed-methods study. BMJ Open. 2022;12:e057292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8977454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35365534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann S, Gaucher L, Mahrez I, Gautier S, Rousseau A. Experiences of teleconsultation by French liberal midwives during the COVID-19 crisis. Sante Publique. 2022;34:821–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37019795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. Health at a Glance 2019: OECD Indicators. Paris: Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development. 2019. 10.1787/888934070320</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sortie de maternité. après accouchement: conditions et organisation Du Retour à Domicile Des mères et de leurs nouveau-nés. La Revue Sage-Femme. 2014;13:84–98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley T, Nethery E, Chung EK, Souter V. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on perinatal care and outcomes in the United States: an interrupted time series analysis. Birth. 2022;49:298–309.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34957595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermann A, Deligiannidis KM, Bergink V, Monk C, Fitelson EM, Robakis TK, et al. Response to SARS-Covid-19-related visitor restrictions on labor and delivery wards in New York City. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2020;23:793–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7156902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32296947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lalor JG, Sheaf G, Mulligan A, Ohaja M, Clive A, Murphy-Tighe S, et al. Parental experiences with changes in maternity care during the Covid-19 pandemic: a mixed-studies systematic review. Women Birth. 2023;36:e203–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9364727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35973917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson L, De Pascalis L, Harrold JA, Fallon V, Silverio SA. Postpartum women’s psychological experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic: a modified recurrent cross-sectional thematic analysis. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2021;21:625.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8445650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34530772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panda S, O’Malley D, Barry P, Vallejo N, Smith V. Women’s views and experiences of maternity care during COVID-19 in Ireland: a qualitative descriptive study. Midwifery. 2021;103:103092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8582075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34325384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosn W. Indicateurs écologiques synthétiques du Niveau socio-économique pour la recherche en Santé. Cépi-Dc Inserm; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tennant R, Hiller L, Fishwick R, Platt S, Joseph S, Weich S, et al. The Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being scale (WEMWBS): development and UK validation. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2007;5:63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2222612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18042300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maslach C, Jackson SE. The measurement of experienced burnout. J Organiz Behav. 1981;2:99–113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison E, Drake T, Pius R, finalfit. Quickly Create Elegant Regression Results Tables and Plots when Modelling. 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Textor J, van der Zander B, Gilthorpe MS, Liśkiewicz M, Ellison GT. Robust causal inference using directed acyclic graphs: the R package ‘dagitty’. Int J Epidemiol. 2016;45:1887–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28089956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R: The R Project for Statistical Computing. https://www.r-project.org/. Accessed 6 Aug 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Rieben MA, Boyd L, Sheen J. Care in the time of COVID: an interpretative phenomenological analysis of the impact of COVID-19 control measures on post-partum mothers’ experiences of pregnancy, birth and the health system. Front Psychol. 2022;13:986472.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9537098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36211889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostacoli L, Cosma S, Bevilacqua F, Berchialla P, Bovetti M, Carosso AR, et al. Psychosocial factors associated with postpartum psychological distress during the Covid-19 pandemic: a cross-sectional study. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2020;20:703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7671935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33208115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rousseau A, Dubel-Jam M, Schantz C, Gaucher L. Barrier measures implemented in French maternity hospitals during the COVID-19 pandemic: a cross-sectional survey. Midwifery. 2023;118:103600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9839455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36680960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vivanti AJ, Deruelle P, Picone O, Guillaume S, Roze J-C, Mulin B, et al. Post-natal follow-up for women and neonates during the COVID-19 pandemic: French National Authority for Health recommendations. J Gynecol Obstet Hum Reprod. 2020;49:101805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7212945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32407898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaucher L, Barasinski C, Dupont C, Razurel C, Pichon S, Leavy E, et al. Pregnancy, Mental Well-Being and Lockdown: a Nationwide Online Survey in France. Healthcare. 2022;10:1855.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9602192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36292301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Zhang C, Liu H, Duan C, Li C, Fan J, et al. Perinatal depressive and anxiety symptoms of pregnant women during the coronavirus disease 2019 outbreak in China. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2020;223:e2401–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7211756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smythe KL, Petersen I, Schartau P. Prevalence of Perinatal Depression and anxiety in both parents: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5:e2218969.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9233234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35749112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dennis C-L, Falah-Hassani K, Shiri R. Prevalence of antenatal and postnatal anxiety: systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Psychiatry. 2017;210:315–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28302701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray CL, Lelong N, Cinelli H, Blondel B. Collaborators - members of the ENP2021 Study Group. Results of the 2021 French National Perinatal Survey and trends in perinatal health in metropolitan France since 1995. J Gynecol Obstet Hum Reprod. 2022;:102509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36410664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Öhrn U, Parment H, Hildingsson I. Quality improvement in postnatal care: findings from two cohorts of women in Sweden. Eur J Midwifery. 2020;4:45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7839109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33537646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones E, Stewart F, Taylor B, Davis PG, Brown SJ. Early postnatal discharge from hospital for healthy mothers and term infants. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2021;2021:CD002958.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8185906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34100558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>