<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39438066</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1943-3654</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Respiratory care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Respir Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Long-Term Disabilities in ICU Survivors of COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">respcare.12032</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4187/respcare.12032</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">COVID-19 is associated with prolonged disability, particularly after critical illness. This study aimed to assess and compare disability post-hospital discharge of subjects who were invasively ventilated versus those who were not, following ICU admission due to COVID-19. This study also explored variables associated with long-term disability.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this prospective cohort study, subjects with COVID-19 who received invasive ventilation, noninvasive ventilation, or high-flow nasal cannula during ICU stay were assessed with the World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule (WHODAS) 2.0 at 3 and 6 months post-hospital discharge. Data were analyzed collectively and stratified as subjects with and without invasive mechanical ventilation. Analysis of variance and multiple regression analyses were applied.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The subjects (<i>N =</i> 43) were mainly male, middle age, and overweight. Subjects who were invasively ventilated (<i>n =</i> 21) had decreased physical function compared to those who were not during hospital assessments. From 3-6 months after discharge, all WHODAS domains and the overall score decreased in both groups (<i>P</i> &lt; .001), indicating disability recovery. The participation domain, which assesses joining in society, was the only domain that remained worse in the ventilation group compared to the no ventilation group (<i>P</i> = .01). No interaction was found between time and the study groups, suggesting that the recovery trajectory was similar. At 6 months, considering the entire cohort, 70% and 56% had no disability in self-care and getting along domains, respectively, while 42% exhibited moderate to severe disability in the participation domain. According to the overall WHODAS score, 86% of subjects still had some level of disability at 6 months. In multivariate analyses, the overall WHODAS score along with the household and participation domains showed significant positive correlations, indicating higher disability, with corticosteroid use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Disability persisted at 6 month post-hospital discharge for ICU survivors of COVID-19, regardless of the need for invasive mechanical ventilation. Participation was the only domain that showed higher disability among those who received invasive ventilation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 by Daedalus Enterprises.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soares da Silva</LastName><ForeName>Karina Ramiceli</ForeName><Initials>KR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Drs Soares da Silva, Prazeres, and Volpe are affiliated with Departamento de Ciências do Movimento Humano, Universidade Federal de São Paulo, Santos, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prazeres</LastName><ForeName>Dimas Cavalheiro</ForeName><Initials>DC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Drs Soares da Silva, Prazeres, and Volpe are affiliated with Departamento de Ciências do Movimento Humano, Universidade Federal de São Paulo, Santos, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gaspar</LastName><ForeName>Silvia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dr Gaspar is affiliated with Serviço de Fisioterapia, Instituto do Coração, Hospital das Clínicas, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Souza</LastName><ForeName>Felipe Granado</ForeName><Initials>FG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dr de Souza is affiliated with Universidade Federal de São Paulo, Santos, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chiavegato</LastName><ForeName>Luciana D</ForeName><Initials>LD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dr Chiavegato is affiliated with Disciplina de Pneumologia, Universidade Federal de São Paulo, São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil; and Programa de Mestrado e Doutorado, Universidade Cidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leite</LastName><ForeName>Camila Ferreira</ForeName><Initials>CF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Drs Leite and Castro are affiliated with Programa de Pós-graduação em Fisioterapia e Funcionalidade, Universidade Federal do Ceará, Fortaleza, Ceará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Castro</LastName><ForeName>Shamyr Sulyvan</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Drs Leite and Castro are affiliated with Programa de Pós-graduação em Fisioterapia e Funcionalidade, Universidade Federal do Ceará, Fortaleza, Ceará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carvalho</LastName><ForeName>Carlos Rr</ForeName><Initials>CR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dr Carvalho is affiliated with Divisão de Pneumologia, Instituto do Coração, Hospital das Clínicas, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Volpe</LastName><ForeName>Marcia S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Drs Soares da Silva, Prazeres, and Volpe are affiliated with Departamento de Ciências do Movimento Humano, Universidade Federal de São Paulo, Santos, São Paulo, Brazil. marcia.volpe@unifesp.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Respir Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7510357</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0020-1324</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intensive care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">long-term outcomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mechanical ventilation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">post–COVID-19 condition</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39438066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4187/respcare.12032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">respcare.12032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>