<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439599</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical Presentation and Outcomes of Myocarditis Among the COVID-19 Pediatric Population: A Review of 100 Cases.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69885</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69885</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69885</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69885</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">COVID-19 has been associated with myocarditis in the pediatric population, leading to severe cardiac complications.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To determine the clinical presentations and outcomes of myocarditis among the COVID-19-positive pediatric population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This retrospective cross-sectional study included 100 cases from the Saidu Group of Teaching Hospitals, Swat. Inclusion criteria involved children of both genders, confirmed COVID-19 by PCR, and a myocarditis diagnosis. Exclusion criteria were other comorbid conditions, incomplete records, and age over five years. Data included age, gender, weight, clinical features, cardiac enzyme levels, ejection fraction, PCR results, immunoglobulin treatment, outcomes, and hospital stay duration. Statistical analysis was performed in SPSS employing descriptive statistics, chi-square tests, and Fisher's exact tests.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The mean age was 24.72±18.67 months, with 67 males and 33 females. Irritability was noted in 18 children, cyanosis in 27, and cough in 74. Tachycardia was observed in 91 children. Elevated cardiac enzymes and positive Troponin-I levels were found in 91 and 84 children, respectively. The mean ejection fraction was 36.29±9.12%. The average hospital stay was 7.11±2.49 days. Among 100 children, 26 died while 74 recovered. Immunoglobulin administration showed no significant difference between the expired and improved groups (p=0.6). Longer hospital stays were associated with mortality (p=0.002). Troponin-I levels were significantly higher in the expired group (p=0.01).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Key factors associated with poor outcomes include low ejection fraction, elevated cardiac enzymes, positive Troponin-I levels, and shorter hospital stays.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Ahmed et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Ashfaq</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Department, Saidu Teaching Hospital, Saidu Sharif, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iqbal</LastName><ForeName>Asad</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Department, Saidu Teaching Hospital, Saidu Sharif, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdullah</LastName><ForeName>Amir</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Department, Saidu Teaching Hospital, Saidu Sharif, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Irshad</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Department, Lady Reading Hospital Peshawar, Peshawar, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Muhmamad Qasim</ForeName><Initials>MQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Department, Bacha Khan Medical College, Mardan, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Department, Mardan Medical Complex, Mardan, PAK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cardiac enzymes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ejection fraction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hospital stay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunoglobulin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">myocarditis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">outcomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pediatric clinical presentations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">troponin-i</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ethical Review Board of Saidu Group of Teaching Hospitals issued approval 119/ERB. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Myocarditis in children and adolescents: a literature review. Tomik A, Chanas A, Werner B. Folia Cardiol. 2020;15:293–302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incidence, risk factors, natural history, and hypothesised mechanisms of myocarditis and pericarditis following covid-19 vaccination: living evidence syntheses and review. Pillay J, Gaudet L, Wingert A, Bialy L, Mackie AS, Paterson DI, Hartling L. BMJ. 2022;378:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9277081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35830976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>One-year risk of myocarditis after COVID-19 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Zuin M, Rigatelli G, Bilato C, Porcari A, Merlo M, Roncon L, Sinagra G. Can J Cardiol. 2023;39:839–844.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9743686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36521730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical presentation and early predictors for poor outcomes in pediatric myocarditis: a retrospective study. Rodriguez-Gonzalez M, Sanchez-Codez MI, Lubian-Gutierrez M, Castellano-Martinez A. World J Clin Cases. 2019;7:548–561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6406197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30863755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myocarditis in the pediatric and adolescent population. Rowlett JD. https://www.proquest.com/openview/27cfd7b903088fe8c969d9bacadd54e5/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=2034852 J Altern Med Res. 2021;13:31–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardiac function in relation to functional status and fatigue in patients with post-COVID syndrome. Baum P, Do L, Deterding L, et al.  https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-022-24038-3. Sci Rep. 2022;12:19575.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9664421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36380000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myocarditis: Etiology, pathogenesis, and their implications in clinical practice. Brociek E, Tymińska A, Giordani AS, Caforio AL, Wojnicz R, Grabowski M, Ozierański K. Biology (Basel) 2023;12:874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10295542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37372158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 and myocarditis: review of clinical presentations, pathogenesis and management. Lovell JP, Čiháková D, Gilotra NA. Heart Int. 2022;16:20–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9524641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36275349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covid-19 heart lesions in children: clinical, diagnostic and immunological changes. Vasichkina E, Alekseeva D, Kudryavtsev I, et al. Int J Mol Sci. 2023;24:1147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9866514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36674665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Features of myocarditis: Morphological differential diagnosis in post-Covid-19 children. Karev V, Starshinova AY, Glushkova A, Kudlay D, Starshinova A. Diagnostics (Basel) 2023;13:2499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10417761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37568863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myocarditis mortality with and without COVID-19: insights from a national registry. Bemtgen X, Kaier K, Rilinger J, et al. Clin Res Cardiol. 2024;113:216–222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9789728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36565377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The wide spectrum of COVID-19 clinical presentation in children. Nathan N, Prevost B, Sileo C, et al. J Clin Med. 2020;9:2950.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7564665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32932612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardiac manifestations in COVID-19 patients: a focus on the pediatric population. Abi Nassif T, Fakhri G, Younis NK, Zareef R, Al Amin F, Bitar F, Arabi M. Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol. 2021;2021:5518979.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8287458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34326911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sex-related factors in cardiovascular complications associated to COVID-19. Megiorni F, Pontecorvi P, Gerini G, Anastasiadou E, Marchese C, Ceccarelli S. Biomolecules. 2021;12:21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8773922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35053169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronavirus-induced myocarditis: a meta-summary of cases. Ho JS, Sia CH, Chan MY, Lin W, Wong RC. Heart Lung. 2020;49:681–685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32861884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence, characteristics, and outcomes of COVID-19-associated acute myocarditis. Ammirati E, Lupi L, Palazzini M, et al. Circulation. 2022;145:1123–1139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8989611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35404682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 myocarditis and prospective heart failure burden. Shchendrygina A, Nagel E, Puntmann VO, Valbuena-Lopez S. Expert Rev Cardiovasc Ther. 2021;19:5–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33119418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Systematic review of COVID-19 related myocarditis: insights on management and outcome. Sawalha K, Abozenah M, Kadado AJ, et al. Cardiovasc Revasc Med. 2021;23:107–113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7434380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32847728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 associated myocarditis clinical outcomes among hospitalized patients in the United States: a propensity matched analysis of National Inpatient Sample. Davis MG, Bobba A, Chourasia P, et al. Viruses. 2022;14:2791.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9785561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myocardial inflammation and dysfunction in COVID-19-associated myocardial injury. Weckbach LT, Curta A, Bieber S, et al. Circultion Cardiovas Imag. 2021;14:12220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33463366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Predictive value of cardiac markers in the prognosis of COVID-19 in children. Güllü UU, Güngör Ş, İpek S, Yurttutan S, Dilber C. Am J Emerg Med. 2021;48:307–311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8257396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34246919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The evaluation of troponin I levels and myocarditis in children with COVID-19: a pediatric single-center experience. Guner Ozenen G, Akaslan Kara A, Kiymet E, et al. Pediatr Cardiol. 2023;44:873–881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9548337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36210385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>