<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39430690</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2976-8357</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>18</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jan-Dec</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Substance use : research and treatment</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Subst Use</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Recovery From Substance Use Disorder: Findings From a Qualitative Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>29768357241287405</StartPage><MedlinePgn>29768357241287405</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">29768357241287405</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/29768357241287405</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study considers how the COVID-19 pandemic impacted individuals recovering from a substance use disorder (SUD).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Fifty individuals recovering from SUD in Vermont, a rural New England state (U.S.), were recruited for an interview from 12-step recovery meetings (Alcoholics Anonymous, Narcotics Anonymous) as well as via word-of-mouth. Interviews were transcribed and coded, and qualitative analyses were performed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Many of the participants who were in recovery prior to the pandemic starting remained substance-free and in recovery throughout the pandemic period. Some individuals used substances during the pandemic period, although not typically in the context of a relapse caused by negative emotions (eg, distress over a loved one contracting COVID-19). The majority of those individuals indicated that the risk of catching COVID-19 did not alter their substance use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Many individuals already in SUD recovery before COVID-19 remained in recovery despite the challenges of pandemic era. The role of peer support in recovering individuals managing negative emotions caused by COVID-19 is considered.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hassett-Walker</LastName><ForeName>Connie</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7518-8840</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Norwich University, Northfield, VT, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P20 GM103449</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Subst Use</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918769579606676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2976-8357</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Substance use disorder</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">recovery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">relapse</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author declared the following potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: Dr. Connie Hassett-Walker, the study PI and author of the paper, has no conflicts of interest in conducting this study or writing this manuscript.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39430690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11489921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/29768357241287405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_29768357241287405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bridgland VME, Moeck EK, Green DM, et al.. Why the COVID-19 pandemic is a traumatic stressor. PLoS One. 2021;16:e0240146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7799777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33428630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phelps C, Sperry LL. Children and the COVID-19 pandemic. J Psychol Trauma. 2020;12:S73-S75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32525366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez-Gomez M, Giorgi G, Finstad GL, et al.. COVID-19 pandemic as a traumatic event and its associations with fear and mental health: a cognitive-activation approach. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:7422.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8303753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34299873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benfante A, Di Tella M, Romeo A, Castelli L. Traumatic stress in healthcare workers during COVID-19 pandemic: a review of the immediate impact. Front Psychol. 2020;11:2816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7645025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33192854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horesh D, Brown AD. Traumatic stress in the age of COVID-19: a call to close critical gaps and adapt to new realities. J Psychol Trauma. 2020;12:331-335.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32271070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassett-Walker C. Recovering individuals’ feelings about addict and alcoholic as stigmatized terms: implications for treatment. Subst Abuse. 2023;17:1-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10687927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38033430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Hamel L, Kearney A, Kirzinger A, et al.. KFF Health Tracking Poll. July
27
2020. Accessed June 20, 2024. https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/report/kff-health-tracking-poll-july-2020/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chacon NC, Walia N, Allen A, et al.. Substance use during COVID-19 pandemic: impact on the underserved communities. Discoveries. 2021;9:e141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8896880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35261922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali F, Russell C, Nafeh F, et al.. Changes in substance supply and use characteristics among people who use drugs (PWUD) during the COVID-19 global pandemic: a national qualitative assessment in Canada. Int J Drug Policy. 2021;93:103237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9759688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33893026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dror AA, Eisenbach N, Taiber S, et al.. Vaccine hesitancy: the next challenge in the fight against COVID-19. Eur J Epidemiol. 2020;35:775-779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8851308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32785815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saloner B, Krawczyk N, Solomon K, et al.. Experiences with substance use disorder treatment during the COVID-19 pandemic: findings from a multistate survey. Int J Drug Policy. 2022;101:1-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8602971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34871945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avena NM, Simkus J, Lewandowski A, Gold MS, Potenza MN. Substance use disorders and behavioral addictions during the COVID-19 pandemic and COVID-19-related restrictions. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:1-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8085389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33935838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hulsey J, Mellis A, Kelly B. COVID-19 pandemic impact on patients, families and individuals in recovery from substance use disorders. Addict Policy Forum. 2020;May.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinclair DL, Vanderplasschen W, Savahl S, et al.. Substitute addictions in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. J Behav Addict. 2020;9:1098-1102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8969734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33216014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiappini S, Guirguis A, John A, Corkery JM, Schifano F. COVID-19: the hidden impact on mental health and drug addiction. Front Psychol. 2020;11:767.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7403495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32848937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinotti G, Alessi MC, Di Natale C, et al.. Psychopathological burden and quality of life in substance users during the COVID-19 lockdown period in Italy. Front Psychol. 2020;11:896.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7497905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33101086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volkow ND. Collision of the COVID-19 and addiction epidemics. Ann Intern Med. 2020;173:61-62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7138334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32240293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mead S, Hilton D, Curtis L. Peer support: a theoretical perspective. Psychiatr Rehabil J. 2001;25:134-141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11769979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker G, Bryant W. Peer support in adult mental health services: a metasynthesis of qualitative findings. Psychiatr Rehabil J. 2013;36:28-34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23477647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith E, Carter M, Walklet E, Hazell P. Investigating the experiences of individuals in recovery from problem substance use and their perceptions of the COVID-19 pandemic. Drugs Alcohol Today. 2022;22:17-27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ornell F, Moura HF, Scherer JN, et al.. The COVID-19 pandemic and its impact on substance use: implications for prevention and treatment. Psychiatry Res. 2020;289:1-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7219362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32405115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jemberie WB, Stewart Williams J, Eriksson M, et al.. Substance use disorders and COVID-19: multi-faceted problems which require multi-pronged solutions. Front Psychiatry. 2020;11:714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7396653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32848907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez MN, Colgan DD, Leyde S, et al.. Trauma exposure across the lifespan among individuals engaged in treatment with medication for opioid use disorder: differences by gender, PTSD status, and chronic pain. Subst Abuse Treat Prev Policy. 2024;19:25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11067259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38702783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farley M, Golding JM, Young G, Mulligan M, Minkoff JR. Trauma history and relapse probability among patients seeking substance abuse treatment. J Subst Abuse Treat. 2004;27:161-167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15450649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gielen N, Krumeich A, Tekelenburg M, Nederkoorn C, Havermans RC. How patients perceive the relationship between trauma, substance abuse, craving, and relapse: a qualitative study. J Subst Use. 2016;21:466-470.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michaels TI, Stone E, Singal S, et al.. Brain reward circuitry: the overlapping neurobiology of trauma and substance use disorders. World J Psychiatry. 2021;11:222-231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8209534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34168969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassett-Walker C. The longitudinal impact of arrest, criminal conviction, and incarceration on smoking classes. Tob Use Insights. 2022;15:1-12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9134438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35634273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hennink MM, Kaiser BN, Marconi VC. Code saturation versus meaning saturation: how many interviews are enough? Qual Health Res. 2017;27:591-608.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9359070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27670770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Rural Health Resources for States from the Rural Health Information Hub. 2023-23. Accessed July 3, 2023. https://www.ruralhealthinfo.org/states</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Briere J, Elliott DM, Harris K, Cotman A. Trauma symptom inventory. J Interpers Violence. 1995;10:387-401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
 https://traumareliefunlimited.com/TRU-Method-Effectiveness.html
. </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raskind IG, Shelton RC, Comeau DL, et al.. A review of qualitative data analysis practices in health education and health behavior research. Health Educ Behav. 2019;46:32-39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6386595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30227078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pope C, Ziebland S, Mays N. Qualitative research in health care: analysing qualitative data. BMJ. 2000;320:114-116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1117368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10625273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miles MB, Huberman AM. Qualitative Data Analysis: An Expanded Sourcebook. Sage; 1994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elo S, Kyngäs H. The qualitative content analysis process. J Adv Nurs. 2008;62:107-115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18352969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller JC. 12-Step treatment for alcohol and substance abuse revisited: best available evidence suggests lack of effectiveness or harm. Int J Ment Health Addict. 2008;6:568-576.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bøg M, Filges T, Brännström L, Jørgensen AM, Fredrikksson MK. 12-step programs for reducing illicit drug use. Campbell Syst Rev. 2017;13:1-49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>

 https://nida.nih.gov/nidamed-medical-health-professionals/health-professions-education/words-matter-terms-to-use-avoid-when-talking-about-addiction
. 
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiorentine R. After drug treatment: are 12-step programs effective in maintaining abstinence? Amer J Drug Alc Abuse. 1999;25:93-116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10078980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>