<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39432177</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2110-5820</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Annals of intensive care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ann Intensive Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Immunological sub-phenotypes and response to convalescent plasma in COVID-19 induced ARDS: a secondary analysis of the CONFIDENT trial.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>160</StartPage><MedlinePgn>160</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">160</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s13613-024-01392-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Convalescent plasma (CP) reduced the mortality in COVID-19 induced ARDS (C-ARDS) patients treated in the CONFIDENT trial. As patients are immunologically heterogeneous, we hypothesized that clusters may differ in their treatment responses to CP.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We measured 20 cytokines, chemokines and cell adhesion markers using a multiplex technique at the time of inclusion in the CONFIDENT trial in patients of centers having accepted to participate in this secondary study. We performed descriptive statistics, unsupervised hierarchical cluster analysis, and examined the association between the clusters and CP effect on day-28 mortality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Of the 475 patients included in CONFIDENT, 391 (82%) were sampled, and 196/391 (50.1%) had been assigned to CP. We identified four sub-phenotypes representing 89 (22.8%), 178 (45.5%), 38 (9.7%), and 86 (22.0%) patients. The most contributing biomarkers in the principal component analysis were IL-1β, IL-12p70, IL-6, IFN-α, IL-17A, IFN-γ, IL-13, TFN-α, total IgG, and CXCL10. Sub-phenotype-1 displayed a lower immune response, sub-phenotype-2 a higher adaptive response, sub-phenotype-3 the highest innate antiviral, pro and anti-inflammatory response, and adhesion molecule activation, and sub-phenotype-4 a higher pro and anti-inflammatory response, migration protein and adhesion molecule activation. Sub-phenotype-2 and sub-phenotype-4 had higher severity at the time of inclusion. The effect of CP treatment on mortality appeared higher than standard care in each sub-phenotype, without heterogeneity between sub-phenotypes (p = 0.97).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In patients with C-ARDS, we identified 4 sub-phenotypes based on their immune response. These sub-phenotypes were associated with different clinical profiles. The response to CP was similar across the 4 sub-phenotypes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="TRIAL REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Ethics Committee of the University Hospital of Liège CE 2020/239.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CLINICALTRIALS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">gov NCT04558476. Registered 2020-09-11, https://www.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CLINICALTRIALS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">gov/study/NCT04558476 .</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Misset</LastName><ForeName>Benoît</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6466-0065</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Liège University, CHU de Liège, Liege, Belgium. benoit.misset@chuliege.be.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, University Hospital of Liège, Domaine Universitaire du Sart-Tilman, 4000, Liège, Belgium. benoit.misset@chuliege.be.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diep</LastName><ForeName>Anh Nguyet</ForeName><Initials>AN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biostatistic Unit, Public Health Department, Liège University, Liege, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bertrand</LastName><ForeName>Axelle</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Liège University, CHU de Liège, Liege, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Piagnerelli</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Marie-Curie University Hospital, Université Libre de Bruxelles, Charleroi, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoste</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, University Hospital, Ghent, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Michaux</LastName><ForeName>Isabelle</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care, Université Catholique de Louvain, CHU UCL Namur, Yvoir, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>De Waele</LastName><ForeName>Elisabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Nutrition, Vrije Universiteit Brussel Brussels University Hospital, Jette, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dumoulin</LastName><ForeName>Alexander</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Delta General Hospital, Roeselare, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jorens</LastName><ForeName>Philippe G</ForeName><Initials>PG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Antwerp University Hospital, University of Antwerp, LEMP, Edegem, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van der Hauwaert</LastName><ForeName>Emmanuel</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Imelda General Hospital, Bonheiden, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vallot</LastName><ForeName>Frédéric</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Wallonie Picarde General Hospital, Tournai, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Swinnen</LastName><ForeName>Walter</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Sint Blasius General Hospital, Dendermonde, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>De Schryver</LastName><ForeName>Nicolas</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Saint-Pierre Medical Clinic, Ottignies, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Mey</LastName><ForeName>Nathalie</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, OLV General Hospital, Aalst, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Layios</LastName><ForeName>Nathalie</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Liège University, CHU de Liège, Liege, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mesland</LastName><ForeName>Jean-Baptiste</ForeName><Initials>JB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Saint-Luc University Hospital, Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Robinet</LastName><ForeName>Sébastien</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Liège University, CHU de Liège, Liege, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cavalier</LastName><ForeName>Etienne</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Chemistry, University of Liege, CIRM, CHU de Liège, Liege, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Donneau</LastName><ForeName>Anne-Françoise</ForeName><Initials>AF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biostatistic Unit, Public Health Department, Liège University, Liege, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moutschen</LastName><ForeName>Michel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, CHU de Liège, Liege, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laterre</LastName><ForeName>Pierre-François</ForeName><Initials>PF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Medicine, Mons-Hainaut Regional Hospital, Mons, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT04558476</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>KCE 2020</GrantID><Agency>Belgian Health Care Knowledge Centre</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>1-0-1 AXA</GrantID><Agency>AXA Research Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Crédit classique facultaire</GrantID><Agency>Université de Liège</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Ann Intensive Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101562873</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2110-5820</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ARDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Convalescent plasma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immune response</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phenotypes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39432177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11493925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13613-024-01392-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s13613-024-01392-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tan E, Song J, Deane AM, Plummer MP. Global impact of coronavirus disease 2019 infection requiring admission to the ICU. Chest. 2021;159:524–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7557272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffiths M, Meade S, Summers C, McAuley DF, Proudfoot A, Baladia MM, et al. RAND appropriateness panel to determine the applicability of UK guidelines on the management of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and other strategies in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. Thorax. 2022;77:129–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34045363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Axfors C, Janiaud P, Schmitt AM, Van’t Hooft J, Smith ER, Haber NA, et al. Association between convalescent plasma treatment and mortality in COVID-19: a collaborative systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials. BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21:1170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8605464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34800996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iannizzi C, Chai KL, Piechotta V, Valk SJ, Kimber C, Monsef I, et al. Convalescent plasma for people with COVID-19: a living systematic review. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2023;5:CD013600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10171886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37162745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Writing Committee for the REMAP-CAP Investigators, Estcourt LJ, Turgeon AF, McQuilten ZK, McVerry BJ, Al-Beidh F, et al. Effect of convalescent plasma on organ support-free days in critically ill patients with COVID-19: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2021;326:1690–702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8491132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34606578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fish M, Rynne J, Jennings A, Lam C, Lamikanra AA, Ratcliff J, et al. Coronavirus disease 2019 subphenotypes and differential treatment response to convalescent plasma in critically ill adults: secondary analyses of a randomized clinical trial. Intensive Care Med. 2022;48:1525–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9472738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36102943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kox M, Waalders NJB, Kooistra EJ, Gerretsen J, Pickkers P. Cytokine levels in critically Ill patients with COVID-19 and other conditions. JAMA. 2020;324:1565–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7489366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32880615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brabander J de, Boers LS, Kullberg RFJ, Zhang S, Nossent EJ, Heunks LMA, et al. Persistent alveolar inflammatory response in critically ill patients with COVID-19 is associated with mortality. Thorax. 2023 [cited 2023 Jul 18]; Available from: https://thorax.bmj.com/content/early/2023/05/04/thorax-2023-219989</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37142421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakkerus L, Pickkers P. Personalized medicine in COVID-19. Intensive Care Med. 2022;48:1607–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9548417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36210384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misset B, Piagnerelli M, Hoste E, Dardenne N, Grimaldi D, Michaux I, et al. Convalescent plasma for Covid-19–induced ARDS in mechanically ventilated patients. N Engl J Med. 2023;389:1590–600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10755833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37889107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laing AG, Lorenc A, Barrio IDMD, DasFishMonin AML, et al. A dynamic COVID-19 immune signature includes associations with poor prognosis. Nat Med. 2020;26:1623–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32807934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Valle DM, Kim-Schulze S, Huang H-H, Beckmann ND, Nirenberg S, Wang B, et al. An inflammatory cytokine signature predicts COVID-19 severity and survival. Nat Med. 2020;26:1636–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7869028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucas C, Wong P, Klein J, Castro TBR, Silva J, Sundaram M, et al. Longitudinal analyses reveal immunological misfiring in severe COVID-19. Nature. 2020;584:463–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7477538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32717743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sposito B, Broggi A, Pandolfi L, Crotta S, Clementi N, Ferrarese R, et al. The interferon landscape along the respiratory tract impacts the severity of COVID-19. Cell. 2021;184:4953-4968.e16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8373821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34492226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thwaites RS, Sanchez Sevilla Uruchurtu A, Siggins MK, Liew F, Russell CD, Moore SC, et al. Inflammatory profiles across the spectrum of disease reveal a distinct role for GM-CSF in severe COVID-19. Sci Immunol. 2021;6:eabg9873.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8128298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33692097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Rapid Evidence Appraisal for COVID-19 Therapies (REACT) Working Group, Shankar-Hari M, Vale CL, Godolphin PJ, Fisher D, Higgins JPT, et al. Association between administration of IL-6 antagonists and mortality among patients hospitalized for COVID-19: a meta-analysis. JAMA. 2021;326:499–518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8261689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34228774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merad M, Martin JC. Pathological inflammation in patients with COVID-19: a key role for monocytes and macrophages. Nat Rev Immunol. 2020;20:355–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7201395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32376901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodin P. Immune determinants of COVID-19 disease presentation and severity. Nat Med. 2021;27:28–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33442016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidet B, de Lange DW, Boumendil A, Leaver S, Watson X, Boulanger C, et al. The contribution of frailty, cognition, activity of daily life and comorbidities on outcome in acutely admitted patients over 80 years in European ICUs: the VIP2 study. Intensive Care Med. 2020;46:57–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7223711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31784798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Working Group on the Clinical Characterisation and Management of COVID-19 infection. A minimal common outcome measure set for COVID-19 clinical research. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:e192–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32539990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ARDS Definition Task Force, Ranieri VM, Rubenfeld GD, Thompson BT, Ferguson ND, Caldwell E, et al. Acute respiratory distress syndrome: the Berlin Definition. JAMA. 2012;307:2526–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22797452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padoan A, Cosma C, Bonfante F, Rocca FD, Barbaro F, Santarossa C, et al. SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies after one or two doses of Comirnaty (BNT162b2, BioNTech/Pfizer): Kinetics and comparison with chemiluminescent assays. Clin Chim Acta Int J Clin Chem. 2021;523:446–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8553360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34755646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shakoory B, Carcillo JA, Chatham WW, Amdur RL, Zhao H, Dinarello CA, et al. Interleukin-1 receptor blockade is associated with reduced mortality in sepsis patients with features of macrophage activation syndrome: reanalysis of a prior phase III trial. Crit Care Med. 2016;44:275–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5378312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26584195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angus DC, van der Poll T. Severe sepsis and septic shock. N Engl J Med. 2013;369:840–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23984731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorndike RL. Who belongs in the family? Psychometrika. 1953;18:267–76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keegan MT, Gajic O, Afessa B. Severity of illness scoring systems in the intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 2011;39:163–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20838329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parlato M, Cavaillon J-M. Host response biomarkers in the diagnosis of sepsis: a general overview. Methods Mol Biol Clifton NJ. 2015;1237:149–211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25319788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Poll T, Shankar-Hari M, Wiersinga WJ. The immunology of sepsis. Immunity. 2021;54:2450–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34758337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fajgenbaum DC, June CH. Cytokine Storm. N Engl J Med. 2020;383:2255–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7727315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33264547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavaillon J-M, Annane D. Compartmentalization of the inflammatory response in sepsis and SIRS. J Endotoxin Res. 2006;12:151–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16719987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parlato M, Philippart F, Rouquette A, Moucadel V, Puchois V, Blein S, et al. Circulating biomarkers may be unable to detect infection at the early phase of sepsis in ICU patients: the CAPTAIN prospective multicenter cohort study. Intensive Care Med. 2018;44:1061–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29959455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carroll TD, Wong T, Morris MK, Di Germanio C, Ma Z-M, Stone M, et al. Administration of vaccine-boosted COVID-19 convalescent plasma to SARS-CoV-2 infected hamsters decreases virus replication in lungs and hastens resolution of the infection despite transiently enhancing disease and lung pathology. BioRxiv Prepr Serv Biol. 2023;55:3458.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>