<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39436490</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1869-4101</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Insights into imaging</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Insights Imaging</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Reproducibility of ultrasound-derived fat fraction in measuring hepatic steatosis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>254</StartPage><MedlinePgn>254</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">254</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s13244-024-01834-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Steatotic liver disease (SLD) has become the most common cause of chronic liver disease. Nevertheless, the non-invasive quantitative diagnosis of steatosis is still lacking in clinical practice. This study aimed to evaluate the reproducibility of the new parameter for steatosis quantification named ultrasound-derived fat fraction (UDFF).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The UDFF values were independently executed by two operators in two periods. In the process, repeated measurements of the same patient were performed by the same operator under different conditions (liver segments, respiration, positions, and dietary). Finally, the results of some subjects (28) were compared with the MRI-derived proton density fat fraction (PDFF). The concordance analysis was mainly achieved by the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) and Bland-Altman.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">One hundred-five participants were included in the study. UDFF had good reliability in measuring the adult liver (ICC<sub>intra-observer</sub> = 0.96, ICC<sub>inter-observer</sub> = 0.94). Meanwhile, the ICC of the two operators increased over time. The variable measurement states did not influence the UDFF values on the surface, but they affected the coefficient of variation (Cov) of the results. Segment 8 (S8), end-expiratory, supine, and fasting images had the most minor variability. On the other hand, the UDFF value of S8 displayed satisfied consistency with PDFF (mean difference, -0.24 ± 1.44), and the results of both S5 (mean difference: -0.56 ± 3.95) and S8 (mean difference: 0.73 ± 1.87) agreed well with the whole-liver PDFF.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">UDFF measurements had good reproducibility. Furthermore, the state of S8, end-expiration, supine, and fasting might be the more stable measurement approach.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CRITICAL RELEVANCE STATEMENT" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">UDFF is the quantitative ultrasound parameter of hepatic steatosis and has good reproducibility. It can show more robust performance under specific measurement conditions (S8, end-expiratory, supine, and fasting).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="TRIAL REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The research protocol was registered at the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry on October 9, 2023 ( http://www.chictr.org.cn/ ). The registration number is ChiCTR 2300076457.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="KEY POINTS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">There is a lack of non-invasive quantitative measurement options for hepatic steatosis. UDFF demonstrated excellent reproducibility in measuring hepatic steatosis. S8, end-expiratory, supine, and fasting may be the more stable measuring condition. Training could improve the operators' measurement stability. Variable measurement state affects the repeatability of the UDFF values (Cov).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Danlei</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ultrasound, Zhongda Hospital, Medical School, Southeast University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Pingping</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ultrasound, Zhongda Hospital, Medical School, Southeast University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Han</LastName><ForeName>Jiahao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ultrasound, Zhongda Hospital, Medical School, Southeast University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Huihui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ultrasound, Zhongda Hospital, Medical School, Southeast University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Ruixia</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ultrasound, Zhongda Hospital, Medical School, Southeast University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Endocrinology, Zhongda Hospital, Medical School, Southeast University, Nanjing, China. li-ling76@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jia</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0318-8961</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ultrasound, Zhongda Hospital, Medical School, Southeast University, Nanjing, China. 13951609892@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>202301014r6</GrantID><Agency>horizontal research projects, Zhongda Hospital, Affiliated to Southeast University</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Insights Imaging</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101532453</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1869-4101</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Steatotic liver disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ultrasound</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ultrasound-derived fat fraction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no potential conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39436490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11496408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13244-024-01834-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s13244-024-01834-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rinella ME, Lazarus JV, Ratziu V et al (2023) A multisociety Delphi consensus statement on new fatty liver disease nomenclature. J Hepatol 79:1542–1556</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37364790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalasani N, Younossi Z, Lavine JE et al (2018) The diagnosis and management of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: practice guidance from the American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases. Hepatology 67:328–357</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28714183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younossi ZM, Golabi P, Paik JM, Henry A, Van Dongen C, Henry L (2023) The global epidemiology of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH): a systematic review. Hepatology 77:1335–1347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10026948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36626630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thiele M, Madsen BS, Hansen JF, Detlefsen S, Antonsen S, Krag A (2018) Accuracy of the enhanced liver fibrosis test vs fibrotest, elastography, and indirect markers in detection of advanced fibrosis in patients with alcoholic liver disease. Gastroenterology 154:1369–1379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29317276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younossi ZM, Stepanova M, Ong J et al (2021) Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis is the most rapidly increasing indication for liver transplantation in the United States. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 19:580–589.e585</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32531342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Powell EE, Wong VW, Rinella M (2021) Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. Lancet 397:2212–2224</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33894145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reeder SB, Cruite I, Hamilton G, Hamilton G, Sirlin CB (2011) Quantitative assessment of liver fat with magnetic resonance imaging and spectroscopy. J Magn Reson Imaging 34:729–749</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3177109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22025886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Lu W, Li P, Shen F, Mi YQ, Fan JG (2017) A comparison of hepatic steatosis index, controlled attenuation parameter and ultrasound as noninvasive diagnostic tools for steatosis in chronic hepatitis B. Dig Liver Dis 49:910–917</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28433586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferraioli G, Kumar V, Ozturk A, Nam K, de Korte C, Barr R (2022) US attenuation for liver fat quantification: an AIUM-RSNA QIBA pulse–echo quantitative ultrasound initiative. Radiology 302:495–506</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35076304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han A, Zhang YN, Boehringer AS et al (2019) Inter-platform reproducibility of ultrasonic attenuation and backscatter coefficients in assessing NAFLD. Eur Radiol 29:4699–4708</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6684824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30783789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dillman JR, Thapaliya S, Tkach JA, Trout AT (2022) Quantification of hepatic steatosis by ultrasound: prospective comparison with MRI proton density fat fraction as reference standard. AJR Am J Roentgenol 219:784–791</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35674351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson SI, Fort D, Shortt KJ et al (2021) Ultrasound stratification of hepatic steatosis using hepatorenal index. Diagnostics 11:1443</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8391375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34441377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vehmas T, Kaukiainen A, Luoma K, Lohman M, Nurminen M, Taskinen H (2004) Liver echogenicity: Measurement or visual grading? Comput Med Imaging Graph 28:289–293</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15249074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferraioli G, Tinelli C, Lissandrin R et al (2014) Ultrasound point shear wave elastography assessment of liver and spleen stiffness: effect of training on repeatability of measurements. Eur Radiol 24:1283–1289</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24643497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong CW, Wolfson T, Sy EZ et al (2018) Optimization of region-of-interest sampling strategies for hepatic MRI proton density fat fraction quantification. J Magn Reson Imaging 47:988–994</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5826828</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28842937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dick BM (1928) “Stream-lines” in the portal vein: their Influence on the selective distribution of blood in the liver. Edinb Med J 35:533–539</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5314083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29645748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonekamp S, Tang A, Mashhood A et al (2014) Spatial distribution of MRI-determined hepatic proton density fat fraction in adults with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. J Magn Reson Imaging 39:1525–1532</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4083476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24987758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armstrong T, Ly KV, Murthy S et al (2018) Free-breathing quantification of hepatic fat in healthy children and children with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease using a multi-echo 3-D stack-of-radial MRI technique. Pediatr Radiol 48:941–953</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29728744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taraldsen V, Tomasgard S, Rudlang M, Gilja O, Vesterhus M, Mjelle A (2020) Point shear wave elastography and the effect of physical exercise, alcohol consumption, and respiration in healthy adults. Ultrasound Int J Open 6:E54–E61</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7723471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33305164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Jia M, Zhang C et al (2022) Reproducibility of ultrasound-guided attenuation parameter (UGAP) to the noninvasive evaluation of hepatic steatosis. Sci Rep 12:2876</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8861045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35190618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paverd C, Kupfer S, Kirchner IN et al (2023) Impact of breathing phase, liver segment, and prandial state on ultrasound shear wave speed, shear wave dispersion, and attenuation imaging of the liver in healthy volunteers. Diagnostics 13:989</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10001107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36900133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Şendur HN, Cerit MN, Fatullayeva T, Erdal ZS, Karabörk Kılıç AC, Özhan Oktar S (2023) Do ultrasound based quantitative hepatic fat content measurements have differences between respiratory phases? Acad Radiol 30:1832–1837</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36628802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang X, Li L, Xue H-Y (2022) The impact of body position and exercise on the measurement of liver Young’s modulus by real-time shear wave elastography. Technol Health Care 30:445–454</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34657862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berzigotti A, De Gottardi A, Vukotic R et al (2013) Effect of meal ingestion on liver stiffness in patients with cirrhosis and portal hypertension. PLoS One 8:e58742</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3592829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23520531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ratchatasettakul K, Rattanasiri S, Promson K, Sringam P, Sobhonslidsuk A (2017) The inverse effect of meal intake on controlled attenuation parameter and liver stiffness as assessed by transient elastography. BMC Gastroenterol 17:50</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5390386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28407734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu P, Yang H, Qi X et al (2022) Gender differences in the ideal cutoffs of visceral fat area for predicting MAFLD in China. Lipids Health Dis 21:148</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9805250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36585702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimura S, Tanaka K, Oeda S et al (2021) Effect of skin-capsular distance on controlled attenuation parameter for diagnosing liver steatosis in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Sci Rep 11:15641</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8329228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34341368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goertz RS, Egger C, Neurath MF, Strobel D (2012) Impact of food intake, ultrasound transducer, breathing maneuvers and body position on acoustic radiation force impulse (ARFI) elastometry of the liver. Ultraschall Med 33:380–385</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22723037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han A, Labyed Y, Sy EZ et al (2018) Inter-sonographer reproducibility of quantitative ultrasound outcomes and shear wave speed measured in the right lobe of the liver in adults with known or suspected non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. Eur Radiol 28:4992–5000</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7235946</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29869170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>