<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39432462</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1559-713X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Simulation in healthcare : journal of the Society for Simulation in Healthcare</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Simul Healthc</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Gaming the System? A Qualitative Exploration of Physician Assistant Learner Perceptions of Virtual Patient Education.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/SIH.0000000000000823</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Virtual patients (VPs) are increasingly used in health professions education. How learners engage with VPs and the relationship between engagement and authenticity is not well understood. We explored learners' perceptions of VP education to gain an understanding of the characteristics promoting meaningful engagement in learning, including perceived authenticity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Using a constructivist grounded theory approach, we conducted interviews and focus groups with 11 students from 2 Canadian Physician Assistant programs, where VP learning was implemented to supplement clinical education during the COVID-19 pandemic. We explored trainee perspectives on the use of VPs as an educational modality. Data were iteratively collected and descriptively analyzed thematically using a constant comparison approach until theoretical sufficiency was reached.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We identified 3 groups of factors influencing these students' VP learning experiences: (1) technical factors related to the VP platform influenced the perceived authenticity of the patient interactions; (2) individual factors of learners' attitudes influenced their engagement and motivation; and (3) contextual factors related to the learning environment influenced the acceptability and perceived value of the learning experience. Overall, the psychological authenticity of the learning platform and students' motivation for self-directed learning were perceived as most important for students' learning experiences.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Implementing VP learning as a supplement to clinical education should be done with consideration of factors that enhance the psychological authenticity of the learning platform, promote learner engagement and accountability, and encourage acceptability of the learning modality through curricular placement and messaging.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Society for Simulation in Healthcare.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanofsky</LastName><ForeName>Sharona</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physician Assistant Program (S.K)., Department of Family and Community Medicine, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Li Ka Shing Knowledge Institute (K.H.), St Michael's Hospital, Unity Health Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; University of Toronto (P.T.), Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Michael Garron Hospital (P.T.), Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Family and Community Medicine (J.M.N.-Y.), University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Academics Program and Family Practice Health Centre (J.M.N.-Y.), Women's College Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Family Medicine (J.M.N.-Y.), St Michael's Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; and Division of Gastroenterology, Hepatology, and Nutrition and the SickKids Research and Learning Institutes (C.M.W.), The Hospital for Sick Children, Department of Paediatrics and The Wilson Centre, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hodwitz</LastName><ForeName>Kathryn</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tzakas</LastName><ForeName>Peter</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nyhof-Young</LastName><ForeName>Joyce M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walsh</LastName><ForeName>Catharine M</ForeName><Initials>CM</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Simul Healthc</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101264408</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1559-2332</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39432462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SIH.0000000000000823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">01266021-990000000-00153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>O'Doherty D, Dromey M, Lougheed J, Hannigan A, Last J, McGrath D. Barriers and solutions to online learning in medical education—an integrative review. BMC Med Educ 2018;18(1):130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabatabai S. Simulations and virtual learning supporting clinical education during the COVID 19 pandemic. Adv Med Educ Pract 2020;11:513–516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellaway R, Poulton T, Fors U, McGee JB, Albright S. Building a virtual patient commons. Med Teach 2008;30(2):170–174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGee JB, Neill J, Goldman L, Casey E. Using multimedia virtual patients to enhance the clinical curriculum for medical students. Stud Health Technol Inform 1998;52(Pt 2):732–735.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tworek J, Coderre S, Wright B, McLaughlin K. Virtual patients: ED-2 band-aid or valuable asset in the learning portfolio? Acad Med 2010;85(1):155–158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janda MS, Mattheos N, Nattestad A, et al. Simulation of patient encounters using a virtual patient in periodontology instruction of dental students: design, usability, and learning effect in history-taking skills. Eur J Dent Educ 2004;8(3):111–119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonnetain E, Boucheix J-M, Hamet M, Freysz M. Benefits of computer screen-based simulation in learning cardiac arrest procedures. Med Educ 2010;44(7):716–722.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kononowicz AA, Krawczyk P, Cebula G, et al. Effects of introducing a voluntary virtual patient module to a basic life support with an automated external defibrillator course: a randomised trial. BMC Med Educ 2012;12(1):41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehmann R, Thiessen C, Frick B, et al. Improving pediatric basic life support performance through blended learning with web-based virtual patients: randomized controlled trial. J Med Internet Res 2015;17(7):e162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liaw SY, Chan SW, Chen FG, Hooi SC, Siau C. Comparison of virtual patient simulation with mannequin-based simulation for improving clinical performances in assessing and managing clinical deterioration: randomized controlled trial. J Med Internet Res 2014;16(9):e214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao H. Computer-based simulative training system—a new approach to teaching pre-hospital trauma care. Journal of Medical Colleges of PLA 2011;26(6):335–344.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu Y, Zou Z, Chen X. The effects of vSIM for Nursing™ as a teaching strategy on fundamentals of nursing education in undergraduates. Clin Simul Nurs 2017;13(4):194–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaltman S, Talisman N, Pennestri S, Syverson E, Arthur P, Vovides Y. Using technology to enhance teaching of patient-centered interviewing for early medical students. Simul Healthc 2018;13(3):188–194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fidler BD. Use of a virtual patient simulation program to enhance the physical assessment and medical history taking skills of doctor of pharmacy students. Curr Pharm Teach Learn 2020;12(7):810–816.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peddle M, Bearman M, Nestel D. Virtual patients and nontechnical skills in undergraduate health professional education: an integrative review. Clin Simul Nurs 2016;12(9):400–410.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kandasamy T, Fung K. Interactive Internet-based cases for undergraduate otolaryngology education. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 2009;140(3):398–402.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinney P, Keskula DR, Perry JF. The effect of a computer assisted instructional program on physical therapy students. J Allied Health 1997;26(2):57–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Dahir S, Bryant K, Kennedy KB, Robinson DS. Online virtual-patient cases versus traditional problem-based learning in advanced pharmacy practice experiences. Am J Pharm Educ 2014;78(4):76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kononowicz AA, Woodham LA, Edelbring S, et al. Virtual patient simulations in health professions education: systematic review and meta-analysis by the digital health education collaboration. J Med Internet Res 2019;21(7):e14676.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peddle M, Bearman M, McKenna L, Nestel D. Exploring undergraduate nursing student interactions with virtual patients to develop 'non-technical skills' through case study methodology. Adv Simul (Lond) 2019;4:2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook DA, Erwin PJ, Triola MM. Computerized virtual patients in health professions education: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Acad Med 2010;85(10):1589–1602.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deladisma AM, Gupta M, Kotranza A, et al. A pilot study to integrate an immersive virtual patient with a breast complaint and breast examination simulator into a surgery clerkship. Am J Surg 2009;197(1):102–106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bearman M. Is virtual the same as real? Medical students' experiences of a virtual patient. Acad Med 2003;78(5):538–545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liaw T, Kennedy G, Keppell M, Marty J, McNair R. Using multimedia to assist students with communication skills and biopsychosocial integration: an evaluation. Aust J Educ Technol 2000;16(2):104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shoemaker MJ, Platko CM, Cleghorn SM, Booth A. Virtual patient care: an interprofessional education approach for physician assistant, physical therapy and occupational therapy students. J Interprof Care 2014;28(4):365–367.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Courteille O, Fahlstedt M, Ho J, et al. Learning through a virtual patient vs. recorded lecture: a comparison of knowledge retention in a trauma case. Int J Med Educ 2018;9:86–92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foster A, Chaudhary N, Murphy J, Lok B, Waller J, Buckley PF. The use of simulation to teach suicide risk assessment to health profession trainees—rationale, methodology, and a proof of concept demonstration with a virtual patient. Acad Psychiatry 2015;39(6):620–629.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson J, White S, Chapman S. Virtual patients as a tool for training pre-registration pharmacists and increasing their preparedness to practice: A qualitative study. PLoS One 2020;15(8):e0238226.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arthur C, Kable A, Levett-Jones T. Human patient simulation manikins and information communication technology use in Australian schools of nursing: a cross-sectional survey. Clin Simul Nurs 2011;7(6):e219–e227.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahri K, MacNeil K, Chan F, et al. Curriculum integration of virtual patients. Curr Pharm Teach Learn 2019;11(12):1309–1315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleinsmith A, Rivera-Gutierrez D, Finney G, Cendan J, Lok B. Understanding empathy training with virtual patients. Comput Hum Behav 2015;52:151–158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triola M, Feldman H, Kalet AL, et al. A randomized trial of teaching clinical skills using virtual and live standardized patients. J Gen Intern Med 2006;21(5):424–429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botezatu M, Hult H, Fors UG. Virtual patient simulation: what do students make of it? A focus group study. BMC Med Educ 2010;10(1):91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huwendiek S, Reichert F, Bosse H-M, et al. Design principles for virtual patients: a focus group study among students. Med Educ 2009;43(6):580–588.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bateman J, Allen M, Samani D, Kidd J, Davies D. Virtual patient design: exploring what works and why. A grounded theory study. Med Educ 2013;47(6):595–606.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hege I, Kononowicz AA, Berman NB, Lenzer B, Kiesewetter J. Advancing clinical reasoning in virtual patients - development and application of a conceptual framework. GMS J Med Educ 2018;35(1):Doc12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edelbring S, Dastmalchi M, Hult H, Lundberg IE, Dahlgren LO. Experiencing virtual patients in clinical learning: a phenomenological study. Advances in Health Sciences Education 2011;16(3):331–345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maran NJ, Glavin RJ. Low- to high-fidelity simulation - a continuum of medical education? Med Educ 2003;37(s1):22–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chernikova O, Heitzmann N, Stadler M, Holzberger D, Seidel T, Fischer F. Simulation-based learning in higher education: a meta-analysis. Review of educational research 2020;90(4):499–541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamstra SJ, Brydges R, Hatala R, Zendejas B, Cook DA. Reconsidering fidelity in simulation-based training. Acad Med 2014;89(3):387–392.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padgett J, Cristancho S, Lingard L, Cherry R, Haji F. Engagement: what is it good for? The role of learner engagement in healthcare simulation contexts. Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract 2019;24(4):811–825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hege I, Kononowicz AA, Tolks D, Edelbring S, Kuehlmeyer K. A qualitative analysis of virtual patient descriptions in healthcare education based on a systematic literature review. BMC Med Educ 2016;16(146):146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charmaz K. Constructing Grounded Theory : A Practical Guide Through Qualitative Analysis. London: Sage Publications; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watling CJ, Lingard L. Grounded theory in medical education research: AMEE guide no. 70. Med Teach 2012;34(10):850–861.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bunniss S, Kelly DR. Research paradigms in medical education research. Med Educ 2010;44(4):358–366.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temerty Faculty of Medicine Univeristy of Toronto. Physician assistant program information; 2023. Available at: https://paconsortium.ca/program-information. Accessed February 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMaster University Faculty of Health Sciences. Physician assistant education program information; 2023. Available at: https://fhs.mcmaster.ca/physicianassistant/index.html. Accessed February 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CanMEDS-PA. Ottawa, Ontario: Canadian Association of Physician Assistants; 2015. Available at: https://capa-acam.ca/_uploads/65010706a11c6.pdf. Accessed February 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CanMEDS 2015 Physician Competency Framework. Ottawa: Royal College of Physicians and Surgeons of Canada; 2015. Available at: https://canmeds.royalcollege.ca/en/framework. Accessed February 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>i-Human patients by Kaplan. Physician assistant cases; 2023. Available at: https://www.i-human.com/. Accessed February 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kononowicz AA, Zary N, Edelbring S, Corral J, Hege I. Virtual patients--what are we talking about? A framework to classify the meanings of the term in healthcare education. BMC Med Educ 2015;15:11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willett T. Virtual Patients: Review of Pedagogical and Technological Options. Toronto: Simulation Canada; 2020. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mardpQYRP_8. Accessed February 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter N, Bryant-Lukosius D, DiCenso A, Blythe J, Neville AJ. The use of triangulation in qualitative research. Oncol Nurs Forum 2014;41(5):545–547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambert SD, Loiselle CG. Combining individual interviews and focus groups to enhance data richness. J Adv Nurs 2008;62(2):228–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belgrave L, Charmaz K. Qualitative interviewing and grounded theory analysis. In: Gubrium J, Holstein J, Marvasti A, McKinney K, eds. The SAGE Handbook of Interview Research: The Complexity of the Craft. 2nd ed. Thousand Oaks: SAGE Publications, Inc; 2012:347–365.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey I. Grounding Grounded Theory : Guidelines for Qualitative Inquiry. San Diego: Academic Press; 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glaser BG. The constant comparative method of qualitative analysis. Soc Probl 1965;12(4):436–445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol 2006;3(2):77–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guest G, Namey E, Taylor J, Eley N, McKenna K. Comparing focus groups and individual interviews: findings from a randomized study. International journal of social research methodology 2017;20(6):693–708.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naismith LM, Kowalski C, Soklaridis S, Kelly A, Walsh CM. Participant perspectives on the contributions of physical, psychological, and sociological fidelity to learning in interprofessional mental health simulation. Simul Healthc 2020;15(3):141–146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker R, Walonoski J, Heffernan N, Roll I, Corbett A, Koedinger K. Why students engage in "gaming the system" behavior in interactive learning environments. J Interact Learn Res 2008;19(2):185–224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Gaalen AEJ, Brouwer J, Schönrock-Adema J, Bouwkamp-Timmer T, Jaarsma ADC, Georgiadis JR. Gamification of health professions education: a systematic review. Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract 2021;26(2):683–711.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnamurthy K, Selvaraj N, Gupta P, et al. Benefits of gamification in medical education. Clin Anat 2022;35(6):795–807.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muckler VC. Exploring suspension of disbelief during simulation-based learning. Clin Simul Nurs 2017;13(1):3–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jäger F, Riemer M, Abendroth M, Sehner S, Harendza S. Virtual patients: the influence of case design and teamwork on students' perception and knowledge – a pilot study. BMC Med Educ 2014;14(1):137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benedict N, Schonder K, McGee J. Promotion of self-directed learning using virtual patient cases. Am J Pharm Educ 2013;77(7):151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewitt-Taylor J. Teachers' and students' views on self-directed learning. Nurs Stand 2002;17(1):33–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tessmer M, Richey RC. The role of context in learning and instructional design. Educational technology research and development 1997;45(2):85–115.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>