<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39433969</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1348-4214</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Hypertension research : official journal of the Japanese Society of Hypertension</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Hypertens Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Secular trends in blood pressure among university students in Japan over the last two decades.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41440-024-01955-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>High blood pressure (BP) increases the risk of cardiovascular disease, not only among middle-aged and older adults, but also in young adults. Early interventions for high BP may prevent future organ damage. Therefore, it is essential to monitor BP trends in young adults to support this approach. During the COVID-19 pandemic, a trend of increasing BP was observed worldwide. However, young adults have not been fully evaluated. Therefore, this study examined BP trends among university students (n = 106,691) over two decades, every 5 years from 2003 to 2023, including the period before and after the COVID-19 pandemic. From 2003 to 2018, there were no notable changes in BP. However, following the COVID-19 pandemic, increased BP was observed in both men and women, with systolic BP increasing from 118.1 (SD, 14.2) mmHg in 2018 to 120.6 (SD, 12.5) mmHg in 2023 among men, and from 104.6 (SD, 11.8) mmHg to 105.1 (SD, 11.7) mmHg among women. These trends were particularly pronounced among students with normal and underweight somatotypes and among first- and second-year students. The results of the lifestyle survey showed a decrease in smoking and drinking habits, insufficient sleep, mental stress, consumption of fast food and snacks, and an increase in exercise habits. Although contributing factors to the recent increase in BP were not identified, there was an upward trend in BP among Japanese university students. It is important to carefully observe how BP trends change over the long term following the end of the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to The Japanese Society of Hypertension.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adachi</LastName><ForeName>Keika</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Nephrology, Endocrinology and Metabolism, Department of Internal Medicine, Keio University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azegami</LastName><ForeName>Tatsuhiko</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Nephrology, Endocrinology and Metabolism, Department of Internal Medicine, Keio University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan. t.azegami-1114@keio.jp.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sei</LastName><ForeName>Nahomi</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yamada-Goto</LastName><ForeName>Nobuko</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Uchida</LastName><ForeName>Keiko</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Murai-Takeda</LastName><ForeName>Ayano</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Inokuchi</LastName><ForeName>Mikako</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hayashi</LastName><ForeName>Kaori</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Nephrology, Endocrinology and Metabolism, Department of Internal Medicine, Keio University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mori</LastName><ForeName>Masaaki</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hirose</LastName><ForeName>Hiroshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Keio University Health Center, Yokohama-shi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Hypertens Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9307690</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0916-9636</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Blood pressure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lifestyle</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Secular trend</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Young adult</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39433969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41440-024-01955-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41440-024-01955-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>NCD Risk Factor Collaboration. Worldwide trends in hypertension prevalence and progress in treatment and control from 1990 to 2019: a pooled analysis of 1201 population-representative studies with 104 million participants. Lancet. 2021;398:957–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)01330-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imano H, Kitamura A, Sato S, Kiyama M, Ohira T, Yamagishi K, et al. Trends for blood pressure and its contribution to stroke incidence in the middle-aged Japanese population: the circulatory risk in communities study (CIRCS). Stroke. 2009;40:1571–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.108.538629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19342607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujiyoshi A, Ohkubo T, Miura K, Murakami Y, Nagasawa SY, Okamura T, et al. Blood pressure categories and long-term risk of cardiovascular disease according to age group in Japanese men and women. Hypertens Res. 2012;35:947–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/hr.2012.87</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22739419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lida M, Ueda K, Okayama A, Kodama K, Sawai K, Shibata S, et al. Impact of elevated blood pressure on mortality from all causes, cardiovascular diseases, heart disease and stroke among Japanese: 14 year follow-up of randomly selected population from Japanese - nippon data 80. J Hum Hypertens. 2003;17:851–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.jhh.1001602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14704729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takashima N, Ohkubo T, Miura K, Okamura T, Murakami Y, Fujiyoshi A, et al. Long-term risk of BP values above normal for cardiovascular mortality: a 24-year observation of Japanese aged 30 to 92 years. J Hypertens. 2012;30:2299–306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/HJH.0b013e328359a9f7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23079682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yano Y, Reis JP, Colangelo LA, Shimbo D, Viera AJ, Allen NB, et al. Association of BP classification in young adults using the 2017 American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association BP guideline with cardiovascular events later in life. JAMA. 2018;320:1774–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.13551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30398601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6248102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen W, Zhang T, Li S, Zhang H, Xi B, Shen H, et al. Race and sex differences of long-term blood pressure profiles from childhood and adult hypertension: the Bogalusa heart study. Hypertension. 2017;70:66–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.117.09537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28533330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacobs DR Jr, Woo JG, Sinaiko AR, Daniels SR, Ikonen J, Juonala M, et al. Childhood cardiovascular risk factors and adult cardiovascular events. N. Engl J Med. 2022;386:1877–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2109191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35373933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9563825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valenzuela PL, Carrera-Bastos P, Gálvez BG, Ruiz-Hurtado G, Ordovas JM, Ruilope LM, et al. Lifestyle interventions for the prevention and treatment of hypertension. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2021;18:251–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41569-020-00437-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33037326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appel LJ, Moore TJ, Obarzanek E, Vollmer WM, Svetkey LP, Sacks FM, et al. A clinical trial of the effects of dietary patterns on blood pressure. DASH Collaborative Research Group. N. Engl J Med. 1997;336:1117–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJM199704173361601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9099655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hisamatsu T, Segawa H, Kadota A, Ohkubo T, Arima H, Miura K. Epidemiology of hypertension in Japan: beyond the new 2019 Japanese guidelines. Hypertens Res. 2020;43:1344–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41440-020-0508-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32636526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laffin LJ, Kaufman HW, Chen Z, Niles JK, Arellano AR, Bare LA, et al. Rise in blood pressure observed among US adults during the COVID-19 pandemic. Circulation. 2022;145:235–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.121.057075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34865499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolde JM, Streets F, Meyer D, Chen WS, Wei J, Wickramasinghe N, et al. Trends in blood pressure changes and hypertension prevalence in Australian adults before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Clin Hypertens. 2024;26:145–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jch.14761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umemura S, Arima H, Arima S, Asayama K, Dohi Y, Hirooka Y, et al. The Japanese Society of Hypertension guidelines for the management of hypertension (JSH 2019). Hypertens Res. 2019;42:1235–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41440-019-0284-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31375757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogawa W, Hirota Y, Miyazaki S, Nakamura T, Ogawa Y, Shimomura I, et al. Definition, criteria, and core concepts of guidelines for the management of obesity disease in Japan. Endocr J. 2024;71:223–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1507/endocrj.EJ23-0593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38123337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Consultation on Obesity (1999: Geneva, Switzerland) &amp; World Health Organization. (2000). Obesity: preventing and managing the global epidemic: report of a WHO consultation. World Health Organization. https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/42330 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Expert Consultation. Appropriate body-mass index for Asian populations and its implications for policy and intervention strategies. Lancet. 2004;363:157–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)15268-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare. The results of the 2018 National Health and Nutrition Survey in Japan. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/content/000711007.pdf Accessed 8 March 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare. The results of the 2013 National Health and Nutrition Survey in Japan. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/bunya/kenkou/eiyou/dl/h25-houkoku-05.pdf Accessed 8 March 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare. The results of the 2008 National Health and Nutrition Survey in Japan. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/bunya/kenkou/eiyou/dl/h20-houkoku-03.pdf Accessed 8 March 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare. The results of the 2003 National Health and Nutrition Survey in Japan. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/bunya/kenkou/eiyou-chosa2-01/pdf/05a.pdf Accessed 8 March 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abramson JL, Lewis C, Murrah NV. Relationship of self-reported alcohol consumption to ambulatory blood pressure in a sample of healthy adults. Am J Hypertens. 2010;23:994–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ajh.2010.109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20489685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell NRC, Whelton PK, Orias M, Wainford RD, Cappuccio FP, Ide N, et al. 2022 World hypertension league, resolve to save lives and international society of hypertension dietary sodium (salt) global call to action. J Hum Hypertens. 2023;37:428–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41371-022-00690-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35581323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Zhang D, Liu Y, Sun X, Han C, Wang B, et al. Dose-response association between physical activity and incident hypertension: a systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies. Hypertension. 2017;69:813–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.116.08994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28348016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fugger G, Dold M, Bartova L, Kautzky A, Souery D, Mendlewicz J, et al. Comorbid hypertension in patients with major depressive disorder - results from a European multicenter study. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol. 2019;29:777–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2019.03.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31006562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications. Digital use in the public sector during the COVID-19 pandemic. https://www.soumu.go.jp/johotsusintokei/whitepaper/ja/r03/pdf/n2200000.pdf Accessed 8 March 2024.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>