<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39430654</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1708-6892</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>45</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The journal of the Canadian Health Libraries Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Can Health Libr Assoc</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>"It's not just teaching for the sake of teaching anymore": a quality improvement project for online instruction in a hospital library.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>65</StartPage><EndPage>75</EndPage><MedlinePgn>65-75</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.29173/jchla29771</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Medical libraries had to swiftly change how instruction services were provided in response to the COVID-19 pandemic. This article describes a Quality Improvement (QI) project to assess one hospital library's move to virtual instructional services. Information was gathered via a survey to Canadian hospital library workers and a focus group with internal staff with instructional responsibilities. Moving to online instruction increased audience attendance and garnered positive feedback, however library instructors report experiencing uncertainty about quality and effectiveness of online instruction. The article concludes with a description of planned actions to improve online instructional services in an urban research and teaching hospital library environment.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Anderson, Nault, and Serban.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anderson</LastName><ForeName>Melanie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Information Specialist, Library and Information Services, The Institute for Education Research, University Health Network, Toronto, ON.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nault</LastName><ForeName>Caleb</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>E-Collections and Discovery Librarian, Library and Information Services, University Health Network, Toronto, ON.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Serban</LastName><ForeName>Raluca</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Library Technician, Education Coordinator, Library and Information Services, University Health Network, Toronto, ON.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Canada</Country><MedlineTA>J Can Health Libr Assoc</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101229936</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1708-6892</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39430654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11485160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.29173/jchla29771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JCHLA-45-065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Colton D. Quality improvement in health care: conceptual and historical foundations. Eval Health Prof. 2000. Mar 1;23(1):7–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10787951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gray H, Sutton G, Treadway V. Do quality improvement systems improve health library services? A systematic review. Health Info Libr J. 2012;29(3):180–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22925382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esparza JM. A librarian’s experience with Six Sigma® tools. J Hosp Librariansh. 2008. Aug 11;8(3):332–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas DA. The Lean librarian. J Hosp Librariansh. 2015. Jan 2;15(1):23–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hug GP. Literature search improvement project. Med Ref Serv Q. 2001. Dec 1;20(4):39–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11865761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu F, Ball AL. Using quality improvement tools to redefine a clinical librarianship program: a case study. J Hosp Librariansh. 2018. Jan 2;18(1):31–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wildish D. An introduction to quality improvement methods and principles e-learning module: part 1 [Internet]. E-learning module presented at; 2018 Jul. Available from: https://tools.michener.ca/bbvirtual/Continuing_Education/Unsorted/QI-Module_Part-1-and-Part-2/index.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>University Health Network QIRC . Research - Quality Improvement (QI) Review Process. 2000. [cited 2024 May 29]. Quality Improvement (QI) review process. Available from: University Health Network QIRC. Research - Quality Improvement (QI) Review Process. 2000 [cited 2024 May 29]. Quality Improvement (QI) review process.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frati F, Oja LA, Kleinberg J. CHLA standards for library and information services in
J Can Health Libr Assoc [Internet]. 2021.  Apr 2 [cited 2024 May 1];42(1). Available from: https://journals.library.ualberta.ca/jchla/index.php/jchla/article/view/29526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9327607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35949504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medical Library Association, Task Force to Review MLA’s Competencies for Lifelong Learning and Professional Success . MLA: Professional Development: MLA Competencies (2017). 2017. 
[cited 2024 May 29]. Medical Library Association competencies for lifelong learning and professional success 2017. Available from: https://www.mlanet.org/page/test-competencies.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartman TL, Fial AV. Creating interactive online instruction: the McGoogan Library experience. Med Ref Serv Q. 2015. Oct;34(4):407–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26496395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoberecht T, Randall K, Schweikhard AJ. Library tutorials in an allied health evidence-based practice class. Med Ref Serv Q. 2015. Apr 3;34(2):240–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25927516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCaul M, Durao S, Kredo T, Garner P, Young T, Rohwer A. Evidence synthesis workshops: moving from face-to-face to online learning. BMJ Evid Based Med. 2021. Oct 1;26(5):255–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8479735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32763960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballance D. E pluribus unum: using Google Classroom to bring together a statewide student and faculty cohort. J Hosp Librariansh. 2020. Apr 2;20(2):166–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aronoff N, Maloney MK, Lyons AG, Stellrecht E. Health sciences library workshops in the covid era: librarian perceptions and decision making. J Med Libr Assoc. 2023. Jul 10;111(3):657–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10361557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37483364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma LFH, Yu LL. Ubiquitous learning for distance education students: the experience of conducting real-time online library instruction programs through mobile technology. 2019;4(1):93–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lierman A, McCandless B, Kowalsky M. Learning from academic libraries’ pivot to online instruction during the covid-19 pandemic. J Libr Inf Serv Distance Learn. 2022. Apr 3;16(2):136–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordova L, Jasmin H, Nelson T, Strahan K, Wu L. Rapidly remote: providing seamless library support during a pandemic. J Hosp Librariansh. 2021. Jan 2;21(1):82–92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandieson R, Goodman M. The current environment of e-learning development for information literacy instruction by hospital librarians. J Hosp Librariansh. 2018. Oct 2;18(4):348–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sobczak D. A strategy for developing an internet training course for health professionals. J Hosp Librariansh. 2001. Dec;1(4):31–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orchanian-Cheff A. Librarian office hours in a family practice unit. J Can Health Libr Assoc. 2005;26(2):55–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babish J. Evidence based medicine morning report: overview and the role of the librarian. J Hosp Librariansh. 2003. Dec;3(4):35–45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azadbakht E. The many faces of instruction: an exploration of academic librarians’ teaching personas. Commun Inf Lit [Internet]. 2021. 
Jun
1;15(1). Available from: https://pdxscholar.library.pdx.edu/comminfolit/vol15/iss1/3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blume R. Learning instructional methods and practices: an early career health sciences librarian perspective. Med Ref Serv Q. 2022. Jan 2;41(1):117–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35225736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budhai SS, Williams M. Humanizing virtual library instruction: anchoring teaching presence in online information literacy sessions. J Libr Inf Serv Distance Learn. 2021. Jul 3;15(3):204–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julien H, Genuis SK. Librarians’ experiences of the teaching role: a national survey of librarians. Libr Inf Sci Res. 2011. Apr 1;33(2):103–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koos JA, Scheinfeld L. An investigation of the backgrounds of health sciences librarians. Med Ref Serv Q. 2020. Jan 2;39(1):35–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32069198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moran C, Mulvihill R. Finding the balance in online library instruction: sustainable and personal. 2017. Jan 2;11(1–2):13–24.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>