<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39437830</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1439-4413</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>149</Volume><Issue>22</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Deutsche medizinische Wochenschrift (1946)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Dtsch Med Wochenschr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>[Outpatient exercise training for chronic lung disease - for whom, how and why?].</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1367</StartPage><EndPage>1371</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1367-1371</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1055/a-2165-5788</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>There is a legal entitlement to participate in outpatient exercise groups in accordance with the German Social Code (Book IX) which regulates and facilitates prescriptions for patients with chronic respiratory diseases. A medical examination with specific inclusion and exclusion criteria prior to admission to an exercise group ensures safe participation.Traditional outpatient exercise groups are conducted in face-to-face groups for 60 to 90 minutes, once a week, with structured warm-up, main and cool-down phases. In addition, since the coronavirus pandemic, the introduction of online exercise groups via videoconferencing has enabled flexible participation (even without a prescription). To date, more than 11,000 German patients have participated in online exercise groups since 2021.Scientific evidence confirms the significant benefits of regular exercise, such as improved physical performance and reduced breathlessness. The psychosocial benefits and the promotion of self-efficacy are additionally supported by the supervision of a specialized trainer. Regular exercise (e.g. in outpatient exercise groups) is an inexpensive and very effective form of therapy to improve the quality of life of people with chronic respiratory diseases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Thieme. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gloeckl</LastName><ForeName>Rainer</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Forschungsinstitut für Pneumologische Rehabilitation, Schön Klinik Berchtesgadener Land, Schönau am Königssee, Deutschland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jarosch</LastName><ForeName>Inga</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Forschungsinstitut für Pneumologische Rehabilitation, Schön Klinik Berchtesgadener Land, Schönau am Königssee, Deutschland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koczulla</LastName><ForeName>Andreas Rembert</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Forschungsinstitut für Pneumologische Rehabilitation, Schön Klinik Berchtesgadener Land, Schönau am Königssee, Deutschland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Philipps-Universität Marburg (Standort Schönau), Deutsches Zentrum für Lungenforschung (DZL), Schön Klinik Berchtesgadener Land.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lehrkrankenhaus, Paracelsus Medizinische Privatuniversität, Salzburg, Österreich.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>ger</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D004740">English Abstract</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Lungensport: Für wen, wie und warum?</VernacularTitle><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Dtsch Med Wochenschr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0006723</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0012-0472</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005081" MajorTopicYN="Y">Exercise Therapy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002908" MajorTopicYN="N">Chronic Disease</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008171" MajorTopicYN="Y">Lung Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000534" MajorTopicYN="N">rehabilitation</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005858" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Germany</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011788" MajorTopicYN="N">Quality of Life</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000553" MajorTopicYN="N">Ambulatory Care</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ger"><AbstractText>LUNGENSPORT – FüR WEN?: Lungensport ist als Rechtsanspruch im SGB IX verankert, was die Teilnahme und Verordnung für Patienten mit chronischen Atemwegs- und Lungenerkrankungen vereinfacht. Eine ärztliche Untersuchung unter Berücksichtigung spezifischer Ein- und Ausschlusskriterien vor Aufnahme in eine Lungensportgruppe gewährleistet die sichere Teilnahme. Aktuell gibt es in Deutschland 1868 Lungensportgruppen für Erwachsene und 45 Lungensportgruppen für Kinder, an insgesamt 872 Standorten. LUNGENSPORT – WIE?: Der klassische Lungensport wird in Präsenzgruppen über eine Dauer von 60 bis 90 Minuten einmal wöchentlich mit einer strukturierten Aufwärm-, Haupt- und Nachbereitungsphase durchgeführt. Die Einführung von Online-Lungensportgruppen seit der Corona-Pandemie ermöglicht ergänzend eine flexible Teilnahme (auch ohne Verordnung). Seit 2021 haben bereits mehr als 11 000 Patienten an Online-Lungensportgruppen teilgenommen. LUNGENSPORT – WARUM?: Studien bestätigen den signifikanten Nutzen eines regelmäßigen körperlichen Trainings, wie z.B. die Steigerung der körperlichen Belastbarkeit und die Reduktion von Atemnot. Der psychosoziale Nutzen und die Förderung der Selbstwirksamkeit werden durch die Gruppenstruktur und die Betreuung durch spezialisierte Übungsleiter unterstützt. Regelmäßiges körperliches Training (z.B. im Rahmen des Lungensports) ist eine kostengünstige und sehr effektive Therapieform zur Verbesserung der Lebensqualität von Patienten mit chronischen Atemwegs- und Lungenerkrankungen.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Thieme. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><CoiStatement>RG ist Vorstandsmitglied der AG Lungensport in Deutschland e.V.; IJ und RK haben keine Interessenskonflikte angegeben.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39437830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/a-2165-5788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>