<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39430718</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2667-2766</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>16</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Exploratory research in clinical and social pharmacy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Explor Res Clin Soc Pharm</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessment of knowledge, perception, and readiness for telepharmacy-assisted pharmaceutical services among young pharmacists in rural Indonesia.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100513</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100513</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100513</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.rcsop.2024.100513</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The implementation of telepharmacy technology has expanded significantly, particularly during the COVID-19 pandemic, to ensure continuous pharmaceutical care services. This practice is vital in rural and underserved areas where access to healthcare is limited.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study aims to assess the knowledge, perception, and readiness of young pharmacists in rural Indonesia towards telepharmacy-assisted pharmaceutical services.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A cross-sectional study was conducted from January to July 2023 in rural areas of Java, Sumatra, and Kalimantan, Indonesia. A convenience sampling method was employed with the aim of recruiting 520 registered pharmacists under 35 years of age (23-34 years old). Data were collected using an online questionnaire adapted for the local context and analyzed using SPSS version 26.0.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The study achieved an 86.67 % response rate. Most participants were female (73.1 %) and aged between 26 and 30 years (53.8 %). Nearly all pharmacists (97.1 %) held a Pharm.D degree. The knowledge assessment showed high awareness of telepharmacy's importance and its role during the COVID-19 pandemic, with 96.15 % recognizing the need for a strong internet connection. Positive perception was noted, with 90.38 % agreeing that telepharmacy enhances medication access in rural areas. However, concerns about increased error rates and workload were highlighted. A substantial proportion of pharmacists expressed readiness for conducting drug counselling via video consultation (44.23 %) and showed a willingness to undergo relevant training (59.62 %).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Young pharmacists in rural Indonesia demonstrate a good level of knowledge and generally positive perceptions about telepharmacy, with notable readiness among pharmacists with less than five years of experience. While there is notable willingness to engage in telepharmacy practices and training, addressing concerns about workload and data security through targeted support and training will be crucial for the successful implementation of telepharmacy, potentially enhancing healthcare access in rural areas.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghozali</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Thesa</ForeName><Initials>MT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Management, School of Pharmacy, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Universitas Muhammadiyah Yogyakarta, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Explor Res Clin Soc Pharm</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918266300706676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2667-2766</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Knowledge</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Perception</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Readiness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rural health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Young pharmacists</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39430718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11489386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.rcsop.2024.100513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2667-2766(24)00110-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alhmoud E., Al Khiyami D., Barazi R., et al. Perspectives of clinical pharmacists on the provision of pharmaceutical care through telepharmacy services during COVID-19 pandemic in Qatar: a focus group. PLoS One. 2022 Oct 13;17(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9560548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36228028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dat T.V., Tran T.D., My N.T., et al. Pharmacists’ perspectives on the use of Telepharmacy in response to COVID-19 pandemic in Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam. J Pharm Technol. 2022 Apr;38(2):106–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9096850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35571348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viegas R., Dineen-Griffin S., Söderlund L.Å., Acosta-Gómez J., Maria Guiu J. Telepharmacy and pharmaceutical care: a narrative review by international pharmaceutical federation. Farm. Hosp. 2022 Oct 30;46(7):86–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36520563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimber M., Peterson G. Telepharmacy-enabling technology to provide quality pharmacy services in rural and remote communities. J. Pharm. Pract. Res. 2006 Jun;1(36):128–133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poudel A., Nissen L. Telepharmacy: a pharmacist&amp;rsquo;s perspective on the clinical benefits and challenges. IPRP. 2016 Oct;5:75–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5741040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29354542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alotaibi Y.K., Federico F. The impact of health information technology on patient safety. Saudi Med J. 2017 Dec;38(12):1173–1180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5787626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29209664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhammad K., Baraka M.A., Shah S.S., et al. Exploring the perception and readiness of pharmacists towards telepharmacy implementation; a cross sectional analysis. PeerJ. 2022;10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9147315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35637711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alfian SD, Khoiry QA, Andhika A. Pratama M, Pradipta IS, Kristina SA, Zairina E, Hak E, Abdulah R. Knowledge, perception, and willingness to provide telepharmacy services among pharmacy students: a multicenter cross-sectional study in Indonesia. BMC Med Educ 2023 Oct 26;23:800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10601297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37884985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unni E.J., Patel K., Beazer I.R., Hung M. Telepharmacy during COVID-19: a scoping review. Pharmacy (Basel) 2021 Nov 11;9(4):183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8628897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34842823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nwachuya C.A., Umeh A.U., Ogwurumba J.C., Chinedu-Eze I.N., Azubuike C.C., Isah A. Effectiveness of Telepharmacy in rural communities in Africa: a scoping review. J Pharm Technol. 2023 Oct;39(5):241–246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10515969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37745733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermansyah A., Wulandari L., Kristina S.A., Meilianti S. Primary health care policy and vision for community pharmacy and pharmacists in Indonesia. Pharm Pract (Granada) 2020;18(3):2085</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32774531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wathoni N., Lestari K., Iftinan G.N., et al. Knowledge, perception, and readiness of Indonesian pharmacists for the implementation of Telepharmacy-based Pharmaceutical Services in Indonesia. Integr Pharm Res Pract. 2023 Nov;22(12):213–225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10676650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38021082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poudel A., Nissen L.M. Telepharmacy: a pharmacist&amp;rsquo;s perspective on the clinical benefits and challenges. IPRP. 2016 Oct;26(5):75–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5741040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29354542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ameri A., Salmanizadeh F., Keshvardoost S., Bahaadinbeigy K. Investigating Pharmacists’ views on Telepharmacy: prioritizing key relationships, barriers, and benefits. J Pharm Technol. 2020 Oct;36(5):171–178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7453475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34752571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senbekov M., Saliev T., Bukeyeva Z., et al. The recent Progress and applications of digital Technologies in Healthcare: a review. Int. J. Telemed. Appl. 2020 Dec;3(2020):8830200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7732404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33343657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abu-Farha R., Alzoubi K.H., Abu Assab M., et al. Perception and willingness to use Telepharmacy among the general population in Jordan. Patient Prefer Adherence. 2023 Aug;25(17):2131–2140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10464898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37650044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moulaei K., Shanbehzadeh M., Bahaadinbeigy K., Kazemi-Arpanahi H. Survey of the patients’ perspectives and preferences in adopting telepharmacy versus in-person visits to the pharmacy: a feasibility study during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMC Med. Inform. Decision Making. 2022 Apr 13;22(1):99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9005615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35418072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeman A. The digital transformation in pharmacy: embracing online platforms and the cosmeceutical paradigm shift. J. Health Popul. Nutr. 2024 May;8(43):60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11080122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38720390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Mutairi A.M., Alshabeeb M.A., Abohelaika S., Alomar F.A., Bidasee K.R. Impact of telemedicine on glycemic control in type 2 diabetes mellitus during the COVID-19 lockdown period. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 2023 Feb;3(14):1068018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9936328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36817609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farooqi M.H., Abdelmannan D.K., Al Buflasa M.M., et al. The Impact of Telemonitoring on Improving Glycemic and Metabolic Control in Previously Lost-to-Follow-Up Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus: A Single-Center Interventional Study in the United Arab Emirates. Int. J. Clin. Pract. 2022 Apr 20:6286574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9159213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35685530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruns B.E., Lorenzo-Castro S.A., Hale G.M. Controlling blood pressure during a pandemic: the impact of Telepharmacy for primary care patients. J. Pharm. Pract. 2024 Apr;37(2):364–368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9606639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vo A.T., Gustafson D.L. Telepharmacy in oncology care: a scoping review. J. Telemed. Telecare. 2023 Apr;29(3):165–176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33377820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tegegne M.D., Wubante S.M., Melaku M.S., et al. Tele-pharmacy perception, knowledge and associated factors among pharmacy students in Northwest Ethiopia: an input for implementers. BMC Medical Education. 2023 Feb 27;23(1):130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9969706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36849956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AbdK Umar, Limpikirati P., Zothantluanga J.H., Shumkova M.M., Prosvirkin G., Luckanagul J.A.  In: Artificial Intelligence, Big Data, Blockchain and 5G for the Digital Transformation of the Healthcare Industry [Internet] De Pablos P.O., Zhang X., editors. Academic Press; 2024 [cited 2024 May 17]. Chapter 6 - Telepharmacy: A modern solution for expanding access to pharmacy services; pp. 111–150.https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9780443215988000099 (Information Technologies in Healthcare Industry). Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghozali M.T. Implementation of the IoT-based technology on patient medication adherence: a comprehensive bibliometric and systematic review. J Inform. Comm. Technol. 2023 Oct 25;22(4):503–544.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marjadi B., Alfian R., Susanto Y., Tjandra L., Pratama A.N.W., Schneider C. Pharmacists’ continuing professional development for non-communicable diseases management: a consensus study. Res. Soc. Adm. Pharm. 2022 Nov 1;18(11):3964–3973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35864038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meilianti S., Smith F., Ernawati D.K., Pratita R.N., Bates I. A country-level national needs assessment of the Indonesian pharmacy workforce. Res. Soc. Adm. Pharm. 2021 Nov 1;17(11):1989–1996.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33766504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim O.M., Ibrahim R.M., Meslamani A.Z.A., Mazrouei N.A. Role of telepharmacy in pharmacist counselling to coronavirus disease 2019 patients and medication dispensing errors. J. Telemed Telecare [Internet] 2020 Oct 15 doi: 10.1177/1357633X20964347. [cited 2024 May 17]; Available from.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1357633X20964347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33059541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thai T., Plotke M., Downing G., Olmsted E., Cook B., Jafri F.N. Telehealth pharmacist approach to comprehensive medication Management in Post-Discharge High-Risk Patients: a quality improvement initiative. Telemedicine and e-Health. 2024 Apr;30(4):976–986.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37976134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed N.J., Almalki Z.S., Alsawadi A.H., et al. Knowledge, perceptions, and readiness of telepharmacy among community pharmacists. Saudi Pharmaceutical Journal. 2023 Sep 1;31(9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10406857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37559867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alnajrani R., Alnajrani N., Aldakheel F., et al. An assessment of the knowledge, perception, and willingness to use Telepharmacy services among the general public in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. Cureus. 2022 Nov;22:14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9772859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36569686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stratton S.J. Population research: convenience sampling strategies. Prehosp Disaster med. 2021 Aug;36(4):373–374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34284835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emerson R.W. Convenience sampling revisited: embracing its limitations through thoughtful study design. J. Vis. Impair. Blindness. 2021 Jan;115(1):76–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yani NSBM, Hussein SSB, Bakar NAA, Lokman A. Evaluating the Adoption of Enterprise Architecture in Universiti Teknologi MARA, Malaysia. In: Uden L, Ting IH, editors. Knowledge Management in Organisations [Internet]. Cham: Springer Nature Switzerland; 2024 [cited 2024 Jul 23]. p. 211–22. (Communications in Computer and Information Science; vol. 2152). Available from: 10.1007/978-3-031-63269-3_16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-63269-3_16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elnaem M.H., Akkawi M.E., Al-shami A.K., Elkalmi R. Telepharmacy knowledge, perceptions, and readiness among future Malaysian pharmacists amid the COVID-19 pandemic. IJPER. 2022 Jan 12;56(1):09–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed N.J., Almalki Z.S., Alsawadi A.H., et al. Knowledge, perceptions, and readiness of Telepharmacy among hospital pharmacists in Saudi Arabia. Healthcare (Basel) 2023 Apr 11;11(8):1087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10137432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37107921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed N.J., Almalki Z.S., Alsawadi A.H., et al. Knowledge, perceptions, and readiness of telepharmacy among community pharmacists. Saudi Pharm J. 2023 Sep;31(9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10406857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37559867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dzakadzie Y., Quansah F. Modeling unit non-response and validity of online teaching evaluation in higher education using generalizability theory approach. Front Psychol [Internet] 2023 Sep 4:14. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1202896/full. [cited 2024 May 20]. Available from:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1202896/full</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10507623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37731882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiedermann C.J., Barbieri V., Engl A., Piccoliori G. Relational Coordination at the Primary–Secondary Care Interface: Insights from a Cross-Sectional Survey in the South Tyrolean Healthcare System. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2024 Apr;21(4):425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11050390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38673336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilma L., Putri K., Mustikaningtias I., Sholihat N., Parmasari D. Telepharmacy knowledge, attitude, and experience among pharmacy students in Indonesia: a cross-sectional study. Pharm. Educ. 2024 Jan;20(24):40–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jauza J., Dari I.I.  In: 2023 3rd International Conference on Emerging Smart Technologies and Applications (eSmarTA) [Internet] IEEE; Taiz, Yemen: 2023. Understanding the knowledge, attitudes, and perceptions of Indonesian young pharmacists towards Telepharmacy implementation in pharmacy services; pp. 1–7.https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10293223/ [cited 2024 May 20]. Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Meslamani A.Z. Technical and regulatory challenges of digital health implementation in developing countries. J. Med. Econ. 2023 Dec 31;26(1):1057–1060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37594521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeman A. The digital transformation in pharmacy: embracing online platforms and the cosmeceutical paradigm shift. J. Health Popul. Nutr. 2024 May;8(43):60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11080122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38720390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tjiptoatmadja N.N., Alfian S.D. Knowledge, perception, and willingness to use Telepharmacy among the general population in Indonesia. Front. Public Health. 2022 May;11(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9130580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35646788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilma D.L., Putri K.M., Mustikaningtias I., Sholihat N.K., Parmasari D.H. Telepharmacy knowledge, attitude, and experience among pharmacy students in Indonesia: a cross-sectional study. Pharm. Educ. 2024 Jan 20;24(1):40–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muflih S.M., Al-Azzam S., Abuhammad S., Jaradat S.K., Karasneh R., Shawaqfeh M.S. Pharmacists’ experience, competence and perception of telepharmacy technology in response to COVID-19. Int J Clin Pract [Internet] 2021 Jul;75(7) doi: 10.1111/ijcp.14209. Available from:. [cited 2024 Jul 22];</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijcp.14209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33819372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yingngam B., Khumsikiew J., Netthong R.  Multi-Sector Analysis of the Digital Healthcare Industry [Internet] IGI Global; 2024. Motivations and Barriers to Using Digital Healthcare; pp. 33–79.https://www.igi-global.com/chapter/motivations-and-barriers-to-using-digital-healthcare/www.igi-global.com/chapter/motivations-and-barriers-to-using-digital-healthcare/343157 [cited 2024 May 20]. Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondi DS, Acquisto NM, Buckley MS, Erdman G, Kerns ST, Nwaesei AS, Szymanski TW, Walkerly A, Yau AS, Martello JL. Rewards, Recognition, and Advancement for Clinical Pharmacists. JACCP: JOURNAL OF THE AMERICAN COLLEGE OF CLINICAL PHARMACY. 2023;Vol. 6(4):427–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alfian S., Khoiry Q.A., Pratama M., et al. Knowledge, perception, and willingness to provide telepharmacy services among pharmacy students: a multicenter cross-sectional study in Indonesia. BMC Medical Education. 2023 Oct;26:23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10601297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37884985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tjiptoatmadja N.N., Alfian S.D. Knowledge, perception, and willingness to use Telepharmacy among the general population in Indonesia. Front. Public Health. 2022 May;11(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9130580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35646788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovacs R., Lagarde M. Does high workload reduce the quality of healthcare? Evidence from rural Senegal. J. Health Econ. 2022 Mar;82</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9023795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35196633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warnes E., Done E.J., Knowler H. Mainstream teachers’ concerns about inclusive education for children with special educational needs and disability in England under pre-pandemic conditions. J. Res. Spec. Educ. Needs. 2022;22(1):31–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Entringer Bottacin W., de Souza T.T., Melchiors A.C., Reis W.C.T. Preparing pharmacists for the digital age: how pharmacy courses are adapting to challenges and opportunities. Am. J. Pharm. Educ. 2024 Jun 1;88(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38636780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Worafi Y.M. In: Handbook of Medical and Health Sciences in Developing Countries: Education, Practice, and Research [Internet] Al-Worafi Y.M., editor. Springer International Publishing; Cham: 2023 [cited 2024 May 20]. Pharmacy education: Comparison between the developing countries; pp. 1–38. Available from:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-74786-2_499-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shafiee Hanjani L., Caffery L.J., Freeman C.R., Peeters G., Peel N.M. A scoping review of the use and impact of telehealth medication reviews. Res. Soc. Adm. Pharm. 2020 Aug 1;16(8):1140–1153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31874815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vo A.T., Gustafson D.L. Telepharmacy in oncology care: a scoping review. J. Telemed. Telecare. 2023 Apr 1;29(3):165–176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33377820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poudel A., Nissen L.M. Telepharmacy: a pharmacist’s perspective on the clinical benefits and challenges. Integr Pharm Res Pract. 2016 Oct;26(5):75–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5741040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29354542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frenzel J., Porter A. The need to educate pharmacy students in Telepharmacy and telehealth. Am. J. Pharm. Educ. 2021 Sep;85(8):8566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34615629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Worafi Y.M. In: Handbook of Medical and Health Sciences in Developing Countries: Education, Practice, and Research [Internet] Al-Worafi Y.M., editor. Springer International Publishing; Cham: 2023 [cited 2024 May 20]. Pharmacy education, practice, and research in Palestine; pp. 1–50. Available from:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-74786-2_486-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Worafi Y.M. In: Handbook of Medical and Health Sciences in Developing Countries: Education, Practice, and Research [Internet] Al-Worafi Y.M., editor. Springer International Publishing; Cham: 2023 [cited 2024 May 20]. Pharmacy education, practice, and research in Saudi Arabia; pp. 1–38. Available from:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-74786-2_477-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anawade P.A., Sharma D., Gahane S. A comprehensive review on exploring the impact of telemedicine on healthcare accessibility. Cureus [Internet]. 2024 Mar 12. [cited 2024 Jul 22]. 16 (3); p. 1-12. Available from: https://www.cureus.com/articles/232773-a-comprehensive-review-on-exploring-the-impact-of-telemedicine-on-healthcare-accessibility.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11009553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38618307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Widowati I.G.A.R., Zamroni M. Indonesia facing challenges of pharmaceutical care implementation in community pharmacies: a legal perspective. Jurnal Hukum Prasada. 2023 Oct 2;10(2):69–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guadamuz J.S., McCormick C.D., Choi S., Urick B., Alexander G.C., Qato D.M. Telepharmacy and medication adherence in urban areas. J. Am. Pharm. Assoc. 2021 Mar 1;61(2):e100–e113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33246835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emadi F., Ghanbarzadegan A., Ghahramani S., Bastani P., Baysari M.T. Factors affecting medication adherence among older adults using tele-pharmacy services: a scoping review. Arch. Public Health. 2022 Aug 31;80(1):199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9429665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36042508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpini J.A., Sharma A., Kubicki Evans M., et al. Pharmacists and mental health first aid training: a comparative analysis of confidence, mental health assistance behaviours and perceived barriers. Early Intervention in Psychiatry. 2023;17(7):670–680.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36203236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alowais M., Rudd G., Besa V., Nazar H., Shah T., Tolley C. Digital literacy in undergraduate pharmacy education: a scoping review. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2024 Mar 1;31(3):732–745.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10873839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38055635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>