<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439913</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1664-0640</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in psychiatry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Psychiatry</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Psychological distress and academic success: a two-year study comparing the outcome of two online interventions at a university counseling and consultation service in Italy.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1427316</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1427316</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1427316</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1427316</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The mental health of college students has been a significant concern in higher education, representing a priority for the institutions. Enhancing effective online interventions could represent excellent support for university counseling services that deal with students' well-being. The present study aimed to evaluate the effectiveness of two online interventions provided by the Counseling and Consultation Service for Students (SACS) of the University of L'Aquila (Italy), namely Videochat with Clinical Mental Health consultation (VCMH) and Therapist-supported Internet Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (Ts-iCBT), a 12-module asynchronous program for anxiety management. The primary outcome was focused on the emotional well-being of students (GHQ-12). The secondary academic outcome was represented by the attainment of their final degree.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Students requesting help from the SACS between March 2020 and March 2022 during different periods of the COVID-19 pandemic restrictions were asked to fill out a brief structured screening tool and access the PSYDIT.COM platform. Based on their personal preferences, students chose to access one of the two different online interventions: VCMH and Ts-iCBT.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Over the two-year duration of this study, 379 students (267 women, 70.4%) contacted the service. Out of 334 students, 72.5% asked to be included in the Ts-iCBT group, whereas 27.5% expressed a preference for the VCMH group. A statistically significant decrease in emotional distress was obtained by both forms of online intervention, highlighting a better outcome for VCMH. In addition to clinical variables, 28.8% of students who completed online interventions attained their degree, with a statistically significantly higher percentage of graduated students in the Ts-iCBT compared to VCMH group. A high proportion of students (37.7% of total sample) dropped out (DO) of digital interventions, with a statistically significant lower rate of dropouts in the VCMH group.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The effectiveness of online interventions is extremely promising and yields a growing source of suggestions for use in providing more tailored interventions. Videochats and frequent therapist online contacts would be recommended for more severe psychopathological conditions. Students in conditions of moderate and non-severe emotional distress who feel more able to "manage the problem alone" could be addressed to asynchronous online interventions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Mammarella, Giusti, Del Vecchio, Salza, Casacchia and Roncone.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mammarella</LastName><ForeName>Silvia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life, Health and Environmental Sciences, University of L'Aquila, L'Aquila, Abruzzo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giusti</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life, Health and Environmental Sciences, University of L'Aquila, L'Aquila, Abruzzo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Del Vecchio</LastName><ForeName>Sasha</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life, Health and Environmental Sciences, University of L'Aquila, L'Aquila, Abruzzo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salza</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life, Health and Environmental Sciences, University of L'Aquila, L'Aquila, Abruzzo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Casacchia</LastName><ForeName>Massimo</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life, Health and Environmental Sciences, University of L'Aquila, L'Aquila, Abruzzo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roncone</LastName><ForeName>Rita</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life, Health and Environmental Sciences, University of L'Aquila, L'Aquila, Abruzzo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Unit Rehabilitation Treatment, Early Interventions in Mental Health-San Salvatore Hospital, L'Aquila, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Psychiatry</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101545006</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1664-0640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Italian university counseling services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">academic outcome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical psychology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cognitive-behavioral therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">online intervention</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">synchronous vs asynchronous technologies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">young people</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11493717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1427316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kim B, Jee S, Lee J, An S, Lee SM. Relationships between social support and student burnout: A meta-analytic approach. Stress Health. (2018) 34(1):127–34. doi: 10.1002/smi.v34.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/smi.v34.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28639354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahedi H, Sahebihagh MH, Sarbakhsh P. The magnitude of loneliness and associated risk factors among university students: A cross-sectional study. Iran J Psychiatry. (2022) 17:411–7. doi: 10.18502/ijps.v17i4.10690</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18502/ijps.v17i4.10690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9922349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36817808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarokhani D, Delpisheh A, Veisani Y, Sarokhani MT, Manesh RE, Sayehmiri K. Prevalence of depression among university students: A systematic review and meta-analysis study. Depress Res Treat. (2013) 2013:373857. doi: 10.1155/2013/373857</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2013/373857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3800630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24187615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramon-Arbues E, Gea-Caballero V, Granada-Lopez JM, Juarez-Vela R, Pellicer-Garcia B, Anton-Solanas I. The prevalence of depression, anxiety and stress and their associated factors in college students. Int J Environ Res Public Health. (2020) 17(19). doi: 10.3390/ijerph17197001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17197001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7579351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32987932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan GXD, Soh XC, Hartanto A, Goh AYH, Majeed NM. Prevalence of anxiety in college and university students: An umbrella review. J Affect Disord Rep. (2023) 14. doi: 10.1016/j.jadr.2023.100658</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadr.2023.100658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L. Research on the construction of university public health emergency management system based on psychological counseling intervention. J Healthc Eng. (2022) 2022:2033018. doi: 10.1155/2022/2033018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/2033018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8769819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35070227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giusti L, Mammarella S, Salza A, Del Vecchio S, Ussorio D, Casacchia M, et al. . Predictors of academic performance during the covid-19 outbreak: impact of distance education on mental health, social cognition and memory abilities in an Italian university student sample. BMC Psychol. (2021) 9(1):142. doi: 10.1186/s40359-021-00649-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40359-021-00649-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8441245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34526153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Martinez I, Augusto-Landa JM, Quijano-Lopez R, Leon SP. Self-concept as a mediator of the relation between university students' Resilience and academic achievement. Front Psychol. (2021) 12:747168. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.747168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.747168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8764197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35058836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Z, Luo W. Discrete achievement emotions as mediators between achievement goals and academic engagement of Singapore students. Educ Psychol. (2022) 42:749–66. doi: 10.1080/01443410.2022.2048795</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01443410.2022.2048795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem MS, Isha ASN, Awan MI, Yusop YB, Naji GMA. Fostering academic engagement in post-graduate students: assessing the role of positive emotions, positive psychology, and stress. Front Psychol. (2022) 13:920395. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2022.920395</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.920395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9397401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36017439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell SL. The work of college counseling centers in the early 21st century. Am Psychol. (2023) 78:1125–36. doi: 10.1037/amp0001249</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/amp0001249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38166284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Co MJ, Hamadeh Kerbage S, Willetts G, Garvey L, Bhattacharya A, Croy G, et al. . Students coping with change in higher education: An overview. Educ Res Rev. (2023) 38. doi: 10.1016/j.edurev.2023.100508</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.edurev.2023.100508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erekson DM, Bailey RJ, Cattani K, Klundt JS, Lynn AM, Jensen D, et al. . Psychotherapy session frequency: A naturalistic examination in a university counseling center. J Couns Psychol. (2022) 69:531–40. doi: 10.1037/cou0000593</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/cou0000593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34780207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ning X, Wong JP, Huang S, Fu Y, Gong X, Zhang L, et al. . Chinese university students' Perspectives on help-seeking and mental health counseling. Int J Environ Res Public Health. (2022) 19. doi: 10.3390/ijerph19148259</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19148259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9323838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35886103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghilardi A, Buizza C, Carobbio EM, Lusenti R. Detecting and managing mental health issues within young adults. A systematic review on college counselling in Italy. Clin Pract Epidemiol Ment Health. (2017) 13:61–70. doi: 10.2174/1745017901713010061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1745017901713010061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5543617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28839455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scruggs R, Broglia E, Barkham M, Duncan C. The impact of psychological distress and university counselling on academic outcomes: Analysis of a routine practice-based dataset. Counselling Psychother Res. (2023) 23:781–9. doi: 10.1002/capr.12640</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/capr.12640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKenzie K, Murray KR, Murray AL, Richelieu M. The effectiveness of university counselling for students with academic issues. Counselling Psychother Res. (2015) 15:284–8. doi: 10.1002/capr.12034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/capr.12034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Lauretis I, Giordani Paesani N, Di Venanzio C, Pollice R, Roncone R, Casacchia M. Servizio di Ascolto e Consultazione per Studenti. L’esperienza del S.A.C.S. dell’Università degli Studi dell’Aquila. Med Chir. (2013) 8:2582–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casacchia M, Pollice R, Roncone R. The narrative epidemiology of L'Aquila 2009 earthquake. Epidemiol Psychiatr Sci. (2012) 21:13–21. doi: 10.1017/S2045796011000801</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S2045796011000801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22670407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giusti L, Ussorio D, Salza A, Malavolta M, Aggio A, Bianchini V, et al. . Preliminary study of effects on paranoia ideation and jumping to conclusions in the context of group treatment of anxiety disorders in young people. Early Interv Psychiatry. (2018) 12(6):1072–80. doi: 10.1111/eip.2018.12.issue-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/eip.2018.12.issue-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28124444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salza A, Giusti L, Ussorio D, Casacchia M, Roncone R. Cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) anxiety management and reasoning bias modification in young adults with anxiety disorders: A real-world study of a therapist-assisted computerized (TACCBT) program Vs. "person-to-person" group CBT. Internet Interv. (2020) 19:100305. doi: 10.1016/j.invent.2020.100305</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.invent.2020.100305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7005461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32055452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giusti L, Salza A, Mammarella S, Bianco D, Ussorio D, Casacchia M, et al. . #Everything will be fine. Duration of home confinement and "All-or-nothing" Cognitive thinking style as predictors of traumatic distress in young university students on a digital platform during the COVID-19 Italian lockdown. Front Psychiatry. (2020) 11:574812. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2020.574812</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.574812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7770221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33384623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collaborators C-MD. Global prevalence and burden of depressive and anxiety disorders in 204 countries and territories in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Lancet. (2021) 398:1700–12. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02143-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02143-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34634250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haig-Ferguson A, Cooper K, Cartwright E, Loades ME, Daniels J. Practitioner review: health anxiety in children and young people in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. Behav Cognit Psychother. (2021) 49(6):129–43. doi: 10.1017/S1352465820000636</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1352465820000636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7503041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32829718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Brien M, McNicholas F. The use of telepsychiatry during COVID-19 and beyond. Ir J Psychol Med. (2020) 37:250–5. doi: 10.1017/ipm.2020.54</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/ipm.2020.54</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7411439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32434596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hubley S, Lynch SB, Schneck C, Thomas M, Shore J. Review of key telepsychiatry outcomes. World J Psychiatry. (2016) 6(2):269–82. doi: 10.5498/wjp.v6.i2.269</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5498/wjp.v6.i2.269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4919267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27354970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Rodriguez MA, Qian M, Kishimoto T, Lin M, Berger T. Predictors of treatment outcomes and adherence in internet-based cognitive behavioral therapy for social anxiety in China. Behav Cognit Psychother. (2020) 48(3):291–303. doi: 10.1017/S1352465819000730</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1352465819000730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31928568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pauley D, Cuijpers P, Papola D, Miguel C, Karyotaki E. Two decades of digital interventions for anxiety disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis of treatment effectiveness. Psychol Med. (2023) 53(2):567–79. doi: 10.1017/S0033291721001999</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0033291721001999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9899576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34047264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weineland S, Ribbegardh R, Kivi M, Bygdell A, Larsson A, Vernmark K, et al. . Transitioning from face-to-face treatment to iCBT for youths in primary care - therapists' attitudes and experiences. Internet Interv. (2020) 22:100356. doi: 10.1016/j.invent.2020.100356</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.invent.2020.100356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7724368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33318951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ierardi E, Bottini M, Riva Crugnola C. Effectiveness of an online versus face-to-face psychodynamic counselling intervention for university students before and during the COVID-19 period. BMC Psychol. (2022) 10(1):35. doi: 10.1186/s40359-022-00742-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40359-022-00742-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8861610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35193671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celia G, Tessitore F, Cavicchiolo E, Girelli L, Limone P, Cozzolino M. Improving university students' Mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: evidence from an online counseling intervention in Italy. Front Psychiatry. (2022) 13:886538. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2022.886538</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.886538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9157237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35664487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carbone GA, Zarfati A, Nicoli MS, Paulis A, Tourjansky G, Valenti G, et al. . Online psychological counselling during lockdown reduces anxiety symptoms and negative affect: Insights from Italian framework. Clin Psychol Psychother. (2022) 29(1):367–72. doi: 10.1002/cpp.v29.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cpp.v29.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33950537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paganin G, Apolinario-Hagen J, Simbula S. Introducing mobile apps to promote the well-being of German and Italian university students. A cross-national application of the Technology Acceptance Model. Curr Psychol. (2022) p:1–12. doi: 10.1007/s12144-022-03856-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12144-022-03856-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9610310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36320558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan S, Li L, Torous J, Gratzer D, Yellowlees PM. Review of use of asynchronous technologies incorporated in mental health care. Curr Psychiatry Rep. (2018) 20(10):85. doi: 10.1007/s11920-018-0954-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11920-018-0954-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30155593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaya M, Erdem C. Students’ Well-being and academic achievement: A meta-analysis study. Child Indic Res. (2021) 14:1743–67. doi: 10.1007/s12187-021-09821-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12187-021-09821-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klap J. Cross-sectional examination of the relationship between learning environment and anxiety among dental hygiene students. J Dent Educ. (2024). doi: 10.1002/jdd.13694</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jdd.13694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39177150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaharias G. What is narrative-based medicine? Narrative-based medicine 1. Can Fam Physician. (2018) 64:176–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5851389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29540381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Launer J. Narrative-Based Primary Care. A Practical Guide. Abington, UK: Radcliffe Medical Press; (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fontanesi F, Gobetti C, Zimmermann-Tansella C, Tansella M. Validation of the Italian version of the GHQ in a general practice setting. Psychol Med. (1985) 15(2):411–5. doi: 10.1017/S0033291700023710</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0033291700023710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4023145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldberg DP, Rickels K, Downing R, Hesbacher P. A comparison of two psychiatric screening tests. Br J Psychiatry. (1976) 129:61–7. doi: 10.1192/bjp.129.1.61</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.129.1.61</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">938806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piccinelli M, Bisoffi G, Bon MG, Cunico L, Tansella M. Validity and test-retest reliability of the Italian version of the 12-item General Health Questionnaire in general practice: a comparison between three scoring methods. Compr Psychiatry. (1993) 34(3):198–205. doi: 10.1016/0010-440X(93)90048-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0010-440X(93)90048-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8339539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zung WW. A rating instrument for anxiety disorders. Psychosomatics. (1971) 12:371–9. doi: 10.1016/S0033-3182(71)71479-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0033-3182(71)71479-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5172928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beck AT, Steer RA, Brown GK. Manual for the Beck Depression Inventory-Ii. (1996) San Antonio: Psychological Corporation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creamer M, Bell R, Failla S. Psychometric properties of the impact of event scale - revised. Behav Res Ther. (2003) 41:1489–96. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2003.07.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.brat.2003.07.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14705607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daly M, Robinson E. Anxiety Reported by Us Adults in 2019 and During the 2020 Covid-19 Pandemic: Population-Based Evidence from Two Nationally Representative Samples. J Affect Disord. (2021) 286:296–300. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2021.02.054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.02.054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9754788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33756307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ettman CK, Abdalla SM, Cohen GH, Sampson L, Vivier PM, Galea S, et al. . Prevalence of Depression Symptoms in Us Adults before and During the Covid-19 Pandemic. JAMA Netw Open. (2020) 3:e2019686. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.19686</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.19686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7489837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32876685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roncone R, Ussorio D, Salza A, Casacchia M. Psychiatric Rehabilitation in Italy: Cinderella No More—the Contribution of Psychiatric Rehabilitation Technicians. International Journal of Mental Health. (2016) 45:24–31. doi: 10.1080/00207411.2015.1119376</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00207411.2015.1119376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connell J, Barkham M, Mellor-Clark J. The effectiveness of UK student counselling services: an analysis using the CORE System. Br J Guidance Counselling. (2008) 36(1):1–18. doi: 10.1080/03069880701715655</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03069880701715655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strepparava MG, Bani M, Zorzi F, Corrias D, Dolce R, Rezzonico G. Cognitive counselling intervention: treatment effectiveness in an Italian university centre. Br J Guidance Counselling. (2015) 44(4):423–33. doi: 10.1080/03069885.2015.1110561</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03069885.2015.1110561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo Moro G, Gualano MR, Vicentini C, Marengo N, Bert F, Siliquini R. Effectiveness of university-provided individual counselling for healthcare students: A systematic review. Student Success. (2023). doi: 10.5204/ssj.3019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5204/ssj.3019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerolini S, Zagaria A, Franchini C, Maniaci VG, Fortunato A, Petrocchi C, et al. . Psychological counseling among university students worldwide: A systematic review. Eur J Investig Health Psychol Educ. (2023) 13(9):1831–49. doi: 10.3390/ejihpe13090133</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ejihpe13090133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10528000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37754472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granieri A, Franzoi IG, Chung MC. Editorial: psychological distress among university students. Front Psychol. (2021) 12:647940. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.647940</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.647940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8019774</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33828513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quintiliani L, Sisto A, Vicinanza F, Curcio G, Tambone V. Resilience and psychological impact on Italian university students during COVID-19 pandemic. Distance learning and health. Psychol Health Med. (2022) 27(1):69–80. doi: 10.1080/13548506.2021.1891266</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13548506.2021.1891266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33602027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villani L, Pastorino R, Molinari E, Anelli F, Ricciardi W, Graffigna G, et al. . Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on psychological well-being of students in an Italian university: a web-based cross-sectional survey. Global Health. (2021) 17(1):39. doi: 10.1186/s12992-021-00680-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12992-021-00680-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8022300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33823897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meda N, Pardini S, Slongo I, Bodini L, Zordan MA, Rigobello P, et al. . Students' mental health problems before, during, and after COVID-19 lockdown in Italy. J Psychiatr Res. (2021) 134:69–77. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2020.12.045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2020.12.045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33360865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savarese G, Curcio L, D'Elia D, Fasano O, Pecoraro N. Online university counselling services and psychological problems among italian students in lockdown due to Covid-19. Healthcare (Basel). (2020) 8(4). doi: 10.3390/healthcare8040440</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/healthcare8040440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7712388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33137963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpiniello B, Tusconi M, Zanalda E, Di Sciascio G, Di Giannantonio M, Executive Committee of The Italian Society of P . Psychiatry during the Covid-19 pandemic: a survey on mental health departments in Italy. BMC Psychiatry. (2020) 20(1):593. doi: 10.1186/s12888-020-02997-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-020-02997-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7739792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33327940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franzoi IG, Sauta MD, Barbagli F, Avalle C, Granieri A. Psychological interventions for higher education students in Europe: A systematic literature review. Youth. (2022) 2(3):236–57. doi: 10.3390/youth2030017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/youth2030017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebert DD, Mortier P, Kaehlke F, Bruffaerts R, Baumeister H, Auerbach RP, et al. . Barriers of mental health treatment utilization among first-year college students: First cross-national results from the WHO World Mental Health International College Student Initiative. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. (2019) 28(2):e1782. doi: 10.1002/mpr.v28.2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mpr.v28.2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6522323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31069905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osborn TG, Li S, Saunders R, Fonagy P. University students’ use of mental health services: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Ment Health Syst. (2022) 16(1). doi: 10.1186/s13033-022-00569-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13033-022-00569-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9758037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36527036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautam S, Jain A, Gautam M, Vahia VN, Grover S. Clinical practice guidelines for the management of depression. Indian J Psychiatry. (2017) 59(Suppl 1):S34–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5310101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28216784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
National Institute for Care and Clinical Excellence, N . Depression in children and young people: identification and management. (2019). Available from: https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31577402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodas JA, Leon-Rojas J, Rooney B. Mind over mood: exploring the executive function's role in downregulation. Front Psychol. (2024) 15:1322055. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1322055</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1322055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10850342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38333058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acosta-Gonzaga E. The effects of self-esteem and academic engagement on university students' Performance. Behav Sci (Basel). (2023) 13(4). doi: 10.3390/bs13040348</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bs13040348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10136102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37102862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giusti L, Mammarella S, Salza A, Ussorio D, Bianco D, Casacchia M, et al. . Heart and Head: Profiles and Predictors of Self-Assessed Cognitive and Affective Empathy in a Sample of Medical and Health Professional Students. Front Psychol. (2021) 12:632996. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.632996</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.632996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34220610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laquale MG, Stella A, Taurino A. Il counselling psicodinamico per studenti universitari. In: Una ricerca empirica di valutazione dell'efficacia, vol. 2. Psicologia Della Salute; (2015) (2):76–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buizza C, Ghilardi A, Olivetti E, Costa A. Dropouts from a university counselling service: a quantitative and qualitative study. Br J Guidance Counselling. (2019) 47(5):590–602. doi: 10.1080/03069885.2019.1566513</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03069885.2019.1566513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monti FT,L, Ricci Bitti PE. Il Servizio di Aiuto Psicologico (SAP) dell’Università di Bologna. Psicologia Clinica Dello Sviluppo. (2013) 1:147–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buyruk Genç A, Amanvermez Y, Zeren ŞG, Erus SM. Early separations: Dropout from online and face-to-face counseling. Pegem Eğitim ve Öğretim Dergisi. (2019) 9:1001–30. doi: 10.14527/pegegog.2019.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14527/pegegog.2019.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Vecchio S, Mammarella S, Giusti L, Casacchia M, Roncone R. I Can’t Get No Satisfaction’… experience in the treatment, satisfaction, and professional support of young depressed people using SPARX. Riv Psichiatr. (2024) 59:139–46. doi: 10.1708/4320.43054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1708/4320.43054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39072604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solmi M, Radua J, Olivola M, Croce E, Soardo L, Salazar de Pablo G, et al. . Age at onset of mental disorders worldwide: large-scale meta-analysis of 192 epidemiological studies. Mol Psychiatry. (2022) 27:281–95. doi: 10.1038/s41380-021-01161-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41380-021-01161-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8960395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34079068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>