<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39438943</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1756-0381</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>17</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BioData mining</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BioData Min</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>From COVID-19 to monkeypox: a novel predictive model for emerging infectious diseases.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>42</StartPage><MedlinePgn>42</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">42</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s13040-024-00396-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The outbreak of emerging infectious diseases poses significant challenges to global public health. Accurate early forecasting is crucial for effective resource allocation and emergency response planning. This study aims to develop a comprehensive predictive model for emerging infectious diseases, integrating the blending framework, transfer learning, incremental learning, and the biological feature Rt to increase prediction accuracy and practicality. By transferring features from a COVID-19 dataset to a monkeypox dataset and introducing dynamically updated incremental learning techniques, the model's predictive capability in data-scarce scenarios was significantly improved. The research findings demonstrate that the blending framework performs exceptionally well in short-term (7-day) predictions. Furthermore, the combination of transfer learning and incremental learning techniques significantly enhanced the adaptability and precision, with a 91.41% improvement in the RMSE and an 89.13% improvement in the MAE. In particular, the inclusion of the Rt feature enabled the model to more accurately reflect the dynamics of disease spread, further improving the RMSE by 1.91% and the MAE by 2.17%. This study underscores the significant application potential of multimodel fusion and real-time data updates in infectious disease prediction, offering new theoretical perspectives and technical support. This research not only enriches the theoretical foundation of infectious disease prediction models but also provides reliable technical support for public health emergency responses. Future research should continue to explore integrating data from multiple sources and enhancing model generalization capabilities to further enhance the practicality and reliability of predictive tools.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Deren</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Computing, Universiti Teknologi Malaysia, Johor Bahru, 81310, Malaysia. 2008xuderen@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chan</LastName><ForeName>Weng Howe</ForeName><Initials>WH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UTM Big Data Centre, Ibnu Sina Institute For Scientific and Industrial Resarch Universiti Teknologi, Johor Bahru, 81310, Malaysia. cwenghowe@utm.my.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haron</LastName><ForeName>Habibollah</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Computing, Universiti Teknologi Malaysia, Johor Bahru, 81310, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nies</LastName><ForeName>Hui Wen</ForeName><Initials>HW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Computing, Universiti Teknologi Malaysia, Johor Bahru, 81310, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moorthy</LastName><ForeName>Kohbalan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Computing, Universiti Malaysia Pahang Al-Sultan Abdullah, Pekan, Pahang, 26600, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BioData Min</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101319161</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1756-0381</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biological feature Rt</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Blending framework</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emerging infectious disease prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Incremental learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Transfer learning</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.
</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39438943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13040-024-00396-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s13040-024-00396-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alizargar A, Chang YL, Alkhaleefah M, Tan TH. Precision Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD) Diagnosis: Leveraging Ensemble Machine Learning and Gender Insights for Cost-Effective Detection. Bioengineering (Basel). 2024;11(6):600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11201081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38927836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alqaissi EY, Alotaibi FS, Ramzan MS. Modern machine-learning predictive models for diagnosing infectious diseases. Comput Math Methods Med. 2022;2022(1):1–13. 10.1155/2022/6902321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9185172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35693267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvarez L, Colom M, Morel JD, Morel JM. Computing the daily reproduction number of COVID-19 by inverting the renewal equation using a variational technique. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2021;118(50):e2105112118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8685677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34876517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anjum M, Saher R, Saeed MN. Optimizing type 2 diabetes management: AI-enhanced time series analysis of continuous glucose monitoring data for personalized dietary intervention. PeerJ Computer science. 2024;10: e1971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11057654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38686006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Błażkiewicz M. Evaluation of geometric attractor structure and recurrence analysis in professional dancers. Entropy (Basel). 2022;24(9):1310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9497806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36141196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borré A, Seman LO, Camponogara E, Stefenon SF, Mariani VC, Coelho LDS. Machine fault detection using a hybrid CNN-LSTM attention-based model. Sensors. 2023;23(9):4512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10181692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37177716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canino MP, Cesario E, Vinci A, Zarin S. Epidemic forecasting based on mobility patterns: an approach and experimental evaluation on COVID-19 Data. Soc Netw Anal Min. 2022;12(1):116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9386209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35996384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Champredon D, Papst I, Yusuf W. ern: An [Formula: see text] package to estimate the effective reproduction number using clinical and wastewater surveillance data. PLoS ONE. 2024;19(6): e0305550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11192340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38905266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang H, Esteves IM, Neumann AR, Mohajerani MH, McNaughton BL. Cortical reactivation of spatial and non-spatial features coordinates with hippocampus to form a memory dialogue. Nat Commun. 2023;14(1):7748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10682454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38012135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary V, Khanna V, Ahmed Awan HT, Singh K, Khalid M, Mishra YK, Kaushik A. Towards hospital-on-chip supported by 2D MXenes-based 5th generation intelligent biosensors. Biosensors and bioelectronics. 2023;220: 114847.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9605918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36335709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Guo C, Lu M, Ding S. Unifying diagnosis identification and prediction method embedding the disease ontology structure from electronic medical records. Front Public Health. 2021;9: 793801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8811031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35127624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi SH, Park JK, An D, Kim CH, Park G, Lee I, Lee S. Fault Diagnosis Method for Human Coexistence Robots Based on Convolutional Neural Networks Using Time-Series Data Generation and Image Encoding. Sensors. 2023;23(24):9753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10748154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38139599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciobanu-Caraus O, Aicher A, Kernbach JM, Regli L, Serra C, Staartjes VE. A critical moment in machine learning in medicine: on reproducible and interpretable learning. Acta Neurochir. 2024;166(1):14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10791964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38227273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui L, Agrawal A. Special supplement issue on quality assurance and enrichment of biological and biomedical ontologies and terminologies. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2024;23(Suppl 1):302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11363377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39215285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui R, Hua W, Qu K, Yang H, Tong Y, Li Q, Liu C. An interpretable early dynamic sequential predictor for sepsis-induced coagulopathy progression in the real-world using machine learning. Frontiers in medicine. 2021;8: 775047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8678506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34926518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunningham GB, Watanabe NM, Buzuvis E. Anti-transgender rights legislation and internet searches pertaining to depression and suicide. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(12): e0279420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9778603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36548266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Salazar PM, Lu F, Hay JA, Gómez-Barroso D, Fernández-Navarro P, Martínez EV, Hernán MA. Near real-time surveillance of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic with incomplete data. PLoS computational biology. 2022;18(3): e1009964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9004750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35358171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng Z, Zhang J, Li J, Zhang X. Application of deep learning in plant-microbiota association analysis. Front Genet. 2021;12: 697090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8531731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34691142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Didier AJ, Nigro A, Noori Z, Omballi MA, Pappada SM, Hamouda DM. Application of machine learning for lung cancer survival prognostication-A systematic review and meta-analysis. Frontiers in artificial intelligence. 2024;7: 1365777.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11026647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38646415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding D, Zhang R. China’s COVID-19 control strategy and its impact on the global pandemic. Front Public Health. 2022;10:857003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8964044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35359767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du H, Yu M, Xue H, Lu X, Chang Y, Li Z. Association between sarcopenia and cognitive function in older Chinese adults: Evidence from the China health and retirement longitudinal study. Front Public Health. 2022;10:1078304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9871477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36703834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du M, Huang X, Li S, Xu L, Yan B, Zhang Y, Liu X. A nomogram model to predict malignant cerebral edema in ischemic stroke patients treated with endovascular thrombectomy: an observational study. Neuropsychiatric disease and treatment. 2020;16:2913–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7719319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33293816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Taha L, Beyrouthy C, Tamim H, Ghazeeri G. Knowledge and attitudes among Lebanese pregnant women and women seeking fertility treatment during the COVID-19 outbreak: a cross-sectional survey. BMJ Open. 2022;12(3): e057873.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8927896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35296487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estiri H, Strasser ZH, Klann JG, Naseri P, Wagholikar KB, Murphy SNJN, d. m. Predicting COVID-19 mortality with electronic medical records. NPJ digital medicine. 2021. 10.1038/s41746-021-00383-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7862405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33542473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goetz C, Humm B. Decentralized real-time anomaly detection in cyber-physical production systems under industry constraints. Sensors (Basel). 2023;23(9):4207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10181007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37177411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong H, Wang M, Zhang H, Elahe MF, Jin M. An explainable AI approach for the rapid diagnosis of COVID-19 Using Ensemble Learning Algorithms. Front Public Health. 2022;10: 874455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9253566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35801239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo X, Yang W, Xiong X, Wang Z, Zou X. MEMS reservoir computing system with stiffness modulation for multi-scene data processing at the edge. Microsyst Nanoeng. 2024;10:84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11194282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38915829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang L, Li OZ, Yin X. Inferring China’s excess mortality during the COVID-19 pandemic using online mourning and funeral search volume. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):15665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10511516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37730765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Zhang P, Wang Z, Lu Z, Wang ZJNPL. HFMD cases prediction using transfer one-step-ahead learning. 2023;55(3):2321–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji B, Pi W, Liu W, Liu Y, Cui Y, Zhang X, Peng S. HyperVR: a hybrid deep ensemble learning approach for simultaneously predicting virulence factors and antibiotic resistance genes. NAR genomics and bioinformatics. 2023;5(1): lqad012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9918863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36789031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Y, Li Q, Trevisan G, Linhares DCL, MacKenzie C. Investigating the relationship of porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus RNA detection between adult/sow farm and wean-to-market age categories. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(7): e0253429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8253390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34214081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jorge DCP, Oliveira JF, Miranda JGV, Andrade RFS, Pinho STR. Estimating the effective reproduction number for heterogeneous models using incidence data. Royal Society open science. 2022;9(9): 220005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9449464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36133147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang Z, Fan R, Zhan C, Wu Y, Lin Y, Li K, et al. The Rapid non-destructive differentiation of different varieties of rice by fluorescence hyperspectral technology combined with machine learning. Molecules (Basel). 2024;29(3):682.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10856461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38338424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keshavamurthy R, Charles LE. Predicting Kyasanur forest disease in resource-limited settings using event-based surveillance and transfer learning. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):11067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10329696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37422454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwon B, Son H. Accurate Path Loss Prediction Using a Neural Network Ensemble Method. Sensors. 2024;24(1):304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10781234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38203166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsen SL, Kraay ANM. Transparent transmission models for informing public health policy: the role of trust and generalizability. Proceedings Biological sciences. 2024;291(2015):20232273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10806397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38264775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J, Kim JN, Dallan LAP, Zimin VN, Hoori A, Hassani NS, Wilson DL. Deep learning segmentation of fibrous cap in intravascular optical coherence tomography images. Scientific reports. 2024;14(1):4393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10884035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38388637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenatti M, Narteni S, Paglialonga A, Rampa V, Mongelli M. Dual-view single-shot multibox detector at urban intersections: Settings and performance evaluation. Sensors. 2023;23(6):3195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10057596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36991906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H, Yang Y, Chen J, Li Q, Chen Y, Zhang Y, Xiang J. Epidemiological characteristics of overseas-imported infectious diseases identified through airport health-screening measures: a case study on Fuzhou, China. Trop Med Infect Dis. 2024;9(6):138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11209573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38922050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Patel V, Duan L, Mikuliak J, Basran J, Osgood ND. Real-Time Epidemiology and Acute Care Need Monitoring and Forecasting for COVID-19 via Bayesian Sequential Monte Carlo-Leveraged Transmission Models. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2024;21(2):193. 10.3390/ijerph21020193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10888645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38397684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Su H. Prediction of martensite start temperature of steel combined with expert experience and machine learning. Sci Technol Adv Mater. 2024;25(1):2354655.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11138230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38817248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M, Liu Y, Liu J. Epidemiology-aware Deep Learning for Infectious Disease Dynamics Prediction. In: Proceedings of the 32nd ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management, vol. 33. New York: Association for Computing Machinery; 2023. p. 4084–8. 10.1145/3583780.3615139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T, Huang J, He Z, Zhang Y, Yan N, Zhang CJP, Ming W-K. Rethinking of value of early-stage infectious disease modelling to public health: a real-world data validation of SIR models. 2022. 10.21203/rs.3.rs-2069781/v1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T, Huang J, He Z, Zhang Y, Yan N, Zhang CJP, Ming W-K. A real-world data validation of the value of early-stage SIR modelling to public health. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):9164. 10.1038/s41598-023-36386-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10242229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37280428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lou J, Wang B, Li J, Ni P, Jin Y, Chen S, Duan G. The CRISPR-Cas system as a tool for diagnosing and treating infectious diseases. Molecular biology reports. 2022;49(12):11301–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9297709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35857175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madewell ZJ, Yang Y, Longini IM, Halloran ME, Vespignani A, Dean NE. Rapid review and meta-analysis of serial intervals for SARS-CoV-2 Delta and Omicron variants. BMC Infect Dis. 2023;23(1):429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10291789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37365505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mei H, Peng J, Wang T, Zhou T, Zhao H, Zhang T, Yang Z. Overcoming the limits of cross-sensitivity: pattern recognition methods for chemiresistive gas sensor array. Nano-micro letters. 2024;16(1):269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11324646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39141168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair A, Ahirwar A, Singh S, Lodhi R, Lodhi A, Rai A, Vinayak V. Astaxanthin as a king of ketocarotenoids: structure, synthesis, accumulation, bioavailability and antioxidant properties. Marine Drugs. 2023;21(3):176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10056084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36976225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narkhede P, Walambe R, Poddar S, Kotecha K. Incremental learning of LSTM framework for sensor fusion in attitude estimation. PeerJ Computer science. 2021;7: e662.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8356651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34435103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noordman CR, Yakar D, Bosma J, Simonis FFJ, Huisman H. Complexities of deep learning-based undersampled MR image reconstruction. European radiology experimental. 2023;7(1):58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10547669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37789241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olum R, Ahaisibwe B, Atuhairwe I, Balizzakiwa T, Kizito P, Apiyo M, Kalanzi J, Nabawanuka A, Bahatungire R, Kerry V. Readiness To Manage Ebola Virus Disease Among Emergency Healthcare Workers in Uganda: A Nationwide Multicenter Survey. 2024. 10.21203/rs.3.rs-4212996/v1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortiz-Barrios M, Petrillo A, Arias-Fonseca S, McClean S, de Felice F, Nugent C, Uribe-López SA. An AI-based multiphase framework for improving the mechanical ventilation availability in emergency departments during respiratory disease seasons: a case study. Int J Emerg Med. 2024;17(1):45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10986051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38561694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perichart-Perera O, Avila-Sosa V, Solis-Paredes JM, Montoya-Estrada A, Reyes-Muñoz E, Rodríguez-Cano AM, González-Leyva CP, Sánchez-Martínez M, Estrada-Gutierrez G, Irles C. Vitamin D deficiency, excessive gestational weight gain, and oxidative stress predict small for gestational age newborns using an artificial neural network model. Antioxidants (Basel). 2022;11(3):574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8944993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35326224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perramon-Malavez A, Bravo M, de Rioja VL, Català M, Alonso S, Álvarez-Lacalle E, Prats C. A semi-empirical risk panel to monitor epidemics: multi-faceted tool to assist healthcare and public health professionals. Frontiers in public health. 2023;11:1307425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10801172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38259774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popescu S, Myers N. Interdisciplinary information for infectious disease response: exercising for improved medical/public health communication and collaboration. Disaster Med Public Health Prep. 2021;15(5):546–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32895074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu H, Luo L, Su Z, Zhou L, Wang L, Chen Y. Machine learning approaches to predict peak demand days of cardiovascular admissions considering environmental exposure. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2020;20(1):83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32357880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raza S, Schwartz B. Constructing a disease database and using natural language processing to capture and standardize free text clinical information. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):8591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10215040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37237101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigues J, Studer E, Streuber S, Meyer N, Sandi C. Locomotion in virtual environments predicts cardiovascular responsiveness to subsequent stressful challenges. Nat Commun. 2020;11(1):5904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7677550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33214564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roster K, Connaughton C, Rodrigues FA. Forecasting new diseases in low-data settings using transfer learning. Chaos Solitons Fractals. 2022;161:112306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9222348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35765601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan Y, Huang T, Zhou W, Zhu J, Liang Q, Zhong L, Xie Y. The lead time and geographical variations of Baidu Search Index in the early warning of COVID-19. Scientific reports. 2023;13(1):14705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10484897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37679512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shyaa MA, Zainol Z, Abdullah R, Anbar M, Alzubaidi L, Santamaría J. Enhanced Intrusion Detection with Data Stream Classification and Concept Drift Guided by the Incremental Learning Genetic Programming Combiner. Sensors (Basel). 2023;23(7):3736.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10098915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37050795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soliman M, Lyubchich V, Gel YR. Complementing the power of deep learning with statistical model fusion: Probabilistic forecasting of influenza in Dallas County, Texas, USA. Epidemics. 2019;28: 100345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31182294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soni M, Khan IR, Basir S, Chadha R, Alguno AC, Bhowmik T. Light-weighted deep learning model to detect fault in IoT-based industrial equipment. Comput Intell Neurosci. 2022;2022:2455259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9259252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35814591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su K, Yuan X, Huang Y, Yuan Q, Yang M, Sun J, Yuan Z. Improved prediction of knee osteoarthritis by the machine learning model XGBoost. Indian journal of orthopaedics. 2023;57(10):1667–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10519887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37766962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vobugari N, Raja V, Sethi U, Gandhi K, Raja K, Surani SR. Advancements in oncology with artificial intelligence—a review article. Cancers. 2022;14(5):1349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8909088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35267657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Cui W, Guo Y, Du Y, Zhou Y. Machine Learning Prediction of Foodborne Disease Pathogens: Algorithm Development and Validation Study. JMIR Med Inform. 2021;9(1): e24924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7872834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33496675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Qiu J, Li C, Wan H, Yang C, Zhang T. Applying the spatial transmission network to the forecast of infectious diseases across multiple regions. Front Public Health. 2022;10: 774984.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8962516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35359784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Zhang H, Chen N, Zeng T, Ai X, Wu K. PorcineAI-enhancer: prediction of pig enhancer sequences using convolutional neural networks. Animals. 2023;13(18):2935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10526013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37760334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Liu Y, Chen H, Qiu S, Liu Y, Yang M, Du X, Li Z, Hao R, Tian H, Song H. Search-engine-based surveillance using artificial intelligence for early detection of coronavirus disease outbreak. J Big Data. 2023;10(1):169. 10.1186/s40537-023-00847-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang P, Zhang W, Wang H, Shi C, Li Z, Wang D, Hao Y. Predicting the incidence of infectious diarrhea with symptom surveillance data using a stacking-based ensembled model. BMC infectious diseases. 2024;24(1):265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10898154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38408967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Cao Z, Zeng D, Wang X, Wang Q. Using deep learning to predict the hand-foot-and-mouth disease of enterovirus A71 subtype in Beijing from 2011 to 2018. Sci Rep. 2020;10(1):12201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7376109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32699245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Xu C, Li Y, Wu W, Gui L, Ren J, Yao S. An advanced data-driven hybrid model of sarima-nnnar for tuberculosis incidence time series forecasting in Qinghai Province, China. Infection and drug resistance. 2020;13:867–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32273731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Zhang P, Huang Y, Chao G, Xie X, Fu YJAI. Oriented transformer for infectious disease case prediction. 2023;53(24):30097–112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White L, Basurra S, Alsewari AA, Saeed F, Addanki SM. Temporal meta-optimiser based sensitivity analysis (TMSA) for agent-based models and applications in children’s services. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):9105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11032329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38643325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie M, Lin S, Dong K, Zhang S. Short-Term Prediction of Multi-Energy Loads Based on Copula Correlation Analysis and Model Fusions. Entropy (Basel). 2023;25(9):1343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10530182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37761642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu D, Chan WH, Haron HJPCS. Enhancing infectious disease prediction model selection with multi-objective optimization: an empirical study. 2024;10: e2217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11323180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39145229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J, Zhou J, Luo T, Xie Y, Wei Y, Mai H, Huang J. Predicting pulmonary tuberculosis incidence in China using Baidu search index: an ARIMAX model approach. Environmental health and preventive medicine. 2023;28:68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10636285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37926526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Li G, Yang J, Zhang T, Du J, Liu T, Zhang X, Han X, Li W, Ma L, Feng L. Deep-learning model for influenza prediction from multisource heterogeneous data in a megacity. J Med Internet Res. 2023;25:e44238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9972203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36780207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Yang J, He Y, Zhang M, Han X, Hu X, Li W, Zhang T, Yang W. Enhancing infectious diseases early warning: A deep learning approach for influenza surveillance in China. Prev Med Rep. 2024;43:102761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11127166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38798906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang R, Lin Z, Cai Y, Chen N, Zhou Y, Zhang J, Hong G. Assessing the risk of prenatal depressive symptoms in Chinese women: an integrated evaluation of serum metabolome, multivitamin supplement intake, and clinical blood indicators. Front Psych. 2023;14:1234461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10808622</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38274432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S, Cui L, Wang L, Wang T, You J. Enhancing multimodal depression diagnosis through representation learning and knowledge transfer. Heliyon. 2024;10(4): e25959.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10877283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38380046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoo HY, Lee KC, Woo JE, Park SH, Lee S, Joo J, Park BJ. A genome-wide association study and machine-learning algorithm analysis on the prediction of facial phenotypes by genotypes in Korean women. Clinical, cosmetic and investigational dermatology. 2022;15:433–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8933694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35313536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Y, Tan J, Yang Y, Zhang B, Yao X, Sang S, Deng S. The differential diagnostic value of radiomics signatures between single-nodule pulmonary metastases and second primary lung cancer in patients with colorectal cancer. Technol Cancer Res Treat. 2023;22: 15330338231175735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10226291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37226476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zemariam AB, Yimer A, Abebe GK, Wondie WT, Abate BB, Alamaw AW, Ngusie HS. Employing supervised machine learning algorithms for classification and prediction of anemia among youth girls in Ethiopia. Scientific reports. 2024;14(1):9080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11032364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38643324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Yang W, Chen D, Fu C, Wei F. AM-MSFF: A Pest Recognition Network Based on Attention Mechanism and Multi-Scale Feature Fusion. Entropy (Basel). 2024;26(5):431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11119940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38785680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Wang Z, Huang Y, Wang MJK-BS. Dual-grained directional representation for infectious disease case prediction. 2022;256: 109806.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou W, Huang D, Liang Q, Huang T, Wang X, Pei H, Qin L. Early warning and predicting of COVID-19 using zero-inflated negative binomial regression model and negative binomial regression model. BMC Infect Dis. 2024;24(1):1006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39300391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu D, Bu Q, Zhu Z, Zhang Y, Wang Z. Advancing autonomy through lifelong learning: a survey of autonomous intelligent systems. Front Neurorobot. 2024;18: 1385778.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11027131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38644905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>