<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439725</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2055-2076</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jan-Dec</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Digital health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Digit Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Role of mobile health applications in prevention and detection of pandemic disease: A population perspective.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>20552076241292106</StartPage><MedlinePgn>20552076241292106</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">20552076241292106</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/20552076241292106</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The Saudi government and the MOH launched six mobile application help in tracking positive cases, get medical consultation from home, and vaccination for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Our study was conducted to evaluate the role of mobile health applications in the prevention and detection of pandemic disease from population perspectives.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A cross-sectional descriptive exploratory research design was utilized in this study. Based on the sample size calculation (described below), we recruited a convenience sample of 462 participants from the Northern Border Region according to the set of inclusion and exclusion criteria: Anyone over 12 years of age, including both genders and both Saudi citizens and non-Saudi citizens, were eligible to participate during the period from March 2022 to the end of July.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In total 462 were participated, and 79.2% of them were females. There was a statistically significant difference between educational level and the overall score of public satisfaction with the ease of use of mobile health applications as well as overall satisfaction with the services provided by mobile health apps during the COVID-19 pandemic. Additionally, there was a statistically significant difference between gender and the role of mobile applications in the prevention of COVID-19 (<i>p</i> = 0.028).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The study found that most participants agree that the mobile health applications launched by the Saudi government and Ministry of Health have been successful in aiding the anticipation and early detection of COVID-19 cases, as well as facilitating access to healthcare services. Over half of the participants strongly agree that these mobile applications have been very effective and beneficial for their health and have helped save time.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elbilgahy</LastName><ForeName>Amal Ahmed</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0465-6061</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Maternal &amp; Child Health Nursing Department, Faculty of Nursing, Northern Border University, Arar, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Nursing, Northern Border University, Arar, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alenezi</LastName><ForeName>Mada Huwaydi</ForeName><Initials>MH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Maternal &amp; Child Health Nursing Department, Faculty of Nursing, Northern Border University, Arar, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alruwaili</LastName><ForeName>Aseel Hamed</ForeName><Initials>AH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Maternal &amp; Child Health Nursing Department, Faculty of Nursing, Northern Border University, Arar, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alhathal</LastName><ForeName>Sarah Muteb</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Maternal &amp; Child Health Nursing Department, Faculty of Nursing, Northern Border University, Arar, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Digit Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101690863</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2055-2076</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mobile health app</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public perception and satisfaction</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20552076241292106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_20552076241292106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lai CC, Shih TP, Ko WC, et al. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19): the epidemic and the challenges. Int J Antimicrob Agents 2020; 55: 105924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32081636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mogaji E. Financial vulnerability during a pandemic: insights for coronavirus disease (COVID-19). In: Mogaji E, editor. 2020. p.57–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health. MOH launches New App (Tetamman) to prevent COVID-19 [Internet]. Ministry Of Health Saudi Arabia. 2020. 
Apr 11 [cited 2022 Jan 29]. Available from: https://www.moh.gov.sa/en/Ministry/MediaCenter/News/Pages/News-2020-04-11-004.aspx</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shereen MA, Khan S, Kazmi A, et al. COVID-19 infection: emergence, transmission, and characteristics of human coronaviruses. J Adv Res 2020; 24: 91–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7113610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32257431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Algaissi AA, Alharbi NK, Hassanain Met al. et al. Preparedness and response to COVID-19 in Saudi Arabia: building on MERS experience. J Infect Public Health 2020; 13: 834–838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7211706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32451260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perveen S, Orfali R, ul Azam MS, et al. Coronavirus nCOVID-19: a pandemic disease and the Saudi precautions. Saudi Pharm J 2020; 28: 888–897.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7299861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32641901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alrashed S, Min-Allah N, Saxena A, et al. Impact of lockdowns on the spread of COVID-19 in Saudi Arabia. Informatics in Medicine Unlocked 2020; 20: 100420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7462775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32905098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. COVID-19 strategic preparedness and response plan: operational planning guideline: 1 February 2021 to 31 January 2022 (No. WHO/WHE/2021.03). (2021). World Health Organization. https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/340073/WHO-WHE-2021.03-eng.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Hanawi MK, Angawi K, Alshareef N, et al. Knowledge, attitude and practice toward COVID-19 among the public in the kingdom of Saudi Arabia: a cross-sectional study. Front Public Health 2020; 8: 17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7266869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32574300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alnasser AHA, Al-Tawfiq JA, Al Kalif MSH, et al. The positive impact of social media on the level of COVID-19 awareness in Saudi Arabia: a web-based cross-sectional survey. Infez Med 2020; 28: 545–550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33257629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassounah M, Raheel H, Alhefzi M. Digital response during the COVID-19 pandemic in Saudi Arabia. J Med Internet Res 2020; 22: e19338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7473704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32790642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alghamdi SM, Alqahtani JS, Aldhahir AM. Current status of telehealth in Saudi Arabia during COVID-19. J Family Community Med 2020; 27: 08.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7745786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33354152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SDAIA. (2020). Saudi Data &amp; Artificial Intelligence Authority. Retrieved from: https://sdaia.gov.sa/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry Of Health. (2021). Moh apps for smartphones. Ministry Of Health Saudi Arabia. Retrieved January 29, 2022, from https://www.moh.gov.sa/en/Support/Pages/MobileApp.aspx.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naar I. (2020). Coronavirus: Saudi Arabia's Mawid app guides on self-isolation or hospital visit. https://english.alarabiya.net/media/digital/2020/03/21/Coronavirus-Saudi-Arabia-s-Mawid-app-guides-on-self-isolation-or-hospital-visit</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He W, Zhang ZJ, Li W. Information technology solutions, challenges, and suggestions for tackling the COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Inf Manage 2021; 57: 102287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7724285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33318721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaishya R, Javaid M, Khan IHet al. et al. Artificial intelligence (AI) applications for COVID-19 pandemic. Diabetes &amp; Metabolic Syndrome: Clinical Research &amp; Reviews 2020; 14: 337–339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32305024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A, Gupta PK, Srivastava A. A review of modern technologies for tackling COVID-19 pandemic. Diabetes Metab Syndr 2020; 14: 569–573.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7204706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32413821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghaderzadeh M, Eshraghi M, Asadi F, et al. Efficient framework for detection of COVID-19 omicron and delta variants based on two intelligent phases of CNN models. Comput Math Methods Med 2022; 2022: 4838009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9050257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35495884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gheisari M, Ghaderzadeh M, Li H, et al. Mobile apps for COVID-19 detection and diagnosis for future pandemic control: multidimensional systematic review. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth 2024; 12: e44406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10896318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38231538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binkheder S, Aldekhyyel RN, AlMogbel A, et al. Public perceptions around mHealth applications during COVID-19 pandemic: a network and sentiment analysis of tweets in Saudi Arabia. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2021; 18: 13388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8708161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34948997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alanzi TM, Althumairi A, Aljaffary A, et al. Evaluation of the Mawid mobile healthcare application in delivering services during the COVID-19 pandemic in Saudi Arabia. Int Health 2021; 14: 142–151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8083325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33864074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montazeri M, Galavi Z, Ahmadian L. The role of mobile health in prevention, diagnosis, treatment and self-care of COVID-19 from the healthcare professionals’ perspectives. Digital Health 2023; 9: 20552076231171969.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10159248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37152239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alwashmi MF. The use of digital health in the detection and management of COVID-19. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2020; 17: 2906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7215737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32340107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ting DSW, Carin L, Dzau V, et al. Digital technology and COVID-19. Nat Med 2020; 26: 459–461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7100489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32284618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moazzami B, Razavi-Khorasani N, Moghadam AD, et al. COVID-19 and telemedicine: immediate action required for maintaining healthcare providers well-being. J Clin Virology 2020; 126: 104345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7129277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32278298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aldhahir AM, Alqahtani JS, Althobiani MA, et al. Current knowledge, satisfaction, and use of E-health Mobile application (seha) among the general population of Saudi Arabia: a cross-sectional study. J Multidiscip Healthc 2022; 15: 67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8983872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35399807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Global diffusion of eHealth: Making universal health coverage achievable. Report on the Third Global Survey on eHealth. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2016. p. 156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sondaal SFV, Browne JL, Amoakoh-Coleman M, et al. Assessing the effect of mHealth interventions in improving maternal and neonatal care in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review. PLoS One 2016; 11: e0154664. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0154664.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4856298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27144393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Veer AJ, Peeters JM, Brabers AE, et al. Determinants of the intention to use e-health by community dwelling older people. BMC Health Serv Res 2015; 15: 03.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4364096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25889884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam MZ, Hoque MR, Hu Wet al. et al. Factors influencing the adoption of mHealth services in a developing country: a patient-centric study. Int J Inf Manage 2020; 50: 128–143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Guo X, Lai KH, et al. Understanding gender differences in m-health adoption: a modified theory of reasoned action model. Telemedicine and e-Health 2014; 20: 39–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24161004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallagher R, Roach K, Sadler L, et al. Mobile technology use across age groups in patients eligible for cardiac rehabilitation: survey study. JMIR mHealth UHealth 2017; 5: e161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5676027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29066425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gheisari M, Ghaderzadeh M, Li H, et al. Mobile apps for COVID-19 detection and diagnosis for future pandemic control: multidimensional systematic review. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth 2024; 12: e44406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10896318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38231538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutierrez M, Moreno R, Rebelo M. Information and communication technologies and global health challenges. In: Global health informatics. Academic Press, 2017, pp.50–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiberu VM, Mars M, Scott RE. Barriers and opportunities to implementation of sustainable e-health programmes in Uganda: a literature review. Afr J Prim Health Care Fam Med 2017; 9: 1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5458569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28582996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osei E, Mashamba-Thompson TP. Mobile health applications for disease screening and treatment support in low-and middle-income countries: a narrative review. Heliyon 2021; 7: e0154664. DOI: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8035664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33869857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>