<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39431279</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1939-1382</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>17</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>IEEE transactions on learning technologies</Title><ISOAbbreviation>IEEE Trans Learn Technol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhancing Medical Training Through Learning From Mistakes by Interacting With an Ill-Trained Reinforcement Learning Agent.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1248</StartPage><EndPage>1260</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1248-1260</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1109/tlt.2024.3372508</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study presents a 3D medical simulation that employs reinforcement learning (RL) and interactive reinforcement learning (IRL) to teach and assess the procedure of donning and doffing personal protective equipment (PPE). The simulation is motivated by the need for effective, safe, and remote training techniques in medicine, particularly in light of the COVID-19 pandemic. The simulation has two modes: a tutorial mode and an assessment mode. In the tutorial mode, a computer-based, ill-trained RL agent utilizes RL to learn the correct sequence of donning the PPE by trial and error. This allows students to experience many outlier cases they might not encounter in an in-class educational model. In the assessment mode, an IRL-based method is used to evaluate how effective the participant is at correcting the mistakes performed by the RL agent. Each time the RL agent interacts with the environment and performs an action, the participants provide positive or negative feedback regarding the action taken. Following the assessment, participants receive a score based on the accuracy of their feedback and the time taken for the RL agent to learn the correct sequence. An experiment was conducted using two groups, each consisting of 10 participants. The first group received RL-assisted training for donning PPE, followed by an IRL-based assessment. Meanwhile, the second group observed a video featuring the RL agent demonstrating only the correct donning order without outlier cases, replicating traditional training, before undergoing the same assessment as the first group. Results showed that RL-assisted training with many outlier cases was more effective than traditional training with only regular cases. Moreover, combining RL with IRL significantly enhanced the participants' performance. Notably, 90% of the participants finished the assessment with perfect scores within three iterations. In contrast, only 10% of those who did not engage in RL-assisted training finished the assessment with a perfect score, highlighting the substantial impact of RL and IRL integration on participants' overall achievement.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kakdas</LastName><ForeName>Yasar C</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Florida Polytechnic Univ., Dept. of Computer Science, Lakeland, FL, USA 33805.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kockara</LastName><ForeName>Sinan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Rice Univ., Dept. of Computer Science, Houston, TX, USA 77005.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Halic</LastName><ForeName>Tansel</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Intuitive Surgical, Peachtree Corners, GA, USA 30092.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Demirel</LastName><ForeName>Doga</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Florida Polytechnic Univ., Dept. of Computer Science, Lakeland, FL, USA 33805.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P20 GM103429</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 EB005807</GrantID><Acronym>EB</Acronym><Agency>NIBIB NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 EB025241</GrantID><Acronym>EB</Acronym><Agency>NIBIB NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R44 AR075481</GrantID><Acronym>AR</Acronym><Agency>NIAMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>IEEE Trans Learn Technol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918250309906676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1939-1382</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">agent-based</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">donning and doffing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">interactive reinforcement learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medical training</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">reinforcement learning</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39431279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1979410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11486497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/tlt.2024.3372508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Elmoazen R, Saqr M, Khalil M, and Wasson B, “Learning analytics in virtual laboratories: a systematic literature review of empirical research,” Smart Learning Environments, vol. 10, no. 1, p. 23, Mar. 2023, doi: 10.1186/s40561-023-00244-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40561-023-00244-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam A, “Leveraging the Power of ‘Modeling and Computer Simulation’ for Education: An Exploration of its Potential for Improved Learning Outcomes and Enhanced Student Engagement,” in 2023 International Conference on Device Intelligence, Computing and Communication Technologies, (DICCT), Mar. 2023, pp. 445–450. doi: 10.1109/DICCT56244.2023.10110159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/DICCT56244.2023.10110159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Zou D, Xie H, and Wang FL, “Metaverse in Education: Contributors, Cooperations, and Research Themes,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, pp. 1–18, 2023, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2023.3277952.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2023.3277952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang W-Y, Nurtantyana R, Purba SWD, Hariyanti U, and Suprapto, “Augmented Reality With Authentic GeometryGo App to Help Geometry Learning and Assessments,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, vol. 16, no. 5, pp. 769–779, Oct. 2023, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2023.3251398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2023.3251398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teplá M, Teplý P, and Šmejkal P, “Influence of 3D models and animations on students in natural subjects,” International Journal of STEM Education, vol. 9, no. 1, p. 65, Oct. 2022, doi: 10.1186/s40594-022-00382-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40594-022-00382-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyelere SS, Bouali N, Kaliisa R, Obaido G, Yunusa AA, and Jimoh ER, “Exploring the trends of educational virtual reality games: a systematic review of empirical studies,” Smart Learning Environments, vol. 7, no. 1, p. 31, Oct. 2020, doi: 10.1186/s40561-020-00142-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40561-020-00142-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laine TH and Lindberg RSN, “Designing Engaging Games for Education: A Systematic Literature Review on Game Motivators and Design Principles,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, vol. 13, no. 4, pp. 804–821, Oct. 2020, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2020.3018503.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2020.3018503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellas N, Dengel A, and Christopoulos A, “A Scoping Review of Immersive Virtual Reality in STEM Education,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, vol. 13, no. 4, pp. 748–761, Oct. 2020, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2020.3019405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2020.3019405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao S et al., “An Intelligent Augmented Reality Training Framework for Neonatal Endotracheal Intubation,” in 2020 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), Nov. 2020, pp. 672–681. doi: 10.1109/ISMAR50242.2020.00097.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ISMAR50242.2020.00097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8084704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33935605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vlachopoulos D and Makri A, “The effect of games and simulations on higher education: a systematic literature review,” International Journal of Educational Technology in Higher Education, vol. 14, no. 1, p. 22, Jul. 2017, doi: 10.1186/s41239-017-0062-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s41239-017-0062-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibáñez M-B, Di-Serio Á, and Delgado-Kloos C, “Gamification for Engaging Computer Science Students in Learning Activities: A Case Study,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, vol. 7, no. 3, pp. 291–301, Jul. 2014, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2014.2329293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2014.2329293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai C-P and Ke F, “Educational applications of artificial intelligence in simulation-based learning: A systematic mapping review,” Computers and Education: Artificial Intelligence, vol. 3, p. 100087, Jan. 2022, doi: 10.1016/j.caeai.2022.100087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.caeai.2022.100087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ke F, Dai Z, Dai C-P, Pachman M, Chaulagain RS, and Yuan X, “Designing Virtual Agents for Simulation-Based Learning in Virtual Reality,” in Cognitive and Affective Perspectives on Immersive Technology in Education, IGI Global, 2020, pp. 151–170. doi: 10.4018/978-1-7998-3250-8.ch008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4018/978-1-7998-3250-8.ch008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dials J, Demirel D, Sanchez-Arias R, Halic T, De S, and Gromski MA, “Endoscopic sleeve gastroplasty: stomach location and task classification for evaluation using artificial intelligence,” Int J CARS, Jan. 2024, doi: 10.1007/s11548-023-03054-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11548-023-03054-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10978260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38212470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalalimanesh A, Shahabi Haghighi H, Ahmadi A, and Soltani M, “Simulation-based optimization of radiotherapy: Agent-based modeling and reinforcement learning,” Mathematics and Computers in Simulation, vol. 133, pp. 235–248, Mar. 2017, doi: 10.1016/j.matcom.2016.05.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.matcom.2016.05.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bi Y, Jiang Z, Gao Y, Wendler T, Karlas A, and Navab N, “VesNet-RL: Simulation-Based Reinforcement Learning for Real-World US Probe Navigation,” IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 7, no. 3, pp. 6638–6645, Jul. 2022, doi: 10.1109/LRA.2022.3176112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/LRA.2022.3176112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng J, Parks S, and Shang J, “To learn scientifically, effectively, and enjoyably: A review of educational games,” Human Behavior and Emerging Technologies, vol. 2, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1002/hbe2.188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hbe2.188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah A, Mai CL, Shah R, and Levine AI, “Simulation-Based Education and Team Training,” Otolaryngologic Clinics of North America, vol. 52, no. 6, pp. 995–1003, Dec. 2019, doi: 10.1016/j.otc.2019.08.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.otc.2019.08.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31526536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ören T, Turnitsa C, Mittal S, and Diallo SY, “Simulation-Based Learning and Education,” in Guide to Simulation-Based Disciplines, Mittal S, Durak U, and Ören T, Eds., in Simulation Foundations, Methods and Applications., Cham: Springer International Publishing, 2017, pp. 293–314. doi: 10.1007/978-3-319-61264-5_13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-61264-5_13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lateef F, “Simulation-based learning: Just like the real thing,” J Emerg Trauma Shock, vol. 3, no. 4, pp. 348–352, 2010, doi: 10.4103/0974-2700.70743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0974-2700.70743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2966567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21063557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>So HY, Chen PP, Wong GKC, and Chan TTN, “Simulation in Medical Education,” Journal of the Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh, vol. 49, no. 1, pp. 52–57, Mar. 2019, doi: 10.4997/jrcpe.2019.112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4997/jrcpe.2019.112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30838994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aebersold M, “The History of Simulation and Its Impact on the Future,” AACN Advanced Critical Care, vol. 27, no. 1, pp. 56–61, Feb. 2016, doi: 10.4037/aacnacc2016436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4037/aacnacc2016436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26909454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Offiah G et al., “Evaluation of medical student retention of clinical skills following simulation training,” BMC Medical Education, vol. 19, no. 1, p. 263, Jul. 2019, doi: 10.1186/s12909-019-1663-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-019-1663-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6632214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31311546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Elq AH, “Simulation-based medical teaching and learning,” J Family Community Med, vol. 17, no. 1, pp. 35–40, 2010, doi: 10.4103/1319-1683.68787.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/1319-1683.68787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3195067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22022669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>N.d S, M.s S, Sh.T M, and H.k B, “SIMULATION TRAINING IN MEDICINE,” jmea, vol. 3, no. 3, Art. no. 3, 3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DEMIREL D et al., “Virtual Airway Skills Trainer (VAST) Simulator,” Stud Health Technol Inform, vol. 220, pp. 91–97, 2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5033599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27046559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demirel D, Yu A, Halic T, and Kockara S, “Web based camera navigation for virtual pancreatic cancer surgery: Whipple surgery simulator (VPanSS),” in 2014 IEEE Innovations in Technology Conference, May 2014, pp. 1–8. doi: 10.1109/InnoTek.2014.6877375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/InnoTek.2014.6877375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cetinsaya B et al., “Design of Virtual Endoluminal Surgery Simulator (VESS): Colorectal Endoscopic Submucosal Dissection Training Module: 809,” Official journal of the American College of Gastroenterology | ACG, vol. 112, p. S452, Oct. 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farmer J et al., “Virtual Rotator Cuff Arthroscopic Skill Trainer: Results and Analysis of a Preliminary Subject Study,” in Proceedings of the 2020 the 4th International Conference on Information System and Data Mining, in ICISDM ‘20. New York, NY, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, Jul. 2020, pp. 139–143. doi: 10.1145/3404663.3404673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1145/3404663.3404673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi D et al., “Surgeons With Five or More Actual Cricothyrotomies Perform Significantly Better on a Virtual Reality Simulator,” Journal of Surgical Research, vol. 252, pp. 247–254, Aug. 2020, doi: 10.1016/j.jss.2020.03.021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2020.03.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7295680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32304931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motola I, Devine LA, Chung HS, Sullivan JE, and Issenberg SB, “Simulation in healthcare education: A best evidence practical guide. AMEE Guide No. 82,” Medical Teacher, vol. 35, no. 10, pp. e1511–e1530, Oct. 2013, doi: 10.3109/0142159X.2013.818632.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/0142159X.2013.818632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23941678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera-Aliaga E and Estrada LD, “Trends and Innovations of Simulation for Twenty First Century Medical Education,” Frontiers in Public Health, vol. 10, 2022, Accessed: Dec. 11, 2023. [Online].
Available: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2022.619769</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.619769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8929194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35309206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gill D, Whitehead C, and Wondimagegn D, “Challenges to medical education at a time of physical distancing,” Lancet, vol. 396, no. 10244, pp. 77–79, 2020, doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31368-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31368-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7289574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32534631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guze PA, “Using Technology to Meet the Challenges of Medical Education,” Trans Am Clin Climatol Assoc, vol. 126, pp. 260–270, 2015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4530721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26330687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutton RS and Barto AG, Reinforcement Learning, second edition: An Introduction. MIT Press, 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramanian K, Jr CLI, and Thomaz AL, “Exploration from Demonstration for Interactive Reinforcement Learning”.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwon JH et al., “Assessment of Healthcare Worker Protocol Deviations and Self-Contamination During Personal Protective Equipment Donning and Doffing,” Infection Control &amp; Hospital Epidemiology, vol. 38, no. 9, pp. 1077–1083, Sep. 2017, doi: 10.1017/ice.2017.121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/ice.2017.121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6263164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28606192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook TM, “Personal protective equipment during the coronavirus disease (COVID) 2019 pandemic – a narrative review,” Anaesthesia, vol. 75, no. 7, pp. 920–927, 2020, doi: 10.1111/anae.15071.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/anae.15071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32246849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan L, Chen S, and Xu Y, “Donning and doffing of personal protective equipment protocol and key points of nursing care for patients with COVID-19 in ICU,” Stroke Vasc Neurol, vol. 5, no. 3, pp. 302–307, Sep. 2020, doi: 10.1136/svn-2020-000456.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/svn-2020-000456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7548514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32817272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christensen L, Rasmussen CS, Benfield T, and Franc JM, “A Randomized Trial of Instructor-Led Training Versus Video Lesson in Training Health Care Providers in Proper Donning and Doffing of Personal Protective Equipment,” Disaster Medicine and Public Health Preparedness, vol. 14, no. 4, pp. 514–520, Aug. 2020, doi: 10.1017/dmp.2020.56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/dmp.2020.56</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7156576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32223776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aminizadeh S et al., “The applications of machine learning techniques in medical data processing based on distributed computing and the Internet of Things,” Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine, vol. 241, p. 107745, Nov. 2023, doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107745.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37579550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rainey C, Villikudathil AT, McConnell J, Hughes C, Bond R, and McFadden S, “An experimental machine learning study investigating the decision-making process of students and qualified radiographers when interpreting radiographic images,” PLOS Digital Health, vol. 2, no. 10, p. e0000229, Oct. 2023, doi: 10.1371/journal.pdig.0000229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pdig.0000229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10599497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37878569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manickam P et al., “Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Internet of Medical Things (IoMT) Assisted Biomedical Systems for Intelligent Healthcare,” Biosensors, vol. 12, no. 8, Art. no. 8, Aug. 2022, doi: 10.3390/bios12080562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bios12080562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9330886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35892459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajwa J, Munir U, Nori A, and Williams B, “Artificial intelligence in healthcare: transforming the practice of medicine,” Future Healthc J, vol. 8, no. 2, pp. e188–e194, Jul. 2021, doi: 10.7861/fhj.2021-0095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7861/fhj.2021-0095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8285156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34286183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rong G, Mendez A, Bou Assi E, Zhao B, and Sawan M, “Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare: Review and Prediction Case Studies,” Engineering, vol. 6, no. 3, pp. 291–301, Mar. 2020, doi: 10.1016/j.eng.2019.08.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eng.2019.08.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He J, Baxter SL, Xu J, Xu J, Zhou X, and Zhang K, “The practical implementation of artificial intelligence technologies in medicine,” Nat Med, vol. 25, no. 1, Art. no. 1, Jan. 2019, doi: 10.1038/s41591-018-0307-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-018-0307-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6995276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30617336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang F et al., “Artificial intelligence in healthcare: past, present and future,” Stroke Vasc Neurol, vol. 2, no. 4, Dec. 2017, doi: 10.1136/svn-2017-000101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/svn-2017-000101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5829945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29507784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dagli MM, Rajesh A, Asaad M, and Butler CE, “The Use of Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning in Surgery: A Comprehensive Literature Review,” The American SurgeonTM, vol. 89, no. 5, pp. 1980–1988, May 2023, doi: 10.1177/00031348211065101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/00031348211065101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34958252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan P, Chen X, Zhang H, Wei Q, and Luo K, “Artificial intelligence aids in development of nanomedicines for cancer management,” Seminars in Cancer Biology, vol. 89, pp. 61–75, Feb. 2023, doi: 10.1016/j.semcancer.2023.01.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.semcancer.2023.01.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36682438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu X et al., “Beyond Supervised Learning for Pervasive Healthcare,” IEEE Reviews in Biomedical Engineering, pp. 1–21, 2023, doi: 10.1109/RBME.2023.3296938.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/RBME.2023.3296938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37471188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meenigea N and Kolla VRK, “Exploring the Current Landscape of Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare,” International Journal of Sustainable Development in Computing Science, vol. 5, no. 1, Mar. 2023, Accessed: Dec. 12, 2023. [Online].
Available: https://www.ijsdcs.com/index.php/ijsdcs/article/view/285</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albahri AS et al., “A systematic review of trustworthy and explainable artificial intelligence in healthcare: Assessment of quality, bias risk, and data fusion,” Information Fusion, vol. 96, pp. 156–191, Aug. 2023, doi: 10.1016/j.inffus.2023.03.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.inffus.2023.03.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alowais SA et al., “Revolutionizing healthcare: the role of artificial intelligence in clinical practice,” BMC Med Educ, vol. 23, no. 1, p. 689, Sep. 2023, doi: 10.1186/s12909-023-04698-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-023-04698-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10517477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37740191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donins U and Behmane D, “Challenges and Solutions for Artificial Intelligence Adoption in Healthcare – A Literature Review,” in Innovation in Medicine and Healthcare, Chen Y-W, Tanaka S, Howlett RJ, and Jain LC, Eds., in Smart Innovation, Systems and Technologies. Singapore: Springer Nature, 2023, pp. 53–62. doi: 10.1007/978-981-99-3311-2_6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-981-99-3311-2_6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saraswat D et al., “Explainable AI for Healthcare 5.0: Opportunities and Challenges,” IEEE Access, vol. 10, pp. 84486–84517, 2022, doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3197671.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3197671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loh HW, Ooi CP, Seoni S, Barua PD, Molinari F, and Acharya UR, “Application of explainable artificial intelligence for healthcare: A systematic review of the last decade (2011–2022),” Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine, vol. 226, p. 107161, Nov. 2022, doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2022.107161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2022.107161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36228495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao S, Zhang X, Jin F, and Hahn J, “An Auxiliary Tasks Based Framework for Automated Medical Skill Assessment with Limited Data,” in 2021 43rd Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine &amp; Biology Society (EMBC), Nov. 2021, pp. 1613–1617. doi: 10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9630498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9630498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34891594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdellatif AA, Mhaisen N, Mohamed A, Erbad A, and Guizani M, “Reinforcement Learning for Intelligent Healthcare Systems: A Review of Challenges, Applications, and Open Research Issues,” IEEE Internet of Things Journal, vol. 10, no. 24, pp. 21982–22007, Dec. 2023, doi: 10.1109/JIOT.2023.3288050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JIOT.2023.3288050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronato A, Naeem M, De Pietro G, and Paragliola G, “Reinforcement learning for intelligent healthcare applications: A survey,” Artificial Intelligence in Medicine, vol. 109, p. 101964, Sep. 2020, doi: 10.1016/j.artmed.2020.101964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.artmed.2020.101964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34756216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saghafian S, “Ambiguous Dynamic Treatment Regimes: A Reinforcement Learning Approach,” Management Science, Oct. 2023, doi: 10.1287/mnsc.2022.00883.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1287/mnsc.2022.00883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho H, Holloway ST, Couper DJ, and Kosorok MR, “Multi-stage optimal dynamic treatment regimes for survival outcomes with dependent censoring,” Biometrika, vol. 110, no. 2, pp. 395–410, Jun. 2023, doi: 10.1093/biomet/asac047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/biomet/asac047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10183834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37197739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang C-Y, Shiranthika C, Wang C-Y, Chen K-W, and Sumathipala S, “Reinforcement learning strategies in cancer chemotherapy treatments: A review,” Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine, vol. 229, p. 107280, Feb. 2023, doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2022.107280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2022.107280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36529000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah SIH, Coronato A, Naeem M, and De Pietro G, “Learning and Assessing Optimal Dynamic Treatment Regimes Through Cooperative Imitation Learning,” IEEE Access, vol. 10, pp. 78148–78158, 2022, doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3193494.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3193494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Zhang W, He X, and Zha H, “Supervised reinforcement learning with recurrent neural network for dynamic treatment recommendation,” in Proceedings of the 24th ACM SIGKDD international conference on knowledge discovery &amp; data mining, 2018, pp. 2447–2456.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Logan B, Liu N, Xu Z, Tang J, and Wang Y, “Deep Reinforcement Learning for Dynamic Treatment Regimes on Medical Registry Data,” in 2017 IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics (ICHI), Aug. 2017, pp. 380–385. doi: 10.1109/ICHI.2017.45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ICHI.2017.45</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5856473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29556119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pineau J, Guez A, Vincent R, Panuccio G, and Avoli M, “Treating epilepsy via adaptive neurostimulation: a reinforcement learning approach,” Int. J. Neur. Syst, vol. 19, no. 04, pp. 227–240, Aug. 2009, doi: 10.1142/S0129065709001987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1142/S0129065709001987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4884089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19731397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Zeng D, Socinski MA, and Kosorok MR, “Reinforcement Learning Strategies for Clinical Trials in Nonsmall Cell Lung Cancer,” Biometrics, vol. 67, no. 4, pp. 1422–1433, 2011, doi: 10.1111/j.1541-0420.2011.01572.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-0420.2011.01572.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3138840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21385164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu C and Huang Q, “Towards more efficient and robust evaluation of sepsis treatment with deep reinforcement learning,” BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making, vol. 23, no. 1, p. 43, Mar. 2023, doi: 10.1186/s12911-023-02126-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12911-023-02126-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9979564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36859257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu M, Zhang J, Matkovic L, Liu T, and Yang X, “Reinforcement learning in medical image analysis: Concepts, applications, challenges, and future directions,” Journal of Applied Clinical Medical Physics, vol. 24, no. 2, p. e13898, 2023, doi: 10.1002/acm2.13898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/acm2.13898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9924115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36626026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Zhu S, and Wen N, “Deep reinforcement learning and its applications in medical imaging and radiation therapy: a survey,” Phys. Med. Biol, vol. 67, no. 22, p. 22TR02, Nov. 2022, doi: 10.1088/1361-6560/ac9cb3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1361-6560/ac9cb3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36270582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calisto FM, Nunes N, and Nascimento JC, “Modeling adoption of intelligent agents in medical imaging,” International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, vol. 168, p. 102922, Dec. 2022, doi: 10.1016/j.ijhcs.2022.102922.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijhcs.2022.102922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maicas G, Carneiro G, Bradley AP, Nascimento JC, and Reid I, “Deep Reinforcement Learning for Active Breast Lesion Detection from DCE-MRI,” in Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention − MICCAI 2017, Descoteaux M, Maier-Hein L, Franz A, Jannin P, Collins DL, and Duchesne S, Eds., in Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Cham: Springer International Publishing, 2017, pp. 665–673. doi: 10.1007/978-3-319-66179-7_76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-66179-7_76</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stember JN and Shalu H, “Reinforcement learning using Deep Q Networks and Q learning accurately localizes brain tumors on MRI with very small training sets,” BMC Med Imaging, vol. 22, no. 1, p. 224, Dec. 2022, doi: 10.1186/s12880-022-00919-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12880-022-00919-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9784281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36564724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen S et al., “Reinforcement Learning Based Diagnosis and Prediction for COVID-19 by Optimizing a Mixed Cost Function From CT Images,” IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics, vol. 26, no. 11, pp. 5344–5354, Nov. 2022, doi: 10.1109/JBHI.2022.3197666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JBHI.2022.3197666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35951561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourdillon AT, Garg A, Wang H, Woo YJ, Pavone M, and Boyd J, “Integration of Reinforcement Learning in a Virtual Robotic Surgical Simulation,” Surg Innov, vol. 30, no. 1, pp. 94–102, Feb. 2023, doi: 10.1177/15533506221095298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/15533506221095298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35503302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahkoo AA and Abin AA, “Deep reinforcement learning in continuous action space for autonomous robotic surgery,” Int J CARS, vol. 18, no. 3, pp. 423–431, Mar. 2023, doi: 10.1007/s11548-022-02789-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11548-022-02789-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36383302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheikl PM et al., “Sim-to-Real Transfer for Visual Reinforcement Learning of Deformable Object Manipulation for Robot-Assisted Surgery,” IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 8, no. 2, pp. 560–567, Feb. 2023, doi: 10.1109/LRA.2022.3227873.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/LRA.2022.3227873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen ND, Nguyen T, Nahavandi S, Bhatti A, and Guest G, “Manipulating Soft Tissues by Deep Reinforcement Learning for Autonomous Robotic Surgery,” in 2019 IEEE International Systems Conference (SysCon), Apr. 2019, pp. 1–7. doi: 10.1109/SYSCON.2019.8836924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/SYSCON.2019.8836924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiu Z-Y, Richter F, Funk EK, Orosco RK, and Yip MC, “Bimanual Regrasping for Suture Needles using Reinforcement Learning for Rapid Motion Planning,” in 2021 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), May 2021, pp. 7737–7743. doi: 10.1109/ICRA48506.2021.9561673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ICRA48506.2021.9561673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan X, Chng C-B, Su Y, Lim K-B, and Chui C-K, “Robot-Assisted Training in Laparoscopy Using Deep Reinforcement Learning,” IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 4, no. 2, pp. 485–492, Apr. 2019, doi: 10.1109/LRA.2019.2891311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/LRA.2019.2891311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouyang L et al., “Training language models to follow instructions with human feedback,” Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, vol. 35, pp. 27730–27744, Dec. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shuvo SS and Yilmaz Y, “Home Energy Recommendation System (HERS): A Deep Reinforcement Learning Method Based on Residents’ Feedback and Activity,” IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid, vol. 13, no. 4, pp. 2812–2821, Jul. 2022, doi: 10.1109/TSG.2022.3158814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TSG.2022.3158814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alshumaimeri YA and Alshememry AK, “The Extent of AI Applications in EFL Learning and Teaching,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, pp. 1–11, 2023, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2023.3322128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2023.3322128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma H, Huang Z, Tang W, Zhu H, Zhang H, and Li J, “Predicting Student Performance in Future Exams via Neutrosophic Cognitive Diagnosis in Personalized E-Learning Environment,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, vol. 16, no. 5, pp. 680–693, Oct. 2023, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2023.3240931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2023.3240931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain GP, Gurupur VP, Schroeder JL, and Faulkenberry ED, “Artificial Intelligence-Based Student Learning Evaluation: A Concept Map-Based Approach for Analyzing a Student’s Understanding of a Topic,” IEEE Trans. Learning Technol, vol. 7, no. 3, pp. 267–279, Jul. 2014, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2014.2330297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2014.2330297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magnisalis I, Demetriadis S, and Karakostas A, “Adaptive and Intelligent Systems for Collaborative Learning Support: A Review of the Field,” IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, vol. 4, no. 1, pp. 5–20, Jan. 2011, doi: 10.1109/TLT.2011.2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TLT.2011.2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munir H, Vogel B, and Jacobsson A, “Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning Approaches in Digital Education: A Systematic Revision,” Information, vol. 13, no. 4, Art. no. 4, Apr. 2022, doi: 10.3390/info13040203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/info13040203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mousavinasab E, Zarifsanaiey N, Niakan Kalhori SR, Rakhshan M, Keikha L, and Ghazi Saeedi M, “Intelligent tutoring systems: a systematic review of characteristics, applications, and evaluation methods,” Interactive Learning Environments, vol. 29, no. 1, pp. 142–163, Jan. 2021, doi: 10.1080/10494820.2018.1558257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10494820.2018.1558257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarma BHS and Ravindran B, “Intelligent Tutoring Systems using Reinforcement Learning to teach Autistic Students,” in Home Informatics and Telematics: ICT for The Next Billion, Venkatesh, Gonsalves T, Monk A, and Buckner K, Eds., in IFIP — The International Federation for Information Processing. Boston, MA: Springer US, 2007, pp. 65–78. doi: 10.1007/978-0-387-73697-6_5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-0-387-73697-6_5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gascueña JM and Fernández-Caballero A, “An agent-based intelligent tutoring system for enhancing e-learning/e-teaching,” International Journal of Instructional Technology and Distance Learning, vol. 2, no. 11, pp. 11–24, 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grochow K, Martin SL, Hertzmann A, and Popović Z, “Style-based inverse kinematics,” in ACM SIGGRAPH 2004 Papers, in SIGGRAPH ‘04. New York, NY, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, Aug. 2004, pp. 522–531. doi: 10.1145/1186562.1015755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1145/1186562.1015755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puterman ML, Markov decision processes: discrete stochastic dynamic programming. John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Otterlo M and Wiering M, “Reinforcement Learning and Markov Decision Processes,” in Reinforcement Learning: State-of-the-Art, Wiering M and van Otterlo M, Eds., in Adaptation, Learning, and Optimization., Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer, 2012, pp. 3–42. doi: 10.1007/978-3-642-27645-3_1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-27645-3_1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffith S, Subramanian K, Scholz J, Isbell CL, and Thomaz AL, “Policy shaping: Integrating human feedback with reinforcement learning,” Advances in neural information processing systems, vol. 26, 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watkins CJCH and Dayan P, “Q-learning,” Mach Learn, vol. 8, no. 3, pp. 279–292, May 1992, doi: 10.1007/BF00992698.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF00992698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodgson JS, Spackman M, Pearman A, and Phillips LD, “Multi-criteria analysis: a manual,” 2009.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>