<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39436731</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0392-856X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical and experimental rheumatology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Exp Rheumatol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of SARS-COV-2 humoral response between rheumatoid arthritis, psoriatic arthritis and spondyloarthritis patients and controls in two unvaccinated cohorts.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.55563/clinexprheumatol/48440j</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To compare the humoral response after a SARS-CoV-2 infection in an inflammatory rheumatic disease population with a healthy control population in a case-control study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Cases: between March and September 2021, all consecutive unvaccinated patients followed for rheumatoid arthritis (RA), spondyloarthritis (SpA) or psoriatic arthritis (PsA) in 16 hospitals in France were systematically screened with a SARS-CoV-2 serological test. Patients with a positive test were included in the COVID-RIC-2 cohort.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONTROLS" NlmCategory="METHODS">between June and July 2020, healthcare professionals working in the Toulouse University Hospital were screened with a SARS-CoV-2 serological test. Those with a positive test were included in the COVID-BIOTOUL cohort and matched to those from COVID-RIC-2 by age, sex and time-sampling on infection date.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ANALYSES" NlmCategory="METHODS">total SARS-CoV-2 antibody titres were centrally measured and compared.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">95 patients from COVID-RIC-2 (mean age 49 years, 76% females, median delay of COVID infection: 149 days) including 48 RA, 33 SpA and 14 PsA were compared to 95 matched controls. Globally, there was no significant difference of SARS-CoV-2 antibody titres between both populations: 155 Binding Antibody Units (BAU) (IQR:7-376) in COVID-RIC-2 vs. 120 BAU (IQR:35-320) in COVID-BIOTOUL. There was a trend towards higher antibody titres in patients from COVID-RIC-2 with severe COVID-19 symptoms. In COVID-RIC-2, there was no impact of age, sex, time-sampling or underlying disease on antibody titres and patients taking glucocorticoids, abatacept or rituximab trended toward having lower antibody titres after COVID-19 infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study provides reassuring data on humoral response after COVID-19 infection in patients treated with disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruyssen-Witrand</LastName><ForeName>Adeline</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Toulouse University Hospital, Centre d'Investigation Clinique de Toulouse CIC1436, Inserm, Paul Sabatier University, Toulouse, France. ruyssen-witrand.a@chu-toulouse.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dimeglio</LastName><ForeName>Chloé</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CHU Toulouse, Hôpital Purpan, Virology Laboratory, Toulouse; INSERM UMR1291 - CNRS UMR5051, Toulouse Institute for Infectious and Inflammatory Diseases (INFINITy), Toulouse, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nogue</LastName><ForeName>Erika</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Research and Epidemiology Unit, CHU Montpellier, University of Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Molinary</LastName><ForeName>Nicolas</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UA11 Institute of Epidemiology and Public Health, INSERM, University of Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pham</LastName><ForeName>Thao</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Sainte Marguerite, Université Aix Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gaujoux-Viala</LastName><ForeName>Cécile</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Desbrest Institute of Epidemiology and Public Health (IDESP), Université de Montpellier, INSERM, Department of Rheumatology, CHU Nîmes, Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miceli-Richard</LastName><ForeName>Corinne</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service de Rhumatologie, Université de Paris, Hôpital Cochin Port Royal, AP-HP, and Unité Mixte AP-HP/Institut Pasteur, Institut Pasteur, Immunoregulation Unit, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fogel</LastName><ForeName>Olivier</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Cochin University Hospital, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Herin</LastName><ForeName>Fabrice</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Occupational Diseases Department, Toulouse University Hospital; Inserm UMR 1295: Center for Research in Population Health (CERPOP), Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, University of Toulouse, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martin-Blondel</LastName><ForeName>Guillaume</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service des Maladies Infectieuses et Tropicales, CHU de Toulouse &amp; Institut Toulousain des Maladies Infectieuses et Inflammatoires (Infinity), INSERM UMR1291 - CNRS UMR5051, Université Toulouse, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berenbaum</LastName><ForeName>Francis</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sorbonne University, CRSA, INSERM Department of Rheumatology, AP-HP Saint-Antoine Hospital, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Breuil</LastName><ForeName>Véronique</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Côte d'Azur (UCA), Service de Rhumatologie, CHU de Nice, Hôpital Pasteur, Nice; UMR E-4320 MATOs CEA/iBEB/SBTN, Faculté de Médecine, Université Nice Sophia Antipolis, Nice, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chary-Valckenaere</LastName><ForeName>Isabelle</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Nancy University Hospital Nancy, and IMoPA 7561 CNRS, University of Lorraine, Vandoeuvre‑Lès‑Nancy, Nancy, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Confavreux</LastName><ForeName>Cyrille</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Lyon, INSERM U1033 LYOS and Department of Rheumatology, Groupement Hospitalier Sud, Hospice Civils de Lyon, Pierre-Bénite, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Devauchelle-Pensec</LastName><ForeName>Valérie</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, CHU de Brest, and INSERM 1227 LBAI Université de Bretagne Occidentale, Centre de Référence des Maladies Auto-Immunes Rares de l'Adulte, Brest, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fautrel</LastName><ForeName>Bruno</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sorbonne Université, Assistance Publique Hôpitaux de Paris, Service de Rhumatologie, Groupe Hospitalier Pitié-Salpêtrière, Institut Pierre Louis d'Épidémiologie et de Santé Publique Département de Biostatistiques, INSERM UMR 1136, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Flipo</LastName><ForeName>René-Marc</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hôpital Roger Salengro, University of Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mulleman</LastName><ForeName>Denis</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Regional University Hospital Centre Tours, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Richez</LastName><ForeName>Christophe</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bordeaux University Hospital, Department of Rheumatology, Reference Center for Rare Systemic Autoimmune and Autoinflammatory Diseases RESO, and Bordeaux University, CNRS, Immuno ConcEpT, UMR 5164, Bordeaux, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tournadre</LastName><ForeName>Anne</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, CHU Clermont-Ferrand, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vittecoq</LastName><ForeName>Olivier</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Rouen University, Rouen University Hospital, Service de Rhumatologie, CIC-CRB 1404, INSERM, U1234, Rouen, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Constantin</LastName><ForeName>Arnaud</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Toulouse University Hospital INSERM UMR1291 - CNRS UMR5051, Toulouse Institute for Infectious and Inflammatory Diseases (INFINITy) and University Toulouse, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Izopet</LastName><ForeName>Jacques</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CHU Toulouse, Hôpital Purpan, Virology Laboratory, Toulouse; INSERM UMR1291 - CNRS UMR5051, Toulouse Institute for Infectious and Inflammatory Diseases (INFINITy), Toulouse, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morel</LastName><ForeName>Jacques</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, CHU and University of Montpellier, Phymedexp, Université de Montpellier, INSERM, CNRS, Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Italy</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Exp Rheumatol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8308521</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0392-856X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39436731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.55563/clinexprheumatol/48440j</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">20730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>