<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39434532</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0004-1955</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>86</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Arkhiv patologii</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Arkh Patol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>[Issues of morphological diagnosis and pathogenesis of tuberculosis].</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>81</StartPage><EndPage>93</EndPage><MedlinePgn>81-93</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.17116/patol20248605181</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Tuberculosis remains a serious global problem of our time. The epidemiological situation regarding tuberculosis in the Russian Federation and in Moscow is quite favorable, however, many manifestations of diseases and morphological changes in tuberculosis require a serious approach to the timely diagnosis of the disease, especially intravital morphological verification of the process. The article outlines the main aspects of the pathogenesis of tuberculosis, including deep immunosuppression associated with HIV. A typical microscopic picture of tuberculosis inflammation is described with an algorithm for identifying the causative agent of tuberculosis in histological sections and cytological preparations, and species identification of mycobacteria in material from paraffin blocks. Attention is paid to the morphology of HIV-associated tuberculosis, which is characterized by the loss of signs of granulomatous inflammation in condition of deep immune suppression. The need for differential diagnosis of tuberculosis with many infectious and non-infectious granulomatous-necrotic processes is noted, which requires the morphologist to compare the cellular composition of granulomas, study perifocal tissue reactions and features of vascular damage, correctly assess the activity of inflammatory changes, etc. Attention is drawn to the features of the morphological diagnostic search in cases combined pathology of tuberculosis with other infectious diseases, incl. with Covid 19. Changes are difficult to analyze due to the combination of morphological manifestations of several diseases, each of which may have atypical microscopic manifestations, as well as the varying activity of several simultaneously occurring infectious processes.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zyuzya</LastName><ForeName>Yu R</ForeName><Initials>YR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2814-4826</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Moscow Research and Clinical Center for TB Control, Moscow, Russia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>rus</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D004740">English Abstract</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Voprosy morfologicheskoi diagnostiki i patogeneza tuberkuleza.</VernacularTitle></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Russia (Federation)</Country><MedlineTA>Arkh Patol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370604</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0004-1955</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014376" MajorTopicYN="Y">Tuberculosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003937" MajorTopicYN="N">Diagnosis, Differential</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009169" MajorTopicYN="N">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000472" MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenicity</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006099" MajorTopicYN="N">Granuloma</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="rus"><AbstractText>Туберкулез остается серьезной глобальной проблемой современности. Эпидемиологическая ситуация по туберкулезу в Российской Федерации и Москве довольно благополучная, однако многообразие клинических проявлений и морфологических изменений при туберкулезе требует серьезного подхода к своевременной диагностике заболевания, особенно прижизненной морфологической верификации процесса. В статье изложены основные аспекты патогенеза туберкулеза, в том числе при глубокой иммуносупрессии, связанной с ВИЧ. Описана типичная микроскопическая картина туберкулезного воспаления с алгоритмом выявления возбудителя туберкулеза в гистологических срезах и цитологических препаратах, видовой идентификацией микобактерий в материале из парафиновых блоков. Уделено внимание морфологии ВИЧ-ассоциированного туберкулеза, при котором характерна утрата признаков гранулематозного воспаления в условиях глубокой иммунной супрессии. Отмечена необходимость дифференциальной диагностики туберкулеза с многими инфекционными и неинфекционными гранулематозно-некротическими процессами, что требует от морфолога сравнения клеточного состава гранулем, исследования перифокальных тканевых реакций и особенностей поражения сосудов, правильной оценки активности воспалительных изменений и др. Обращено внимание на особенности морфологического диагностического поиска в случаях сочетанной патологии туберкулеза с другими инфекционными заболеваниями, в том числе с COVID-19. Изменения сложно анализировать вследствие сочетания морфологических проявлений нескольких заболеваний, каждое из которых может иметь нетипичные микроскопические проявления, а также различной активности нескольких одновременно протекающих инфекционных процессов.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HIV-associated tuberculosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">differential diagnosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">granulomatous inflammation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">morphology of tuberculosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenesis of tuberculosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tuberculosis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39434532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17116/patol20248605181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>