<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39442817</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-1208</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbial pathogenesis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microb Pathog</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prevalence of Toxoplasma gondii infection in covid-19 patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>107064</StartPage><MedlinePgn>107064</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.107064</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0882-4010(24)00531-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Toxoplasma gondii is a parasite that affects over one billion people worldwide. COVID-19, caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus, has resulted in over 4.8 million deaths worldwide. Both diseases activate the innate immune response via the same pathway. Studies have suggested that Toxoplasma infection may either protect against or worsen the severity of COVID-19. This meta-analysis investigated the relationship between toxoplasmosis prevalence and COVID-19. The selection of studies was based on a systematic search using specific keywords in Scopus, Web of Science, PubMed, and Google Scholar databases between 2019 and 2023. The study findings were analyzed using STATA software version 17.0, and the prevalence of toxoplasmosis in people with COVID-19 and its confidence interval were extracted from the selected studies. The study's heterogeneity was assessed using the I2 test, and publication bias was evaluated using a funnel plot and Egger's test. A p value of 0.05 was considered significant. The meta-analysis included nine studies with a total of 1,972 COVID-19-positive individuals, and the results showed a significant association between T. gondii infection and COVID-19 severity. The I2 statistic was almost 99%, indicating large heterogeneity among the studies. The Egger's test showed no publication bias. The pooled prevalence of T. gondii infection in COVID-19-positive individuals was 0.680 (95% CI: 0.613-0.748), which was significantly higher than the prevalence observed in the general population. The forest plot shows that the prevalence rate was significantly different from that of 0% (P &lt; 0.001). The meta-analysis found that the prevalence of T. gondii infection was significantly higher in individuals with COVID-19 than in the general population, indicating a possible association between the two infections. However, the significant heterogeneity among the studies underscores the need for further research to understand the underlying mechanisms and clinical implications of this association.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fakhar</LastName><ForeName>Mahdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Iranian National Registry Center for Lophomoniasis (INRCL) and Toxoplasmosis (INRCT), Imam Khomeini Hospital, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Najafi Ghobadi</LastName><ForeName>Khadijeh</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, School of Public Health, Faculty of Health, Ilam University of Medical Sciences, Ilam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barati</LastName><ForeName>Nastaran</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Molecular Medicine, Hamadan University of Medical Sciences, Hamadan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zafari</LastName><ForeName>Salman</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Parasitology and Mycology, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran; Student's Scientific Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hosseini</LastName><ForeName>Seyed Ali</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Parasitology and Mycology, School of Medicine, Hamadan University of Medical Sciences, Hamadan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soleymani</LastName><ForeName>Eissa</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Parasitology and Mycology, School of Medicine, Hamadan University of Medical Sciences, Hamadan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Motavallihaghi</LastName><ForeName>Seyedmousa</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Parasitology and Mycology, School of Medicine, Hamadan University of Medical Sciences, Hamadan, Iran. Electronic address: m.motevali@umsha.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Microb Pathog</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8606191</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0882-4010</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Toxoplasma gondii</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest All authors clarify the manuscript neither the entire paper nor any part of its content has been published or submitted elsewhere. The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. We hope this manuscript meets the requirement for publication in the journal. Please let us know if there is any further information you may require regarding this manuscript.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39442817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.107064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0882-4010(24)00531-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>