<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39449001</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The effects of mass media messages, perceived susceptibility and self-rated health on public attitude towards COVID-19 in South Africa.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2951</StartPage><MedlinePgn>2951</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2951</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-024-20442-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">South Africa was the worst affected country in Africa by the COVID-19 pandemic and it is important to interrogate the attitude of the populace towards the pandemic for future interventions. Therefore, this study examined effects of mass media messages, susceptibility to COVID-19 and self-rated health on the attitudes of South Africans towards the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Data was from the National Income Dynamics Study - Coronavirus Rapid Mobile Survey (NIDS-CRAM) of 2021 which is a nationally representative panel survey of about 7,000 South African individuals in all the nine provinces. Analyses of data were through descriptive statistics, chi square test and logistic regression models.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The results showed that 61.28% of the resondents did not take COVID-19 test while 91.09% of them engaged in behavioral changes such as social distancing and wearing of face masks. In addition, 74.27% of the respondents had access to mass media information, 70.44% believed they have good physical health while 32.43% felt they were not susceptible to COVID-19. The chi-square results of attitude towards COVID-19 showed significant differences in access to mass media messages on COVID-19, race, and province of residence. Furthermore, respondents who had access to mass media information on COVID-19 (OR = 1.469; p = 0.001) and respondents who believed that they were susceptible to COVID-19 infection (OR = 1.443; p = 0.001) were significantly associated with increased likelihood of engagement in behavioral changes to avoid the COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These findings therefore emphasize the need for increased awareness and sensitization of the people about the susceptibility and adverse effects of diseases to ensure that they adopt the appropriate attitudes that will safeguard them from such diseases outbreak.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nwachukwu</LastName><ForeName>Chidiebere A</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mass Communication, University of Nigeria Nsukka, Enugu, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ajaero</LastName><ForeName>Chukwuedozie K</ForeName><Initials>CK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Geography, University of Nigeria Nsukka, Enugu, Nigeria. chukwuedozie.ajaero@unn.edu.ng.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology and International Public Health, Bielefeld University, Bielefeld, Germany. chukwuedozie.ajaero@unn.edu.ng.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ajaero</LastName><ForeName>Ijeoma D</ForeName><Initials>ID</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mass Communication, University of Nigeria Nsukka, Enugu, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Strategic Communication, University of Johannesburg, Johannesburg, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013019" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">South Africa</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008402" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mass Media</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011639" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Opinion</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007722" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001294" MajorTopicYN="N">Attitude to Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004198" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Susceptibility</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mass media</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Self-rated health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">South Africa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Susceptibility</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11505730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-20442-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-024-20442-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation, WHO COVID-19 dashboard. 2024 https://data.who.int/dashboard/covid19/deaths?n=0. Accessed April 21, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anwar A, Malik M, Raees V, Anwar A. Role of mass media and public health communication in the COVID-19 pandemic. Cureus. 2020;12:e10453.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7557800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33072461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wogu JO, Chukwu CO, Nwafor KA, Ugwuoke JC, Ugwulor-Onyinyechi CC. Assessing the role of the media in the prevention and control of meningitis in Nigeria. J Int Med Res. 2019;48:1–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7140183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30983454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kigatiira KK. Fear of contracting COVID-19: influence of information sources and message content on fear-arousal among Boda-Boda riders in Nairobi County, Kenya. Int J Res -Granthaalayah. 2020;8:190–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, LiuY. Media exposure and anxiety during COVID-19: the mediation effect of media vicarious traumatization. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:4720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7370076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32630054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ufuophu-Biri E, Bebenimibo P. Exploring the relationship between exposure to media messages on COVID-19 and compliance with its preventive measures among residents of Delta State. J Educ Soc Res 2021; 11–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anorue LI, Ugboaja SU, Ayogu GO, Okonkwo CP. An assessment of public response to media campaigns on COVID-19 preventive measures in Southeast, Nigeria. Jos J Relig Philos. 2021;3:96–115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papagiannis D, Malli F, Raptis DG, Papathanasiou IV, Fradelos EC, Daniel Z, Rachiotis G, Gourgoulianis K. Assessment of knowledge, attitudes, and practices towards new corononavirus (SARS COV-2) of health care professionals in Greece before the outbreak period. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:4925.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7400230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32650614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barua Z, Barua S, Aktar S, Kabir N, Li M. Effects of misinformation on COVID-19 individual responses and recommendations for resilience of disastrous consequences of misinformation. Prog Disaster Sci. 2020;8:100119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7373041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34173443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazir M, Hussain I, Tian J, Akram S, Tshiaba SM, Mushtaq S, Shad MA. A multidimensional model of public health approaches against COVID-19. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:3780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7312600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32466581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalid A, Ali S, Qamar AC. The relationship between media advertising and attitudinal changes during COVID-19. n.d; 10.21203/rs.3.rs-77596/vi</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azlan AA, Hamzah MR, Sern TJ, Ayub SH, Mohamad E. Public knowledge, attitudes and practices towards COVID-19: a cross-sectional study in Malaysia. PLoS ONE. 2020;15:e0233668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7241824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amoo OS, Tijani B, Onuigbo TI, Oraegbu JI, Kareithi DN, Obi JC, Adeniji ET, Dosunmu AA, Karera S, Filani T, Akinreni T, Ezike E, Owoseni K, Audu RA, Salako BL. Factors affecting COVID-19 testing behaviours among the population in South Western Nigeria. Int J Public Health. 2022;67:1604993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9582156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36275434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adesegun OA, Binuyo T, Adeyemi O, Ehioghae O, Rabor DF, Amusan O, Akinboboye O, Duke OF, Olamifihan AG, Ajose O, Idowu AO, Abiodun O. The COVID-19 crisis in sub-saharan Africa: knowledge, attitude, and practices of the Nigerian public. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2020;10:1997–004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7646756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32975179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed HM. Adherence to COVID-19 preventive measures among male medical students, Egypt. J Egypt Public Health Assoc. 2022;97:8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8853074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35175444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omaka-Amari LN, Aleke CO, Obande-Ogbuinya NE, Ngwake PC, Nwankwo O, Afoke EN. Corononavirus (COVID-19) pandemic in Nigeria: preventive and control challenges within the first two months of outbreak. Afr J Reprod Health. 2020;24:87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34077058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ditekemena JD, Nkamba DM, Muhindo HM, Siewe JNF, Luhata C, Bergh RV, Kitoto AT, Damme WV, Muyembe JJ, Colebunders R. Factors associated with adherence to COVID-19 prevention measures in the Democratic Republic of the Congo (DRC): results of an online survey. BMJ Open. 2021;11:e043356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7813390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33462101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun N, Hua CL, Qiu X, Brown JS. Detrminants of COVID-19 testing among late middle-aged and older adults: appyling the health belief model. Aging Health Res. 2022;2:100066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8949689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35350777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Y, Cheng Y, Sui M. The moderating effects of perceived severity on the generational gap in preventive behaviors during the COVID-19 pandemic in the U.S. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:2011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7922035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33669713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanherle R, Kurten S, Rousseau A. How social media, news media and interpersonal communication relate to COVID-19 risk perceptions and behaviours. Eur J Health Commun. 2023;4:28–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh SH, Lee SY, Han C. The effects of social media use on preventive behaviours during infectious disease outbreaks: the mediating role of self-relevant emotions and public risk-perception. Health Commun. 2020. 10.1080/10410236.2020.1724639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32064932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harper CA, Satchell LP, Fido D, Latzman RD. Functional fear predicts health compliance in the COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Ment Health Addict. 2021;19:1875–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7185265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32346359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsing J, Ma J, Barrero-Castillero A, Jani SG, Pulendram UP, Lin BJ, Thomas-Uribe M, Wang CJ. Influence of health beliefs on adherence to COVID-19 preventative practices: International social media-based survey study. J Med Internet Res. 2021;23:e23720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7919844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33571103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li PP, Zhong F. A study on the correlation between media usage frequency and audiences’ risk perception, emotion and behaviour. Front Psychol. 2022;12:822300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8811358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35126265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen XT, Biu HN, Nguyen TH. The impact of media exposure on COVID-19 preventive behaviors among Vietnamese people: evidence using expanded Protection Motivation Theory. Sage Open. 2022. 10.1177/21582440221096129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harorli E. Perceptions of risk factors that influence COVID-19 protective behaviour determinants. Trends Bus Econ. 2023;37:2–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeDonno MA, Lonzo J, Lev X, Morris JD. Perceived susceptibility and severity of COVID-19 on prevention practices, early in the pandemic in the state of Florida. J Community Health. 2022;47:627–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9024286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35451692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mody A, Pfeifauf K, Bradley C, Fox B, Hlastshwayo MG, Ross W, Sanders-Thompson V, Maddox KJ, Reidhead M, Schootman M, Powderly WG, Geng EH. Understanding drivers of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) racial disparities: a population-level analysis of COVID-19 testing among black and white populations. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;73:e2921–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7799327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33315066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rentsch CT, Kidwai-Khan F, Tate JP, Park LS, King JT, Skanderson M, Hauser RG, Schultze A, Jarvis CI, Holodniyi M, Re VL, Akgu KM, Crothers K, Tadde TH, Freiberg MS, Justice AC. Patterns of COVID-19 testing and mortality by race and ethnicity among United States veterans: a nationwide cohort study. PLoS ONE. 2020;17:e1003379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7508372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32960880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sauceda JA, Neilands TB, Lightfoot M, Saberi P. Findings from a probability-based survey of United States households about preventive measures based on race, ethnicity, and age in response to severe aute respiratory syndrome coronoavirus 2. J Infect Dis. 2020;XX:0–0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7499587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32860499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah BH, Khan Z, Riaz S. Challenges in tackling COVID-19: use of the mass media versus interpersonal channels in Pakistan. Inf. Tarsadalon. 2021;XX1:67–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miilunpalo S, Vuori I, Oja P, Pasanen PM, Urponen H. Self-rated health status as a health measure: the predictive value of self-reported health status on the use of physician services and on mortality in the working-age populations. J Clin Epidemiol. 1997;50:517–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9180644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abuladze L, Kunder N, Lang K, Vaask S. Associations between self-rated health and health behaviour among older adults in Estonia: a cross-sectional analysis. BMJ Open. 2017;7:e013257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5734211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28601816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riediger ND, Bombak AE, Mudryj AN. Health related behaviours and their relationship with self-rated health among Canadian adults. BMC Public Health. 2019;19:960.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6637547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31319817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guthrie J, Fisman D, Gardy JL. Self-rated health and reasons for non-vaccination against seasonal influenza in Canadian adults with asthma. PLoS ONE. 2017;12:eo17211736.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5312957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28207823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Halloram AC, Lu P, Williams WW, Bridges CB, Singleton JA. Influenza vaccination coverage among people with high risk conditions in the U.S. Am J Prev Med. 2015. 10.1016/j.amepre.2015.06.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4770254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26238603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu S. Sickness and preventive medical behavior. J Health Econ. 2003;22:675–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12842321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ArthurC, Abenes K, Waselewski M, Chuisano S, Chang T. Ýouths’ perceptions and behaviors on COVID-19 testing. PLoS ONE. 2023;18:eo290007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10420336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37566576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fridman I, Lucas N, Henke D, Zigler CK. Association between public about COVID-19 trust in information sources and adherence to social distancing: cross sectional survey. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2020;6:e22060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7511226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32930670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matias LDM, Luciena JGS, Azevedo TF, Silva ALDA, Andrade CMML. Factors related to the prevention of COVID-19 in people with diabetes:a cross-sectional study. Online Braz J Nurs. 2021;20:e20216517.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng Y, Pei C, Zhang Y, Wang J, Zhang K, Zhang Z, Zhu ZP. A cross-sectional survey of knowledge, attitude and practice associated with COVID-19 among undergraduate students in China. BMC Public Health. 2020;20:1292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7447607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32847554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ipinnimo TM, Sanni TA, Aladesuru TA, Adebayo OA, Omowaye MT, Adeniyi IO, Ipinnimo OM, Olasehinde OK, Adetunbi AR. Knowledge of COVID-19 and practice of preventive measures among adult residents during the ease of lockdown in Nigeria. Nig J Med. 2021;30:464–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li ZH, Zhang XR, Zhong WF, Song WQ, Wang ZH, Chen Q, Liu D, Huang QM, Shen D, Chen PL, Mao A, Zhang D, Yang X, Wu XB. C.Mao C. Knowledge, attitudes, and practices related to coronavirus disease 2019 during the outbreak among workers in China: a large cross-sectional study. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2020;14:e0008584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7498029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32941447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rural Health Information Hub. The Health Belief Model. 2002. https://www.ruralhealthinfo.org/toolkits/health-promotion/2/theories-and-models/health-belief. Accessed June 15, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LaMorte WW. Behavioral change models. 2019 https://www.sphweb.bumc.bu.edu.otlt/MPH-Modules/SB/BehavioralChangeTheories/BehavioralChangeTheories2/html. Accessed April 12, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gili A, Caminiti M, Lupi C, Zichichi S, Minicucci I, Pezzotti P, Primieri C, Bietta C, Stracci F. Factors associated with ethnic disparities in SARS-CoV-2 infection and hospitalization. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20:6521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10418672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37569061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mesch GS, Liu XJ. Differential media exposure and perceptions of fear and behavior change in China and Israel during the COVID-19 pandemic. New Media Soc. 2021. 10.1177/14614448231164638.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu T, Mack JA, Salvatore M, Sankar SP, Valley TS, Singh K, Nallamothu BK, Kheterpal S, Lisabeth L, Fritsche LG, Mukherjee B. Characteristics associated with racial/ethnic disparities in COVID-19 outcomes in an academic health care system. JAMA NETW OPEN. 2020;3: e2025197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7578774</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33084902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yehualashet SS, Asefa KK, Mekonnen AG, Gemeda BN, Shiferaw WS, Aynalem A, Bilchut AH, Derseh BT, Mekuria AD, Mekonnen WN, Meseret WA, Tegegnework SS, Abosetegn AE. Predictors of adherence to COVID-19 prevention measure among communities in North Shoa Zone, Ethiopia based on health belief model: a cross-sectional study. PLoS ONE. 2021;16:e0246006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7822535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33481962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bante A, Mersha A, Tesfaye A, Tsegaye B, Shibiru S, Ayele G, Girma M. Adherence with COVID-19 preventive measures and associated factors among residents of Dirashe district, Southern Ethiopia. Patient Prefer Adherence. 2021;15:237–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7868191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33568900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>