<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39449246</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-1446</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Public health nursing (Boston, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Public Health Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Public Health Interventions Targeting the Prevention of Adolescent Vaping: A Scoping Review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/phn.13464</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Despite a brief decline during the COVID-19 pandemic, vaping behaviors among adolescents continue to be an international public health concern because of associated health risks and harms. A thorough investigation of existing interventions preventing adolescent vaping is needed to help address this public health crisis and reduce serious and avoidable vaping-related health risks. We reviewed the literature to identify public health interventions aimed at preventing adolescent vaping and summarized their key components and outcome measures.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">We conducted a scoping review of the literature using the Joanna Briggs Institute methodology searching in MEDLINE, CINAHL, Embase, PubMed, PsycINFO, ProQuest, and Web of Science. Two reviewers screened 589 records for relevance. Studies from any location, reported in English, and described vaping prevention interventions targeting adolescents were included. Records were excluded if they were reported in other languages, published outside the review timeframe, lacked an evaluation, focused on cessation-based interventions, or were review articles. Data extracted included intervention type, key components, and outcome measures.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Thirty-eight included articles were identified and categorized into three intervention categories: school-based, public education/risk communication campaigns, and public policies/government regulations. Key components of the interventions included format, duration, and topics. Formats varied from single to multi-sessions. Prominent topics covered included risks and harms associated with vaping, and the most frequently reported outcome measures used were knowledge, attitudes, and beliefs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our findings summarize existing public health interventions found in the literature and insights into approaches used to address the global adolescent vaping crisis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Public Health Nursing published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>DiCasmirro</LastName><ForeName>Jamie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7377-1816</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queens' University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Faculty of Health and Behavioural Sciences, Lakehead University, Thunder Bay, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tranmer</LastName><ForeName>Joan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queens' University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davison</LastName><ForeName>Colleen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Science, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queens' University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Development Studies, Faculty of Arts and Science, Queens' University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Woo</LastName><ForeName>Kevin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queens' University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Toon</LastName><ForeName>Danielle</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queens' University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hubeny</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Faculty of Health and Behavioural Sciences, Lakehead University, Thunder Bay, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ross-White</LastName><ForeName>Amanda</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Q, ueen's Collaboration for Health Care Quality: A JBI Centre of Excellence, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bracken Health Sciences Library, Queen's University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goldie</LastName><ForeName>Catherine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queens' University, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Q, ueen's Collaboration for Health Care Quality: A JBI Centre of Excellence, Kingston, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Public Health Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8501498</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0737-1209</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">e‐cigarettes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health interventions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tobacco</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaping</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">youth</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/phn.13464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Andrews, J. C., D. Mays, R. G. Netemeyer, S. Burton, and J. Kees. 2019. “Effects of E‐Cigarette Health Warnings and Modified Risk Ad Claims on Adolescent E‐Cigarette Craving and Susceptibility.” Nicotine &amp; Tobacco Research 21, no. 6: 792–798. https://doi.org/10.1093/ntr/nty076.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aleyan, S., A. Cole, W. Qian, and S. T. Leatherdale. 2018. “Risky Business: A Longitudinal Study Examining Cigarette Smoking Initiation Among Susceptible and Non‐Susceptible E‐Cigarette Users in Canada.” BMJ Open 8, no. 5: e021080. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen‐2017‐021080.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asdigian, N. L., N. R. Riggs, P. A. Valverde, and L. A. Crane. 2022. “Reducing Youth Vaping: A Pilot Test of the Peer‐Led “Youth Engaged Strategies for Changing Adolescent Norms!” (YES‐CAN!) Program.” Health Promotion Practice 24, no. 5: 956–962. https://doi.org/10.1177/15248399221100793.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baig, S. A., S. M. Noar, N. C. Gottfredson, M. H. Boynton, K. M. Ribisl, and N. T. Brewer. 2019. “UNC Perceived Message Effectiveness: Validation of a Brief Scale.” Annals of Behavioral Medicine 53, no. 8: 732–742. https://doi.org/10.1093/abm/kay080.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker, K. A., N. J. Campbell, D. Noonan, J. A. Thompson, and A. Derouin. 2022. “Vaping Prevention in a Middle School Population Using CATCH My Breath.” Journal of Pediatric Health Care 36, no. 2: 90–98. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pedhc.2021.07.013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birdsey, J., M. Cornelius, A. Jamal, et al. 2023. “Tobacco Product Use Among U.S. Middle and High School Students—National Youth Tobacco Survey, 2023.” MMWR. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 72, no. 44: 1173–1182. https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm7244a1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boynton, M. H., N. Sanzo, W. Brothers, et al. 2022. “Perceived Effectiveness of Objective Elements of Vaping Prevention Messages Among Adolescents.” Tobacco Control 32, no. e2: e228–e235. https://doi.org/10.1136/tobaccocontrol‐2021‐057151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bracken‐Clarke, D., D. Kapoor, A. M. Baird, et al. 2021. “Vaping and Lung Cancer—A Review of Current Data and Recommendations.” Lung Cancer (Amsterdam, Netherlands) 153: 11–20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lungcan.2020.12.030.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown, L. D., F. C. Bandiera, and M. B. Harrell. 2019. “Cluster Randomized Trial of Teens Against Tobacco Use: Youth Empowerment for Tobacco Control in El Paso, Texas.” American Journal of Preventive Medicine 57, no. 5: 592–600. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2019.06.013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadi, N., S. E. Hadland, and S. K. Harris. 2019. “Understanding the Implications of the “Vaping Epidemic” Among Adolescents and Young Adults: a Call for Action.” Substance Abuse 40, no. 1: 7–10. https://doi.org/10.1080/08897077.2019.1580241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu, K.‐H., J. Sidani, S. Matheny, et al. 2021. “Implementation of a Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial: Identifying Student Peer Leaders to Lead E‐Cigarette Interventions.” Addictive Behaviors 114: 106726. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2020.106726.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DiCasmirro, J., J. Tranmer, C. Davison, et al. 2023. “Public Health Interventions to Prevent Adolescent Vaping: A Scoping Review Protocol.” JBI Evidence Synthesis 21, no. 11: 2272–2278. https://doi.org/10.11124/JBIES‐23‐00055.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>England, K. J., A. L. Edwards, A. C. Paulson, E. P. Libby, P. T. Harrell, and K. A. Mondejar. 2021. “Rethink Vape: Development and Evaluation of a Risk Communication Campaign to Prevent Youth E‐cigarette Use.” Addictive Behaviors 113: 106664. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2020.106664.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrington, D. P. 2006. “Key Longitudinal–Experimental Studies in Criminology.” Journal of Experimental Criminology 2, no. 2: 121–141. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11292‐006‐9000‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzwater, H. F. 2020. Evaluation of the Impact of an Educational Intervention Focused on Adolescent Vaping among Rural Middle School Students. Morgantown, West Virginia, United States: ProQuest Dissertations Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaiha, S. M., J. Cheng, and B. Halpern‐Felsher. 2020. “Association Between Youth Smoking, Electronic Cigarette Use, and COVID‐19.” Journal of Adolescent Health 67, no. 4: 519–523. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.07.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaiha, S. M., A. Duemler, L. Silverwood, A. Razo, B. Halpern‐Felsher, and S. C. Walley. 2021. “School‐Based E‐Cigarette Education in Alabama: Impact on Knowledge of E‐Cigarettes, Perceptions and Intent to Try.” Addictive Behaviors 112: 106519–106519. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2020.106519.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner, L. A., A.‐L. Rowe, N. C. Newton, et al. 2024. “A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of School‐Based Preventive Interventions Targeting E‐Cigarette Use Among Adolescents.” Prevention Science Published September 26, 2024. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11121-024-01730-6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, J.‐L., H.‐P. Hsu, T.‐M. Lai, M.‐L. Lin, C.‐M. Chung, and C.‐M. Huang. 2021. “Acceptability Evaluation of the Use of Virtual Reality Games in Smoking‐Prevention Education for High School Students: Prospective Observational Study.” Journal of Medical Internet Research 23, no. 9: e28037. https://doi.org/10.2196/28037.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hailemariam, M., T. Bustos, B. Montgomery, R. Barajas, L. B. Evans, and A. Drahota. 2019. “Evidence‐Based Intervention Sustainability Strategies: A Systematic Review.” Implementation Science 14, no. 1: 57. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13012‐019‐0910‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammond, D., J. L. Reid, R. Burkhalter, and D. Hong. 2023. Trends in Smoking and Vaping Among Young People: Findings From the ITC Youth Survey. Waterloo, Ontario, Canada: University of Waterloo. https://tobaccocontrol‐bmj‐com.proxy.queensu.ca/content/tobaccocontrol/suppl/2023/11/08/tc‐2023‐058241.DC1/tc‐2023‐058241supp001_data_supplement.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris, K. M., G. Duncan, J., and J. Boisjoly. 2002. “Evaluating the Role of “Nothing to Lose” Attitudes on Risky Behavior in Adolescence.” Social Forces 80, no. 3: 1005–1039. https://doi.org/10.1353/sof.2002.0008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawkins, S. S., M. Ghiani, and C. F. Baum. 2019. “Associations Between State Tobacco Control Policies and Adolescent ENDS Use.” Journal of Public Health Management and Practice 25, no. 6: 529–536. https://doi.org/10.1097/PHH.0000000000000859.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hieftje, K. D., C.‐S. F. Fernandes, I.‐H. Lin, and L. E. Fiellin. 2021. “Effectiveness of a Web‐Based Tobacco Product Use Prevention Videogame Intervention on Young Adolescents' Beliefs and Knowledge.” Substance Abuse 42, no. 1: 47–53. https://doi.org/10.1080/08897077.2019.1691128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang, J.‐E., and S.‐I. Cho. 2020. “The Association Between New Graphic Health Warning Labels on Tobacco Products and Attitudes Toward Smoking Among south Korean Adolescents: a National Cross‐sectional Study.” BMC Public Health [Electronic Resource] 20, no. 1: 748–748. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889‐020‐08638‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jongenelis, M. I. 2023. “Challenges and Opportunities Associated With E‐Cigarettes in Australia: A Qualitative Study.” Australian and New Zealand Journal of Public Health 47, no. 1: 100006. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anzjph.2022.100006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katz, S. J., W. Shi, M. Erkkinen, B. Lindgren, and D. Hatsukami. 2020. “High School Youth and E‐Cigarettes: The Influence of Modified Risk Statements and Flavors on E‐Cigarette Packaging.” American Journal of Health Behavior 44, no. 2: 130–145. https://doi.org/10.5993/AJHB.44.2.2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelder, S. H., D. S. Mantey, D. Van Dusen, K. Case, A. Haas, and A. E. Springer. 2020. “A Middle School Program to Prevent E‐Cigarette Use: A Pilot Study of “CATCH My Breath”.” Public Health Reports (1974) 135, no. 2: 220–229. https://doi.org/10.1177/0033354919900887.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowitt, S. D., J. Mendel Sheldon, R. N. Vereen, et al. 2023. “The Impact of the Real Cost Vaping and Smoking Ads Across Tobacco Products.” Nicotine &amp; Tobacco Research 25, no. 3: 430–437. https://doi.org/10.1093/ntr/ntac206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazard, A. J. 2021. “Social Media Message Designs to Educate Adolescents About E‐Cigarettes.” Journal of Adolescent Health 68, no. 1: 130–137. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.05.030.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levac, D., H. Colquhoun, and K. K. O'Brien. 2010. “Scoping Studies: Advancing the Methodology.” Implementation Science 5, no. 1: 69. https://doi.org/10.1186/1748‐5908‐5‐69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ly, C. 2015. The Texas Tobacco Prevention Program (T2P 2): an Update of the Minnesota Smoking Prevention Program (MSPP). Houston Texas, US: ProQuest Dissertations Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyzwinski, L. N., J. A. Naslund, C. J. Miller, and M. J. Eisenberg. 2022. “Global Youth Vaping and Respiratory Health: Epidemiology, Interventions, and Policies.” NPJ Primary Care Respiratory Medicine 32, no. 1: 14. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41533‐022‐00277‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, J., S. M. Gaiha, and B. Halpern‐Felsher. 2020. “A Breath of Knowledge: Overview of Current Adolescent E‐Cigarette Prevention and Cessation Programs.” Current Addiction Reports 7, no. 4: 520–532. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40429‐020‐00345‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macinko, J., and D. Silver. 2018. “Impact of New York City's 2014 Increased Minimum Legal Purchase Age on Youth Tobacco Use.” American Journal of Public Health 108, no. 5: 669–675. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2018.304340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacMonegle, A. J., A. A. Smith, J. Duke, et al. 2022. “Effects of a National Campaign on Youth Beliefs and Perceptions About Electronic Cigarettes and Smoking.” Preventing Chronic Disease 19: E16. https://doi.org/10.5888/pcd19.210332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLeroy, K. R., D. Bibeau, A. Steckler, and K. Glanz. 1988. “An Ecological Perspective on Health Promotion Programs.” Health Education Quarterly 15, no. 4: 351–377. https://doi.org/10.1177/109019818801500401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMenamin, S. B., S. E. Cummins, Y. L. Zhuang, et al. 2018. “Evaluation of the Tobacco‐Use Prevention Education (TUPE) Program in California.” PLoS ONE 13, no. 11: e0206921. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0206921.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meienberg, A., M. Mayr, A. Vischer, M. J. Zellweger, and T. Burkard. 2021. “Smoking Prevention in Adolescents: A Cross‐Sectional and Qualitative Evaluation of a Newly Implemented Prevention Program in Switzerland.” BMJ Open 11, no. 12: e048319. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen‐2020‐048319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno, R. 2021. “A Community‐Based Pilot Prevention Program to Prevent Electronic Cigarette Use Among Teens.” Doctor of Nursing Practice Projects. 36. https://scholarworks.boisestate.edu/dnp/36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno, M. A., K. Binger, Q. Zhao, J. Eickhoff, M. Minich, and Y. T. Uhls. 2022. “Digital Technology and Media Use by Adolescents: Latent Class Analysis.” JMIR Pediatrics and Parenting 5, no. 2: e35540. https://doi.org/10.2196/35540.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrill, A. M., C. A. Abel, M. Januszweski, and B. Chamberlain. 2017. “Community Education by Advanced Pharmacy Practice Experience Students: Increasing Electronic Cigarette Awareness Amongst Teens.” Currents in Pharmacy Teaching and Learning 9, no. 6: 1147–1150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cptl.2017.07.022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munn, Z., T. H. Barker, S. Moola, et al. 2020. “Methodological Quality of Case Series Studies: an Introduction to the JBI Critical Appraisal Tool.” JBI Evidence Synthesis 18, no. 10: 2127–2133. https://doi.org/10.11124/JBISRIR‐D‐19‐00099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mylocopos, G., E. Wennberg, A. Reiter, et al. 2024. “Interventions for Preventing E‐Cigarette Use Among Children and Youth: a Systematic Review.” American Journal of Preventive Medicine 66, no. 2: 351–370. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2023.09.028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine. 2018. Public Health Consequences of E‐Cigarettes. Washington, DC: The National Academies Press. https://doi.org/10.17226/24952.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicksic, N. E., E. K. Do, and A. J. Barnes. 2020. “Cannabis Legalization, Tobacco Prevention Policies, and Cannabis Use in E‐Cigarettes Among Youth.” Drug and Alcohol Dependence 206: 107730. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2019.107730.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikitin, D., D. S. Timberlake, and R. S. Williams. 2016. “Is the E‐liquid Industry Regulating Itself? A Look at E‐liquid Internet Vendors in the United States.” Nicotine &amp; Tobacco Research 18, no. 10: 1967–1972. https://doi.org/10.1093/ntr/ntw091.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noar, S. M., T. Bell, D. Kelley, J. Barker, and M. Yzer. 2018. “Perceived Message Effectiveness Measures in Tobacco Education Campaigns: a Systematic Review.” Communication Methods and Measures 12, no. 4: 295–313. https://doi.org/10.1080/19312458.2018.1483017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noar, S. M., J. A. Rohde, C. Horvitz, A. J. Lazard, J. Cornacchione Ross, and E. L. Sutfin. 2019. “Adolescents' receptivity to E‐Cigarette Harms Messages Delivered Using Text Messaging.” Addictive Behaviors 91: 201–207. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2018.05.025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noar, S. M., J. A. Rohde, H. Prentice‐Dunn, A. Kresovich, M. G. Hall, and N. T. Brewer. 2020. “Evaluating the Actual and Perceived Effectiveness of E‐cigarette Prevention Advertisements Among Adolescents.” Addictive Behaviors 109: 106473–106473. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2020.106473.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noar, S. M., N. C. Gottfredson, T. Kieu, et al. 2022. “Impact of Vaping Prevention Advertisements on US Adolescents: a Randomized Clinical Trial.” JAMA Network Open 5, no. 10: e2236370. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.36370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Connor, S., H. Pelletier, D. Bayoumy, and R. Schwartz. 2019. Interventions to Prevent Harms From Vaping. Special Report. https://www.otru.org/wp‐content/uploads/2019/05/special_vape_interventions.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onrust, S. A., R. Otten, J. Lammers, and F. Smit. 2016. “School‐Based Programmes to Reduce and Prevent Substance Use in Different Age Groups: What Works for Whom? Systematic Review and Meta‐Regression Analysis.” Clinical Psychology Review 44: 45–59. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpr.2015.11.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page, M. J., J. E. McKenzie, P. M. Bossuyt, et al. 2021. “The PRISMA 2020 Statement: An Updated Guideline for Reporting Systematic Reviews.” Journal of Clinical Epidemiology 134: 178–189. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2021.03.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pentz, M. A., K. D. Hieftje, T. M. Pendergrass, et al. 2019. “A Videogame Intervention for Tobacco Product Use Prevention in Adolescents.” Addictive Behaviors 91: 188–192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2018.11.016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters, M. D. J., C. Marnie, A. C. Tricco, et al. 2020. “Updated Methodological Guidance for the Conduct of Scoping Reviews.” JBI Evidence Synthesis 18, no. 10: 2119–2126. https://doi.org/10.11124/JBIES‐20‐00167.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters, M. D. J., C. Marnie, H. Colquhoun, et al. 2021. “Scoping Reviews: Reinforcing and Advancing the Methodology and Application.” Systematic Reviews 10, no. 1: 263. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13643‐021‐01821‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pienkowski, M., M. Chaiton, S. J. Bondy, et al. 2024. “Milestones in the Natural Course of the Onset of E‐cigarette Dependence Among Adolescents and Young Adults: Retrospective Study.” Addictive Behaviors 148: 107846–107846. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2023.107846.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rideout, V., A. Peebles, S. Mann, and M. B. Robb. 2022. Common Sense Census: Media Use by Tweens and Teens, 2021. San Francisco, CA: Common Sense. https://www.commonsensemedia.org/sites/default/files/research/report/8‐18‐census‐integrated‐report‐final‐web_0.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roditis, M. L., A. Dineva, A. Smith, et al. 2020. “Reactions to Electronic Nicotine Delivery System (ENDS) Prevention Messages: Results From Qualitative Research Used to Inform FDA's First Youth ENDS Prevention Campaign.” Tobacco Control 29, no. 5: 510–515. https://doi.org/10.1136/tobaccocontrol‐2019‐055104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roeseler, A., T. D. Vuong, L. Henriksen, and X. Zhang. 2019. “Assessment of Underage Sales Violations in Tobacco Stores and Vape Shops.” JAMA Pediatrics 173, no. 8: 795–797. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2019.1571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rozema, A. D., M. Hiemstra, J. J. P. Mathijssen, M. J. Jansen, and H. J. A. M. van Oers. 2018. “Impact of an Outdoor Smoking Ban at Secondary Schools on Cigarettes, E‐Cigarettes and Water Pipe Use Among Adolescents: An 18‐Month Follow‐Up.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 15, no. 2: 205. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph15020205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rychetnik, L., M. Frommer, P. Hawe, and A. Shiell. 2002. “Criteria for Evaluating Evidence on Public Health Interventions.” Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health 56, no. 2: 119–127. https://doi.org/10.1136/jech.56.2.119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Short, M., and A. G. Cole. 2021. “Factors Associated With E‐Cigarette Escalation Among High School Students: A Review of the Literature.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 19: 10067. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph181910067.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simcoe Muskoka District Health Unit. 2023. Not an experiment. https://www.notanexperiment.ca.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, S., S. B. Windle, K. B. Filion, et al. 2020. “E‐Cigarettes and Youth: Patterns of Use, Potential Harms, and Recommendations.” Preventive Medicine 133: 106009. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2020.106009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevens, E. M., E. T. Hébert, B. Keller‐Hamilton, et al. 2021. “Associations Between Exposure to the Real Cost Campaign, Pro‐Tobacco Advertisements, and Tobacco Use Among Youth in the U.S.” American Journal of Preventive Medicine 60, no. 5: 706–710. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2020.11.006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas, R. E., J. McLellan, R. Perera, and R. E. Thomas. 2013. “School‐Based Programmes for Preventing Smoking.” Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 2013, no. 5: CD001293. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD001293.pub3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tricco, A. C., E. Lillie, W. Zarin, et al. 2018. “PRISMA Extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA‐ScR): Checklist and Explanation.” Annals of Internal Medicine 169, no. 7: 467–473. https://doi.org/10.7326/M18‐0850.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tzortzi, A., M. Kapetanstrataki, V. Evangelopoulou, and P. Beghrakis. 2020. “A Systematic Literature Review of E‐Cigarette‐Related Illness and Injury: Not Just for the Respirologist.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 17, no. 7: 2248. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17072248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. 2012. Preventing Tobacco Use Among Youth and Young Adults: a Report of the Surgeon General. Atlanta, GA: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK99242/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villanti, A. C., R. S. Niaura, D. B. Abrams, and R. Mermelstein. 2019. “Preventing Smoking Progression in Young Adults: The Concept of Prevescalation.” Prevention Science 20, no. 3: 377–384. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11121‐018‐0880‐y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker, M. W., M. Navarro, M. Roditis, and A. Dineva (Nasi). 2022. “Adolescent Risk Perceptions of ENDS Use: Room for Change in Tobacco Education.” Preventive Medicine Reports 26: 101719. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.101719.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weser, V. U., L. R. Duncan, T. M. Pendergrass, C.‐S. Fernandes, L. E. Fiellin, and K. D. Hieftje. 2021a. “A Quasi‐Experimental Test of a Virtual Reality Game Prototype for Adolescent E‐Cigarette Prevention.” Addictive Behaviors 112: 106639. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2020.106639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weser, V. U., L. R. Duncan, B. E. Sands, et al. 2021b. “Evaluation of a Virtual Reality E‐Cigarette Prevention Game for Adolescents.” Addictive Behaviors 122: 107027. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2021.107027.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, G. C., A. G. Cole, M. de Groh, Y. Jiang, and S. T. Leatherdale. 2022. “More support needed: Evaluating the impact of school e‐cigarette prevention and cessation programs on e‐cigarette initiation among a sample of Canadian secondary school students.” Preventive Medicine 155: 106924–106924. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2021.106924.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>