<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39442812</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-1208</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>197</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbial pathogenesis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microb Pathog</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A review of the role of graphene-based nanomaterials in tackling challenges posed by the COVID-19 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>107059</StartPage><MedlinePgn>107059</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.107059</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0882-4010(24)00526-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In 2020, the World Health Organization (WHO) declared a pandemic due to the emergence of the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) which had resulted by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). At present, the emergence of many new variants and mutants were found to be more harmful compared to the previous strains. As a result, research scientists around the world had devoted significant efforts to understand the mechanism, causes and transmission due to COVID-19 along with the treatment to cure these diseases. However, despite achieving several findings, much more was unknown and yet to be explored. Hence, along with these developments, it is also extremely essential to design effective systems by incorporating smart materials to battle the COVID-19. Therefore, several approaches have been implemented to combat against COVID-19. Recently, the graphene-based materials have been explored for the current COVID-19 and future pandemics due to its superior physicochemical properties, providing efficient nanoplatforms for optical and electrochemical sensing and diagnostic applications with high sensitivity and selectivity. Moreover, based on the photothermal effects or reactive oxygen species formation, the carbon-based nanomaterials have shown its potentiality for targeted antiviral drug delivery and the inhibitory effects against pathogenic viruses. Therefore, this review article sheds light on the recent progress and the most promising strategies related to graphene and related materials and its applications for detection, decontamination, diagnosis, and protection against COVID-19. In addition, the key challenges and future directives are discussed in detail for fundamental design and development of technologies based on graphene-based materials along with the demand aspects of graphene-based products and lastly, our personal opinions on the appropriate approaches to improve these technologies respectively.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashok Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Sachin Sharma</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Ionics Universiti Malaya, Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Universiti Malaya, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia; School of Engineering, Taylor's University, 1 Jalan Taylor's, 47500, Subang Jaya, Selangor, Malaysia. Electronic address: sachin.sharma@taylors.edu.my.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bashir</LastName><ForeName>Shahid</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Higher Institution Centre of Excellence (HICoE), UM Power Energy Dedicated Advanced Centre (UMPEDAC), Level 4, Wisma R&amp;D, Universiti Malaya, Jalan Pantai Baharu, 59990, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pershaanaa</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Ionics Universiti Malaya, Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Universiti Malaya, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kamarulazam</LastName><ForeName>Fathiah</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Ionics Universiti Malaya, Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Universiti Malaya, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kuppusamy</LastName><ForeName>A V</ForeName><Initials>AV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Engineering and Computing, Manipal International University, Putra Nilai, 71800, Nilai, Negeri Sembilan, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Badawi</LastName><ForeName>Nujud</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Hafr Al-Batin College of Science, Hafer Al-Batin, 39921, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramesh</LastName><ForeName>K</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Ionics Universiti Malaya, Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Universiti Malaya, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia; Department of Physical Sciences, Saveetha School of Engineering, Saveetha University (SIMATS), Chennai, India. Electronic address: rameshkasi@um.edu.my.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramesh</LastName><ForeName>S</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Ionics Universiti Malaya, Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Universiti Malaya, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia; Department of Physical Sciences, Saveetha School of Engineering, Saveetha University (SIMATS), Chennai, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Microb Pathog</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8606191</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0882-4010</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-viral</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Electrochemical biosensors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Face mask</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Graphene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Graphene oxide (GO)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39442812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.107059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0882-4010(24)00526-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>