<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39440166</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessing Vaccine Intentions, Knowledge, Self-Efficacy, and Trust: A Cross-Sectional Study on Perceptions of Monkeypox Vaccination and Public Health Risk Awareness in Makurdi, Benue State, Nigeria.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e72131</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e72131</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e72131</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.72131</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Introduction The global emergence of monkeypox has heightened public health concerns, particularly in regions with limited vaccine uptake. In Nigeria, understanding the factors influencing vaccination intentions is essential for developing effective public health strategies. Despite vaccine availability, hesitancy and varying degrees of acceptance persist, driven by factors such as self-efficacy, vaccine trust, and overall attitudes toward vaccination. Previous research highlights the importance of these factors in shaping health behaviors, particularly in vulnerable populations. In Benue State, where distinct health challenges affect key demographic groups such as people living with human immunodeficiency virus (PLHIV) and men who have sex with men (MSM), addressing vaccination intentions is critical for public health efforts. Objectives The objective was to assess the intention to receive the monkeypox vaccine, self-assessed knowledge levels, self-efficacy, and risk perception among the PLHIV, MSM, and the healthcare population in Benue State, Nigeria. Additionally, the study aimed to evaluate public trust in vaccines and health authorities and to understand how these factors influence attitudes toward vaccination and overall perceptions of monkeypox-related health risks. Methodology A cross-sectional survey was conducted among 377 participants in Makurdi, Benue State, Nigeria, focusing on PLHIV, MSM, and healthcare workers. Participants were recruited using a snowball sampling technique, which leveraged social media platforms (WhatsApp, Facebook, and Telegram) and the Federal Medical Center in Makurdi. Data were collected using a structured questionnaire designed to assess self-efficacy, trust in vaccines, vaccination attitudes, and prior vaccination experiences. Statistical analysis was performed using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, version 25.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY). Descriptive statistics were used to summarize the characteristics of the study population. Bivariate analyses, including chi-square tests and independent t-tests, were employed to explore the relationships between socio-demographic characteristics and vaccination intentions. Statistical significance was set at p &lt; 0.05 for all analyses. Results The study revealed a significant positive relationship between self-efficacy and vaccination intention (p = 0.001). Trust in vaccinations and health authorities was also found to be a significant predictor of vaccination intention (p &lt; 0.05). Furthermore, participants who had previously received the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccine were more likely to express intention to receive the monkeypox vaccine (p = 0.000). However, the perception that the threat of monkeypox was exaggerated did not significantly impact vaccination intention (p = 0.4). Conclusion This study highlights the critical role of self-efficacy, trust in vaccines, and prior vaccination experiences in shaping the intention to receive the monkeypox vaccine in Benue State, Nigeria. The findings suggest that public health policies should prioritize enhancing trust in vaccines and health authorities, as well as boosting self-efficacy, to improve vaccination uptake. Addressing these factors may lead to more effective public health interventions against monkeypox and other infectious diseases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Lawrence et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lawrence</LastName><ForeName>Adewale</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmaceutical Medicine, Bioluminux Clinical Research, Naperville, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">benue state</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19 vaccination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">monkeypox</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nigeria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">self-efficacy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">trust in vaccines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination intention</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Health Research Ethics Committee issued approval FMH/FMC/HREC/108/VOL.I. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.72131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The re-emergence of mpox: old illness, modern challenges. Zinnah MA, Uddin MB, Hasan T, et al. Biomedicines. 2024;12:1457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11274818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39062032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monkeypox (mpox) virus: classification, origin, transmission, genome organization, antiviral drugs, and molecular diagnosis. Karagoz A, Tombuloglu H, Alsaeed M, et al. J Infect Public Health. 2023;16:531–541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9908738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36801633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology, host range, and associated risk factors of monkeypox: an emerging global public health threat. Ullah M, Li Y, Munib K, Zhang Z. Front Microbiol. 2023;14:1160984.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10196482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37213509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health inequalities in infectious diseases: a systematic overview of reviews. Ayorinde A, Ghosh I, Ali I, et al. BMJ Open. 2023;13:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10083762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37015800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpox in Nigeria: perceptions and knowledge of the disease among critical stakeholders-global public health consequences. Awoyomi OJ, Njoga EO, Jaja IF, et al. PLoS One. 2023;18:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10062623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36996122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public understanding and awareness of and response to monkeypox virus outbreak: a cross-sectional survey of the most affected communities in the United Kingdom during the 2022 public health emergency. Paparini S, Whitacre R, Smuk M, et al.  https://doi.org/ HIV Med. 2023;24:544–557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36385726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 in LMICs: the need to place stigma front and centre to its response. Roelen K, Ackley C, Boyce P, Farina N, Ripoll S. Eur J Dev Res. 2020;32:1592–1612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7575856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33100598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disinformation and epidemics: anticipating the next phase of biowarfare. Bernard R, Bowsher G, Sullivan R, Gibson-Fall F. Health Secur. 2021;19:3–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9195489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33090030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Review of epidemic, containment strategies, clinical management, and economic evaluation of COVID-19 pandemic. Chen CL, Lai CC, Luh DL, et al. J Formos Med Assoc. 2021;120 Suppl 1:0–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8156902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34116896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical and epidemiological features of mpox in a Brazilian reference center for HIV and sexually transmitted infections: a cross-sectional study. Costa AF, Rocha SQ, Fonsi M, et al. IJID Reg. 2024;10:114–122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10805638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38269305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpox: an overview of pathogenesis, diagnosis, and public health implications. Branda F, Romano C, Ciccozzi M, Giovanetti M, Scarpa F, Ciccozzi A, Maruotti A. J Clin Med. 2024;13:2234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11050819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38673507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Information needs of health care workers in developing countries: a literature review with a focus on Africa. Pakenham-Walsh N, Bukachi F. Hum Resour Health. 2009;7:30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2680393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19356239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engagement of gay men and other men who have sex with men (MSM) in the response to HIV: a critical step in achieving an AIDS-free generation. Stahlman S, Beyrer C, Sullivan PS, Mayer KH, Baral SD. AIDS Behav. 2016;20:330–340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27048235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Addressing disease-related stigma during infectious disease outbreaks. Fischer LS, Mansergh G, Lynch J, Santibanez S. Disaster Med Public Health Prep. 2019;13:989–994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6889068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31156079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The strategies to support the COVID-19 vaccination with evidence-based communication and tackling misinformation. Rzymski P, Borkowski L, Drąg M, et al. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9:109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7912910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33535716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpox: epidemiology, clinical manifestations and recent developments in treatment and prevention. Selvaraj N, Shyam S, Dhurairaj P, Thiruselvan K, Thiruselvan A, Kancherla Y, Kandamaran P. Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther. 2023;21:641–653.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37101419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Risk factors for rectal gonococcal infection amidst resurgence in HIV transmission. Kim AA, Kent CK, Klausner JD. Sex Transm Dis. 2003;30:813–817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14603087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attitudes towards Monkeypox vaccination and predictors of vaccination intentions among the US general public. Winters M, Malik AA, Omer SB. PLoS One. 2022;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9714903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36454991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors associated with uptake of vaccination against pandemic influenza: a systematic review. Bish A, Yardley L, Nicoll A, Michie S. Vaccine. 2011;29:6472–6484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21756960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors that are associated with parental acceptance of human papillomavirus vaccines: a randomized intervention study of written information about HPV. Dempsey AF, Zimet GD, Davis RL, Koutsky L. Pediatrics. 2006;117:1486–1493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16651301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The use of the health belief model to assess predictors of intent to receive the COVID-19 vaccine and willingness to pay. Wong LP, Alias H, Wong PF, Lee HY, AbuBakar S. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2020;16:2204–2214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32730103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Measuring trust in vaccination: a systematic review. Larson HJ, Clarke RM, Jarrett C, Eckersberger E, Levine Z, Schulz WS, Paterson P. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2018;14:1599–1609.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6067893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29617183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attitudes toward a potential SARS-CoV-2 vaccine: a survey of US adults. Fisher KA, Bloomstone SJ, Walder J, Crawford S, Fouayzi H, Mazor KM. Ann Intern Med. 2020;173:964–973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7505019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32886525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Measuring vaccine hesitancy, confidence, trust and flu vaccine uptake: results of a national survey of White and African American adults. Quinn SC, Jamison AM, An J, Hancock GR, Freimuth VS. https://doi.org/ Vaccine. 2019;37:1168–1173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30709722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccine hesitancy: definition, scope and determinants. MacDonald NE. Vaccine. 2015;33:4161–4164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25896383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Detrimental effects of introducing partial compulsory vaccination: experimental evidence. Betsch C, Böhm R. Eur J Public Health. 2016;26:378–381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26297722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attitudes to vaccination: a critical review. Yaqub O, Castle-Clarke S, Sevdalis N, Chataway J. Soc Sci Med. 2014;112:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24788111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Predictors of COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy: socio-demographics, co-morbidity, and past experience of racial discrimination. Savoia E, Piltch-Loeb R, Goldberg B, et al. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9:767.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8310049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34358184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>