<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">39441860</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Factors influencing physical activity and sedentary behaviour in contact centres during the COVID-19 pandemic and their relevance for the future of hybrid working.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0312473</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0312473</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0312473</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0312473</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic changed the way many industries work, including contact centres, with some employees working from home and new on-site restrictions/measures in place representing even greater challenges for employers around staff engagement and wellbeing. This study aimed to understand the interplay of individual, social, environmental and organisational factors influencing physical activity and sedentary behaviour in UK contact centre employees, how the pandemic impacted these factors, and their relevance for the future of hybrid working.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Individual interviews (n = 33) were conducted with participants (staff working full and part time, on site and from home) from four UK contact centres. A topic guide based on the ecological model was developed to understand current barriers and facilitators to physical activity and (reducing) sedentary behaviour during and outside of working hours. Thematic analysis was carried out using a codebook and a deductive coding approach to identify themes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Three key insights are provided. First, participants felt they were generally sitting more and moving less since the first UK-wide lockdown. Second, factors which negatively impacted on these behaviours were evident across all levels of the ecological model. These included individual and social barriers (e.g., lack of motivation and preferable physical activity options) as well as environmental and organisational barriers (e.g., poor home office setup, back-to-back virtual meetings). There were a mix of new and existing barriers (exacerbated by the pandemic) and several of these were linked to homeworking. Third, organisational support requirements (e.g., homeworking ergonomic support) and existing facilitators (such as the provision of informational support and flexible working arrangements) were identified.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Solutions to reduce sedentary behaviours and increase physical activity in contact centres need to address barriers from the individual to the organisational level. Whilst the study was undertaken in the UK, the results are like to be applicable globally.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="TRIAL REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Clinical trial registration: The trial for the wider project has been registered on the ISRCTN database: http://www.isrctn.com/ISRCTN11580369.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Manner et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manner</LastName><ForeName>Jillian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4411-5056</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Scottish Collaboration for Public Health Research and Policy, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sivaramakrishnan</LastName><ForeName>Divya</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Scottish Collaboration for Public Health Research and Policy, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baker</LastName><ForeName>Graham</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physical Activity for Health Research Centre, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lloyd</LastName><ForeName>Scott</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9617-4838</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health South Tees, Middlesbrough Council and Redcar &amp; Cleveland Borough Council, Middlesbrough, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fuse-UKCRC Centre for Translational Research in Public Health, Population Health Sciences Institute, William Leech Building, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Teesside University, Middlesbrough, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jepson</LastName><ForeName>Ruth</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Scottish Collaboration for Public Health Research and Policy, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016448">Multicenter Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016449">Randomized Controlled Trial</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015444" MajorTopicYN="Y">Exercise</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="Y">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057185" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sedentary Behavior</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006113" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United Kingdom</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017132" MajorTopicYN="N">Workplace</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39441860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11498657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0312473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-23-35700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tremblay MS, Aubert S, Barnes JD, Saunders TJ, Carson V, Latimer-Cheung AE, et al.. Sedentary Behavior Research Network (SBRN)–Terminology Consensus Project process and outcome. International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity. 2017;14(1):75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5466781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28599680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chau JY, Grunseit AC, Chey T, Stamatakis E, Brown WJ, Matthews CE, et al.. Daily Sitting Time and All-Cause Mortality: A Meta-Analysis. PLOS ONE. 2013;8(11):e80000. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0080000</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0080000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3827429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24236168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proper KI, Singh AS, van Mechelen W, Chinapaw MJM. Sedentary Behaviors and Health Outcomes Among Adults: A Systematic Review of Prospective Studies. American Journal of Preventive Medicine. 2011;40(2):174–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21238866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorp AA, Owen N, Neuhaus M, Dunstan DW. Sedentary Behaviors and Subsequent Health Outcomes in Adults: A Systematic Review of Longitudinal Studies, 1996–2011. American Journal of Preventive Medicine. 2011;41(2):207–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21767729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Rezende LFM, Rodrigues Lopes M, Rey-López JP, Matsudo VKR, Luiz OdC. Sedentary behavior and health outcomes: an overview of systematic reviews. PloS one. 2014;9(8):e105620-e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4140795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25144686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai L, Zhang Y, Zhang D. Sedentary behaviour and the risk of depression: a meta-analysis. British Journal of Sports Medicine. 2015;49(11):705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25183627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marconcin P, Zymbal V, Gouveia É, Jones B, Marques A. Sedentary Behaviour: Definition, Determinants, Impacts on Health, and Current Recommendations. Sedentary Behaviour—A Contemporary View: IntechOpen; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekelund U, Brown WJ, Steene-Johannessen J, Fagerland MW, Owen N, Powell KE, et al.. Do the associations of sedentary behaviour with cardiovascular disease mortality and cancer mortality differ by physical activity level? A systematic review and harmonised meta-analysis of data from 850 060 participants. 2019;53(14):886–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29991570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekelund U, Steene-Johannessen J, Brown WJ, Fagerland MW, Owen N, Powell KE, et al.. Does physical activity attenuate, or even eliminate, the detrimental association of sitting time with mortality? A harmonised meta-analysis of data from more than 1 million men and women. The Lancet. 2016;388(10051):1302–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27475271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stamatakis E, Gale J, Bauman A, Ekelund U, Hamer M, Ding D. Sitting Time, Physical Activity, and Risk of Mortality in Adults. Journal of the American College of Cardiology. 2019;73(16):2062–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31023430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. WHO guidelines on physical activity and sedentary behaviour. 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33369898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner B, Smith L, Lorencatto F, Hamer M, Biddle SJH. How to reduce sitting time? A review of behaviour change strategies used in sedentary behaviour reduction interventions among adults. Health Psychology Review. 2016;10(1):89–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4743603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26315814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fellowes. Brits sedentary for up to nine hours a day in the workplace alone, study finds. 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazi A, Duncan M, Clemes S, Haslam C. A survey of sitting time among UK employees. Occupational Medicine. 2014;64(7):497–502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25135938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borodulin K, Laatikainen T, Juolevi A, Jousilahti P. Thirty-year trends of physical activity in relation to age, calendar time and birth cohort in Finnish adults. European Journal of Public Health. 2007;18(3):339–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17875578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brownson RC, Boehmer TK, Luke DA. Declining rates of physical activity in the United States: What Are the Contributors? Annual Review of Public Health. 2005;26(1):421–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15760296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng SW, Popkin BM. Time use and physical activity: a shift away from movement across the globe. Obesity Reviews. 2012;13(8):659–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3401184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22694051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sallis JF, Owen N, Fisher E. Ecological models of health behavior. Health behavior: Theory, research, and practice. 2015;5(43–64).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Cocker K, Duncan MJ, Short C, van Uffelen JGZ, Vandelanotte C. Understanding occupational sitting: Prevalence, correlates and moderating effects in Australian employees. Preventive Medicine. 2014;67:288–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25117522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadgraft NT, Winkler EAH, Healy GN, Lynch BM, Neuhaus M, Eakin EG, et al.. Intervening to reduce workplace sitting: mediating role of social-cognitive constructs during a cluster randomised controlled trial. International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity. 2017;14(1):27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5340005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28264684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu AHY, Ng SHX, Tan CS, Win AM, Koh D, Müller-Riemenschneider F. A systematic review and meta-analysis of workplace intervention strategies to reduce sedentary time in white-collar workers. Obesity Reviews. 2016;17(5):467–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26990220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorp AA, Healy GN, Winkler E, Clark BK, Gardiner PA, Owen N, et al.. Prolonged sedentary time and physical activity in workplace and non-work contexts: a cross-sectional study of office, customer service and call centre employees. International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity. 2012;9(1):128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3546308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23101767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris A, Murphy R, Shepherd S, Graves L. Multi-Stakeholder Perspectives of Factors That Influence Contact Centre Call Agents’ Workplace Physical Activity and Sedentary Behaviour. International journal of environmental research and public health. 2018;15(7):1484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6069165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30011821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toomingas A, Forsman M, Mathiassen SE, Heiden M, Nilsson T. Variation between seated and standing/walking postures among male and female call centre operators. BMC Public Health. 2012;12(1):154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3348085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22385536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sprigg CA, Smith PR, Jackson PR. Psychological risk factors in call centres: An evaluation of work design and well-being.:
University of Sheffield, Health and Safety Laboratory and UMIST for the Health and Safety Executive 2003; 2003. 
https://www.hse.gov.uk/research/rrpdf/rr169.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centres for Disease Control and Prevention. The Social-Ecological Model: A Framework for Prevention
2020. 
https://www.cdc.gov/violenceprevention/publichealthissue/social-ecologicalmodel.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oakman J, Kinsman N, Stuckey R, Graham M, Weale V. A rapid review of mental and physical health effects of working at home: how do we optimise health? BMC Public Health. 2020;20(1).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7703513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33256652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nijp HH, Beckers DGJ, Van De Voorde K, Geurts SAE, Kompier MAJ. Effects of new ways of working on work hours and work location, health and job-related outcomes. Chronobiology International. 2016;33(6):604–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27223247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giorgi G, Lecca LI, Alessio F, Finstad GL, Bondanini G, Lulli LG, et al.. COVID-19-Related Mental Health Effects in the Workplace: A Narrative Review. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. 2020;17(21):7857.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7663773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33120930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilms P, Schroeder J, Reer R, Scheit L. The impact of “Home Office” work on physical activity and sedentary behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. 2022;19(19):12344. doi: 0.3390/ijerph191912344</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9566552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36231651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morton S, Fitzsimons C, Sivaramakrishnan D, Jepson R, Niven A. “Are we working (too) comfortably?”: a focus group study to understand sedentary behaviour when working at home and identify intervention strategies. BMC Public Health. 2024;24(1):1516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11155077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38844904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falk GE, Mailey EL, Okut H, Rosenkranz SK, Rosenkranz RR, Montney JL, et al.. Effects of sedentary behavior interventions on mental well-being and work performance while working from home during the COVID-19 pandemic: A pilot randomized controlled trial. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. 2022;19(11):6401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9180109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35681986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Thematic analysis: a practical guide / Virginia Braun and Victoria Clarke. Los Angeles: SAGE; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith B, Mcgannon KR. Developing rigor in qualitative research: problems and opportunities within sport and exercise psychology. International Review of Sport and Exercise Psychology. 2018;11(1):101–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A, Sainsbury P, Craig J. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): a 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. International Journal for Quality in Health Care. 2007;19(6):349–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tirman L, Biggs H, Morrison K, Manner J, Sivaramakrishnan D, Baker G, et al.. Stand Up for Health: Programme theory for an intervention to reduce sedentary behaviour in contact centres. Evaluation and Program Planning. 2021;89:102002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34634757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jepson R, Williams AJ, Doi L, Buelo A. Developing Public Health Interventions: A Step-by-Step Guide: SAGE; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker RA, Manner J, Sivaramakrishnan D, Baker G, Stoddart A, Lloyd S, et al.. Design, rationale and analysis plan for the Stand Up for Health trial in contact centres: a stepped wedge feasibility study. Pilot and Feasibility Studies. 2020;6(1):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7513324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32983556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jepson R, Baker G, Sivaramakrishnan D, Manner J, Parker R, Lloyd S, et al.. Feasibility of a theory-based intervention to reduce sedentary behaviour among contact centre staff: the SUH stepped-wedge cluster RCT. Public Health Research. 2022;10(13):1–120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36538605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Can I use TA? Should I use TA? Should I not use TA? Comparing reflexive thematic analysis and other pattern‐based qualitative analytic approaches. Counselling and Psychotherapy Research. 2021;21(1):37–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qualtrics. Qualtrics. Provo, Utah, USA. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beasley D.
Google Gives Employees $1,000 Work-From-Home Allowance
2020. 
https://www.forbes.com/sites/beasleydavid/2020/05/27/google-gives-employees-1000-work-from-home-allowance/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor P. ‘The petri dish and Russian roulette’: working in UK contact centres during the COVID-19 pandemic. Work in the Global Economy. 2021;1(1–2):185–208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor P. Covid-19: Contact/Call Centre Workers in Scotland: GIRUY Press; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edmunds S, Hurst L, Harvey K. Physical activity barriers in the workplace. International Journal of Workplace Health Management. 2013;6(3):227–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allender S, Cowburn G, Foster C. Understanding participation in sport and physical activity among children and adults: a review of qualitative studies. Health Education Research. 2006;21(6):826–35. doi: 10.1093/her/cyl063</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/her/cyl063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16857780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farah BQ, Do Prado WL, Malik N, Lofrano-Prado MC, De Melo PH, Botero JP, et al.. Barriers to physical activity during the COVID-19 pandemic in adults: a cross-sectional study. Sport Sciences for Health. 2021;17(2):441–7. doi: 10.1007/s11332-020-00724-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11332-020-00724-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7998080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33815618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roche C, Fisher A, Fancourt D, Burton A. Exploring barriers and facilitators to physical activity during the COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative study. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. 2022;19(15):9169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9367830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35954538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koh YS, Asharani PV, Devi F, Roystonn K, Wang P, Vaingankar JA, et al.. A cross-sectional study on the perceived barriers to physical activity and their associations with domain-specific physical activity and sedentary behaviour. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9132675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35614402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kass L, Desai T, Sullivan K, Muniz D, Wells A. Changes to Physical Activity, Sitting Time, Eating Behaviours and Barriers to Exercise during the First COVID-19 ‘Lockdown’ in an English Cohort. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. 2021;18(19):10025. doi: 10.3390/ijerph181910025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph181910025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8508153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34639327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smite D, Moe NB, Hildrum J, Huerta JG, Mendez D. Work-from-home is here to stay: Call for flexibility in post-pandemic work policies. Journal of Systems and Software. 2023;195:111552. doi: 10.1016/j.jss.2022.111552</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2022.111552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9613780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36320721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>