<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39440160</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effectiveness of Telemedicine in Managing Health-Related Issues in the Pediatric Population: A Systematic Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e72144</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e72144</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e72144</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.72144</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Healthcare delivery is made more convenient and effective via telemedicine, which enables physicians to conduct virtual consultations and evaluations with pediatric patients. The purpose of this systematic review was to evaluate the efficacy of telemedicine as compared to physical appointments in the pediatric population. We used Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines to search for the available literature using pre-specified inclusion and exclusion criteria. These databases provided 968 relevant research articles, which Endnote software screened for duplicates. Fourteen studies were considered relevant for full-text evaluation. After complete text evaluation, only 11 of these articles were found to be relevant. The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) was used for the risk of bias assessment of all included studies. Eleven articles in all satisfied the requirements for inclusion and were added to the review. Every study was classified as either a cluster randomized trial (27%) or a randomized controlled trial (RCT) (73%). There were between 22 and 400 participants in each trial. Medical conditions evaluated included obesity (27%), mental health disorders (9%), asthma (18%), otitis media (9%), skin disorders (9%), type 1 diabetes (9%), attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) (9%), and pancreatic insufficiency associated with cystic fibrosis (1/11). Telemedicine strategies employed included telemedicine-based screening visits (9%), smartphone-based therapies (27%), phone counseling (18%), and videoconferencing visits between patients and doctors (45%). The outcomes of the telemedicine procedures in every included study were on par with or superior to those of the control groups. Medication adherence, appointment completion rates, life satisfaction, symptom management, and disease progression were all outcomes associated with these findings. Although more research is needed, the evidence from this review suggests that telemedicine services for the general public and pediatric care are comparable to or better than in-person services. Patients, healthcare professionals, and caregivers may benefit from using both telemedicine services and traditional in-person healthcare services. To maximize the potential of telemedicine, future research should focus on improving patients' access to care, increasing the cost-effectiveness of telemedicine services, and eliminating barriers to telemedicine use.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Taher Do Alfuqhar et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taher Do Alfuqhar</LastName><ForeName>Iman Mohammed</ForeName><Initials>IM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>General Practice, Primary Health Care Center, Emirates Health Services (EHS), Dubai, ARE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali Khalafalla</LastName><ForeName>Alaa Eldirdiri</ForeName><Initials>AE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatrics, Hull University Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust, Hull Royal Infirmary, Hull, GBR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahmoud Ali</LastName><ForeName>Salma Hassan</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Najran Armed Forces Hospital, Najran, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aydaross Adam</LastName><ForeName>Elwaleed Idrees</ForeName><Initials>EI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatrics, Ibri Regional Hospital, Oman, OMN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Osman</LastName><ForeName>Hanady M</ForeName><Initials>HM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Family Medicine, Najran Armed Forces Hospital, Najran, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Safar Alrabie</LastName><ForeName>Rwabi</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Najran Armed Forces Hospital, Najran, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mobile health technology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pediatrics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sars-cov-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tele-health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telemedicine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.72144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Pediatric telehealth: opportunities and challenges. Utidjian L, Abramson E. Pediatr Clin North Am. 2016;63:367–378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27017042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Addressing the COVID-19 burden on medical education and training: the role of telemedicine and tele-education during and beyond the pandemic. Sharma D, Bhaskar S. Front Public Health. 2020;8:589669.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7728659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33330333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine: a cornerstone of healthcare assistance during the SARS-Cov2 pandemic outbreak but also a great opportunity for the near future. Tartaglia E, Vozzella EA, Iervolino A, et al. Smart Health (Amst) 2022;26:100324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9485424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36159079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The development of telemedicine and eHealth in surgery during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. Taha A, Saad B, Enodien B, Bachmann M, Frey DM, Taha-Mehlitz S. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:11969.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8619571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34831725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine: pediatric applications. Burke BL Jr, Hall RW. Pediatrics. 2015;136:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5754191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26122813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in pediatrics: systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Shah AC, Badawy SM. JMIR Pediatr Parent. 2021;4:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8078694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33556030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Use of telemedicine to provide pediatric critical care inpatient consultations to underserved rural Northern California. Marcin JP, Nesbitt TS, Kallas HJ, Struve SN, Traugott CA, Dimand RJ. J Pediatr. 2004;144:375–380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15001947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in pediatrics: possibilities and pitfalls. Chandler AL, Beavers JC, Hall RW. Pediatr Rev. 2020;41:376–378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32611805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in malignant and nonmalignant hematology: systematic review of pediatric and adult studies. Shah AC, O'Dwyer LC, Badawy SM. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2021;9:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8299344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34255706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine acceptance among older adult patients with cancer: scoping review. Pang NQ, Lau J, Fong SY, Wong CY, Tan KK. J Med Internet Res. 2022;24:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9006130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35348462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Older adults' satisfaction with telemedicine during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review. Alsabeeha NH, Atieh MA, Balakrishnan MS. Telemed J E Health. 2023;29:38–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35613380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effectiveness of ambulatory telemedicine care in older adults: a systematic review. Batsis JA, DiMilia PR, Seo LM, et al. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2019;67:1737–1749.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6684409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31066916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in paediatric emergency care: a systematic review. Mitra A, Veerakone R, Li K, Nix T, Hashikawa A, Mahajan P. J Telemed Telecare. 2023;29:579–590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34590883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The effectiveness of telemedicine consultation in improving outcomes of asthma in the paediatric population: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Ong LT, Loh AC, Chee NZ. Pediatr Respirol Crit Care Med. 2024;8:33–42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. Moher D, Liberati A, Tetzlaff J, Altman DG. Int J Surg. 2010;8:336–341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3090117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21603045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behavioral and nutritional treatment for preschool-aged children with cystic fibrosis: a randomized clinical trial. Powers SW, Stark LJ, Chamberlin LA, et al. JAMA Pediatr. 2015;169:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25938655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Treating rural paediatric obesity through telemedicine vs. telephone: outcomes from a cluster randomized controlled trial. Davis AM, Sampilo M, Gallagher KS, et al. J Tel Telecare. 2016;22:86–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4830380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26026186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The children’s attention- deficit hyperactivity disorder telemental health treatment study: caregiver outcomes. Vander Stoep A, McCarty CA, Zhou C, Rockhill CM, Schoenfelder EN, Myers K. J Abnorm Child Psychol. 2017;45:27–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5083233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27117555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A telephone intervention to achieve differentiation in dietary intake: a randomized trial in paediatric primary care. Rhodes ET, Vernacchio L, Mitchell AA, Fischer C, Giacalone P, Ludwig DS, Ebbeling CB. Pediatr Obes. 2017;12:494–501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5529253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27492865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creating an integrated care model for childhood obesity: a randomized pilot study utilizing telehealth in a community primary care setting. Fleischman A, Hourigan SE, Lyon HN, et al. Clin Obes. 2016;6:380–388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5523655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27863024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young patients with type 1 diabetes poorly controlled and poorly compliant with self-monitoring of blood glucose: can technology help? Results of the i-NewTrend randomized clinical trial. Di Bartolo P, Nicolucci A, Cherubini V, Iafusco D, Scardapane M, Rossi MC. Acta Diabetol. 2017;54:393–402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28138788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnostic accuracy of pediatric teledermatology using parent-submitted photographs: a randomized clinical trial. O'Connor DM, Jew OS, Perman MJ, Castelo-Soccio LA, Winston FK, McMahon PJ. JAMA Dermatol. 2017;153:1243–1248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5817452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29141082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effect of the school-based telemedicine enhanced asthma management (SB-TEAM) program on asthma morbidity: a randomized clinical trial. Halterman JS, Fagnano M, Tajon RS, et al. JAMA Pediatr. 2018;172:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5885835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29309483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Results of an asthma education program delivered via telemedicine in rural schools. Perry TT, Halterman JS, Brown RH, Luo C, Randle SM, Hunter CR, Rettiganti M. Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol. 2018;120:401–408.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5889729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smartphone otoscopy performed by parents. Erkkola-Anttinen N, Irjala H, Laine MK, Tähtinen PA, Löyttyniemi E, Ruohola A. Telemed J E Health. 2019;25:477–484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30040525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A telehealth-enhanced referral process in pediatric primary care: a cluster randomized trial. Coker TR, Porras-Javier L, Zhang L, et al. Pediatrics. 2019;143</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30770523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The use of telemedicine to address access and physician workforce shortages. Marcin JP, Rimsza ME, Moskowitz WB. Pediatrics. 2015;136:202–209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26122802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The medical virtualist: is pediatric patient care using telemedicine, a new specialty? Waller M, Taylor L, Portnoy J. Pediatr Ann. 2019;48:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31185116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>What drives attitude towards telemedicine among families of pediatric patients? A survey. Russo L, Campagna I, Ferretti B, et al. BMC Pediatr. 2017;17:21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5240275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28095894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Text messaging and mobile phone apps as interventions to improve adherence in adolescents with chronic health conditions: a systematic review. Badawy SM, Barrera L, Sinno MG, Kaviany S, O'Dwyer LC, Kuhns LM. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2017;5:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5447825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28506955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overview on the challenges and benefits of using telehealth tools in a pediatric population. Brophy PD. Adv Chronic Kidney Dis. 2017;24:17–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28224938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antibiotic prescribing during pediatric direct-to-consumer telemedicine visits. Ray KN, Shi Z, Gidengil CA, Poon SJ, Uscher-Pines L, Mehrotra A. Pediatrics. 2019;143:143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6565339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30962253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparative analysis of a private telehealth clinic and country-wide COVID-19 patient management results. Chakhunashvili K, Chakhunashvili DG, Kvirkvelia E, Kiknadze N. Discover Health Systems. 2023;8:22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 transforms health care through telemedicine: evidence from the field. Mann DM, Chen J, Chunara R, Testa PA, Nov O. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2020;27:1132–1135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7188161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32324855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapid development of telehealth capabilities within pediatric patient portal infrastructure for COVID-19 care: barriers, solutions, results. Patel PD, Cobb J, Wright D, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2020;27:1116–1120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7188108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assessment of acute kidney injury in critically ill SARS-Cov-2 patients: a narrative review. Ullah W, Bano S, Talal H, Ahmed K, Arshad T, Khan S, Ajmal A. J Health Rehab Res. 2024;4:1616–1624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strategies for evaluating telehealth. Chuo J, Macy ML, Lorch SA. Pediatrics. 2020;146</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7887706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32817398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Managing childhood allergies and immunodeficiencies during respiratory virus epidemics - The 2020 COVID-19 pandemic: a statement from the EAACI-section on pediatrics. Brough HA, Kalayci O, Sediva A, et al. Pediatr Allergy Immunol. 2020;31:442–448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32319129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assessment of serum urea and creatinine levels in diabetic patients. Ullah W, Nazir A, Israr H, Hussain S, Farooq M. BioScientific Review. 2023;5:26–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Migraine care in the era of COVID-19: clinical pearls and plea to insurers. Szperka CL, Ailani J, Barmherzig R, Klein BC, Minen MT, Halker Singh RB, Shapiro RE. Headache. 2020;60:833–842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7228371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32227596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in pediatric surgery. Harting MT, Wheeler A, Ponsky T, et al. J Pediatr Surg. 2019;54:587–594.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29801660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in pediatric gastroenterology: an overview of utility. Stone JM, Gibbons TE. Telemed J E Health. 2018;24:577–581.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29271722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in a pediatric headache clinic: a prospective survey. Qubty W, Patniyot I, Gelfand A. Neurology. 2018;90:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29626180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potential solutions for pediatric weight loss programs in the treatment of obesity in rural communities. Novick MB, Wilson CT, Walker-Harding LR. Transl Behav Med. 2019;9:460–467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31094444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Using telehealth to address pediatric obesity in rural Pennsylvania. Hosseini H, Yilmaz A. Hosp Top. 2019;97:107–118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31244391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>When will telemedicine appear in the ICU? . Avdalovic MV, Marcin JP. J Intensive Care Med. 2019;34:271–276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29756527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transforming gastroenterology care with telemedicine. Siegel CA. Gastroenterology. 2017;152:958–963.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28192101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>