<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39449269</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-1446</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Public health nursing (Boston, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Public Health Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Research Trends and Hot Topics of Nursing Studies on Hypertension: A Retrospective Bibliometric Analysis From 1979 to 2024.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/phn.13472</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study aimed to evaluate research trends and hot topics in the 45-year history of nursing studies on hypertension (1979-2024).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This retrospective bibliometric analysis study was conducted with 2678 data obtained from the WoSCC database on April 1, 2024. Data analysis and graphical presentation were presented using the Bibliometrix Package in R software, VOSviewer, and WoSCC.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study revealed that nursing studies on hypertension were growing rapidly in the scientific world. The most productive journal in the field was the Journal of Clinical Nursing, while the most productive and collaborative country was the United States. "Frailty," "COVID-19," "complications," "Meta-analysis," "vital signs," "systematic review", "self-care," and "chronic disease" were determined as hot topics. "COVID-19" and "mhealth" were global trends. Additionally, the issues of "anxiety, pair, vital signs" and "elderly, nursing home, mortality" needed to be addressed more by nurses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Nursing studies on hypertension have increased to date. This area is likely to continue to be an active area of study for nursing researchers in the coming years. Focusing on the topics "anxiety, pair, vital signs" and "elderly, nursing home, mortality" will contribute to filling the gap in the field.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dağistan Akgöz</LastName><ForeName>Ayşe</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2933-3402</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Nursing, Faculty of Nursing, Akdeniz University, Antalya, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaya</LastName><ForeName>Ayla</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0281-0299</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatric Nursing, Faculty of Nursing, Akdeniz University, Antalya, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Public Health Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8501498</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0737-1209</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bibliometrics analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood pressure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">high blood pressure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hypertension</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nursing</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/phn.13472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Agrawal, A., and N. K. Wenger. 2020. “Hypertension During Pregnancy.” Current Hypertension Reports 22, no. 9: 64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ancoli‐Israel, S., R. Cole, C. Alessi, M. Chambers, W. Moorcroft, and C. P. Pollak. 2003. “The Role of Actigraphy in the Study of Sleep and Circadian Rhythms.” Sleep 26, no. 3: 342–392. https://doi.org/10.1093/sleep/26.3.342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bae, S., S. R. Kim, M. N. Kim, W. J. Shim, and S. M. Park. 2021. “Impact of Cardiovascular Disease and Risk Factors on Fatal Outcomes in Patients With COVID‐19 According to Age: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Heart 107, no. 5: 373. https://doi.org/10.1136/heartjnl‐2020‐317901.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bulto, L. N., J. Roseleur, S. Noonan, M. A. P. de Plaza, S. Champion, and H. A. Dafny. 2024. “Effectiveness of Nurse‐Led Interventions Versus Usual Care to Manage Hypertension and Lifestyle Behaviour: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 23, no. 1: 21–32. https://doi.org/10.1093/eurjcn/zvad040.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). 2022. Million Hearts. Estimated Hypertension Prevalence, Treatment, and Control Among U.S. Adults. Retrieved April 5 from https://millionhearts.hhs.gov/data‐reports/hypertension‐prevalence.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). 2023. Facts About Hypertension in the United States. Retrieved April 8 from https://www.cdc.gov/bloodpressure/facts.htm.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuspidi, C., M. Tadic, G. Grassi, and G. Mancia. 2018. “Treatment of Hypertension: The ESH/ESC Guidelines Recommendations.” Pharmacological Research 128: 315–321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dirik, D., I. Eryilmaz, and T. Erhan. 2023. “Post‐Truth Kavramı Üzerine Yapılan Çalışmaların VOSviewer ile Bibliyometrik Analizi.” Sosyal Mucit Academic Review 4, no. 2: 164–188. https://doi.org/10.54733/smar.1271369 (Turkish).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donthu, N., S. Kumar, N. Pandey, and W. M. Lim. 2021. “Research Constituents, Intellectual Structure, and Collaboration Patterns in Journal of International Marketing: An Analytical Retrospective.” Journal of International Marketing 29, no. 2: 1–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falcao, L. M., M. V. C. Guedes, J. W. P. Borges, and G. R. F. da Silva. 2023. “Educational Intervention Performed by Nurses for Blood Pressure Control: A Systematic Review With Meta‐Analysis.” Revista Latino‐Americana De Enfermagem 31: e3930. https://doi.org/10.1590/1518‐8345.6648.3930.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flack, J. M., M. G. Buhnerkempe, and K. T. Moore. 2024. “Resistant Hypertension: Disease Burden and Emerging Treatment Options.” Current Hypertension Reports 26, no. 5: 183–199. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11906‐023‐01282‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuchs, F. D., and P. K. Whelton. 2020. “High Blood Pressure and Cardiovascular Disease.” Hypertension 75, no. 2: 285–292. https://doi.org/10.1161/hypertensionaha.119.14240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He, Z., L. Dai, Y. Y. Zuo, Y. Chen, H. J. Wang, and H. S. Zeng. 2022. “Hotspots and Frontiers in Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension Research: A Bibliometric and Visualization Analysis From 2011 to 2020.” Bioengineered 13, no. 6: 14667–14680. https://doi.org/10.1080/21655979.2022.2100064.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández‐Galdamez, D., K. Mansilla, A. L. Peralta, et al. 2021. “Monitoring Study Participants and Implementation With Phone Calls to Support Hypertension Control During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: The Case of a Multicomponent Intervention Trial in Guatemala.” Global Heart 16, no. 1: 77. https://doi.org/10.5334/gh.954.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Himmelfarb, C. R., Y. Commodore‐Mensah, and M. N. Hill. 2016. “Expanding the Role of Nurses to Improve Hypertension Care and Control Globally.” Annual Global Health 82, no. 2: 243–253. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aogh.2016.02.003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horta, B. L., C. Loret de Mola, and C. G. Victora. 2015. “Long‐Term Consequences of Breastfeeding on Cholesterol, Obesity, Systolic Blood Pressure and Type 2 Diabetes: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Acta Paediatrica 104: 30–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang, M., and A. K. Chang. 2023. “The Effect of Nurse‐Led Digital Health Interventions on Blood Pressure Control for People With Hypertension: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Journal of Nursing Scholarship 55, no. 5: 1020–1035. https://doi.org/10.1111/jnu.12882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kappes, M., P. Espinoza, V. Jara, and A. Hall. 2023. “Nurse‐Led Telehealth Intervention Effectiveness on Reducing Hypertension: A Systematic Review.” BMC Nursing 22, no. 1: 19. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12912‐022‐01170‐z.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kronebusch, B. J., D. L. Rismeyer, M. M. Enos, L. L. Swenson, S. G. Witwer, and V. L. Hunt. 2020. “Registered Nurse Visits to Improve Hypertension Management: A Quality Improvement Project.” Nursing Economics 38, no. 3: 121–132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, J. J., Z. Q. Fu, Q. Liu, et al. 2022. “Interactions Among Maternal Smoking, Breastfeeding, and Offspring Genetic Factors on the Risk of Adult‐Onset Hypertension.” BMC Medicine 20, no. 1: 454. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916‐022‐02648‐y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, J. 2020. “Highlights of the 2018 Chinese Hypertension Guidelines.” Clinical Hypertension 26, no. 1: 8. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40885‐020‐00141‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Robles, J. R., M. J. Cobo, M. Gutiérrez‐Salcedo, M. A. Martínez‐Sánchez, N. K. Gamboa‐Rosales, and E. Herrera‐Viedma. 2021. “30th Anniversary of Applied Intelligence: A Combination of Bibliometrics and Thematic Analysis Using SciMAT.” Applied Intelligence 51, no. 9: 6547–6568. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10489‐021‐02584‐z.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mancia, G., R. Kreutz, M. Brunström, et al. 2023. “2023 ESH Guidelines for the Management of Arterial Hypertension the Task Force for the Management of Arterial Hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension: Endorsed by the International Society of Hypertension (ISH) and the European Renal Association (ERA).” Journal of Hypertension 41, no. 12: 1874–2071. https://doi.org/10.1097/hjh.0000000000003480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McHale, S., J. Hanley, and M. Paterson. 2023. “Patient Experiences of Remote Hypertension Management During Covid‐19: A Qualitative Study.” European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 22: I155–I155.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mills, K. T., J. D. Bundy, T. N. Kelly, et al. 2016. “Global Disparities of Hypertension Prevalence and Control: A Systematic Analysis of Population‐Based Studies from 90 Countries.” Circulation 134, no. 6: 441–450. https://doi.org/10.1161/circulationaha.115.018912.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institutes of Health (NIH). 2022. High Blood Pressure Research. Retrieved April 8 from https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/research/high‐blood‐pressure#Related‐high‐blood‐pressure‐programs.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nozato, Y., K. Yamamoto, and H. Rakugi. 2023. “Hypertension Management Before and Under the COVID‐19 Pandemic: Lessons and Future Directions.” Hypertension Research 46, no. 6: 1471–1477. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41440‐023‐01253‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olayinka, T. 2022. “Effect of the Novel Coronavirus Disease (COVID‐19) Pandemic on Patients' Self‐Management of Chronic Diseases (Hypertension and Diabetes).” Nursing Research 71, no. 3: S36–S36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SCImago. 2024. SJR—SCImago Journal &amp; Country Rank. Retrieved April 10 from https://www.scimagojr.com/journalrank.php?area=2900&amp;type=j#google_vignette.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah, N. P., R. M. Clare, K. Chiswell, A. M. Navar, B. R. Shah, and E. D. Peterson. 2022. “Trends of Blood Pressure Control in the US During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” American Heart Journal 247: 15–23. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ahj.2021.11.017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sott, M. K., M. S. Bender, L. B. Furstenau, L. M. Machado, M. J. Cobo, and N. L. Bragazzi. 2020. “100 Years of Scientific Evolution of Work and Organizational Psychology: A Bibliometric Network Analysis From 1919 to 2019.” Frontiers in Psychology 11: 598676. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.598676.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suwanno, J., C. Phonphet, C. Mayurapak, P. Ninla‐aesong, and L. Thaimwong. 2023. “Exploring Factors Associated With Hypertension Self‐Care in Primary Care: The Role of Nurse Education Levels and Patient‐Related Factors.” International Journal of Nursing Practice 30: e13208. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijn.13208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tripathi, M., S. Kumar, S. K. Sonker, and P. Babbar. 2018. “Occurrence of Author Keywords and Keywords Plus in Social Sciences and Humanities Research: A Preliminary Study.” Journal of Scientometrics and Information Management 12, no. 2: 215–232. https://doi.org/10.1080/09737766.2018.1436951.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. 2020. The Surgeon General's Call to Action to Control Hypertension. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK567645/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Eck, N. J., and L. Waltman. 2010. “Software Survey: VOSviewer, a Computer Program for Bibliometric Mapping.” Scientometrics 84, no. 2: 523–538. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192‐009‐0146‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Victora, C. G., R. Bahl, A. J. Barros, et al. 2016. “Breastfeeding in the 21st Century: Epidemiology, Mechanisms, and Lifelong Effect.” Lancet 387, no. 10017: 475–490. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140‐6736(15)01024‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warnes, G. R., B. Bolker, G. Gorjanc, et al. 2016. gdata: Various R Programming Tools for Data Manipulation. https://cran.r‐project.org/web/packages/gplots/index.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whelton, P. K., J. M. Flack, G. Jennings, A. Schutte, J. Wang, and R. M. Touyz. 2023. “Editors' Commentary on the 2023 ESH Management of Arterial Hypertension Guidelines.” Hypertension 80, no. 9: 1795–1799. https://doi.org/10.1161/hypertensionaha.123.21592.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). 2023. Hypertension. Retrieved April 3 from https://www.who.int/news‐room/fact‐sheets/detail/hypertension.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). 2024. Cardiovascular Diseases (CVDs). Retrieved March 18 from https://www.who.int/health‐topics/cardiovascular‐diseases#tab=tab_1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wulan, W. R., E. Widianawati, I. Pantiawati, and F. Wulandari. 2023. “Telemedicine Homecare Among the Hypertension and Diabetes Mellitus Risk Elderly Group in Indonesian Primary Healthcare: A Technology Acceptance Model.” Home Health Care Management and Practice 36, no. 2: 88–94. https://doi.org/10.1177/10848223231195638.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, B., P. Perel, G. A. Mensah, and M. Ezzati. 2021. “Global Epidemiology, Health Burden and Effective Interventions for Elevated Blood Pressure and Hypertension.” Nature Reviews Cardiology 18, no. 11: 785–802. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41569‐021‐00559‐8.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>