<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39449519</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1746-1561</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>94</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Journal of school health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sch Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Impact of Lockdown in Cyberbullying in Primary Education: Transitions of Cyberbullying and Bullying.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1058</StartPage><EndPage>1068</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1058-1068</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/josh.13505</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic triggered a worldwide socio-sanitary crisis, continuing to impact societies worldwide. With many school systems shifted to online education, the current study presents a unique opportunity to investigate relevant phenomena related to serious health issues during the schooling and later in life, cyberbullying and bullying. This study began just before the COVID-19 lockdown was declared and resumed 5 months later allowing to explore 2 main objectives: first, to explore whether cyberbullying increased during the lockdown, and second, to analyze transitions from to time of bullying and cyberbullying.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The participants included 792 students from sixth and seventh years of Primary Education (Mean<sub>age</sub> = 10.81, SD = 0.85) in Ecuador. This is a quantitative longitudinal study. Cyberbullying and bullying scales were used for data collection before the lockdown in January and February 2020 (T1), and after 5 months of lockdown, at the end of the same academic year in July 2020 (T2). Descriptive, comparative and predictive analyses, a latent transition analysis was used to identify latent status of cyberbullying and bullying behavior at T1 and T2.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The results revealed a significant increase of cyberbullying after 5 months of the lockdown. Interestingly, only a small percentage of students who were uninvolved in cyberbullying and bullying in T1 remained uninvolved in T2.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The discussion explores the dynamics of cyberbullying involvement and examines changes in the roles and groups of bullying and cyberbullying after 5 months of lockdown. The political- and school-related implications of these findings are thoroughly discussed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of School Health published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American School Health Association.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Llorent</LastName><ForeName>Vicente J</ForeName><Initials>VJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6795-2933</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Education, University of Cordoba, Córdoba, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seade-Mejía</LastName><ForeName>Carolina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8325-1977</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universidad Nacional de Educación, Cañar, Ecuador.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vélez-Calvo</LastName><ForeName>Ximena</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4451-9547</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universidad del Azuay, Cuenca, Ecuador.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nasaescu</LastName><ForeName>Elena</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4499-9445</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of Cordoba, Cordoba, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Sch Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376370</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-4391</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000077224" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cyberbullying</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058445" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bullying</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008137" MajorTopicYN="N">Longitudinal Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012574" MajorTopicYN="Y">Schools</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020375" MajorTopicYN="N">Education, Distance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011790" MajorTopicYN="N">Quarantine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bullying</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cyberbullying</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">school</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transitions</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/josh.13505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Filgueira F, Galindo L, Giambruno C, Blofield M. América Latina ante la crisis del COVID‐19: Vulnerabilidad socioeconómica y respuesta social. Santiago: Naciones Unidas; 2020 Available at: https://repositorio.cepal.org/bitstream/handle/11362/46484/S2000718_es.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackman A, Ibáñez A, Izquierdo A, et al. La política pública frente al COVID‐19: Recomendaciones para América Latina y el Caribe. Nueva York: Banco Interamericano de Desarrollo; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gazca A. Implicaciones del coronavirus Covid‐19 en los procesos de enseñanza en la educación superior. RIDE Rev Iberoam Investig Desarro Educ. 2020;11(21):1‐30. https://doi.org/10.23913/ride.v11i21.753.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministerio de Educación. Plan Educativo COVID‐19. Quito: Gobierno del Ecuador; 2020 Available at: https://educacion.gob.ec/plan‐educativo‐covid‐19/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Bueno R, López‐Sánchez GF, Casajús JA, et al. Health‐related behaviors among school‐aged children and adolescents during the Spanish Covid‐19 confinement. Front Pediatr. 2020;8:573. https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/pediatrics/articles/10.3389/fped.2020.00573/full.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palacio‐Ortiz J, Londoño‐Herrera J, Nanclares‐Márquez A, Robledo‐Rengifo P, Quintero‐Cadavid CP. Psychiatric disorders in children and adolescents during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Rev Col Psic. 2020;49(4):279‐288. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rcpeng.2020.11.003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pizarro‐Ruiz JP, Ordóñez‐Camblor N. Effects of Covid‐19 confinement on the mental health of children and adolescents in Spain. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1):11713 Available at: https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598‐021‐91299‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caurcel‐Cara M, Crisol‐Moya E. Ciberacoso en estudiantes universitarios antes y durante el confinamiento por la COVID‐19. Educación XX1. 2022;25(1):67‐91. https://doi.org/10.5944/educxx1.30525.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patchin J, Hinduja S. Measuring cyberbullying: implications for research. Aggress Violent Behav. 2015;23:69‐74. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.avb.2015.05.013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega‐Ruiz R, Del Rey R, Casas JA. Evaluar el bullying y el cyberbullying validación española del EBIP‐Q y del ECIPQ. Psicol Educ. 2016;22(1):71‐79. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pse.2016.01.004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez M. Disminución de la ansiedad en las víctimas del bullying durante el confinamiento por el COVID‐19. Rev Educ Distancia. 2021;21(65):1‐20 Available at: https://revistas.um.es/red/article/view/439601/298611.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega‐Ruiz R. Treinta años de investigación y prevalencia del bullying y la violencia escolar. In: Ortega‐Ruiz R, ed. Agresividad injustificada, bullying y violencia escolar. Madrid: Alianza Editorial; 2010:13‐15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNESCO. Safe Learning Environments: Preventing and Addressing Violence in and around School. Paris: UNESCO; 2023 Available at: https://www.unesco.org/en/health‐education/safe‐learning‐environments.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zych I, Ortega‐Ruiz R, Del Rey R. Systematic review of theoretical studies on bullying and cyberbullying: facts, knowledge, prevention, and intervention. Aggress Violent Behav. 2015;23:1‐21. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.avb.2015.10.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zych I, Farrington D, Llorent VJ, Ttofi M. Protecting Children Against Bullying and its Consequences. New York: Springer; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiménez T, Moreno‐Ruiz D, Estévez E, Callejas J, López‐Crespo G, Valdivia S. Academic competence, teacher–student relationship, and violence and victimisation in adolescents: the classroom climate as a mediator. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(3):1163. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18031163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore S, Norman R, Suetani S, Thomas H, Sly P, Scott J. Consequences of bullying victimization in childhood and adolescence: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. World J Psychiatry. 2017;7(1):60‐76 Available at: https://www.wjgnet.com/2220‐3206/full/v7/i1/60.htm.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cénat J, Hébert M, Blais M, Lavoie F, Guerrier M, Derivois D. Cyberbullying, psychological distress and self‐esteem among youth in Quebec schools. J Affect Disord. 2014;169(1):7‐9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2014.07.019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shpiegel Y, Klomek AB, Apter A. Bullying, cyberbullying, depression and suicide ideation among youth: comparing online to paper‐and‐pencil questionnaires. In: Merrick J, ed. Child and Adolescent Health Yearbook 2015. New York: Nova Science Publishers; 2016:179‐187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarro R, Yubero S, Larrañaga E. Cyberbullying victimization and fatalism in adolescence: resilience as a moderator. Child Youth Serv Rev. 2018;84:215‐221. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.childyouth.2017.12.011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilić V, Buljan‐Flander G, Rafajac B. Life satisfaction and school performance of children exposed to classic and cyber peer bullying. Coll Antropol. 2014;38(1):21‐29 Available at: https://hrcak.srce.hr/clanak/178668.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Povedano A, Hendry L, Ramos M, Varela R. Victimización escolar: Clima familiar, autoestima y satisfacción con la vida desde una perspectiva de género. Psychosoc Interv. 2011;20(1):5‐12. https://doi.org/10.5093/in2011v20n1a1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garaigordobil M, Mollo‐Torrico JP, Larrain E. Prevalencia de bullying y cyberbullying en Latinoamérica: una revisión. Rev Iberoam Psicol. 2019;11(3):1‐18. https://doi.org/10.33881/2027‐1786.rip.11301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell S, Seegan P, Roush J, Brown S, Sustaíta M, Cukrowicz K. Retrospective cyberbullying and suicide ideation: the mediating roles of depressive symptoms, perceived burdensomeness, and thwarted belongingness. J Interpers Violence. 2018;33(16):2602‐2620. https://doi.org/10.1177/0886260516628291.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young R, Subramanian R, Miles S, Hinnant A, Andsager J. Social representation of cyberbullying and adolescent suicide: a mixed‐method analysis of news stories. Health Commun. 2016;32(9):1082‐1092. https://doi.org/10.1080/10410236.2016.1214214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinduja S, Patchin J. Bullying, cyberbullying, and suicide. Arch Suicide Res. 2010;14(3):206‐221. https://doi.org/10.1080/13811118.2010.494133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoff D, Mitchell S. Cyberbullying: causes, effects, and remedies. J Educ Adm. 2009;47(5):652‐655. https://doi.org/10.1108/09578230910981107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauman S, Toomey R, Walker J. Associations among bullying, cyberbullying, and suicide in high school students. J Adolesc. 2013;36(2):341‐350. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.adolescence.2012.12.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasaescu E, Zych I, Ortega‐Ruiz R, Farrington D, Llorent VJ. Longitudinal patterns of antisocial behaviours in early adolescence: a latent class and latent transition analysis. Eur J Psychology Appl Legal Context. 2020;12(2):85‐92. https://doi.org/10.5093/ejpalc2020a10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldry AC, Farrington DP, Sorrentino A. School bullying and cyberbullying among boys and girls: roles and overlap. J Aggress Maltreat Trauma. 2017;26:937‐951. https://doi.org/10.1080/10926771.2017.1330793.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldry AC, Farrington DP, Sorrentino A. Cyberbullying in youth: a pattern of disruptive behaviour. Psicol Educ. 2016;22(1):19‐26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pse.2016.02.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barboza G. The association between school exclusion, delinquency and subtypes of cyber‐and F2F‐victimizations: identifying and predicting risk profiles and subtypes using latent class analysis. Child Abuse Negl. 2015;39:109‐122. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chiabu.2014.08.007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paez GR, Hart TC. Context matters (but some contexts matter more): disentangling the influence of traditional bullying victimization on patterns of cyberbullying outcomes. J Bullying Prev. 2022;4:297‐309. https://doi.org/10.1007/s42380‐021‐00104‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubiszewski V, Fontaine R, Potard C, Auzoult L. Does cyberbullying overlap with school bullying when taking modality of involvement into account? Comput Hum Behav. 2015;43:49‐57. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2014.10.049.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rey R, Elipe Muñoz P, Ortega Ruiz R. Bullying and cyberbullying: overlapping and predictive value of the co‐occurrence. Psicothema. 2012;24(4):608‐613 Available at: https://idus.us.es/handle/11441/58142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sorrentino A, Sulla F, Santamato M, Di Furia M, Toto GA, Monacis L. Has the COVID‐19 pandemic affected cyberbullying and cybervictimization prevalence among children and adolescents? A systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20(10):5825 Available at: https://www.mdpi.com/1660‐4601/20/10/5825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang N, Zhang S, Mu Y, Yu Y, Riem MM, Guo J. Does the COVID‐19 pandemic increase or decrease the global cyberbullying behaviors? A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Trauma Violence Abuse. 2024;25(2):1018‐1035. https://doi.org/10.1177/152483802311711.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy RS, Dendy K. Traditional bullying and cyberbullying victimization before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic: a meta‐analysis. Int J Bullying Prev. 2024;6(2):1‐15. https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42380‐024‐00255‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kee D, Al‐Anesi M, Al‐Anesi S. Cyberbullying on social media under the influence of COVID‐19. Glob Bus Organ Excell. 2022;41(6):11‐22. https://doi.org/10.1002/joe.22175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Llorent VJ, Díaz‐Chaves A, Zych I, Twardowska‐Staszek E, Marín‐López I. Bullying and cyberbullying in Spain and Poland, and their relation to social, emotional and moral competencies. Sch Ment Heal. 2021;13:535‐547. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12310‐021‐09473‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanza ST, Dziak JJ, Huang L, Wagner A, Collins LM. PROC LCA &amp; PROC LTA users' guide (Version 1.3.2). University Park: Methodology Center, Penn State; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papathanasopoulou NV. The explosive rise in cyberbullying behavior and online victimization rates among university students in Athens and the role of forced confinement due to the Covid‐19 pandemic. Urban Crime. 2022;3(2):124‐146 Available at: https://ojs.panteion.gr/index.php/uc/article/view/292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowalski R, Giumetti G, Schroeder A, Lattanner M. Bullying in the digital age: a critical review and meta‐analysis of cyberbullying research among youth. Psychol Bull. 2014;140(4):1073‐1137. https://doi.org/10.1037/a0035618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barlett C, Simmers M, Roth B, Gentile D. Comparing cyberbullying prevalence and process before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic. J Soc Psychol. 2021;161(4):408‐418. https://doi.org/10.1080/00224545.2021.1918619.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boals A, Banks J. Stress and cognitive functioning during a pandemic: thoughts from stress researchers. Psychol Trauma Theory Res Pract Policy. 2020;12(S1):255‐257. https://doi.org/10.1037/tra0000716.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garaigordobil M, Machimbarrena J. Victimization and perpetration of bullying /cyberbullying: connections with emotional and behavioral problems and childhood stress. Psychosoc Interv. 2019;28(2):67‐73. https://doi.org/10.5093/pi2019a3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berg MT, Mulford CF. Reappraising and redirecting research on the victim–offender overlap. Trauma Violence Abuse. 2020;21(1):16‐30. https://doi.org/10.1177/1524838017735925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hesselink A. Illustrating the victim offender overlap utilizing the general strain theory with females that committed murder: a criminological case study analysis. J Biomed Sci. 2022;4(6):2179‐2186. https://doi.org/10.38125/OAJBS.000510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwan C, Wong C, Chen Z, Yip PS. Youth bullying and suicide: risk and protective factor profiles for bullies, victims, bully‐victims and the uninvolved. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(5):2828. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19052828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J, Roh B, Yang K. Exploring the association between social support and patterns of bullying victimization among school‐aged adolescents. Child Youth Serv Rev. 2022;136:106418. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.childyouth.2022.106418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achuthan K, Nair VK, Kowalski R, Ramanathan S, Raman R. Cyberbullying research—alignment to sustainable development and impact of COVID‐19: bibliometrics and science mapping analysis. Comput Hum Behav. 2023;140:107566. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2022.107566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang CL, Zhang S, Yang SC. How students react to different cyberbullying events: past experience, judgment, perceived seriousness, helping behavior and the effect of online disinhibition. Comput Hum Behav. 2020;110:106338. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2020.106338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khairi AK, Li W, Yeo SH, et al. The importance of emotional competence in preventing cyberbullying: the role of family as moderator. Int J Acad Res Bus Soc Sci. 2022;12(4):262‐278. https://doi.org/10.6007/IJARBSS/v12‐i4/13062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marín‐López I, Zych I, Ortega‐Ruiz R, Hunter SC, Llorent VJ. Relations among online emotional content use, social and emotional competencies and cyberbullying. Child Youth Serv Rev. 2020;108:104647. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.childyouth.2019.104647.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaffney H, Ttofi MM, Farrington DP. Evaluating the effectiveness of school‐bullying prevention programs: an updated meta‐analytical review. Aggress Violent Behav. 2019;45:111‐133. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.avb.2018.07.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oriol X, Miranda R, Amutio A. Dispositional and situational moral emotions, bullying and prosocial behavior in adolescence. Curr Psychol. 2023;42(13):11115‐11132. https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12144‐021‐02396‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández P, Extremera N. El uso de las medidas de habilidad en el ámbito de la inteligencia emocional: Ventajas e inconvenientes con respecto a las medidas de auto‐informe. Boletín Psicol. 2004;80:59‐78 Available at: https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2005‐14095‐003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allom V, Panetta G, Mullan B, Hagger M. Self‐report and behavioural approaches to the measurement of self‐control: are we assessing the same construct? Personal Individ Differ. 2016;90:137‐142. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2015.10.051.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciarrochi JV, Deane F, Anderson S. Emotional intelligence moderates the relationship between stress and mental health. Personal Individ Differ. 2002;32(2):197‐209. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0191‐8869(01)00012‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glassman L, Martin L, Bradley L, et al. A brief report on the assessment of distress tolerance: are we measuring the same construct? J Ration Emot Cogn Behav Ther. 2016;34(2):87‐99. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10942‐015‐0224‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Valle M, Zamora EV. El uso de las medidas de auto‐informe: ventajas y limitaciones en la investigación en Psicología. Alternativas Psicol. 2021;47:22‐35 Available at: https://www.alternativas.me/attachments/article/264/El%20uso%20de%20las%20medidas%20de%20auto‐informe.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Llorent VJ, González‐Gómez A, Farrington D, Zych I. Improving literacy competence and social and emotional competencies in primary education through cooperative project‐based learning. Psicothema. 2022;34(1):102‐109. https://doi.org/10.7334/psicothema2020.372.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>