<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39444142</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1529-8817</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of phycology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Phycol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessing climatic conditions and biotic interactions shaping the success of Cystoseira foeniculacea early-life stages.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jpy.13516</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Early-life stages of canopy-forming macroalgae are critical for the maintenance of natural populations and the success of restoration actions. Unfortunately, the abiotic conditions and biotic interactions shaping the success of these stages have received less attention than the interactions shaping the success of adults. Here, we combined field and mesocosm experiments to explore the effects of temperature, herbivory, and canopy presence on the development of early-life stages of the brown seaweed Cystoseira foeniculacea. We assessed these effects by examining changes in recruit density and size. After recruiting zygotes under laboratory conditions, we conducted one laboratory and three field experiments. In the first field experiment, the density of recruits decreased over time in all rockpools and was negatively affected by rising temperatures and turf cover. Additionally, a marine heatwave (MHW; 11 days &gt;25°C) was recorded in the donor pools, producing strong decay in the density of transplanted recruits and a significant reduction of the mature canopy. The second field experiment tested the survival of recruits based on their positioning within the canopy. We observed a higher density of recruits when placed at the edge or outside the canopy compared to recruits placed under the canopy. In the third field experiment, an herbivory-exclusion experiment, we show how density of recruits decreased in less than 48 h in noncaged treatments. In the laboratory, we conducted a thermotolerance experiment under controlled conditions, exposing the recruits to 19, 22, 25, 28, and 31°C for 7 weeks to assess thermal impacts on their survival and growth. Temperatures above the 25°C threshold reduced the density and size of the recruits. This study sheds light on the performance of the early-life stages of a Cystoseira spp. in Macaronesia, showing a low survival ratio against the current pressures even in the context of the potential refuge provided by the intertidal rockpools.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Phycology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Phycological Society of America.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bernal-Ibáñez</LastName><ForeName>Alejandro</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9221-3983</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MARE - Marine and Environmental Sciences Centre/ARNET - Aquatic Research Network, Agência Regional Para o Desenvolvimento da Investigação Tecnologia e Inovação (ARDITI), Funchal, Madeira, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Madeira, Funchal, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cacabelos</LastName><ForeName>Eva</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MARE - Marine and Environmental Sciences Centre/ARNET - Aquatic Research Network, Agência Regional Para o Desenvolvimento da Investigação Tecnologia e Inovação (ARDITI), Funchal, Madeira, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Madeira, Funchal, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hydrosphere-Environmental Laboratory for the Study of Aquatic Ecosystems, Vigo, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Oceanográfico de Vigo (COV-IEO), CSIC, Vigo, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Triay-Portella</LastName><ForeName>Raul</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MARE - Marine and Environmental Sciences Centre/ARNET - Aquatic Research Network, Agência Regional Para o Desenvolvimento da Investigação Tecnologia e Inovação (ARDITI), Funchal, Madeira, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Madeira, Funchal, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Grupo en Biodiversidad y Conservación, IU-ECOAQUA, Universidad de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Las Palmas, Canary Islands, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramalhosa</LastName><ForeName>Patrício</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MARE - Marine and Environmental Sciences Centre/ARNET - Aquatic Research Network, Agência Regional Para o Desenvolvimento da Investigação Tecnologia e Inovação (ARDITI), Funchal, Madeira, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Madeira, Funchal, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gestoso</LastName><ForeName>Ignacio</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MARE - Marine and Environmental Sciences Centre/ARNET - Aquatic Research Network, Agência Regional Para o Desenvolvimento da Investigação Tecnologia e Inovação (ARDITI), Funchal, Madeira, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Madeira, Funchal, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, Faculty of Marine and Environmental Sciences &amp; Marine Research Institute (INMAR), Universidad de Cádiz (UCA), Puerto Real, Cádiz, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smithsonian Environmental Research Center (SERC), Edgewater, Maryland, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>European Union-Next GenerationEU/PRTR</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>UIDB/04292/2020</GrantID><Agency>MARE UI&amp;I</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Margarita Salas Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Fundaçao para a Ciência e a Tecnologia</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Phycol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9882935</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-3646</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">climate change</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">grazing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">marine forests</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">marine heatwaves</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thermotolerance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39444142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jpy.13516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Airoldi, L. (2003). The effects of sedimentation on rocky coast assemblages. Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review, 41, 161–236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alves, F. M. A., Chícharo, L. M., Serrao, E., &amp; Abreu, A. D. (2001). Algal cover and sea urchin spatial distribution at Madeira Island (NE Atlantic). Scientia Marina, 65(4), 383–392. https://doi.org/10.3989/scimar.2001.65n4383</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alves, F. M. A., Chícharo, L. M., Serrao, E., &amp; Abreu, A. D. (2003). Grazing by Diadema antillarum (Philippi) upon algal communities on rocky substrates. Scientia Marina, 67(3), 307–311. https://doi.org/10.3989/scimar.2003.67n3307</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assis, J., Legrand, T., Fragkopoulou, E., Gouvêa, L., Serrão, E. A., &amp; Araújo, M. (2024). Oceanographic connectivity strongly restricts future range expansions of critical ecosystem structuring species.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benedetti‐Cecchi, L., &amp; Cinelli, F. (1992). Effects of canopy cover, herbivores and substratum type on patterns of Cystoseira spp. settlement and recruitment in littoral rockpools. Marine Ecology Progress Series. Oldendorf, 90(2), 183–191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett, S., Wernberg, T., De Bettignies, T., Kendrick, G. A., Anderson, R. J., Bolton, J. J., Rodgers, K. L., Shears, N. T., Leclerc, J.‐C., &amp; Lévêque, L. (2015). Canopy interactions and physical stress gradients in subtidal communities. Ecology Letters, 18(7), 677–686.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernal‐Ibáñez, A., Cacabelos, E., Melo, R., &amp; Gestoso, I. (2021). The role of sea‐urchins in marine forests from Azores, Webbnesia, and Cabo Verde: Human pressures, climate‐change effects and restoration opportunities. Frontiers in Marine Science, 8, 649873. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2021.649873</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernal‐Ibáñez, A., Gestoso, I., Ramalhosa, P., Campanati, C., &amp; Cacabelos, E. (2022). Interaction of marine heatwaves and grazing on two canopy‐forming algae. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 556, 151795. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jembe.2022.151795</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernal‐Ibáñez, A., Gestoso, I., Wirtz, P., Kaufmann, M., Serrão, E. A., Canning‐Clode, J., &amp; Cacabelos, E. (2021). The collapse of marine forests: Drastic reduction in populations of the family Sargassaceae in Madeira Island (NE Atlantic). Regional Environmental Change, 21(3), 71. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113‐021‐01801‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bevilacqua, S., Savonitto, G., Lipizer, M., Mancuso, P., Ciriaco, S., Srijemsi, M., &amp; Falace, A. (2019). Climatic anomalies may create a long‐lasting ecological phase shift by altering the reproduction of a foundation species. Ecology, 100(12), 1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanfuné, A., Verlaque, M., Boudouresque, C. F., Rozis, E., &amp; Thibaut, T. (2022). Les forêts marines de France et de Méditerranée: guide de détermination des espèces‐ingénieurs (Sargassaceae, Fucales, Phaeophyceae) [The marine forests of France and the Mediterranean: identification guide for engineer species (Sargassaceae, Fucales, Phaeophyceae)]. Pu De Provence.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brawley, S. H., &amp; Johnson, L. E. (1991). Survival of fucoid embryos in the intertidal zone depends upon developmental stage and microhabitat. Journal of Phycology, 27(2), 179–186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bulleri, F., &amp; Benedetti‐Cecchi, L. (2006). Mechanisms of recovery and resilience of different components of mosaics of habitats on shallow rocky reefs. Oecologia, 149, 482–492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capdevila, P., Hereu, B., Riera, J. L., &amp; Linares, C. (2016). Unravelling the natural dynamics and resilience patterns of underwater Mediterranean forests: Insights from the demography of the brown alga Cystoseira zosteroides. Journal of Ecology, 104(6), 1799–1808. https://doi.org/10.1111/1365‐2745.12625</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capdevila, P., Linares, C., Aspillaga, E., Navarro, L., Kersting, D. K., &amp; Hereu, B. (2015). Recruitment patterns in the Mediterranean deep‐water alga Cystoseira zosteroides. Marine Biology, 162, 1165–1174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capdevila, P., Linares, C., Aspillaga, E., Riera, J. L., &amp; Hereu, B. (2018). Effective dispersal and density‐dependence in mesophotic macroalgal forests: Insights from the Mediterranean species Cystoseira zosteroides. PLoS ONE, 13(1), e0191346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casado‐Amezúa, P., Araújo, R., Bárbara, I., Bermejo, R., Borja, Á., Díez, I., Fernández, C., Gorostiaga, J., Guinda, X., Hernández, I., Juanes, J. A., Peña, V., Peteiro, C., Puente, A., Quintana, I., Tuya, F., Viejo, R. M., Altamirano, M., Gallardo, T., &amp; Martínez, B. (2019). Distributional shifts of canopy‐forming seaweeds from the Atlantic coast of southern Europe. Biodiversity and Conservation, 28(5), 1151–1172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cebrian, E., Tamburello, L., Verdura, J., Guarnieri, G., Medrano, A., Linares, C., Hereu, B., Garrabou, J., Cerrano, C., Galobart, C., &amp; Fraschetti, S. (2021). A roadmap for the restoration of Mediterranean macroalgal forests. Frontiers in Marine Science, 8, 709219. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2021.709219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celis‐Plá, P. S., Martínez, B., Korbee, N., Hall‐Spencer, J. M., &amp; Figueroa, F. L. (2017). Ecophysiological responses to elevated CO2 and temperature in Cystoseira tamariscifolia (Phaeophyceae). Climatic Change, 142, 67–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman, A. R. O. (1995). Functional ecology of fucoid algae: Twenty‐three years of progress. Phycologia, 34(1), 1–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheminée, A., Sala, E., Pastor, J., Bodilis, P., Thiriet, P., Mangialajo, L., Cottalorda, J.‐M., &amp; Francour, P. (2013). Nursery value of Cystoseira forests for Mediterranean rocky reef fishes. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 442, 70–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coelho, S. M., Rijstenbil, J. W., &amp; Brown, M. T. (2000). Impacts of anthropogenic stresses on the early development stages of seaweeds. Journal of Aquatic Ecosystem Stress and Recovery, 7, 317–333.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dawson, A. E. (1941). Some observations on Cystoseira foeniculacea (L.) Grev. emend. Sauvageau. New Phytologist, 40, 316–325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Caralt, S., Verdura, J., Vergés, A., Ballesteros, E., &amp; Cebrian, E. (2020). Differential effects of pollution on adult and recruits of a canopy‐forming alga: Implications for population viability under low pollutant levels. Scientific Reports, 10(1), 17825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dudgeon, S., Kübler, J. E., Wright, W. A., Vadas, R. L., Sr., &amp; Petraitis, P. S. (2001). Natural variability in zygote dispersal of Ascophyllum nodosum at small spatial scales. Functional Ecology, 15, 595–604.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eger, A. M., Marzinelli, E., Baes, R., Blain, C., Blamey, L., Carnell, P. E., Choi, C. G., Hessing‐Lewis, M., Kim, K. Y., &amp; Lorda, J. (2021). The economic value of fisheries, blue carbon, and nutrient cycling in global marine forests. EcoEvoRxiv. https://doi.org/10.32942/osf.io/n7kjs</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falace, A., Kaleb, S., De La Fuente, G., Asnaghi, V., &amp; Chiantore, M. (2018). Ex situ cultivation protocol for Cystoseira amentacea var. Stricta (Fucales, Phaeophyceae) from a restoration perspective. PLoS ONE, 13(2), e0193011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedlander, A. M., Ballesteros, E., Clemente, S., Gonçalves, E. J., Estep, A., Rose, P., &amp; Sala, E. (2017). Contrasts in the marine ecosystem of two Macaronesian islands: A comparison between the remote Selvagens Reserve and Madeira Island. PLoS ONE, 12(11), e0187935. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0187935</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galobart, C., Ballesteros, E., Golo, R., &amp; Cebrian, E. (2023). Addressing marine restoration success: Evidence of species and functional diversity recovery in a ten‐year restored macroalgal forest. Frontiers in Marine Science, 10, 1176655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gianni, F., Bartolini, F., Airoldi, L., Ballesteros, E., Francour, P., Guidetti, P., Meinesz, A., Thibaut, T., &amp; Mangialajo, L. (2013). Conservation and restoration of marine forests in the Mediterranean sea and the potential role of marine protected areas. Advances in Oceanography and Limnology, 4, 83–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gianni, F., Bartolini, F., Airoldi, L., &amp; Mangialajo, L. (2018). Reduction of herbivorous fish pressure can facilitate focal algal species forestation on artificial structures. Marine Environmental Research, 138, 102–109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gissi, E., Manea, E., Mazaris, A. D., Fraschetti, S., Almpanidou, V., Bevilacqua, S., Coll, M., Guarnieri, G., Lloret‐Lloret, E., Pascual, M., Petza, D., Rilov, G., Schonwald, M., Stelzenmüller, V., &amp; Katsanevakis, S. (2021). A review of the combined effects of climate change and other local human stressors on the marine environment. Science of the Total Environment, 755, 142564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gran García, A., Movilla, J., Ballesteros, E., Sales, M., Bolado, I., Galobart, C., &amp; Cefalì, M. E. (2022). Assessing the expansion and success of a restored population of Gongolaria barbata (Stackhouse) Kuntze (Fucales, Phaeophyceae) using high‐precision positioning tools and size distribution frequencies. Mediterranean Marine Science, 23(4), 907–916. https://doi.org/10.12681/mms.30500</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández, J. C., Brito, A., García, N., Gil‐Rodríguez, M. C., Herrera, G., Cruz‐Reyes, A., &amp; Falcón, J. M. (2006). Spatial and seasonal variation of the gonad index of Diadema antillarum (Echinodermata: Echinoidea) in the Canary Islands. Scientia Marina, 70(4), 689–698.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández, J. C., Clemente, S., Brito, A., Falcón, J. M., García, N., &amp; Barquín, J. (2005). Estado de las poblaciones de Diadema antillarum (Echinoidea: Diadematidae) y del recubrimiento de macroalgas en las Reservas Marinas de Canarias: Patrones de distribución espacial [Status of Diadema antillarum populations (Echinoidea: Diadematidae) and macroalgae coverage in the Marine Reserves of the Canary Islands: Patterns of spatial distribution]. Vieraea, 33, 367–383.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irving, A. D., Balata, D., Colosio, F., Ferrando, G. A., &amp; Airoldi, L. (2009). Light, sediment, temperature, and the early life‐history of the habitat‐forming alga Cystoseira barbata. Marine Biology, 156, 1223–1231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iveša, L., Bilajac, A., Gljušćić, E., &amp; Najdek, M. (2022). Gongolaria barbata forest in the shallow lagoon on the southern Istrian coast (northern Adriatic Sea). Botanica Marina, 65(4), 255–268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenkins, S. R., Hawkins, S. J., &amp; Norton, T. A. (1999). Direct and indirect effects of a macroalgal canopy and limpet grazing in structuring a sheltered inter‐tidal community. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 188, 81–92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kendrick, G. A., Nowicki, R. J., Olsen, Y. S., Strydom, S., Fraser, M. W., Sinclair, E. A., Statton, J., Hovey, R. K., Thomson, J. A., Burkholder, D. A., &amp; others. (2019). A systematic review of how multiple stressors from an extreme event drove ecosystem‐wide loss of resilience in an iconic seagrass community. Frontiers in Marine Science, 6, 455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kletou, D., Savva, I., Tsiamis, K., &amp; Hall‐Spencer, J. M. (2018). Opportunistic seaweeds replace Cystoseira forests on an industrialised coast in Cyprus. Mediterranean Marine Science, 19(3), 598. https://doi.org/10.12681/mms.16891</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konar, B., &amp; Estes, J. A. (2003). The stability of boundary regions between kelp beds and deforested areas. Ecology, 84(1), 174–185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling, S., Johnson, C., Frusher, S., &amp; Ridgway, K. (2009). Overfishing reduces resilience of kelp beds to climate‐driven catastrophic phase shift. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 106(52), 22341–22345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling, S., Scheibling, R., Rassweiler, A., Johnson, C., Shears, N., Connell, S., Salomon, A., Norderhaug, K., Pérez‐Matus, A., Hernández, J., Clemente, S., Blamey, L. K., Hereu, B., Ballesteros, E., Sala, E., Garrabou, J., Cebrian, E., Zabala, M., Fujita, D., &amp; Johnson, L. E. (2015). Global regime shift dynamics of catastrophic sea urchin overgrazing. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society, B: Biological Sciences, 370(1659), 20130269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling, S. D., Ibbott, S., &amp; Sanderson, J. C. (2010). Recovery of canopy‐forming macroalgae following removal of the enigmatic grazing sea urchin Heliocidaris erythrogramma. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 395(1–2), 135–146. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jembe.2010.08.027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mangialajo, L., Chiantore, M., &amp; Cattaneo‐Vietti, R. (2008). Loss of fucoid algae along a gradient of urbanisation, and structure of benthic assemblages. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 358, 63–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mangialajo, L., Chiantore, M., Susini, M. L., Meinesz, A., Cattaneo‐Vietti, R., &amp; Thibaut, T. (2012). Zonation patterns and interspecific relationships of fucoids in microtidal environments. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 412, 72–80. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jembe.2011.10.03</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martín García, L., Rancel‐Rodríguez, N. M., Sangil, C., Reyes, J., Benito, B., Orellana, S., &amp; Sansón, M. (2022). Environmental and human factors drive the subtropical marine forests of Gongolaria abies‐marina to extinction. Marine Environmental Research, 181, 105759. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marenvres.2022.105759</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medrano, A., Hereu, B., Cleminson, M., Pagès‐Escolà, M., Rovira, G., Solà, J., &amp; Linares, C. (2020). From marine deserts to algal beds: Treptacantha elegans revegetation to reverse stable degraded ecosystems inside and outside a no‐take marine reserve. Restoration Ecology, 28(3), 632–644. https://doi.org/10.1111/rec.13123</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monserrat, M., Verdura, J., Comeau, S., Cottalorda, J.‐M., Priouzeau, F., Romero, G., &amp; Mangialajo, L. (2023). The role of grazers in early‐life stages of Cystoseira sensu lato can be crucial in the restoration of marine forests. Frontiers in Marine Science, 10, 1176780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliver, E. C., Burrows, M. T., Donat, M. G., Sen Gupta, A., Alexander, L. V., Perkins‐Kirkpatrick, S. E., Benthuysen, J. A., Hobday, A. J., Holbrook, N. J., &amp; Moore, P. J. (2019). Projected marine heatwaves in the 21st century and the potential for ecological impact. Frontiers in Marine Science, 6, 734.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orlando‐Bonaca, M., &amp; Rotter, A. (2018). Any signs of replacement of canopy‐forming algae by turf‐forming algae in the northern Adriatic Sea? Ecological Indicators, 87, 272–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pardi, G., Piazzi, L., &amp; Cinelli, F. (2000). Demographic study of a Cystoseira humilis Kützing (Fucales: Cystoseiraceae) population in the western mediterranean. Botanica Marina, 43(1), 81–86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pessarrodona, A., Filbee‐Dexter, K., Alcoverro, T., Boada, J., Feehan, C. J., Fredriksen, S., Grace, S. P., Nakamura, Y., Narvaez, C. A., Norderhaug, K. M., &amp; Wernberg, T. (2021). Homogenization and miniaturization of habitat structure in temperate marine forests. Global Change Biology, 27(20), 5262–5275. https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.15759</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piazzi, L., Bonaviri, C., Castelli, A., Ceccherelli, G., Costa, G., Curini‐Galletti, M., Langeneck, J., Manconi, R., Montefalcone, M., &amp; Pipitone, C. (2018). Biodiversity in canopy‐forming algae: Structure and spatial variability of the Mediterranean Cystoseira assemblages. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 207, 132–141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. (2024). _R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. https://www.R‐project.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sala, E., Boudouresque, C. F., &amp; Harmelin‐Vivien, M. (1998). Fishing, trophic cascades, and the structure of algal assemblages: Evaluation of an old but untested paradigm. Oikos, 82, 425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sala, E., Kizilkaya, Z., Yildirim, D., &amp; Ballesteros, E. (2011). Alien marine fishes deplete algal biomass in the eastern Mediterranean. PLoS ONE, 6(2), e17356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez de Pedro, R., Fernández, A. N., García‐Sánchez, M. J., Flores‐Moya, A., &amp; Bañares‐España, E. (2022). Seasonal and ontogenetic variability in the photosynthetic thermal tolerance of early‐life stages of Fucus guiryi (Phaeophyceae, Fucales). Phycologia, 61(4), 363–374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangil, C., Martins, G. M., Hernández, J. C., Alves, F., Neto, A. I., Ribeiro, C., León‐Cisneros, K., Canning‐Clode, J., Rosas‐Alquicira, E., Mendoza, J. C., Titley, I., Wallenstein, F., Couto, R. P., &amp; Kaufmann, M. (2018). Shallow subtidal macroalgae in the North‐eastern Atlantic archipelagos (Macaronesian region): A spatial approach to community structure. European Journal of Phycology, 53(1), 83–98. https://doi.org/10.1080/09670262.2017.1385098</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider, C. A., Rasband, W. S., &amp; Eliceiri, K. W. (2012). NIH image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis. Nature Methods, 9(7), 671–675.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scrosati, R. (2005). Review of studies on biomass‐density relationships (including self‐thinning lines) in seaweeds: Main contributions and persisting misconceptions. Phycological Research, 53(3), 224–233.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sjøtun, K., Christie, H., &amp; Helge Fosså, J. (2006). The combined effect of canopy shading and sea urchin grazing on recruitment in kelp forest (Laminaria hyperborea). Marine Biology Research, 2(01), 24–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, C. J., Verdura, J., Papadopoulou, N., Fraschetti, S., Cebrian, E., Fabbrizzi, E., Monserrat, M., Drake, M., Bianchelli, S., &amp; Danovaro, R. (2023). A decision‐support framework for the restoration of Cystoseira sensu lato forests. Frontiers in Marine Science, 10, 1159262.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thibaut, T., Bottin, L., Aurelle, D., Boudouresque, C.‐F., Blanfuné, A., Verlaque, M., Pairaud, I., &amp; Millet, B. (2016). Connectivity of populations of the seaweed Cystoseira amentacea within the bay of Marseille (Mediterranean Sea): Genetic structure and hydrodynamic connections. Cryptogamie, Algologie, 37(4), 233–255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thibaut, T., Pinedo, S., Torras, X., &amp; Ballesteros, E. (2005). Long‐term decline of the populations of Fucales (Cystoseira spp. and Sargassum spp.) in the Albères coast (France, North‐western Mediterranean). Marine Pollution Bulletin, 50(12), 1472–1489. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2005.06.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vadas, R. L., Johnson, S., &amp; Norton, T. A. (1992). Recruitment and mortality of early post‐settlement stages of benthic algae. British Phycological Journal, 27(3), 331–351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valdazo, J., Viera‐Rodríguez, M. A., Espino, F., Haroun, R., &amp; Tuya, F. (2017). Massive decline of Cystoseira abies‐marina forests in Gran Canaria Island (Canary Islands, eastern Atlantic). Scientia Marina, 81(4), 499. https://doi.org/10.3989/scimar.04655.23A</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verdura, J., Rehues, L., Mangialajo, L., Fraschetti, S., Belattmania, Z., Bianchelli, S., Blanfuné, A., Sabour, B., Chiarore, A., &amp; Danovaro, R. (2023). Distribution, health and threats to Mediterranean macroalgal forests: Defining the baselines for their conservation and restoration. Frontiers in Marine Science, 10, 1258842.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verdura, J., Sales, M., Ballesteros, E., Cefalì, M. E., &amp; Cebrian, E. (2018). Restoration of a canopy‐forming alga based on recruitment enhancement: Methods and long‐term success assessment. Frontiers in Plant Science, 9, 1832.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verdura, J., Santamaría, J., Ballesteros, E., Smale, D. A., Cefalì, M. E., Golo, R., Caralt, S., Vergés, A., &amp; Cebrian, E. (2021). Local‐scale climatic refugia offer sanctuary for a habitat‐forming species during a marine heatwave. Journal of Ecology, 109(4), 1758–1773. https://doi.org/10.1111/1365‐2745.13599</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vergés, A., Steinberg, P. D., Hay, M. E., Poore, A. G., Campbell, A. H., Ballesteros, E., Heck, K. L., Jr., Booth, D. J., Coleman, M. A., Feary, D. A., Figueira, W., Langlois, T., Marzinelli, E. M., Mizerek, T., Mumby, P. J., Nakamura, Y., Roughan, M., van Sebille, E., Gupta, A. S., … Wilson, S. K. (2014). The tropicalization of temperate marine ecosystems: Climate‐mediated changes in herbivory and community phase shifts. Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 281(1789), 20140846.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham, H. (2011). ggplot2. Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Computational Statistics, 3(2), 180–185.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>