<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39441523</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2196-8837</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of racial and ethnic health disparities</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Trust in Health Institutions Across Racial Groups: Implications for Dual Flu-Coronavirus Vaccine Adoption.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40615-024-02213-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">This study investigates the factors that influence individuals' willingness to accept a combined COVID-19 and flu vaccine. The primary focus is on examining the impact of trust in health institutions, frequency of flu vaccine uptake, and COVID-19 vaccine uptake. The analysis further delves into racial differences to better understand variations among different racial groups.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This study employs t-tests to compare the means of trust in health institutions, frequency of flu vaccine uptake, and COVID-19 vaccine uptake between individuals who are willing and unwilling to accept the combined vaccine. Additionally, a weighted logistic regression analysis is conducted to predict the likelihood of individuals to receive the combined vaccine, considering key independent and control variables.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The t-test results reveal that individuals who are willing to accept the combined vaccine exhibit higher levels of trust in health institutions, more frequent flu vaccine uptake, and higher COVID-19 vaccine uptake. This pattern holds true across all racial groups. The logistic regression analysis demonstrates that trust in health institutions, frequency of flu vaccine uptake, and COVID-19 vaccine uptake significantly predict individuals' willingness to accept the combined vaccine. Partisanship and demographic characteristics also exert influence on vaccine acceptance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Trust in health institutions plays a pivotal role in vaccine acceptance among individuals from all racial groups. Encouraging routine vaccination practices and leveraging existing vaccination campaigns can facilitate the adoption of combined vaccines. It is imperative to address racial disparities and tailor communication strategies to specific demographic groups to enhance vaccine uptake.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. W. Montague Cobb-NMA Health Institute.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nkouaga</LastName><ForeName>Florent</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0004-9200-9471</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Association of Insurance Commissioners (NAIC), Kansas City, MO, USA. fnkouaga@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101628476</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2196-8837</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 vaccine uptake</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Combined vaccines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Flu vaccine uptake</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Racial disparities in health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Trust in health institutions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine hesitancy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39441523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40615-024-02213-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s40615-024-02213-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bish A, Yardley L, Nicoll A, Michie S. Factors associated with uptake of vaccination against pandemic influenza: a systematic review. Vaccine. 2011;29(38):6472–6484. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.06.107 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blank PR, Schwenkglenks M, Szucs TD. Flu vaccination coverage and perceived risks, benefits, and barriers in adults with chronic respiratory disease in Germany-an update after five years. Vaccine. 2012;30(39):7027–33. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2012.08.007 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2012.08.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogart LM, Ojikutu BO, Tyagi K, Klein DJ, Mutchler MG, Dong L, Kellman S. COVID-19 related medical mistrust, health impacts, and potential vaccine hesitancy among Black Americans living with HIV. JAIDS Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes. 2021;86(2):200–207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogart LM, Ojikutu BO, Tyagi K, et al. COVID-19 related medical mistrust, health impacts, and potential vaccine hesitancy among Black Americans living with HIV. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2021;86(2):200–7. https://doi.org/10.1097/QAI.0000000000002574 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QAI.0000000000002574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33196555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpiano RM, FitzGerald G, Colvin AJ, Pampel FC. The influence of partisanship, political context, and individual factors on COVID-19 vaccination hesitancy across the united states: a comparative analysis. Vaccine. 2021;39(35):5120–5126. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2021.07.066 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher KA, Bloomstone SJ, Walder J, et al. Attitudes toward a potential SARS-COV-2 vaccine: a survey of us adults. Ann Intern Med. 2020;173(12):964–973. https://doi.org/10.7326/M20-3569 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman D, Lambe S, Yu L-M, Freeman J, Chadwick A, Vaccari C, et al. Injection fears and COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy. Psychol Med. 2021;53(4):1185–1195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman D, Loe BV, Chadwick A, Vaccari C, Waite F, Rosebrock L, Lambe S. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in the UK: the oxford coronavirus explanations, attitudes, and narratives survey (OCEANS) II. Psychol Med. 2021;52(14):3127–3141. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291720005188 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freimuth VS, Jamison AM, An J, Hancock GR, Quinn SC. Determinants of trust in the flu vaccine for African Americans and whites. Social Science &amp; Medicine. 2017;193:70–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freimuth VS, Jamison AM, Quinn SC. Perceptions of the US public health system: assessing public confidence in the performance of health institutions during the COVID-19 pandemic. Am J Public Health. 2020;110(7):1022–1028. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2020.305752 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fridman I, Gershon R, Gneezy A. Association between political partisanship and willingness to vaccinate against COVID-19: mediation by trust in government and beliefs about vaccine safety. Vaccine. 2021;39(49):7001–7008. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2021.10.079 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagneux M, Mach N, Humair, J.- P., Rougemont, A., Cornuz, J. Promotion of influenza vaccination in retirement homes: a randomized clinical trial. Epidemiol Infect. 1998;120(3):441–445. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0950268898008832 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendriks SM, Qureshi FM, Finlay A, Bose S. The impact of trust in health authorities on COVID-19 vaccine acceptance: a cross-sectional study. J Public Health Res. 2022;11(3):22799036221124370. https://doi.org/10.1177/22799036221124367 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/22799036221124367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernandez I, Dickson S, Tang S, Gabriel N, Berenbrok LA, Guo J. Disparities in distribution of COVID-19 vaccines across US counties: a geographic information system-based cross-sectional study. PLoS Med. 2022;19(7):e1004069. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1004069 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hornsey MJ, Harris EA, Fielding KS. The politicized science of COVID-19: ideological differences in attitudes towards the pandemic and scientists predict vaccine acceptance. Social Science &amp; Medicine. 2020;277:113957. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113957 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt KA, Gaba A, Lavizzo-Mourey R. Racial and ethnic disparities and perceptions of health care: does health plan type matter? Health Serv Res. 2005;40(2):551–576.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaiswal J, LoSchiavo C, Perlman DC. Disinformation, misinformation and inequality-driven mistrust in the time of COVID-19: lessons unlearned from AIDS denialism. AIDS Behav. 2020;24:2776–2780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamison AM, Quinn SC, Freimuth VS. You don’t trust a government vaccine: narratives of institutional trust and influenza vaccination among African American and white adults. Social Science &amp; Medicine. 2019;221:87–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jolley D, Douglas KM. The effects of anti-vaccine conspiracy theories on vaccination intentions. PLoS ONE. 2014;9(2): e89177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24586574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3930676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones DR, McDermott ML. Partisanship and the politics of covid vaccine hesitancy. Polity. 2022;54(3):408–434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kricorian K, Turner K. COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and beliefs among black and Hispanic Americans. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(8):e0256122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson HJ, Clarke RM, Jarrett C, Eckersberger E, Levine Z, Schulz WS, Jones NS. Measuring trust in vaccination: a global analysis of trust determinants and vaccination uptake. EClinicalMedicine. 2018;2–3:48–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eclinm.2018.11.004 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2018.11.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson HJ, Jarrett C, Eckersberger E, Smith DM, Paterson P. Understanding vaccine hesitancy around vaccines and vaccination from a global perspective: a systematic review of published literature, 2007–2012. Vaccine. 2014;32(19):2150–2159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson HJ, Jarrett C, Schulz WS, Chaudhuri M, Zhou Y, Dube E, Schuster M. Measuring trust in vaccination: a systematic review. Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics. 2014;10(2):258–265. https://doi.org/10.4161/hv.28216 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindley MC, Wortley PM, Winston CA, Bardenheier BH. School-based vaccination: current successes and future challenges. Hum Vaccin. 2007;3(5):176–179. https://doi.org/10.4161/hv.3.5.4289 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milkman KL, Duckworth AL, Grant AM, Gromet DM, Wangerin DA, Pope DG. The effect of partisan media and ideological polarization on vaccine uptake during the COVID-19 pandemic. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2021;118(43). https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2102134118 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman PA, Dinh DD, Nyoni T, et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and under-vaccination among marginalized populations in the United States and Canada: a scoping review. J Racial Ethn Health Disparities. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40615-023-01882-1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40615-023-01882-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38117443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen HTT, Dao TH, Nguyen TTM, Nguyen TD, Nguyen LH, Tran BN, et al. COVID-19 vaccination intent, perceptions, and reasons for hesitancy: findings from a nationally representative survey in the Philippines. The Lancet Regional Health-Western Pacific. 2021;14:100253. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100253 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen KH, Yankey D, Coy KC, Klevens RM. COVID-19 vaccination coverage, intent, knowledge, attitudes, and perceptions by race/ethnicity among adults, United States, September and December 2020. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2021;70(6):202–207. https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm7006a1 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen LH, Joshi AD, Drew DA, Merino J, Ma W, Lo C-H, et al. Racial and ethnic differences in COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and uptake. medRxiv. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nichol KL, Margolis KL, Wuorenma J, Von Sternberg T. Effectiveness of influenza vaccine in the elderly. N Engl J Med. 1998;338(22):1709–17014. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJM199805283382201 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Offit PA, Quarles J, Gerber MA, Hackett CJ, Marcuse EK, Kollman TR, Landry S. Addressing parents’ concerns: do multiple vaccines overwhelm or weaken the infant’s immune system? Pediatrics. 2002;109(1):124–129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padamsee TJ, Bond RM, Dixon GN, Hovick SR, Na K, Nisbet EC, Garrett RK. Changes in COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy among black and white individuals in the US. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5(1):e2144470–e2144470.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plotkin S. History of vaccination. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2014;111(34):12283–12287.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quinn SC, Jamison AM. Determinants of trust in the flu vaccine for African Americans and whites. Social Science &amp; Medicine. 2017;193:70–79. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2017.10.001 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quinn SC, Jamison AM, Freimuth VS, An J, Hancock GR. Determinants of influenza vaccination among high-risk black and white adults. Vaccine. 2017;35(51):7154–7159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiter RAC, Kessels LTE, Jansma EP, Brug J. Vaccination and perceived vulnerability to disease: a longitudinal study on the role of partisanship, trust, and demographic factors. Vaccine. 2016;34(42):5297–5302. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.07.110 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savoia E, Piltch-Loeb R, Goldberg B, Miller-Idriss C, Hughes B, Montrond A, Testa MA. Predictors of COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy: socio-demographics, co-morbidity, and past experience of racial discrimination. Vaccines. 2021;9(7):767.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines9070767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34358184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8310049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider EC, Leape LL, Weissman JS, Schneider JR, Epstein AM. Healthcare access and utilization among US adults with chronic conditions: a racial/ethnic perspective. Am J Public Health. 2016;106(5):957–966. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2015.302891 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siegel M, Critchfield-Jain I, Boykin M, et al. Racial/ethnic disparities in state-level COVID-19 vaccination rates and their association with structural racism. J Racial Ethn Health Disparities. 2022;9(6):2361–2374. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40615-021-01173-7 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor B, Miller E, Farrington C, Petropoulos M-C, Favot-Mayaud I, Li J, Waight PA. Autism and measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine: no epidemiological evidence for a causal association. The Lancet. 1999;353(9169):2026–2029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Troiano G, Nardi A. Vaccine hesitancy in the era of COVID-19. Public Health. 2021;194:245–251.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong TTK, Nguyen TQ, Truong VB, Ngo TT, Pham TNH, Vo TLH, Nguyen TL. COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and associated factors among the adult population in Vietnam: implications for vaccine hesitancy and campaign strategies. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1):1–9. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-022-13298-1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-13298-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verger P, Scronias D, Dauby N, Adedzi KA, Gobert C, Bergeat M, Druais, P.- L. Attitudes of healthcare workers towards COVID-19 vaccination: a survey in France and French-speaking parts of Belgium and Canada, 2020. Eurosurveillance. 2021;26(3):2002047. https://doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2021.26.3.2002047 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wakefield AJ, Murch SH, Anthony A, Linnell J, Casson DM, Malik M, et al. Retracted: ileal-lymphoid-nodular hyperplasia, non-specific colitis, and pervasive developmental disorder in children. The lancet. 1998;351(9103):637–641.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams L, Gallant AJ, Rasmussen S, Nicholls LA, Cogan N, Deakin K, White C. Factors associated with attitudes towards COVID-19 vaccines among the general population in Poland: a cross-sectional survey in December 2020. Vaccines. 2021;9(4):388. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines9040388 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines9040388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson RF, Kota KK, Sheats KJ, Luna-Pinto C, Owens C, Harrison DD, Razi S. Call out racism and inequity in reports on vaccine intentions. Nat Hum Behav. 2023;7(3):300–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41562-023-01532-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36755132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye X. Exploring the relationship between political partisanship and COVID-19 vaccination rate. J Public Health. 2023;45(1):91–98.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>