<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39445701</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2648</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of advanced nursing</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Adv Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>No Backstage: The Relentless Emotional Management of Acute Nursing Through the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jan.16563</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM(S)" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To explore the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on nurse's well-being, experiences of delivering healthcare within acute settings and their emotional management.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">Sequential mixed methods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">February to July 2021 an online well-being survey was disseminated to nurses working in acute settings within one Scottish health board. In-depth interviews with a purposive sample of respondents were conducted. Survey data were analysed descriptively, and interview data using Framework analysis and emotional management as the theoretical framework.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Well-being was poor overall. Infection control measures impeded interactions, with loss of connection between patients, families and nurses. Emotional work was extended in caring for patients and families when visits were forbidden or restricted. Disconnect between colleagues was intensely felt. On COVID and non-COVID wards, nurses were caring for patients with a significantly reduced workforce and often outside their clinical speciality. Nurses masked their own anxieties, fears, moral distress and exhaustion on the ward. Communal 'backstage' spaces, were reduced to enable more infection-control space but reduced opportunity for collegial support. Formal psychological intervention required access after shift, and/or nurses feared they could not contain their emotions afterwards.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Working during the pandemic was emotionally and physically demanding for those in COVID a.nd non-COVID wards. Unintended consequences of infection control measures significantly extended nurses' emotional management, by caring for isolated patients and families but impeding opportunities to care for each other, compounding their emotions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPLICATIONS FOR THE PROFESSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">There is a need to value emotional work in nursing to better support mental well-being.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPACT" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">We advance the nursing emotional management literature by addressing the gap of exploration in challenging conditions. The importance of emotional management on nurses' mental well-being has been overlooked but focusing on this in the next crisis could improve nurse's well-being.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PATIENT OR PUBLIC CONTRIBUTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">No patient or public contribution.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="REPORTING METHOD" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">GRAMMS.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Advanced Nursing published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grant</LastName><ForeName>Aileen</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6146-101X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing Midwifery and Paramedic Practice, Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Brien</LastName><ForeName>Rosaleen</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Independent Scholar, Glasgow, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Douglas</LastName><ForeName>Flora</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0333-6605</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing Midwifery and Paramedic Practice, Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kennedy</LastName><ForeName>Catriona</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3510-9113</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing Midwifery and Paramedic Practice, Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baldie</LastName><ForeName>Debbie</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NHS Grampian, Scotland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Torrance</LastName><ForeName>Nicola</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7856-7408</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing Midwifery and Paramedic Practice, Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Adv Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7609811</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0309-2402</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">burnout</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">compassion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">emotional intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nurse–patient interaction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">organisational behaviour</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">patient safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">teamwork</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">work organisation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39445701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jan.16563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Ahmed, S. 2004. “Affective Economies.” Social Text 79, no. 22: 117–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashley, C., S. James, A. Williams, et al. 2021. “The Psychological Well‐Being of Primary Healthcare Nurses During COVID‐19: A Qualitative Study.” Journal of Advanced Nursing 77, no. 9: 3820–3828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell, V., and D. Wade. 2021. “Mental Health of Clinical Staff Working in High‐Risk Epidemic and Pandemic Health Emergencies a Rapid Review of the Evidence and Living Meta‐Analysis.” Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology 56: 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolton, S. 2001. “Changing Faces: Nurses as Emotional Jugglers.” Sociology of Health &amp; Illness 23, no. 1: 85–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolton, S. C., and C. Boyd. 2003. “Trolley Dolly or Skilled Emotion Manager? Moving on From Hochschild's Managed Heart.” Work, Employment and Society 17, no. 2: 289–308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen, S., T. Kamarck, and R. Mermelstein. 1983. “A Global Measure of Perceived Stress.” Journal of Health and Social Behavior 24, no. 4: 385–396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Couper, K., T. Murrells, J. Sanders, et al. 2022. “The Impact of COVID‐19 on the Wellbeing of the UK Nursing and Midwifery Workforce During the First Pandemic Wave: A Longitudinal Survey Study.” International Journal of Nursing Studies 127: 104155.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delgado, C., M. Roche, J. Fethney, and K. Foster. 2020. “Workplace Resilience and Emotional Labour of Australian Mental Health Nurses: Results of a National Survey.” International Journal of Mental Health Nursing 29, no. 1: 35–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delgado, C., D. Upton, K. Ranse, T. Furness, and K. Foster. 2017. “Nurses' Resilience and the Emotional Labour of Nursing Work: An Integrative Review of Empirical Literature.” International Journal of Nursing Studies 70: 71–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Tella, M., A. Romeo, A. Benfante, and L. Castelli. 2020. “Mental Health of Healthcare Workers During the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Italy.” Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice 26, no. 6: 1583–1587.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douglas, F., C. Kennedy, N. Torrance, et al. 2021. An Investigation of Health and Social Care Students' and Recent Graduates' Clinical Placement and Professional Practice Experiences and Coping Strategies During the Wave 1 COVID‐19 Pandemic Period. Edinburgh, Scotland: Chief Scientist Office, Scottish Government Health Directorates. https://www.cso.scot.nhs.uk/wp‐content/uploads/COVrgu2002rpb.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowrick, A., L. Mitchinson, K. Hoernke, et al. 2021. “Re‐Ordering Connections: UK Healthcare Workers' Experiences of Emotion Management During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Sociology of Health &amp; Illness 43, no. 9: 2156–2177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher, N., L. Bramley, J. Cooper, S. E. Field‐Richards, J. Lymn, and S. Timmons. 2022. “A Qualitative Study Exploring the Influence of a Talent Management Initiative on Registered Nurses' Retention Intentions.” Journal of Nursing Management 30, no. 8: 4472–4479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goffman, E. 1959. The Presentation of Self in Everyday Life. New York: Anchor Books.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gray, B. 2010. “Emotional Labour, Gender and Professional Stereotypes of Emotional and Physical Contact, and Personal Perspectives on the Emotional Labour of Nursing.” Journal of Gender Studies 19, no. 4: 349–360.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holton, S., K. Wynter, M. Trueman, et al. 2021. “Psychological Well‐Being of Australian Hospital Clinical Staff During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Australian Health Review 45, no. 3: 297–305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Council of Nurses. 2023. “Recover to Rebuild: Investing in the Nursing Workforce for Health Sytems Effectiveness.” Geneva, Switzerland: ICN. https://www.icn.ch/sites/default/files/2023‐07/ICN_Recover‐to‐Rebuild_report_EN.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson, E. K. 2015. “The Business of Care: The Moral Labour of Care Workers.” Sociology of Health &amp; Illness 37, no. 1: 112–126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, S. C., C. Quiban, C. Sloan, and A. Montejano. 2021. “Predictors of Poor Mental Health Among Nurses During COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Nursing Open 8, no. 2: 900–907.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kings Fund. 2021. “NHS Workforce: Our Position.” https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/projects/positions/nhs‐workforce.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liberati, E., N. Richards, J. Willars, et al. 2021. “A Qualitative Study of Experiences of NHS Mental Healthcare Workers During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” BioMed Central Psychiatry 21, no. 1: 250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lincoln, Y. S., and G. E. Guba. 1985. Naturalistic Inquiry. Vol. 9, 438–439. Beverly Hills, CA: Sage Publications Ltd.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., H. Chen, N. Zhang, et al. 2021. “Anxiety and Depression Symptoms of Medical Staff Under COVID‐19 Epidemic in China.” Journal of Affective Disorders 278: 144–148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maben, J., A. Conolly, R. Abrams, et al. 2022. “‘You Can't Walk Through Water Without Getting Wet’ UK Nurses' Distress and Psychological Health Needs During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Longitudinal Interview Study.” International Journal of Nursing Studies 131: 104242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moynihan, R., S. Sanders, Z. A. Michaleff, et al. 2021. “Impact of COVID‐19 Pandemic on Utilisation of Healthcare Services: A Systematic Review.” British Medical Journal Open 11, no. 3: e045343.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelis, D., J. Quoidbach, M. Mikolajczak, and M. Hansenne. 2009. “Increasing Emotional Intelligence: (How) is It Possible?” Personality and Individual Differences 47, no. 1: 36–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Cathain, A., E. Murphy, and J. Nicholl. 2008. “The Quality of Mixed Methods Studies in Health Services Research.” Journal of Health Services Research &amp; Policy 13, no. 2: 92–98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley, R., and M. C. Weiss. 2016. “A Qualitative Thematic Review: Emotional Labour in Healthcare Settings.” Journal of Advanced Nursing 72, no. 1: 6–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ritchie, J., L. Spencer, and W. O'Connor. 2003. “Carrying Out Qualitative Analysis.” In Qualitative Research Practice, A Guide for Social Science Students and Researchers, edited by J. Ritchie and J. Lewis. London: Sage Publications Ltd.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt, K.‐H., and S. Diestel. 2014. “Are Emotional Labour Strategies by Nurses Associated With Psychological Costs? A Cross‐Sectional Survey.” International Journal of Nursing Studies 51, no. 11: 1450–1461.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scottish Government. 2019. “The Scottish Health Survey 2019–Vol. 1 Main: Report.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scottish Government, P.H.D. 2023. “The Scottish Health Survey 2022–volume 1: main report.” https://www.gov.scot/publications/scottish‐health‐survey‐2022‐volume‐1‐main‐report/pages/14/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serrano‐Ripoll, M. J., J. F. Meneses‐Echavez, I. Ricci‐Cabello, et al. 2020. “Impact of Viral Epidemic Outbreaks on Mental Health of Healthcare Workers: A Rapid Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Journal of Affective Disorders 277: 347–357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, P., and B. Gray. 2000. “The Emotional Labour of Nursing: How Student and Qualified Nurses Learn to Care.” In Report on Nurse Education, Nursing Practice and Emotional Labour in the Contemporary NHS. London: South Bank University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theodosius, C. 2008. Emotional Labour in Health Care: The Unmanaged Heart of Nursing. Brighton, UK: University of Brighton.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timmermans, S., and I. Tavory. 2012. “Theory Construction in Qualitative Research: From Grounded Theory to Abductive Analysis.” Sociological Theory 30, no. 3: 167–186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warwick Medical School. 2023. “Collect, Score, Analyse and Interpret WEMWBS.” https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/med/research/platform/wemwbs/using/howto/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wetherall, K., S. Cleare, S. Eschle, et al. 2018. “From Ideation to Action: Differentiating Between Those Who Think About Suicide and Those Who Attempt Suicide in a National Study of Young Adults.” Journal of Affective Disorders 241: 475–483.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>