<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39445302</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Incidence of Delirium in ICU Patients With and Without COVID-19 in a Costa Rican Hospital.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70007</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70007</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70007</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.70007</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND"> Delirium is a common and serious neurological complication in intensive care units (ICUs), often leading to poor patient outcomes and increased mortality. This study aimed to compare the incidence of delirium in ICU patients with COVID-19 to those with other respiratory infections in a private hospital in Costa Rica. Additionally, it evaluated the prevalence, severity, duration, and treatment of delirium in these critically ill patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A retrospective observational study was conducted, analyzing multiple variables obtained from the electronic health records of patients hospitalized in the ICU of Hospital Clinica Biblica. The study included patients admitted between January 2020 and December 2023. It compared the incidence of delirium among patients admitted for COVID-19 and those admitted for other diagnoses. The main outcomes measured were the incidence of delirium and the correlation of its management with international guidelines. The measures included the use of mechanical ventilation, the development of delirium, and the use of sedatives.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 137 patients were analyzed, of whom 57.7% were over 70 years old, 67.2% were men, 45.2% were admitted with a diagnosis of COVID-19, 90.5% used mechanical ventilation, and 49.6% of patients developed delirium. Dexmedetomidine was the most used sedative, which was the only one that showed a significant relationship with the development of delirium (p=0.0002). Delirium management was mainly done through the administration of dexmedetomidine (52.9%) and quetiapine (41.2%). There was no correlation between delirium development and mortality (p=0.2670).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The study results do not show a significant relationship between COVID-19-positive patients and the development of delirium. Similarly, no higher mortality was observed in those patients who experienced delirium during their ICU stay.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Zavaleta-Monestel et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zavaleta-Monestel</LastName><ForeName>Esteban</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacy, Hospital Clínica Bíblica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martínez-Vargas</LastName><ForeName>Ernesto</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Medicine, Universidad de Costa Rica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chaverri-Fernández</LastName><ForeName>José</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacology, Toxicology and Drug Dependence, Universidad de Costa Rica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Díaz-Madriz</LastName><ForeName>José Pablo</ForeName><Initials>JP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacy, Hospital Clínica Bíblica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fallas-Mora</LastName><ForeName>Abigail</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacology, Toxicology and Drug Dependence, Universidad de Costa Rica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacy, Hospital Clínica Bíblica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alvarado-Ajun</LastName><ForeName>Paola</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing, Hospital Clínica Bíblica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rojas-Chinchilla</LastName><ForeName>Carolina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacy, Hospital Clínica Bíblica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García-Montero</LastName><ForeName>Jonathan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacy, Hospital Clínica Bíblica, San José, CRI.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">delirium</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intensive care unit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mechanical ventilation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sedation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Scientific Ethical Committee of the University of Costa Rica Board issued approval CEC-554-2023. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39445302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11498352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.70007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Risk factors associated with the development of delirium in general ICU patients. A prospective observational study. Lobo-Valbuena B, Gordo F, Abella A, et al. PLoS One. 2021;16:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8412262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34473734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium in the intensive care unit. Arumugam S, El-Menyar A, Al-Hassani A, et al. J Emerg Trauma Shock. 2017;10:37–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5316795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28243012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ICU delirium is associated with cardiovascular burden and higher mortality in patients with severe COVID-19 pneumonia. Gutowski M, Klimkiewicz J, Michałowski A, Ordak M, Możański M, Lubas A. J Clin Med. 2023;12:5049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10420272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37568451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incidence of delirium in critically ill patients with and without COVID-19. Westphal GA, Fernandes RP, Pereira AB, Moerschberger MS, Pereira MR, Gonçalves AR. J Intensive Care Med. 2023;38:751–759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10030890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36939479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium in hospitalized COVID-19 patients: predictors and implications for patient outcome. Wilke V, Sulyok M, Stefanou MI, et al. PLoS One. 2022;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9778494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36548347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence and risk factors for delirium in critically ill patients with COVID-19 (COVID-D): a multicentre cohort study. Pun BT, Badenes R, Heras La Calle G, et al. Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9:239–250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33428871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium in COVID-19. Practical aspects of a frequent association. Giménez-Esparza Vich C, Alcántara Carmona S, García Sánchez M. Med Intensiva. 2022;46:336–340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9042944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35527194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19: what do we need to know about ICU delirium during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic? Kotfis K, Williams Roberson S, Wilson J, et al. Anaesthesiol Intensive Ther. 2020;52:132–138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7667988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32419438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effectiveness of bundle interventions on ICU delirium: a meta-analysis. Zhang S, Han Y, Xiao Q, Li H, Wu Y. Crit Care Med. 2021;49:335–346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7803454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33332818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevention and management of delirium in the intensive care unit. Mart MF, Williams Roberson S, Salas B, Pandharipande PP, Ely EW. Semin Respir Crit Care Med. 2021;42:112–126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7855536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32746469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neurologic manifestations of hospitalized patients with coronavirus disease 2019 in Wuhan, China. Mao L, Jin H, Wang M, et al. JAMA Neurol. 2020;77:683–690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7149362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32275288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neurologic features in severe SARS-CoV-2 infection. Helms J, Kremer S, Merdji H, et al. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:2268–2270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7179967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32294339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical characteristics and outcomes of inpatients with neurologic disease and COVID-19 in Brescia, Lombardy, Italy. Benussi A, Pilotto A, Premi E, et al. Neurology. 2020;95:0–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32444493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium and neuropsychological outcomes in critically Ill patients with COVID-19: a cohort study. Ragheb J, McKinney A, Zierau M, et al. BMJ Open. 2021;11:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8450964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34535480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparison of COVID-19 induced respiratory failure and typical ARDS: similarities and differences. Lu S, Huang X, Liu R, et al. Front Med (Lausanne) 2022;9:829771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9196311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35712114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium in adults with COVID-19-related acute respiratory distress syndrome: comparison with other etiologies. Bernard-Valnet R, Favre E, Bernini A, Oddo M, Chiche JD, Du Pasquier RA, Rossetti AO. Neurology. 2022;99:0–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9695422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36376086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium in critical illness: clinical manifestations, outcomes, and management. Stollings JL, Kotfis K, Chanques G, Pun BT, Pandharipande PP, Ely EW. Intensive Care Med. 2021;47:1089–1103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8366492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34401939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Current status of delirium assessment tools in the intensive care unit: a prospective multicenter observational survey. Ishii K, Kuroda K, Tokura C, et al. Sci Rep. 2022;12:2185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8828828</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35140285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Recent advances in delirium. Grover S, Naskar C. https://journals.lww.com/jgmh/fulltext/2023/10010/recent_advances_in_delirium.1.aspx J Geriatr Ment Health. 2023;10:1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Predisposing and precipitating factors associated with delirium: a systematic review. Ormseth CH, LaHue SC, Oldham MA, Josephson SA, Whitaker E, Douglas VC. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9856673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36607634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium: a marker of vulnerability in older people. Bellelli G, Brathwaite JS, Mazzola P. Front Aging Neurosci. 2021;13:626127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8119654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33994990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Why is delirium more frequent in the elderly? Bugiani O. Neurol Sci. 2021;42:3491–3503.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8143064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34031797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gender differences in the use of atypical antipsychotic medications for ICU delirium. Karamchandani K, Schoaps RS, Printz J, Kowaleski JM, Carr ZJ. Crit Care. 2018;22:220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6148964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30236134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association of blood pressure variability with delirium in patients with critical illness. Zorko Garbajs N, Valencia Morales DJ, Singh TD, et al. Neurocrit Care. 2023;39:646–654.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9757627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36526945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute kidney injury-associated delirium: a review of clinical and pathophysiological mechanisms. Pang H, Kumar S, Ely EW, Gezalian MM, Lahiri S. Crit Care. 2022;26:258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9420275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36030220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium and psychotic symptoms associated with hyperglycemia in a patient with poorly controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus. Lopes R, Pereira BD. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6040722/ Innov Clin Neurosci. 2018;15:30–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6040722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30013817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium. Thom RP, Levy-Carrick NC, Bui M, Silbersweig D. Am J Psychiatry. 2019;176:785–793.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31569986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium in intensive care. Poulsen LM, Estrup S, Mortensen CB, Andersen-Ranberg NC. Curr Anesthesiol Rep. 2021;11:516–523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8413710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34493931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association of incident delirium with short-term mortality in adults with critical illness receiving mechanical ventilation. Li HC, Yeh TY, Wei YC, et al. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9547314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36205994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effect of midazolam on delirium in critically ill patients: a propensity score analysis. Shi HJ, Yuan RX, Zhang JZ, Chen JH, Hu AM. J Int Med Res. 2022;50:3000605221088695.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9044793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35466751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sedation strategy and ICU delirium: a multicentre, population-based propensity score-matched cohort study. Casault C, Soo A, Lee CH, Couillard P, Niven D, Stelfox T, Fiest K. BMJ Open. 2021;11:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8292822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34285003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delirium risk of dexmedetomidine and midazolam in patients treated with postoperative mechanical ventilation: a meta-analysis. Peng W, Shimin S, Hongli W, Yanli Z, Ying Z. Open Med (Wars) 2017;12:252–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5553133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28828407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dexmedetomidine in prevention and treatment of postoperative and intensive care unit delirium: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Flükiger J, Hollinger A, Speich B, Meier V, Tontsch J, Zehnder T, Siegemund M. Ann Intensive Care. 2018;8:92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6148680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30238227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Use of dexmedetomidine in critical-ill patients: is it time to look to the actual evidence? Pérez-Nieto OR, Reyes-Monge RA, Rodríguez-Guevara I, Zamarrón-López EI, Meade-Aguilar JA. Crit Care. 2023;27:332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10463279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37644608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sedation and paralysis. Piriyapatsom A, Bittner EA, Hines J, Schmidt UH. Respir Care. 2013;58:1024–1037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23709198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antipsychotic medication for prevention and treatment of delirium in hospitalized adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Neufeld KJ, Yue J, Robinson TN, Inouye SK, Needham DM. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2016;64:705–714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4840067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27004732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antipsychotics for delirium-the consent conundrum. Morris NP. Lancet Psychiatry. 2020;7:5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31981540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antipsychotic drugs in prevention of postoperative delirium-what is known in 2020? Pluta MP, Dziech M, Czempik PF, Szczepańska AJ, Krzych ŁJ. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:6069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7503241</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32825428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>No benefit to routine antipsychotic use for treatment or prevention of delirium in hospitalized patients. Kulkarni NS. https://www.aafp.org/pubs/afp/issues/2020/0401/p435a.html#:~:text=Although%20there%20is%20some%20evidence,to%20determine%20effect%20on%20delirium Am Fam Physician. 2020;101:435–436.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy and tolerability of atypical antipsychotics in the treatment of delirium: a systematic review of the literature. Rivière J, van der Mast RC, Vandenberghe J, Van Den Eede F. Psychosomatics. 2019;60:18–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30181002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy of quetiapine for delirium prevention in hospitalized older medical patients: a randomized double-blind controlled trial. Thanapluetiwong S, Ruangritchankul S, Sriwannopas O, et al. BMC Geriatr. 2021;21:215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8010962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33789580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strategies for prevention of postoperative delirium: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized trials. Zhang H, Lu Y, Liu M, Zou Z, Wang L, Xu FY, Shi XY. Crit Care. 2013;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3672487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23506796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quetiapine for delirium prophylaxis in high-risk critically ill patients. Abraham MP, Hinds M, Tayidi I, et al. Surgeon. 2021;19:65–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32213291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Psychiatric Association. American Psychiatric Association; 2013. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Role of dexmedetomidine in the treatment of delirium in critically ill patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Liu X, Xiong J, Tang Y, Gong CC, Wang DF. Minerva Anestesiol. 2021;87:65–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33300321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Are dexmedetomidine and olanzapine suitable to control delirium in critically ill elderly patients? A retrospective cohort study. Liu S, Zhao R, Yang R, Zhao H, Ji C, Duan M, Liu J. Biomed Pharmacother. 2021;139:111617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33915500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dexmedetomidine for the treatment of hyperactive delirium refractory to haloperidol in nonintubated ICU patients: a nonrandomized controlled trial. Carrasco G, Baeza N, Cabré L, Portillo E, Gimeno G, Manzanedo D, Calizaya M. Crit Care Med. 2016;44:1295–1306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26925523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SOP: treatment of delirium. Kukolja J, Kuhn J. Neurol Res Pract. 2021;3:12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7934272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33663599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effect of antipsychotics and non-pharmacotherapy for the management of delirium in people receiving palliative care. Lee KY, Tan EC, Hanrahan JR, Chircop C, Michael F, Ong JA. J Pain Palliat Care Pharmacother. 2020;34:225–236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32730108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparison of haloperidol and quetiapine for treatment of delirium in critical illness: a prospective randomised double-blind placebo-controlled trial. Garg R, Singh VK, Pratishruti Pratishruti, Singh GP. https://www.jcdr.net/articles/PDF/16615/56141_CE[Nik]_F[SH]_PF1(PS_KM_KR_SS)_PFA(PS_KM)__PN(KM).pdf J Clin Diagn Res. 2022;16:31–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quetiapine versus haloperidol in the management of hyperactive delirium: randomized controlled trial. Zakhary T, Ahmed I, Luttfi I, Montasser M. Neurocrit Care. 2024;41:550–557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11377686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38561588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association of delirium with increased short-term mortality among older emergency department patients: a cohort study. Arneson ML, Oliveira J E Silva L, Stanich JA, et al. Am J Emerg Med. 2023;66:105–110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10038894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36738568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association between frailty, delirium, and mortality in older critically ill patients: a binational registry study. Sahle BW, Pilcher D, Litton E, Ofori-Asenso R, Peter K, McFadyen J, Bucknall T. Ann Intensive Care. 2022;12:108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9672151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36394660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Post-discharge mortality in patients with delirium and dementia: a 3-year follow up study. Schnorr T, Fleiner T, Schroeder H, et al. Front Psychiatry. 2022;13:835696.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8918771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35295785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>