<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39440974</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2150-7511</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>mBio</Title><ISOAbbreviation>mBio</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Biochemical analysis of packing and assembling heptad repeat motifs in the coronavirus spike protein trimer.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0120324</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0120324</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/mbio.01203-24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>During a coronavirus infection, the spike protein undergoes sequential structural transitions triggered by its receptor and the host protease at the interface between the virus and cell membranes, thereby mediating membrane fusion. After receptor binding, the heptad repeat motif (HR1/HR2) within the viral spike protein bridges the viral and cellular membranes; however, the intermediate conformation adopted by the spike protein when drawing the viral and cellular membranes into close proximity remains unclear due to its transient and unstable nature. Here, we experimentally induced conformational changes in the spike protein of a murine coronavirus by incubating the virus with its receptor, followed by exposure to trypsin. We then treated the virus/receptor complex with proteinase K to probe the tightly packed core structure of the spike protein. The conformations of the spike protein were predicted from the sizes of the protease digestion products detected by western blot analysis. Upon receptor binding, two bands (each showing different reactivity with a fusion-inhibiting HR2-peptide) were detected; we propose that these bands correspond to the packed and unpacked HR1/HR2 motifs. After trypsin-mediated triggering, measurement of temperature and time dependency revealed that packing of the remaining unpacked HR1/HR2 motifs and assembly of three HR1 motifs in a trimer occur almost simultaneously. Thus, the trimeric spike protein adopts an asymmetric-unassembled conformation after receptor binding, followed by direct assembly into the post-fusion form triggered by the host protease. This biochemical study provides mechanistic insight into the previously unknown intermediate structure of the viral fusion protein.IMPORTANCEDuring infection by an enveloped virus, receptor binding triggers fusion between the cellular membrane and the virus envelope, enabling delivery of the viral genome to the cytoplasm. The viral spike protein mediates membrane fusion; however the molecular mechanism underlying this process is unclear. This is because using structural biology methods to track the transient conformational changes induced in the unstable spike trimer is challenging. Here, we harnessed the ability of protease enzymes to recognize subtle differences on protein surfaces, allowing us to detect structural differences in the spike protein before and after conformational changes. Differences in the size of the degradation products were analyzed by western blot analysis. The proposed model explaining the conformational changes presented herein is a plausible candidate that provides valuable insight into unanswered questions in the field of virology.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kobayashi</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Influenza and Respiratory Viruses, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanou</LastName><ForeName>Kazuhiko</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Quality Assurance, Radiation Safety, and Information Management, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okura</LastName><ForeName>Hiyori</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Influenza and Respiratory Viruses, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akter</LastName><ForeName>Tahmina Mst</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Influenza and Respiratory Viruses, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fukushi</LastName><ForeName>Shuetsu</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0001-1296-4320</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology I, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Matsuyama</LastName><ForeName>Shutoku</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9077-3549</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Influenza and Respiratory Viruses, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>mBio</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101519231</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ACE2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CEACAM1a</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MHV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coronavius</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fusion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intermediate</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">protease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spike</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mbio.01203-24</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>