<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39448760</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Cough2COVID-19 detection using an enhanced multi layer ensemble deep learning framework and CoughFeatureRanker.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>25207</StartPage><MedlinePgn>25207</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">25207</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-76639-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In response to the pressing requirement for precise and easily accessible COVID-19 detection methods, we present the Cough2COVID-19 framework, which is cost-effective, non-intrusive, and widely accessible. The conventional diagnostic methods, notably the PCR test, are encumbered by limitations such as cost and invasiveness. Consequently, the exploration of alternative solutions has gained momentum. Our innovative approach employs a multi-layer ensemble deep learning (MLEDL) framework that capitalizes on cough audio signals to achieve heightened efficiency in COVID-19 detection. This study introduces the Cough2COVID-19 framework, effectively addressing these challenges through AI-driven analysis. Additionally, this study proposed the CoughFeatureRanker algorithm, which delves into the robustness of pivotal features embedded within cough audios. The CoughFeatureRanker algorithm selects the most prominent features based on their optimal discriminatory performance from 15 features to detect COVID-19. The effectiveness of the CoughFeatureRanker algorithm within the ensemble framework is scrutinized, confirming its favorable influence on the accuracy of COVID-19 detection. The Cough2COVID-19 (MLEDL) framework achieves remarkable outcomes in COVID-19 detection through cough audio signals, boasting a specificity of 98%, sensitivity of 97%, accuracy of 98%, and an AUC score of 0.981. Our framework asserts its supremacy in precise non-invasive screening through an exhaustive comparison with cutting-edge methodologies. This groundbreaking innovation holds the potential to enhance urban resilience by transforming disease diagnosis, offering a significant approach to curtailing transmission risks and facilitating timely interventions in the ongoing battle against the pandemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Husssain</LastName><ForeName>Shabir</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biopharmaceutical and Health Engineering, Tsinghua Shenzhen International Graduate School, Tsinghua University, Shenzhen, 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ayoub</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wahid</LastName><ForeName>Junaid Abdul</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computer and Artificial Intelligence, Zhengzhou University, Henan, 450001, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Akmal</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Data Science, The Islamia University of Bahawalpur, Bahawalpur, Punjab, 63100, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alabrah</LastName><ForeName>Amerah</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Information Systems, College of Computer and Information Science, King Saud University, Riyadh, 11543, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amran</LastName><ForeName>Gehad Abdullah</ForeName><Initials>GA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Management Science and Engineering, Dalian University of Technology, Dalian, 116024, China. jehad.westran@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>RSP2024R476</GrantID><Agency>King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000077321" MajorTopicYN="Y">Deep Learning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003371" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cough</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000465" MajorTopicYN="Y">Algorithms</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multi-layer ensemble deep learning (MLEDL)CoughAudio analysis CoughFeatureRanker algorithm</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rapid screening</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted without any commercial or financial relationships construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39448760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11502923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-76639-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-76639-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zaim, S., Chong, J. H., Sankaranarayanan, V. &amp; Harky, A. Covid-19 and multiorgan response. Curr. Probl. Cardiol. 45, 100618 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7187881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32439197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain, S. et al. Iot and deep learning based approach for rapid screening and face mask detection for infection spread control of covid-19. Appl. Sci. 11, 3495 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahid, J. A. et al. Identifying and characterizing the propagation scale of covid-19 situational information on twitter: A hybrid text analytic approach. Appl. Sci. 11, 6526 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schrom, J. et al. Comparison of sars-cov-2 reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction and binaxnow rapid antigen tests at a community site during an omicron surge: a cross-sectional study. Ann. Intern. Med. 175, 682–690 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8943844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35286144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purohit, M. &amp; Mustafa, T. Laboratory diagnosis of extra-pulmonary tuberculosis (eptb) in resource-constrained setting: State of the art, challenges and the need. J. Clin. Diagn. Res. 9, EE01 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4437077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26023563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carmody, S., Murray, A., Borodina, M., Gouttebarge, V. &amp; Massey, A. When can professional sport recommence safely during the covid-19 pandemic? Risk assessment and factors to consider (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7418613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32381501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahid, J. A. et al. Topic2labels: A framework to annotate and classify the social media data through lda topics and deep learning models for crisis response. Expert Syst. Appl. 195, 116562 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal, Y., Khan, A., Hussain, S. &amp; Rafiq, U. Analysis of remote learning challenges during covid-19 pandemic on Pakistan’s education sector. Pak. J. Eng. Technol. 7, 59–65. 10.51846/vol7iss2pp59-65 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tena, A., Claria, F. &amp; Solsona, F. Automated detection of covid-19 cough. Biomed. Process. Control 71, 103175 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8435366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34539811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahid, J. A. et al. Topic2features: A novel framework to classify noisy and sparse textual data using lda topic distributions. PeerJ Comput. Sci. 7, e677 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8372003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34458576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashby, A. E., Meister, J. A., Nguyen, K. A., Luo, Z. &amp; Gentzke, W. Cough-based covid-19 detection with audio quality clustering and confidence measure based learning. In Conformal and Probabilistic Prediction with Applications 129–148 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soomro, A. M., Naeem, A. B., Rajwana, M. A., Bashir, M. Y. &amp; Senapati, B. Advancements in ai-guided analysis of cough sounds for covid-19 screening: A comprehensive review. J. Comput. Biomed. Inform. 5, 105–117 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alafif, T., Tehame, A. M., Bajaba, S., Barnawi, A. &amp; Zia, S. Machine and deep learning towards covid-19 diagnosis and treatment: Survey, challenges, and future directions. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 18, 1117 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7908539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33513984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, Y., Carl, O., Hussain, S., Hou, W. &amp; Weis, T. A privacy-protecting step-level walking direction detection algorithm based on floor vibration. IEEE Sens. J. (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sen, S., Saha, S., Chatterjee, S., Mirjalili, S. &amp; Sarkar, R. A bi-stage feature selection approach for covid-19 prediction using chest ct images. Appl. Intell. 51, 8985–9000 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8053442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34764594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdoğan, Y. E. &amp; Narin, A. Covid-19 detection with traditional and deep features on cough acoustic signals. Comput. Biol. Med. 136, 104765 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8364172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34416571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hemdan, E. E.-D., El-Shafai, W. &amp; Sayed, A. Cr19: A framework for preliminary detection of covid-19 in cough audio signals using machine learning algorithms for automated medical diagnosis applications. J. Ambient Intell. Hum. Comput. 1–13 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8803577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35126765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pahar, M., Klopper, M., Warren, R. &amp; Niesler, T. Covid-19 detection in cough, breath and speech using deep transfer learning and bottleneck features. Comput. Biol. Med. 141, 105153 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8679499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34954610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laguarta, J., Hueto, F. &amp; Subirana, B. Covid-19 artificial intelligence diagnosis using only cough recordings. IEEE Open J. Eng. Med. Biol. 1, 275–281 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8545024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34812418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, N. et al. Coswara: A database of breathing, cough, and voice sounds for covid-19 diagnosis. arXiv preprint[SPACE]arXiv:2005.10548 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mouawad, P., Dubnov, T. &amp; Dubnov, S. Robust detection of covid-19 in cough sounds: Using recurrence dynamics and variable Markov model. SN Comput. Sci. 2, 34 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7802616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33458700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pal, A. &amp; Sankarasubbu, M. Pay attention to the cough: Early diagnosis of covid-19 using interpretable symptoms embeddings with cough sound signal processing. In Proceedings of the 36th Annual ACM Symposium on Applied Computing 620–628 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imran, A. et al. Ai4covid-19: Ai enabled preliminary diagnosis for covid-19 from cough samples via an app. Inform. Med. Unlock. 20, 100378 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7318970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta, R., Krishna, T. A. &amp; Adeeb, M. Cough sound based covid-19 detection with stacked ensemble model. In 2022 4th International Conference on Smart Systems and Inventive Technology (ICSSIT) 1391–1395. 10.1109/ICSSIT53264.2022.9716373 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melek Manshouri, N. Identifying covid-19 by using spectral analysis of cough recordings: A distinctive classification study. Cognit. Neurodyn. 16, 239–253 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8320312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34341676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shekhar, K., Chittaragi, N. B. &amp; Koolagudi, S. G. Automatic diagnosis of covid-19 related respiratory diseases from speech. Multimed. Tools Appl. 1–16 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10050801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37362694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malviya, A., Dixit, R., Shukla, A. &amp; Kushwaha, N. Long short-term memory-based deep learning model for covid-19 detection using coughing sound. SN Comput. Sci. 4, 505 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamidi, M., Zealouk, O., Satori, H., Laaidi, N. &amp; Salek, A. Covid-19 assessment using hmm cough recognition system. Int. J. Inf. Technol. 15, 193–201 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9595586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36313860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulukaya, S., Sarıca, A. A., Erdem, O. &amp; Karaali, A. Msccov19net: Multi-branch deep learning model for covid-19 detection from cough sounds. Med. Biol. Eng. Comput. 1–11 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9955529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36828944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan, A., Shahin, I. &amp; Alsabek, M. B. Covid-19 detection system using recurrent neural networks. In 2020 International Conference on Communications, Computing, Cybersecurity, and Informatics (CCCI) 1–5 (IEEE, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loey, M. &amp; Mirjalili, S. Covid-19 cough sound symptoms classification from scalogram image representation using deep learning models. Comput. Biol. Med. 139, 105020 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8628520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34775155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bukhari, N., Hussain, S., Ayoub, M., Yu, Y. &amp; Khan, A. Deep learning based framework for emotion recognition using facial expression. Pak. J. Eng. Technol. 5, 51–57 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leng, L. &amp; Zhang, J. Palmhash code vs. palmphasor code. Neurocomputing 108, 1–12 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leng, L., Li, M., Kim, C. &amp; Bi, X. Dual-source discrimination power analysis for multi-instance contactless palmprint recognition. Multimed. Tools Appl. 76, 333–354 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leng, L., Li, M. &amp; Teoh, A. B. J. Conjugate 2dpalmhash code for secure palm-print-vein verification. In 2013 6th International congress on image and signal processing (CISP) Vol. 3 1705–1710 (IEEE, 2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pancaldi, F. et al. Vector: An algorithm for the detection of covid-19 pneumonia from velcro-like lung sounds. Comput. Biol. Med. 142, 105220 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8734059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35030495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bensid, K., Lati, A., Benlamoudi, A., Ghouar, B. E. &amp; Senoussi, M. L. Efficient covid-19 disease diagnosis based on cough signal processing and supervised machine learning. Diagnostyka 24 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trivedy, S., Goyal, M., Mohapatra, P. R. &amp; Mukherjee, A. Design and development of smartphone-enabled spirometer with a disease classification system using convolutional neural network. IEEE Trans. Instrum. Meas. 69, 7125–7135 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreu-Perez, J. et al. A generic deep learning based cough analysis system from clinically validated samples for point-of-need covid-19 test and severity levels. IEEE Trans. Serv. Comput. 15, 1220–1232 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9328729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35936760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant, D., McLane, I. &amp; West, J. Rapid and scalable covid-19 screening using speech, breath, and cough recordings. In 2021 IEEE EMBS International Conference on Biomedical and Health Informatics (BHI) 1–6 (IEEE, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deshpande, G., Batliner, A. &amp; Schuller, B. W. Ai-based human audio processing for covid-19: A comprehensive overview. Pattern Recognit. 122, 108289 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8404390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34483372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orlandic, L., Teijeiro, T. &amp; Atienza, D. The coughvid crowdsourcing dataset, a corpus for the study of large-scale cough analysis algorithms. Sci. Data 8, 156 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8222356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34162883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coppock, H. et al. End-to-end convolutional neural network enables covid-19 detection from breath and cough audio: A pilot study. BMJ Innov. 7 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34192022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuller, B. W. et al. The interspeech 2021 computational paralinguistics challenge: Covid-19 cough, covid-19 speech, escalation &amp; primates. arXiv preprint[SPACE]arXiv:2102.13468 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chawla, N. V., Bowyer, K. W., Hall, L. O. &amp; Kegelmeyer, W. P. Smote: Synthetic minority over-sampling technique. J. Artif. Intell. Res. 16, 321–357 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Zarzà, I., de Curtò, J. &amp; Calafate, C. T. Optimizing neural networks for imbalanced data. Electronics[SPACE]10.3390/electronics12122674 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brinkmann, F. &amp; Weinzierl, S. Comparison of head-related transfer functions pre-processing techniques for spherical harmonics decomposition. In Audio Engineering Society Conference: 2018 AES International Conference on Audio for Virtual and Augmented Reality (Audio Engineering Society, 2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McFee, B. et al. librosa: Audio and music signal analysis in python. In Proceedings of the 14th Python in Science Conference Vol. 8 18–25 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wyatt, H. &amp; Amyes, T. Audio Post Production for Television and Film: An Introduction to Technology and Techniques (Taylor &amp; Francis, 2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belkacem, A. N., Ouhbi, S., Lakas, A., Benkhelifa, E. &amp; Chen, C. End-to-end ai-based point-of-care diagnosis system for classifying respiratory illnesses and early detection of covid-19: a theoretical framework. Front. Med. 8, 585578 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8044874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33869239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, T., Nadarajan, A., Vaz, C., Booth, B. &amp; Narayanan, S. Tiles audio recorder: An unobtrusive wearable solution to track audio activity. In Proceedings of the 4th ACM Workshop on Wearable Systems and Applications 33–38 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartusiak, E. R. &amp; Delp, E. J. Frequency domain-based detection of generated audio. arXiv preprint[SPACE]arXiv:2205.01806 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, G., Umapathy, K. &amp; Krishnan, S. Trends in audio signal feature extraction methods. Appl. Acoust. 158, 107020 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kavitha, S. &amp; Manikandan, J. Improved methodology of svm to classify acoustic signal by spectral centroid. J. Trends Comput. Sci. Smart Technol. 3, 294–304 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, D.-N., Lu, L., Zhang, H.-J., Tao, J.-H. &amp; Cai, L.-H. Music type classification by spectral contrast feature. In Proceedings. IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo Vol. 1 113–116 (IEEE, 2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazaro, A., Sarno, R., Andre, R. J. &amp; Mahardika, M. N. Music tempo classification using audio spectrum centroid, audio spectrum flatness, and audio spectrum spread based on mpeg-7 audio features. In 2017 3rd International Conference on Science in Information Technology (ICSITech) 41–46 (IEEE, 2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, Y. &amp; Nishihara, A. Efficient voice activity detection algorithm using long-term spectral flatness measure. EURASIP J. Audio Speech Music Process. 2013, 1–18 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kos, M., Kačič, Z. &amp; Vlaj, D. Acoustic classification and segmentation using modified spectral roll-off and variance-based features. Digit. Signal Process. 23, 659–674 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramashini, M., Abas, P. E., Mohanchandra, K. &amp; De Silva, L. C. Robust cepstral feature for bird sound classification. Int. J. Electr. Comput. Eng. 12, 1477 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puspitasari, R. D. I., Wintarti, A. &amp; Imah, E. M. Comparison of feature extraction for noise-robust gamelan tone signal recognition. Procedia Comput. Sci. 216, 698–705 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gondohanindijo, J., Noersasongko, E. et al. Multi-features audio extraction for speech emotion recognition based on deep learning. Int. J. Adv. Sci. Appl. 14 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistry, Y. D., Birajdar, G. K. &amp; Khodke, A. M. Time-frequency visual representation and texture features for audio applications: A comprehensive review, recent trends, and challenges. Multimedia Tools and Applications 1–35 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mcuba, M., Singh, A., Ikuesan, R. A. &amp; Venter, H. The effect of deep learning methods on deepfake audio detection for digital investigation. Procedia Comput. Sci. 219, 211–219 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magai, G., Polevoi, A., Shanin, I. &amp; Sorokin, K. Chordal embeddings based on topology of the tonal space. In Artificial Intelligence in Music, Sound, Art and Design: 12th International Conference, EvoMUSART 2023, Held as Part of EvoStar 2023, Brno, Czech Republic, April 12–14, 2023, Proceedings Vol. 13988 (Springer Nature, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunekar, P. R. et al. Audio feature extraction: Foreground and background audio separation using knn algorithm. Int. J. Sci. Res. Arch. 9, 269–276 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lahmiri, S., Tadj, C., Gargour, C. &amp; Bekiros, S. Optimal tuning of support vector machines and k-nn algorithm by using bayesian optimization for newborn cry signal diagnosis based on audio signal processing features. Chaos Solitons Fractals 167, 112972 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kihal, M. &amp; Hamza, L. Robust multimedia spam filtering based on visual, textual, and audio deep features and random forest. Multimedia Tools and Applications 1–19 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angelucci, S., Rinaldi, C., Franchi, F. &amp; Graziosi, F. Comparison of ml solutions for hrir individualization design in binaural audio. In International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications 271–278 (Springer, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahid, J. A. et al. A hybrid resnet-vit approach to bridge the global and local features for myocardial infarction detection. Sci. Rep. 14, 4359 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10883929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38388668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain, S., Wahid, J. A., Ayoub, M., Tong, H. &amp; Rehman, R. Automated segmentation of coronary arteries using attention-gated unet for precise diagnosis. Pak. J. Sci. Res. 3, 124–129 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain, S. et al. Ensemble deep learning framework for situational aspects-based annotation and classification of international student’s tweets during covid-19. Comput. Mater. Continua 75 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, Y., Qin, X., Hussain, S., Hou, W. &amp; Weis, T. Pedestrian counting based on piezoelectric vibration sensor. Appl. Sci. 12, 1920 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain, S. et al. Aspect2labels: A novelistic decision support system for higher educational institutions by using multi-layer topic modelling approach. Expert Syst. Appl. 209, 118119 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amodeo, L., Wiersema, J. R., Brass, M. &amp; Nijhof, A. D. A comparison of self-bias measures across cognitive domains. BMC Psychol. 9, 1–15 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8414869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34479639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>