<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39446926</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Wearable neurofeedback acceptance model for students' stress and anxiety management in academic settings.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0304932</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0304932</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0304932</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0304932</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study investigates the technology acceptance of a proposed multimodal wearable sensing framework, named mSense, within the context of non-invasive real-time neurofeedback for student stress and anxiety management. The COVID-19 pandemic has intensified mental health challenges, particularly for students. Non-invasive techniques, such as wearable biofeedback and neurofeedback devices, are suggested as potential solutions. To explore the acceptance and intention to use such innovative devices, this research applies the Technology Acceptance Model (TAM), based on the co-creation approach. An online survey was conducted with 106 participants, including higher education students, health researchers, medical professionals, and software developers. The TAM key constructs (usage attitude, perceived usefulness, perceived ease of use, and intention to use) were validated through statistical analysis, including Partial Least Square-Structural Equation Modeling. Additionally, qualitative analysis of open-ended survey responses was performed. Results confirm the acceptance of the mSense framework for neurofeedback-based stress and anxiety management. The study contributes valuable insights into factors influencing user intention to use multimodal wearable devices in educational settings. The findings have theoretical implications for technology acceptance and practical implications for extending the usage of innovative sensors in clinical and educational environments, thereby supporting both physical and mental health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Dias et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dias</LastName><ForeName>Sofia B</ForeName><Initials>SB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8239-583X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Interdisciplinary Centre for the Study of Human Performance (CIPER), Faculdade de Motricidade Humana, Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jelinek</LastName><ForeName>Herbert F</ForeName><Initials>HF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Sciences, Khalifa University of Science and Technology, Abu Dhabi, UAE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hadjileontiadis</LastName><ForeName>Leontios J</ForeName><Initials>LJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering and Biotechnology; Healthcare Engineering Innovation Group (HEIG), Khalifa University of Science and Technology, Abu Dhabi, UAE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058765" MajorTopicYN="Y">Neurofeedback</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000076251" MajorTopicYN="Y">Wearable Electronic Devices</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013315" MajorTopicYN="Y">Stress, Psychological</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001007" MajorTopicYN="Y">Anxiety</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11501020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-24-19965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. World Mental Health Report: Transforming Mental Health for all. Geneva: WHO; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auerbach RP, Mortier P, Bruffaerts R, Alonso J, Benjet C, Cuijpers P, et al..; WHO WMH‐ICS Collaborators. Mental disorder comorbidity and suicidal thoughts and behaviors in the world health organization world mental health surveys international college student initiative. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2019;28(2):e1752.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6877246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30450753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quek TC, Tam WS, Tran BX, Zhang M, Zhang Z, Ho SH, et al.. The global prevalence of anxiety among medical students: a meta-analysis. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(15):2735. doi: 10.3390/ijerph16152735</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph16152735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6696211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31370266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastien L, Boke BN, Mettler J, Zito S, Di Genova L, Romano V, et al.. Peer-Presented Versus Mental Health Service Provider–Presented Mental Health Outreach Programs for University Students: Randomized Controlled Trial. JMIR Ment Health. 2022;9(7):e34168. doi: 10.2196/34168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/34168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9356327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35762935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steel Z, Marnane C, Iranpour C, Chey T, Jackson JW, Patel V, et al.. The global prevalence of common mental disorders: A systematic review and meta-analysis 1980–2013. Int J Epidemiol. 2014;43(2):476–493. doi: 10.1093/ije/dyu038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ije/dyu038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3997379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24648481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yahia M. Dealing with mental illness in the Middle East. Nature Middle East. Available from: https://www.natureasia.com/en/nmiddleeast/article/10.1038/nmiddleeast.2012.103. Accessed Sept 1st, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nmiddleeast.2012.103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Gelban KS, Al-Amri HS, Mostafa OA. Prevalence of depression, anxiety and stress as measured by the depression, anxiety, and stress scale (DASS-42) among secondary school girls in Abha, Saudi Arabia. Sultan Qaboos Univ Med J. 2009;9(2):140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3074779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21509290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Marzouqi AM, Otim ME, Alblooshi A, Al Marzooqi S, Talal M, Wassim F. State of Emotional Health Disorders of Undergraduate Students in the United Arab Emirates: A Cross-Sectional Survey. Psychol Res Behav Manag. 2022;15:1423–1433. doi: 10.2147/PRBM.S365012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/PRBM.S365012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9188331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35698566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Storrie K, Ahern K, Tuckett A. A systematic review: students with mental health problems—a growing problem. Int J Nurs Pract. 2010;16(1):1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20158541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wathelet M, Duhem S, Vaiva G, Baubet T, Habran E, Veerapa E, et al.. Factors Associated with Mental Health Disorders Among University Students in France Confined During the COVID-19 Pandemic. JAMA Netw Open. 2020;3:e2025591. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.25591</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.25591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7584927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33095252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liyanage S, Saqib K, Khan AF, Thobani TR, Tang WC, Chiarot CB, et al.. Prevalence of Anxiety in University Students during the COVID-19 Pandemic: A Systematic Review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8750929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35010323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alshammari TK, Alkhodair AM, Alhebshi HA, Rogowska AM, Albaker AB, et al.. Examining Anxiety, Sleep Quality, and Physical Activity as Predictors of Depression among University Students from Saudi Arabia during the Second Wave of the COVID-19 Pandemic. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:6262. doi: 10.3390/ijerph19106262</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19106262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9141415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35627799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Z, Zhao J, Li Y, Chen D, Wang T, Zhang Z, et al.. Mental health problems and correlates among 746,217 college students during the coronavirus disease 2019 outbreak in China. Epidemiol Psychiatr Sci. 2020;29:e181. doi: 10.1017/S2045796020000931</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S2045796020000931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7681173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33185174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ochnik D, Rogowska AM, Küsnierz C, Jakubiak M, Schütz A, Held MJ, et al.. Mental health prevalence and predictors among university students in nine countries during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-national study. Sci Rep. 2021;11:18644. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-97697-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-97697-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8452732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34545120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Son C, Hegde S, Smith A, Wang X, Sasangohar F. Effects of COVID-19 on college students’ mental health in the United States: Interview survey study. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22(9):e21279. doi: 10.2196/21279</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/21279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7473764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32805704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carr E, Davis K, Bergin-Cartwright G, Lavelle G, Leightley D, Oetzmann C, et al.. Mental health among UK university staff and postgraduate students in the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic. Occup Environ Med. 2021;79:259–267. doi: 10.1136/oemed-2021-107667</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/oemed-2021-107667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34675129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen T, Lucock M. The mental health of university students during the COVID-19 pandemic: An online survey in the UK. PLoS One. 2022;17:e0262562. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0262562</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0262562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8754313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35020758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saddik B, Hussein A, Sharif-Askari FS, Kheder W, Temsah MH, Koutaich RA, et al.. Increased levels of anxiety among medical and non-medical university students during the COVID-19 pandemic in the United Arab Emirates. Risk Manag Healthc Policy. 2020;13:2395. doi: 10.2147/RMHP.S273333</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/RMHP.S273333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7652570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33177898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saito T, Suzuki H, Kishi A. Predictive modeling of mental illness onset using wearable devices and medical examination data: Machine learning approach. Front Digit Health. 2022;4:861808. doi: 10.3389/fdgth.2022.861808</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2022.861808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9046696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35493532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fonseka LN, Woo BK. Wearables in schizophrenia: Update on current and future clinical applications. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2022;10(4):e35600. doi: 10.2196/35600</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/35600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9030897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35389361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soleymani M, Riegler M, Halvorsen P. Multimodal analysis of image search intent: Intent recognition in image search from user behavior and visual content. Proc ACM Int Conf Multimedia Retr. 2017;pp. 251–259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Ceja E, Riegler M, Nordgreen T, Jakobsen P, Oedegaard KJ, Tørresen J. Mental health monitoring with multimodal sensing and machine learning: A survey. Pervasive Mobile Comput. 2018;51:1–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasrat SA, et al.. Emotion recognition in the wild from long-term heart rate recording using wearable sensor and deep learning ensemble classification. Proc IEEE Int Conf Bioinformatics Biomed. 2021;pp. 1676–1678.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimenez-Molina A, Retamal C, Lira H. Using psychophysiological sensors to assess mental workload during web browsing. Sensors. 2018;18:458. doi: 10.3390/s18020458</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s18020458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5855035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29401688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posada-Quintero HF, Bolkhovsky JB. Machine learning models for the identification of cognitive tasks using autonomic reactions from heart rate variability and electrodermal activity. Behav Sci. 2019;9:45. doi: 10.3390/bs9040045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bs9040045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6523197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31027251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto G, Carvalho JM, Barros F, Soares SC, Pinho AJ, Brás S. Multimodal emotion evaluation: A physiological model for cost-effective emotion classification. Sensors. 2020;20:3515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7349550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32575894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee S, Lee T, Yang T, Yoon C, Kim SP. Detection of drivers’ anxiety invoked by driving situations using multimodal biosignals. Processes. 2020;8:155.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alskafi F, Khandoker AH, Jelinek HF. A comparative study of arousal and valence dimensional variations for emotion recognition using peripheral physiological signals acquired from wearable sensors. Proc EMBC. 2021;pp. 1104–1107. doi: 10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9630759</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9630759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34891480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Abbod M, Shieh JS. Pain and stress detection using wearable sensors and devices—A review. Sensors. 2021;21:1030. doi: 10.3390/s21041030</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s21041030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7913347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33546235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Betti S, Lova RM, Rovini E, Acerbi G, Santarelli L, Cabiati M, et al.. Evaluation of an integrated system of wearable physiological sensors for stress monitoring in working environments by using biological markers. IEEE Trans Biomed Eng. 2028;65:1748–1758.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29989933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pourmohammadi S, Maleki A. Stress detection using ECG and EMG signals: A comprehensive study. Comput Methods Programs Biomed. 2020;193:105482. doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2020.105482</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2020.105482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32408236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muaremi A, Arnrich B, Tröster G. Towards measuring stress with smartphones and wearable devices during workday and sleep. Bionanoscience. 2013;3:172–183. doi: 10.1007/s12668-013-0089-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12668-013-0089-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4269214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25530929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakajima M, Lemieux AM, Fiecas M, Chatterjee S, Sarker H, Saleheen N, et al.. Using novel mobile sensors to assess stress and smoking lapse. Int J Psychophysiol. 2020;158:411–418. doi: 10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2020.11.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2020.11.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9195636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33189770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beck JS. Cognitive behavior therapy: Basics and beyond. Guilford Publications; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cash M, Whittingham K. What facets of mindfulness contribute to psychological well-being and depressive, anxious, and stress-related symptomatology? Mindfulness. 2010;1(3):177–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amanvermez Y, Rahmadiana M, Karyotaki E, de Wit L, Ebert DD, Kessler RC, et al.. Stress management interventions for college students: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Psychol Sci Pract. doi: 10.1111/cpsp.12342</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cpsp.12342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8861419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35242591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walkowiak H. EEG biofeedback: Characteristics, application, opinions of specialists. Poznań: Adam Mickiewicz University Press; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwak M, Zaczyk I, Wilczek-Ruzyczka E. Stress and ways of coping with it by Polish nurses–a meta-analysis of research. Med Og Nauki Zdr. 2018;24(2):120–125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morr M, Lieberz J, Dobbelstein M, Philipsen A, Hurlemann R, Scheele D. Insula reactivity mediates subjective isolation stress in alexithymia. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1). doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-94799-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-94799-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8319294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34321519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Schießl J, Plößl L, Hofmann F, Gläser-Zikuda M. Acceptance of artificial intelligence among pre-service teachers: A multigroup analysis. Int J Educ Technol High Educ. 2023;20:49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Y, Yu Z. Extending Technology Acceptance Model to higher-education students’ use of digital academic reading tools on computers. Int J Educ Technol High Educ. 2023;20:34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noble SM, Saville JD, Foster LL. VR as a choice: What drives learners’ technology acceptance? Int J Educ Technol High Educ. 2022;19:6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis FD. Perceived usefulness, perceived ease of use, and user acceptance of information technology. MIS quarterly. 1989;319–340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ajzen I. The Theory of Planned Behavior. Organ Behav Hum Decis Process. 1991;50(2):179–211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers EM. Diffusion of Innovations. New York, NY: Free Press; 1995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandura A. Social foundations of thought and action: A social cognitive theory. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall; 1986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huarng K-H, Yu THK, Fang Lee C. Adoption model of healthcare wearable devices. Technol Forecast Soc Change. 2022;174:121286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesh V, Thong J, Xu X. Unified Theory of Acceptance and Use of Technology: A Synthesis and the Road Ahead. J Assoc Inf Syst. 2016;17(5):328–376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dias SB, Oikonomidis Y, Diniz JA, Baptista F, Carnide F, Bensenousi A, et al.. Users’ Perspective on the AI-Based Smartphone PROTEIN App for Personalized Nutrition and Healthy Living: A Modified Technology Acceptance Model (mTAM) Approach. Front Nutr. 2022;9. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2022.898031</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.898031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9307489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35879982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu X, Zhang J, He S, Zhu R, Shen S, Liu B. E-learning intention of students with anxiety: Evidence from the first wave of COVID-19 pandemic in China. J Affect Disord. 2022;309:115–122. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2022.04.121</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.04.121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9033630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35472479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong H, Bayro A, Umesh SP, Mamgain K, Lee M. A Perspective of COVID-19 and Healthcare: Using Social Media Data and an Aspect-based Sentiment Analysis for Usability Evaluation of a Wearable Mixed Reality Headset. JMIR Serious Games. 2022;10(3):e36850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9359310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35708916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buck B, Nguyen J, Porter S, Ben-Zeev D, Reger GM. FOCUS mHealth Intervention for Veterans with Serious Mental Illness in an Outpatient Department of Veterans Affairs Setting: Feasibility, Acceptability, and Usability Study. JMIR Ment Health. 2022;9(1):e26049. doi: 10.2196/26049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/26049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8838564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35089151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez-Valero E, Vaquero-Blasco MA, Lopez-Gordo MA, Morillas C. Quantitative assessment of stress through EEG during a virtual reality stress-relax session. Front Comput Neurosci. 2021;15:684423. doi: 10.3389/fncom.2021.684423</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fncom.2021.684423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8317646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34335216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni N, Phalle S, Desale M, Gokhale N, Kasture K. A review on EEG based stress monitoring system using deep learning approach. Mukt Shabd J. 2020;9(6):1317–1325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schaal NK, Hepp P, Schweda A, Wolf OT, Krampe C. A functional near-infrared spectroscopy study on the cortical haemodynamic responses during the Maastricht acute stress test. Sci Rep. 2019;9(1):13459. doi: 10.1038/s41598-019-49826-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-49826-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6748987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31530845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goumopoulos C, Menti E. Stress Detection in Seniors Using Biosensors and Psychometric Tests. Procedia Comput Sci. 2019;152:18–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B, Morère Y, Sieler L, Langlet C, Bolmont B, Bourhis G. Stress Recognition from Heterogeneous Data. J Image Graphics. 2016;4(2):116–121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oka T, Oka K, Hori T. Mechanisms and mediators of psychological stress-induced rise in core temperature. Psychosom Med. 2001;63(3):476–486. doi: 10.1097/00006842-200105000-00018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00006842-200105000-00018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11382276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem S, Khandoker AH, Alkhodari M, Hadjileontiadis LJ, Jelinek HF. A two-step pre-processing tool to remove Gaussian and ectopic noise for heart rate variability analysis. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):18396. doi: 10.1038/s41598-022-21776-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-21776-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9626590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36319659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyvärinen A. Independent component analysis: recent advances. Philos Trans A Math Phys Eng Sci. 2012;371(1984):20110534. doi: 10.1098/rsta.2011.0534</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsta.2011.0534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3538438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23277597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thannoon HH, Hashim IA. Efficient enhanced Recursive Least Square algorithm adaptive filtering scheme for artifacts removal in ECG signals. e-Prime-Advances in Electrical Engineering, Electronics and Energy. 2023;6:100318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashida M, Habib MA. Feature Extraction from Regenerated EEG–A better approach for ICA based eye blink artifact detection. Frontiers in Biomedical Technologies. 2024;11(2):199–206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ladakis I, Chouvarda I. Overview of biosignal analysis methods for the assessment of stress. Emerg Sci J. 2021;5(2):233–244.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katmah R, Al-Shargie F, Tariq U, Babiloni F, Al-Mughairbi F, Al-Nashash H. A review on mental stress assessment methods using EEG signals. Sensors. 2021;21(15):5043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8347831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34372280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mallat SG. A theory for multiresolution signal decomposition: the wavelet representation. IEEE Trans Pattern Anal Mach Intell. 1989;11(7):674–693.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang NE, Shen Z, Long SR, Wu MC, Shih HH, Zheng Q, et al.. The empirical mode decomposition and the Hilbert spectrum for nonlinear and non-stationary time series analysis. Proc R Soc Lond Ser A Math Phys Eng Sci. 1998;454(1971):903–995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dragomiretskiy K, Zosso D. Variational mode decomposition. IEEE Trans Signal Process. 2013;62(3):531–544.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apostolidis GK, Hadjileontiadis LJ. Swarm decomposition: A novel signal analysis using swarm intelligence. Signal Process. 2017;132:40–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alfalahi H, Khandoker A, Alhussein G, Hadjileontiadis LJ. Cochlear Decomposition: A novel bio-inspired multiscale analysis framework. Proc IEEE ICASSP 2023, Int Conf Acoust Speech Signal Process (ICASSP). 2023;pp. 1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shatte AB, Hutchinson DM, Teague SJ. Machine learning in mental health: A scoping review of methods and applications. Psychol Med. 2019;49(9):1426–1448. doi: 10.1017/S0033291719000151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0033291719000151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30744717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AR SB, Nagaveni V. Bio-Signal Analysis for Stress Detection Using Machine Learning Methods: A Review. Proc 2020 Int Conf Smart Technol Comput Electr Electron (ICSTCEE). IEEE. 2020;pp. 452–458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ancillon L, Elgendi M, Menon C. Machine learning for anxiety detection using biosignals: A review. Diagnostics. 2022;12(8):1794. doi: 10.3390/diagnostics12081794</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/diagnostics12081794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9332282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35892505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gil-Martin M, San-Segundo R, Mateos A, Ferreiros-Lopez J. Human stress detection with wearable sensors using convolutional neural networks. IEEE Aerosp Electron Syst Mag. 2022;37(1):60–70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekruksavanich S, Hnoohom N, Jitpattanakul A. A Deep Residual-based Model on Multi-Branch Aggregation for Stress and Emotion Recognition through Biosignals. Proc 2022 19th Int Conf Electr Eng/Electron, Comput, Telecommun Inf Technol (ECTI-CON) IEEE. 2022;pp. 1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poria S, Cambria E, Bajpai R, Hussain A. A review of affective computing: From unimodal analysis to multimodal fusion. Inf Fusion. 2017;37:98–125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Arce J, Lara-Flores L, Portillo-Rodríguez O, Martínez-Méndez R. Towards an anxiety and stress recognition system for academic environments based on physiological features. Comput Methods Programs Biomed. 2020;190:105408. doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2020.105408</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2020.105408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32139112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaume A, Vialatte A, Mora-Sánchez A, Ramdani C, Vialatte FB. A psychoengineering paradigm for the neurocognitive mechanisms of biofeedback and neurofeedback. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2016;68:891–910. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2016.06.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2016.06.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27339691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik K, Dua A. Biofeedback. [Updated 2022 Sep 26]. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023. 
Jan-. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK553075/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weibel RP, Kerr JI, Naegelin M, Ferrario A, Schinazi VR, La Marca R, et al.. Virtual reality-supported biofeedback for stress management: Beneficial effects on heart rate variability and user experience. Comput Human Behav. 2023;141:107607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang H, Yu J, Zo H, Choi M. User acceptance of wearable devices: An extended perspective of perceived value. Telematics Inform. 2016;33(2):256–269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis FD, Bagozzi RP, Warshaw PR. User acceptance of computer technology: A comparison of two theoretical models. Manag Sci. 1989;35:9821003. doi: 10.1287/mnsc.35.8.982</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1287/mnsc.35.8.982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holden R, Karsh BT. The Technology Acceptance Model: Its past and its future in health care. J Biomed Inform. 2010;43:159–172. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2009.07.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2009.07.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2814963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19615467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farivar S, Abouzahra M, Ghasemaghaei M. Wearable device adoption among older adults: A mixed-methods study. Int J Inf Manage. 2020;55:102209. doi: 10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2020.102209</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2020.102209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7402656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rauschnabel PA, He J, Ro YK. Antecedents to the adoption of augmented reality smart glasses: A closer look at privacy risks. J Bus Res. 2018;92:374–384.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Dijk-de Vries A, Stevens A, van der Weijden T, Beurskens AJHM. How to support a co-creative research approach in order to foster impact. The development of a Co-creation impact compass for healthcare researchers. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(10):e0240543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7549764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33045033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed AHH, Tawfik H, Al-Jumeily D, Norton L. MoHTAM: A technology acceptance model for mobile health applications. In: 2011 Developments in E-systems Engineering. IEEE; 2011. pp. 13–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cronbach LJ. Coefficient alpha and the internal structure of tests. Psychometrika. 1951;16(3):297–334.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dijkstra TK, Henseler J. Consistent partial least squares path modeling. MIS Q. 2015;39(2):297–316.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hair JF, Risher JJ, Sarstedt M, Ringle CM. When to use and how to report the results of PLS-SEM. Eur Bus Rev. 2019;31(1):2–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark LA, Watson DB. Constructing validity: Basic issues in objective scale development. Psychol Assess. 1995;7:309–319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hair JF, Hult GTM, Ringle CM, Sarstedt M. A primer on partial least squares structural equation modeling (PLS-SEM). 3rd ed. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibbs GR. Thematic coding and categorizing. Analyzing qualitative data. 2007;703:38–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesh V, Morris MG, Davis GB, Davis FD. User acceptance of information technology: Toward a unified view. MIS Q. 2003;425–478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Chung T, Den Yeoh E. A Hybrid SEM-ANN Approach for Intention to Adopt Metaverse Using C-TAM-TPB and IDT in China. In: Strategies and Opportunities for Technology in the Metaverse World. IGI Global; 2023. pp. 263–293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mardiana S, Tjakraatmadja JH, Aprianingsih A. DeLone–McLean information system success model revisited: The separation of intention to use-use and the integration of technology acceptance models. Int J Econ Financ Issues. 2015;5(1):172–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revythi A, Tselios N. Extension of technology acceptance model by using system usability scale to assess behavioral intention to use e-learning. Educ Inf Technol. 2019;24:2341–2355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panisoara IO, Lazar I, Panisoara G, Chirca R, Ursu AS. Motivation and continuance intention towards online instruction among teachers during the COVID-19 pandemic: The mediating effect of burnout and technostress. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(21):8002. doi: 10.3390/ijerph17218002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17218002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7672544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33143180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesh V, Davis FD. A theoretical extension of the technology acceptance model: Four longitudinal field studies. Manag Sci. 2000;46(2):186–204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estriegana R, Medina-Merodio JA, Barchino R. Student acceptance of virtual laboratory and practical work: An extension of the technology acceptance model. Comput Educ. 2019;135:1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang Y, Choi N, Kim S. Searching for new model of digital informatics for human–computer interaction: testing the Institution-Based Technology Acceptance Model (ITAM). Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(11):5593. doi: 10.3390/ijerph18115593</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18115593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8197211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34073786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An S, Eck T, Yim H. Understanding consumers’ acceptance intention to use mobile food delivery applications through an extended technology acceptance model. Sustainability. 2023;15(1):832.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad N, Abdulkarim H. The impact of flow experience and personality type on the intention to use virtual world. Int J Human–Computer Interaction. 2019;35(12):1074–1085.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salahshour Rad M, Nilashi M, Mohamed Dahlan H, Ibrahim O. Academic researchers’ behavioural intention to use academic social networking sites: A case of Malaysian research universities. Inf Dev. 2019;35(2):245–261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad S, Bhatti SH, Hwang Y. E-service quality and actual use of e-banking: Explanation through the Technology Acceptance Model. Inf Dev. 2020;36(4):503–519.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shuhaiber A, Mashal I. Understanding users’ acceptance of smart homes. Technol Soc. 2019;58:101110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q, Collet JP, Liu W, Lang X, Feng D, Ding F, et al.. Work-related stress and stress management practice among Chinese hospital staff working night shifts: A mixed-methods study. Int J Stress Manage. 2023. doi: 10.1037/str0000281</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/str0000281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelders SM, Kok RN, Ossebaard HC, Van Gemert-Pijnen JE. Persuasive system design does matter: a systematic review of adherence to web-based interventions. J Med Internet Res. 2012;14:e152. doi: 10.2196/jmir.2104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.2104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3510730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23151820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwon M-W, Mun K, Lee JK, Mcleod DM, D’angelo J. Is mobile health all peer pressure? The influence of mass media exposure on the motivation to use mobile health apps. Convergence. 2016;23:565–86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oinas-Kukkonen H. A Foundation for the Study of behavior change support systems. Pers Ubiquitous Comput. 2013;17:1223–1235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manz CC. Self-leadership: Toward an expanded theory of self-influence processes in organizations. Acad Manage Rev. 1986;11(3):585–600.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehrer C, Eseryel UY, Rieder A, et al.. Behavior change through wearables: the interplay between self-leadership and IT-based leadership. Electron Markets. 2021;31:747–764.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>James TL, Wallace L, Deane JK. Using organismic integration theory to explore the associations between Users’ exercise motivations and fitness technology feature set use. Manag Inf Syst Q. 2019;43(1):287–312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milne-Ives M, Lam C, De Cock C, Van Velthoven MH, Meinert E. Mobile apps for health behavior change in physical activity, diet, drug and alcohol use, and mental health: systematic review. JMIR mHealth uHealth. 2020;8:e17046. doi: 10.2196/17046</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/17046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7113799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32186518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghezzi D. Engineering Materials for Neurotechnology. Adv Eng Mater. 2023;2201412. doi: 10.1002/adem.202201412</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adem.202201412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schall MC, Sesek RF, Cavuoto LA. Barriers to the adoption of wearable sensors in the workplace: A survey of occupational safety and health professionals. J Hum Factors Ergon Soc. 2018;60(3):351–362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9307130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29320232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin D. The actualization of meta affordances: Conceptualizing affordance actualization in the metaverse games. Comput Human Behav. 2022;133:107292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell F, Blank L, Cantrell A, Baxter S, Blackmore C, Dixon J, et al.. Factors that influence mental health of university and college students in the UK: A systematic review. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1):1–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9484851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36123714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suhail TA, Vinod AP. Enhancing Overt and Covert Attention Using a Real-time Neurofeedback Game with Consumer-grade EEG. IEEE Trans Cogn Dev Syst. 2023. doi: 10.1109/TCDS.2023.3260441</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TCDS.2023.3260441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stinson B, Arthur D. A novel EEG for alpha brain state training, neurobiofeedback and behavior change. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2013;19(3):114–118. doi: 10.1016/j.ctcp.2013.03.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ctcp.2013.03.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23890456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinterberger T. The sensorium: a multimodal neurofeedback environment. In: Advances in Human-Computer Interaction. 2011:1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ates HC, Nguyen PQ, Gonzalez-Macia L, Morales-Narváez E, Güder F, Collins JJ, et al.. End-to-end design of wearable sensors. Nat Rev Mater. 2022;7(11):887–907. doi: 10.1038/s41578-022-00460-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41578-022-00460-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9306444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35910814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang YS, Lin HH, Luarn P. Predicting consumer intention to use mobile services. Inf Syst J. 2006;16(2):157–179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan GWH, Sim JJ, Ooi KB, Kongkiti P. Determinants of mobile learning adoption: An empirical analysis. J Comput Inform Syst. 2012;52(3):82–91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bewernick BH, Schlaepfer TE. Chronic depression as a model disease for cerebral aging. Dialogues Clin Neurosci. 2022;15(1):77–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3622471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23576891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song SH, Kim DK. Development of a stress classification model using deep belief networks for stress monitoring. Healthc Inform Res. 2017;23(4):285–292. doi: 10.4258/hir.2017.23.4.285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4258/hir.2017.23.4.285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5688028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29181238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heimerl A, Prajod P, Mertes S, Baur T, Kraus M, Liu A, et al.. ForDigitStress: A multi-modal stress dataset employing a digital job interview scenario. arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.07742.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-Alrazaq A, AlSaad R, Aziz S, Ahmed A, Denecke K, Househ M, et al.. Wearable Artificial Intelligence for Anxiety and Depression: Scoping Review. J Med Internet Res. 2023;25:e42672. doi: 10.2196/42672</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/42672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9896355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36656625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>