<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39443939</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6920</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC medical education</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Med Educ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Racial biases in clinical practice and medical education: a scoping review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1196</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1196</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1196</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12909-024-06119-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Health inequalities represent a major challenge in contemporary medicine, with some attributed to racial biases. Recently, in the United States, a call to combat discrimination in the field of health has resonated, particularly in the context of the COVID-19 crisis, in which minorities have been disproportionately affected. These calls echo recommendations from the Institute of Medicine dating back to 2001, urging the fight against inequalities in access to health care. In France, inequalities based on presumed origin persist, yet medical education on these issues is virtually nonexistent.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We conducted a scoping review literature review in accordance with the JBI recommendations for scoping review writing and applied the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA-ScR) checklist to explore existing conceptual and educational data on racial biases in medicine. The inclusion criteria were interventional studies or evaluations of existing educational programs in medical training addressing the fight against racial biases in clinical settings published in French or English between 2003 and 2023. Six databases were systematically consulted.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Out of 748 initial studies, 28 were included in our study. The median number of participants in the studies was low, interventions were diverse, and participants were generally well received, most of whom were self-selected. No study has evaluated the clinical impact of these interventions. The highlighted concepts included levels of racism, cultural competence, cultural humility, and critical race theory.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The authors most frequently referred to institutionalized racism, demonstrating the systemic nature of these issues. At an individual level, implicit and unconscious biases were most often emphasized. It appears that the concept of "race" is a sociopolitical construct without supporting biological determinants. Humility is central to this field of study, as it encourages questioning of individual or collective medical practices. In France, the context, including the prohibition of ethnic statistics, may hinder the objectification of discrimination. Immersion and virtual patient scenarios emerged as potential solutions for evaluating the clinical impact of interventions. A more horizontal medical pedagogy seems better suited to teach these sensitive issues.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mouhab</LastName><ForeName>Adil</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université des Antilles, Pointe-à-Pitre, Guadeloupe, France. adil.mouhab@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Radjack</LastName><ForeName>Rahmeth</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>APHP, Hôpital Cochin, Maison de Solenn, Paris, 75014, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris Cité, PCPP, Boulogne-Billancourt, 92100, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, UVSQ, Inserm, CESP, Team DevPsy, Villejuif, 94807, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moro</LastName><ForeName>Marie Rose</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>APHP, Hôpital Cochin, Maison de Solenn, Paris, 75014, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris Cité, PCPP, Boulogne-Billancourt, 92100, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, UVSQ, Inserm, CESP, Team DevPsy, Villejuif, 94807, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lambert</LastName><ForeName>Mathilde</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>APHP, Hôpital Cochin, Maison de Solenn, Paris, 75014, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris Cité, PCPP, Boulogne-Billancourt, 92100, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, UVSQ, Inserm, CESP, Team DevPsy, Villejuif, 94807, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Med Educ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088679</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6920</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D063505" MajorTopicYN="Y">Racism</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004501" MajorTopicYN="Y">Education, Medical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054625" MajorTopicYN="N">Healthcare Disparities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005602" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">France</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health inequities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Implicit bias</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Racism</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39443939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-024-06119-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12909-024-06119-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bailey ZD, Krieger N, Agénor M, Graves J, Linos N, Bassett MT. Structural racism and health inequities in the USA: evidence and interventions. Lancet 8 avr. 2017;389(10077):1453–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paradies Y, Ben J, Denson N, Elias A, Priest N, Pieterse A, et al. Racism as a determinant of health: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. PLoS ONE. sept 2015;23(9):e0138511.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tobin MJ. Fiftieth Anniversary of Uncovering the Tuskegee Syphilis Study: The Story and Timeless Lessons. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 15 mai. 2022;205(10):1145–58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on Understanding and Eliminating Racial and Ethnic Disparities in Health Care. Unequal Treatment: Confronting Racial and Ethnic Disparities in Health Care, Smedley BD, Stith AY, Nelson AR. éditeurs. Washington (DC): National Academies Press (US); 2003 [cité 30 août 2023]. Disponible sur: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK220358/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaya S, Yeboah H, Charles CH, Otu A, Labonte R. Ethnic and racial disparities in COVID-19-related deaths: counting the trees, hiding the forest. BMJ Glob Health juin. 2020;5(6):e002913.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beauchemin C, Hamel C, Simon P, Trajectoires. et origines: Enquête sur la diversité des populations en France. Ined Éditions; 2016 [cité 13 août 2023]. Disponible sur: https://books.openedition.org/ined/https://books.openedition.org/ined/676</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Legha RK, Richards M, Kataoka SH. Foundations in racism: a novel and contemporary curriculum for child and adolescent psychiatry fellows. Acad Psychiatry févr. 2021;45(1):61–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guh J, Krinsky L, White-Davis T, Sethi T, Hayon R, Edgoose J. Teaching racial Affinity Caucusing as a Tool to learn about racial Health Inequity through an Experiential Workshop. FAMILY Med oct. 2020;52(9):656–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jindal M, Thornton RLJ, McRae A, Unaka N, Johnson TJ, Mistry KB. Effects of a curriculum addressing racism on Pediatric residents’ racial biases and Empathy. J Grad Med Educ août. 2022;14(4):407–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Ryn M, Hardeman R, Phelan SM, Burgess DJ, Dovidio JF, Herrin J, et al. Medical School Experiences Associated with change in implicit racial Bias among 3547 students: A Medical Student CHANGES Study Report. J Gen Intern Med déc. 2015;30(12):1748–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis D, Tran-Taylor D, Imbert E, Wong J, Chou C. Start the Way you want to Finish: an intensive diversity, equity, inclusion orientation curriculum in Undergraduate Medical Education. Journal of medical education and curricular development. mars 2021;8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Godley B, Dayal D, Manekin E, Estroff S. Toward an anti-racist curriculum: incorporating art into Medical Education to Improve Empathy and Structural Competency. Journal of medical education and curricular development. oct 2020;7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DallaPiazza M, Padilla-Register M, Dwarakanath M, Obamedo E, Hill J, Soto-Greene ML. Exploring Racism and Health: An Intensive Interactive Session for Medical Students. MedEdPORTAL. 14 déc. 2018;14:10783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reliford A, Berry OO, Burgos JJ, Liaw KRL. Holding space for facilitated dialogues on antiracism in academic medicine. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry août. 2022;61(8):953–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crampton P, Dowell A, Parkin C, Thompson C. Combating effects of Racism through a Cultural Immersion Medical Education Program. Acad Med juin. 2003;78(6):595–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lypson ML, Ross PT, Kumagai AK. Medical students’ perspectives on a multicultural curriculum. J Natl Med Association sept. 2008;100(9):1078–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garrison CB, McKinney-Whitson V, Johnston B, Munroe A. Race matters: addressing racism as a health issue. Int J Psychiatry Med Nov. 2018;53(5–6):436–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnston B, McKinney-Whitson V, Garrison V. Race matters: addressing racism as a Health Issue. WMJ mars. 2021;120(S1):S74–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White-Davis T, Edgoose J, Brown Speights JS, Fraser K, Ring JM, Guh J, et al. Addressing racism in Medical Education An Interactive Training Module. Fam Med mai. 2018;50(5):364–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roswell RO, Cogburn CD, Tocco J, Martinez J, Bangeranye C, Bailenson JN, et al. Cultivating Empathy through virtual reality: advancing conversations about Racism, Inequity, and Climate in Medicine. Acad Med déc. 2020;95(12):1882–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Leeuw S, Larstone R, Fell B, Cross N, Greenwood M, Auerbach K, et al. Educating medical students’ « hearts and minds »: a humanities- informed Cultural Immersion Program in Indigenous Experiential Community Learning. Int J indigenous health. 2021;16(1):87–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garvey A, Lynch G, Mansour M, Coyle A, Gard S, Truglio J. From race to racism: Teaching a Tool to critically appraise the use of race in Medical Research. MedEdPORTAL. 2022;18:11210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8784584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35128047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson T, Evans J, Goepfert A, Elopre L. Implementing a graduate medical education anti-racism workshop at an academic university in the Southern USA. Med Educ Online déc. 2022;27(1):1981803.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dennis SN, Gold RS, Wen FK. Learner reactions to activities exploring racism as a Social Determinant of Health. Fam Med janv. 2019;51(1):41–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edgoose J, Brown Speights J, White-Davis T, Guh J, Bullock K, Roberson K, et al. Teaching about racism in Medical Education: a mixed-method analysis of a train-the-trainer Faculty Development Workshop. Fam Med janv. 2021;53(1):23–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatahi G, Racic M, Roche-Miranda MI, Patterson DG, Phelan S, Riedy CA, et al. The current state of Antiracism Curricula in Undergraduate and Graduate Medical Education: a qualitative study of US Academic Health Centers. Ann Fam Med févr. 2023;21(Suppl 2):S14–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herzog LS, Wright SR, Pennington JJ, Richardson L. The KAIROS Blanket Exercise: engaging indigenous ways of knowing to foster critical consciousness in medical education. Med Teach déc. 2021;43(12):1437–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onyeador IN, Wittlin NM, Burke SE, Dovidio JF, Perry SP, Hardeman RR, et al. The value of interracial contact for reducing Anti-black Bias among Non-black Physicians: a cognitive habits and Growth evaluation (CHANGE) study report. Psychol Sci Janv. 2020;31(1):18–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holdren S, Iwai Y, Lenze N, Weil A, Randolph A. A Novel Narrative Medicine Approach to DEI Training for Medical School Faculty. Teaching and learning in medicine.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jindal M, Mistry KB, McRae A, Unaka N, Johnson T, Thornton RLJ. « it makes me a better person and doctor »: a qualitative study of residents’ perceptions of a curriculum addressing racism. Acad Pediatr mars. 2022;22(2):332–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrijo A, de Moura A, Oliveira A, Rodrigues L, de Oliveira J, de Castro T et al. Teaching of the Black Population’s Health: Anti-Racist Lenses for a Paradigm Shift to Address Racial Inequities. International journal of environmental research and public health. déc. 2022;19(24).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee D, Nassikas N, Singh P, Andrea S, Zhang A, Aswad Y, et al. Feasibility of an antiracism curriculum in an Academic Pulmonary, critical care, and Sleep Medicine Division. ATS scholar sept. 2022;3(3):433–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marbin J, Lewis L, Kuo AK, Schudel C, Gutierrez JR. The power of place: travel to explore Structural Racism and Health disparities. Acad Med. nov 2021;1(11):1569–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shankar M, Henderson K, Garcia R, Li G, Titer K, Acholonu RG, et al. Presence 5 for racial justice workshop: Fostering Dialogue Across Medical Education to Disrupt Anti-black Racism in Clinical encounters. MedEdPORTAL. 2022;18:11227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8828658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35198729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones C. Levels of racism: a theoretic framework and a gardener’s tale. Am J Public Health 1 août. 2000;90(8):1212–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bivens DK. What Is Internalized Racism?.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yudell M, Roberts D, DeSalle R, Tishkoff S. Taking race out of human genetics. Sci 5 févr. 2016;351(6273):564–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witzig R. The medicalization of race: scientific legitimization of a flawed Social Construct. Ann Intern Med. oct 1996;15(8):675.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark LT, Watkins L, Piña IL, Elmer M, Akinboboye O, Gorham M, et al. Increasing diversity in clinical trials: overcoming critical barriers. Curr Probl Cardiol Mai. 2019;44(5):148–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tervalon M. Components of culture in health for medical students’ education. Acad Med juin. 2003;78(6):570–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumagai AK, Lypson ML. Beyond Cultural Competence: Critical Consciousness, Social Justice, and Multicultural Education: Academic Medicine. juin. 2009;84(6):782–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tervalon M, Murray-García J. Cultural humility versus cultural competence: a critical distinction in defining physician training outcomes in multicultural education. J Health Care Poor Underserved Mai. 1998;9(2):117–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Razack S, Richardson L, Pillay SR. The violence of curriculum: Dismantling systemic racism, colonisation and indigenous erasure within medical education. Med Educ. 11 juill. 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fanon F. Le « syndrome nord-africain ». 1952.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambert M, Lachal J, Mansouri M, Radjack R, Moro MR. Syndrome méditerranéen et monde médical français, un préjugé raciste encore actif. Un parallèle avec l’article sur le « syndrome nord-africain » de Frantz Fanon. La Revue De Médecine Interne Juill. 2022;43(7):399–401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambert M, Lachal J, Mansouri M, Moro MR. Expérience subjective Du rapport aux soins pédopsychiatriques chez des adolescents franco-algériens: une perspective individuelle, et historique. Neuropsychiatrie De l’Enfance et de l’Adolescence 1 déc. 2022;70(8):441–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azria E, Sauvegrain P, Blanc J, Crenn-Hebert C, Fresson J, Gelly M, et al. Racisme systémique et inégalités de santé, une urgence sanitaire et sociétale révélée par la pandémie COVID-19. Gynécologie Obstétrique Fertilité. Sénologie déc. 2020;48(12):847–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Héran F. « Cessons d’opposer les principes républicains à la statistique ethnique ». Le Monde.fr. 24 juin 2020 [cité 7 août 2023]; Disponible sur: https://www.lemonde.fr/idees/article/2020/06/24/cessons-d-opposer-les-principes-republicains-a-la-statistique-ethnique_6043968_3232.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones R, Crowshoe L, Reid P, Calam B, Curtis E, Green M, et al. Educating for Indigenous Health Equity: An International Consensus Statement. Acad Med avr. 2019;94(4):512–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan A, Shim RS, Rodriguez CI, Bath E, Alves-Bradford JM, Eyler L, et al. Psychiatry Diversity Leadership in Academic Medicine: guidelines for success. AJP 1 mars. 2021;178(3):224–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sternadori M, Empathy may curb, bias: Two studies of the effects of news stories on implicit attitudes toward African Americans and native Americans. Contemp Read Law Soc Justice. 2017;9(2):11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pantziaras I, Fors U, Ekblad S. Innovative Training with Virtual Patients in Transcultural Psychiatry: The Impact on Resident Psychiatrists’ Confidence. Federici S, éditeur. PLoS ONE. 20 mars. 2015;10(3):e0119754.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleinsmith A, Rivera-Gutierrez D, Finney G, Cendan J, Lok B. Understanding empathy training with virtual patients. Computers Hum Behav Nov. 2015;52:151–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piot MA, Attoe C, Billon G, Cross S, Rethans JJ, Falissard B. Simulation Training in Psychiatry for Medical Education: a review. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:658967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8175985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34093275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman EN, Kaatz A, Carnes M. Physicians and Implicit Bias: how doctors may unwittingly perpetuate Health Care disparities. J Gen Intern Med Nov. 2013;28(11):1504–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devine PG. Stereotypes and prejudice: their automatic and controlled components. J Personal Soc Psychol. 1989;56(1):5–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green AR, Carney DR, Pallin DJ, Ngo LH, Raymond KL, Iezzoni LI, et al. Implicit bias among physicians and its prediction of thrombolysis decisions for black and white patients. J Gen Intern Med sept. 2007;22(9):1231–8.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>