<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39440020</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2752-6542</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>3</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PNAS nexus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PNAS Nexus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enough but not too many: A bi-threshold model for behavioral diffusion.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>pgae428</StartPage><MedlinePgn>pgae428</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">pgae428</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae428</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Behavioral diffusion is commonly modeled with the linear threshold model, which assumes that individuals adopt a behavior when enough of their social contacts do so. We observe, however, that in many common empirical settings individuals also appear to abandon a behavior when too many of their close contacts exhibit it. The bi-threshold model captures this tendency by adding an upper threshold, which, when exceeded, triggers behavioral disadoption. Here we report an empirical test of the bi-threshold model. We overcome the significant challenge of estimating individuals' heterogeneous thresholds by extending a recently introduced decision-tree based algorithm to the bi-threshold setting. Using the context of the spread of news about three different topics on social media (the Higgs boson, the Melbourne Cup horse race, and the COVID-19 vaccination campaign in China), we show that the bi-threshold model predicts user engagement with the news orders of magnitude more accurately than the linear threshold model. We show that the performance gains are due especially to the bi-threshold model's comparative advantage in predicting behavioral decline, an important but previously overlooked stage of the behavioral diffusion cycle. Overall, the results confirm the existence of the second upper threshold in some contexts of diffusion of information and suggest that a similar mechanism may operate in other decision-making contexts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of National Academy of Sciences.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alipour</LastName><ForeName>Fahimeh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-8880-3878</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Isfahan University of Technology, Khomeyni Shahr, Daneshgah e Sanati Hwy, Isfahan PG9G+39R, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dokshin</LastName><ForeName>Fedor</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8841-4755</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, University of Toronto, 700 University Ave, Toronto, Ontario, Canada M5G 1Z5.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maleki</LastName><ForeName>Zeinab</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Isfahan University of Technology, Khomeyni Shahr, Daneshgah e Sanati Hwy, Isfahan PG9G+39R, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Yunya</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5159-1689</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Communication, Hong Kong Baptist University, Hereford Road, Kowloon, Hong Kong.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramazi</LastName><ForeName>Pouria</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4906-0090</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Brock University, 1812 Sir Isaac Brock Way, St. Catharines, Ontario, Canada L2S 3A1.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>PNAS Nexus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918367777906676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2752-6542</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bi-threshold model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">information diffusion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">linear threshold model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social network</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">pgae428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Granovetter  M. 1978. Threshold models of collective behavior. Am J Sociol. 83(6):1420–1443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann  C, Singmann  H, Gershman  SJ, von Helversen  B. 2020. A linear threshold model for optimal stopping behavior. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 117(23):12750–12755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7293628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32461363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathak  N, Banerjee  A, Srivastava  J. 2010. A generalized linear threshold model for multiple cascades. In: 2010 IEEE International Conference on Data Mining; Sydney, NSW, Australia. IEEE. p. 965–970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimkhani  K, Aleahmad  A, Rahgozar  M, Moeini  A. 2015. A fast algorithm for finding most influential people based on the linear threshold model. Expert Syst Appl. 42(3):1353–1361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young  HP. 2011. The dynamics of social innovation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 108(supplement_4):21285–21291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3271568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22198762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham  DV, Nguyen  GL, Nguyen  TN, Pham  CV, Nguyen  AV. 2020. Multi-topic misinformation blocking with budget constraint on online social networks. IEEE Access. 8:78879–78889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centola  D. 2010. The spread of behavior in an online social network experiment. Science. 329(5996):1194–1197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20813952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montanari  A, Saberi  A. 2010. The spread of innovations in social networks. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 107(47):20196–20201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2996710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21076030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naimzada  AK, Pireddu  M. 2018. Fashion cycle dynamics in a model with endogenous discrete evolution of heterogeneous preferences. Chaos: Interdiscip J Nonlin Sci. 28(5):055907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29857680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmel  G. 1957. Fashion. Am J Sociol. 62(6):541–558.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoganarasimhan  H. 2017. Identifying the presence and cause of fashion cycles in data. J Mark Res. 54(1):5–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DiMaggio  P, Garip  F. 2011. How network externalities can exacerbate intergroup inequality 1. Am J Sociol. 116(6):1887–1933.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamshidian  M, Maleki  Z, Ramazi  P. 2021. The neglected bi-threshold aspect of human decision-making: equilibrium analysis. In: 2021 60th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC); Austin, TX, USA. IEEE. p. 2354–2359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez-Pintado  D, Watts  DJ. 2008. Social influence, binary decisions and collective dynamics. Rationality Soc. 20(4):399–443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granovetter  M, Soong  R. 1983. Threshold models of diffusion and collective behavior. J Math Sociol. 9(3):165–179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cornes  R, Sandler  T. 1996. The theory of externalities, public goods, and club goods. 2nd ed. Cambridge, New York: Cambridge University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McConnell  KE. 1977. Congestion and willingness to pay: a study of beach use. Land Econ. 53(2):185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leibenstein  H. 1950. Bandwagon, snob, and veblen effects in the theory of consumers’ demand. Q J Econ. 64(2):183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourdieu  BP. 1987. Distinction a social critique of the judgement of taste. Harvard University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kempe  D, Kleinberg  J, Tardos  É. 2003. Maximizing the spread of influence through a social network. In: Proceedings of the Ninth ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining. Association of Computing Machinery; New York, NY. p. 137–146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen  W, Lin  T, Tan  Z, Zhao  M, Zhou  X. 2016. Robust influence maximization. In: Proceedings of the 22nd ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining. Association for Computing Machinery; New York, NY. p. 795–804.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lerman  K, Yan  X, Wu  X-Z. 2016. The “majority illusion” in social networks. PLoS One. 11(2):e0147617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4757419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26886112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tran  C, Zheleva  E. 2019. Learning triggers for heterogeneous treatment effects. In: Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence; Honolulu, HI, Vol. 33. p. 5183–5190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tran  C, Zheleva  E. 2022. Heterogeneous peer effects in the linear threshold model. Proc AAAI Conf Artif Intell. 36(4):4175–4183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ronzhyn  A, Cardenal  AS, Rubio  AB. 2023. Defining affordances in social media research: a literature review. New Media Soc. 25(11):3165–3188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehmann  DR, Parker  JR. 2017. Disadoption. Ams Rev. 7:36–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strang  D, Macy  MW. 2001. In search of excellence: fads, success stories, and adaptive emulation. Am J Sociol. 107(1):147–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhlman  C, et al.  2011. A bi-threshold model of complex contagion and its application to the spread of smoking behavior. In: Proceedings of the Workshop on Social Network Mining and Analysis (SNA-KDD 2011); San Diego, CA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher  JC. 2019. Social space diffusion: applications of a latent space model to diffusion with uncertain ties. Sociol Methodol. 49(1):258–294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8025911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33833476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Domenico  M, Lima  A, Mougel  P, Musolesi  M. 2013. The anatomy of a scientific rumor. Sci Rep. 3(1):1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3798885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24135961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang  Z, Zhao  W, Yang  J, Paris  C, Nepal  S. 2019. Learning influence probabilities and modelling influence diffusion in twitter. In: Companion Proceedings of The 2019 World Wide Web Conference. Association for Computing Machinery; New York, NY. p. 1087–1094.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song  Y. 2024 Sep. Weibo-covid-19. 10.5281/zenodo.13787781.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5281/zenodo.13787781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>