<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39448893</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2318</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC geriatrics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Geriatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The effects of the changes in the depression on suicidal ideation among older adults aged 75 and above before and after the COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>867</StartPage><MedlinePgn>867</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">867</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12877-024-05427-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The unprecedented pandemic situation of COVID-19 has had a negative impact on the mental health of many people, especially among the "old-old" older adults who are aged 75 or older. Therefore, the aim of this study is to investigate the changes in depression among "old-old" older adults before and after the onset of COVID-19, and the extent to which depression affects suicidal ideations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">The 12th to 16th Korea Welfare Panel Study(KoWePS) conducted from 2017 to 2021 was used for analysis. For this study, 771 older individuals with complete data to estimate the degree of change of depression were selected as the final analysis subjects.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULT" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A Growth Mixture Modeling(GMM) analysis was conducted, resulting in the classification of two groups: an increasing group and a decreasing group. The study findings showed that "old-old" older individuals with high levels of depression, specifically those in the decreasing group, may be more susceptible to suicidal ideation. Despite this steep change slope, the decreasing group still exhibited a higher level of depression in 2021 compared to the increasing group. As per characteristics, the decreasing group, which showed a higher prevalence of suicidal ideation, had a higher proportion of women and individuals with lower levels of education, those living alone, and a lower household income compared to the increasing group.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">It is important to note that although the study emphasized the need to prioritize intervention for the decreasing group with consistently high levels of depression, the majority of individuals belong to the increasing group, which exhibited a gradual increase in depression levels over time. Therefore, intervention plans should be developed concurrently for both groups. Also, it is crucial to implement proactive efforts targeting groups with understandings of these characteristics when establishing preventative measures for depression and suicidal ideation among "old-old" older adults.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jeong</LastName><ForeName>Kyu-Hyoung</ForeName><Initials>KH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1126-9406</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social Welfare, Jeonbuk National University, 567 Baekje-Daero, Jeonju, 54896, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cho</LastName><ForeName>Sunghwan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7616-8094</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Social Welfare, The Catholic University of Korea, 43 Jibong-Ro, Bucheon-Si, Gyeonggi-Do, 14662, Republic of Korea. scho9595@catholic.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hwang</LastName><ForeName>Yeon Jae</ForeName><Initials>YJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3274-7494</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social Welfare, University of California, Los Angeles, 337 Charles Young Dr E, Los Angeles, CA, 90095-1656, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Dayoon</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8830-2334</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Korea Central Public Agency for Social Service, 340, Samil-daero, Jung-Gu, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Seoyoon</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4013-7987</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Policy and Management, School of Public Health, Texas A&amp;M University, 212 Adriance Lab Rd, College Station, Texas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Geriatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968548</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2318</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059020" MajorTopicYN="Y">Suicidal Ideation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D056910" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Republic of Korea</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003863" MajorTopicYN="Y">Depression</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000369" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged, 80 and over</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depressive Symptom</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Republic of Korea</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39448893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12877-024-05427-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12877-024-05427-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Agustini B, Lotfaliany M, Mohebbi M, Woods RL, McNeil JJ, Nelson MR, et al. Trajectories of depressive symptoms in older adults and associated health outcomes. Nat Aging. 2022;2(4):295–302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10351394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida OP, Draper B, Snowdon J, Lautenschlager NT, Pirkis J, Byrne G, Sim M, Stocks N, Flicker L, Pfaff JJ. Factors associated with suicidal thoughts in a large community study of older adults. Br J Psychiatry. 2012;201(6):466–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23209090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blazer D, Burchett B, Service C, George LK. The association of age and depression among the elderly: an epidemiologic exploration. J Gerontol. 1991;46(6):M210–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1834726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattell H. Suicide in the elderly. Adv Psychiatr Treat. 2000;6(2):102–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Program Helps Older Adults Manage Depresssion. 2022. https://www.cdc.gov/prc/study-findings/research-briefs/program-helps-elderly.htm. Accessed Date: 2023.02.09.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duncan TE, Duncan SC, Strycker LA. An introduction to latent variable growth curve modeling: Concepts, issues, and application. Routledge; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epanchin-Niell R, Lu J, Thompson A, Tobin PC, Gray DR, Liebhold AM. Socio-environmental drivers of establishment of Lymantria dispar, a nonnative forest pest, in the United States. Biol Invasions. 2022;24(1):157–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Firth D. Bias reduction of maximum likelihood estimates. Biometrika. 1993;80(1):27–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawton K, Casañas I Comabella C, Haw C, Saunders K. Risk factors for suicide in individuals with depression: a systematic review. J Affect Dis. 2013;147(1–3):17–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23411024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeon HS, Dunkle RE. Stress and depression among the oldest-old: a longitudinal analysis. Res Aging. 2009;31(6):661–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3092309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21572921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ju YJ, Park EC, Han KT, Choi JW, Kim JL, Cho KH, Park S. Low socioeconomic status and suicidal ideation among elderly individuals. Int Psychogeriatr. 2016;28(12):2055–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27456081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung T, Wickrama KA. An introduction to latent class growth analysis and growth mixture modeling. Soc Person Psychol Compass. 2008;2(1):302–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang EN, Choi JS. Multiple trajectories of depressive symptoms among older adults. J Korean Gerontol Soc. 2014;34(2):387–407.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King G, Zeng L. Logistic regression in rare events data. Polit Anal. 2001;9(2):137–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim HK, Sung JM. The longitudinal factors related to the depression of the korean elderly : comparison of younger-old and older-old. J Welfare Aged. 2014;66:427–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohout FJ, Berkman LF, Evans DA, Cornoni-Huntley J. Two shorter forms of the CES-D depression symptoms index. J Aging Health. 1993;5(2):179–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10125443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koo CY, Kim JS, Yu J. A study on factors influencing elders’ suicidal ideation: Focused on comparison of gender differences. J Korean Acad Commun Health Nurs. 2014;25(1):24–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A, Nayar KR. COVID 19 and its mental health consequences. Taylor Francis. 2021;30:1–2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lebret S, Perret-Vaille E, Mulliez A, Gerbaud L, Jalenques I. Elderly suicide attempters: characteristics and outcome. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2006;21(11):1052–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16955444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee HJ. Longitudinal changes in depression in older adults: differences across age groups and risk factors. J Welfare Aged. 2013;61:225–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lekamwasam R, Lekamwasam S. Effects of COVID-19 pandemic on health and wellbeing of older people: a comprehensive review. Ann Geriatr Med Res. 2020;24(3):166–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7533189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32752587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim KC, Kim SH. Prevalence and correlates of depression in older koreans: comparison of young-old and old-old. J Korean Acad Psychiatr Mental Health Nurs. 2012;21(1):1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minayo MCD, Cavalcante FG. Suicide attempts among the elderly: a review of the literature (2002/2013). Ciencia Saude Coletiva. 2015;20:1751–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26060953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare. Announcement of the results of the COVID-19 National Mental Health Survey in the second quarter of 2022. August 10, 2022. Press Release. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare &amp; Korea Institute for Health and Social Affairs. The 2020 National Survey of the Living Conditions and Welfare Needs of Older Koreans. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muthén B. Latent variable analysis. In D, Kaplan (Ed.), The Sage handbook of quantitative methodology for the social sciences (pp. 345–368). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications. 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare &amp; Korea Foundation For Suicide Prevention. 2022 White Paper On Suicide Prevention. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neugarten BL. Age groups in American society and the rise of the young-old. Ann Am Acad Political Soc Sci. 1974;415(1):187–98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. Tackling the Mental Health Impact of the COVID-19 Crisis: An Integrated, Whole-of-Society Response. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh JJ, Go HM, Kim SH, Jang G, Kim YS. Results from the Korean Longitudinal Study on Health and Aging (KLoSHA). Korean Public Health Res. 2016;42(2):84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh YJ, Kim HD. A study on predictive factors of elderly suicidal ideation. J Converg Inform Technol. 2018;8(2):1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park YR, Park KS. Social support network and welfare of the elderly in korea: research trends and future tasks. J Welfare Aged. 2013;60:323–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponte C, Almeida V, Fernandes L. Suicidal ideation, depression and quality of life in the elderly: study in a gerontopsychiatric consultation. Spanish J Psychol. 2014;17:E14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radloff LS. The CES-D scale: a self-report depression scale for research in the general population. Appl Psycholog Measure. 1977;1(3):385–401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sa HJ, Lee WS, Lee BG. Corona blue and leisure activities: focusing on Korean case. J Int Comput Serv. 2021;22(2):109–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seong KO, Kim SJ, Moon JH. Effects of life changes due to COVID-19 on depression in the elderly. Soc Work Pract Res. 2021;18(2):99–129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohn JN. A study on factors influencing the suicidal ideation in elderly people who live alone or live with family. J Korean Acad Psychiatr Mental Health Nurs. 2012;21(2):118–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stek ML, Vinkers DJ, Gussekloo J, Van Der Mast RC, Beekman AT, Westendorp RG. Natural history of depression in the oldest old: population-based prospective study. Br J Psychiatry. 2006;188(1):65–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16388072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiktorsson S, Runeson B, Skoog I, Östling S, Waern M. Attempted suicide in the elderly: characteristics of suicide attempters 70 years and older and a general population comparison group. American J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2010;18(1):57–67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yen YC, Yang MJ, Yang MS, Lung FW, Shih CH, Hahn CY, Lo HY. Suicidal ideation and associated factors among community-dwelling elders in Taiwan. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2005;59(4):365–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16048440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>