<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39449059</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1468-3148</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>38</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2025</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of applied research in intellectual disabilities : JARID</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Appl Res Intellect Disabil</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Feasibility, Experiences and Short-Term Outcomes on Challenging Behaviour and Well-Being of a Partially Online Music Intervention Pilot Study for Adults With Intellectual Disabilities.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13314</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13314</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jar.13314</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">During the COVID-19 pandemic we implemented a partially online music intervention to examine the feasibility, experiences and short-term outcomes on the challenging behaviour and well-being of adults with intellectual disabilities.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">This mixed-methods study included 10 participants with mild or moderate intellectual disabilities who received 16 one-hour individual music sessions in 10 weeks, either face-to-face or online. Data on feasibility and experiences from participants and music workers were collected and analysed using inductive thematic analysis. Challenging behaviour and well-being were measured before and after intervention.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Overall experiences were positive and concerned appreciation, positive feelings, musical abilities, attention span, relatedness and personalisation. Online experiences varied, but most participants preferred face-to-face over online sessions. After the intervention, challenging behaviour scores were better than before.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Engaging in a partially online music intervention is feasible for people with intellectual disabilities and seems to improve challenging behaviour. Experiences are discussed and recommendations for future online sessions are provided.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smeets</LastName><ForeName>Gerianne J J</ForeName><Initials>GJJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9246-1477</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Philadelphia Care Foundation, Amersfoort, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Volkers</LastName><ForeName>Karin M</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1532-429X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Philadelphia Care Foundation, Amersfoort, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Swart</LastName><ForeName>Eline A K</ForeName><Initials>EAK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-3978-711X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Philadelphia Care Foundation, Amersfoort, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moonen</LastName><ForeName>Xavier M H</ForeName><Initials>XMH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1336-9152</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of Child Development and Education, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Scherder</LastName><ForeName>Erik J A</ForeName><Initials>EJA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1203-3208</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Neuropsychology, VU University Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Philadelphia Care Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Appl Res Intellect Disabil</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9613616</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1360-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008607" MajorTopicYN="Y">Intellectual Disability</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000534" MajorTopicYN="N">rehabilitation</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009147" MajorTopicYN="Y">Music Therapy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010865" MajorTopicYN="N">Pilot Projects</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005240" MajorTopicYN="Y">Feasibility Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000066553" MajorTopicYN="Y">Problem Behavior</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000079382" MajorTopicYN="N">Internet-Based Intervention</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">challenging behaviour</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">feasibility</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intellectual disability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">music intervention</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">online music</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">well‐being</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jar.13314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Aman, M. G., N. N. Singh, A. W. Stewart, and C. J. Field. 1985. “The Aberrant Behavior Checklist: A Behavior Rating Scale for the Assessment of Treatment Effects.” American Journal of Mental Deficiency 89, no. 5: 485–491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amor, A. M., P. Navas, M. Verdugo, and M. Crespo. 2021. “Perceptions of People With Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities About COVID‐19 in Spain: A Cross‐Sectional Study.” Journal of Intellectual Disability Research 65, no. 5: 381–396. https://doi.org/10.1111/jir.12821.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andring, J. L. 2015. “Contributing to Quality of Life by Facilitating Music‐Based Social Interaction for Adults With Intellectual Disability.” Expressive Therapies Dissertations 17. https://digitalcommons.lesley.edu/expressive_dissertations/17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baksh, R. A., S. E. Pape, J. Smith, and A. Strydom. 2021. “Understanding Inequalities in COVID‐19 Outcomes Following Hospital Admission for People With Intellectual Disability Compared to the General Population: A Matched Cohort Study in the UK.” BMJ Open 11: e052482. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen‐2021‐052482.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun, V., and V. Clarke. 2006. “Using Thematic Analysis in Psychology.” Qualitative Research in Psychology 3, no. 2: 77–101. https://doi.org/10.1191/1478088706qp063oa.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruinsma, E., B. J. Van Den Hoofdakker, A. P. Groenman, et al. 2020. “Non‐Pharmacological Interventions for Challenging Behaviours of Adults With Intellectual Disabilities: A Meta‐Analysis.” Journal of Intellectual Disability Research 64, no. 8: 561–578. https://doi.org/10.1111/jir.12736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter, N., D. Bryant‐Lukosius, A. Dicenso, J. Blythe, and A. J. Neville. 2014. “The Use of Triangulation in Qualitative Research.” Oncology Nursing Forum 41, no. 5: 545–547. https://doi.org/10.1188/14.ONF.545‐547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadwick, D., K. A. Ågren, S. Caton, et al. 2022. “Digital Inclusion and Participation of People With Intellectual Disabilities During COVID‐19: A Rapid Review and International Bricolage.” Journal of Policy and Practice in Intellectual Disabilities 19, no. 3: 242–256. https://doi.org/10.1111/jppi.12410.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang, B., B. Chen, J. W. Beckstead, and C. Yang. 2018. “Effects of a Music‐Creation Programme on the Anxiety, Self‐Esteem, and Quality of Life of People With Severe Mental Illness: A Quasi‐Experimental Design.” International Journal of Mental Health Nursing 27, no. 3: 1066–1076. https://doi.org/10.1111/inm.12414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cleaver, S., and A. Sakar. 2010. “Participation in Intellectual Disability Research: A Review of 20 Years of Studies.” Journal of Intellectual Disability Research 54, no. March: 187–193. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2788.2010.01256.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook, T., A. R. K. Roy, and K. M. Welker. 2019. “Music as an Emotion Regulation Strategy: An Examination of Genres of Music and Their Roles in Emotion Regulation.” Psychology of Music 47, no. 1: 144–154. https://doi.org/10.1177/0305735617734627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creswell, J. W. 2009. Qualitative, Quantitative, and Mixed‐Methods Research. 3rd ed. Thousand Oaks, California: Sage Publications. https://doi.org/10.1128/microbe.4.485.1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummins, R. A. 2005. “Caregivers as Managers of Subjective Wellbeing: A Homeostatic Perspective.” Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities 18, no. 4: 335–344. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468‐3148.2005.00267.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummins, R. A., and A. L. D. Lau. 2005. Personal Wellbeing Index‐Intellectual Disability (PWI‐ID) Manual. Vertaling Door Expertisecentrum Quality of Life (E‐QUAL)—HoGent 2013. 3rd ed. Melbourne, Victoria: School of Psychology Deakin University. https://www.hogent.be/sites/hogent/assets/File/HandleidingPersoonlijkWelzijnIndex.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desroches, M. L., S. Ailey, K. Fisher, and J. Stych. 2021. “Impact of COVID‐19: Nursing Challenges to Meeting the Care Needs of People With Developmental Disabilities.” Disability and Health Journal 14, no. 1: 101015. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dhjo.2020.101015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doody, O., and P. M. Keenan. 2021. “The Reported Effects of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on People With Intellectual Disability and Their Carers: A Scoping Review.” Annals of Medicine 53, no. 1: 786–804. https://doi.org/10.1080/07853890.2021.1922743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowson, B., R. Atkinson, J. Barnes, et al. 2021. “Digital Approaches to Music‐Making for People With Dementia in Response to the COVID‐19 Pandemic: Current Practice and Recommendations.” Frontiers in Psychology 12: 625258. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.625258.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Embregts, P. J. C. M., K. J. H. M. V. D. Bogaard, N. Frielink, A. C. Voermans, M. Thalen, and A. Jahoda. 2020. “A Thematic Analysis Into the Experiences of People With a Mild Intellectual Disability During the COVID‐19 Lockdown Period.” International Journal of Developmental Disabilities 68: 578–582. https://doi.org/10.1080/20473869.2020.1827214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerdner, L. A. 2000. “Effects of Individualized Versus Classical Relaxation Music on the Frequency of Agitation in Elderly Persons With Alzheimers Disease and Related Disorders.” International Psychogeriatrics 12, no. 1: 49–65. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1041610200006190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geretsegger, M., K. A. Mössler, L. Bieleninik, X. J. Chen, T. O. Heldal, and C. Gold. 2017. “Music Therapy for People With Schizophrenia and Schizophrenia‐Like Disorders.” Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 5: CD004025. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD004025.pub4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez‐Gallego, M., J. C. Gómez‐Gallego, M. Gallego‐Mellado, and J. García‐García. 2021. “Comparative Efficacy of Active Group Music Intervention Versus Group Music Listening in Alzheimer's Disease.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18: 8067. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18158067.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, P., M. Kwan, D. Chen, et al. 2010. “A Controlled Naturalistic Study on a Weekly Music Therapy and Activity Program on Disruptive and Depressive Behaviors in Dementia.” Dementia and Geriatric Cognitive Disorders 30: 540–546. https://doi.org/10.1159/000321668.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassiotis, A., A. Ali, A. Courtemanche, et al. 2020. “In the Time of the Pandemic: Safeguarding People With Developmental Disabilities Against the Impact of Coronavirus.” Journal of Mental Health Research in Intellectual Disabilities 13, no. 2: 63–65. https://doi.org/10.1080/19315864.2020.1756080.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heyvaert, M., B. Maes, and P. Onghena. 2010. “A Meta‐Analysis of Intervention Effects on Challenging Behaviour Among Persons With Intellectual Disabilities.” Journal of Intellectual Disability Research 54, no. 7: 634–649. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2788.2010.01291.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaschke, A. C., and E. J. A. Scherder. 2015. “Music Intervention, Agitation, Quality of Life and Repetitive Behaviour in People With a Form of Intellectual Disability: A Brief Pilot Report.” Journal of Neurology and Neuroscience S1: 1–7. https://doi.org/10.21767/2171‐6625.S10006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalgotra, R., and J. S. Warwal. 2017. “Effect of Music Intervention on Behaviour Disorders of Children With Intellectual Disability Using Strategies From Applied Behaviour Analysis.” Disability, CBR &amp; Inclusive Development 28, no. 1: 161–177. https://doi.org/10.5463/DCID.v28i1.584.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keenan, P. M., and O. Doody. 2023. “An Update of the Reported Effects of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on People With Intellectual Disability and Their Carers: A Scoping Review.” Annals of Medicine 55, no. 1: 2196437. https://doi.org/10.1080/07853890.2023.2196437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai, C. C., T. P. Shih, W. C. Ko, H. J. Tang, and P. R. Hsueh. 2020. “Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS‐CoV‐2) and Coronavirus Disease‐2019 (COVID‐19): The Epidemic and the Challenges.” International Journal of Antimicrobial Agents 55, no. 3: 105924. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lake, J. K., P. Jachyra, T. Volpe, et al. 2021. “The Wellbeing and Mental Health Care Experiences of Adults With Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities During COVID‐19.” Journal of Mental Health Research in Intellectual Disabilities 14, no. 3: 285–300. https://doi.org/10.1080/19315864.2021.1892890.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lunsky, Y., N. Bobbette, A. Selick, and M. I. Jiwa. 2021. ““The Doctor Will See You Now”: Direct Support Professionals' Perspectives on Supporting Adults With Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities Accessing Health Care During COVID‐19.” Disability and Health Journal 14, no. 3: 101066. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dhjo.2021.101066.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lunsky, Y., A. Jahoda, P. Navas, S. Campanella, and S. M. Havercamp. 2022. “The Mental Health and Well‐Being of Adults With Intellectual Disability During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Narrative Review.” Journal of Policy and Practice in Intellectual Disabilities 19, no. 1: 35–47. https://doi.org/10.1111/jppi.12412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lussier‐Desrochers, D., C. L. Normand, A. Romero‐Torres, et al. 2017. “Bridging the Digital Divide for People With Intellectual Disability.” Cyberpsychology: Journal of Psychosocial Research on Cyberspace 11, no. 1: 1. https://doi.org/10.5817/CP2017‐1‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGillivray, J. A., A. L. D. Lau, R. A. Cummins, and G. Davey. 2009. “The Utility of the Personal Wellbeing Index Intellectual Disability Scale in an Australian Sample.” Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities 22, no. 3: 276–286. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468‐3148.2008.00460.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mino‐Roy, J., J. St‐Jean, O. Lemus‐Folgar, et al. 2021. “Effects of Music, Dance and Drama Therapies for People With an Intellectual Disability: A Scoping Review.” British Journal of Learning Disabilities 50, no. 3: 385–401. https://doi.org/10.1111/bld.12402.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno, M. T., J. C. Sans, and M. T. C. Fosch. 2021. “Behavioral and Cognitive Interventions With Digital Devices in Subjects With Intellectual Disability: A Systematic Review.” Frontiers in Psychiatry 12: 647399. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2021.647399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno‐Morales, C., R. Calero, P. Moreno‐Morales, and C. Pintado. 2020. “Music Therapy in the Treatment of Dementia: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Frontiers in Medicine 7: 160. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmed.2020.00160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Näslund, R., and Å. Gardelli. 2013. ““I Know, I Can, I Will Try”: Youths and Adults With Intellectual Disabilities in Sweden Using Information and Communication Technology in Their Everyday Life.” Disability and Society 28, no. 1: 28–40. https://doi.org/10.1080/09687599.2012.695528.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navas, P., A. M. Amor, M. Crespo, and Z. Wolowiec. 2021. “Supports for People With Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities During the COVID‐19 Pandemic From Their Own Perspective.” Research in Developmental Disabilities 108: 103813.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oudshoorn, C. E. M., N. Frielink, S. L. P. Nijs, and P. J. C. M. Embregts. 2021. “Psychological eHealth Interventions for People With Intellectual Disabilities: A Scoping Review.” Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities 34, no. 4: 950–972. https://doi.org/10.1111/jar.12877.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paclawskyj, T. R., J. L. Matson, J. W. Bamburg, and C. S. Baglio. 1997. “A Comparison of the Diagnostic Assessment for the Severely Handicapped‐II (DASH‐II) and the Aberrant Behavior Checklist (ABC).” Research in Developmental Disabilities 18, no. 4: 289–298. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0891‐4222(97)00010‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen, S. K. A., P. N. Andersen, R. G. Lugo, M. Andreassen, and S. Sütterlin. 2017. “Effects of Music on Agitation in Dementia: A Meta‐Analysis.” Frontiers in Psychology 8: 742. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00742.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelletier, C. L. 2004. “The Effect of Music on Decreasing Arousal due to Stress: A Meta‐Analysis.” Journal of Music Therapy 41, no. 3: 192–214. https://doi.org/10.1093/jmt/41.3.192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rauf, B., H. Sheikh, H. Majid, A. Roy, and R. Pathania. 2021. “COVID‐19‐Related Prescribing Challenge in Intellectual Disability.” BJPsych Open 7, no. 2: e66. https://doi.org/10.1192/bjo.2021.26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawlings, G. H., C. Gaskell, K. Rolling, and N. Beail. 2021. “Exploring How to Deliver Videoconference‐Mediated Psychological Therapy to Adults With an Intellectual Disability During the Coronavirus Pandemic.” Advances in Mental Health and Intellectual Disabilities 15, no. 1: 20–32. https://doi.org/10.1108/amhid‐06‐2020‐0014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakamoto, M., H. Ando, and A. Tsutou. 2013. “Comparing the Effects of Different Individualized Music Interventions for Elderly Individuals With Severe Dementia.” International Psychogeriatrics 25, no. 5: 775–784. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1041610212002256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savarimuthu, D., and T. Bunnell. 2002. “The Effects of Music on Clients With Learning Disabilities: A Literature Review.” Complementary Therapies in Nursing &amp; Midwifery 8, no. 3: 160–165. https://doi.org/10.1054/ctnm.2001.0629.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheffers, F., X. Moonen, and E. van Vugt. 2021. “Assessing the Quality of Support and Discovering Sources of Resilience During COVID‐19 Measures in People With Intellectual Disabilities by Professional Carers.” Research in Developmental Disabilities 111, no. September 2020: 103889. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ridd.2021.103889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuengel, C., J. Tummers, P. J. C. M. Embregts, and G. L. Leusink. 2020. “Impact of the Initial Response to COVID‐19 on Long‐Term Care for People With Intellectual Disability: An Interrupted Time Series Analysis of Incident Reports.” Journal of Intellectual Disability Research 64, no. 11: 817–824. https://doi.org/10.1111/jir.12778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheehan, R., and A. Hassiotis. 2017. “Digital Mental Health and Intellectual Disabilities: State of the Evidence and Future Directions.” Evidence‐Based Mental Health 20, no. 4: 107–111. https://doi.org/10.1136/eb‐2017‐102759.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>St. John, L., T. Volpe, M. I. Jiwa, et al. 2022. “‘More Together Than Apart’: The Evaluation of a Virtual Course to Improve Mental Health and Well‐Being of Adults With Intellectual Disabilities During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities 35, no. 6: 1360–1369. https://doi.org/10.1111/jar.13024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topooco, N., H. Riper, R. Araya, et al. 2017. “Attitudes Towards Digital Treatment for Depression: A European Stakeholder Survey.” Internet Interventions 8: 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.invent.2017.01.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Der Geer, E. R., A. C. Vink, J. M. G. A. Schols, and J. P. J. Slaets. 2009. “Music in the Nursing Home: Hitting the Right Note! The Provision of Music to Dementia Patients With Verbal and Vocal Agitation in Dutch Nursing Homes.” International Psychogeriatrics 21, no. 1: 86–93. https://doi.org/10.1017/S104161020800793X.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Der Steen, J., M. Van Soest‐Poortvliet, J. Van Der Wouden, M. Bruinsma, R. Scholten, and A. Vink. 2017. “Music‐Based Therapeutic Interventions for People With Dementia (Review).” Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 5: CD003477. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD003477.pub3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Schijndel‐Speet, M., H. M. Evenhuis, R. Van Wijck, and M. A. Echteld. 2014. “Implementation of a Group‐Based Physical Activity Programme for Ageing Adults With ID: A Process Evaluation.” Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice 20, no. 4: 401–407. https://doi.org/10.1111/jep.12145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vereniging Gehandicaptenzorg Nederland. 2020. “Handreiking bezoek en logeren gehandicaptenzorg voor verantwoord bezoek en logeren in coronatijd.” https://www.vgn.nl/system/files/2021‐05/Handreiking_Bezoekenlogeren_10mei2021.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinberg, M. K., and D. Joseph. 2017. “If You're Happy and You Know It: Music Engagement and Subjective Wellbeing.” Psychology of Music 45, no. 2: 257–267. https://doi.org/10.1177/0305735616659552.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wentzel, J., R. van der Vaart, E. T. Bohlmeijer, and J. E. W. C. van Gemert‐Pijnen. 2016. “Mixing Online and Face‐To‐Face Therapy: How to Benefit From Blended Care in Mental Health Care.” JMIR Mental Health 3, no. 1: e9. https://doi.org/10.2196/mental.4534.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>