<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39446622</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Standardized Approach to Pediatric Post-COVID Syndrome and Its Impact on Children and Adolescents: A Perspective From a Tertiary Center.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004593</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Pediatric post-COVID syndrome (pPCS) affects a notable number of children. This study aims to describe its clinical manifestations, biopsychosocial impact and management strategies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A prospective, single-center study was conducted to analyze data of pPCS patients presenting to our institution between May 2021 and November 2022. Functional impact was evaluated by assessing school absenteeism and by using the Adolescent Depression Rating Scale (ADRS), Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PedsQL) and Fatigue Severity Scale.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Among the 50 patients included [median age (interquartile range): 14.0 (12.9-15.8) years; females: 70%], the most common symptoms were extreme fatigue (84%), exertion intolerance (82%), orthostatism (66%), dyspnea (66%) and headache (66%); 25% had an abnormal Schellong test. Median (interquartile range) ADRS, PedsQL and Fatigue Severity Scale scores were 3.0 (1.0-5.0), 56% (49%-71%) and 45.0 (32.0-53.0), respectively. Sixty percent experienced partial (34%) or complete (26%) school absenteeism. The most common referrals to specialized consultations were child psychiatry (48%), pulmonology (46%), physiotherapy (36%) and an ear-nose-throat specialist (24%). Eighty percent had a typical form of pPCS, whereas 20% had a clinical presentation suggestive of a functional disorder triggered by COVID-19. The latter had more frequent thoracic pain (P = 0.012) and more referrals to pediatric neurology (P = 0.01), gastroenterology (P = 0.011), ophthalmology (P = 0.037) and child psychiatry (P = 0.035), but less to pulmonology (P = 0.014). School absenteeism and social withdrawal were also more common in this group, with more severe PedsQL and ADRS scores.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">pPCS is associated with a significant socio-educational burden that should be taken into account in medical, social and educational care.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nzale</LastName><ForeName>Shadya</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Faculty of Medicine, University of Geneve.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Perrin</LastName><ForeName>Anne</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2023-3157</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General Pediatrics, Department of Women, Child and Adolescent Health.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soroken</LastName><ForeName>Cindy</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3557-6328</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Faculty of Medicine, University of Geneve.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General Pediatrics, Department of Women, Child and Adolescent Health.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nehme</LastName><ForeName>Mayssam</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Faculty of Medicine, University of Geneve.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Primary Care Medicine, Department of Primary Care Medicine, Geneva University Hospitals, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Posfay-Barbe</LastName><ForeName>Klara M</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9464-5704</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Faculty of Medicine, University of Geneve.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General Pediatrics, Department of Women, Child and Adolescent Health.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>L'Huillier</LastName><ForeName>Arnaud G</ForeName><Initials>AG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9230-7285</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Faculty of Medicine, University of Geneve.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General Pediatrics, Department of Women, Child and Adolescent Health.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446622</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-990000000-01057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Soriano JB, Murthy S, Marhall JC, et al. A clinical case definition of post COVID-19 condition by Delphi consensus. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22:e102–e107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. A Clinical Case Definition for Post COVID-19 Condition in Children and Adolescents by Expert Consensus. World Health Organization; 2023. Available from: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-Post-COVID-19-condition-CA-Clinical-case-definition-2023-1. Accessed October 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellegrino R, Chiappini E, Licari A, et al. Prevalence and clinical presentation of long COVID in children: a systematic review. Eur J Pediatr. 2022;181:3995–4009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmermann P, Pittet LF, Curtis N. How common is long COVID in children and adolescents? Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2021;40:e482–e487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toepfner N, Brinkmann F, Augustin S, et al. Long COVID in pediatrics-epidemiology, diagnosis, and management. Eur J Pediatr. 2024;183:1543–1553.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumont R, Richard V, Lorthe E, et al.; SEROCoV-KIDS study group. A population-based serological study of post-COVID syndrome prevalence and risk factors in children and adolescents. Nat Commun. 2022;13:7086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varni JW, Seid M, Kurtin PS. PedsQL 4.0: reliability and validity of the Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory version 4.0 generic core scales in healthy and patient populations. Med Care. 2001;39:800–812.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varni JW, Limbers CA. The pediatric quality of life inventory: measuring pediatric health-related quality of life from the perspective of children and their parents. Pediatr Clin North Am. 2009;56:843–863.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revah-Levy A, Birmaher B, Gasquet I, et al. The Adolescent Depression Rating Scale (ADRS): a validation study. BMC Psychiatry. 2007;7:2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krupp LB, LaRocca NG, Muir-Nash J, et al. The fatigue severity scale: application to patients with multiple sclerosis and systemic lupus erythematosus. Arch Neurol. 1989;46:1121–1123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valko PO, Bassetti CL, Bloch KE, et al. Validation of the fatigue severity scale in a Swiss cohort. Sleep. 2008;31:1601–1607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naik H, Shao S, Tran KC, et al. Evaluation fatigue in patients recovering from COVID-19: validation of the fatigue severity scale and single item screening questions. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2022;20:170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soroken C, Posfay-Barbe KM, Caflisch M, et al. Postural tachycardia syndrome among adolescents. Arch Pediatr. 2022;29:398–403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oosterhoff B, Palmer CA, Wilson J, et al. Adolescents’ motivations to engage in social distancing during the COVID-19 pandemic: associations with mental and social health. J Adolesc Health. 2020;67:179–185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shorey S, Ng ED, Wong CHJ. Global prevalence of depression and elevated depressive symptoms among adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Clin Psychol. 2022;61:287–305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Mental Disorders Collaborators. Global prevalence and burden of depressive and anxiety disorders in 204 countries and territories in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Lancet. 2021;398:1700–1712.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson E, Sutin AR, Daly M, et al. A systematic review and meta-analysis of longitudinal cohort studies comparing mental health before versus during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020. J Affect Disord. 2022;296:567–576.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Roy D, Sinha K, et al. Impact of COVID-19 and lockdown on mental health of children and adolescents: a narrative review with recommendations. Psychiatry Res. 2020;293:113429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorisdottir IE, Agustsson G, Oskarsdottir SY, et al. Effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on adolescent mental health and substance use up to March 2022, in Iceland: a repeated, cross-sectional, population-based study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2023;7:347–357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahn SN. The potential impact of COVID-19 on health-related quality of life in children and adolescents: a systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:14740.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racine N, McArthur BA, Cooke JE, et al. Global prevalence of depressive and anxiety symptoms in children and adolescents during COVID-19: a meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatr. 2021;175:1142–1150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dun-Dery F, Xie J, Winston K, et al.; Pediatric Emergency Research Canada (PERC) COVID Study Group. Post-COVID-19 condition in children 6 and 12 months after infection. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:e2349613.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hilberath J, Mast AS, Holweg M, et al. Quality of life and healthcare utilization during the COVID-19 pandemic are more restricted in chronically ill than in healthy children: a tertiary care children’s hospital experience. Eur J Pediatr. 2024;183:1801–1810.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Y-B, Zeng N, Yuan K, et al. Prevalence and risk factor for long COVID in children and adolescents: a meta-analysis and systematic review. J Infect Public Health. 2023;16:660–672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez-Leon S, Wegman-Ostrosky T, Cipatli Azuyo Del Valle N, et al. Long-COVID in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analyses. Sci Rep. 2022;12:9950.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuodi P, Gorelik Y, Gausi B, et al. Characterization of post-COVID syndromes by symptom cluster and time period up to 12 months post-infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Infect Dis. 2023;134:1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Q, Zheng B, Daines L, et al. Long-term sequelae of COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis of one-year follow-up studies on post-COVID symptoms. Pathogens. 2022;11:269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen NN, Hoang VT, Dao TL, et al. Clinical patterns of somatic symptoms in patients suffering from post-acute long COVID: a systematic review. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2022;41:515–545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C, Haupert SR, Zimmermann L, et al. Global prevalence of post COVID-19 condition or long COVID: a meta-analysis and systematic review. J Infect Dis. 2022;226:1593–1607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrow AK, Malone LA, Kokorelis C, et al. Long-term COVID-19 sequelae in adolescents: the overlap with orthostatic intolerance and ME/CFS. Curr Pediatr Rep. 2022;10:31–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vernon SD, Funk S, Bateman L, et al. Orthostatic challenge causes distinctive symptomatic, hemodynamic and cognitive responses in long COVID and myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome. Front Med. 2022;9:917019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J, Han Z, Li X, et al. Risk factors for postural tachycardia syndrome in children and adolescents. PLoS One. 2014;9:e113625.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morello R, Martino L, Buonsenso D. Diagnosis and management of post-COVID (long COVID) in children: a moving target. Curr Opin Pediatr. 2023;35:184–192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malone LA, Morrow A, Chen Y, et al. Multi-disciplinary collaborative consensus guidance statement on the assessment and treatment of postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection (PASC) in children and adolescents. PM R. 2022;14:1241–1269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achkar M, Jamal O, Chaaban T. Post-COVID lung disease(s). Ann Thorac Med. 2022;17:137–144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heiss R, Tan L, Schmidt S, et al. Pulmonary dysfunction after pediatric COVID-19. Radiology. 2023;306:e221250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campos C, Prokopich S, Loewen H, et al. Long-term effect of COVID-19 on lung imaging and function, cardiorespiratory symptoms, fatigue, exercise capacity, and functional capacity in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Healthcare (Basel). 2022;10:2492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwendinger F, Knaier R, Radtke T, et al. Low cardiorespiratory fitness post-COVID-19: a narrative review. Sports Med. 2023;53:51–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbagelata L, Masson W, Iglesias D, et al. Cardiopulmonary exercise testing in patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome. Med Clin (Engl Ed). 2022;159:6–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barisione G, Brusasco V. Lung diffusing capacity for nitric oxide and carbon monoxide following mild-to-severe COVID-19. Physiol Rep. 2021;9:e14748.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raman B, Cassar MP, Tunnicliffe EM, et al. Medium-term effects of SARS-CoV-2 infection on multiple vital organs, exercise capacity, cognition, quality of life and mental health, post-hospital discharge. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;31:100683.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoeffl I, Raming R, Tratzky JP, et al. Cardiopulmonary function in paediatric post-COVID-19: a controlled clinical trial. Eur J Pediatr. 2024;183:1645–1655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goretzki SC, Brasseler M, Dogan B, et al. High prevalence of alternative diagnoses in children and adolescents with suspected long COVID-a single center cohort study. Viruses. 2023;15:579.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>