<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39443958</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1743-422X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>21</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virology journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virol J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Influence of COVID-19 pandemic on prevalence and genotype distribution of HPV in cervical cancer screening population.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>261</StartPage><MedlinePgn>261</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">261</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12985-024-02497-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Human Papillomavirus (HPV) DNA screening was a crucial element in the fight against cervical cancer and had been adopted in many countries, including China. However, the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic in March 2020 disrupted this program significantly.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The aim of this study is to investigate the prevalence and distribution of HPV genotypes among the population undergoing cervical cancer screening during the pandemic period. From January 2017 to December 2022, Peking Union Medical College Hospital gathered 45,496 cervical swabs from individuals undergoing cervical cancer screening. These samples were analyzed to detect fifteen high-risk HPV (HR-HPV) DNA types and a combination of two low-risk HPV (LR-HPV) types.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study revealed an overall infection rate of 11.24% (5,114/45,496), with 11.06% (5,032/45,496) of individuals infected with HR-HPV. The number of HPV screening patients and the infection rates of HPV, HR-HPV, LR-HPV, multiple genotype HPV (M-HPV), and single genotype HPV (S-HPV) during the pandemic were lower than those observed before the pandemic. Moreover, the age group with the highest percentage of infected individuals was under 45-49 years, with HPV52, HPV58, HPV16, and HPV51 being the most prevalent genotypes. Notably, HPV66 emerged as the fifth most commonly detected genotype during the pandemic. Additionally, among the eleven age groups examined, women under 25 exhibited the highest detection rate, with HPV52 and HPV16 infection rates exceeding those observed in the pre-pandemic period.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The findings of this study offer significant insights for shaping HPV prevention strategies and enhancing cervical cancer screening initiatives in China following the epidemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Han</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Xu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Coyote Bioscience Co., Ltd, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Zhuo</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Ruzhen</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Binghan</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Coyote Bioscience Co., Ltd, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Sabrina</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Coyote Bioscience Co., Ltd, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Yingchun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China. wuj8289@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Yi</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China. yijie0908@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2022-PUMCH-B-074</GrantID><Agency>National High Level Hospital Clinical Research Funding</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2022-PUMCH-A-139</GrantID><Agency>National High Level Hospital Clinical Research Funding</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Virol J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101231645</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1743-422X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D004279">DNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030361" MajorTopicYN="Y">Papillomavirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002583" MajorTopicYN="Y">Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="Y">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055088" MajorTopicYN="Y">Early Detection of Cancer</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D027383" MajorTopicYN="Y">Papillomaviridae</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004279" MajorTopicYN="N">DNA, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HPV genotype</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human papillomavirus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39443958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-024-02497-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12985-024-02497-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Pešut E, Đukić A, Lulić L, Skelin J, Šimić I, Milutin Gašperov N, Tomaić V, Sabol I, Grce M. Human papillomaviruses-Associated cancers: an update of current knowledge. Viruses 2021, 13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, Laversanne M, Soerjomataram I, Jemal A, Bray F. Global Cancer statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and Mortality Worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. Cancer J Clin. 2021;71:209–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruni LAG, Serrano B, Mena M, Collado JJ, Gómez D, Muñoz J, Bosch FX, de Sanjosé S. Human papillomavirus and related diseases in China. ICO/IARC Information Centre on HPV and Cancer (HPV Information Centre). 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walboomers JMM, Jacobs MV, Manos MM, Bosch FX, Kummer JA, Shah KV, Snijders PJF, Peto J, Meijer CJLM, Muoz N. Human papillomavirus is a necessary cause of invasive cervical cancer worldwide. J Pathol. 1999;189:12–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10451482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castellsagué X. Natural history and epidemiology of HPV infection and cervical cancer. Gynecol Oncol. 2008;110:S4–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18760711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serrano B, Brotons M, Bosch FX, Bruni L. Epidemiology and burden of HPV-related disease. Best Pract Res Clin Obstet Gynecol. 2018;47:14–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonde J, Bottari F, Iacobone AD, Cocuzza CE, Sandri M-T, Bogliatto F, Khan KS, Ejegod DM, Gary DS, Andrews JC. Human papillomavirus same genotype persistence and risk: a systematic review. J Lower Genit Tract Dis. 2021;25:27–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Liu T, Luo G, Sun X, Hu G, Lu Y, Xu H, Zou R, Luo H. Incidence, persistence and clearance of cervical human papillomavirus among women in Guangdong, China 2007–2018: a retrospective cohort study. J Infect Public Health. 2021;14:42–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33341483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh D, Vignat J, Lorenzoni V, Eslahi M, Ginsburg O, Lauby-Secretan B, Arbyn M, Basu P, Bray F, Vaccarella S. Global estimates of incidence and mortality of cervical cancer in 2020: a baseline analysis of the WHO Global Cervical Cancer Elimination Initiative. Lancet Global Health. 2023;11:e197–206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9848409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36528031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. WHO Director-General’s Opening Remarks at the Media Briefing on COVID-19–11 March 2020. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pujolar G, Oliver-Anglès A, Vargas I, Vázquez M-L. Changes in Access to Health Services during the COVID-19 pandemic: a scoping review. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2022, 19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuczyńska M, Matthews-Kozanecka M, Baum E. Accessibility to Non-COVID Health Services in the World during the COVID-19 pandemic: review. Front Public Health 2021, 9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simms KT, Steinberg J, Caruana M, Smith MA, Lew J-B, Soerjomataram I, Castle PE, Bray F, Canfell K. Impact of scaled up human papillomavirus vaccination and cervical screening and the potential for global elimination of cervical cancer in 181 countries, 2020–99: a modelling study. Lancet Oncol. 2019;20:394–407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30795950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hildesheim A, Gonzalez P, Kreimer AR, Wacholder S, Schussler J, Rodriguez AC, Porras C, Schiffman M, Sidawy M, Schiller JT, et al. Impact of human papillomavirus (HPV) 16 and 18 vaccination on prevalent infections and rates of cervical lesions after excisional treatment. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2016;215:e212211–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortiz AP, Gierbolini-Bermúdez A, Ramos-Cartagena JM, Colón-López V, Sonawane K, Deshmukh AA, Ortiz-Ortiz KJ. Cervical Cancer Screening among Medicaid patients during Natural disasters and the COVID-19 pandemic in Puerto Rico, 2016 to 2020. JAMA Netw Open 2021, 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Yi J, Dou Y-l, Chen Y, Kong L-j, Wu J. Prevalence and Genotype Distribution of Human Papillomavirus among Healthy Females in Beijing, China, 2016–2019. Infect Drug Resist. 2021;14:4173–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8519791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34675562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu X, Wang Y, Lv Z, Su J. Prevalence and genotype distribution of high-risk HPV infection among women in Beijing, China. J Med Virol. 2021;93:5103–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33847386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long W, Yang Z, Li X, Chen M, Liu J, Zhang Y, Sun X. HPV-16, HPV-58, and HPV-33 are the most carcinogenic HPV genotypes in Southwestern China and their viral loads are associated with severity of premalignant lesions in the cervix. Virol J 2018, 15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiang F, Guan Q, Liu X, Xiao H, Xia Q, Liu X, Sun H, Song X, Zhong Y, Yuan CH, Xiang Y. Distribution characteristics of different human papillomavirus genotypes in women in Wuhan, China. J Clin Lab Anal 2018, 32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, Li Y, Tang Y, Li Z, Wang S, Luo X, He T, Yin A, Luo M. Cervical HPV infection in Guangzhou, China: an epidemiological study of 198,111 women from 2015 to 2021. Emerg Microbes Infections 2023, 12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao S, Zhao X, Hu S, Lu J, Duan X, Zhang X, Chen F, Zhao F. Distribution of high-risk human papillomavirus genotype prevalence and attribution to cervical precancerous lesions in rural North China. Chin J Cancer Res. 2019;31:663–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6736663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31564809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCredie MRE, Sharples KJ, Paul C, Baranyai J, Medley G, Jones RW, Skegg DCG. Natural history of cervical neoplasia and risk of invasive cancer in women with cervical intraepithelial neoplasia 3: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet Oncol. 2008;9:425–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18407790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng L-l, Chen S-f, Yang F, Wang W-h, Xu C, Zheng L-y. High-risk HPV prevalence and genotype distribution among women in Liaocheng, Shandong Province, China from 2016 to 2022. Front Public Health 2023, 11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Guo N, Li B, Shang E, Wang J, Zhang M, Yang X. Prevalence and genotype distribution of human papillomavirus infections in Beijing, China between 2016 and 2020. Virol J 2023, 20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serra IGSS, Araujo ED, Barros GS, Santos FLSG, Gurgel RQ, Batista MVA. Prevalence of human papillomavirus types associated with cervical lesions in Sergipe state, Northeastern Brazil: high frequency of a possibly carcinogenic type. Epidemiol Infect. 2018;146:1184–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9134353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29781414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouedraogo RA, Zohoncon TM, Guigma SP, Angèle Traore IM, Ouattara AK, Ouedraogo M, Djigma FW, Obiri-Yeboah D, Ouedraogo C, Simpore J. Oncogenic human papillomavirus infection and genotypes characterization among sexually active women in Tenkodogo at Burkina Faso, West Africa. Papillomavirus Res. 2018;6:22–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6159001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30244072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martora F, Della Pepa ME, Grimaldi E, Franci G, Folliero V, Petrillo A, Schettino MT, De Franciscis P, Galdiero M, Galdiero M. Seven years prevalence and distribution of high and low risk HPV genotypes in women living in the metropolitan area of Naples. Cancer Epidemiol 2019, 63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juárez-González K, Paredes-Cervantes V, Gordillo-Rodríguez S, González-Guzmán S, Moncayo-Valencia X, Méndez-Martínez R, García-Carrancá A, Martínez-Ezquerro JD, Rivas-Ruiz R, Sánchez-Suárez P, et al. High prevalence of human papillomavirus type 66 in low-grade cervical lesions of Mexican women. Arch Virol. 2020;165:2633–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32812092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Louvanto K, Rintala Marjut A, Syrjänen Kari J, Grénman Seija E, Syrjänen Stina M. Genotype-specific persistence of Genital Human Papillomavirus (HPV) infections in women followed for 6 years in the Finnish Family HPV Study. J Infect Dis. 2010;202:436–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20557239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muñoz N, Bosch FX, de Sanjosé S, Herrero R, Castellsagué X, Shah KV, Snijders PJF, Meijer CJLM. Epidemiologic classification of human papillomavirus types Associated with Cervical Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2003;348:518–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12571259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trottier H, Mahmud S, Costa MC, Sobrinho JoP, Duarte-Franco E, Rohan TE, Ferenczy A, Villa LL, Franco EL. Human papillomavirus infections with multiple types and risk of cervical neoplasia. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2006;15:1274–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16835323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaturvedi AK, Katki HA, Hildesheim A, Rodríguez AC, Quint W, Schiffman M, Van Doorn L-J, Porras C, Wacholder S, Gonzalez P, et al. Human papillomavirus infection with multiple types: pattern of Coinfection and Risk of Cervical Disease. J Infect Dis. 2011;203:910–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3068034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21402543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wentzensen N, Nason M, Schiffman M, Dodd L, Hunt WC, Wheeler CM. No evidence for synergy between human papillomavirus genotypes for the risk of high-Grade squamous intraepithelial lesions in a large Population-based study. J Infect Dis. 2014;209:855–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3935473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24179110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li T, Chen S, Li X, Wu Z, Zhao Y, Cui J, Liu B, Chen F, Zhang X, Qiao Y, Chen W. The features of high-risk human papillomavirus infection in different female genital sites and impacts on HPV-based cervical cancer screening. Virol J 2023, 20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wendland EM, Villa LL, Unger ER, Domingues CM, Benzaken AS, Maranhão AGK, Kops NL, Bessel M, Caierão J, Hohenberger GF et al. Prevalence of HPV infection among sexually active adolescents and young adults in Brazil: the POP-Brazil Study. Sci Rep 2020, 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Ding C, Liu X, Zhou Y, Tian G, Lan L, Chen C, Yan D, Huang C, Fu X, et al. Worldwide burden of genital human papillomavirus infection in female sex workers: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Epidemiol. 2021;50:527–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33517415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J, Wang W, Wang Z, Wang Z, Wang Y, Wang J, Zhao W, Li D, Liu H, Hao M. Prevalence, genotype distribution and risk factors of cervical HPV infection in Yangqu, China: a population-based survey of 10086 women. Hum Vaccines Immunotherapeutics. 2019;16:1645–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gountas I, Favre-Bulle A, Saxena K, Wilcock J, Collings H, Salomonsson S, Skroumpelos A, Sabale U. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on HPV vaccinations in Switzerland and Greece: Road to Recovery. Vaccines 2023, 11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz-Valdez A, Palacio-Mejía LS, Quezada-Sánchez AD, Hernández-Ávila JE, Galicia-Carmona T, Cetina-Pérez LdC, Arango-Bravo EA, Isla-Ortiz D, Aranda-Flores CE, Uscanga-Sánchez S-R et al. Cervical cancer prevention program in Mexico disrupted due to COVID-19 pandemic: challenges and opportunities. Front Oncol 2023, 13.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>