<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39448631</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Experimental study on recycling rubber to increase the impact resistance of cement mortar.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>25230</StartPage><MedlinePgn>25230</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">25230</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-73834-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The COVID-19 pandemic has led to a surge in medical waste generation, posing hazards to both the environment and global health. The impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic's medical waste hazard may persist long after the pandemic itself subsides. Improper disposal of medical waste can contaminate environment, posing risks to ecosystems and public health. Discarded medical rubber gloves, for example, can become a source of infection, improper disposal of these gloves can escalate the spread of infectious diseases and increase the risk of transmission of the virus to the general public. This study proposes an innovative and sustainable method to reinforce cement mortar by adding recycled glove rubber as an additive to cement mortar to increase its resistance to impact loads. This study conducted uniaxial compression tests, separating hopkinson pressure bar (SHPB) experiments and SEM observations to evaluate the quasi-static compressive strength and dynamic stress of recycled rubber fiber mortar (RRFM) with varying recycled rubber fiber (RRF) contents (0, 1%, 2%, 3%). Strain curves, dynamic increase factor (DIF), energy absorption rules, failure modes, and microstructure of RRFM mixtures. The experimental results demonstrate that with the addition of RRF, the dynamic stress-strain curve flattens and the peak strain gradually increases. The RRFM sample shows stronger toughness. In comparison to regular cement mortar (NM), RRFM has a higher DIF and specific absorbed energy, a faster increase in dynamic compressive strength, and the ability to absorb more energy per unit volume. Under the same impact load, RRFM has fewer and smaller cracks than NM. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) testing also observed that RRF formed a strong connection pattern with the cement mortar matrix.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ran</LastName><ForeName>Tao</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Anhui University of Science and Technology, Huainan, 232001, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computing, Macquarie University, Macquarie Park, NSW, 2109, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pang</LastName><ForeName>Jianyong</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Anhui University of Science and Technology, Huainan, 232001, China. jypang@aust.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Di</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Anhui University of Science and Technology, Huainan, 232001, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cement mortar</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Recycled rubber</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Separating hopkinson pressure bar</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Waste management</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39448631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11502711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-73834-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-73834-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Karimi, H., Wassan, N., Ehsani, B., Tavakkoli-Moghaddam, R. &amp; Ghodratnama, A. Optimizing COVID-19 medical waste management using goal and robust possibilistic programming. Eng. Appl. Artif. Intell.131, 107838 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S. Assessing the impact of COVID-19 on waste generation: Focus on plastic, food, and medical wastes in South Korea. Heliyon9, e18881 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10428051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37593634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, J., Liu, X. &amp; Wang, W. COVID-19 medical waste transportation risk evaluation integrating type-2 fuzzy total interpretive structural modeling and Bayesian network. Expert Syst. Appl.213, 118885 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9507804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36188673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, C., Xie, Y., Liu, Y., Liu, J. &amp; Zhang, F. Two-phase COVID-19 medical waste transport optimisation considering sustainability and infection probability. J. Clean. Prod.389, 135985 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9833647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36647542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, C., Liu, J., Liu, Y., Wang, H. &amp; Liu, M. Digital twin-driven robust bi-level optimisation model for COVID-19 medical waste location-transport under circular economy. Comput. Ind. Eng.186, 109107 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idowu, G. A. &amp; Olonimoyo, E. A. How has COVID-19 medical face mask altered the dynamics of pollutants from incinerated wastes?. J. Hazard. Mater. Adv.11, 100351 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangkham, S. Face mask and medical waste disposal during the novel COVID-19 pandemic in Asia. Case Stud. Chem. Environ. Eng.2, 100052 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7543915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38620353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ran, T., Pang, J., Liu, Y., Zou, J. &amp; Cai, F. Improving concrete fatigue resistance with COVID-19 rubber gloves: An innovative sustainable approach. Case Stud. Constr. Mater.18, e01914 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilmartin-Lynch, S., Roychand, R., Saberian, M., Li, J. &amp; Zhang, G. Application of COVID-19 single-use shredded nitrile gloves in structural concrete: Case study from Australia. Sci. Total Environ.812, 151423 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8568329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34742992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ran, T., Pang, J. &amp; Zou, J. An emerging solution for medical waste: Reuse of COVID-19 protective suit in concrete. 1–18 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, F. et al. Advances and perspectives on the life-cycle impact assessment of personal protective equipment in the post-COVID-19 pandemic. J. Clean. Prod.437, 140783 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramalingam, S., Thamizhvel, R., Sudagar, S. &amp; Silambarasan, R. Production of third generation bio-fuel through thermal cracking process by utilizing Covid-19 plastic wastes. Mater. Today Proc.72, 1618–1623 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9529355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36213622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demir, A. T. &amp; Moslem, S. Evaluating the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on medical waste disposal using preference selection index with CRADIS in a fuzzy environment. Heliyon10, e26997 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10937520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38486721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masud, R. I. et al. A review on enhanced microplastics derived from biomedical waste during the COVID-19 pandemic with its toxicity, health risks, and biomarkers. Environ. Res.216, 114434 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9536876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36209789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dadwal, T., Kumar, V. &amp; Bhatia, U. Experimental investigation on the use of COVID-19 waste in bituminous concrete. Mater. Today Proc.74, 218–224 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9359932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35966411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury, T. et al. Estimation of the healthcare waste generation during COVID-19 pandemic in Bangladesh. Sci. Total Environ.811, 152295 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8656249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34896490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neves, R. A. F., Seixas, J. T. C., Rodrigues, N. &amp; Santos, L. N. Impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic restrictions on solid waste pollution in the worldwide iconic Copacabana Beach (Rio de Janeiro, Brazil). Mar. Pollut. Bull.181 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9217137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35759900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benson, N. U., Bassey, D. E. &amp; Palanisami, T. COVID pollution: Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on global plastic waste footprint. Heliyon7, e06343 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7896824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33655084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Q. et al. COVID-19 estimated to have increased plastics, diclofenac, and triclosan pollution in more than half of urban rivers worldwide. Cell Rep. Sustain.1, 100001 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doad, R., Gupta, R. &amp; Shitak, R. Evaluation of biomedical waste generation in Himachal Pradesh before and during the Covid 19 pandemic. Sci. Total Environ.906, 167689 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37820814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, W. et al. Risk evaluation of venue types and human behaviors of COVID-19 outbreaks in public indoor environments: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Environ. Pollut.341, 122970 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37979645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kathiravan, K. et al. Chorographic assessment on the overburden of single-use plastics bio-medical wastes risks and management during COVID-19 pandemic in India. Total Environ. Res. Themes7, 100062 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saxena, P., Pradhan, I. P. &amp; Kumar, D. Redefining bio medical waste management during COVID-19 in india: A way forward. Mater. Today Proc.60, 849–858 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8506110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34660210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilyas, S., Srivastava, R. R. &amp; Kim, H. Disinfection technology and strategies for COVID-19 hospital and bio-medical waste management. Sci. Total Environ.749, 141652 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7419320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32822917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alomari, A. H., Aga, O., El Sahmarany, L., Hegazi, M. &amp; Almulla, L. Public perception towards medical waste generated in the environment during the COVID-19 pandemic in Eastern Province. Saudi Arabia. Heliyon7, e08363 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8580859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34786514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohana, A. A. et al. Generation and consequence of nano/microplastics from medical waste and household plastic during the COVID-19 pandemic. Chemosphere311, 137014 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9619086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36328315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De-la-Torre, G. E. et al. Release of phthalate esters (PAEs) and microplastics (MPs) from face masks and gloves during the COVID-19 pandemic. Environ. Res.215 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9476362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36116495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katerusha, D. Attitude towards sustainability, study contents and the use of recycled concrete in building construction: Case study Germany and Switzerland. J. Clean. Prod.289, 125688 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nanayakkara, O. et al. Alkali activated slag concrete incorporating recycled aggregate concrete: Long term performance and sustainability aspect. Constr. Build. Mater.271, 121512 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Z., Chin, C. S., Xia, J., Lu, J. &amp; Wang, X. Exploring the sustainability of concrete with fly ash, recycled coarse aggregate and biomineralisation method by life cycle assessment. J. Clean. Prod.406, 137077 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coffetti, D. et al. Pathways towards sustainable concrete. Cem. Concr. Res.154, 106718 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, F., Zheng, W., Li, L., Feng, W. &amp; Ning, G. Mechanical and fatigue performance of rubber concrete. Constr. Build. Mater.47, 711–719 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He, L. et al. Research on the properties of rubber concrete containing surface-modified rubber powders. J. Build. Eng.35 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta, T., Siddique, S., Sharma, R. K. &amp; Chaudhary, S. Investigating mechanical properties and durability of concrete containing recycled rubber ash and fibers. J. Mater. Cycles Waste Manag.23, 1048–1057 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong, Q., Huang, B. &amp; Shu, X. Rubber modified concrete improved by chemically active coating and silane coupling agent. Constr. Build. Mater.48, 116–123 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, M., Lu, J., Ming, P. &amp; Yin, Y. Study of fracture properties and post-peak softening process of rubber concrete based on acoustic emission. Constr. Build. Mater.313, 125487 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su, P., Dai, Q., Li, M., Ma, Y. &amp; Wang, J. Investigation of the mechanical and shrinkage properties of plastic-rubber compound modified cement mortar with recycled tire steel fiber. Constr. Build. Mater.334, 127391 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, R. &amp; Dev, N. Mechanical and microstructural properties of rubberized concrete after surface modification of waste tire rubber crumb. Arab. J. Sci. Eng.47, 4571–4587 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, A. et al. Analytical evaluation of compressive strength for concrete with rubber fine aggregates and the predictive model. Constr. Build. Mater.345, 128359 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Zhuang, J., Shen, S. &amp; Dong, S. Experimental investigation on the impact resistance of rubber self-compacting concrete. Structures39, 691–704 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, W. et al. Compressive behaviour and fragment size distribution model for failure mode prediction of rubber concrete under impact loads. Constr. Build. Mater.273, 121767 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, Q., Shi, Y., Xu, Z., Ma, D. &amp; Huang, K. Research on a multivariate non-linear regression model of dynamic mechanical properties for the alkali-activated slag mortar with rubber tire crumb. Case Stud. Constr. Mater.17, e01371 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, J. et al. Reusing COVID-19 disposable nitrile gloves to improve the mechanical properties of expansive clay subgrade: An innovative medical waste solution. J. Clean. Prod.375, 134086 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9484270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36160313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham, T. M. et al. Dynamic compressive properties of lightweight rubberized concrete. Constr. Build. Mater.238, 117705 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, L., Yao, X., Di Luzio, G., Jiang, M. &amp; Han, Y. Mix optimization of hybrid steel and polypropylene fiber-reinforced concrete for anti-thermal spalling. J. Build. Eng.63, 105409 (2023).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>