<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39444725</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2523-2754</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jul-Sep</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Revista cientifica odontologica (Universidad Cientifica del Sur)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Cient Odontol (Lima)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>[Craniofacial osteomyelitis in a patient with systemic involvement: a case report].</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e213</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e213</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e213</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.21142/2523-2754-1203-2024-213</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This report presents the case of a 61-year-old male patient with diabetes, hypertension, and a history of severe COVID-19 with osteomyelitis of the frontal sinus and upper jaw. The patient reported intense pain in the facial and maxillary area for two months. The computed tomography images showed mucoperiosteal thickening of the maxillary sinus and the magnetic resonance imaging showed multiple lytic lesions at the frontal sinus level, as well as brain abscesses in the left frontal region that were correlated with the microbiological cultures. In the intraoral clinical examination, segments with a necrotic appearance of the upper jaw, orosinusal fistula and multiple dental infectious foci were observed. The patient was treated with antibiotics, analgesics, anti-inflammatories, insulin, and proton pump inhibitor. Trephination of the frontal sinus, drainage of the abscess and sequestrectomy in the maxilla were performed and sessions with a hyperbaric chamber were ordered.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Serpa-Romero</LastName><ForeName>Xiomara Zilena</ForeName><Initials>XZ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8012-4067</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Facultad de Odontología, Universidad del Magdalena. Santa Marta, Colombia. xiomaraserpa@gmail.com Universidad del Magdalena Facultad de Odontología Universidad del Magdalena Santa Marta Colombia xiomaraserpa@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guzmán-Maciel</LastName><ForeName>Gustavo Julio</ForeName><Initials>GJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7252-5461</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departamento Cirugía Maxilofacial. Clínica Mar Caribe, Santa Marta, Colombia. gguzman@unimagdalena.edu.co Departamento Cirugía Maxilofacial Clínica Mar Caribe Santa Marta Colombia gguzman@unimagdalena.edu.co.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Montes-García</LastName><ForeName>Raúl</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8389-012X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universidad del Magdalena. Santa Marta, Colombia. raulmontesag@unimagdalena.edu.co Universidad del Magdalena Universidad del Magdalena Santa Marta Colombia raulmontesag@unimagdalena.edu.co.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Romo-Pérez</LastName><ForeName>Camilo A</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9157-5093</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fundación Universitaria San Martín. Puerto Colombia, Colombia. camilo.romo@sanmartin.edu.co Universidad San Martín Fundación Universitaria San Martín Puerto Colombia Colombia camilo.romo@sanmartin.edu.co.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>spa</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D004740">English Abstract</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Osteomielitis craneofacial en un paciente con compromiso sistémico: reporte de un caso.</VernacularTitle><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Peru</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Cient Odontol (Lima)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918697384606676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2523-2794</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>Este informe presenta el caso de un paciente masculino de 61 años con diabetes, hipertensión y antecedentes de COVID-19 grave, con osteomielitis del seno frontal y maxilar superior. El paciente refirió dolor intenso en la zona facial y maxilar durante dos meses. Las imágenes de tomografía computarizada mostraron un engrosamiento mucoperióstico del seno maxilar y la resonancia magnética mostró múltiples lesiones líticas a nivel del seno frontal, así como abscesos cerebrales en la región frontal izquierda que se correlacionaron con los cultivos microbiológicos. En el examen clínico intraoral se observaron segmentos con aspecto necrótico del maxilar superior, fístula orosinusal y múltiples focos infecciosos dentales. El paciente fue tratado con antibióticos, analgésicos, antiinflamatorios, insulina e inhibidores de la bomba de protones. Se realizó trepanación del seno frontal, drenaje del absceso y secuestrotomía en el maxilar superior, y se solicitaron sesiones con cámara hiperbárica.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">brain abscess</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">osteomyelitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">osteonecrosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">post-COVID-19</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicto de intereses: Los autores declaran no tener conflictos de intereses</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39444725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21142/2523-2754-1203-2024-213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Serra MÁ. Las enfermedades crónicas no transmisibles y la pandemia por COVID-19. Finlay. 2020;10(2):78–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halboub E, Al-Maweri SA, Alanazi RH, Qaid NM, Abdulrab S. Orofacial manifestations of COVID-19 a brief review of the published literature. Braz Oral Res. 2020;34:e124. doi: 10.1590/1807-3107bor-2020.vol34.0124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1807-3107bor-2020.vol34.0124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33146320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bobamuratova DT, Boymuradov SA, Dar-Odeh NS, Kurbanov YK, Umarov RZ. Impact of COVID-19 disease and its treatment on the development of maxillofacial complications. Adv Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2021;4:100169–100169. doi: 10.1016/j.adoms.2021.100169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.adoms.2021.100169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arshad W, Mahmood Kamal M, Rafique Z, Rahat M, Mumtaz H. Case of maxillary actinomycotic osteomyelitis, a rare post COVID complication-case report. Ann Med Surg. 2022;80:104242–104242. doi: 10.1016/j.amsu.2022.104242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amsu.2022.104242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9339092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35936558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sai Krishna D, Raj H, Kurup P, Juneja M. Maxillofacial Infections in Covid-19 Era-Actuality or the Unforeseen 2 Case Reports. Indian J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2022;74(Suppl 2):2959–2962. doi: 10.1007/s12070-021-02618-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12070-021-02618-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8127475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34026593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Mahalawy H, El-Mahallawy Y, Dessoky NY, Ibrahim S, Amer H, Ayad HM, et al. Post-COVID-19 related osteonecrosis of the jaw (PC-RONJ) an alarming morbidity in COVID-19 surviving patients. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):544–544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9192922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35701730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta G, Gupta D, Gupta P, Gupta N. Osteonecrosis of Jaw as an Oral Manifestation of COVID-19 A Case Report. Acta Sci Dent Scienecs. 2021;5(4):21–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley DS, Barber MS, Kienle GS, Aronson JK, von Schoen-Angerer T, Tugwell P. CARE guidelines for case reports explanation and elaboration document. J Clin Epidemiol. 2017;89:218–235. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2017.04.026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2017.04.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28529185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebada HA, Abd El-Fattah AM, Tawfik A. Management of frontal sinus fungal osteomyelitis in the COVID 19 era A case series. J Craniomaxillofac Surg. 2022;50(9):692–698. doi: 10.1016/j.jcms.2022.07.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcms.2022.07.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9339170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35961885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huh S, Lee CY, Ohe JY, Lee JW, Choi BJ, Lee BS, et al. Chronic maxillary sinusitis and diabetes related maxillary osteonecrosis a case report. J Korean Assoc Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2015;41(6):332–337. doi: 10.5125/jkaoms.2015.41.6.332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5125/jkaoms.2015.41.6.332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4699935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26734561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jawanda MK, Narula R, Gupta S, Sharma V, Sidhu SK, Kaur N. Mixed Infections (Mucormycosis, Actinomycosis and Candidiasis) Leading to Maxillary Osteomyelitis in a Diabetic Mellitus Patient in Post COVID Phase First Case Report. Acta Medica (Hradec Kralove) 2021;64(4):218–223. doi: 10.14712/18059694.2022.5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14712/18059694.2022.5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35285444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora P, Kaur G, Tyagi N, Nair MK. Maxillary mucormycosis and concurrent osteomyelitis in a post-COVID-19 patient with new onset diabetes mellitus. Proc Bayl Univ Med Cent. 2023;36(3):389–391. doi: 10.1080/08998280.2023.2177081.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08998280.2023.2177081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10120457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37091750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan MA, Rahman T, Rahman SA, Hashmi GS, Ansari MK, Danish M, et al. Is post-COVID osteonecrosis of jaw (PCONJ) Masquerading as osteomyelitis A largest unicentric report of 13 cases. Adv Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2023;11:100435–100435. doi: 10.1016/j.adoms.2023.100435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.adoms.2023.100435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh A, Joshi A, Desai AK, Juturu U, Kurian DJ, Jain P, et al. Covid-19-associated fungal osteomyelitis of jaws and sinuses An experience-driven management protocol. Med Mycol. 2022;60(2):myab082–myab082. doi: 10.1093/mmy/myab082.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/mmy/myab082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8822410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35076069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>