<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39449915</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Disparities in Syphilis Trends and the Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic: A Joinpoint Analysis of Florida Surveillance Data (2013-2022).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69934</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69934</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69934</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69934</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Syphilis, a sexually transmitted infection caused by the bacterium ​​​​​​<i>Treponema pallidum</i>, has reemerged at an increasing rate globally in recent years, posing a significant public health concern. Visualizing and analyzing time series trends of syphilis across various demographics and geographic regions, and how syphilis trends varied during the pandemic coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), would help public health policymakers develop targeted strategies and interventions to effectively address the rising rates of syphilis, ultimately improving overall public health outcomes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS"> A retrospective study was conducted using surveillance data on infectious syphilis cases reported to the Florida Department of Health, between 2013 and 2022. Age-standardized syphilis rates (ASSRs) per 100,000 persons were calculated using the 2000 U.S. standard population data. The average annual percentage change (AAPC) in the ASSRs was analyzed according to age, gender, race, geographic locations, and the COVID-19 pandemic period to quantify the epidemiological syphilis trends using joinpoint regression models.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS"> In Florida, the ASSR significantly increased from 8.65/100,000 in 2013 to 23.08/100,000 in 2022 across different demographic groups, with an overall AAPC of 11.47 (95% confidence interval (CI): 9.85-13.43). This increase in the AAPC was more pronounced in females (AAPC = 20.97; 95% CI, 18.61-24.49) than in males (AAPC = 10.34; 95% CI, 8.19-12.98). The increasing trends of infectious syphilis were observed across all age groups, with greater increases among those aged 25-49 years (AAPC = 12.32; 95% CI, 10.09-15.18), aged 50-69 years (AAPC = 13.42; 95% CI, 9.41-18.89), and aged over 70 years (AAPC = 13.63; 95% CI, 9.23-21.95), compared to those aged less than 24 years (AAPC = 7.86; 95% CI, 7.06-8.81). The increasing trends were comparable across racial groups, with an AAPC of 8.08 (95% CI, 5.47-11.15) for Hispanics, 11.84 (95% CI, 10.02-14.09) for non-Hispanic Whites, 10.49 (95% CI, 8.75-12.66) for non-Hispanic Blacks, and 11.29 (95% CI, 5.28-19.57) for non-Hispanic individuals of other races, respectively. The AAPC for the COVID-19 pandemic period was 12.99 (95% CI, 8.48-16.21), which was comparable to the pre-pandemic period (AAPC = 11.58; 95% CI, 10.17-12.76), indicating that this upward trend in infectious syphilis persisted throughout the COVID-19 pandemic. At the county level, over the 10-year period, the average ASSRs ranged from 0.89/100,000 in 2013 to 25.41/100,000 in 2022, with the estimated AAPCs varied from 2.47 (95% CI, -1.89 to 6.92) in Monroe County to 50.01 (95% CI, 37.71-62.27) in Okaloosa County.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS"> The trend of infectious syphilis increases substantially from 2013 to 2022, with notable differences observed among age, gender, and geographic regions in Florida. Females experienced a greater rise in infectious syphilis cases compared to males. This upward trend in infectious syphilis persisted throughout the COVID-19 pandemic. Efforts are needed to implement strategies to address the rising syphilis rates within high-incidence groups and communities across the state.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Niu et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Niu</LastName><ForeName>Evan</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Office of Human Research, Memorial Healthcare System, Hollywood, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sareli</LastName><ForeName>Rachel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Office of Human Research, Memorial Healthcare System, Hollywood, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eckardt</LastName><ForeName>Paula</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease, Memorial Healthcare System, Hollywood, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sareli</LastName><ForeName>Candice</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Office of Human Research, Memorial Healthcare System, Hollywood, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Niu</LastName><ForeName>Jianli</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Office of Human Research, Memorial Healthcare System, Hollywood, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">joinpoint regression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">syphilis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">trend analysis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Memorial Healthcare System (MHS) Institutional Review Board issued approval MHS.2024.033. This study was reviewed by the Memorial Healthcare System (MHS) Institutional Review Board and was ruled exempt from review because it uses publicly available, deidentified data (MHS.2024.033). Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11499729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Evaluating the global, regional, and national impact of syphilis: results from the global burden of disease study 2019. Chen T, Wan B, Wang M, Lin S, Wu Y, Huang J. Sci Rep. 2023;13:11386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10349077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37452074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. World Health Organization: Global progress report on HIV, viral hepatitis and sexually transmitted infections, 2021.  [
May;
2024 
]. 2021. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240027077 https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240027077</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention: Sexually transmitted infections surveillance.  [
May;
2024 
]. 2022. https://www.cdc.gov/std/statistics/2022/default.htm https://www.cdc.gov/std/statistics/2022/default.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Screening for syphilis infection in nonpregnant adolescents and adults: US Preventive Services Task Force Reaffirmation Recommendation Statement. Mangione CM, Barry MJ, Nicholson WK, et al. JAMA. 2022;328:1243–1249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36166020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resurgence of syphilis in the United States: an assessment of contributing factors. Schmidt R, Carson PJ, Jansen RJ. Infect Dis (Auckl) 2019;12:1178633719883282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6798162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31666795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Repeat syphilis among HIV-infected men in Florida and Louisiana 2000-2018: implications for screening recommendations. Newman DR, Matthias J, Rahman MM, Brantley A, Peterman TA. AIDS Patient Care STDS. 2021;35:435–440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8715870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34739335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence of syphilis among people living with HIV and its implication for enhanced coinfection monitoring and management in China: a meta-analysis. Wu Y, Zhu W, Sun C, Yue X, Zheng M, Fu G, Gong X. Front Public Health. 2022;10:1002342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9618949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36324449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resurgence of sexually transmitted diseases in the US. Kuehn BM. JAMA. 2022;327:1951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35608573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The burden of chlamydia, gonorrhea, and syphilis in older adults in the United States: a systematic review. Htet KZ, Lindrose AR, O'Connell S, Marsh J, Kissinger P. Int J STD AIDS. 2023;34:288–298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36626249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Age adjustment using the 2000 projected U.S. population. Klein RJ, Schoenborn CA. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11676466/ Healthy People 2010 Stat Notes. 2001:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11676466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A join point regression analysis of trends in mortality due to osteoporosis in Spain. Dragomirescu I, Llorca J, Gómez-Acebo I, Dierssen-Sotos T. Sci Rep. 2019;9:4264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6414692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30862942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Examining associations in congenital syphilis infection and socioeconomic factors between California's small-to-medium and large metro counties. Fang J, Silva RM, Tancredi DJ, Pinkerton KE, Sankaran D. J Perinatol. 2022;42:1434–1439.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35739308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An update on the global epidemiology of syphilis. Kojima N, Klausner JD. Curr Epidemiol Rep. 2018;5:24–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6089383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30116697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Variation in patterns of racial and ethnic disparities in primary and secondary syphilis diagnosis rates among heterosexually active women by region and age group in the United States. Martin EG, Ansari B, Rosenberg ES, et al. Sex Transm Dis. 2022;49:330–337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8994035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35121717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention: Sexually transmitted disease surveillance 2017.  [
May;
2024 
]. 2018. https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/59237 https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/59237</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maternal syphilis rates tripled in the US between 2016 and 2022, data show. Tanne JH. BMJ. 2024;384:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38359912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exploring changes in maternal and congenital syphilis epidemiology to identify factors contributing to increases in congenital syphilis in Florida: a two time-period observational study (2013-2014 vs 2018-2019) Matthias J, Spencer EC, Bowen VB, Peterman TA. BMJ Open. 2022;12:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9422834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36008067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Increased methamphetamine, injection drug, and heroin use among women and heterosexual men with primary and secondary syphilis: United States, 2013-2017. Kidd SE, Grey JA, Torrone EA, Weinstock HS. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2019;68:144–148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6375651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30763294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rates of primary and secondary syphilis among White and Black Non-Hispanic men who have sex with men, United States, 2014. Grey JA, Bernstein KT, Sullivan PS, et al. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2017;76:0–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5634915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28749823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical and socioeconomic determinants of congenital syphilis in Posadas, Argentina. Parker LA, Deschutter EJ, Bornay-Llinares FJ, Hernandez-Aguado I, Silva G, Piragine Rdel C, Lumbreras B. Int J Infect Dis. 2012;16:0–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22321725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rise of syphilis surge amidst COVID-19 pandemic in the USA: a neglected concern. Nazir A, Masood W, Ahmad S, et al. Ann Med Surg (Lond) 2022;80:104239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9339075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35937637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rising syphilis rates during the COVID-19 pandemic. Stanford KA, Almirol E, Schneider J, Hazra A. Sex Transm Dis. 2021;48:0–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33783406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A national, county-level evaluation of the association between COVID-19 and sexually transmitted infections within the United States in 2020. Pollack CC, Bradburne J, Lee NK, et al. Sex Transm Dis. 2023;50:536–542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10348633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37213194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syphilis and the COVID-19 pandemic: did the lockdown stop risky sexual behavior? Bonato F, Ferreli C, Satta R, Rongioletti F, Atzori L. Clin Dermatol. 2021;39:710–713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34809778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The potential impact and availability of sexual health services during the COVID-19 pandemic. Nagendra G, Carnevale C, Neu N, Cohall A, Zucker J. Sex Transm Dis. 2020;47:434–436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7448722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32520878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syphilis in pregnancy: an ongoing public health threat. Eppes CS, Stafford I, Rac M. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2022;227:822–838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35932881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>