<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39446575</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1550-5022</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of public health management and practice : JPHMP</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Public Health Manag Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The NEW Soul Study: Implementation and Evaluation Impact From the Secular Trend of the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/PHH.0000000000002071</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="CONTEXT" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">In process evaluation research, secular trends refer to external factors unrelated to an intervention that impact implementation. The COVID-19 pandemic was a secular trend that affected the implementation of the Nutritious Eating with Soul (NEW Soul) study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This paper describes steps taken in modifying intervention delivery due to the secular trend of the pandemic. This paper also addresses process evaluation measures of dose delivered, dose received, and satisfaction.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">This study is a longitudinal study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study took place in Columbia, SC, from 2018 to 2021.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PARTICIPANTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">African American adults between 18 and 65 years old.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERVENTION" NlmCategory="METHODS">The NEW Soul study, a dietary lifestyle intervention, lasted 24 months.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES" NlmCategory="METHODS">Process evaluation variables of dose delivered, dose received, and satisfaction.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study team shifted intervention delivery and maintained the timeline of classes for participants and intervention activities. Dose delivered was higher in-person (7.0 out of 8) compared to online (6.4 out of 8; t = -3.92, P = .002). Attendance was higher in-person compared to online (t = 2.80, P = .006). Overall, satisfaction of the intervention was favorable in-person and online. Helpfulness of nutrition information in the class was rated lower online compared to in-person (t = 2.05, P = .04).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Even though the study team successfully shifted intervention delivery online, dose delivered was higher in-person. Evaluations of classes remained high across cohorts and for in-person and online classes. Future lifestyle interventions working with African American adults requires consistent flexibility in intervention delivery.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bernhart</LastName><ForeName>John A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6710-4195</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Author Affiliations: Department of Health Promotion, Education, and Behavior (Drs Bernhart and Turner-McGrievy, Ms Davey, Dr Okpara, and Ms Harrell), Prevention Research Center (Dr Wilcox), Department of Health Services, Policy, and Management (Dr Bailey), Department of Exercise Science (Dr Wilcox), Arnold School of Public Health, University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina; and Department of Psychiatry and Human Behavior (Dr Okpara), The Miriam Hospital and Warren Alpert Medical School of Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Turner-McGrievy</LastName><ForeName>Gabrielle M</ForeName><Initials>GM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1683-5729</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davey</LastName><ForeName>Marty</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5245-8879</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okpara</LastName><ForeName>Nkechi</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1364-5468</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harrell</LastName><ForeName>E Grace</ForeName><Initials>EG</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bailey</LastName><ForeName>Shiba</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2399-6923</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wilcox</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4992-4610</Identifier></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Public Health Manag Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9505213</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1078-4659</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>All authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PHH.0000000000002071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00124784-990000000-00382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Micha R, Shulkin ML, Peñalvo JL, et al. Etiologic effects and optimal intakes of foods and nutrients for risk of cardiovascular diseases and diabetes: systematic reviews and meta-analyses from the Nutrition and Chronic Diseases Expert Group (NutriCoDE). PLoS One. 2017;12(4):e0175149. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0175149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0175149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mozaffarian D. Dietary and policy priorities for cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and obesity: a comprehensive review. Circulation. 2016;133(2):187-225. doi:10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.018585.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.018585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogden CL, Fryar CD, Martin CB, et al. Trends in obesity prevalence by race and Hispanic origin—1999-2000 to 2017-2018. JAMA. 2020;324(12):1208-1210. doi:10.1001/jama.2020.14590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.14590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser G, Katuli S, Anousheh R, Knutsen S, Herring P, Fan J. Vegetarian diets and cardiovascular risk factors in black members of the Adventist Health Study-2. Public Health Nutr. 2015;18(3):537-545. doi:10.1017/S1368980014000263.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1368980014000263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson S. Soul Food: Classic Cuisine from the Deep South. Reprint ed. Grove Press; 1994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner-McGrievy G, Wilcox S, Frongillo EA, et al. The Nutritious Eating with Soul (NEW Soul) Study: study design and methods of a two-year randomized trial comparing culturally adapted soul food vegan vs. omnivorous diets among African American adults at risk for heart disease. Contemp Clin Trials. 2020;88:105897. doi:10.1016/j.cct.2019.105897.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cct.2019.105897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner-McGrievy GM, Wilcox S, Frongillo EA, et al. Effect of a plant-based vs omnivorous soul food diet on weight and lipid levels among African American adults: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Network Open. 2023;6(1):e2250626. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.50626.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.50626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner-McGrievy GM, Wilson MJ, Bailey S, et al. Effective recruitment strategies for African-American men and women: the nutritious eating with soul study. Health Educ Res. 2021;36(2):206-211. doi:10.1093/her/cyab003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/her/cyab003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller A. Soul Food: The Surprising Story of an American Cuisine, One Plate at a Time. The University of North Carolina Press; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oldways Preservation and Exchange Trust. Oldways African Heritage Pyramid. Published online 2011. https://oldwayspt.org/resources/oldways-african-heritage-pyramid</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NHLBI. Your Guide to Lowering Cholesterol with Therapeutic Lifestyle Changes (TLC); 2005. https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/public/heart/chol_tlc.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steckler AB, Linnan L. Process Evaluation for Public Health Interventions and Research. 1st ed. Jossey-Bass; 2002. http://catdir.loc.gov/catdir/toc/fy034/2002012702.html. Accessed July 6, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saunders RP. Implementation Monitoring and Process Evaluation. 1st ed. SAGE Publications, Inc; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner-McGrievy G, Halliday TM, Moore JB. COVID-19 messed up my research: insights from physical activity and nutrition translational research. Transl J Am Coll Sports Med. 2021;6(4):e000169. doi:10.1249/TJX.0000000000000169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1249/TJX.0000000000000169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saunders RP, Evans MH, Joshi P. Developing a process-evaluation plan for assessing health promotion program implementation: a how-to guide. Health Promot Pract. 2005;6(2):134-147. doi:10.1177/1524839904273387.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1524839904273387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernhart JA, Quattlebaum M, Eustis S, et al. “It’s Gonna Be Okay”-A qualitative exploration of the COVID-19 pandemic’s effects on African American participants during a dietary intervention study. J Acad Nutr Diet. 2023;123(12):1763-1771. doi:10.1016/j.jand.2023.07.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jand.2023.07.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson B, Schmidt E, Mallar C, et al. Risk and resilience of well-being in caregivers of young children in response to the COVID-19 pandemic. Transl Behav Med. 2021;11(2):305-313. doi:10.1093/tbm/ibaa124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/tbm/ibaa124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, McKee M, Torbica A, Stuckler D. Systematic literature review on the spread of health-related misinformation on social media. Soc Sci Med. 2019;240:112552. doi:10.1016/j.socscimed.2019.112552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2019.112552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhow C, Graham CR, Koehler MJ. Foundations of online learning: challenges and opportunities. Educ Psychol. 2022;57(3):131-147. doi:10.1080/00461520.2022.2090364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00461520.2022.2090364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>