<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39446608</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1600-0412</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Acta obstetricia et gynecologica Scandinavica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial of melatonin as an adjuvant agent for induction of labor: The MILO trial.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/aogs.14951</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Melatonin has been suggested to have a biological role in the onset and progress of labor. We tested the hypothesis that the addition of melatonin during an induction of labor will reduce the need for a cesarean birth.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIAL AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This trial underwent protocol amendments that are detailed in the main text of the article. This trial is registered with the Australian and New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry (ACTRN12616000311459). At a multi-center health service including secondary and tertiary obstetric hospitals, we performed a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in women with a singleton cephalic pregnancy, free of significant maternal or perinatal complications who were undergoing induction of labor (with or without cervical ripening). Women were randomized to 10 mg melatonin vs placebo, with cervical ripening as required, and then 6-h during their induction of labor to a maximum of four doses or until birth. The primary outcome was cesarean birth. Secondary outcomes included labor, maternal, and neonatal outcomes. Data were analyzed using intention to treat. Sub-group analyses based on mode of ripening and parity were also performed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Between 2019 and 2021 we randomized 189 women (103 to melatonin and 86 to placebo). The study was prematurely terminated due to logistical complications resulting from the COVID-19 pandemic. Cesarean rates were 28/103 (27.2%) in the melatonin group versus 20/84 (23.3%) in the placebo group (RR 1.17 95% CI 0.71-1.92). There were no significant differences in rate of cesarean birth between the melatonin and placebo groups for failure to progress (13.4% and 9.3%, respectively, RR 1.46; 95% CI 0.64-3.32) or suspected fetal distress (10.7% and 10.5%, respectively, RR 1.02; 95% CI 0.44-2.34). The melatonin group had significantly lower rates of spontaneous vaginal birth within 24 h (35.0% vs. 50.0%; RR 0.70 95% CI 0.50-0.98). The rates of secondary outcomes such as total length of labor, rate of postpartum hemorrhage, and instrumental birth were comparable. Babies born in the melatonin group were more likely to need admission to the special care nursery, namely for hypoglycemic monitoring (18.5% vs. 8.1% RR 2.26; 95% CI 1.00-5.10).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In women undergoing induction of labor, melatonin does not reduce the cesarean section rate. Melatonin use intrapartum may also be associated with neonatal hypoglycemia.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Acta Obstetricia et Gynecologica Scandinavica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Nordic Federation of Societies of Obstetrics and Gynecology (NFOG).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Quach</LastName><ForeName>Diane</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2638-209X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash Women's, Monash Health, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mol</LastName><ForeName>Ben W</ForeName><Initials>BW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8337-550X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Aberdeen Centre for Women's Health Research, School of Medicine, Medical Sciences and Nutrition, University of Aberdeen, Aberdeen, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Springer</LastName><ForeName>Jamie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash Women's, Monash Health, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tully</LastName><ForeName>Erin</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash Women's, Monash Health, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Higgins</LastName><ForeName>Chloe</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash Women's, Monash Health, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jones</LastName><ForeName>Madeleine</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash Women's, Monash Health, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hennes</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash Women's, Monash Health, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pham</LastName><ForeName>Yen</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Ritchie Centre, Hudson Institute of Medical Research, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Swarnamani</LastName><ForeName>Kamala</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Ritchie Centre, Hudson Institute of Medical Research, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Palmer</LastName><ForeName>Kirsten</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash Women's, Monash Health, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davies-Tuck</LastName><ForeName>Miranda</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1918-5538</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Ritchie Centre, Hudson Institute of Medical Research, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>APP1123498</GrantID><Agency>National Health and Medical Research Council</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370343</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0001-6349</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cesarean birth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hypoglycemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">induction of labor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">melatonin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">obstetrics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacokinetics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/aogs.14951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Welfare AIoHa. Australia's mothers and babies 2022, 2022. https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/mothers‐babies/australias‐mothers‐babies/contents/summary</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grobman WA, Rice MM, Reddy UM, et al. Labor induction versus expectant management in low‐risk nulliparous women. N Engl J Med. 2018;379:513‐523.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biaggi A, Conroy S, Pawlby S, Pariante CM. Identifying the women at risk of antenatal anxiety and depression: a systematic review. J Affect Disord. 2016;191:62‐77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel A, Bucher S, Pusdekar Y, et al. Rates and determinants of early initiation of breastfeeding and exclusive breast feeding at 42 days postnatal in six low and middle‐income countries: a prospective cohort study. Reprod Health. 2015;12(Suppl 2):S10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Portela DS, Vieira TO, Matos SM, de Oliveira NF, Vieira GO. Maternal obesity, environmental factors, cesarean delivery and breastfeeding as determinants of overweight and obesity in children: results from a cohort. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2015;15:94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nedberg IH, Rylander C, Skjeldestad FE, Blix E, Ugulava T, Anda EE. Factors associated with cesarean section among primiparous women in Georgia: a registry‐based study. J Epidemiol Glob Health. 2020;10:337‐343.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCarthy R, Jungheim ES, Fay JC, Bates K, Herzog ED, England SK. Riding the rhythm of melatonin through pregnancy to deliver on time. Front Endocrinol. 2019;10:616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charles E. The hour of birth; a study of the distribution of times of onset of labor and of delivery throughout the 24‐hour period. Br J Prev Soc Med. 1953;7:43‐59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seron‐Ferre M, Ducsay CA, Valenzuela GJ. Circadian rhythms during pregnancy. Endocr Rev. 1993;14:594‐609.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honnebier MBOM, Nathanielsz PW. Primate parturition and the role of the maternal circadian system. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 1994;55:193‐203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olcese J, Lozier S, Paradise C. Melatonin and the circadian timing of human parturition. Reprod Sci. 2013;20:168‐174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharkey JT, Puttaramu R, Word RA, Olcese J. Melatonin synergizes with oxytocin to enhance contractility of human myometrial smooth muscle cells. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2009;94:421‐427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman SA, Bibbo C, Olcese J, Czeisler CA, Robinson JN, Klerman EB. Relationship between endogenous melatonin concentrations and uterine contractions in late third trimester of human pregnancy. J Pineal Res. 2019;66:e12566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakker JJ, De Vos R, Pel M, et al. Start of induction of labor with oxytocin in the morning or in the evening. A randomized controlled trial. BJOG. 2009;116:562‐568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fulia F, Gitto E, Cuzzocrea S, et al. Increased levels of malondialdehyde and nitrite/nitrate in the blood of asphyxiated newborns: reduction by melatonin. J Pineal Res. 2001;31:343‐349.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gitto E, Pellegrino S, Gitto P, Barberi I, Reiter RJ. Oxidative stress of the newborn in the pre‐ and postnatal period and the clinical utility of melatonin. J Pineal Res. 2009;46:128‐139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen LP, Gogenur I, Rosenberg J, Reiter RJ. The safety of melatonin in humans. Clin Drug Investig. 2016;36:169‐175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reiter RJ, Tan DX, Manchester LC, Paredes SD, Mayo JC, Sainz RM. Melatonin and reproduction revisited. Biol Reprod. 2009;81:445‐456.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silman RE. Melatonin: a contraceptive for the nineties. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 1993;49:3‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okatani Y, Okamoto K, Hayashi K, Wakatsuki A, Tamura S, Sagara Y. Maternal‐fetal transfer of melatonin in pregnant women near term. J Pineal Res. 1998;25:129‐134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobson SR, Gurusinghe S, Lim R, et al. Melatonin improves endothelial function in vitro and prolongs pregnancy in women with early‐onset preeclampsia. J Pineal Res. 2018;65:e12508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller SL, Yawno T, Alers NO, et al. Antenatal antioxidant treatment with melatonin to decrease newborn neurodevelopmental deficits and brain injury caused by fetal growth restriction. J Pineal Res. 2014;56:283‐294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swarnamani K, Davies‐Tuck M, Wallace E, Mol BW, Mockler J. A double‐blind randomized placebo‐controlled trial of melatonin as an adjuvant agent in induction of labor (MILO): a study protocol. BMJ Open. 2020;10:e032480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wormer K, Bauer A, Williford A. Bishop Score, 2024. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK470368/#:~:text=The%20most%20common%20modification%20to,than%205%20is%20considered%20favorable.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Promotion OoDPaH. Healthy people targets 2020—maternal, infant and child health ODPHD, 2024. https://wayback.archive‐it.org/5774/20220414032744/https://www.healthypeople.gov/2020/topics‐objectives/topic/maternal‐infant‐and‐child‐health/objectives</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho JH, Bhutani S, Kim CH, Irwin MR. Anti‐inflammatory effects of melatonin: a systematic review and meta‐analysis of clinical trials. Brain Behav Immun. 2021;93:245‐253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomez‐Lopez N, StLouis D, Lehr MA, Sanchez‐Rodriguez EN, Arenas‐Hernandez M. Immune cells in term and preterm labor. Cell Mol Immunol. 2014;11:571‐581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakker R, Pierce S, Myers D. The role of prostaglandins E1 and E2, dinoprostone, and misoprostol in cervical ripening and the induction of labor: a mechanistic approach. Arch Gynecol Obstet. 2017;296:167‐179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng WG, Tang ST, Tseng HP, Wu KK. Melatonin suppresses macrophage cyclooxygenase‐2 and inducible nitric oxide synthase expression by inhibiting p52 acetylation and binding. Blood. 2006;15(108):518‐524.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olcese J, Beesley S. Clinical significance of melatonin receptors in the human myometrium. Fertil Steril. 2014;102:329‐335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wierrani F, Grin W, Hlawka B, Kroiss A, Grunberger W. Elevated serum melatonin levels during human late pregnancy and labor. J Obstet Gynaecol. 1997;17:449‐451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pourhanifeh MH, Hosseinzadeh A, Dehdashtian E, Hemati K, Mehrzadi S. Melatonin: new insights on its therapeutic properties in diabetic complications. Diabetol Metab Syndr. 2020;12:30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nisa H, Qi KHT, Leng J, et al. The circadian rhythm‐related MTNR1B genotype, gestational weight gain, and postpartum glycemic changes. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2018;103:2284‐2290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laste G, Silva AAD, Gheno BR, Rychcik PM. Relationship between melatonin and high‐risk pregnancy: a review of investigations published between the years 2010 and 2020. Chronobiol Int. 2021;38:168‐181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Melo IMF, Ferreira CGM, Alves ER, et al. Melatonin administration prevents placental and fetal changes induced by gestational diabetes. Reprod Sci. 2022;29:1111‐1123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balduini W, Weiss MD, Carloni S, et al. Melatonin pharmacokinetics and dose extrapolation after enteral infusion in neonates subjected to hypothermia. J Pineal Res. 2019;66:e12565.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palmer KR, Mockler JC, Davies‐Tuck ML, et al. Protect‐me: a parallel‐group, triple blinded, placebo‐controlled randomized clinical trial protocol assessing antenatal maternal melatonin supplementation for fetal neuroprotection in early‐onset fetal growth restriction. BMJ Open. 2019;9:e028243.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Registry ANZCT. Melatonin supplementation effect on induction of labor rates in first time mothers: the MyTIME trial. Australian New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry, 2024. https://www.anzctr.org.au/Trial/Registration/TrialReview.aspx?id=385355&amp;isReview=true</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verteramo R, Pierdomenico M, Greco P, Milano C. The role of melatonin in pregnancy and the health benefits for the newborn. Biomedicine. 2022;10:3252.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>