<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39452140</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2079-7737</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biology (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Unveiling the Interplay-Vitamin D and ACE-2 Molecular Interactions in Mitigating Complications and Deaths from SARS-CoV-2.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">831</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/biology13100831</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The interaction of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein with membrane-bound angiotensin-converting enzyme-2 (ACE-2) receptors in epithelial cells facilitates viral entry into human cells. Despite this, ACE-2 exerts significant protective effects against coronaviruses by neutralizing viruses in circulation and mitigating inflammation. While SARS-CoV-2 reduces ACE-2 expression, vitamin D increases it, counteracting the virus's harmful effects. Vitamin D's beneficial actions are mediated through complex molecular mechanisms involving innate and adaptive immune systems. Meanwhile, vitamin D status [25(OH)D concentration] is inversely correlated with severity, complications, and mortality rates from COVID-19. This study explores mechanisms through which vitamin D inhibits SARS-CoV-2 replication, including the suppression of transcription enzymes, reduced inflammation and oxidative stress, and increased expression of neutralizing antibodies and antimicrobial peptides. Both hypovitaminosis D and SARS-CoV-2 elevate renin levels, the rate-limiting step in the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAS); it increases ACE-1 but reduces ACE-2 expression. This imbalance leads to elevated levels of the pro-inflammatory, pro-coagulatory, and vasoconstricting peptide angiotensin-II (Ang-II), leading to widespread inflammation. It also causes increased membrane permeability, allowing fluid and viruses to infiltrate soft tissues, lungs, and the vascular system. In contrast, sufficient vitamin D levels suppress renin expression, reducing RAS activity, lowering ACE-1, and increasing ACE-2 levels. ACE-2 cleaves Ang-II to generate Ang<sub>(1-7)</sub>, a vasodilatory, anti-inflammatory, and anti-thrombotic peptide that mitigates oxidative stress and counteracts the harmful effects of SARS-CoV-2. Excess ACE-2 molecules spill into the bloodstream as soluble receptors, neutralizing and facilitating the destruction of the virus. These combined mechanisms reduce viral replication, load, and spread. Hence, vitamin D facilitates rapid recovery and minimizes transmission to others. Overall, vitamin D enhances the immune response and counteracts the pathological effects of SARS-CoV-2. Additionally, data suggests that widely used anti-hypertensive agents-angiotensin receptor blockers and ACE inhibitors-may lessen the adverse impacts of SARS-CoV-2, although they are less potent than vitamin D.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wimalawansa</LastName><ForeName>Sunil J</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1096-8595</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CardioMetabolic and Endocrine Institute, North Brunswick, NJ 08902, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Biology (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101587988</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2079-7737</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">1,25(OH)2D</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">25(OH)D</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">calcitriol</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">endocrine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mechanisms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">morbidity and mortality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">renin-angiotensin axis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Despite the availability of over 200 independent RCTs and extensive data on vitamin D related to preventing and treating COVID-19 [200,294], regulatory agencies withheld approvals for the use of vitamin D [240,295]. Preventing access and use of widely available, cost-effective, generic agents, such as vitamin D and ivermectin [296,297], may have proven detrimental to patient welfare [193,242,295], increasing hospitalizations and deaths [48,132,240]. The actions mentioned above may have been driven by the desire to maintain Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) for vaccines and anti-viral agents [298]. However, this created a scenario for the approval and use of COVID-19 vaccines and anti-viral agents under (EUA), but not widely available, cost-effective generic agents like vitamin D and ivermectin [48,193,242,298]. The lack of approvals for repurposed early therapies may have harmed people [48,132,240,294,296,297,299].  The author has no conflicts of interest. </CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39452140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biology13100831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">biology13100831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Santaolalla A., Beckmann K., Kibaru J., Josephs D., Van Hemelrijck M., Irshad S. Association between vitamin D and novel SARS-CoV-2 respiratory dysfunction—A scoping review of current evidence and Its implication for COVID-19 pandemic. Front. Physiol. 2020;11:564387. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2020.564387.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphys.2020.564387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7726316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33324234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Global epidemic of coronavirus—COVID-19: What can we do to minimize risks? Eur. J. Biomed. Pharma Sci. 2020;7:432–438.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieth R. Why “Vitamin D” is not a hormone, and not a synonym for 1,25-dihydroxy-vitamin D, its analogs or deltanoids. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2004;89–90:571–573. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2004.03.037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2004.03.037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15225841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Infections and autoimmunity-The immune system and vitamin D: A Systematic Review. Nutrients. 2023;15:3842. doi: 10.3390/nu15173842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu15173842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10490553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37686873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Physiological basis for using vitamin D to improve health. Biomedicines. 2023;11:1542. doi: 10.3390/biomedicines11061542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biomedicines11061542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10295227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37371637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu J., Zhang M., Dong X., Long J., Li Y., Tan P., He T., Giovannucci E.L., Zhang X., Zhou Z., et al. Vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms, bioavailable 25-hydroxyvitamin D, and hepatocellular carcinoma survival. J. Natl. Cancer Inst. 2024 doi: 10.1093/jnci/djae116. Online ahead of print .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jnci/djae116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38830043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciocarlie T., Motofelea A.C., Motofelea N., Dutu A.G., Craciun A., Costachescu D., Roi C.I., Silaghi C.N., Crintea A. Exploring the role of vitamin D, vitamin D-dependent proteins, and vitamin D receptor gene variation in lung cancer risk. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2024;25:6664. doi: 10.3390/ijms25126664.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms25126664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11203461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38928369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voltan G., Cannito M., Ferrarese M., Ceccato F., Camozzi V. Vitamin D: An overview of gene regulation, ranging from metabolism to genomic effects. Genes. 2023;14:1691. doi: 10.3390/genes14091691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/genes14091691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10531002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37761831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamczak D.M. The role of Toll-Like receptors and vitamin D in cardiovascular diseases-A review. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2017;18:2252. doi: 10.3390/ijms18112252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms18112252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5713222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29077004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D., Kim M.A., Cho I.H., Kim M.S., Lee S., Jo E.K., Choi S.Y., Park K., Kim J.S., Akira S., et al. A critical role of toll-like receptor 2 in nerve injury-induced spinal cord glial cell activation and pain hypersensitivity. J. Biol. Chem. 2007;282:14975–14983. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M607277200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M607277200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17355971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu P.T., Stenger S., Li H., Wenzel L., Tan B.H., Krutzik S.R., Ochoa M.T., Schauber J., Wu K., Meinken C., et al. Toll-like receptor triggering of a vitamin D-mediated human antimicrobial response. Science. 2006;311:1770–1773. doi: 10.1126/science.1123933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1123933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16497887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koivisto O., Hanel A., Carlberg C. Key vitamin D target genes with functions in the immune system. Nutrients. 2020;12:1140. doi: 10.3390/nu12041140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12041140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7230898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32325790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S. Overcoming infections including COVID-19, by maintaining circulating 25(OH)D concentrations above 50 ng/mL. Pathol. Lab. Med. Int. 2022;14:37–60. doi: 10.2147/PLMI.S373617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/PLMI.S373617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veldman C.M., Cantorna M.T., DeLuca H.F. Expression of 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D(3) receptor in the immune system. Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 2000;374:334–338. doi: 10.1006/abbi.1999.1605.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1006/abbi.1999.1605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10666315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams J.S., Sharma O.P., Gacad M.A., Singer F.R. Metabolism of 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 by cultured pulmonary alveolar macrophages in sarcoidosis. J. Clin. Investig. 1983;72:1856–1860. doi: 10.1172/JCI111147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1172/JCI111147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC370476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6688814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoffels K., Overbergh L., Giulietti A., Verlinden L., Bouillon R., Mathieu C. Immune regulation of 25-hydroxyvitamin-D3-1alpha-hydroxylase in human monocytes. J. Bone Miner. Res. 2006;21:37–47. doi: 10.1359/JBMR.050908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1359/JBMR.050908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16355272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trochoutsou A.I., Kloukina V., Samitas K., Xanthou G. Vitamin-D in the immune system: Genomic and non-genomic actions. Mini Rev. Med. Chem. 2015;15:953–963. doi: 10.2174/1389557515666150519110830.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1389557515666150519110830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25985946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daneshkhah A., Agrawal V., Eshein A., Subramanian H., Roy H.K., Backman V. Evidence for possible association of vitamin D status with cytokine storm and unregulated inflammation in COVID-19 patients. Aging Clin. Exp. Res. 2020;32:2141–2158. doi: 10.1007/s40520-020-01677-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40520-020-01677-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7465887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32876941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. ACE inhibitors and angiotensin receptor blockers reduce the complications associated with COVID-19 infection. World J. Pharma Res. 2021;10:2579–2600. doi: 10.17605/OSF.IO/2ME36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17605/OSF.IO/2ME36</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michigami T. Rickets/osteomalacia. consensus on vitamin D deficiency and insufficiency in children. Clin. Calcium. 2018;28:1307–1311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30269111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gogulothu R., Nagar D., Gopalakrishnan S., Garlapati V.R., Kallamadi P.R., Ismail A. Disrupted expression of genes essential for skeletal muscle fibre integrity and energy metabolism in vitamin D deficient rats. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2020;197:105525. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2019.105525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2019.105525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31705962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffin G., Hewison M., Hopkin J., Kenny R.A., Quinton R., Rhodes J., Subramanian S., Thickett D. Perspective: Vitamin D supplementation prevents rickets and acute respiratory infections when given as daily maintenance but not as intermittent bolus: Implications for COVID-19. Clin. Med. 2021;21:e144–e149. doi: 10.7861/clinmed.2021-0035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7861/clinmed.2021-0035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8002781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33593830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schlumpf M., Reichrath J., Lehmann B., Sigmundsdottir H., Feldmeyer L., Hofbauer G.F., Lichtensteiger W. Fundamental questions to sun protection: A continuous education symposium on vitamin D, immune system and sun protection at the University of Zurich. Dermatoendocrinol. 2010;2:19–25. doi: 10.4161/derm.2.1.12016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4161/derm.2.1.12016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3084961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21547144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borges M.C., Martini L.A., Rogero M.M. Current perspectives on vitamin D, immune system, and chronic diseases. Nutrition. 2011;27:399–404. doi: 10.1016/j.nut.2010.07.022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2010.07.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20971616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Himani K.R., Haq A., Wimalawansa S.J., Sharma A. Putative roles of vitamin D in modulating immune response and immunopathology associated with COVID-19. Virus Res. 2020;292:198235. doi: 10.1016/j.virusres.2020.198235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2020.198235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7680047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33232783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dzik K.P., Kaczor J.J. Mechanisms of vitamin D on skeletal muscle function: Oxidative stress, energy metabolism and anabolic state. Eur. J. Appl. Physiol. 2019;119:825–839. doi: 10.1007/s00421-019-04104-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00421-019-04104-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6422984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30830277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogata M., Iwasaki N., Ide R., Takizawa M., Tanaka M., Tetsuo T., Sato A., Uchigata Y. Role of vitamin D in energy and bone metabolism in postmenopausal women with type 2 diabetes mellitus: A 6-month follow-up evaluation. J. Diabetes Investig. 2018;9:211–222. doi: 10.1111/jdi.12666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.12666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5754515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28371517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta R., Sharma U., Gupta N., Kalaivani M., Singh U., Guleria R., Jagannathan N.R., Goswami R. Effect of cholecalciferol and calcium supplementation on muscle strength and energy metabolism in vitamin D-deficient Asian Indians: A randomized, controlled trial. Clin. Endocrinol. 2010;73:445–451. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2010.03816.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2010.03816.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20455886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Controlling chronic diseases and acute infections with vitamin D sufficiency. Nutrients. 2023;15:3623. doi: 10.3390/nu15163623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu15163623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10459179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37630813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilz S., Tomaschitz A., Marz W., Drechsler C., Ritz E., Zittermann A., Cavalier E., Pieber T.R., Lappe J.M., Grant W.B., et al. Vitamin D, cardiovascular disease and mortality. Clin. Endocrinol. 2011;75:575–584. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2011.04147.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2011.04147.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21682758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Vitamin D and cardiovascular diseases: Causality. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2018;175:29–43. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2016.12.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2016.12.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28027913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieth R. How to optimize vitamin D supplementation to prevent cancer, based on cellular adaptation and hydroxylase enzymology. Anticancer. Res. 2009;29:3675–3684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19667164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X., Zhou M., Yan H., Chen J., Wang Y., Mo X. Association of serum total 25-hydroxy-vitamin D concentration and risk of all-cause, cardiovascular and malignancies-specific mortality in patients with hyperlipidemia in the United States. Front. Nutr. 2022;9:971720. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2022.971720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.971720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9631937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36337630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fletcher R.H. Calcium plus vitamin D did not prevent hip fracture or colorectal cancer in postmenopausal women. ACP J. Club. 2006;145:4–5. doi: 10.7326/ACPJC-2006-145-1-004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/ACPJC-2006-145-1-004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16813354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riddell L. Calcium plus vitamin D did not prevent fractures or colorectal cancer in postmenopausal women. Evid. Based Nurs. 2006;9:114. doi: 10.1136/ebn.9.4.114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/ebn.9.4.114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17076014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boucher B.J. Vitamin D deficiency in British South Asians, a persistent but avoidable problem associated with many health risks (including rickets, T2DM, CVD, COVID-19 and pregnancy complications): The case for correcting this deficiency. Endocr. Connect. 2022;11:e220234. doi: 10.1530/EC-22-0234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1530/EC-22-0234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9641767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36149836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hollis B.W., Wagner C.L. Vitamin D supplementation during pregnancy: Improvements in birth outcomes and complications through direct genomic alteration. Mol. Cell. Endocrinol. 2017;453:113–130. doi: 10.1016/j.mce.2017.01.039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2017.01.039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28188842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Musharaf S., Fouda M.A., Turkestani I.Z., Al-Ajlan A., Sabico S., Alnaami A.M., Wani K., Hussain S.D., Alraqebah B., Al-Serehi A., et al. Vitamin D deficiency prevalence and predictors in early pregnancy among Arab women. Nutrients. 2018;10:489. doi: 10.3390/nu10040489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu10040489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5946274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29662044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heyden E.L., Wimalawansa S.J. Vitamin D: Effects on human reproduction, pregnancy, and fetal well-being. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2018;180:41–50. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2017.12.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2017.12.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29262380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almuqbil M., Almadani M.E., Albraiki S.A., Alamri A.M., Alshehri A., Alghamdi A., Alshehri S., Asdaq S.M.B. Impact of vitamin D deficiency on mental health in university students: A cross-sectionalstudy. Healthcare. 2023;11:2097. doi: 10.3390/healthcare11142097.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/healthcare11142097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10379599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37510537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamilian H., Amirani E., Milajerdi A., Kolahdooz F., Mirzaei H., Zaroudi M., Ghaderi A., Asemi Z. The effects of vitamin D supplementation on mental health, and biomarkers of inflammation and oxidative stress in patients with psychiatric disorders: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Prog. Neuro-Psychopharmacol. Biol. Psychiatry. 2019;94:109651. doi: 10.1016/j.pnpbp.2019.109651.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pnpbp.2019.109651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31095994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi S., Mirzaei K., Hossein-Nezhad A., Shariati G. Vitamin D receptor FokI genotype may modify the susceptibility to schizophrenia and bipolar mood disorder by regulation of dopamine D1 receptor gene expression. Minerva Med. 2012;103:383–391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23042374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahan-Mihan A., Stevens P., Medero-Alfonso S., Brace G., Overby L.K., Berg K., Labyak C. The role of water-soluble citamins and vitamin D in prevention and treatment of depression and seasonal affective disorder in adults. Nutrients. 2024;16:1902. doi: 10.3390/nu16121902.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu16121902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11206829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38931257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Koning E.J., van Schoor N.M., Penninx B.W., Elders P.J., Heijboer A.C., Smit J.H., Bet P.M., van Tulder M.W., den Heijer M., van Marwijk H.W., et al. Vitamin D supplementation to prevent depression and poor physical function in older adults: Study protocol of the D-Vitaal study, a randomized placebo-controlled clinical trial. BMC Geriatr. 2015;15:151. doi: 10.1186/s12877-015-0148-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12877-015-0148-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4653865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26585952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martineau A.R., Jolliffe D.A., Hooper R.L., Greenberg L., Aloia J.F., Bergman P., Dubnov-Raz G., Esposito S., Ganmaa D., Ginde A.A., et al. Vitamin D supplementation to prevent acute respiratory tract infections: Systematic review and meta-analysis of individual participant data. BMJ. 2017;356:i6583. doi: 10.1136/bmj.i6583.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.i6583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5310969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28202713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jolliffe D.A., Griffiths C.J., Martineau A.R. Vitamin D in the prevention of acute respiratory infection: Systematic review of clinical studies. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2013;136:321–329. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2012.11.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2012.11.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23220552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quraishi S.A., Bittner E.A., Blum L., Hutter M.M., Camargo C.A., Jr. Association between preoperative 25-hydroxyvitamin D level and hospital-acquired infections following Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery. JAMA Surg. 2014;149:112–118. doi: 10.1001/jamasurg.2013.3176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2013.3176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4062917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24284777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Group-C19.com. Vitamin D for COVID-19: Real-Time Analysis of all 300 Studies.  [(accessed on 25 March 2024)].  Available online:  https://c19vitamind.com/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawahara T., Suzuki G., Mizuno S., Tominaga N., Toda M., Toyama N., Inazu T., Kawahara C., Okada Y., Tanaka Y. Active vitamin D treatment in the prevention of sarcopenia in adults with prediabetes (DPVD ancillary study): A randomised controlled trial. Lancet Healthy Longev. 2024;5:e255–e263. doi: 10.1016/S2666-7568(24)00009-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-7568(24)00009-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38437855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandra H., Rahman A., Yadav P., Maurya G., Kumar Shukla S. Effect of adjunct Vitamin D treatment in vitamin D deficient pulmonary tuberculosis patients: A randomized, double blind, active controlled clinical trial. Indian J. Tuberc. 2024;71:170–178. doi: 10.1016/j.ijtb.2023.04.026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijtb.2023.04.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38589121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Rapidly increasing serum 25(OH)D boosts the immune system, against infections-sepsis and COVID-19. Nutrients. 2022;14:2997. doi: 10.3390/nu14142997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14142997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9319502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35889955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karonova T.L., Chernikova A.T., Golovatyuk K.A., Bykova E.S., Grant W.B., Kalinina O.V., Grineva E.N., Shlyakhto E.V. Vitamin D intake may reduce SARS-CoV-2 infection morbidity in health care workers. Nutrients. 2022;14:505. doi: 10.3390/nu14030505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14030505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8839300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35276863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Extra-skeletal and endocrine functions and toxicity of vitamin D. J. Endocrinol. Diabetes. 2016;3:1–5. doi: 10.15226/2374-6890/3/3/00152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15226/2374-6890/3/3/00152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smaha J., Jackuliak P., Kuzma M., Max F., Binkley N., Payer J. Vitamin D deficiency prevalence in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 significantly fecreased during the pandemic in Slovakia from 2020 to 2022 Which Was associated with decreasing mortality. Nutrients. 2023;15:1132. doi: 10.3390/nu15051132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu15051132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10005285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36904131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S. Commonsense approaches to minimizing risks from COVID-19. Open J. Pulmonol. Respir. Med. 2020;2:28–37. doi: 10.36811/ojprm.2020.110010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36811/ojprm.2020.110010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Fighting against COVID-19: Boosting the immunity with micronutrients, stress reduction, physical activity, and vitamin D. Nutr. Food Sci. J. (Sci Lit.) 2020;3:126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giordano D., De Masi L., Argenio M.A., Facchiano A. Structural dissection of viral Spike-protein binding of SARS CoV-2 and SARS-CoV-1 to the human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) as cellular receptor. Biomedicines. 2021;9:1038. doi: 10.3390/biomedicines9081038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biomedicines9081038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8394803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34440241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mancini T., Macis S., Mosetti R., Luchetti N., Minicozzi V., Notargiacomo A., Pea M., Marcelli A., Ventura G.D., Lupi S., et al. Infrared Spectroscopy of SARS-CoV-2 Viral Protein: From Receptor Binding Domain to Spike Protein. Adv. Sci. 2024:e2400823. doi: 10.1002/advs.202400823.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.202400823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11497030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39001588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei C., Qian K., Li T., Zhang S., Fu W., Ding M., Hu S. Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 spike pseudotyped virus by recombinant ACE2-Ig. Nat. Commun. 2020;11:2070. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-16048-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-16048-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7265355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32332765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui D., Liu Y., Jiang X., Ding C., Poon L.C., Wang H., Yang H. Single-cell RNA expression profiling of SARS-CoV-2-related ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in human trophectoderm and placenta. Ultrasound Obstet. Gynecol. 2021;57:248–256. doi: 10.1002/uog.22186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/uog.22186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7461088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32851697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsuyama S., Kawase M., Nao N., Shirato K., Ujike M., Kamitani W., Shimojima M., Fukushi S. The inhaled steroid ciclesonide blocks SARS-CoV-2 RNA replication by targeting the viral replication-transcription complex in cultured cells. J. Virol. 2020;95:10-1128. doi: 10.1128/JVI.01648-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.01648-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7737752</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33055254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Shi Y., Reiss K., Allen B., Maschietto F., Lolis E., Konigsberg W.H., Lisi G.P., Batista V.S. Insights into binding of single-stranded viral RNA template to the replication-transcription complex of SARS-CoV-2 for the priming reaction from molecular dynamics simulations. Biochemistry. 2022;61:424–432. doi: 10.1021/acs.biochem.1c00755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.1c00755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8887646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35199520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang C., Barajas D., Qin J., Nagy P.D. Inactivation of the host lipin gene accelerates RNA virus replication through viral exploitation of the expanded endoplasmic reticulum membrane. PLoS Pathog. 2014;10:e1003944. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1003944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3930575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24586157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanyal S. How SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) spreads within infected hosts—What we know so far. Emerg. Top. Life Sci. 2020;4:371–378. doi: 10.1042/ETLS20200165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/ETLS20200165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7733667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33269805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malek Mahdavi A. A brief review of interplay between vitamin D and angiotensin-converting enzyme 2: Implications for a potential treatment for COVID-19. Rev. Med. Virol. 2020;30:e2119. doi: 10.1002/rmv.2119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.2119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7362103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32584474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas Vargas R.A., Varela Millan J.M., Fajardo Bonilla E. Renin-angiotensin system: Basic and clinical aspects-A general perspective. Endocrinol. Diabetes Nutr. (Engl. Ed.) 2022;69:52–62. doi: 10.1016/j.endien.2022.01.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.endien.2022.01.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8882059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35232560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaddam R.R., Chambers S., Bhatia M. ACE and ACE2 in inflammation: A tale of two enzymes. Inflamm. Allergy Drug Targets. 2014;13:224–234. doi: 10.2174/1871528113666140713164506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1871528113666140713164506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25019157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos R.A., Simoes e Silva A.C., Maric C., Silva D.M., Machado R.P., de Buhr I., Heringer-Walther S., Pinheiro S.V., Lopes M.T., Bader M., et al. Angiotensin-(1–7) is an endogenous ligand for the G protein-coupled receptor Mas. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2003;100:8258–8263. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1432869100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1432869100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC166216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12829792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fedson D.S. Treating the host response to emerging virus diseases: Lessons learned from sepsis, pneumonia, influenza and Ebola. Ann. Transl. Med. 2016;4:421. doi: 10.21037/atm.2016.11.03.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21037/atm.2016.11.03</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5124618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27942512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wee C.L., Azemi A.K., Mokhtar S.S., Yahaya S., Yaacob N.S., Rasool A.H.G. Vitamin D deficiency enhances vascular oxidative stress, inflammation, and angiotensin II levels in the microcirculation of diabetic patients. Microvasc. Res. 2023;150:104574. doi: 10.1016/j.mvr.2023.104574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mvr.2023.104574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37390963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kong J., Zhu X., Shi Y., Liu T., Chen Y., Bhan I., Zhao Q., Thadhani R., Li Y.C. VDR attenuates acute lung injury by blocking Ang-2-Tie-2 pathway and renin-angiotensin system. Mol. Endocrinol. 2013;27:2116–2125. doi: 10.1210/me.2013-1146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/me.2013-1146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3857197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24196349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beltran-Garcia J., Osca-Verdegal R., Pallardo F.V., Ferreres J., Rodriguez M., Mulet S., Sanchis-Gomar F., Carbonell N., Garcia-Gimenez J.L. Oxidative stress and Inflammation in COVID-19-associated sepsis: The potential role of anti-oxidant therapy in avoiding disease progression. Antioxidants. 2020;9:936. doi: 10.3390/antiox9100936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox9100936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7599810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33003552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosh A.P.M., Krishnananda K., Mohit Changani M., Patel N., Shenoy Belle V. Vitamin D as a biomarker in predicting sepsis outcome at a tertiary care hospital. Asian J. Med. Sci. 2023;14:89–94. doi: 10.3126/ajms.v14i11.57095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3126/ajms.v14i11.57095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan W., Pan W., Kong J., Zheng W., Szeto F.L., Wong K.E., Cohen R., Klopot A., Zhang Z., Li Y.C. 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3 suppresses renin gene transcription by blocking the activity of the cyclic AMP response element in the renin gene promoter. J. Biol. Chem. 2007;282:29821–29830. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M705495200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M705495200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17690094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson P.G., Qin L., Puah S.H. COVID-19 acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS): Clinical features and differences from typical pre-COVID-19 ARDS. Med. J. Aust. 2020;213:54–56.e51. doi: 10.5694/mja2.50674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5694/mja2.50674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32572965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLachlan C.S. The angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor in the prevention and treatment of COVID-19 are distinctly different paradigms. Clin. Hypertens. 2020;26:14. doi: 10.1186/s40885-020-00147-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40885-020-00147-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7360378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32685191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng H., Wang Y., Wang G.Q. Organ-protective effect of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 and its effect on the prognosis of COVID-19. J. Med. Virol. 2020;92:726–730. doi: 10.1002/jmv.25785.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.25785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7317908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32221983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devaux C.A., Rolain J.M., Raoult D. ACE2 receptor polymorphism: Susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2, hypertension, multi-organ failure, and COVID-19 disease outcome. J. Microbiol. Immunol. Infect. 2020;53:425–435. doi: 10.1016/j.jmii.2020.04.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmii.2020.04.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7201239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32414646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosso M., Thanaraj T.A., Abu-Farha M., Alanbaei M., Abubaker J., Al-Mulla F. The two faces of ACE2: The role of ACE2 receptor and Its polymorphisms in hypertension and COVID-19. Mol. Ther. Methods Clin. Dev. 2020;18:321–327. doi: 10.1016/j.omtm.2020.06.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.omtm.2020.06.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7314689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32665962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souza A.P., Sobrinho D.B., Almeida J.F., Alves G.M., Macedo L.M., Porto J.E., Vencio E.F., Colugnati D.B., Santos R.A., Ferreira A.J., et al. Angiotensin II type 1 receptor blockade restores angiotensin-(1–7)-induced coronary vasodilation in hypertrophic rat hearts. Clin. Sci. 2013;125:449–459. doi: 10.1042/CS20120519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/CS20120519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23718715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souza L.L., Costa-Neto C.M. Angiotensin-(1–7) decreases LPS-induced inflammatory response in macrophages. J. Cell. Physiol. 2012;227:2117–2122. doi: 10.1002/jcp.22940.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcp.22940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21769868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong W.Q., Bai B., Lin Y.P., Gao J., Yu N.S. Detection of the mRNA expression of human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 as a SARS coronavirus functional receptor in human femoral head. Nan Fang Yi Ke Da Xue Xue Bao. 2008;28:441–443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18359708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W., Moore M.J., Vasilieva N., Sui J., Wong S.K., Berne M.A., Somasundaran M., Sullivan J.L., Luzuriaga K., Greenough T.C., et al. Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 is a functional receptor for the SARS coronavirus. Nature. 2003;426:450–454. doi: 10.1038/nature02145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature02145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14647384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zisman L.S. ACE and ACE2: A tale of two enzymes. Eur. Heart J. 2005;26:322–324. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehi043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehi043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15671047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goulter A.B., Goddard M.J., Allen J.C., Clark K.L. ACE2 gene expression is up-regulated in the human failing heart. BMC Med. 2004;2:19. doi: 10.1186/1741-7015-2-19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-2-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC425604</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15151696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Q., Keller R.S., Weaver B., Zisman L.S. Interaction of ACE2 and integrin beta1 in failing human heart. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 2004;1689:175–178. doi: 10.1016/j.bbadis.2004.05.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbadis.2004.05.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15276642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M., Shi P., Sumners C. Direct anti-inflammatory effects of angiotensin-(1–7) on microglia. J. Neurochem. 2016;136:163–171. doi: 10.1111/jnc.13386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jnc.13386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4688174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26448556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mori J., Patel V.B., Ramprasath T., Alrob O.A., DesAulniers J., Scholey J.W., Lopaschuk G.D., Oudit G.Y. Angiotensin 1–7 mediates renoprotection against diabetic nephropathy by reducing oxidative stress, inflammation, and lipotoxicity. Am. J. Physiol. Renal Physiol. 2014;306:F812–F821. doi: 10.1152/ajprenal.00655.2013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajprenal.00655.2013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24553436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silveira K.D., Coelho F.M., Vieira A.T., Sachs D., Barroso L.C., Costa V.V., Bretas T.L., Bader M., de Sousa L.P., da Silva T.A., et al. Anti-inflammatory effects of the activation of the angiotensin-(1–7) receptor, MAS, in experimental models of arthritis. J. Immunol. 2010;185:5569–5576. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1000314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1000314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20935211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraga-Silva R.A., Pinheiro S.V., Goncalves A.C., Alenina N., Bader M., Santos R.A. The antithrombotic effect of angiotensin-(1–7) involves mas-mediated NO release from platelets. Mol. Med. 2008;14:28–35. doi: 10.2119/2007-00073.Fraga-Silva.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2119/2007-00073.Fraga-Silva</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2078558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18026570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel V.B., Zhong J.C., Grant M.B., Oudit G.Y. Role of the ACE2/angiotensin 1–7 axis of the renin-angiotensin system in heart failure. Circ. Res. 2016;118:1313–1326. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.307708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.307708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4939482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27081112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grobe J.L., Mecca A.P., Lingis M., Shenoy V., Bolton T.A., Machado J.M., Speth R.C., Raizada M.K., Katovich M.J. Prevention of angiotensin II-induced cardiac remodeling by angiotensin-(1–7) Am. J. Physiology. Heart Circ. Physiol. 2007;292:H736–H742. doi: 10.1152/ajpheart.00937.2006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00937.2006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17098828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurdi M., Booz G.W. New take on the role of angiotensin II in cardiac hypertrophy and fibrosis. Hypertension. 2011;57:1034–1038. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.111.172700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.111.172700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3098302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21502563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos S.H., Giani J.F., Burghi V., Miquet J.G., Qadri F., Braga J.F., Todiras M., Kotnik K., Alenina N., Dominici F.P., et al. Oral administration of angiotensin-(1–7) ameliorates type 2 diabetes in rats. J. Mol. Med. 2014;92:255–265. doi: 10.1007/s00109-013-1087-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00109-013-1087-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24162089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maleki M., Nematbakhsh M. Renal blood flow response to angiotensin 1–7 versus hypertonic sodium chloride 7.5% administration after acute hemorrhagic shock in rats. Int. J. Vasc. Med. 2016;2016:6562017. doi: 10.1155/2016/6562017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2016/6562017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4814681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27073699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DelliPizzi A.M., Hilchey S.D., Bell-Quilley C.P. Natriuretic action of angiotensin(1–7) Br. J. Pharmacol. 1994;111:1–3. doi: 10.1111/j.1476-5381.1994.tb14014.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1476-5381.1994.tb14014.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1910022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8012686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruhns R.P., Sulaiman M.I., Gaub M., Bae E.H., Davidson Knapp R.B., Larson A.R., Smith A., Coleman D.L., Staatz W.D., Sandweiss A.J., et al. Angiotensin-(1–7) improves cognitive function and reduces inflammation in mice following mild traumatic brain injury. Front. Behav. Neurosci. 2022;16:903980. doi: 10.3389/fnbeh.2022.903980.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnbeh.2022.903980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9386567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35990729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J., Zhao Y., Chen S., Wang J., Xiao X., Ma X., Penchikala M., Xia H., Lazartigues E., Zhao B., et al. Neuronal over-expression of ACE2 protects brain from ischemia-induced damage. Neuropharmacology. 2014;79:550–558. doi: 10.1016/j.neuropharm.2014.01.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2014.01.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3992949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24440367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regenhardt R.W., Mecca A.P., Desland F., Ritucci-Chinni P.F., Ludin J.A., Greenstein D., Banuelos C., Bizon J.L., Reinhard M.K., Sumners C. Centrally administered angiotensin-(1–7) increases the survival of stroke-prone spontaneously hypertensive rats. Exp. Physiol. 2014;99:442–453. doi: 10.1113/expphysiol.2013.075242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.2013.075242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7416533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24142453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos R.A.S., Sampaio W.O., Alzamora A.C., Motta-Santos D., Alenina N., Bader M., Campagnole-Santos M.J. The ACE2/Angiotensin-(1–7)/MAS axis of the renin-angiotensin system: Focus on angiotensin-(1–7) Physiol. Rev. 2018;98:505–553. doi: 10.1152/physrev.00023.2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/physrev.00023.2016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7203574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29351514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satou R., Penrose H., Navar L.G. Inflammation as a regulator of the renin-angiotensin system and blood pressure. Curr. Hypertens. Rep. 2018;20:100. doi: 10.1007/s11906-018-0900-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11906-018-0900-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6203444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30291560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benigni A., Cassis P., Remuzzi G. Angiotensin II revisited: New roles in inflammation, immunology and aging. EMBO Mol. Med. 2010;2:247–257. doi: 10.1002/emmm.201000080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/emmm.201000080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3377325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20597104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samavati L., Uhal B.D. ACE2, much more than just a receptor for SARS-COV-2. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 2020;10:317. doi: 10.3389/fcimb.2020.00317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2020.00317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7294848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32582574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monteil V., Kwon H., Prado P., Hagelkruys A., Wimmer R.A., Stahl M., Leopoldi A., Garreta E., Hurtado Del Pozo C., Prosper F., et al. Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 infections in engineered human tissues using clinical-grade soluble human ACE2. Cell. 2020;181:905–913.e907. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2020.04.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.04.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7181998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32333836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hollis B.W., Wagner C.L., Drezner M.K., Binkley N.C. Circulating vitamin D3 and 25-hydroxyvitamin D in humans: An important tool to define adequate nutritional vitamin D status. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2007;103:631–634. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2006.12.066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2006.12.066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1868557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17218096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bold A., Gross H., Holzmann E., Smetak M., Birkmann J., Bertsch T., Triebel J., Sauer K., Wilhelm M., Hoeres T. Immune activating and inhibiting effects of calcitriol on gammadelta T cells and NK cells. Immunobiology. 2022;227:152286. doi: 10.1016/j.imbio.2022.152286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.imbio.2022.152286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36244091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zdrenghea M.T., Makrinioti H., Bagacean C., Bush A., Johnston S.L., Stanciu L.A. Vitamin D modulation of innate immune responses to respiratory viral infections. Rev. Med. Virol. 2017;27:e1909. doi: 10.1002/rmv.1909.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.1909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27714929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gotelli E., Soldano S., Hysa E., Paolino S., Campitiello R., Pizzorni C., Sulli A., Smith V., Cutolo M. Vitamin D and COVID-19: Narrative review after 3 years of pandemic. Nutrients. 2022;14:4907. doi: 10.3390/nu14224907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14224907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9699333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36432593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Prophylactic use of vitamin D to maintain a robust immune system against infections like SARS-CoV-2. Glob. J. Endocrinol. Metab. GJEM. 2023;3:000571. doi: 10.31031/GJEM.2023.03.000571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31031/GJEM.2023.03.000571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pender M.P. CD8+ T-cell deficiency, Epstein-Barr virus infection, vitamin D deficiency, and steps to autoimmunity: A unifying hypothesis. Autoimmune Dis. 2012;2012:189096. doi: 10.1155/2012/189096.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2012/189096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3270541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22312480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quraishi S.A., Bittner E.A., Blum L., McCarthy C.M., Bhan I., Camargo C.A., Jr. Prospective study of vitamin D status at initiation of care in critically ill surgical patients and risk of 90-day mortality. Crit. Care Med. 2014;42:1365–1371. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000000210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000000210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4064717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24557421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez G.J., Ramirez-Mejia J.M., Castillo J.A., Urcuqui-Inchima S. Vitamin D modulates expression of antimicrobial peptides and proinflammatory cytokines to restrict Zika virus infection in macrophages. Int. Immunopharmacol. 2023;119:110232. doi: 10.1016/j.intimp.2023.110232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2023.110232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37150017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalantari N., Sepidarkish M., Ghaffari S., Rostami-Mansoor S. Does vitamin D reduce the mortality rate of Plasmodium infection?: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Malar. J. 2023;22:173. doi: 10.1186/s12936-023-04612-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-023-04612-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10243038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37277818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shoemaker M.E., Huynh L.M., Smith C.M., Mustad V.A., Duarte M.O., Cramer J.T. Immunomodulatory effects of vitamin D and prevention of respiratory tract infections and COVID-19. Top. Clin. Nutr. 2022;37:203–217. doi: 10.1097/TIN.0000000000000284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/TIN.0000000000000284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9222791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35761885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merzon E., Tworowski D., Gorohovski A., Vinker S., Golan Cohen A., Green I., Frenkel-Morgenstern M. Low plasma 25(OH) vitamin D level is associated with increased risk of COVID-19 infection: An Israeli population-based study. FEBS J. 2020;287:3693–3702. doi: 10.1111/febs.15495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/febs.15495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7404739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32700398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sposito F., Pennington S.H., David C.A.W., Duggan J., Northey S., Biagini G.A., Liptrott N.J., Charras A., McNamara P.S., Hedrich C.M. Age-differential CD13 and interferon expression in airway epithelia affect SARS-CoV-2 infection—Effects of vitamin D. Mucosal Immunol. 2023;16:776–787. doi: 10.1016/j.mucimm.2023.08.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mucimm.2023.08.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37574128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dror A.A., Morozov N., Daoud A., Namir Y., Yakir O., Shachar Y., Lifshitz M., Segal E., Fisher L., Mizrachi M., et al. Pre-infection 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 levels and association with severity of COVID-19 illness. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0263069. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0263069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0263069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8812897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35113901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gan Y., You S., Ying J., Mu D. The association between serum vitamin D levels and urinary tract infection risk in children: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Nutrients. 2023;15:2690. doi: 10.3390/nu15122690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu15122690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10305600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37375601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayrak H., Ozturk D., Bolat A., Unay B. Association between vitamin D levels and COVID-19 infection in children: A case-control study. Turk. Arch. Pediatr. 2023;58:250–255. doi: 10.5152/TurkArchPediatr.2023.22217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5152/TurkArchPediatr.2023.22217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10210747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37017281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raju A., Luthra G., Shahbaz M., Almatooq H., Foucambert P., Esbrand F.D., Zafar S., Panthangi V., Cyril Kurupp A.R., Khan S. Role of vitamin D deficiency in increased susceptibility to respiratory infections among children: A systematic review. Cureus. 2022;14:e29205. doi: 10.7759/cureus.29205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.29205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9573008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36259029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekele A., Gebreselassie N., Ashenafi S., Kassa E., Aseffa G., Amogne W., Getachew M., Aseffa A., Worku A., Raqib R., et al. Daily adjunctive therapy with vitamin D(3) and phenylbutyrate supports clinical recovery from pulmonary tuberculosis: A randomized controlled trial in Ethiopia. J. Intern. Med. 2018;284:292–306. doi: 10.1111/joim.12767.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joim.12767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6202271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29696707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salahuddin N., Ali F., Hasan Z., Rao N., Aqeel M., Mahmood F. Vitamin D accelerates clinical recovery from tuberculosis: Results of the SUCCINCT Study [Supplementary Cholecalciferol in recovery from tuberculosis]. A randomized, placebo-controlled, clinical trial of vitamin D supplementation in patients with pulmonary tuberculosis’. BMC Infect. Dis. 2013;13:22. doi: 10.1186/1471-2334-13-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-13-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3556334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23331510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quraishi S.A., De Pascale G., Needleman J.S., Nakazawa H., Kaneki M., Bajwa E.K., Camargo C.A., Jr., Bhan I. Effect of cholecalciferol supplementation on vitamin D status and cathelicidin levels in sepsis: A randomized, placebo-controlled trial. Crit. Care Med. 2015;43:1928–1937. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000001148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000001148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4537665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26086941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu G., Wu R., Zhang R., Chen D., Li H., Zheng Q., Ma Y. Preoperative vitamin D deficiency is associated with increased one-year mortality in Chinese geriatric hip fracture patients—A propensity score matching study. Clin. Interv. Aging. 2023;18:263–272. doi: 10.2147/CIA.S395228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/CIA.S395228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9945644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36843634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charoenngam N., Shirvani A., Reddy N., Vodopivec D.M., Apovian C.M., Holick M.F. Association of vitamin D status with hospital morbidity and mortality in adult hospitalized patients wth COVID-19. Endocr. Pract. 2021;27:271–278. doi: 10.1016/j.eprac.2021.02.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eprac.2021.02.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7939977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33705975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rustecka A., Maret J., Drab A., Leszczynska M., Tomaszewska A., Lipinska-Opalka A., Bedzichowska A., Kalicki B., Kubiak J.Z. The Impact of COVID-19 pandemic during 2020-2021 on the vitamin D serum levels in the paediatric population in Warsaw, Poland. Nutrients. 2021;13:1990. doi: 10.3390/nu13061990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13061990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8227523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34207901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borsche L., Glauner B., von Mendel J. COVID-19 mortality risk correlates inversely with vitamin D3 status, and a mortality rate close to zero could theoretically be achieved at 50 ng/mL 25(OH)D3: Results of a systematic review and meta-analysis. Nutrients. 2021;13:3596. doi: 10.3390/nu13103596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13103596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8541492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34684596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dudenkov D.V., Yawn B.P., Oberhelman S.S., Fischer P.R., Singh R.J., Cha S.S., Maxson J.A., Quigg S.M., Thacher T.D. Changing incidence of serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D values above 50 ng/mL: A 10-year population-based study. Mayo Clin. Proc. 2015;90:577–586. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2015.02.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mayocp.2015.02.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4437692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25939935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radujkovic A., Hippchen T., Tiwari-Heckler S., Dreher S., Boxberger M., Merle U. Vitamin D deficiency and outcome of COVID-19 patients. Nutrients. 2020;12:2757. doi: 10.3390/nu12092757.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12092757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7551780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32927735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J., Polonowita A. Boosting immunity with vitamin D for preventing complications and deaths from COVID-19; Proceedings of the COVID 19: Impact, Mitigation, Opportunities and Building Resilience “From Adversity to Serendipity,” Perspectives of Global Relevance Based on Research, Experience and Successes in Combating COVID-19 in Sri Lanka; Colombo, Sri Lanka. January 2021; pp. 171–198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baktash V., Hosack T., Patel N., Shah S., Kandiah P., Van Den Abbeele K., Mandal A.K.J., Missouris C.G. Vitamin D status and outcomes for hospitalised older patients with COVID-19. Postgrad. Med. J. 2020;97:442–447. doi: 10.1136/postgradmedj-2020-138712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/postgradmedj-2020-138712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7456620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32855214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Argano C., Mallaci Bocchio R., Natoli G., Scibetta S., Lo Monaco M., Corrao S. Protective effect of vitamin D supplementation on COVID-19-related intensive care hospitalization and mortality: Sefinitive evidence from meta-analysis and trial sequential analysis. Pharmaceuticals. 2023;16:130. doi: 10.3390/ph16010130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ph16010130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9864223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36678627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greiller C.L., Martineau A.R. Modulation of the immune response to respiratory viruses by vitamin D. Nutrients. 2015;7:4240–4270. doi: 10.3390/nu7064240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu7064240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4488782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26035247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cicero A.F.G., Fogacci F., Borghi C. Vitamin D supplementation and COVID-19 outcomes: Mounting evidence and fewer doubts. Nutrients. 2022;14:3584. doi: 10.3390/nu14173584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14173584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9460517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36079842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonen M.S., Alaylioglu M., Durcan E., Ozdemir Y., Sahin S., Konukoglu D., Nohut O.K., Urkmez S., Kucukece B., Balkan İ.İ., et al. Rapid and effective vitamin D supplementation may present better clinical outcomes in COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) patients by altering serum INOS1, IL1B, IFNg, cathelicidin-LL37, and ICAM1. Nutrients. 2021;13:4047. doi: 10.3390/nu13114047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13114047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8618389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34836309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jolliffe D.A., Camargo C.A., Jr., Sluyter J.D., Aglipay M., Aloia J.F., Ganmaa D., Bergman P., Bischoff-Ferrari H.A., Borzutzky A., Damsgaard C.T., et al. Vitamin D supplementation to prevent acute respiratory infections: A systematic review and meta-analysis of aggregate data from randomised controlled trials. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2021;9:276–292. doi: 10.1016/S2213-8587(21)00051-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-8587(21)00051-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33798465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong M., Xiong T., Huang J., Wu Y., Lin L., Zhang Z., Huang L., Gao D., Wang H., Kang C., et al. Association of vitamin D supplementation with respiratory tract infection in infants. Matern. Child. Nutr. 2020;16:e12987. doi: 10.1111/mcn.12987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/mcn.12987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7296792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32141233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiravi A.A., Saadatkish M., Abdollahi Z., Miar P., Khanahmad H., Zeinalian M. Vitamin D can be effective on the prevention of COVID-19 complications: A narrative review on molecular aspects. Int. J. Vitam. Nutr. Res. 2022;92:134–146. doi: 10.1024/0300-9831/a000676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1024/0300-9831/a000676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32811354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molloy E.J., Murphy N. Vitamin D, Covid-19 and Children. Ir. Med. J. 2020;113:64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32268052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stohs S.J., Aruoma O.I. Vitamin D and Wellbeing beyond Infections: COVID-19 and Future Pandemics. J. Am. Coll. Nutr. 2020;40:41–42. doi: 10.1080/07315724.2020.1786302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07315724.2020.1786302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32795138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garg M., Al-Ani A., Mitchell H., Hendy P., Christensen B. Editorial: Low population mortality from COVID-19 in countries south of latitude 35 degrees North-supports vitamin D as a factor determining severity. Authors’ reply. Aliment. Pharmacol. Ther. 2020;51:1438–1439. doi: 10.1111/apt.15796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apt.15796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7267669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32352178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaun F., Boesing M., Luthi-Corridori G., Abig K., Makhdoomi A., Bloch N., Lins C., Raess A., Grillmayr V., Haas P., et al. High-dose vitamin D substitution in patients with COVID-19: Study protocol for a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multi-center study-VitCov Trial. Trials. 2022;23:114. doi: 10.1186/s13063-022-06016-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13063-022-06016-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8814790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35120577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quesada-Gomez J.M., Lopez-Miranda J., Entrenas-Castillo M., Casado-Diaz A., Nogues Y.S.X., Mansur J.L., Bouillon R. Vitamin D endocrine system and COVID-19: Treatment with calcifediol. Nutrients. 2022;14:2716. doi: 10.3390/nu14132716.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14132716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9268645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35807895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maghbooli Z., Sahraian M.A., Jamalimoghadamsiahkali S., Asadi A., Zarei A., Zendehdel A., Varzandi T., Mohammadnabi S., Alijani N., Karimi M., et al. Treatment With 25-Hydroxyvitamin D3 (Calcifediol) Is Associated With a Reduction in the Blood Neutrophil-to-Lymphocyte Ratio Marker of Disease Severity in Hospitalized Patients With COVID-19: A Pilot Multicenter, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blinded Clinical Trial. Endocr. Pract. 2021;27:1242–1251. doi: 10.1016/j.eprac.2021.09.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eprac.2021.09.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8511889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34653608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling S.F., Broad E., Murphy R., Pappachan J.M., Pardesi-Newton S., Kong M.F., Jude E.B. High-dose cholecalciferol booster therapy is associated with a reduced risk of mortality in patients with COVID-19: A cross-sectional multi-centre observational study. Nutrients. 2020;12:3799. doi: 10.3390/nu12123799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12123799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7763301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33322317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Entrenas Castillo M., Entrenas Costa L.M., Vaquero Barrios J.M., Alcala Diaz J.F., Lopez Miranda J., Bouillon R., Quesada Gomez J.M. Effect of calcifediol treatment and best available therapy versus best available therapy on intensive care unit admission and mortality among patients hospitalized for COVID-19: A pilot randomized clinical study. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2020;203:105751. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2020.105751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2020.105751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7456194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32871238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahimzadeh A., Mohseni S., Narimani B., Ebrahimzadeh A., Kazemi S., Keshavarz F., Yaghoubi M.J., Milajerdi A. Association between vitamin D status and risk of covid-19 in-hospital mortality: A systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2021;63:5033–5043. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2021.2012419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.2012419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34882024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlSafar H., Grant W.B., Hijazi R., Uddin M., Alkaabi N., Tay G., Mahboub B., Al Anouti F. COVID-19 disease severity and death in relation to vitamin D status among SARS-CoV-2-positive UAE residents. Nutrients. 2021;13:1714. doi: 10.3390/nu13051714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13051714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8159141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34069412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bianconi V., Mannarino M.R., Figorilli F., Cosentini E., Batori G., Marini E., Lombardini R., Gargaro M., Fallarino F., Scarponi A.M., et al. Prevalence of vitamin D deficiency and its prognostic impact on patients hospitalized with COVID-19. Nutrition. 2021;91–92:111408. doi: 10.1016/j.nut.2021.111408.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2021.111408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8247197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34388589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies G., Mazess R.B., Benskin L.L. Letter to the editor in response to the article: “Vitamin D concentrations and COVID-19 infection in UK biobank” (Hastie et al.) Diabetes Metab. Syndr. 2021;15:643–644. doi: 10.1016/j.dsx.2021.02.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2021.02.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7871807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33722481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hastie C.E., Pell J.P., Sattar N. Vitamin D and COVID-19 infection and mortality in UK Biobank. Eur. J. Nutr. 2020;60:545–548. doi: 10.1007/s00394-020-02372-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00394-020-02372-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7449523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32851419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raisi-Estabragh Z., McCracken C., Bethell M.S., Cooper J., Cooper C., Caulfield M.J., Munroe P.B., Harvey N.C., Petersen S.E. Greater risk of severe COVID-19 in Black, Asian and Minority Ethnic populations is not explained by cardiometabolic, socioeconomic or behavioural factors, or by 25(OH)-vitamin D status: Study of 1326 cases from the UK Biobank. J. Public Health. 2020;42:451–460. doi: 10.1093/pubmed/fdaa095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/pubmed/fdaa095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7449237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32556213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazemi A., Mohammadi V., Aghababaee S.A., Golzarand M., Clark C.C.T., Babajafari S. Association of vitamin D status with SARS-CoV-2 infection or COVID-19 severity: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Adv. Nutr. 2021;12:1636–1658. doi: 10.1093/advances/nmab012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/advances/nmab012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7989595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33751020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hastie C.E., Mackay D.F., Ho F., Celis-Morales C.A., Katikireddi S.V., Niedzwiedz C.L., Jani B.D., Welsh P., Mair F.S., Gray S.R., et al. Vitamin D concentrations and COVID-19 infection in UK Biobank. Diabetes Metab. Syndr. 2020;14:561–565. doi: 10.1016/j.dsx.2020.04.050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.04.050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7204679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32413819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaufman H.W., Niles J.K., Kroll M.H., Bi C., Holick M.F. SARS-CoV-2 positivity rates associated with circulating 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels. PLoS ONE. 2020;15:e0239252. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0239252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0239252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7498100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32941512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown R.A. Preventing a COVID-19 pandemic-COVID-19. BMJ. 2020;368:m810. doi: 10.1136/bmj.m810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32111649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laird E., Rhodes J., Kenny R.A. Vitamin D and inflammation: Potential implications for severity of Covid-19. Ir. Med. J. 2020;113:81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32603576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Annweiler C., Hanotte B., Grandin de l’Eprevier C., Sabatier J.M., Lafaie L., Celarier T. Vitamin D and survival in COVID-19 patients: A quasi-experimental study. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2020;204:105771. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2020.105771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2020.105771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33065275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Annweiler G., Corvaisier M., Gautier J., Dubee V., Legrand E., Sacco G., Annweiler C. Vitamin D supplementation associated to better survival in hospitalized frail elderly COVID-19 patients: The GERIA-COVID Quasi-Experimental Study. Nutrients. 2020;12:3377. doi: 10.3390/nu12113377.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12113377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7693938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33147894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meltzer D.O., Best T.J., Zhang H., Vokes T., Arora V., Solway J. Association of vitamin D deficiency and treatment with COVID-19 incidence. medRxiv. 2020 doi: 10.1101/2020.05.08.20095893.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2020.05.08.20095893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meltzer D.O., Best T.J., Zhang H., Vokes T., Arora V., Solway J. Association of vitamin D status and other clinical characteristics with COVID-19 Test resultt. JAMA Netw. Open. 2020;3:e2019722. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.19722.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.19722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7489852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32880651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smaha J., Kuzma M., Brazdilova K., Nachtmann S., Jankovsky M., Pastirova K., Gazova A., Jackuliak P., Killinger Z., Kyselovic J., et al. Patients with COVID-19 pneumonia with 25(OH)D levels lower than 12 ng/ml are at increased risk of death. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 2022;116:313–318. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2022.01.044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2022.01.044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8783398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35077879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durazo-Arvizu R.A., Dawson-Hughes B., Kramer H., Cao G., Merkel J., Coates P.M., Sempos C.T. The reverse J-shaped association between serum Total 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentration and all-cause mortality: The impact of assay standardization. Am. J. Epidemiol. 2017;185:720–726. doi: 10.1093/aje/kww244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kww244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5394249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28338905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durup D., Jorgensen H.L., Christensen J., Schwarz P., Heegaard A.M., Lind B. A reverse J-shaped association of all-cause mortality with serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D in general practice: The CopD study. J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab. 2012;97:2644–2652. doi: 10.1210/jc.2012-1176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/jc.2012-1176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22573406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seal K.H., Bertenthal D., Carey E., Grunfeld C., Bikle D.D., Lu C.M. Association of Vitamin D Status and COVID-19-Related Hospitalization and Mortality. J. Gen. Intern. Med. 2022;37:853–861. doi: 10.1007/s11606-021-07170-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-021-07170-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8723909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34981368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bychinin M.V., Klypa T.V., Mandel I.A., Andreichenko S.A., Baklaushev V.P., Yusubalieva G.M., Kolyshkina N.A., Troitsky A.V. Low Circulating Vitamin D in Intensive Care Unit-Admitted COVID-19 Patients as a Predictor of Negative Outcomes. J. Nutr. 2021;151:2199–2205. doi: 10.1093/jn/nxab107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jn/nxab107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8194597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33982128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cervero M., Lopez-Wolf D., Casado G., Novella-Mena M., Ryan-Murua P., Taboada-Martinez M.L., Rodriguez-Mora S., Vigon L., Coiras M., Torres M. Beneficial effect of short-term supplementation of high dose of vitamin D(3) in hospitalized patients with COVID-19: A multicenter, single-blinded, prospective randomized pilot clinical trial. Front. Pharmacol. 2022;13:863587. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2022.863587.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.863587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9289223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35860019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gavioli E.M., Miyashita H., Hassaneen O., Siau E. An evaluation of serum 25-hydroxy vitamin D levels in patients with COVID-19 in New York City. J. Am. Nutr. Assoc. 2022;41:201–206. doi: 10.1080/07315724.2020.1869626.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07315724.2020.1869626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7898298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33605826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben-Eltriki M., Hopefl R., Wright J.M., Deb S. Association between vitamin D status and risk of developing severe COVID-19 infection: A meta-analysis of observational studies. J. Am. Coll. Nutr. 2021;41:679–689. doi: 10.1080/07315724.2021.1951891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07315724.2021.1951891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8425440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34464543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen N.N., Raju M.N.P., da Graca B., Wang D., Mohamed N.A., Mutnal M.B., Rao A., Bennett M., Gokingco M., Pham H., et al. 25-hydroxyvitamin D is a predictor of COVID-19 severity of hospitalized patients. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0268038. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0268038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0268038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9064100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35503795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takase T., Tsugawa N., Sugiyama T., Ikesue H., Eto M., Hashida T., Tomii K., Muroi N. Association between 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels and COVID-19 severity. Clin. Nutr. ESPEN. 2022;49:256–263. doi: 10.1016/j.clnesp.2022.04.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clnesp.2022.04.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8994250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35623823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauss D., Freiwald T., McGregor R., Yan B., Wang L., Nova-Lamperti E., Kumar D., Zhang Z., Teague H., West E.E., et al. Autocrine vitamin D signaling switches off pro-inflammatory programs of TH1 cells. Nat. Immunol. 2022;23:62–74. doi: 10.1038/s41590-021-01080-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41590-021-01080-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7612139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34764490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilezikian J.P., Bikle D., Hewison M., Lazaretti-Castro M., Formenti A.M., Gupta A., Madhavan M.V., Nair N., Babalyan V., Hutchings N., et al. Mechanisums in Endocrinology: Vitamin D and COVID-19. Eur. J. Endocrinol. 2020;183:R133–R147. doi: 10.1530/EJE-20-0665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1530/EJE-20-0665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9494342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32755992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewison M. Vitamin D and innate and adaptive immunity. Vitam. Horm. 2011;86:23–62. doi: 10.1016/B978-0-12-386960-9.00002-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-386960-9.00002-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21419266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh J.B., McCartney D.M., Laird E., McCarroll K., Byrne D.G., Healy M., O’Shea P.M., Kenny R.A., Faul J.L. Understanding a low vitamin D state in the context of COVID-19. Front. Pharmacol. 2022;13:835480. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2022.835480.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.835480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8931482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35308241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werneke U., Gaughran F., Taylor D.M. Vitamin D in the time of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic—A clinical review from a public health and public mental health perspective. Ther. Adv. Psychopharmacol. 2021;11:20451253211027699. doi: 10.1177/20451253211027699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20451253211027699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8274110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34290856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewison M. Vitamin D and immune function: Autocrine, paracrine or endocrine? Scand. J. Clin. Lab. Investig. Suppl. 2012;243:92–102. doi: 10.3109/00365513.2012.682862.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/00365513.2012.682862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22536769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aranow C. Vitamin D and the immune system. J. Investig. Med. 2011;59:881–886. doi: 10.2310/JIM.0b013e31821b8755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2310/JIM.0b013e31821b8755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3166406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21527855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bikle D.D. Vitamin D and the immune system: Role in protection against bacterial infection. Curr. Opin. Nephrol. Hypertens. 2008;17:348–352. doi: 10.1097/MNH.0b013e3282ff64a3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MNH.0b013e3282ff64a3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18660668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hollis B.W., Marshall D.T., Savage S.J., Garrett-Mayer E., Kindy M.S., Gattoni-Celli S. Vitamin D3 supplementation, low-risk prostate cancer, and health disparities. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2013;136:233–237. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2012.11.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2012.11.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23220550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewison M. Vitamin D and the immune system: New perspectives on an old theme. Endocrinol. Metab. Clin. N. Am. 2010;39:365–379. doi: 10.1016/j.ecl.2010.02.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecl.2010.02.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2879394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20511058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giannini S., Giusti A., Minisola S., Napoli N., Passeri G., Rossini M., Sinigaglia L. The immunologic profile of vitamin D and its role in different immune-mediated diseases: An expert opinion. Nutrients. 2022;14:473. doi: 10.3390/nu14030473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14030473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8838062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35276834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olliver M., Spelmink L., Hiew J., Meyer-Hoffert U., Henriques-Normark B., Bergman P. Immunomodulatory effects of vitamin D on innate and adaptive immune responses to Streptococcus pneumoniae. J. Infect. Dis. 2013;208:1474–1481. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jit355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jit355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23922371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schauber J., Dorschner R.A., Yamasaki K., Brouha B., Gallo R.L. Control of the innate epithelial antimicrobial response is cell-type specific and dependent on relevant microenvironmental stimuli. Immunology. 2006;118:509–519. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2567.2006.02399.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2567.2006.02399.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1782325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16895558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosseini A., Esmaeili Gouvarchin Ghaleh H., Aghamollaei H., Fasihi Ramandi M., Alishiri G., Shahriary A., Hassanpour K., Tat M., Farnoosh G. Evaluation of Th1 and Th2 mediated cellular and humoral immunity in patients with COVID-19 following the use of melatonin as an adjunctive treatment. Eur. J. Pharmacol. 2021;904:174193. doi: 10.1016/j.ejphar.2021.174193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2021.174193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8127523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34015316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q., Wang B., Mu K., Zhang J.A. The pathogenesis of thyroid autoimmune diseases: New T lymphocytes—Cytokines circuits beyond the Th1-Th2 paradigm. J. Cell. Physiol. 2019;234:2204–2216. doi: 10.1002/jcp.27180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcp.27180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30246383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Leung D.Y., Richers B.N., Liu Y., Remigio L.K., Riches D.W., Goleva E. Vitamin D inhibits monocyte/macrophage proinflammatory cytokine production by targeting MAPK phosphatase-1. J. Immunol. 2012;188:2127–2135. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1102412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1102412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3368346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22301548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panagiotou G., Tee S.A., Ihsan Y., Athar W., Marchitelli G., Kelly D., Boot C.S., Stock N., Macfarlane J., Martineau A.R., et al. Low serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25[OH]D) levels in patients hospitalized with COVID-19 are associated with greater disease severity. Clin. Endocrinol. 2020;93:508. doi: 10.1111/cen.14276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cen.14276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32621392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira M., Dantas Damascena A., Galvao Azevedo L.M., de Almeida Oliveira T., da Mota Santana J. Vitamin D deficiency aggravates COVID-19: Systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022;62:1308–1316. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2020.1841090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2020.1841090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33146028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng S., Yang J., Hu X., Li M., Wang Q., Dancer R.C.A., Parekh D., Gao-Smith F., Thickett D.R., Jin S. Vitamin D attenuates lung injury via stimulating epithelial repair, reducing epithelial cell apoptosis and inhibits TGF-beta induced epithelial to mesenchymal transition. Biochem. Pharmacol. 2020;177:113955. doi: 10.1016/j.bcp.2020.113955.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2020.113955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32251673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez-Moreno J.M., Herencia C., Montes de Oca A., Munoz-Castaneda J.R., Rodriguez-Ortiz M.E., Diaz-Tocados J.M., Peralbo-Santaella E., Camargo A., Canalejo A., Rodriguez M., et al. Vitamin D modulates tissue factor and protease-activated receptor 2 expression in vascular smooth muscle cells. FASEB J. 2016;30:1367–1376. doi: 10.1096/fj.15-272872.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1096/fj.15-272872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26700731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilie P.C., Stefanescu S., Smith L. The role of vitamin D in the prevention of coronavirus disease 2019 infection and mortality. Aging Clin. Exp. Res. 2020;32:1195–1198. doi: 10.1007/s40520-020-01570-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40520-020-01570-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7202265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32377965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Unlocking insights: Navigating COVID-19 challenges and emulating future pandemic resilience strategies with strengthening natural immunity. Heliyon. 2024;10:e34691. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e34691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e34691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11334859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39166024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeffery L.E., Burke F., Mura M., Zheng Y., Qureshi O.S., Hewison M., Walker L.S., Lammas D.A., Raza K., Sansom D.M. 1,25-Dihydroxyvitamin D3 and IL-2 combine to inhibit T cell production of inflammatory cytokines and promote development of regulatory T cells expressing CTLA-4 and FoxP3. J. Immunol. 2009;183:5458–5467. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.0803217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0803217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2810518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19843932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye K., Tang F., Liao X., Shaw B.A., Deng M., Huang G., Qin Z., Peng X., Xiao H., Chen C., et al. Does serum vitamin D level affect COVID-19 infection and Its severity?-A case-control study. J. Am. Coll. Nutr. 2021;40:724–731. doi: 10.1080/07315724.2020.1826005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07315724.2020.1826005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33048028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y.G., Wu S., Sun J. Vitamin D, vitamin D receptor, and tissue barriers. Tissue Barriers. 2013;1 doi: 10.4161/tisb.23118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4161/tisb.23118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3865708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24358453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Getachew B., Tizabi Y. Vitamin D and COVID-19: Role of ACE2, age, gender, and ethnicity. J. Med. Virol. 2021;93:5285–5294. doi: 10.1002/jmv.27075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33990955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin T.A., Das T., Mansel R.E., Jiang W.G. Enhanced tight junction function in human breast cancer cells by antioxidant, selenium and polyunsaturated lipid. J. Cell. Biochem. 2007;101:155–166. doi: 10.1002/jcb.21162.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcb.21162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17243118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander J., Tinkov A., Strand T.A., Alehagen U., Skalny A., Aaseth J. Early nutritional interventions with zinc, selenium and vitamin D for raising anti-viral resistance against progressive COVID-19. Nutrients. 2020;12:2358. doi: 10.3390/nu12082358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12082358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7468884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32784601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashique S., Gupta K., Gupta G., Mishra N., Singh S.K., Wadhwa S., Gulati M., Dureja H., Zacconi F., Oliver B.G., et al. Vitamin D-A prominent immunomodulator to prevent COVID-19 infection. Int. J. Rheum. Dis. 2023;26:13–30. doi: 10.1111/1756-185X.14477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1756-185X.14477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9874620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36308699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouzine I.M., Rozhnova G. Evolutionary implications of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination for the future design of vaccination strategies. Commun. Med. 2023;3:86. doi: 10.1038/s43856-023-00320-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43856-023-00320-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10279745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37336956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenaillon O., Matic I. The impact of neutral mutations on genome evolvability. Curr. Biol. 2020;30:R527–R534. doi: 10.1016/j.cub.2020.03.056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2020.03.056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32428494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konishi T. Mutations in SARS-CoV-2 are on the increase against the acquired immunity. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0271305. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0271305.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0271305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9273074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35816505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abeywardhana S., Premathilaka M., Bandaranayake U., Perera D., Peiris L.D.C. In silico study of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein RBD and human ACE-2 affinity dynamics across variants and Omicron subvariants. J. Med. Virol. 2023;95:e28406. doi: 10.1002/jmv.28406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9877981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36519577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuekprakhon A., Nutalai R., Dijokaite-Guraliuc A., Zhou D., Ginn H.M., Selvaraj M., Liu C., Mentzer A.J., Supasa P., Duyvesteyn H.M.E., et al. Antibody escape of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA.4 and BA.5 from vaccine and BA.1 serum. Cell. 2022;185:2422–2433.e2413. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2022.06.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2022.06.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9181312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35772405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dejnirattisai W., Zhou D., Ginn H.M., Duyvesteyn H.M.E., Supasa P., Case J.B., Zhao Y., Walter T.S., Mentzer A.J., Liu C., et al. The antigenic anatomy of SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain. Cell. 2021;184:2183–2200.e22. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7891125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33756110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hypponen E., Laara E., Reunanen A., Jarvelin M.R., Virtanen S.M. Intake of vitamin D and risk of type 1 diabetes: A birth-cohort study. Lancet. 2001;358:1500–1503. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(01)06580-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(01)06580-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11705562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Littorin B., Blom P., Scholin A., Arnqvist H.J., Blohme G., Bolinder J., Ekbom-Schnell A., Eriksson J.W., Gudbjornsdottir S., Nystrom L., et al. Lower levels of plasma 25-hydroxyvitamin D among young adults at diagnosis of autoimmune type 1 diabetes compared with control subjects: Results from the nationwide Diabetes Incidence Study in Sweden (DISS) Diabetologia. 2006;49:2847–2852. doi: 10.1007/s00125-006-0426-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-006-0426-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17072585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitri J., Muraru M.D., Pittas A.G. Vitamin D and type 2 diabetes: A systematic review. Eur. J. Clin. Nutr. 2011;65:1005–1015. doi: 10.1038/ejcn.2011.118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ejcn.2011.118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4066381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21731035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zold E., Szodoray P., Gaal J., Kappelmayer J., Csathy L., Gyimesi E., Zeher M., Szegedi G., Bodolay E. Vitamin D deficiency in undifferentiated connective tissue disease. Arthritis Res. Ther. 2008;10:R123. doi: 10.1186/ar2533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/ar2533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2592813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18928561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Pinto R., Pietropaoli D., Chandar A.K., Ferri C., Cominelli F. Association between inflammatory bowel disease and Vitamin D deficiency: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Inflamm. Bowel Dis. 2015;21:2708–2717. doi: 10.1097/MIB.0000000000000546.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MIB.0000000000000546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4615394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26348447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y.C., Wang W.W., Jiang W.Y., Li C.Q., Guo J.C., Xun Y.H. Low vitamin D levels are associated with high viral loads in patients with chronic hepatitis B: A systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Gastroenterol. 2019;19:84. doi: 10.1186/s12876-019-1004-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12876-019-1004-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6558894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31185932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bener A., Ehlayel M.S., Tulic M.K., Hamid Q. Vitamin D deficiency as a strong predictor of asthma in children. Int. Arch. Allergy Immunol. 2012;157:168–175. doi: 10.1159/000323941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000323941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21986034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garland C.F., Garland F.C., Gorham E.D., Lipkin M., Newmark H., Mohr S.B., Holick M.F. The role of vitamin D in cancer prevention. Am. J. Public Health. 2006;96:252–261. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2004.045260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2004.045260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1470481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16380576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garland C.F., Gorham E.D., Mohr S.B., Garland F.C. Vitamin D for cancer prevention: Global perspective. Ann. Epidemiol. 2009;19:468–483. doi: 10.1016/j.annepidem.2009.03.021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2009.03.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19523595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant W.B., Boucher B.J. Randomized controlled trials of vitamin D and cancer incidence: A modeling study. PLoS ONE. 2017;12:e0176448. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0176448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0176448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5411066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28459861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant W.B., Boucher B.J., Bhattoa H.P., Lahore H. Why vitamin D clinical trials should be based on 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentrations. J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2018;177:266–269. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2017.08.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2017.08.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28842142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marino R., Misra M. Extra-Skeletal Effects of Vitamin D. Nutrients. 2019;11:1460. doi: 10.3390/nu11071460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu11071460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6683065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31252594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Amelio P., Quacquarelli L. Hypovitaminosis D and aging: Is there a role in muscle and brain health? Nutrients. 2020;12:628. doi: 10.3390/nu12030628.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12030628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7146116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32121008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giustina A., Bouillon R., Dawson-Hughes B., Ebeling P.R., Lazaretti-Castro M., Lips P., Marcocci C., Bilezikian J.P. Vitamin D in the older population: A consensus statement. Endocrine. 2023;79:31–44. doi: 10.1007/s12020-022-03208-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12020-022-03208-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9607753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36287374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caccamo D., Ricca S., Curro M., Ientile R. Health risks of hypovitaminosis D: A review of new molecular insights. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2018;19:892. doi: 10.3390/ijms19030892.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms19030892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5877753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29562608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tikellis C., Thomas M.C. Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) Is a key modulator of the renin angiotensin system in health and disease. Int. J. Pept. 2012;2012:256294. doi: 10.1155/2012/256294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2012/256294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3321295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22536270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C., Chen X., Cai Y., Xia J., Zhou X., Xu S., Huang H., Zhang L., Zhou X., Du C., et al. Risk factors associated with acute respiratory distress syndrome and death in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 pneumonia in Wuhan, China. JAMA Intern. Med. 2020;180:934–943. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.0994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.0994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7070509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32167524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alloubani A., Akhu-Zaheya L., Samara R., Abdulhafiz I., Saleh A., Altowijri A. Relationship between vitamin D deficiency, diabetes, and obesity. Diabetes Metab. Syndr. 2019;13:1457–1461. doi: 10.1016/j.dsx.2019.02.021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2019.02.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31336506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y.X., Zhou L. Vitamin D deficiency, obesity and diabetes. Cell. Mol. Biol. 2015;61:35–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26068917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismailova A., White J.H. Vitamin D, infections and immunity. Rev. Endocr. Metab. Disord. 2022;23:265–277. doi: 10.1007/s11154-021-09679-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11154-021-09679-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8318777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34322844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarau O.S., Rachabattuni H.C., Gadde S.T., Daruvuri S.P., Marusca L.M., Horhat F.G., Fildan A.P., Tanase E., Prodan-Barbulescu C., Horhat D.I. Exploring the preventive potential of vitamin D against respiratory infections in preschool-age children: A cross-sectional study. Nutrients. 2024;16:1595. doi: 10.3390/nu16111595.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu16111595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11173803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38892528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stagi S., Rigante D., Lepri G., Matucci Cerinic M., Falcini F. Severe vitamin D deficiency in patients with Kawasaki disease: A potential role in the risk to develop heart vascular abnormalities? Clin. Rheumatol. 2016;35:1865–1872. doi: 10.1007/s10067-015-2970-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10067-015-2970-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25994612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okazaki N., Ikeda H., Honda T., Tsuno K., Inoue F., Takahashi S., Sakurai A., Ueki H., Noguchi Y., Hamada H., et al. The impact of vitamin D on the onset and progress of Kawasaki disease. Pediatr. Int. 2022;64:e15191. doi: 10.1111/ped.15191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ped.15191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35831250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karonova T.L., Andreeva A.T., Golovatuk K.A., Bykova E.S., Simanenkova A.V., Vashukova M.A., Grant W.B., Shlyakhto E.V. Low 25(OH)D level is associated with severe course and poor prognosis in COVID-19. Nutrients. 2021;13:3021. doi: 10.3390/nu13093021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13093021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8468115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34578898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlGhatrif M., Tanaka T., Moore A.Z., Bandinelli S., Lakatta E.G., Ferrucci L. Age-associated difference in circulating ACE2, the gateway for SARS-COV-2, in humans: Results from the InCHIANTI study. Geroscience. 2021;43:619–627. doi: 10.1007/s11357-020-00314-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11357-020-00314-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7813532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33462706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marik P.E., Kory P., Varon J. Does vitamin D status impact mortality from SARS-CoV-2 infection? Med. Drug Discov. 2020;6:100041. doi: 10.1016/j.medidd.2020.100041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.medidd.2020.100041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7189189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32352080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuo L., Miller Juve A. Transitioning to a new era: Future directions for staff development during COVID-19. Med. Educ. 2020;55:104–107. doi: 10.1111/medu.14387.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/medu.14387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7675277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33034062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padhi S., Suvankar S., Panda V.K., Pati A., Panda A.K. Lower levels of vitamin D are associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection and mortality in the Indian population: An observational study. Int. Immunopharmacol. 2020;88:107001. doi: 10.1016/j.intimp.2020.107001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2020.107001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7489890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33182040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin Gimenez V.M., Inserra F., Ferder L., Garcia J., Manucha W. Vitamin D deficiency in African Americans is associated with a high risk of severe disease and mortality by SARS-CoV-2. J. Hum. Hypertens. 2021;35:378–380. doi: 10.1038/s41371-020-00398-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41371-020-00398-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7425793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32792611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udaya Kumar V., Pavan G., Murti K., Kumar R., Dhingra S., Haque M., Ravichandiran V. Rays of immunity: Role of sunshine vitamin in management of COVID-19 infection and associated comorbidities. Clin. Nutr. ESPEN. 2021;46:21–32. doi: 10.1016/j.clnesp.2021.09.727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clnesp.2021.09.727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8474796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34857198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alguwaihes A.M., Sabico S., Hasanato R., Al-Sofiani M.E., Megdad M., Albader S.S., Alsari M.H., Alelayan A., Alyusuf E.Y., Alzahrani S.H., et al. Severe vitamin D deficiency is not related to SARS-CoV-2 infection but may increase mortality risk in hospitalized adults: A retrospective case-control study in an Arab Gulf country. Aging Clin. Exp. Res. 2021;33:1415–1422. doi: 10.1007/s40520-021-01831-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40520-021-01831-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8009930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33788172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra P., Parveen R., Bajpai R., Agarwal N. Vitamin D deficiency and comorbidities as risk factors of COVID-19 Infection: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Prev. Med. Public Health. 2022;55:321–333. doi: 10.3961/jpmph.21.640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3961/jpmph.21.640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9371781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35940187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alberca G.G.F., Alberca R.W. Role of vitamin D deficiency and comorbidities in COVID-19. World J. Virol. 2022;11:85–89. doi: 10.5501/wjv.v11.i1.85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5501/wjv.v11.i1.85</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8788214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35117974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polonowita A., Wimalawansa S. The impact of withholding cost-effective early treatments, such as vitamin D, on COVID-19: An analysis using an innovative logical paradigm. World J. Adv. Pharm. Life Sci. 2023;5:13–34. doi: 10.53346/wjapls.2023.5.2.0080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.53346/wjapls.2023.5.2.0080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenali N., Babu G.R.M. A systematic literature review and future perspectives for handling big data analytics in COVID-19 diagnosis. New Gener. Comput. 2023;41:243–280. doi: 10.1007/s00354-023-00211-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00354-023-00211-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10019802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37229177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimalawansa S.J. Decoding the paradox: Understanding elevated hospitalization and reduced mortality in SARS-CoV-2 variants. Int. J. Front. in Sci. Technol. Res. 2024;6:1–20. doi: 10.53294/ijfstr.2024.6.2.0031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.53294/ijfstr.2024.6.2.0031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nafilyan V., Bermingham C.R., Ward I.L., Morgan J., Zaccardi F., Khunti K., Stanborough J., Banerjee A., Doidge J.C. Risk of death following COVID-19 vaccination or positive SARS-CoV-2 test in young people in England. Nat. Commun. 2023;14:1541. doi: 10.1038/s41467-023-36494-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-36494-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10043280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36973247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Israel A., Cicurel A., Feldhamer I., Stern F., Dror Y., Giveon S.M., Gillis D., Strich D., Lavie G. Vitamin D deficiency is associated with higher risks for SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-19 severity: A retrospective case-control study. Intern. Emerg. Med. 2022;17:1053–1063. doi: 10.1007/s11739-021-02902-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11739-021-02902-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8742718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35000118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menshawey E., Menshawey R., Nabeh O.A. Shedding light on vitamin D: The shared mechanistic and pathophysiological role between hypovitaminosis D and COVID-19 risk factors and complications. Inflammopharmacology. 2021;29:1017–1031. doi: 10.1007/s10787-021-00835-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10787-021-00835-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8239482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34185200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou P., Yang X.L., Wang X.G., Hu B., Zhang L., Zhang W., Si H.R., Zhu Y., Li B., Huang C.L., et al. A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin. Nature. 2020;579:270–273. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu R., Zhao X., Li J., Niu P., Yang B., Wu H., Wang W., Song H., Huang B., Zhu N., et al. Genomic characterisation and epidemiology of 2019 novel coronavirus: Implications for virus origins and receptor binding. Lancet. 2020;395:565–574. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30251-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30251-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32007145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scialo F., Daniele A., Amato F., Pastore L., Matera M.G., Cazzola M., Castaldo G., Bianco A. ACE2: The major cell entry receptor for SARS-CoV-2. Lung. 2020;198:867–877. doi: 10.1007/s00408-020-00408-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00408-020-00408-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7653219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33170317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M., Kleine-Weber H., Schroeder S., Kruger N., Herrler T., Erichsen S., Schiergens T.S., Herrler G., Wu N.H., Nitsche A., et al. SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and Is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor. Cell. 2020;181:271–280.e278. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng C., Evans J.P., King T., Zheng Y.M., Oltz E.M., Whelan S.P.J., Saif L.J., Peeples M.E., Liu S.L. SARS-CoV-2 spreads through cell-to-cell transmission. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2022;119:e2111400119. doi: 10.1073/pnas.2111400119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2111400119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8740724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34937699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira G.J., Hirata H., Fimia G.M., do Carmo L.G., Bincoletto C., Han S.W., Stilhano R.S., Ureshino R.P., Bloor-Young D., Churchill G., et al. Nicotinic acid adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NAADP) regulates autophagy in cultured astrocytes. J. Biol. Chem. 2011;286:27875–27881. doi: 10.1074/jbc.C110.216580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.C110.216580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3151033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21610076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarzani R., Giulietti F., Di Pentima C., Giordano P., Spannella F. Disequilibrium between the classic renin-angiotensin system and its opposing arm in SARS-CoV-2-related lung injury. Am. J. Physiol. Lung Cell. Mol. Physiol. 2020;319:L325–L336. doi: 10.1152/ajplung.00189.2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajplung.00189.2020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7414236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32639866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J., Yang J., Chen J., Luo Q., Zhang Q., Zhang H. Vitamin D alleviates lipopolysaccharide-induced acute lung injury via regulation of the renin-angiotensin system. Mol. Med. Rep. 2017;16:7432–7438. doi: 10.3892/mmr.2017.7546.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3892/mmr.2017.7546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5865875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28944831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Notz Q., Herrmann J., Schlesinger T., Kranke P., Sitter M., Helmer P., Stumpner J., Roeder D., Amrein K., Stoppe C., et al. Vitamin D deficiency in critically ill COVID-19 ARDS patients. Clin. Nutr. 2022;41:3089–3095. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2021.03.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clnu.2021.03.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7937427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33745749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faul J.L., Kerley C.P., Love B., O’Neill E., Cody C., Tormey W., Hutchinson K., Cormican L.J., Burke C.M. Vitamin D deficiency and ARDS after SARS-CoV-2 infection. Ir. Med. J. 2020;113:84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32603575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dancer R.C., Parekh D., Lax S., D’Souza V., Zheng S., Bassford C.R., Park D., Bartis D.G., Mahida R., Turner A.M., et al. Vitamin D deficiency contributes directly to the acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) Thorax. 2015;70:617–624. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2014-206680.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2014-206680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4484044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25903964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skultetyova D., Filipova S., Riecansky I., Skultety J. The role of angiotensin type 1 receptor in inflammation and endothelial dysfunction. Recent. Pat. Cardiovasc. Drug Discov. 2007;2:23–27. doi: 10.2174/157489007779606130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/157489007779606130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18221099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J., Zhang Y.G. Vitamin D receptor influences Intestinal barriers in health and disease. Cells. 2022;11:1129. doi: 10.3390/cells11071129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cells11071129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8997406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35406694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danser A.H.J., Epstein M., Batlle D. Renin-angiotensin system blockers and the COVID-19 pandemic: At present there is no evidence to abandon renin-angiotensin system blockers. Hypertension. 2020;75:1382–1385. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.15082.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.15082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7225046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32208987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q.X., Xie L., Wu H.J., Jiang J., Zhao L., Dong H., Yang L.Y., Qiu H. The clinical characteristics and influencing factors of patients with severe COVID-19. Zhongguo Shi Yan Xue Ye Xue Za Zhi. 2021;29:1295–1300. doi: 10.19746/j.cnki.issn.1009-2137.2021.04.044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19746/j.cnki.issn.1009-2137.2021.04.044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34362519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y.C., Kong J., Wei M., Chen Z.F., Liu S.Q., Cao L.P. 1,25-Dihydroxyvitamin D(3) is a negative endocrine regulator of the renin-angiotensin system. J. Clin. Investig. 2002;110:229–238. doi: 10.1172/JCI0215219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1172/JCI0215219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC151055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12122115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forman J.P., Williams J.S., Fisher N.D. Plasma 25-hydroxyvitamin D and regulation of the renin-angiotensin system in humans. Hypertension. 2010;55:1283–1288. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.109.148619.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.109.148619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3023301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20351344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scragg R., Sowers M., Bell C. Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D, ethnicity, and blood pressure in the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey. Am. J. Hypertens. 2007;20:713–719. doi: 10.1016/j.amjhyper.2007.01.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amjhyper.2007.01.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17586404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hintzpeter B., Mensink G.B., Thierfelder W., Muller M.J., Scheidt-Nave C. Vitamin D status and health correlates among German adults. Eur. J. Clin. Nutr. 2008;62:1079–1089. doi: 10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602825.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17538533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessa A.S.M., Jesus E.F., Nunes A.D.C., Pontes C.N.R., Lacerda I.S., Costa J.M., Souza E.J., Lino-Junior R.S., Biancardi M.F., Dos Santos F.C.A., et al. Stimulation of the ACE2/Ang-(1–7)/Mas axis in hypertensive pregnant rats attenuates cardiovascular dysfunction in adult male offspring. Hypertens. Res. Off. J. Jpn. Soc. Hypertens. 2019;42:1883–1893. doi: 10.1038/s41440-019-0321-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41440-019-0321-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31506648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari V., Singh J., Tiwari P., Chaturvedi S., Gupta S., Mishra A., Singh S., Wahajuddin M., Hanif K., Shukla S. ACE2/ANG-(1–7)/Mas receptor axis activation prevents inflammation and improves cognitive functions in streptozotocin induced rat model of Alzheimer’s disease-like phenotypes. Eur. J. Pharmacol. 2023;946:175623. doi: 10.1016/j.ejphar.2023.175623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2023.175623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36871666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin S., Pan H., Wu H., Ren D., Lu J. Role of the ACE2-Ang-(1–7)-Mas axis in blood pressure regulation and its potential as an antihypertensive in functional foods. Mol. Med. Rep. 2017;16:4403–4412. doi: 10.3892/mmr.2017.7168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3892/mmr.2017.7168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28791402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahu S., Patil C.R., Kumar S., Apparsundaram S., Goyal R.K. Role of ACE2-Ang (1–7)-Mas axis in post-COVID-19 complications and its dietary modulation. Mol. Cell. Biochem. 2022;477:225–240. doi: 10.1007/s11010-021-04275-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11010-021-04275-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8520076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34655418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K., Chen W., Zhang Z., Deng Y., Lian J.Q., Du P., Wei D., Zhang Y., Sun X.X., Gong L., et al. CD147-spike protein is a novel route for SARS-CoV-2 infection to host cells. Signal Transduct. Target. Ther. 2020;5:283. doi: 10.1038/s41392-020-00426-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-020-00426-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7714896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33277466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chambers P. Basigin binds Spike S on SARS-CoV2. Sci. Res. 2021;8:1–3. doi: 10.4236/oalib.1108064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4236/oalib.1108064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fenizia C., Galbiati S., Vanetti C., Vago R., Clerici M., Tacchetti C., Daniele T. SARS-CoV-2 entry: At the crossroads of CD147 and ACE2. Cells. 2021;10:1434. doi: 10.3390/cells10061434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cells10061434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8226513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34201214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song X., Hu W., Yu H., Zhao L., Zhao Y., Zhao X., Xue H.H., Zhao Y. Little to no expression of angiotensin-converting enzyme-2 on most human peripheral blood immune cells but highly expressed on tissue macrophages. Cytom. A. 2023;103:136–145. doi: 10.1002/cyto.a.24285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cyto.a.24285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33280254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>V’Kovski P., Kratzel A., Steiner S., Stalder H., Thiel V. Coronavirus biology and replication: Implications for SARS-CoV-2. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2021;19:155–170. doi: 10.1038/s41579-020-00468-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-00468-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7592455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33116300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alipoor S.D., Mirsaeidi M. SARS-CoV-2 cell entry beyond the ACE2 receptor. Mol. Biol. Rep. 2022;49:10715–10727. doi: 10.1007/s11033-022-07700-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11033-022-07700-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9244107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35754059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neerukonda S.N., Vassell R., Herrup R., Liu S., Wang T., Takeda K., Yang Y., Lin T.L., Wang W., Weiss C.D. Establishment of a well-characterized SARS-CoV-2 lentiviral pseudovirus neutralization assay using 293T cells with stable expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2. PLoS ONE. 2021;16:e0248348. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0248348.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0248348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7946320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33690649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahoney M., Damalanka V.C., Tartell M.A., Chung D.H., Lourenco A.L., Pwee D., Mayer Bridwell A.E., Hoffmann M., Voss J., Karmakar P., et al. A novel class of TMPRSS2 inhibitors potently block SARS-CoV-2 and MERS-CoV viral entry and protect human epithelial lung cells. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2021;118:e2108728118. doi: 10.1073/pnas.2108728118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2108728118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8694051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34635581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson A.M., Wysocki J., Batlle D. Interaction of SARS-CoV-2 and other coronavirus with ACE (angiotensin-converting enzyme)-2 as their main receptor: Therapeutic implications. Hypertension. 2020;76:1339–1349. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.15256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.15256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7480804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32851855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yalcin H.C., Sukumaran V., Al-Ruweidi M., Shurbaji S. Do changes in ACE-2 expression affect SARS-CoV-2 virulence and related complications: A closer Look into nembrane-bound and soluble forms. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2021;22:6703. doi: 10.3390/ijms22136703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms22136703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8269184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34201415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei L., Liu S., Lu S., Luo S., An X., Fan H., Chen W., Li E., Tong Y., Song L. Lethal infection of human ACE2-transgenic mice caused by SARS-CoV-2-related Pangolin coronavirus GX_P2V. BioRxiv. 2024 doi: 10.1101/2024.01.03.574008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.01.03.574008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeung M.L., Teng J.L.L., Jia L., Zhang C., Huang C., Cai J.P., Zhou R., Chan K.H., Zhao H., Zhu L., et al. Soluble ACE2-mediated cell entry of SARS-CoV-2 via interaction with proteins related to the renin-angiotensin system. Cell. 2021;184:2212–2228.e2212. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7923941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33713620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>South A.M., Brady T.M., Flynn J.T. ACE2 (angiotensin-converting enzyme 2), COVID-19, and ACE inhibitor and Ang II (angiotensin II) receptor blocker use during the pandemic: The pediatric perspective. Hypertension. 2020;76:16–22. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.15291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.15291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7289676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32367746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou Y., Zhao J., Martin W., Kallianpur A., Chung M.K., Jehi L., Sharifi N., Erzurum S., Eng C., Cheng F. New insights into genetic susceptibility of COVID-19: An ACE2 and TMPRSS2 polymorphism analysis. BMC Med. 2020;18:216. doi: 10.1186/s12916-020-01673-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12916-020-01673-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7360473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32664879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buitrago C.G., Pardo V.G., de Boland A.R., Boland R. Activation of RAF-1 through Ras and protein kinase Calpha mediates 1alpha,25(OH)2-vitamin D3 regulation of the mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway in muscle cells. J. Biol. Chem. 2003;278:2199–2205. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M205732200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M205732200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12417593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castagnoli R., Votto M., Licari A., Brambilla I., Bruno R., Perlini S., Rovida F., Baldanti F., Marseglia G.L. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection in children and adolescents: A systematic review. JAMA Pediatr. 2020;174:882–889. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2020.1467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2020.1467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32320004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bermejo-Jambrina M., Eder J., Kaptein T.M., van Hamme J.L., Helgers L.C., Vlaming K.E., Brouwer P.J.M., van Nuenen A.C., Spaargaren M., de Bree G.J., et al. Infection and transmission of SARS-CoV-2 depend on heparan sulfate proteoglycans. EMBO J. 2021;40:e106765. doi: 10.15252/embj.2020106765.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15252/embj.2020106765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8521309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34510494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrabadi M.E., Hemmati R., Tashakor A., Homaei A., Yousefzadeh M., Hemati K., Hosseinkhani S. Induced dysregulation of ACE2 by SARS-CoV-2 plays a key role in COVID-19 severity. Biomed. Pharmacother. 2021;137:111363. doi: 10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7862910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33582450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Queiroz T.M., Lakkappa N., Lazartigues E. ADAM17-mMediated shedding of inflammatory cytokines in hypertension. Front. Pharmacol. 2020;11:1154. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2020.01154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2020.01154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7403492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32848763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei Y., Zhang J., Schiavon C.R., He M., Chen L., Shen H., Zhang Y., Yin Q., Cho Y., Andrade L., et al. SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein impairs endothelial function via downregulation of ACE 2. Circ. Res. 2021;128:1323–1326. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.121.318902.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.121.318902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8091897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33784827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedges J.F., Snyder D.T., Robison A., Grifka-Walk H.M., Blackwell K., Shepardson K., Kominsky D., Rynda-Apple A., Walcheck B., Jutila M.A. An ADAM17-neutralizing antibody reduces inflammation and mortality while increasing viral burden in a COVID-19 mouse model. Front. Immunol. 2022;13:918881. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2022.918881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.918881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9226444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35757773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haga S., Yamamoto N., Nakai-Murakami C., Osawa Y., Tokunaga K., Sata T., Yamamoto N., Sasazuki T., Ishizaka Y. Modulation of TNF-alpha-converting enzyme by the spike protein of SARS-CoV and ACE2 induces TNF-alpha production and facilitates viral entry. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2008;105:7809–7814. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0711241105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0711241105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2409424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18490652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behl T., Kaur I., Aleya L., Sehgal A., Singh S., Sharma N., Bhatia S., Al-Harrasi A., Bungau S. CD147-spike protein interaction in COVID-19: Get the ball rolling with a novel receptor and therapeutic target. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;808:152072. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8634688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34863742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishikawa M., Kanno H., Zhou Y., Xiao T.H., Suzuki T., Ibayashi Y., Harmon J., Takizawa S., Hiramatsu K., Nitta N., et al. Massive image-based single-cell profiling reveals high levels of circulating platelet aggregates in patients with COVID-19. Nat. Commun. 2021;12:7135. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-27378-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-27378-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8660840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34887400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bunyavanich S., Do A., Vicencio A. Nasal gene expression of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 in children and adults. JAMA. 2020;323:2427–2429. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.8707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.8707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7240631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32432657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lordan R. Notable developments for vitamin D Amid the COVID-19 pandemic, but caution warranted overall: A narrative review. Nutrients. 2021;13:740. doi: 10.3390/nu13030740.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13030740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7996924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33652653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jude E.B., Tentolouris N., Rastogi A., Yap M.H., Pedrosa H.C., Ling S.F. Vitamin D prescribing practices among clinical practitioners during the COVID-19 pandemic. Health Sci. Rep. 2022;5:e691. doi: 10.1002/hsr2.691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hsr2.691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9273939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35844828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryant A., Lawrie T.A., Dowswell T., Fordham E.J., Mitchell S., Hill S.R., Tham T.C. Ivermectin for prevention and treatment of COVID-19 infection: A systematic review, meta-analysis, and trial sequential analysis to inform clinical guidelines. Am. J. Ther. 2021;28:e434–e460. doi: 10.1097/MJT.0000000000001402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MJT.0000000000001402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8248252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34145166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury A., Sajid M., Jahan N., Adelusi T.I., Maitra P., Yin G., Wu X., Gao Y., Wang S. A secondary approach with conventional medicines and supplements to recuperate current COVID-19 status. Biomed. Pharmacother. 2021;142:111956. doi: 10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111956.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8313489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34332377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA  Emergency Use Authorization for Vaccines Explained.  [(accessed on 22 May 2023)]; Available online:  https://www.fda.gov/vaccines-blood-biologics/vaccines/emergency-use-authorization-vaccines-explained.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polonowita A., Wimalawansa S.J. Molecular quantum and logic process of consciousness—Vitamin D big-data in COVID-19—A case for incorporating machine learning in medicine. Euro. J. Biomed. Pharma. Sci. 2023;10:24–43. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.10435649.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5281/zenodo.10435649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viana S.D., Nunes S., Reis F. ACE2 imbalance as a key player for the poor outcomes in COVID-19 patients with age-related comorbidities—Role of gut microbiota dysbiosis. Ageing Res. Rev. 2020;62:101123. doi: 10.1016/j.arr.2020.101123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2020.101123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7365123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32683039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawalha A.H., Zhao M., Coit P., Lu Q. Epigenetic dysregulation of ACE2 and interferon-regulated genes might suggest increased COVID-19 susceptibility and severity in lupus patients. medRxiv. 2020 doi: 10.1016/j.clim.2020.108410.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2020.108410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7139239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32276140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beyerstedt S., Casaro E.B., Rangel E.B. COVID-19: Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) expression and tissue susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infection. Eur. J. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2021;40:905–919. doi: 10.1007/s10096-020-04138-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10096-020-04138-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7778857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33389262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dal Canto E., Beulens J.W.J., Elders P., Rutters F., Stehouwer C.D.A., van der Heijden A.A., van Ballegooijen A.J. The association of vitamin D and vitamin K status with subclinical measures of cardiovascular health and all-cause mortality in older adults: The hoorn study. J. Nutr. 2020;150:3171–3179. doi: 10.1093/jn/nxaa293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jn/nxaa293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7726120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33119768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Ballegooijen A.J., Beulens J.W.J., Kieneker L.M., de Borst M.H., Gansevoort R.T., Kema I.P., Schurgers L.J., Vervloet M.G., Bakker S.J.L. Combined low vitamin D and K status amplifies mortality risk: A prospective study. Eur. J. Nutr. 2021;60:1645–1654. doi: 10.1007/s00394-020-02352-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00394-020-02352-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7987611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32808059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cariolou M., Cupp M.A., Evangelou E., Tzoulaki I., Berlanga-Taylor A.J. Importance of vitamin D in acute and critically ill children with subgroup analyses of sepsis and respiratory tract infections: A systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ Open. 2019;9:e027666. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2018-027666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-027666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6538078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31122993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W., Liu Z., Tang R., Ouyang S., Li S., Wu J. Vitamin D inhibits palmitate-induced macrophage pro-inflammatory cytokine production by targeting the MAPK pathway. Immunol. Lett. 2018;202:23–30. doi: 10.1016/j.imlet.2018.07.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.imlet.2018.07.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30076857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qayyum S., Mohammad T., Slominski R.M., Hassan M.I., Tuckey R.C., Raman C., Slominski A.T. Vitamin D and lumisterol novel metabolites can inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication machinery enzymes. Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab. 2021;321:E246–E251. doi: 10.1152/ajpendo.00174.2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00174.2021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8328521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34181461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz J.H. Hypothesis: Angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin receptor blockers may increase the risk of severe COVID-19. J. Travel. Med. 2020;27:taaa041. doi: 10.1093/jtm/taaa041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jtm/taaa041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32186711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhtar S., Benter I.F., Danjuma M.I., Doi S.A.R., Hasan S.S., Habib A.M. Pharmacotherapy in COVID-19 patients: A review of ACE2-raising drugs and their clinical safety. J. Drug Target. 2020;28:683–699. doi: 10.1080/1061186X.2020.1797754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1061186X.2020.1797754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32700580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung M.K., Karnik S., Saef J., Bergmann C., Barnard J., Lederman M.M., Tilton J., Cheng F., Harding C.V., Young J.B., et al. SARS-CoV-2 and ACE2: The biology and clinical data settling the ARB and ACEI controversy. EBioMedicine. 2020;58:102907. doi: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2020.102907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2020.102907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7415847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32771682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glasgow A., Glasgow J., Limonta D., Solomon P., Lui I., Zhang Y., Nix M.A., Rettko N.J., Zha S., Yamin R., et al. Engineered ACE2 receptor traps potently neutralize SARS-CoV-2. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2020;117:28046–28055. doi: 10.1073/pnas.2016093117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2016093117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7668070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33093202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bracken C.J., Lim S.A., Solomon P., Rettko N.J., Nguyen D.P., Zha B.S., Schaefer K., Byrnes J.R., Zhou J., Lui I., et al. Bi-paratopic and multivalent VH domains block ACE2 binding and neutralize SARS-CoV-2. Nat. Chem. Biol. 2021;17:113–121. doi: 10.1038/s41589-020-00679-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41589-020-00679-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8356808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33082574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aleksova A., Ferro F., Gagno G., Cappelletto C., Santon D., Rossi M., Ippolito G., Zumla A., Beltrami A.P., Sinagra G. COVID-19 and renin-angiotensin system inhibition: Role of angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2)—Is there any scientific evidence for controversy? J. Intern. Med. 2020;288:410–421. doi: 10.1111/joim.13101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joim.13101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7283873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32459372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuba K., Imai Y., Rao S., Gao H., Guo F., Guan B., Huan Y., Yang P., Zhang Y., Deng W., et al. A crucial role of angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) in SARS coronavirus-induced lung injury. Nat. Med. 2005;11:875–879. doi: 10.1038/nm1267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nm1267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16007097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>