<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39450197</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2325-9671</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Orthopaedic journal of sports medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Orthop J Sports Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association of the COVID-19 Pandemic With Outcomes After Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction: A Retrospective Comparative Study Examining Changes in Health Care Access, Delivery, and Functional Outcomes.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>23259671241280982</StartPage><MedlinePgn>23259671241280982</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">23259671241280982</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/23259671241280982</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Structured rehabilitation optimizes outcomes and reduces reinjury risk after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction (ACLR). The coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic interrupted standard rehabilitation, possibly affecting ACLR outcomes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To characterize changes to ACLR functional outcomes related to the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Cohort study; Level of evidence, 3.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Patients who underwent ACLR between June 11, 2019, and March 11, 2020, (postpandemic group) were compared retrospectively with those who underwent ACLR the year before (June 11, 2018, to March 11, 2019). A mixed-effects linear regression model was used to estimate group differences in isokinetic quadriceps testing. A Kaplan-Meier analysis assessed the probability of achieving &gt;90% limb symmetry index (LSI) for isokinetic quadriceps strength at 60 deg/s and passing all return-to-sport functional outcomes at 1 year postoperatively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 176 patients (80 in the control group and 96 in the postpandemic group) were included. The rate of achieving &gt;90% LSI in isokinetic strength at 60 deg/s at 1 year postoperatively was 39% (95% CI, 27%-49%) for the control group versus 22% (95% CI, 13%-30%) for the postpandemic group (<i>P</i> = .01). Similarly, the rate of achieving &gt;90% LSI in all functional tests at 1 year postoperatively was 15% (95% CI, 7%-22%) for the control group versus 7% (95% CI, 2%-12%) for the postpandemic group (<i>P</i> = .04). The number of in-person physical therapy visits per patient was 25.8 ± 6.8 in the control group versus 24.4 ± 7.5 in the postpandemic group (<i>P</i> = .23). Only the postpandemic group accessed physical therapy using remote telemedicine. Each additional telehealth rehabilitation visit was associated with a 1-week delay in achieving &gt;90% LSI in isokinetic quadriceps strength for the postpandemic group.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The COVID-19 pandemic was associated with a decrease in lower extremity strength and a lower probability of achieving limb symmetry and passing the criteria for return to sport at 1 year postoperatively. These results were not due to lack of access to physical therapy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Steiner</LastName><ForeName>Quinn</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zacharias</LastName><ForeName>Anthony</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Froedtert South, Pleasant Prairie, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chumanov</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Wisconsin Health Sciences, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baer</LastName><ForeName>Geoffrey S</ForeName><Initials>GS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walczak</LastName><ForeName>Brian E</ForeName><Initials>BE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Castle Orthopedics and Sports Medicine, Rush Copley Medical Center, Rush University, Aurora, Illinois, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Advancing Translational Orthopedics and Medical Sciences (ATOMS) Laboratory, Department of Orthopedics, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Orthop J Sports Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101620522</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2325-9671</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ACL reconstruction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">functional outcomes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>One or more of the authors has declared the following potential conflict of interest or source of funding: G.S.B. has received consulting fees from Linvatec and Medical Device Business Services and nonconsulting fees from Linvatec. B.E.W. has received hospitality payments from Smith &amp; Nephew and Stryker. AOSSM checks author disclosures against the Open Payments Database (OPD). AOSSM has not conducted an independent investigation on the OPD and disclaims any liability or responsibility relating thereto.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39450197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11500221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/23259671241280982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_23259671241280982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abdelnasser MK, Morsy M, Osman AE, et al.. COVID-19. An update for orthopedic surgeons. SICOT J. 2020;6:24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7328530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32609085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alfano V, Ercolano S. The efficacy of lockdown against COVID-19: a cross-country panel analysis. Appl Health Econ Health Policy. 2020;18(4):509-517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7268966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32495067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brinlee AW, Dickenson SB, Hunter-Giordano A, Snyder-Mackler L. ACL reconstruction rehabilitation: clinical data, biologic healing, and criterion-based milestones to inform a return-to-sport guideline. Sports Health. 2022;14(5):770-779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9460090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34903114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burroughs PJ, Kahan JB, Moore HG, Grauer JN, Gardner EC. Temporal utilization of physical therapy visits after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. Orthop J Sports Med. 2021;9(2):2325967 120982293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7900793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33681401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterji G, Patel Y, Jain V, Geevarughese NM, Haq RU. Impact of COVID-19 on orthopaedic care and practice: a rapid review. Indian J Orthop. 2021;55(4):839-852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7980796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33776130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demeke HB, Merali S, Marks S, et al.. Trends in use of telehealth among health centers during the COVID-19 pandemic – United States, June 26-November 6, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70(7):240-244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7891688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33600385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drole K, Paravlic AH. Interventions for increasing return to sport rates after an anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction surgery: a systematic review. Front Psychol. 2022;13:939209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9443932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36072023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fältström A, Hägglund M, Kvist J. Factors associated with playing football after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction in female football players. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2016;26(11):1343-1352.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26589671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gachabayov M, Latifi LA, Parsikia A, Latifi R. The role of telemedicine in surgical specialties during the COVID-19 pandemic: a scoping review. World J Surg. 2022;46(1):10-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8572066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34743242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaggero A, Fernández-Pérez Á, Jiménez-Rubio D. Effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on depression in older adults: a panel data analysis. Health Policy. 2022;126(9):865-871.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9271012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35868871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardinier ES, Di Stasi S, Manal K, Buchanan TS, Snyder-Mackler L. Knee contact force asymmetries in patients who failed return-to-sport readiness criteria 6 months after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. Am J Sports Med. 2014;42(12):2917-2925.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4314107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25318940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant JA, Mohtadi NGH, Maitland ME, Zernicke RF. Comparison of home versus physical therapy-supervised rehabilitation programs after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. Am J Sports Med. 2005;33(9):1288-1297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16002493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grindem H, Snyder-Mackler L, Moksnes H, Engebretsen L, Risberg MA. Simple decision rules can reduce reinjury risk by 84% after ACL reconstruction: the Delaware-Oslo ACL cohort study. Br J Sports Med. 2016;50(13):804-808.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4912389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27162233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ithurburn MP, Paterno M V, Ford KR, Hewett TE, Schmitt LC. Young athletes after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction with single-leg landing asymmetries at the time of return to sport demonstrate decreased knee function 2 years later. Am J Sports Med. 2017;45(11):2604-2613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28644677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joseph AM, Collins CL, Henke NM, Yard EE, Fields SK, Comstock RD. A multisport epidemiologic comparison of anterior cruciate ligament injuries in high school athletics. J Athl Train. 2013;48(6):810-817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3867093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24143905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyritsis P, Bahr R, Landreau P, Miladi R, Witvrouw E. Likelihood of ACL graft rupture: not meeting six clinical discharge criteria before return to sport is associated with a four times greater risk of rupture. Br J Sports Med. 2016;50(15):946-951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27215935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai CCH, Ardern CL, Feller JA, Webster KE. Eighty-three percent of elite athletes return to preinjury sport after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a systematic review with meta-analysis of return to sport rates, graft rupture rates and performance outcomes. Br J Sports Med. 2018;52(2):128-138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28223305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee D, Lencer AJ, Gibbs BS, Paul RW, Tjoumakaris FP. Disruptions in standard care: anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction outcomes during the SARS-COV2 pandemic. Phys Sportsmed. 2022;50(6):515-521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34424824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemaire A, Ripamonti M, Ritz M, Rahmani A. Agreement of three vs. eight isokinetic preset velocities to determine knee extensor torque- and power-velocity relationships. Isokinet Exerc Sci. 2014;22(1):1-7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lentz TA, Zeppieri G, Jr, Tillman SM, et al.. Return to preinjury sports participation following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: contributions of demographic, knee impairment, and self-report measures. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2012;42(11):893-901.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3680881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22951437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagai T, Schilaty ND, Laskowski ER, Hewett TE. Hop tests can result in higher limb symmetry index values than isokinetic strength and leg press tests in patients following ACL reconstruction. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc. 2020;28(3):816-822.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6814513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31025059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pua YH, Mentiplay BF, Clark RA, Ho JY. Associations among quadriceps strength and rate-of-torque development 6 weeks post anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction and future hop and vertical jump performance: a prospective cohort study. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2017;47(11):845-852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29029566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarac NJ, Sarac BA, Schoenbrunner AR, et al.. A review of state guidelines for elective orthopaedic procedures during the COVID-19 outbreak. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2020;102(11):942-945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7197340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32282419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schenck RC, Jr, Blaschak MJ, Lance ED, Turturro TC, Holmes CF. A prospective outcome study of rehabilitation programs and anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. Arthroscopy. 1997;13(3):285-290.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9195022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmitt LC, Paterno MV, Hewett TE. The impact of quadriceps femoris strength asymmetry on functional performance at return to sport following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2012;42(9):750-759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4157226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22813542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Melick N, van Cingel REH, Brooijmans F, et al.. Evidence-based clinical practice update: practice guidelines for anterior cruciate ligament rehabilitation based on a systematic review and multidisciplinary consensus. Br J Sports Med. 2016;50(24):1506-1515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27539507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vutescu ES, Orman S, Garcia-Lopez E, Lau J, Gage A, Cruz AI., Jr. Psychological and social components of recovery following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction in young athletes: a narrative review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(17):9267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8430793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34501857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weaver A, Ness B, Roman D, Giampetruzzi N, Cleland J. Short-term clinical outcomes after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction in adolescents during the COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Sports Phys Ther. 2022;17(4):585-592.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9159720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35693856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiggins AJ, Grandhi RK, Schneider DK, Stanfield D, Webster KE, Myer GD. Risk of secondary injury in younger athletes after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. Am J Sports Med. 2016;44(7):1861-1876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5501245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26772611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu HH, Liu M, Dines JS, Kelly JD, Garcia GH. Depression and psychiatric disease associated with outcomes after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. World J Orthop. 2016;7(11):709-717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5112339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27900267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Janda KM, Ranjit N, Salvo D, Nielsen A, van den Berg A. Change in depression and its determinants during the COVID-19 pandemic: a longitudinal examination among racially/ethnically diverse US adults. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(3):1194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8835174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35162214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>