<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39452522</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1651-2227</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Acta paediatrica (Oslo, Norway : 1992)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acta Paediatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The prevalence of overweight among 4-year-olds during and after the COVID-19 pandemic was associated with socioeconomic burden.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/apa.17468</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To assess the prevalence of overweight among Swedish 4 year olds in 2018, 2020 and 2022, taking socioeconomic variables into account.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Aggregated regional data on children's body mass index were collected. The socioeconomic Care Need Index (CNI), foreign background, low education, being a single parent, low income and childhood poverty, were assessed. The differences in overweight, including obesity, were tested for Sweden and for regions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Data were available for 303 843 children, representing 87% of children born in 2014, 2016 and 2018. Overweight or obesity were found in 11 177 (11.4%) of children in 2022, decreasing from 2020 (13.3%, p &lt; 0.001) but at the same level as in 2018. Regional low CNI, low level of foreign background, education and income as well as being a single parent were associated with a higher prevalence of overweight or obesity in all cohorts (p &lt; 0.001). In regions with high levels of childhood poverty, overweight or obesity were more prevalent during (p = 0.009) and after the pandemic (p &lt; 0.001).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Three national cohorts demonstrate that the increase in overweight during the COVID-19 pandemic has returned to pre-pandemic levels, but the inequalities in health associated with socioeconomic vulnerability of the regions remained.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nylander</LastName><ForeName>Charlotte</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7077-7865</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Child Health Services Sörmland, Eskilstuna, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Clinical Research Sörmland, Eskilstuna, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Women's and Children's Health, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nowicka</LastName><ForeName>Paulina</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Studies, Nutrition and Dietetics, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Derwig</LastName><ForeName>Mariette</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Sciences, Lunds University, Lunds, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Child Health Services Skåne, Lunds, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Centre for Clinical Rearch Sörmland</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Norway</Country><MedlineTA>Acta Paediatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9205968</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0803-5253</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">child health services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">obeisty</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">overweight</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prevention</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">socioeconomy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39452522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apa.17468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Collaboration NCDRF. Worldwide trends in underweight and obesity from 1990 to 2022: a pooled analysis of 3663 population‐representative studies with 222 million children, adolescents, and adults. Lancet. 2024;403(10431):1027‐1050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel M, Geserick M, Gausche R, et al. Age‐ and weight group‐specific weight gain patterns in children and adolescents during the 15 years before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Int J Obes. 2022;46(1):144‐152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson LN, Yoshida‐Montezuma Y, Dewart N, et al. Obesity and weight change during the COVID‐19 pandemic in children and adults: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. Obes Rev. 2023;24(5):e13550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miregard J, Nowicka P, Nylander C. National data showed an increased prevalence of overweight and obesity among four‐year‐old Swedish children during the first year of COVID‐19. Acta Paediatr. 2023;112(6):1269‐1274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Picchioni F, Goulao LF, Roberfroid D. The impact of COVID‐19 on diet quality, food security and nutrition in low and middle income countries: a systematic review of the evidence. Clin Nutr. 2022;41(12):2955‐2964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowicka P, Ek A, Jurca‐Simina IE, et al. Explaining the complex impact of the Covid‐19 pandemic on children with overweight and obesity: a comparative ecological analysis of parents' perceptions in three countries. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1):1000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long X, Li XY, Jiang H, et al. Impact of the COVID‐19 kindergarten closure on overweight and obesity among 3‐ to 7‐year‐old children. World J Pediatr. 2023;19(5):469‐477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcus C, Danielsson P, Hagman E. Pediatric obesity‐long‐term consequences and effect of weight loss. J Intern Med. 2022;292(6):870‐891.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geserick M, Vogel M, Gausche R, et al. Acceleration of BMI in early childhood and risk of sustained obesity. N Engl J Med. 2018;379(14):1303‐1312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collaboration NCDRF. Worldwide trends in body‐mass index, underweight, overweight, and obesity from 1975 to 2016: a pooled analysis of 2416 population‐based measurement studies in 128.9 million children, adolescents, and adults. Lancet. 2017;390(10113):2627‐2642.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Martinez MP, Chow T, Xiang AH. BMI growth trajectory from ages 2 to 6 years and its association with maternal obesity, diabetes during pregnancy, gestational weight gain, and breastfeeding. Pediatr Obes. 2020;15(2):e12579.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Socialstyrelsen. Guidelines for Child Health Services. Socialstyrelsen; 2014. (In Swedish.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Socialstyrelsen. Nationella riktlinjer för behandling vid obesitas. Socialstyrelsen; 2022. (In Swedish.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cole TJ, Lobstein T. Extended international (IOTF) body mass index cut‐offs for thinness, overweight and obesity. Pediatr Obes. 2012;7(4):284‐294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Folkhälsomyndigheten. Vaccinationsstatistik från barnavårdscentraler. Folkhälsomyndigheten; 2022. (In Swedish.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Folkhälsomyndigheten. Barnvaccinationsprogrammets hållbarhet under den tidiga covid‐19‐pandemin i Sverige – en tvärsnittsundersökning av barnhälsovårdens arbete. Folkhälsomyndigheten; 2020. (In Swedish.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spong E, Miregard J, Nylander C. High levels of overweight and obesity in four year olds in Sweden. Lakartidningen. 2021;118:21107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faldt A, Nejat S, Durbeej N, Holmgren A. Childhood overweight and obesity during and after the COVID‐19 pandemic. JAMA Pediatr. 2024;178:498‐500.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janson A. Unique Swedish data on young children's growth help to fill the gap identified by the World Health Organization. Acta Paediatr. 2023;112(6):1140‐1141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistiska Centralbyrån. Statistikdatabasen. Statistiska Centralbyrån; 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Region Sörmland. Årsrapport Barnhälsovården 2020. Region Sörmland; 2021. (In Swedish.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salonen T, Samzelius T, Soares LM. Barnfattigdom i Sverige: Årsrapport 2021. Save the Children Sweden; 2021. (In Swedish.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faldt A, Nejat S, Edvinsson Sollander S, Durbeej N, Holmgren A. Increased incidence of overweight and obesity among preschool Swedish children during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Eur J Pub Health. 2023;33(1):127‐131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badesha HS, Bagri G, Nagra A, Nijran K, Singh G, Aiyegbusi OL. Tackling childhood overweight and obesity after the COVID‐19 pandemic. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2021;5(10):687‐688.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eriksson M, Lingfors H, Golsater M. Trends in prevalence of thinness, overweight and obesity among Swedish children and adolescents between 2004 and 2015. Acta Paediatr. 2018;107(10):1818‐1825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sares‐Jaske L, Gronqvist A, Maki P, Tolonen H, Laatikainen T. Family socioeconomic status and childhood adiposity in Europe – a scoping review. Prev Med. 2022;160:107095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iguacel I, Fernandez‐Alvira JM, Bammann K, et al. Associations between social vulnerabilities and dietary patterns in European children: the identification and prevention of dietary‐ and lifestyle‐induced health EFfects in children and infantS (IDEFICS) study. Br J Nutr. 2016;116(7):1288‐1297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ludvigsson JF. How Sweden approached the COVID‐19 pandemic: summary and commentary on the National Commission Inquiry. Acta Paediatr. 2023;112(1):19‐33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hjern A, Bergstrom M, Fransson E, Lindfors A, Bergqvist K. Birth order and socioeconomic disadvantage predict behavioural and emotional problems at age 3 years. Acta Paediatr. 2021;110(12):3294‐3301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wennergren M, Berg K, Frisk Cavefors AS, et al. Swedish child health services register: a quality register for child health services and children's well‐being. BMJ Paediatr Open. 2024;7(1):e001805.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>