<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39454482</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-4036</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>86</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Intensive &amp; critical care nursing</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Intensive Crit Care Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Factors associated with the effectiveness of high-flow therapy in patients with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure: An observational study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>103874</StartPage><MedlinePgn>103874</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.iccn.2024.103874</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0964-3397(24)00259-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKWARD" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The COVID-19 pandemic has severely tested global health systems. Non-invasive respiratory support, especially combining high-flow nasal cannula (HFNC) and continuous positive airway pressure, has effectively treated COVID-19 induced Acute Hypoxemic Respiratory Failure and reduced mortality. However, HFNC alone is more comfortable, better tolerated, and less costly than non-invasive ventilation. Understanding which patients benefit from HFNC monotherapy versus combined therapies is essential.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This observational study included patients admitted to the intermediate respiratory care unit of a COVID-19 hospital between December 2020 and September 2021. All patients treated with HFNC were included (n = 1301). HFNC failure was defined as the need for escalated therapy (non-invasive ventilation, intubation) or death. Epidemiological, clinical, non-invasive respiratory support parameters, and laboratory data were collected, and a multivariable analysis identified key determinants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">HFNC was successful in 39.9 % of patients. (n = 511) Risk factors for HFNC failure included increased age, male gender, obesity, obstructive sleep apnea, higher respiratory rate, initial SpO2/FiO2 ≤ 148, and initial PaO2/FiO2 ≤ 100. An increase in the ROX Index at 24 h and slower disease progression were associated with successful treatment. These findings led to the developmet of an index to identify patients who benefit most from HFNC monotherapy.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">HFNC monotherapy can be effective for a specific profile of patients with Acute Hypoxemic Respiratory Failure due to COVID-19. This tool may help manage these patients more appropriately. Further studies are needed to determine if these findings can be applied to Acute Hypoxemic Respiratory Failure caused by other pathologies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPLICATIONS FOR CLINICAL PRACTICE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study underscores the importance of early identification and management of patients at risk of HFNC failure in intermediate respiratory care units. By recognizing factors such as age, comorbidities, and respiratory indices, healthcare providers can implement targeted strategies to enhance HFNC success. These strategies may include more stringent monitoring, tailored respiratory support, and timely escalation to more intensive therapies if needed. Our findings highlight the need for a comprehensive approach to managing severe respiratory failure in critical care settings, ultimately improving patient outcomes and reducing the burden on healthcare systems.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zevallos-Villegas</LastName><ForeName>Annette</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Intermediate Care Unit, "Enfermera Isabel Zendal" Emergency Hospital, Madrid, Spain; Pneumology Department, San Carlos University Hospital, Madrid, Spain. Electronic address: annette.zevallos@madrid.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gonzalez-Rubio</LastName><ForeName>Jesus</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine of Albacete, University of Castilla-La Mancha, Albacete, Spain; Biomedicine Institute (IB-UCLM), University of Castilla-La Mancha, Albacete, Spain. Electronic address: Jesus.Gonzalez@uclm.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Neria Serrano</LastName><ForeName>Fernando</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Support Unit, Faculty of Medicine, Universidad Francisco de Vitoria [Francisco de Vitoria University], Pozuelo de Alarcón, Madrid, Spain. Electronic address: fernando.neria@ufv.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gallego-Rodriguez</LastName><ForeName>Berta</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory intermediate care unit, Isabel Zendal Emergency Hospital, Madrid, Spain. Electronic address: berta.gallego@salud.madrid.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lorente-Gonzalez</LastName><ForeName>Miguel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Intermediate Care Unit, "Enfermera Isabel Zendal" Emergency Hospital, Madrid, Spain; Pneumology Department, San Carlos University Hospital, Madrid, Spain. Electronic address: mlorenteg@salud.madrid.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Najera</LastName><ForeName>Alberto</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine of Albacete, University of Castilla-La Mancha, Albacete, Spain; Biomedicine Institute (IB-UCLM), University of Castilla-La Mancha, Albacete, Spain. Electronic address: Alberto.Najera@uclm.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rafael Teran-Tinedo</LastName><ForeName>Jose</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory intermediate care unit, Isabel Zendal Emergency Hospital, Madrid, Spain; Pneumology Department, National Hospital for Paraplegics, Toledo, Spain; Complutense University of Madrid, Spain. Electronic address: jteran@sescam.jccm.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Navarro-Lopez</LastName><ForeName>Juan D</ForeName><Initials>JD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Castilla-La Mancha, Biomedicine Institute (IB-UCLM), School of Medicine, Ciudad Real, Spain. Electronic address: Juan.Navarro@uclm.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jimenez-Diaz</LastName><ForeName>Lydia</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Castilla-La Mancha, Biomedicine Institute (IB-UCLM), School of Medicine, Ciudad Real, Spain. Electronic address: Lydia.Jimenez@uclm.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Landete</LastName><ForeName>Pedro</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Intermediate Care Unit, "Enfermera Isabel Zendal" Emergency Hospital, Madrid, Spain; Department of Pneumology, Faculty of Medicine, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Madrid, Spain; Hospital Unviersitario la Princesa, Spain. Electronic address: pedro.landete@salud.madrid.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Intensive Crit Care Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9211274</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0964-3397</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39454482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.iccn.2024.103874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0964-3397(24)00259-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>