<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39450230</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2278-1897</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of orthodontic science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Orthod Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Influence of different types of mouthwashes on force decay of elastomeric chain recommended in SARS-COV-2 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>34</StartPage><MedlinePgn>34</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">34</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jos.jos_18_24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study aimed to compare the force decay of the power-chain elastics after exposure to anti-coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) antiseptic mouthwashes at different intervals.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 300 power-chain pieces were used from American Orthodontics (AO) and Dentaurum (D) brands. Each piece composed of five loops that were selected to simulate canine retraction distally. The samples were randomly grouped according to immersion in the tested mouthwashes 0.2% povidone-iodine (PVP-I), 1% hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), and 0.2% chlorhexidine (CHX) and cetylpyridinium chloride (CPC). The maximum tensile load failure testing (MTLT) was assessed at six time points (zero, one hour, 24 hours, 1, 2 and 4 weeks). Analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Tukey's <i>post hoc</i> tests were used to analyse the data, where <i>P</i> &lt; 0.05.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Significant differences in MTLT of power-chain elastics used at different immersion intervals were observed. MTLT, in each tested group, decreased significantly as the immersion time increased with significant differences among the tested mouthwashes at each time point. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> group displays a maximum force decay throughout the time intervals for both brands, in contrast to CPC group, which shows less degradation over time.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Both brands are decade over time during exposure to the tested mouthwashes. CPC mouthwashes is a good option to be described for orthodontic patient during COVID-19 pandemic, whereas H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> mouthwashes should be avoided.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Orthodontic Science.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salih Al Qassar</LastName><ForeName>Sarmad S</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pedodontics, Orthodontics and Prevention, College of Dentistry, University of Mosul, Mosul, Iraq.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ismael</LastName><ForeName>Afnan Jamaluddin</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pedodontics, Orthodontics and Prevention, College of Dentistry, University of Mosul, Mosul, Iraq.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dewachi</LastName><ForeName>Zaid Br</ForeName><Initials>ZB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pedodontics, Orthodontics and Prevention, College of Dentistry, University of Mosul, Mosul, Iraq.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Orthod Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101623468</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2278-0203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antiseptic mouth washes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">force decay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">power chain elastics</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39450230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11500743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jos.jos_18_24</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JOS-13-34</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Li JY, You Z, Wang Q, Zhou ZJ, Qiu Y, Luo R, et al. The epidemic of 2019-novel-coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia and insights for emerging infectious diseases in the future. Microbes Infect. 2020;22:80–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7079563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32087334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou L, Ruan F, Huang M, Liang L, Huang H, Hong Z, et al. SARS-CoV-2 viral load in upper respiratory specimens of infected patients. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:1177–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7121626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32074444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Örgütü DS. WHO coronavirus (COVID-19) dashboard. 2021 Available from: https://covid19.who.int . [Last accessed on 2021 Jul 10]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seneviratne CJ, Balan P, Ko KKK, Udawatte NS, Lai D, Ng DHL, et al. Efficacy of commercial mouth-rinses on SARS-CoV-2 viral load in saliva: Randomized control trial in Singapore. Infection. 2021;49:305–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7734110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33315181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel MP, Novato GF, Dourado GS, Nahás-Scocate ACR, Matias M, Maltagliati LÁ. Post-COVID-19 influence in orthodontic care from the patient’s perspective. Braz Dent Sci. 2023;26:e3597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salih Al Qassar SS, Ahmed MKH, Al-Mallah MR. Estimation of the shear bond strength and adhesive remnant index of orthodontic adhesives stored in static magnetic field. Clin Invest Orthod. 2023;82:204–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>To KKW, Tsang OTY, Yip CCY, Chan KH, Wu TC, Chan JMC, et al. Consistent detection of 2019 novel coronavirus in saliva. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:841–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32047895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qasim AA, Alani BW, Al Qassar SSS. Effects of fluoridated tooth paste on medically erosive enamel in bonded primary teeth during maxillary arch expansion in cleft palate patient: An in vitro study. J Orthod Sci. 2021;10:1–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8423160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34568213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komine A, Yamaguchi E, Okamoto N, Yamamoto K. Virucidal activity of oral care products against SARS-CoV-2 in vitro. J Oral Maxillofac Surg Med Pathol. 2021;33:475–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7898974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33643836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrouel F, Gonçalves LS, Conte MP, Campus G, Fisher J, Fraticelli L, et al. Antiviral activity of reagents in mouth rinses against SARS-CoV-2. J Dent Res. 2021;100:124–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7582358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33089717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muñoz-Basagoiti J, Perez-Zsolt D, León R, Blanc V, Raïch-Regué D, Cano-Sarabia M, et al. Mouthwashes with CPC reduce the infectivity of SARS-CoV-2 variants in vitro. J Dent Res. 2021;100:1265–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34282982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayakumar P, FelsyPremila G, Muthu MS, Kirubakaran R, Panchanadikar N, Al-Qassar SS. Bite force of children and adolescents: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Pediatr Dent. 2023;47:39–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37143420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Qassar SSS, Taqa AA, Mohiaalden HK. Can the static magnetic field improve orthodontic adhesive polymerization? J Int Dent Med Res. 2021;14:67–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshagh M, Ajami S. A comparison of force decay: Elastic chain or tie-back method? World J Orthod. 2010;11:e45–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21490987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eliades T, Bourauel C. Intraoral aging of orthodontic materials: The picture we miss and its clinical relevance. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2005;127:403–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15821684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirhashemi A, Farahmand N, Saffar Shahroudi A, Ahmad Akhoundi MS. Effect of four different mouthwashes on force-degradation pattern of orthodontic elastomeric chains. Orthod Waves. 2017;76:67–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahajan V, Singla A, Negi A, Jaj HS, Bhandari V. Influence of alcohol and alcohol-free mouthrinses on force degradation of different types of space closure auxiliaries used in sliding mechanics. J Indian Orthod Soc. 2014;48:546–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omidkhoda M, Rashed R, Khodarahmi N. Evaluation of the effects of three different mouthwashes on the force decay of orthodontic chains. Dent Res J (Isfahan) 2015;12:348.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4533193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26288625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkasso IR, Al Qassar SSS, Taqa GA. Durability of different types of mouthwashes on the salivary buffering system in orthodontic patients. Dentistry 3000. 2021;9:178–92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molena KF, Martins CROG, de Oliveira CAF, Feres MFN, de Queiroz AM. Silver nanoparticles in mouthwashes against infection caused by SARS-CoV-2: A scoping review. Braz Dent Sci. 2023;26:e3721.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Issa AR, Kadhum AS, Mohammed SA. The effects of zinc-containing mouthwashes on the force degradation of orthodontic elastomeric chains: An in vitro study. Int J Dent. 2022;2022:3557317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9076336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35531573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pithon MM, Santana DA, Sousa KH, Farias IMAO. Does chlorhexidine in different formulations interfere with the force of orthodontic elastics? Angle Orthod. 2013;83:313–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8793648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22928936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pureprasert T, Anuwongnukroh N, Dechkunakorn S, Loykulanant S, Kongkaew C, Wichai W. In: Key Engineering Materials. Trans Tech Publ; 2017. Comparison of mechanical properties of three different orthodontic latex elastic bands leached with NaOH solution; pp. 135–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega KL, Rodrigues de Camargo A, Bertoldi Franco J, Mano Azul A, Pérez Sayáns M, Braz Silva PH. SARS-CoV-2 and dentistry. Clin Oral Investig. 2020;24:2541–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7272235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32500404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bousquet JA, Jr, Tuesta O, Flores-Mir C. In vivo comparison of force decay between injection molded and die-cut stamped elastomers. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2006;129:384–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16527634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassandarvish P, Tiong V, Mohamed NA, Arumugam H, Ananthanarayanan A, Qasuri M, et al. In vitro virucidal activity of povidone iodine gargle and mouthwash against SARS-CoV-2: Implications for dental practice. Br Dent J. 2020:1–4. doi: 10.1038/s41415-020-2402-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7726738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33303923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reis INR, do Amaral GCLS, Mendoza AAH, das Graças YT, Mendes-Correa MC, Romito GA, et al. Can preprocedural mouthrinses reduce SARS-CoV-2 load in dental aerosols? Med Hypotheses. 2021;146:110436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7691843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33288313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lotzof LP, Fine HA, Cisneros GJ. Canine retraction: A comparison of two preadjusted bracket systems. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 1996;110:191–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8760846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Genova DC, McInnes-Ledoux P, Weinberg R, Shaye R. Force degradation of orthodontic elastomeric chains. A product comparison study. Am J Orthod. 1985;87:377–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3857862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baty DL, Storie DJ, Joseph A. Synthetic elastomeric chains: A literature review. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 1994;105:536–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8198077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aldrees AM, Al-Foraidi SA, Murayshed MS, Almoammar KA. Color stability and force decay of clear orthodontic elastomeric chains: An in vitro study. Int Orthod. 2015;13:287–301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26277455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guimarães GS, Morais LS de, Souza MMG de, Elias CN. Superficial morphology and mechanical properties of in vivo aged orthodontic ligatures. Dental Press J Orthod. 2013;18:107–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24094019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salih SI, Jabur AR, Mohammed TA. IOP Conference Series: Materials Science and Engineering. IOP Publishing; 2018. The effect of PVP addition on the mechanical properties of ternary polymer blends; p. 012071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmons KL, Kuang W, Burton SD, Arey BW, Shin Y, Menon NC, et al. H-Mat hydrogen compatibility of polymers and elastomers. Int J Hydrogen Energy. 2021;46:12300–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacerda dos Santos R, Pithon MM, Romanos MTV. The influence of pH levels on mechanical and biological properties of nonlatex and latex elastics. Angle Orthod. 2012;82:709–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8845539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22149622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KH, Chung CH, Choy K, Lee JS, Vanarsdall RL. Effects of prestretching on force degradation of synthetic elastomeric chains. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2005;128:477–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16214630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zainab A, Salih Al Qassar S, Abdulghani Qasim A. The effect of the static magnetic field on some of the mechanical properties of glass ionomer cements. Romanian J Stomatol. 2023;69:4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barczewski M, Matykiewicz D, Szostak M. The effect of two-step surface treatment by hydrogen peroxide and silanization of flax/cotton fabrics on epoxy-based laminates thermomechanical properties and structure. J Mater Res Technol. 2020;9:13813–24.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>