<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39450098</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2732-494X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Antimicrobial stewardship &amp; healthcare epidemiology : ASHE</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Antimicrob Steward Healthc Epidemiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Trends in SARS-CoV-2-related pediatric hospitalizations reported to the Canadian Nosocomial Infection Surveillance Program, March 2020 to December 2022.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e175</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e175</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e175</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1017/ash.2024.427</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study describes trends in COVID-19 hospitalizations and healthcare-associated (HA) COVID-19 in Canada among pediatric (age &lt;18 years) patients during pre-Omicron and Omicron-dominant periods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Prospective surveillance for COVID-19 infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The Canadian Nosocomial Infection Surveillance Program is a sentinel surveillance system with 45 hospitals providing COVID-19 data on pediatric patients, including all 13 pediatric tertiary care facilities in Canada.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PATIENTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Pediatric patients hospitalized with laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 at a participating hospital between March 1, 2020, and December 31, 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Analyzed case-level data on pediatric patients with COVID-19, including demographics, acquisition source, and outcomes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Among 5,143 pediatric cases, the majority (81%) were reported during the Omicron-dominant period (beginning December 26, 2021). However, a lower proportion required intensive care during the Omicron wave (11% vs 14%, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.05); no difference in mortality was observed. Of those patients admitted to hospital due to COVID-19 (n = 2,700), 45% had at least one pre-existing comorbidity. The majority (90%) of patients with HA-COVID-19 were reported during the Omicron period. There was no difference in mortality between patients with HA and community-associated (CA) infection, although a greater proportion of CA infections led to intensive care unit admission (6% vs 13%, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.01).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Surveillance findings indicate that both HA- and CA-COVID-19 hospitalizations in Canada increased among pediatric patients following the emergence of the Omicron variant, although disease severity decreased. Pre-existing health conditions were common among pediatric patients hospitalized with COVID-19, highlighting the importance of preventing severe illness in this sub-population.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Diane</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0001-4660-2109</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Communicable Diseases and Infection Control, Public Health Agency of Canada, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McGill</LastName><ForeName>Erin</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2856-3334</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Communicable Diseases and Infection Control, Public Health Agency of Canada, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pelude</LastName><ForeName>Linda</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Communicable Diseases and Infection Control, Public Health Agency of Canada, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mitchell</LastName><ForeName>Robyn</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Communicable Diseases and Infection Control, Public Health Agency of Canada, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Comeau</LastName><ForeName>Jeannette L</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2132-674X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Dalhousie University, Halifax, NS, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frenette</LastName><ForeName>Charles</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, McGill University Health Centre, Montréal, QC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Bonita E</ForeName><Initials>BE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8510-237X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Alberta, Stollery Children's Hospital, Edmonton, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lefebvre</LastName><ForeName>Marie-Astrid</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Montreal Children's Hospital, McGill University Health Centre, Montréal, QC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srigley</LastName><ForeName>Jocelyn A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0030-7665</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, BC Children's and BC Women's Hospitals, Vancouver, BC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thampi</LastName><ForeName>Nisha</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0208-6277</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario, Ottawa, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Antimicrob Steward Healthc Epidemiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918266096106676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2732-494X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>All authors report no conflicts of interest relevant to this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39450098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11500262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/ash.2024.427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2732494X24004273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tam J, Papenburg J, Fanella S, et al. Pediatric investigators collaborative network on infections in Canada study of respiratory syncytial virus–associated deaths in pediatric patients in Canada, 2003–2013. Clin Infect Dis An Off Publ Infect Dis Soc Am 2019;68:113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29788036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bont L, Checchia PA, Fauroux B, et al. Defining the epidemiology and burden of severe respiratory syncytial virus infection among infants and children in western countries. Infect Dis Ther 2016;5:271–298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5019979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27480325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair H, Brooks WA, Katz M, et al. Global burden of respiratory infections due to seasonal influenza in young children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet (London, England) 2011;378:1917–1930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22078723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Office of the Chief Science Advisor of Canada. COVID-19 and Children – Report of a Special Task Force Led by the Chief Science Advisor of Canada. Ottawa, Canada: Government of Canada; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maru VP, Bapat S. The COVID-19 pandemic in a paediatric population: A health care perspective. J Mother Child 2022;25:102–118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8976585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34786900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui X, Zhao Z, Zhang T, et al. A systematic review and meta-analysis of children with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). J Med Virol 2021;93:1057–1069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7436402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32761898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Souza TH, Nadal JA, Nogueira RJN, Pereira RM, Brandão MB. Clinical manifestations of children with COVID-19: A systematic review. Pediatr Pulmonol 2020;55:1892–1899.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7300659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32492251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhuiyan MU, Stiboy E, Hassan MZ, et al. Epidemiology of COVID-19 infection in young children under five years: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Vaccine 2021;39:667–677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33342635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paquette D, Bell C, Roy M, et al. Laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 in children and youth in Canada, January 15-April 27, 2020. Can Commun Dis Rep 2020;46:174–179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7279124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32558812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward JL, Harwood R, Smith C, et al. Risk factors for PICU admission and death among children and young people hospitalized with COVID-19 and PIMS-TS in England during the first pandemic year. Nat Med 2022;28:193–200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34931076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhopal SS, Bagaria J, Olabi B, Bhopal R. Children and young people remain at low risk of COVID-19 mortality. Lancet Child Adolesc Heal 2021;5:e12–e13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7946566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33713603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marks KJ, Whitaker M, Anglin O, et al. Hospitalizations of children and adolescents with laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 — COVID-NET, 14 States, July 2021–January 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022;71:271–278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8853476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35176003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kozlov M. Does omicron hit kids harder? Scientists are trying to find out. Nature 2022. doi: 10.1038/d41586-022-00309-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/d41586-022-00309-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35121816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scribner C, Patel KI, Tunik M. Pediatric croup due to omicron infection is more severe than non-COVID croup. Pediatr Emerg Care 2023;39:651–653.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36729063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cayen J, Comeau J, Conly J, et al. Surveillance for Viral Respiratory Infections among Inpatients in CNISP Hospitals. Ottawa, Canada: Public Health Agency of Canada; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell R, Cayen J, Thampi N, et al. trends in severe outcomes among adult and pediatric patients hospitalized with COVID-19 in the Canadian nosocomial infection surveillance program, March 2020 to May 2022. JAMA Netw Open 2023;6:e239050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10119741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37079304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Advisory Committee on Immunization (NACI). Recommendation on the Use of MRNA COVID-19 Vaccines in Adolescents 12 to 17 Years of Age. Ottawa, Canada: Government of Canada; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Advisory Committee on Immunization (NACI). Summary of the National Advisory Committee on Immunization (NACI) Statement Of November 19, 2021. Ottawa, Canada: Government of Canada; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Advisory Committee on Immunization (NACI). An Advisory Committee Statement (ACS) National Advisory Committee on Immunization (NACI). Ottawa, Canada: Government of Canada; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor CA, Whitaker M, Anglin O, et al. COVID-19-associated hospitalizations among adults during SARS-CoV-2 delta and omicron variant predominance, by race/ethnicity and vaccination status - COVID-NET, 14 states, July 2021-January 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022;71:466–473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8956338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35324880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havers FP, Patel K, Whitaker M, et al. Laboratory-confirmed COVID-19-associated hospitalizations among adults during SARS-CoV-2 omicron BA.2 variant predominance - COVID-19-associated hospitalization surveillance network, 14 states, June 20, 2021-May 31, 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022;71:1085–1091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9422959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36006841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolter N, Jassat W, Walaza S, et al. Early assessment of the clinical severity of the SARS-CoV-2 omicron variant in South Africa: a data linkage study. Lancet (London, England) 2022;399:437–446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8769664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35065011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewins B, Rahman M, Bermejo-Martin JF, et al. Alpha, beta, delta, omicron, and SARS-CoV-2 breakthrough cases: defining immunological mechanisms for vaccine waning and vaccine-variant mismatch. Front Virol 2022;2:849936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y, Almeida FJ, Baillie JK, et al. International pediatric COVID-19 severity over the course of the pandemic. JAMA Pediatr 2023;177:1073–1084.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10442787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37603343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan Y, Li X, Zhang L, Wan S, Zhang L, Zhou F. SARS-CoV-2 omicron variant: recent progress and future perspectives. Signal Transduct Target Ther 2022;7:141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9047469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35484110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasreen S, Chung H, He S, et al. Effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines against symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection and severe outcomes with variants of concern in Ontario. Nat Microbiol 2022;7:379–385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35132198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez Bernal J, Andrews N, Gower C, et al. Effectiveness of Covid-19 vaccines against the B.1.617.2 (delta) variant. N Engl J Med 2021;385:585–594.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8314739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34289274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public Health Agency of Canada. Canadian COVID-19 Vaccination Coverage Report. Ottawa, Canada: Government of Canada; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kompaniyets L, Agathis NT, Nelson JM, et al. underlying medical conditions associated with severe COVID-19 illness among children. JAMA Netw open 2021;4(6):e2111182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8185607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34097050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govil-Dalela T, Sivaswamy L. Neurological effects of COVID-19 in children. Pediatr Clin North Am 2021;68:1081.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8445748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34538300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim Y, Walser SA, Asghar SJ, Jain R, Mainali G, Kumar A. A comprehensive review of neurologic manifestations of COVID-19 and management of pre-existing neurologic disorders in children. J Child Neurol 2021;36:324–330.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7859660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33112694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsankov BK, Allaire JM, Irvine MA, et al. Severe COVID-19 infection and pediatric comorbidities: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Infect Dis 2021;103:246–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7679116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33227520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leal J, O’Grady HM, Armstrong L, et al. Patient and ward related risk factors in a multi-ward nosocomial outbreak of COVID-19: Outbreak investigation and matched case–control study. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control 2023;12:1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10031162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36949510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson M, Collins C, Nash DB, Panesar LE, Coronavirus Disease Oster ME. 2019 infection in children with pre-existing heart disease. J Pediatr 2020;227:302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7384421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32730815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponsford MJ, Ward TJC, Stoneham SM, et al. a systematic review and meta-analysis of inpatient mortality associated with nosocomial and community COVID-19 exposes the vulnerability of immunosuppressed adults. Front Immunol 2021;12:744696.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8526940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34691049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGill E, Cayen J, Ellison J, et al. An assessment of the validity and reliability of SARS-CoV-2 infection surveillance data from the Canadian Nosocomial Infection Surveillance Program (CNISP). Can J Infect Control in pres. s.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klann JG, Strasser ZH, Hutch MR, et al. Distinguishing admissions specifically for COVID-19 from incidental SARS-CoV-2 admissions: national retrospective electronic health record study. J Med Internet Res. 2022;24:e37931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9119395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35476727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai J, Traub E, Aoki K, et al. Incidentally detected SARS-COV-2 among hospitalized patients in Los Angeles county, August to October 2020. J Hosp Med. 2021;16:480–483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8340959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34328848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>