<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39457519</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2227-9059</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biomedicines</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biomedicines</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficacy of Ivermectin, Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine, and Azithromycin in Managing COVID-19: A Systematic Review of Phase III Clinical Trials.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2206</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/biomedicines12102206</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><b>Background:</b> During the coronavirus disease (COVID)-19 pandemic several drugs were used to manage the patients mainly those with a severe phenotype. Potential drugs were used off-label and major concerns arose from their applicability to managing the health crisis highlighting the importance of clinical trials. In this context, we described the mechanisms of the three repurposed drugs [Ivermectin-antiparasitic drug, Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine-antimalarial drugs, and Azithromycin-antimicrobial drug]; and, based on this description, the study evaluated the clinical efficacy of those drugs published in clinical trials. The use of these drugs reflects the period of uncertainty that marked the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic, which made them a possible treatment for COVID-19. <b>Methods:</b> In our review, we evaluated phase III randomized controlled clinical trials (RCTs) that analyzed the efficacy of these drugs published from the COVID-19 pandemic onset to 2023. We included eight RCTs published for Ivermectin, 11 RCTs for Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine, and three RCTs for Azithromycin. The research question (PICOT) accounted for P-hospitalized patients with confirmed or suspected COVID-19; I-use of oral or intravenous Ivermectin OR Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine OR Azithromycin; C-placebo or no placebo (standard of care); O-mortality OR hospitalization OR viral clearance OR need for mechanical ventilation OR clinical improvement; and T-phase III RCTs. <b>Results:</b> While studying these drugs' respective mechanisms of action, the reasons for which they were thought to be useful became apparent and are as follows: Ivermectin binds to insulin-like growth factor and prevents nuclear transportation of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), therefore preventing cell entrance, induces apoptosis, and osmotic cell death and disrupts viral replication. Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine blocks the movement of SARS-CoV-2 from early endosomes to lysosomes inside the cell, also, this drug blocks the binding between SARS-CoV-2 and Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme (ACE)-2 inhibiting the interaction between the virus spike proteins and the cell membrane and this drug can also inhibit SARS-CoV-2 viral replication causing, ultimately, the reduction in viral infection as well as the potential to progression for a higher severity phenotype culminating with a higher chance of death. Azithromycin exerts a down-regulating effect on the inflammatory cascade, attenuating the excessive production of cytokines and inducing phagocytic activity, and acts interfering with the viral replication cycle. Ivermectin, when compared to standard care or placebo, did not reduce the disease severity, need for mechanical ventilation, need for intensive care unit, or in-hospital mortality. Only one study demonstrated that Ivermectin may improve viral clearance compared to placebo. Individuals who received Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine did not present a lower incidence of death, improved clinical status, or higher chance of respiratory deterioration compared to those who received usual care or placebo. Also, some studies demonstrated that Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine resulted in worse outcomes and side-effects included severe ones. Adding Azithromycin to a standard of care did not result in clinical improvement in hospitalized COVID-19 participants. In brief, COVID-19 was one of the deadliest pandemics in modern human history. Due to the potential health catastrophe caused by SARS-CoV-2, a global effort was made to evaluate treatments for COVID-19 to attenuate its impact on the human species. Unfortunately, several countries prematurely justified the emergency use of drugs that showed only in vitro effects against SARS-CoV-2, with a dearth of evidence supporting efficacy in humans. In this context, we reviewed the mechanisms of several drugs proposed to treat COVID-19, including Ivermectin, Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine, and Azithromycin, as well as the phase III clinical trials that evaluated the efficacy of these drugs for treating patients with this respiratory disease. <b>Conclusions:</b> As the main finding, although Ivermectin, Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine, and Azithromycin might have mechanistic effects against SARS-CoV-2 infection, most phase III clinical trials observed no treatment benefit in patients with COVID-19, underscoring the need for robust phase III clinical trials.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sansone</LastName><ForeName>Nathália Mariana Santos</ForeName><Initials>NMS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Laboratory of Clinical and Molecular Microbiology, LunGuardian Research Group-Epidemiology of Respiratory and Infectious Diseases, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista 12916-900, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boschiero</LastName><ForeName>Matheus Negri</ForeName><Initials>MN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Laboratory of Clinical and Molecular Microbiology, LunGuardian Research Group-Epidemiology of Respiratory and Infectious Diseases, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista 12916-900, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>São Paulo Hospital, Federal University of São Paulo, São Paulo 04023-062, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marson</LastName><ForeName>Fernando Augusto Lima</ForeName><Initials>FAL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4955-4234</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Laboratory of Clinical and Molecular Microbiology, LunGuardian Research Group-Epidemiology of Respiratory and Infectious Diseases, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista 12916-900, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Biomedicines</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101691304</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2227-9059</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibiotics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">azithromycin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chloroquine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical trial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coronavirus disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hydroxychloroquine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ivermectin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39457519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11505156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biomedicines12102206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">biomedicines12102206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alanagreh L., Alzoughool F., Atoum M. The Human Coronavirus Disease COVID-19: Its Origin, Characteristics, and Insights into Potential Drugs and Its Mechanisms. Pathogens. 2020;9:331. doi: 10.3390/pathogens9050331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens9050331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7280997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32365466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C., Wang Y., Li X., Ren L., Zhao J., Hu Y., Zhang L., Fan G., Xu J., Gu X., et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet. 2020;395:497–506. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30183-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30183-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou P., Yang X.-L., Wang X.-G., Hu B., Zhang L., Zhang W., Si H.-R., Zhu Y., Li B., Huang C.-L., et al. A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin. Nature. 2020;579:270–273. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu C.-J., Wang Z.-X., Xu Y., Hu M.-X., Chen K., Qin G. Assessment of basic reproductive number for COVID-19 at global level. Medicine. 2021;100:e25837. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000025837.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000025837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8104145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33950996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alimohamadi Y., Tola H.H., Abbasi-Ghahramanloo A., Janani M., Sepandi M. Case Fatality Rate of COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. J. Prev. Med. Hyg. 2021;62:E311–E320. doi: 10.15167/2421-4248/jpmh2021.62.2.1627.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15167/2421-4248/jpmh2021.62.2.1627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8451339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34604571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero M.N., Palamim C.V.C., Ortega M.M., Mauch R.M., Marson F.A.L. One Year of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Brazil: A Political and Social Overview. Ann. Glob. Health. 2021;87:44. doi: 10.5334/aogh.3182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5334/aogh.3182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8139306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34046307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins J.P., Siqueira B.A., Sansone N.M.S., Marson F.A.L. COVID-19 in Brazil: A 3-year update. Diagn. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2023;107:116074. doi: 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2023.116074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2023.116074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37729718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marson F., Ortega M. COVID-19 in Brazil. Pulmonology. 2020;26:241–244. doi: 10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.04.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.04.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7183991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32371054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Results—RECOVERY Trial.  [(accessed on 29 January 2022)].  Available online:  https://www.recoverytrial.net/results.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreani J., Le Bideau M., Duflot I., Jardot P., Rolland C., Boxberger M., Wurtz N., Rolain J.-M., Colson P., La Scola B., et al. In vitro testing of combined hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin on SARS-CoV-2 shows synergistic effect. Microb. Pathog. 2020;145:104228. doi: 10.1016/j.micpath.2020.104228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2020.104228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7182748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32344177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caly L., Druce J.D., Catton M.G., Jans D.A., Wagstaff K.M. The FDA-approved drug ivermectin inhibits the replication of SARS-CoV-2 in vitro. Antivir. Res. 2020;178:104787. doi: 10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104787.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7129059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32251768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao X., Ye F., Zhang M., Cui C., Huang B., Niu P., Liu X., Zhao L., Dong E., Song C., et al. In Vitro Antiviral Activity and Projection of Optimized Dosing Design of Hydroxychloroquine for the Treatment of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) Clin. Infect. Dis. 2020;71:732–739. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciaa237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Pol K.H., Aljofan M., Blin O., Cornel J.H., Rongen G.A., Woestelandt A.-G., Spedding M. Drug Repurposing of Generic Drugs: Challenges and the Potential Role for Government. Appl. Health Econ. Health Policy. 2023;21:831–840. doi: 10.1007/s40258-023-00816-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40258-023-00816-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10627937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37398987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solla D.J.F. Hydroxychloroquine for the treatment of COVID-19: An approach based on the philosophy of science and heuristics. J. Evid.-Based Health. 2020;2:28–31. doi: 10.17267/2675-021Xevidence.v2i1.2890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17267/2675-021Xevidence.v2i1.2890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ioannidis J.P.A. Why Most Published Research Findings Are False. PLoS Med. 2005;2:e124. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.0020124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1182327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16060722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard|WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard with Vaccination Data.  [(accessed on 26 April 2021)].  Available online:  https://covid19.who.int/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okumuş N., Demirtürk N., Çetinkaya R.A., Güner R., Avcı İ.Y., Orhan S., Konya P., Şaylan B., Karalezli A., Yamanel L., et al. Evaluation of the effectiveness and safety of adding ivermectin to treatment in severe COVID-19 patients. BMC Infect. Dis. 2021;21:411. doi: 10.1186/s12879-021-06104-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06104-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8093585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33947344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niaee M.S., Namdar P., Allami A., Zolghadr L., Javadi A., Karampour A., Varnaseri M., Bijani B., Cheraghi F., Naderi Y., et al. Ivermectin as an adjunct treatment for hospitalized adult COVID-19 patients. Asian Pac. J. Trop. Med. 2021;14:266–273. doi: 10.4103/1995-7645.318304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/1995-7645.318304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez J.L.B., Gámez M.G., Enciso E.A.M., Maldonado R.J.E., Palacios D.H., Campos S.D., Robles I.O., Guzmán M.J.M., Díaz A.L.G., Peña C.M.G., et al. Efficacy and Safety of Ivermectin and Hydroxychloroquine in Patients with Severe COVID-19: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Infect. Dis. Rep. 2022;14:160–168. doi: 10.3390/idr14020020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/idr14020020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8938813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35314650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heydari M.R., Rahimi Y., Foroozanfar Z., Mirahmadizadeh A., Dashti A.S., Afrashteh S., Aminnia S., Ebrahimi N.D., Sadeghi A., Motamedi A., et al. The Efficacy of Ivermectin and Metronidazole vs. Standard Treatment Protocols on Outcomes of COVID-19 in Hospitalized Patients: A Triple-Blinded Randomized Controlled Trial. Arch. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2022;17:e122525. doi: 10.5812/archcid-122525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5812/archcid-122525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim S.C.L., Hor C.P., Tay K.H., Jelani A.M., Tan W.H., Ker H.B., Chow T.S., Zaid M., Cheah W.K., Lim H.H., et al. Efficacy of Ivermectin Treatment on Disease Progression Among Adults With Mild to Moderate COVID-19 and Comorbidities. JAMA Intern. Med. 2022;182:426–435. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.0189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.0189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8980926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35179551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qadeer R., Kashif S.M., Kumar D., Mehmmood M., Lal J., Faizan Ivermectin A Potential Treatment In COVID-19, Related to Critical Illness. Pak. J. Med. Health Sci. 2022;16:24–26. doi: 10.53350/pjmhs2216824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.53350/pjmhs2216824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezai M.S., Ahangarkani F., Hill A., Ellis L., Mirchandani M., Davoudi A., Eslami G., Roozbeh F., Babamahmoodi F., Rouhani N., et al. Non-effectiveness of Ivermectin on Inpatients and Outpatients With COVID-19; Results of Two Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials. Front. Med. 2022;9:919708. doi: 10.3389/fmed.2022.919708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.919708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9244711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35783616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baghbanian R., Savaie M., Soltani F., Rashidi M., MalAmir M.D., Amiri F., Bakhtiari N. The effect of adding ivermectin to the standard COVID-19 treatment in intubated patients. J. Nephropharmacol. 2023;12:e10589. doi: 10.34172/npj.2023.10589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34172/npj.2023.10589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>RECOVERY Collaborative Group Effect of Hydroxychloroquine in Hospitalized Patients with COVID-19. N. Engl. J. Med. 2020;383:2030–2040. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2022926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2022926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7556338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33031652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Self W.H., Semler M.W., Leither L.M., Casey J.D., Angus D.C., Brower R.G., Chang S.Y., Collins S.P., Eppensteiner J.C., Filbin M.R., et al. Effect of Hydroxychloroquine on Clinical Status at 14 Days in Hospitalized Patients With COVID-19. JAMA. 2020;324:2165–2176. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.22240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.22240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7653542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33165621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ader F., Peiffer-Smadja N., Poissy J., Bouscambert-Duchamp M., Belhadi D., Diallo A., Delmas C., Saillard J., Dechanet A., Mercier N., et al. An open-label randomized controlled trial of the effect of lopinavir/ritonavir, lopinavir/ritonavir plus IFN-β-1a and hydroxychloroquine in hospitalized patients with COVID-19. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2021;27:1826–1837. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2021.05.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2021.05.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8149166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34048876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arabi Y.M., Gordon A.C., Derde L.P.G., Nichol A.D., Murthy S., Al Beidh F., Annane D., Al Swaidan L., Beane A., Beasley R., et al. Lopinavir-ritonavir and hydroxychloroquine for critically ill patients with COVID-19: REMAP-CAP randomized controlled trial. Intensiv. Care Med. 2021;47:867–886. doi: 10.1007/s00134-021-06448-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00134-021-06448-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8274471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34251506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubée V., Roy P.-M., Vielle B., Parot-Schinkel E., Blanchet O., Darsonval A., Lefeuvre C., Abbara C., Boucher S., Robineau O., et al. Hydroxychloroquine in mild-to-moderate coronavirus disease 2019: A placebo-controlled double blind trial. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2021;27:1124–1130. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2021.03.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2021.03.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8015393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33813110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernandez-Cardenas C., Thirion-Romero I., Rodríguez-Llamazares S., Rivera-Martinez N.E., Meza-Meneses P., Remigio-Luna A., Perez-Padilla R., on behalf of the Research Group on Hydroxychloroquine for COVID-19 Hydroxychloroquine for the treatment of severe respiratory infection by COVID-19: A randomized controlled trial. PLoS ONE. 2021;16:e0257238. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0257238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0257238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8478184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34582477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Solidarity Trial Consortium Repurposed Antiviral Drugs for COVID-19—Interim WHO Solidarity Trial Results. N. Engl. J. Med. 2021;384:497–511. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2023184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2023184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7727327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33264556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Réa-Neto Á., Bernardelli R.S., Câmara B.M.D., Reese F.B., Queiroga M.V.O., Oliveira M.C. An open-label randomized controlled trial evaluating the efficacy of chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine in severe COVID-19 patients. Sci. Rep. 2021;11:9023. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-88509-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-88509-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8079411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33907251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ader F. An open-label randomized, controlled trial of the effect of lopinavir and ritonavir, lopinavir and ritonavir plus interferon-β-1a, and hydroxychloroquine in hospitalized patients with COVID-19: Final results. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2022;28:1293–1296. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2022.04.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2022.04.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9076583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35533972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NCT04358081 Hydroxychloroquine Monotherapy and in Combination with Azithromycin in Patients with Moderate and Severe COVID-19 Disease.  [(accessed on 22 August 2024)]; Available online:  https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04358081.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavalcanti A.B., Zampieri F.G., Rosa R.G., Azevedo L.C., Veiga V.C., Avezum A., Damiani L.P., Marcadenti A., Kawano-Dourado L., Lisboa T., et al. Hydroxychloroquine with or without Azithromycin in Mild-to-Moderate COVID-19. N. Engl. J. Med. 2020;383:2041–2052. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2019014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2019014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7397242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32706953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furtado R.H.M., Berwanger O., Fonseca H.A., Corrêa T.D., Ferraz L.R., Lapa M.G., Zampieri F.G., Veiga V.C., Azevedo L.C.P., Rosa R.G., et al. Azithromycin in addition to standard of care versus standard of care alone in the treatment of patients admitted to the hospital with severe COVID-19 in Brazil (COALITION II): A randomised clinical trial. Lancet. 2020;396:959–967. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31862-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31862-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7836431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32896292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abaleke E., Abbas M., Abbasi S., Abbott A., Abdelaziz A., Abdelbadiee S., Abdelfattah M., Abdul B., Rasheed A.A., Abdul-Kadir R., et al. Azithromycin in patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 (RECOVERY): A randomised, controlled, open-label, platform trial. Lancet. 2021;397:605–612. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(21)00149-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(21)00149-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7884931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33545096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sterne J.A.C., Savović J., Page M.J., Elbers R.G., Blencowe N.S., Boutron I., Cates C.J., Cheng H.Y., Corbett M.S., Eldridge S.M., et al. RoB 2: A revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials. BMJ. 2019;366:l4898. doi: 10.1136/bmj.l4898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.l4898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31462531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page M.J., Moher D., Bossuyt P.M., Boutron I., Hoffmann T.C., Mulrow C.D., Shamseer L., Tetzlaff J.M., Akl E.A., Brennan S.E., et al. PRISMA 2020 explanation and elaboration: Updated guidance and exemplars for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;372:n160. doi: 10.1136/bmj.n160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33781993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page M.J., McKenzie J.E., Bossuyt P.M., Boutron I., Hoffmann T.C., Mulrow C.D., Shamseer L., Tetzlaff J.M., Akl E.A., Brennan S.E., et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: An updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. Syst. Rev. 2021;10 doi: 10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8008539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33781348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Model Lists of Essential Medicines.  [(accessed on 26 February 2022)].  Available online:  https://www.who.int/groups/expert-committee-on-selection-and-use-of-essential-medicines/essential-medicines-lists.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juarez M., Schcolnik-Cabrera A., Duenas-Gonzalez A. The multitargeted drug ivermectin: From an antiparasitic agent to a repositioned cancer drug. Am. J. Cancer Res. 2018;8:317–331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5835698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29511601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur H., Shekhar N., Sharma S., Sarma P., Prakash A., Medhi B. Ivermectin as a potential drug for treatment of COVID-19: An in-sync review with clinical and computational attributes. Pharmacol. Rep. 2021;73:736–749. doi: 10.1007/s43440-020-00195-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43440-020-00195-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7778723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33389725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heidary F., Gharebaghi R. Ivermectin: A systematic review from antiviral effects to COVID-19 complementary regimen. J. Antibiot. 2020;73:593–602. doi: 10.1038/s41429-020-0336-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41429-020-0336-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7290143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32533071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baudou E., Lespine A., Durrieu G., André F., Gandia P., Durand C., Cunat S. Serious Ivermectin Toxicity and Human ABCB1 Nonsense Mutations. N. Engl. J. Med. 2020;383:787–789. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1917344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc1917344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32813957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gussow L. Toxicology Rounds. Emerg. Med. News. 2021;43:1. doi: 10.1097/01.eem.0000800476.28069.a2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.eem.0000800476.28069.a2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molento M.B. Ivermectin against COVID-19: The unprecedented consequences in Latin America. One Health. 2021;13:100250. doi: 10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8050401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33880395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaidi A.K., Dehgani-Mobaraki P. The mechanisms of action of ivermectin against SARS-CoV-2—An extensive review. J. Antibiot. 2021;75:60–71. doi: 10.1038/s41429-021-00491-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41429-021-00491-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8688140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34931048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhury A., Das N.C., Patra R., Bhattacharya M., Ghosh P., Patra B.C., Mukherjee S. Exploring the Binding Efficacy of Ivermectin Against the Key Proteins of SARS-CoV-2 Pathogenesis: An in silico Approach. Future Virol. 2021;16:277–291. doi: 10.2217/fvl-2020-0342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2217/fvl-2020-0342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharmeen S., Skrtic M., Sukhai M.A., Hurren R., Gronda M., Wang X., Fonseca S.B., Sun H., Wood T.E., Ward R., et al. The antiparasitic agent ivermectin induces chloride-dependent membrane hyperpolarization and cell death in leukemia cells. Blood. 2010;116:3593–3603. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-01-262675.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/blood-2010-01-262675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20644115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dominguez-Gomez G., Chavez-Blanco A., Medina-Franco J.L., Saldivar-Gonzalez F., Flores-Torrontegui Y., Juarez M., Díaz-Chávez J., Gonzalez-Fierro A., Dueñas-González A. Ivermectin as an inhibitor of cancer stem-like cells. Mol. Med. Rep. 2017;17:3397–3403. doi: 10.3892/mmr.2017.8231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3892/mmr.2017.8231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29257278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S.N.Y., Atkinson S.C., Wang C., Lee A., Bogoyevitch M.A., Borg N.A., Jans D.A. The broad spectrum antiviral ivermectin targets the host nuclear transport importin α/β1 heterodimer. Antivir. Res. 2020;177:104760. doi: 10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32135219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mody V., Ho J., Wills S., Mawri A., Lawson L., Ebert M.C.C.J.C., Fortin G.M., Rayalam S., Taval S. Identification of 3-chymotrypsin like protease (3CLPro) inhibitors as potential anti-SARS-CoV-2 agents. Commun. Biol. 2021;4:1–10. doi: 10.1038/s42003-020-01577-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s42003-020-01577-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7817688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33473151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Song Y., Ci X., An N., Ju Y., Li H., Wang X., Han C., Cui J., Deng X. Ivermectin inhibits LPS-induced production of inflammatory cytokines and improves LPS-induced survival in mice. Inflamm. Res. 2008;57:524–529. doi: 10.1007/s00011-008-8007-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00011-008-8007-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19109745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seth C., Mas C., Conod A., Mueller J., Siems K., Kuciak M., Borges I., i Altaba A.R. Long-Lasting WNT-TCF Response Blocking and Epigenetic Modifying Activities of Withanolide F in Human Cancer Cells. PLoS ONE. 2016;11:e0168170. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0168170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0168170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5156407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27973612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Melo G.D., Lazarini F., Larrous F., Feige L., Kornobis E., Levallois S., Marchio A., Kergoat L., Hardy D., Cokelaer T., et al. Attenuation of clinical and immunological outcomes during SARS-CoV-2 infection by ivermectin. EMBO Mol. Med. 2021;13:e14122. doi: 10.15252/emmm.202114122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15252/emmm.202114122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8350903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34170074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzzo C., Furtek C., Porras A., Chen C., Tipping R., Clineschmidt C., Sciberras D., Hsieh J.-K., Lasseter K. Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of Escalating High Doses of Ivermectin in Healthy Adult Subjects. J. Clin. Pharmacol. 2002;42:1122–1133. doi: 10.1177/009127002237994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/009127002237994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12362927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garegnani L.I., Madrid E., Meza N. Misleading clinical evidence and systematic reviews on ivermectin for COVID-19. BMJ Evid.-Based Med. 2021;27:156–158. doi: 10.1136/bmjebm-2021-111678.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjebm-2021-111678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33888547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peña-Silva R., Duffull S.B., Steer A.C., Jaramillo-Rincon S.X., Gwee A., Zhu X. Pharmacokinetic considerations on the repurposing of ivermectin for treatment of COVID-19. Br. J. Clin. Pharmacol. 2021;87:1589–1590. doi: 10.1111/bcp.14476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bcp.14476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7404744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32779815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The RECOVERY Collaborative Group Dexamethasone in Hospitalized Patients with COVID-19. N. Engl. J. Med. 2021;384:693–704. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2021436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2021436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7383595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32678530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dessie Z.G., Zewotir T. Mortality-related risk factors of COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis of 42 studies and 423,117 patients. BMC Infect. Dis. 2021;21:855. doi: 10.1186/s12879-021-06536-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06536-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8380115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34418980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popp M., Stegemann M., Metzendorf M.-I., Gould S., Kranke P., Meybohm P., Skoetz N., Weibel S. Ivermectin for preventing and treating COVID-19. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 2021;2021:CD015017. doi: 10.55633/s3me/E029.2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.55633/s3me/E029.2023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8406455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34318930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinis-Oliveira R.J. COVID-19 research: Pandemic versus “paperdemic”, integrity, values and risks of the “speed science”. Forensic Sci. Res. 2020;5:174–187. doi: 10.1080/20961790.2020.1767754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/20961790.2020.1767754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7476615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32939434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>PubChem Chloroquine.  [(accessed on 24 May 2022)]; Available online:  https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/2719.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent M.J., Bergeron E., Benjannet S., Erickson B.R., Rollin P.E., Ksiazek T.G., Seidah N.G., Nichol S.T. Chloroquine is a potent inhibitor of SARS coronavirus infection and spread. Virol. J. 2005;2:69. doi: 10.1186/1743-422X-2-69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-2-69</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1232869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16115318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vigerust D.J., McCullers J.A. Chloroquine is effective against influenza A virus in vitro but not in vivo. Influ. Other Respir. Viruses. 2007;1:189–192. doi: 10.1111/j.1750-2659.2007.00027.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-2659.2007.00027.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4941887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19453426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan Y., Zou Z., Sun Y., Li X., Xu K.-F., Wei Y., Jin N., Jiang C. Anti-malaria drug chloroquine is highly effective in treating avian influenza A H5N1 virus infection in an animal model. Cell Res. 2012;23:300–302. doi: 10.1038/cr.2012.165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/cr.2012.165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3567830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23208422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>PubChem Hydroxychloroquine.  [(accessed on 24 May 2022)]; Available online:  https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/3652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mauthe M., Orhon I., Rocchi C., Zhou X., Luhr M., Hijlkema K.-J., Coppes R.P., Engedal N., Mari M., Reggiori F. Chloroquine inhibits autophagic flux by decreasing autophagosome-lysosome fusion. Autophagy. 2018;14:1435–1455. doi: 10.1080/15548627.2018.1474314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15548627.2018.1474314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6103682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29940786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satarker S., Ahuja T., Banerjee M., Balaji E V., Dogra S., Agarwal T., Nampoothiri M. Hydroxychloroquine in COVID-19: Potential Mechanism of Action Against SARS-CoV-2. Curr. Pharmacol. Rep. 2020;6:203–211. doi: 10.1007/s40495-020-00231-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40495-020-00231-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7443392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32864299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang A., Guduguntla L.S., Yang B. Potentials of Interferons and Hydroxychloroquine for the Prophylaxis and Early Treatment of COVID-19. J. Cell. Immunol. 2020;2:333–340. doi: 10.33696/immunology.2.063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.33696/immunology.2.063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7793568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33426541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J., Cao R., Xu M., Wang X., Zhang H., Hu H., Li Y., Hu Z., Zhong W., Wang M. Hydroxychloroquine, a less toxic derivative of chloroquine, is effective in inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 infection in vitro. Cell Discov. 2020;6:16. doi: 10.1038/s41421-020-0156-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41421-020-0156-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7078228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32194981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia H.P., Look D.C., Shi L., Hickey M., Pewe L., Netland J., Farzan M., Wohlford-Lenane C., Perlman S., McCray P.B., Jr. ACE2 Receptor Expression and Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus Infection Depend on Differentiation of Human Airway Epithelia. J. Virol. 2005;79:14614–14621. doi: 10.1128/JVI.79.23.14614-14621.2005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.79.23.14614-14621.2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1287568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16282461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M., Kleine-Weber H., Schroeder S., Krüger N., Herrler T., Erichsen S., Schiergens T.S., Herrler G., Wu N.-H., Nitsche A., et al. SARS-CoV-2 Cell Entry Depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and Is Blocked by a Clinically Proven Protease Inhibitor. Cell. 2020;181:271–280.e8. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fantini J., Di Scala C., Chahinian H., Yahi N. Structural and molecular modelling studies reveal a new mechanism of action of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine against SARS-CoV-2 infection. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2020;55:105960. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105960.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7128678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32251731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gbinigie K., Frie K. Should chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine be used to treat COVID-19? A rapid review. BJGP Open. 2020;4 doi: 10.3399/bjgpopen20X101069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/bjgpopen20X101069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7330219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32265182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bansal P., Goyal A., Cusick A., Lahan S., Dhaliwal H.S., Bhyan P., Bhattad P.B., Aslam F., Ranka S., Dalia T., et al. Hydroxychloroquine: A comprehensive review and its controversial role in coronavirus disease 2019. Ann. Med. 2020;53:117–134. doi: 10.1080/07853890.2020.1839959.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07853890.2020.1839959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7880079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33095083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinha N., Balayla G. Hydroxychloroquine and COVID-19. Postgrad. Med. J. 2020;96:550–555. doi: 10.1136/postgradmedj-2020-137785.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/postgradmedj-2020-137785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10016880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32295814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J., Tecson K.M., McCullough P.A. Endothelial dysfunction contributes to COVID-19-associated vascular inflammation and coagulopathy. Rev. Cardiovasc. Med. 2020;21:315–319. doi: 10.31083/j.rcm.2020.03.126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31083/j.rcm.2020.03.126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33070537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pothen L., Yildiz H., Samnick M.M., Yombi J.C. Hydroxychloroquine in the post-COVID-19 era: Will this pandemic upset decades of clinical practice? Clin. Rheumatol. 2021;40:1649–1657. doi: 10.1007/s10067-020-05572-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10067-020-05572-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7810282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33452660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An J., Woodward J.J., Lai W., Minie M., Sun X., Tanaka L., Snyder J.M., Sasaki T., Elkon K.B. Inhibition of Cyclic GMP-AMP Synthase Using a Novel Antimalarial Drug Derivative in Trex1-Deficient Mice. Arthritis Rheumatol. 2018;70:1807–1819. doi: 10.1002/art.40559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/art.40559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29781188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahu P., Mudgal J., Arora D., Kinra M., Mallik S.B., Rao C.M., Pai K.S.R., Nampoothiri M. Cannabinoid receptor 2 activation mitigates lipopolysaccharide-induced neuroinflammation and sickness behavior in mice. Psychopharmacology. 2019;236:1829–1838. doi: 10.1007/s00213-019-5166-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00213-019-5166-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30666359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schrezenmeier E., Dörner T. Mechanisms of action of hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine: Implications for rheumatology. Nat. Rev. Rheumatol. 2020;16:155–166. doi: 10.1038/s41584-020-0372-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41584-020-0372-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32034323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou D., Dai S.-M., Tong Q. COVID-19: A recommendation to examine the effect of hydroxychloroquine in preventing infection and progression. J. Antimicrob. Chemother. 2020;75:1667–1670. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkaa114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/dkaa114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32196083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Izcovich A., Siemieniuk R.A., Bartoszko J.J., Ge L., Zeraatkar D., Kum E., Qasim A., Khamis A.M., Rochwerg B., Agoritsas T., et al. Adverse effects of remdesivir, hydroxychloroquine and lopinavir/ritonavir when used for COVID-19: Systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised trials. BMJ Open. 2022;12:e048502. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2020-048502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-048502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8895418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35236729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh B., Ryan H., Kredo T., Chaplin M., Fletcher T. Chloroquine or hydroxychloroquine for prevention and treatment of COVID-19. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 2021;2021:CD013587. doi: 10.1002/14651858.cd013587.pub2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.cd013587.pub2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8094389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33624299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Moraes V.Y., Marra A.R., Matos L.L., Serpa A., Rizzo L.V., Cendoroglo M., Lenza M. Hydroxychloroquine for treatment of COVID-19 patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Einstein-Sao Paulo. 2022;20 doi: 10.31744/einstein_journal/2022RW0045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31744/einstein_journal/2022RW0045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9744433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36477526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parnham M.J., Haber V.E., Giamarellos-Bourboulis E.J., Perletti G., Verleden G.M., Vos R. Azithromycin: Mechanisms of action and their relevance for clinical applications. Pharmacol. Ther. 2014;143:225–245. doi: 10.1016/j.pharmthera.2014.03.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pharmthera.2014.03.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24631273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien K.S., Emerson P., Hooper P.J., Reingold A.L., Dennis E.G., Keenan J.D., Lietman T.M., Oldenburg C.E. Antimicrobial resistance following mass azithromycin distribution for trachoma: A systematic review. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2018;19:e14–e25. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30444-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30444-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30292480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amsden G. Advanced-generation macrolides: Tissue-directed antibiotics. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2001;18:11–15. doi: 10.1016/S0924-8579(01)00410-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0924-8579(01)00410-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11574189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mertens V., Blondeau K., Pauwels A., Farre R., Vanaudenaerde B., Vos R., Verleden G., Van Raemdonck D.E., Dupont L.J., Sifrim D. Azithromycin Reduces Gastroesophageal Reflux and Aspiration in Lung Transplant Recipients. Dig. Dis. Sci. 2009;54:972–979. doi: 10.1007/s10620-009-0725-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10620-009-0725-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19241165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Renna M., Schaffner C., Brown K., Shang S., Tamayo M.H., Hegyi K., Grimsey N.J., Cusens D., Coulter S., Cooper J., et al. Azithromycin blocks autophagy and may predispose cystic fibrosis patients to mycobacterial infection. J. Clin. Investig. 2011;121:3554–3563. doi: 10.1172/JCI46095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1172/JCI46095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3163956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21804191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang A.F., Palmer J.N., Chiu A.G., Blumer J.L., Crownover P.H., Campbell M.D., Damle B.D. Pharmacokinetics of azithromycin in plasma and sinus mucosal tissue following administration of extended-release or immediate-release formulations in adult patients with chronic rhinosinusitis. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2009;34:67–71. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2009.01.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2009.01.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19307106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amsden G.W. Anti-inflammatory effects of macrolides—An underappreciated benefit in the treatment of community-acquired respiratory tract infections and chronic inflammatory pulmonary conditions? J. Antimicrob. Chemother. 2005;55:10–21. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkh519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/dkh519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15590715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen J.L., Ippolito J.A., Ban N., Nissen P., Moore P.B., Steitz T.A. The Structures of Four Macrolide Antibiotics Bound to the Large Ribosomal Subunit. Mol. Cell. 2002;10:117–128. doi: 10.1016/S1097-2765(02)00570-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(02)00570-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12150912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belser J.A., Zeng H., Katz J.M., Tumpey T.M. Infection With Highly Pathogenic H7 Influenza Viruses Results in an Attenuated Proinflammatory Cytokine and Chemokine Response Early After Infection. J. Infect. Dis. 2011;203:40–48. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiq018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiq018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3086437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21148495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Min J.-Y., Jang Y.J. Macrolide Therapy in Respiratory Viral Infections. Mediat. Inflamm. 2012;2012:1–9. doi: 10.1155/2012/649570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2012/649570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3375106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22719178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarogoulidis P., Papanas N., Kioumis I., Chatzaki E., Maltezos E., Zarogoulidis K. Macrolides: From in vitro anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory properties to clinical practice in respiratory diseases. Eur. J. Clin. Pharmacol. 2012;68:479–503. doi: 10.1007/s00228-011-1161-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00228-011-1161-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22105373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cramer C.L., Patterson A., Alchakaki A., Soubani A.O. Immunomodulatory indications of azithromycin in respiratory disease: A concise review for the clinician. Postgrad. Med. 2017;129:493–499. doi: 10.1080/00325481.2017.1285677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00325481.2017.1285677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28116959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gielen V., Johnston S.L., Edwards M.R. Azithromycin induces anti-viral responses in bronchial epithelial cells. Eur. Respir. J. 2010;36:646–654. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00095809.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/09031936.00095809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20150207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizk J.G., Kalantar-Zadeh K., Mehra M.R., Lavie C.J., Rizk Y., Forthal D.N. Pharmaco-Immunomodulatory Therapy in COVID-19. Drugs. 2020;80:1267–1292. doi: 10.1007/s40265-020-01367-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40265-020-01367-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7372203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32696108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mégarbane B., Scherrmann J. Hydroxychloroquine and Azithromycin to Treat Patients With COVID-19: Both Friends and Foes? J. Clin. Pharmacol. 2020;60:808–814. doi: 10.1002/jcph.1646.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcph.1646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7280673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32434282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray W.A., Murray K.T., Hall K., Arbogast P.G., Stein C.M. Azithromycin and the Risk of Cardiovascular Death. N. Engl. J. Med. 2012;366:1881–1890. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1003833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1003833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3374857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22591294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercuro N.J., Yen C.F., Shim D.J., Maher T.R., McCoy C.M., Zimetbaum P.J., Gold H.S. Risk of QT Interval Prolongation Associated With Use of Hydroxychloroquine With or Without Concomitant Azithromycin Among Hospitalized Patients Testing Positive for Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) JAMA Cardiol. 2020;5:1036–1041. doi: 10.1001/jamacardio.2020.1834.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamacardio.2020.1834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32936252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Million M., Lagier J.-C., Gautret P., Colson P., Fournier P.-E., Amrane S., Hocquart M., Mailhe M., Esteves-Vieira V., Doudier B., et al. Early treatment of COVID-19 patients with hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin: A retrospective analysis of 1061 cases in Marseille, France. Travel Med. Infect. Dis. 2020;35:101738. doi: 10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7199729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32387409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molina J., Delaugerre C., Le Goff J., Mela-Lima B., Ponscarme D., Goldwirt L., de Castro N. No evidence of rapid antiviral clearance or clinical benefit with the combination of hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin in patients with severe COVID-19 infection. Med. Mal. Infect. 2020;50:384. doi: 10.1016/j.medmal.2020.03.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.medmal.2020.03.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32240719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popp M., Stegemann M., Riemer M., Metzendorf M.-I., Romero C.S., Mikolajewska A., Kranke P., Meybohm P., Skoetz N., Weibel S. Antibiotics for the treatment of COVID-19. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 2021;2022 doi: 10.55633/s3me/E028.2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.55633/s3me/E028.2023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8536098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34679203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miranda C., Silva V., Capita R., Alonso-Calleja C., Igrejas G., Poeta P. Implications of antibiotics use during the COVID-19 pandemic: Present and future. J. Antimicrob. Chemother. 2020;75:3413–3416. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkaa350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/dkaa350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7499579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32830266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padda I.S., Mahtani A.U., Parmar M. StatPearls. StatPearls Publishing; Treasure Island, FL, USA: 2024. Sodium-Glucose Transport Protein 2 (SGLT2) Inhibitors.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35015430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMurray J.J.V., Solomon S.D., Inzucchi S.E., Køber L., Kosiborod M.N., Martinez F.A., Ponikowski P., Sabatine M.S., Anand I.S., Bělohlávek J., et al. Dapagliflozin in Patients with Heart Failure and Reduced Ejection Fraction. N. Engl. J. Med. 2019;381:1995–2008. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1911303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1911303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31535829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The EMPA-KIDNEY Collaborative Group. Herrington W.G., Staplin N., Wanner C., Green J.B., Hauske S.J., Emberson J.R., Preiss D., Judge P., Mayne K.J., et al. Empagliflozin in Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease. N. Engl. J. Med. 2023;388:117–127. doi: 10.1056/nejmoa2204233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/nejmoa2204233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7614055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36331190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuberger A., Oraiopoulos N., Drakeman D.L. Renovation as innovation: Is repurposing the future of drug discovery research? Drug Discov. Today. 2019;24:1–3. doi: 10.1016/j.drudis.2018.06.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2018.06.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29936247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palamim C.V.C., Marson F.A.L. COVID-19—The Availability of ICU Beds in Brazil during the Onset of Pandemic. Ann. Glob. Health. 2020;86:100. doi: 10.5334/aogh.3025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5334/aogh.3025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7427679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32864352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero M.N., Palamim C.V.C., Marson F.A.L. The hindrances to perform the COVID-19 vaccination in Brazil. Hum. Vaccines Immunother. 2021;17:3989–4004. doi: 10.1080/21645515.2021.1955607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2021.1955607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8828154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34353218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero M.N., Palamim C.V.C., Marson F.A.L. COVID-19 vaccination on Brazil and the crocodile side-effect. Ethics Med. Public Health. 2021;17:100654. doi: 10.1016/j.jemep.2021.100654.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jemep.2021.100654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7972648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33758776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palamim C.V.C., Boschiero M.N., Faria A.G., Valencise F.E., Marson F.A.L. Opioids in COVID-19: Two Sides of a Coin. Front. Pharmacol. 2022;12:758637. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2021.758637.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2021.758637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8770909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35069193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ralise A.E.G., Camargo T.M., Marson F.A.L. Phase 4 clinical trials in the era of the Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) pandemic and their importance to optimize the COVID-19 vaccination. Hum. Vaccines Immunother. 2023;19:2234784. doi: 10.1080/21645515.2023.2234784.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2023.2234784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10351445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37449956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marson F.A.L. COVID-19-6 million cases worldwide and an overview of the diagnosis in Brazil: A tragedy to be announced. Diagn. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2020;98:115113. doi: 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2020.115113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2020.115113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32682217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho T.A., Boschiero M.N., Marson F.A.L. COVID-19 in Brazil: 150,000 deaths and the Brazilian underreporting. Diagn. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2020;99:115258. doi: 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2020.115258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2020.115258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7576323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33279819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendes M.F., Pereira L.R., Lima T.M., Melani V.F., Palamim C.V.C., Boschiero M.N., Marson F.A.L. COVID-19 pandemic evolution in the Brazilian Indigenous population. J. Racial Ethn. Health Disparities. 2021;9:921–937. doi: 10.1007/s40615-021-01031-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40615-021-01031-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8006870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sansone N.M., Boschiero M.N., Ortega M.M., Ribeiro I.A., Peixoto A.O., Mendes R.T., Marson F.A. Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome by SARS-CoV-2 Infection or Other Etiologic Agents Among Brazilian Indigenous Population: An Observational Study from the First Year of Coronavirus Disease (COVID)-19 Pandemic. Lancet Reg. Health-Am. 2022;8:100177. doi: 10.1016/j.lana.2021.100177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2021.100177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8739500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35018359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saansone N.M., Boschiero M.N., Valencise F.E., Palamim C.V., Marson F.A. Characterization of demographic data, clinical signs, comorbidities, and outcomes according to the race in hospitalized individuals with COVID-19 in Brazil: An observational study. J. Glob. Health. 2022;12:05027. doi: 10.7189/jogh.12.05027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7189/jogh.12.05027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9309002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35871427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sansone N.M.S., Boschiero M.N., Marson F.A.L. Epidemiologic Profile of Severe Acute Respiratory Infection in Brazil During the COVID-19 Pandemic: An Epidemiological Study. Front. Microbiol. 2022;13:911036. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2022.911036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.911036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9288583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35854935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sansone N.M.S., Valencise F.E., Bredariol R.F., Peixoto A.O., Marson F.A.L. Profile of coronavirus disease enlightened asthma as a protective factor against death: An epidemiology study from Brazil during the pandemic. Front. Med. 2022;9:953084. doi: 10.3389/fmed.2022.953084.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.953084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9745079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36523782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sansone N.M.S., Pereira L.R., Boschiero M.N., Valencise F.E., Fraga A.M.A., Marson F.A.L. Characterization of Clinical Features of Hospitalized Patients Due to the SARS-CoV-2 Infection in the Absence of Comorbidities Regarding the Sex: An Epidemiological Study of the First Year of the Pandemic in Brazil. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2022;19:8895. doi: 10.3390/ijerph19158895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19158895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9331852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35897265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero M., Palamim C., Marson F. Learning with the COVID-19 pandemic mistakes: Facing the progression of the first cases of Monkeypox in Brazil. Pulmonology. 2022;29:184–187. doi: 10.1016/j.pulmoe.2022.08.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2022.08.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9458702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36180348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sansone N.M.S., Boschiero M.N., Marson F.A.L. Dengue outbreaks in Brazil and Latin America: The new and continuing challenges. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 2024;147:107192. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2024.107192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2024.107192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39067668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>artins J.P., Marson F.A.L. Forgetting what shouldn’t be forgotten: The new normal after the COVID-19 pandemic in Brazil. Front. Psychol. 2024;15:1362183. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1362183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1362183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11252067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39021656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeJong C., Wachter R.M. The Risks of Prescribing Hydroxychloroquine for Treatment of COVID-19—First, Do No Harm. JAMA Intern. Med. 2020;180:1118–1119. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.1853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.1853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32347894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furlan L., Caramelli B. The regrettable story of the “COVID Kit” and the “Early Treatment of COVID-19” in Brazil. Lancet Reg. Health-Am. 2021;4:100089. doi: 10.1016/j.lana.2021.100089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2021.100089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8484817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34611650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saag M.S. Misguided Use of Hydroxychloroquine for COVID-19. JAMA. 2020;324:2161–2162. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.22389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.22389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33165507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conselho Federal de Farmácia-Brasil.  [(accessed on 12 March 2022)].  Available online:  https://site.cff.org.br.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lalwani P., Salgado B.B., Filho I.V.P., da Silva D.S.S., de Morais T.B.D.N., Jordão M.F., Barbosa A.R.C., Cordeiro I.B., Neto J.N.d.S., de Assunção E.N., et al. SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence and associated factors in Manaus, Brazil: Baseline results from the DETECTCoV-19 cohort study. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 2021;110:141–150. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2021.07.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.07.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8346247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34273518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Correia L.C.L., Sette C., Santos M., Magliano C.A.S., Toscas F.S. Brazil’s COVID-19 guidelines: Political hijack of public health. Lancet. 2022;399:1223–1224. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00338-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00338-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8893727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35248217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Página Inicial.  [(accessed on 29 January 2022)]; Available online:  http://conitec.gov.br/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes E.G., Werneck G.L., Haddad A.E., Maciel E.L.N., Lima N.V.T. Restoring High Vaccine Coverage in Brazil: Successes and Challenges. Rev. Soc. Bras. Med. Trop. 2024;57:e006002024. doi: 10.1590/0037-8682-0614-2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0037-8682-0614-2023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10911277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38359309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins J.P., Alatzatianos G.A., Camargo T.M., Marson F.A.L. Overview of childhood vaccination coverage in Brazil and the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic: Is our children’s health at risk? A review of pre-COVID-19 periods and during the COVID-19 pandemic. Vaccine X. 2024;17:100430. doi: 10.1016/j.jvacx.2024.100430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jvacx.2024.100430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10825611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38299202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>dos Santos K.C.O., Junqueira-Marinho M.d.F., Reis A.T., Camacho K.G., Nehab M.F., Abramov D.M., de Azevedo Z.M.A., de Menezes L.A., Salú M.d.S., Figueiredo C.E.d.S., et al. Social Representations of Hesitant Brazilians about Vaccination against COVID-19. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2023;20:6204. doi: 10.3390/ijerph20136204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20136204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10340750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37444052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verjovsky M., Barreto M.P., Carmo I., Coutinho B., Thomer L., Lifschitz S., Jurberg C. Political quarrel overshadows vaccination advocacy: How the vaccine debate on Brazilian Twitter was framed by anti-vaxxers during Bolsonaro administration. Vaccine. 2023;41:5715–5721. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2023.07.075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2023.07.075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37550146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Barcelos T.D.N., Muniz L.N., Dantas D.M., Junior D.F.C., Cavalcante J.R., Faerstein E. Análise de fake news veiculadas durante a pandemia de COVID-19 no Brasil. Rev. Panam. Salud Publica-Pan Am. J. Public Health. 2021;45 doi: 10.26633/RPSP.2021.65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26633/RPSP.2021.65</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8118089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34007263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galhardi C.P., Freire N.P., Fagundes M.C.M., Minayo M.C.d.S., Cunha I.C.K.O. Fake News and vaccine hesitancy in the COVID-19 pandemic in Brazil. Cienc. Saude Coletiva. 2022;27:1849–1858. doi: 10.1590/1413-81232022275.24092021en.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1413-81232022275.24092021en</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35544814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harb M.d.P., e Silva L.V., Vijaykumar N., da Silva M.S., Frances C.R.L. The COVID-19 infodemic in Brazil: Trends in Google search data. PeerJ. 2022;10:e13747. doi: 10.7717/peerj.13747.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.13747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9357377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35945937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez E.Z., Zucoloto M.L., Aragon D.C. Public interest in “early treatments” for coronavirus disease 2019 in Brazil: Insights from Google Trends. Front. Public Health. 2022;68:308–312. doi: 10.1590/1806-9282.20211292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1806-9282.20211292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35442355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua K.-P., Conti R.M., Becker N.V. US Insurer Spending on Ivermectin Prescriptions for COVID-19. JAMA. 2022;327:584–587. doi: 10.1001/jama.2021.24352.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.24352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8759024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35024763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Painel S.A. Venda de Ivermectina Salta de 1,5 Milhão para 5,5 Milhões em Janeiro.  [(accessed on 18 March 2022)].  Available online:  https://www1.folha.uol.com.br/colunas/painelsa/2022/02/venda-de-ivermectina-salta-de-15-milhao-para-55-milhoes-em-janeiro.shtml.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novack L., Jotkowitz A., Knyazer B., Novack V. Evidence-based medicine: Assessment of knowledge of basic epidemiological and research methods among medical doctors. Postgrad. Med. J. 2006;82:817–822. doi: 10.1136/pgmj.2006.049262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/pgmj.2006.049262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2653930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17148706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temple C., Hoang R., Hendrickson R.G. Toxic Effects from Ivermectin Use Associated with Prevention and Treatment of COVID-19. N. Engl. J. Med. 2021;385:2197–2198. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc2114907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2114907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8552535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34670041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokel-Walker C. Ivermectin buyers clubs. New Sci. 2021;251:8–9. doi: 10.1016/S0262-4079(21)01767-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0262-4079(21)01767-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34658475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Malley P.A. Ivermectin: 21st Century “Snake Oil” or Safe and Effective for COVID-19? Clin. Nurse Spéc. 2021;36:16–19. doi: 10.1097/NUR.0000000000000640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/NUR.0000000000000640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8614192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34843190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryant A.M., Lawrie T.A.M., Dowswell T., Fordham E.J., Mitchell S.M., Hill S.R., Tham T.C.M. Ivermectin for Prevention and Treatment of COVID-19 Infection: A Systematic Review, Meta-analysis, and Trial Sequential Analysis to Inform Clinical Guidelines. Am. J. Ther. 2021;28:e434–e460. doi: 10.1097/MJT.0000000000001402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MJT.0000000000001402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8248252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34145166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manu P. Expression of Concern for Bryant a, Lawrie TA, Dowswell T, Fordham EJ, Mitchell S, Hill SR, Tham TC. Ivermectin for Prevention and Treatment of COVID-19 Infection: A Systematic Review, Meta-Analysis, and Trial Sequential Analysis to Inform Clinical Guidelines. Am J Ther. 2021;28(4): e434-e460. Am. J. Ther. 2022;29:e232. doi: 10.1097/mjt.0000000000001482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/mjt.0000000000001482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8248252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34145166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautret P., Lagier J.C., Parola P., Hoang V.T., Meddeb L., Mailhe M., Doudier B., Courjon J., Giordanengo V., Vieira V.E., et al. Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID-19: Results of an open-label non-randomized clinical trial. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2020;56:105949. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32205204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander P.E., Debono V.B., Mammen M.J., Iorio A., Aryal K., Deng D., Brocard E., Alhazzani W. COVID-19 coronavirus research has overall low methodological quality thus far: Case in point for chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine. J. Clin. Epidemiol. 2020;123:120–126. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2020.04.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2020.04.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32330521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saad M.O. Letter to the editor about “Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID-19: Results of an open-label non-randomized clinical trial”. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2021;57:106171. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.106171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.106171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7781510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33408024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casarões G., Magalhães D. The hydroxychloroquine alliance: How far-right leaders and alt-science preachers came together to promote a miracle drug. Rev. Adm. Publica. 2021;55:197–214. doi: 10.1590/0034-761220200556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0034-761220200556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M., Caputi T.L., Dredze M., Kesselheim A.S., Ayers J.W. Internet Searches for Unproven COVID-19 Therapies in the United States. JAMA Intern. Med. 2020;180:1116–1118. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.1764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.1764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7191468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32347895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultz É., Atlani-Duault L., Peretti-Watel P., Ward J.K. Does the public know when a scientific controversy is over? Public perceptions of hydroxychloroquine in France between April 2020 and June 2021. Therapies. 2022;77:591–602. doi: 10.1016/j.therap.2022.01.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.therap.2022.01.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8801974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35101281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaduganathan M., van Meijgaard J., Mehra M.R., Joseph J., O’donnell C.J., Warraich H.J. Prescription Fill Patterns for Commonly Used Drugs During the COVID-19 Pandemic in the United States. JAMA. 2020;323:2524–2526. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.9184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.9184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7256862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32463459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madanay F.L., McDevitt R.C., Ubel P.A. Hydroxychloroquine for COVID-19: Variation in Regional Political Preferences Predicted New Prescriptions after President Trump’s Endorsement. J. Health Politics Policy Law. 2022;47:429–451. doi: 10.1215/03616878-9716698.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1215/03616878-9716698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35044458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendel A., Bernatsky S., Thorne J.C., Lacaille D., Johnson S.R., Vinet É. Hydroxychloroquine shortages during the COVID-19 pandemic. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 2020;80:e31. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2020-217835.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2020-217835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32434820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakhar D., Kaur I. Potential of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine to treat COVID-19 causes fears of shortages among people with systemic lupus erythematosus. Nat. Med. 2020;26:632. doi: 10.1038/s41591-020-0853-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-0853-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32269358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendel A., Bernatsky S., Askanase A., Bae S.-C., Clarke A.E., Costedoat-Chalumeau N., Gladman D.D., Gordon C., Hanly J., Jacobsen S., et al. Hydroxychloroquine shortages among patients with systemic lupus erythematosus during the COVID-19 pandemic: Experience of the Systemic Lupus International Collaborating Clinics. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 2020;80:1–2. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2020-218164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2020-218164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32586918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma A. Chloroquine paradox may cause more damage than help fight COVID-19. Microbes Infect. 2020;22:154–156. doi: 10.1016/j.micinf.2020.04.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2020.04.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7162740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32305500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falcão M.B., Cavalcanti L.P.d.G., Filho N.M.F., de Brito C.A.A. Case Report: Hepatotoxicity Associated with the Use of Hydroxychloroquine in a Patient with COVID-19. Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg. 2020;102:1214–1216. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.20-0276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.20-0276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7253107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32314698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nogrady B. ‘I hope you die’: How the COVID pandemic unleashed attacks on scientists. Nature. 2021;598:250–253. doi: 10.1038/d41586-021-02741-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/d41586-021-02741-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34645996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ektorp E. Death threats after a trial on chloroquine for COVID-19. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2020;20:661. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30383-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30383-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7255234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32473139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellwanger J.H., Kulmann-Leal B., Kaminski V.L., Valverde-Villegas J.M., DA Veiga A.B.G., Spilki F.R., Fearnside P.M., Caesar L., Giatti L.L., Wallau G.L., et al. Beyond diversity loss and climate change: Impacts of Amazon deforestation on infectious diseases and public health. An. Acad. Bras. Cienc. 2020;92:e20191375. doi: 10.1590/0001-3765202020191375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0001-3765202020191375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32321030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niburski K., Niburski O. Impact of Trump’s Promotion of Unproven COVID-19 Treatments on Social Media and Subsequent Internet Trends: Observational Study. J. Med. Internet Res. 2020;22:e20044. doi: 10.2196/20044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/20044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33151895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelmalek S.M., Mousa A. Azithromycin Misuse During the COVID-19 Pandemic: A Cross-Sectional Study from Jordan. Infect. Drug Resist. 2022;15:747–755. doi: 10.2147/IDR.S351827.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S351827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8900634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35264858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogdanić N., Močibob L., Vidović T., Soldo A., Begovać J. Azithromycin consumption during the COVID-19 pandemic in Croatia, 2020. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0263437. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0263437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0263437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8809604</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35108332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva A.R.O., Salgado D.R., Lopes L.P.N., Castanheira D., Emmerick I.C.M., Lima E.C. Increased Use of Antibiotics in the Intensive Care Unit During Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) Pandemic in a Brazilian Hospital. Front. Pharmacol. 2021;12:778386. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2021.778386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2021.778386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8703131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34955847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King L.M., Lovegrove M.C., Shehab N., Tsay S., Budnitz D.S., Geller A.I., Lind J.N., Roberts R., Hicks L.A., Kabbani S. Trends in US Outpatient Antibiotic Prescriptions During the Coronavirus Disease 2019 Pandemic. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2020;73:e652–e660. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciaa1896.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa1896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7799289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33373435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douglas M., Moy S., Hernandez N. Impact of COVID-19 on Outpatient Antimicrobial Prescribing Patterns in New York City. Infect. Dis. Clin. Pract. 2021;29:E352–E355. doi: 10.1097/IPC.0000000000001071.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/IPC.0000000000001071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8594385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34803343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrara P., Albano L. Azithromycin Has Been Flying Off the Shelves: The Italian Lesson Learnt from Improper Use of Antibiotics against COVID-19. Medicina. 2022;58:363. doi: 10.3390/medicina58030363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/medicina58030363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8955327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35334539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagliotti C., Buttazzi R., Ricchizzi E., Di Mario S., Tedeschi S., Moro M.L. Community use of antibiotics during the COVID-19 lockdown. Infect. Dis. 2020;53:142–144. doi: 10.1080/23744235.2020.1834139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/23744235.2020.1834139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33073645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D., Quinn J., Pinsky B., Shah N.H., Brown I. Rates of Co-infection Between SARS-CoV-2 and Other Respiratory Pathogens. JAMA J. Am. Med. Assoc. 2020;323:2085–2086. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.6266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.6266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7160748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32293646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calcagno A., Ghisetti V., Burdino E., Trunfio M., Allice T., Boglione L., Bonora S., Di Perri G. Co-infection with other respiratory pathogens in COVID-19 patients. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2020;27:297–298. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2020.08.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.08.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7434691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32822882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero M.N., Duarte A., Palamim C.V.C., Alvarez A.E., Mauch R.M., Marson F.A.L. Frequency of respiratory pathogens other than SARS-CoV-2 detected during COVID-19 testing. Diagn. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2021;102:115576. doi: 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2021.115576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2021.115576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8531239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34800846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langford B.J., So M., Raybardhan S., Leung V., Westwood D., MacFadden D.R., Soucy J.-P.R., Daneman N. Bacterial co-infection and secondary infection in patients with COVID-19: A living rapid review and meta-analysis. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2020;26:1622–1629. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2020.07.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.07.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32711058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doan T., Worden L., Hinterwirth A., Arzika A.M., Maliki R., Abdou A., Zhong L., Chen C., Cook C., Lebas E., et al. Macrolide and Nonmacrolide Resistance with Mass Azithromycin Distribution. N. Engl. J. Med. 2020;383:1941–1950. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2002606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2002606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7492079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33176084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pickering H., Hart J.D., Burr S., Stabler R., Maleta K., Kalua K., Bailey R.L., Holland M.J. Impact of azithromycin mass drug administration on the antibiotic-resistant gut microbiome in children: A randomized, controlled trial. Gut Pathog. 2022;14:1–11. doi: 10.1186/s13099-021-00478-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13099-021-00478-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8740015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34991704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez-Jacome L.E., Fernandez-Rodriguez D., Franco-Cendejas R., Camacho-Ortiz A., Morfin-Otero M.d.R., Rodriguez-Noriega E., Ponce-De-Leon A., Ortiz-Brizuela E., Rojas-Larios F., Velazquez-Acosta M.d.C., et al. Increment Antimicrobial Resistance During the COVID-19 Pandemic: Results from the Invifar Network. Microb. Drug Resist. 2022;28:338–345. doi: 10.1089/mdr.2021.0231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/mdr.2021.0231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34870473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azithromycin: MedlinePlus Drug Information.  [(accessed on 2 April 2022)]; Available online:  https://medlineplus.gov/druginfo/meds/a697037.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero M.N., Carvalho T.A., Marson F.A.d.L. Retraction in the era of COVID-19 and its influence on evidence-based medicine: Is science in jeopardy? Pulmonology. 2020;27:97–106. doi: 10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.10.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.10.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7687579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33281107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valencise F.E., Palamim C.V.C., Marson F.A.L. Retraction of Clinical Trials about the SARS-CoV-2 Infection: An Unaddressed Problem and Its Possible Impact on Coronavirus Disease (COVID)-19 Treatment. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2023;20:1835. doi: 10.3390/ijerph20031835.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20031835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9914919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36767202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NIHR Global Health Research Unit on Global Surgery. STARSurg Collaborative A Prognostic Model for Use before Elective Surgery to Estimate the Risk of Postoperative Pulmonary Complications (GSU-Pulmonary Score): A Development and Validation Study in Three International Cohorts. Lancet Digit Health. 2024;6:e507–e519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38906616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glasbey J.C., Abbott T.E., Ademuyiwa A., Adisa A., Alshryda S., Arnaud A.P., Chaudhry D., Costas-Chavarri A., Cunha M.F., Davies J.I., et al. Elective surgery system strengthening: Development, measurement, and validation of the surgical preparedness index across 1632 hospitals in 119 countries. Lancet. 2022;400:1607–1617. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(22)01846-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(22)01846-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9621702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36328042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVIDSurg Collaborative. GlobalSurg Collaborative SARS-CoV-2 infection and venous thromboembolism after surgery: An international prospective cohort study. Anaesthesia. 2021;77:28–39. doi: 10.1111/anae.15563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/anae.15563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8652887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34428858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVIDSurg Collaborative. GlobalSurg Collaborative Effects of pre-operative isolation on postoperative pulmonary complications after elective surgery: An international prospective cohort study. Anaesthesia. 2021;76:1454–1464. doi: 10.1111/anae.15560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/anae.15560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34371522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVIDSurg Collaborative. GlobalSurg Collaborative Timing of surgery following SARS-CoV-2 infection: An international prospective cohort study. Anaesthesia. 2021;76:748–758. doi: 10.1111/anae.15458.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/anae.15458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8206995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33690889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>