<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464934</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2249-4863</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of family medicine and primary care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Family Med Prim Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A clinical study of rhino-orbital-cerebral mucormycosis during the COVID-19 pandemic in western Maharashtra.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3730</StartPage><EndPage>3734</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3730-3734</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_2_24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The aim of the study was to describe the epidemiology and study the risk factors, clinical presentation, management, and outcome of rhino-orbital-cerebral mucormycosis (ROCM) in terms of mortality, exenteration, eye salvage, and vision salvage.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This retrospective, observational study was carried out over a period of two months. A detailed history was noted, and an ophthalmological examination was done. The diagnosis was done by Potassium hydroxide (KOH) mount and fungal culture. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the orbit, brain, and paranasal sinuses were performed. Medical (intravenous amphotericin B, posaconazole), surgical (retrobulbar amphotericin B injection, exenteration, Functional Endoscopic Sinus Surgery (FESS)), or combined management was evaluated, and clinical outcomes was noted.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The mean age of patients was 54.2 years and the male-to-female ratio was 1.77/1. The most common underlying risk factor for ROCM was uncontrolled diabetes mellitus (70%), followed by the use of corticosteroids for the management of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infection in 68% of patients. The most common clinical presentation was diminution of vision followed by eschar, ptosis, and proptosis. Medical and FESS were done in all patients; exenteration was done in 12% of patients. Sixty-six percent of patients were alive with regression of ROCM, 20% of patients were alive with residual, 8% of patients were alive with the progression of ROCM, and 6% of patients had expired. Among the ones who are alive, the ocular outcome was orbital exenteration in 12.76%, the eye was salvaged in 25.53 and vision salvage was achieved in 61.70%.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">ROCM affects older males. Immunosuppression due to COVID-19 infection, diabetes mellitus, and corticosteroid use in the management of COVID-19 are the main risk factors for the development of ROCM. Antifungal therapy along with surgical debridement decreases mortality.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manade</LastName><ForeName>Varsha Vivek</ForeName><Initials>VV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, Dr. D.Y. Patil Medical College and Hospital, Pimpri, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kotecha</LastName><ForeName>Megha R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, Dr. D.Y. Patil Medical College and Hospital, Pimpri, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Family Med Prim Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101610082</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2249-4863</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Amphotericin B</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">exenteration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">posaconazole</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rhino-orbital-cerebral mucormycosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vision salvage</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_2_24</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JFMPC-13-3730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Farnoosh G, Alishiri GH, Hosseini Zijoud SR, Dorostkar R, Farahani AJ. Understanding the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV2) and coronavirus disease (COVID 19) based on available evidence—A narrative review. J Mil Med. 2020;22:1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouchara JP, Oumeziane NA, Lissitzky JC, Larcher G, Tronchin G, Chabasse D. Attachment of spores of the human pathogenic fungus Rhizopus oryzae to extracellular matrix components. Eur J Cell Biol. 1996;70:76–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8738422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skiada A, Pavleas I, Drogari-Apiranthitou M. Epidemiology and diagnosis of mucormycosis: An update. J Fungi. 2020;6:265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7711598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33147877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chander J, Kaur M, Singla N, Punia RPS, Singhal SK, Attri AK, et al. Mucormycosis: Battle with the deadly enemy over a five-year period in India. J Fungi (Basel) 2018;4:46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6023269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29642408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash H, Chakrabarti A. Global epidemiology of mucormycosis. J Fungi (Basel) 2019;5:26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6462913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30901907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AK, Singh R, Joshi SR, Misra A. Mucormycosis in COVID 19: A systematic review of cases reported worldwide and in India. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2021;15:102146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8137376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34192610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sen M, Lahane S, Lahane TP, Parekh R, Honavar SG. Mucor in a viral land: A tale of two pathogens. Indian J Ophthalmol. 2021;69:244–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7933891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33463566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen N, Zhou M, Dong X. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: A descriptive study. Lancet. 2020;395:507–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7135076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32007143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White PL, Dhillon R, Cordey A, Hughes H, Faggian F, Soni S, et al. A national strategy to diagnose COVID 19 associated invasive fungal disease in the ICU. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;73:e1634–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7499527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32860682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yohai R, Bullock J, Aziz A, Markert R. Survival factors in rhino-orbital-cerebral mucormycosis. Surv Ophthalmol. 1994;39:3–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7974189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferry A, Abedi S. Diagnosis and management of rhino orbito-cerebral mucormycosis (phycomycosis)-A report of 16 personally observed cases. Ophthalmology. 1983;90:1096–104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6646648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lionakis MS, Kontoyiannis DP. Glucocorticoids and invasive fungal infections. Lancet. 2003;362:1828–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14654323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoenigl M, Seidel D, Carvalho A, Rudramurthy SM, Arastehfar A, Gangneux JP, et al. The emergence of COVID 19 associated mucormycosis: Analysis of cases from 18 countries. Lancet Microbe. 2022;3:e543–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8789240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35098179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furco A, Mouchet B, Carbonnelle M, Vallerand H. Pulmonary mucormycosis: Benefit of aerosol amphotericin B. Rev Mal Respir. 2001;18:309–313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11468594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manesh A, John AO, Mathew B, Varghese L, Rupa V, Zachariah A, et al. Posaconazole: An emerging therapeutic option for invasive rhino-orbito-cerebral mucormycosis. Mycoses. 2016;59:765–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27443253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cornely OA, Alastruey-Izquierdo A, Arenz D, Chen SC, Dannaoui E, Hochhegger B, et al. Global guideline for the diagnosis and management of mucormycosis: An initiative of the European Confederation of Medical Mycology in cooperation with the Mycoses Study Group Education and Research Consortium. Lancet Infect Dis. 2019;19:e405–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8559573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31699664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sipsas NV, Gamaletsou MN, Anastasopoulou A, Kontoyiannis DP. Therapy of mucormycosis. J Fungi. 2018;4:90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6162664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30065232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee AS, Lee PW, Allworth A, Smith T, Sullivan TJ. Orbital mycoses in an adult subtropical population. Eye. 2020 341640-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7608426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31822858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirabayashi KE, Kalin-Hajdu E, Brodie FL, Kersten RC, Russell MS, Vagefi MR. Retrobulbar injection of amphotericin B for orbital mucormycosis. Ophthalmic Plast Reconstr Surg. 2017;33:e94–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27768642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safi M, Ang MJ, Patel P, Silkiss RZ. Rhino-orbital-cerebral mucormycosis (ROCM) and associated cerebritis treated with adjuvant retrobulbar amphotericin B. Am J Ophthalmol Case Rep. 2020;19:100771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7287239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32551404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash H, Chakrabarti A. Epidemiology of mucormycosis in India. Microorganisms. 2021;9:523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8000977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33806386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>