<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39468457</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2334</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Severe co-infection caused by difficult-to-diagnose hypermucoviscous Klebsiella pneumoniae K1-ST82 in a patient with COVID-19: a case report.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1215</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1215</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12879-024-10092-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Co-infection with Klebsiella pneumoniae presents a significant concern in hospitalized patients with coronavirus disease (COVID-19), increasing the risk of severe disease progression. Hypervirulent (hv) and hypermucoviscous (hm) K. pneumoniae (Kp) has gained prominence in Asia due to its capacity to cause invasive community-acquired infections. However, recognition of hvKp/hmKp co-infections in the context of COVID-19 remains limited. We report a severe case of rapidly progressing co-infection with hmKp exhibiting "difficult-to-diagnose" phenotypes in a hospitalized patient with COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CASE PRESENTATION" NlmCategory="METHODS">A 61-year-old woman with COVID-19 initially exhibited mild symptoms resembling the common cold. However, her condition rapidly deteriorated over 7 days, leading to hospital admission with the development of dyspnea. The patient required supplemental oxygen, antibiotic treatment, and mechanical ventilation. Gram-negative bacteria with atypical phenotypes were isolated from alveolar lavage fluid and blood cultures. Both strains formed small, glossy, non-lactose-fermenting colonies on clinically relevant media and were susceptible to ampicillin. Conventional biochemical tests failed to identify the Enterobacteriales strains owing to the urease-negative phenotype. Consequently, the identification of K. pneumoniae was difficult until matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) analysis was performed. A positive string test indicated mucoviscosity, but with variability in the material used for stretching colonies. Whole-genome sequencing performed on the MiSeq and GridION platforms revealed the blood-derived strain JARB-RN-0063 as belonging to serotype K1 and sequence type (ST) 82. The hvKp-associated genes rmpA and iroCD were located on a 5.0-Mb chromosome, and iucABCD-iutA was identified on a 217.9-kb IncFIB(K)/IncR-type plasmid. Therefore, JARB-RN-0063 was genetically classified as hvKp with a Kleborate virulence score of 3. The intrinsic penicillinase gene bla<sub>SHV</sub> was defective owing to an IS1F element insertion, resulting in the strain being atypically susceptible to ampicillin.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This is the first case of severe COVID-19-associated co-infection with a difficult-to-diagnose K. penummoniae strain. Notably, co-infection by the hmKp K1-ST82 clone exhibited atypical phenotypes, including stunted growth, non-lactose fermentation, urease-negative reaction, ampicillin susceptibility, and abnormal mucoviscosity, posing diagnostic challenges for clinical laboratories and impedes the identification of hvKp/hmKp. Delayed identification may worsen patient outcomes, highlighting the need for increased clinical awareness of such difficult-to-diagnose clones to prevent deterioration.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Itoga</LastName><ForeName>Masamichi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hirosaki University Graduate School of Medicine, 5 Zaihu-cho, Hirosaki, Aomori, Japan. gacchi86@hirosaki-u.ac.jp.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Hayashi</LastName><ForeName>Wataru</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antimicrobial Resistance Research Center, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kayama</LastName><ForeName>Shizuo</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antimicrobial Resistance Research Center, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Liansheng</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antimicrobial Resistance Research Center, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sugawara</LastName><ForeName>Yo</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antimicrobial Resistance Research Center, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kimura</LastName><ForeName>Masahiko</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hirosaki University Hospital, Aomori, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hanada</LastName><ForeName>Hiroyuki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hirosaki University Graduate School of Medicine, 5 Zaihu-cho, Hirosaki, Aomori, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tasaka</LastName><ForeName>Sadatomo</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hirosaki University Graduate School of Medicine, 5 Zaihu-cho, Hirosaki, Aomori, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sugai</LastName><ForeName>Motoyuki</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antimicrobial Resistance Research Center, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>JP23K14723</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>JP23fk0108604</GrantID><Agency>Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>JP22fk0108132</GrantID><Agency>Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968551</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2334</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007711" MajorTopicYN="Y">Klebsiella pneumoniae</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060085" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coinfection</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007710" MajorTopicYN="Y">Klebsiella Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Co-infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hypermucoviscous Klebsiella pneumoniae</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ST82</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">String test</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Whole-genome sequencing</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39468457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-024-10092-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12879-024-10092-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zhu X, Ge Y, Wu T, Zhao K, Chen Y, Wu B, Zhu F, Zhu B, Cui L. Co-infection with respiratory pathogens among COVID-2019 cases. Virus Res. 2020;285:198005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2020.198005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32408156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choby JE, Howard-Anderson J, Weiss DS. Hypervirulent Klebsiella pneumoniae - clinical and molecular perspectives. J Intern Med. 2020;287:283–300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joim.13007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31677303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namikawa H, Yamada K, Sakiyama A, Imoto W, Yamairi K, Shibata W, Yoshii N, Niki M, Nakaie K, Oinuma KI, Tsubouchi T, Niki M, Tochino Y, Takemoto Y, Kaneko Y, Shuto T, Kakeya H. Clinical characteristics of bacteremia caused by hypermucoviscous Klebsiella pneumoniae at a tertiary hospital. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2019;95:84–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2019.04.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31256940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo TA, Olson R, Fang CT, Stoesser N, Miller M, MacDonald U, Hutson A, Barker JH, La Hoz RM, Johnson JR. Identification of biomarkers for differentiation of hypervirulent Klebsiella pneumoniae from classical K. pneumoniae. J Clin Microbiol. 2018;56:e00776–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00776-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29925642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6113484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>bioMérieux. APIWEB<sup>™</sup> identification database. https://apiweb.biomerieux.com/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harada S, Aoki K, Yamamoto S, Ishii Y, Sekiya N, Kurai H, Furukawa K, Doi A, Tochitani K, Kubo K, Yamaguchi Y, Narita M, Kamiyama S, Suzuki J, Fukuchi T, Gu Y, Okinaka K, Shiiki S, Hayakawa K, Tachikawa N, Kasahara K, Nakamura T, Yokota K, Komatsu M, Takamiya M, Tateda K, Doi Y. Clinical and molecular characteristics of Klebsiella pneumoniae isolates causing bloodstream infections in Japan: occurrence of hypervirulent infections in health care. J Clin Microbiol. 2019;57:e01206–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.01206-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31434721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6812994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le MN, Kayama S, Wyres KL, Yu L, Hisatsune J, Suzuki M, Yahara K, Terachi T, Sawa K, Takahashi S, Okuhara T, Kohama K, Holt KE, Mizutani T, Ohge H, Sugai M. Genomic epidemiology and temperature dependency of hypermucoviscous Klebsiella pneumoniae in Japan. Microb Genom. 2022;8(5):mgen000827.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35622495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9465067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam MMC, Wick RR, Watts SC, Cerdeira LT, Wyres KL, Holt KE. A genomic surveillance framework and genotyping tool for Klebsiella pneumoniae and its related species complex. Nat Commun. 2021;12(1):4188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24448-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34234121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8263825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matono T, Morita M, Nakao N, Teshima Y, Ohnishi M. Genomic insights into virulence factors affecting tissue-invasive Klebsiella pneumoniae infection. Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob. 2022;21:2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12941-022-00494-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35123505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8817621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brisse S, Fevre C, Passet V, Issenhuth-Jeanjean S, Tournebize R, Diancourt L, Grimont P. Virulent clones of Klebsiella pneumoniae: identification and evolutionary scenario based on genomic and phenotypic characterization. PLoS ONE. 2009;4:e4982.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19319196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2656620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Yu T, Du R, Fan G, Liu Y, Liu Z, Xiang J, Wang Y, Song B, Gu X, Guan L, Wei Y, Li H, Wu X, Xu J, Tu S, Zhang Y, Chen H, Cao B. Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020;395:1054–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30566-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7270627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pourajam S, Kalantari E, Talebzadeh H, Mellali H, Sami R, Soltaninejad F, Amra B, Sajadi M, Alenaseri M, Kalantari F, Solgi H. Secondary bacterial infection and clinical characteristics in patients with COVID-19 admitted to two intensive care units of an academic hospital in Iran during the first wave of the pandemic. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2022;12:784130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2022.784130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35281440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8904895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosoda T, Harada S, Okamoto K, Ishino S, Kaneko M, Suzuki M, Ito R, Mizoguchi M. COVID-19 and fatal sepsis caused by hypervirulent Klebsiella pneumoniae, Japan, 2020. Emerg Infect Dis. 2021;27:556–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid2702.204662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33320080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7853555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falcone M, Tiseo G, Arcari G, Leonildi A, Giordano C, Tempini S, Bibbolino G, Mozzo R, Barnini S, Carattoli A, Menichetti F. Spread of hypervirulent multidrug-resistant ST147 Klebsiella pneumoniae in patients with severe COVID-19: an observational study from Italy, 2020-21. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2022;77:1140–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/dkab495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35040981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamau E, Ranson EL, Tsan AT, Bergmann-Leitner ES, Garner OB, Yang S. Clinical and genomic characterization of hypervirulent Klebsiella pneumoniae (hvKp) infections via passive surveillance in Southern California, 2020–2022. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:1001169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.1001169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36312975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9614223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morales-León F, Matus-Köhler M, Araya-Vega P, Aguilera F, Torres I, Vera R, Ibarra C, Venegas S, Bello-Toledo H, González-Rocha G, Opazo-Capurro A. Molecular characterization of the convergent carbapenem-resistant and hypervirulent Klebsiella pneumoniae strain K1-ST23, collected in Chile during the COVID-19 pandemic. Microbiol Spectr. 2023;11:e0054023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.00540-23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37191539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirabayashi A, Kajihara T, Yahara K, Shibayama K, Sugai M. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the surveillance of antimicrobial resistance. J Hosp Infect. 2021;117:147–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2021.09.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34562548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8457641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagawara K, Kamata H, Chubachi S, Namkoong H, Tanaka H, Lee H, Otake S, Fukushima T, Kusumoto T, Morita A, Azekawa S, Watase M, Asakura T, Masaki K, Ishii M, Endo A, Koike R, Ishikura H, Takata T, Matsushita Y, Harada N, Kokutou H, Yoshiyama T, Kataoka K, Mutoh Y, Miyawaki M, Ueda S, Ono H, Ono T, Shoko T, Muranaka H, Kawamura K, Mori N, Mochimaru T, Fukui M, Chihara Y, Nagasaki Y, Okamoto M, Amishima M, Odani T, Tani M, Nishi K, Shirai Y, Edahiro R, Ando A, Hashimoto N, Ogura S, Kitagawa Y, Kita T, Kagaya T, Kimura Y, Miyazawa N, Tsuchida T, Fujitani S, Murakami K, Sano H, Sato Y, Tanino Y, Otsuki R, Mashimo S, Kuramochi M, Hosoda Y, Hasegawa Y, Ueda T, Takaku Y, Ishiguro T, Fujiwara A, Kuwahara N, Kitamura H, Hagiwara E, Nakamori Y, Saito F, Kono Y, Abe S, Ishii T, Ohba T, Kusaka Y, Watanabe H, Masuda M, Watanabe H, Kimizuka Y, Kawana A, Kasamatsu Y, Hashimoto S, Okada Y, Takano T, Katayama K, Ai M, Kumanogoh A, Sato T, Tokunaga K, Imoto S, Kitagawa Y, Kimura A, Miyano S, Hasegawa N, Ogawa S, Kanai T, Fukunaga K, Japan COVID-19 Task Force. Impact of respiratory bacterial infections on mortality in Japanese patients with COVID-19: a retrospective cohort study. BMC Pulm Med. 2023;23:146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12890-023-02418-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37101265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10131342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>