<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464911</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2249-4863</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of family medicine and primary care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Family Med Prim Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Healthcare workers' perceptions and acceptance for COVID-19 vaccine for their children aged &lt;18 years from the Region of Eastern Uttar Pradesh, India.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3709</StartPage><EndPage>3718</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3709-3718</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_1727_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccination program among adults in India is one of the highly successful vaccination drives globally, but the acceptance of the COVID-19 vaccine among parents for their children is largely unknown. As parents are primary decision-makers for their children, we aimed to assess parents' perceptions and acceptance for COVID-19 vaccination for children in India.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To assess parental perceptions and acceptance for COVID-19 vaccination for their children (aged &lt;18 years).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A cross-sectional anonymous web-based survey was designed and conducted from November 1 to December 15, 2022. All the healthcare workers of a tertiary care institute in eastern Uttar Pradesh, having a child aged &lt;18 years, constituted the study population and were invited. They were recruited through snowball sampling and were sent the study questionnaire in Google form through email and WhatsApp. Bivariate analysis was performed to determine the predictors of child vaccination acceptance among the parents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 388 healthcare worker parents (HCWPs) having a child &lt;18 years of age completed the survey. The mean age of the parents was 40.28 ± 11.34 years. The majority (96.9%) of them had already received the recommended two doses of the COVID-19 vaccine. Around 91% of the parents agreed that COVID-19 vaccines are important for children's health, whereas 89% agreed that COVID-19 vaccines are effective. A total of 356 (91.7%) parents were willing to vaccinate their children with a COVID-19 vaccine, of which 91.3% intended to do so as soon as possible. The factors significantly associated with the stated willingness for child vaccination among the participants were younger age (<i>P</i> = 0.008), female gender (<i>P</i> = 0000), currently married status (<i>P</i> = 0.00001), urban residence (<i>P</i> = 0.01), lower monthly income (<i>P</i> = 0.03), absence of any chronic illness (<i>P</i> = 0.0003), history of COVID-19 in the child (<i>P</i> = 0.004), and the child being up-to-date with the routine childhood vaccines (<i>P</i> = 0.01).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The HCWPs from eastern Uttar Pradesh, India, have a positive attitude and low vaccine hesitancy toward COVID-19 vaccination for children, with around 92% currently willing to vaccinate their children with COVID vaccine. Further longitudinal studies are required to assess the trend of parental acceptance of COVID vaccine.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Imran Ahmed</ForeName><Initials>IA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, BRD Medical College, Gorakhpur, Uttar Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Bashar</LastName><ForeName>Md Abu</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine and Family Medicine, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Gorakhpur, Uttar Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Amresh Kumar</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, BRD Medical College, Gorakhpur, Uttar Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Family Med Prim Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101610082</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2249-4863</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare workers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">parents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">perception</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">willingness</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_1727_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JFMPC-13-3709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19)  [[Last accessed on 2024 Feb 12]].  Available from: https://www.who.int/health-topics/coronavirus#tab=tab_1 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard.  [[Last accessed on 2024 Feb 12]].  Available from: https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases?n=c .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delahoy MJ, Ujamaa D, Whitaker M, O'Halloran A, Anglin O, Burns E, et al. Hospitalizations associated with COVID-19 among children and adolescents—COVID-NET, 14 states, March 1, 2020–August 14, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:1255–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8437052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34499627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interim statement on COVID-19 vaccination for children and adolescents.  [[Last accessed on 2022 Dec 23]].  Available from: https://www.who.int/news/item/24-11-2021-interim-statement-on-covid-19-vaccination-for-children-and-adolescents .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID-19 Vaccination for Children.  [[Last accessed on 2022 Dec 23]].  Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/covid-19/planning/children.html .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ioannidis JPA. COVID-19 vaccination in children and university students. Eur J Clin Invest. 2021;51:e13678.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34529274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olson SM, Newhams MM, Halasa NB, Price AM, Boom JA, Sahni LC, et al. Effectiveness of BNT162b2 vaccine against critical Covid-19 in adolescents. N. Engl J Med. 2022;386:713–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8781318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35021004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue F, Shen K. COVID-19 in children and the importance of COVID-19 vaccination. World J. Pediatr. 2021;17:462–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8476974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34581958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zambrano LD, Newhams MM, Olson SM, Halasa NB, Price AM, Boom JA. Effectiveness of BNT162b2 (Pfizer-BioNTech) mRNA Vaccination Against Multisystem Inflammatory Syndrome in Children Among Persons Aged 12-18 Years-United States, July-December 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:52–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8757620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35025852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klass P, Ratner AJ. Vaccinating children against covid-19 - the lessons of measles. N Engl J Med. 2021;384:589–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33471977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lurie N, Saville M, Hatchett R, Halton J. Developing Covid-19 vaccines at pandemic speed. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:1969–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32227757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>3 Vaccines. Get Emergency Approval For Children.  [[Last accessed on 2022 Dec 23]].  Available from: https://www.india.com/news/india/vaccine-for-kids-3-vaccines-get-emergency-approval-for-children-zycov-d-corbevax-covaxin-dcgi-green-signal-read-details-5358986/ </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Times of India. Beneficiaries in 15-18 yrs age group to start getting 2nd dose.  [[Last accessed on 2022 Dec 23]].  Available from: https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/beneficiaries-in-15-18-yrs-age-group-to-start-getting-2nd-dose-of-covid-vaccine-from-monday/articleshow/89229669.cms .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacDonald NE. SAGE Working Group on Vaccine Hesitancy Vaccine Hesitancy: Definition, Scope and Determinants. Vaccine. 2015;33:4161–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25896383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ten Health Issues WHO Will Tackle This Year.  [[Last accessed on 2023 Dec 03]].  Available from: https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/beneficiaries-in-15-18-yrs-age-group-to-start-getting-2nd-dose-of-covid-vaccine-from-monday/articleshow/89229669.cms .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domek GJ, O’Leary ST, Bull S, Bronsert M, Contreras-Roldan IL, Bolaños Ventura GA, et al. Measuring Vaccine Hesitancy: Field Testing the WHO SAGE Working Group on Vaccine Hesitancy Survey Tool in Guatemala. Vaccine. 2018;35:5273–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6145454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30061026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubé E, Gagnon D, Nickels E, Jeram S, Schuster M. Mapping vaccine hesitancy—country-specific characteristics of a global phenomenon. Vaccine. 2014;32:6649–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5355208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25280436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang KC, Fang Y, Cao H, Chen H, Hu T, Chen YQ, et al. Parental acceptability of covid-19 vaccination for children under the age of 18 years: Cross-sectional online survey. JMIR Pediatr Parent. 2020;3:e24827.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7775376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33326406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szilagyi PG, Shah MD, Delgado JR, Thomas K, Vizueta N, Cui Y, et al. Parents' intentions and perceptions about covid-19 vaccination for their children: Results from a national survey. Pediatrics. 2021;148:e2021052335.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10116994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34344800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humble RM, Sell H, Dubé E, MacDonald NE, Robinson J, Driedger SM, et al. Canadian parents' perceptions of COVID-19 vaccination and intention to vaccinate their children: Results from a cross-sectional national survey. Vaccine. 2021;39:7669–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34688500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammershaimb EA, Cole LD, Liang Y, Hendrich MA, Das D, Petrin R, et al. COVID-19 vaccine acceptance among us parents: A nationally representative survey. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc. 2022;11:361–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9278238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35748047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee M, Seo S, Choi S, Park JH, Kim S, Choe YJ, et al. Parental Acceptance of covid-19 vaccination for children and its association with information sufficiency and credibility in South Korea. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5:e2246624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9856328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36515950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou Z, Song K, Wang Q, Zang S, Tu S, Chantler T. Childhood COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and preference from caregivers and healthcare workers in China: A survey experiment. Prev Med. 2022;161:107138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9259187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35809825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlKetbi LMB, Al Hosani F, Al Memari S, Al Mazrouei S, Al Shehhi B, AlShamsi N, et al. Parents' views on the acceptability of a COVID-19 vaccine for their children: A cross-sectional study in Abu Dhabi-United Arab Emirates. Vaccine. 2022;40:5562–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9376339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35987873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li JB, Lau EYH, Chan DKC. Why do Hong Kong parents have low intention to vaccinate their children against COVID-19? testing health belief model and theory of planned behavior in a large-scale survey. Vaccine. 2022;40:2772–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8934736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35339306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bianco A, Della Polla G, Angelillo S, Pelullo CP, Licata F, Angelillo IF. Parental COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy: A cross-sectional survey in Italy. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2022;21:541–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34949136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yılmaz M, Sahin MK. Parents' willingness and attitudes concerning the COVID-19 vaccine: A cross-sectional study. Int J Clin Pract. 2021;75:e14364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8236907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33998108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed AH, Hassan BAR, Wayyes AM, Gadhban AQ, Blebil A, Alhija SA, et al. Parental health beliefs, intention, and strategies about COVID-19 vaccine for their children: A cross-sectional analysis from five Arab countries in the Middle East. Vaccine. 2022;40:6549–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9500095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36207222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan YH, Rasheed M, Mallhi TH, Salman M, Alzarea AI, Alanazi AS, et al. Barriers and facilitators of childhood COVID-19 vaccination among parents: A systematic review. Front Pediatr. 2022;10:950406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9731120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36507133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen X, Dong H, Feng J, Jiang H, Dowling R, Lu Z. Assessing the COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in the Chinese adults using a generalized vaccine hesitancy survey instrument. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2021;17:4005–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8828104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35016491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lahariya C. A brief history of vaccines and vaccination in India. Indian J Med Res. 2014;139:491–511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4078488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24927336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boston, 677 Huntington Avenue; Ma 02115 +1495-1000 Barry, R. Bloom's Faculty Website.  [[Last accessed on 2024 Feb 14]].  Available from: https://www.hsph. harvard.edu/barry-bloom/ </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orenstein WA, Ahmed R. Simply put: Vaccination saves lives. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2017;114:4031–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5402432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28396427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trogen B, Pirofski LA. Understanding vaccine hesitancy in COVID-19. Med (N Y) 2021;2:498–501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8030992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33851144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Razai MS, Chaudhry UAR, Doerholt K, Bauld L, Majeed A. Covid-19 vaccination hesitancy. BMJ. 2021;373:n1138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34016653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar D, Mathur M, Kumar N, Rana RK, Tiwary RC, et al. Understanding the phases of vaccine hesitancy during the COVID-19 pandemic. Isr J Health Policy Res. 2022;11:16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8939479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35317859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toth-Manikowski SM, Swirsky ES, Gandhi R, Piscitello G. COVID-19 vaccination hesitancy among health care workers, communication, and policy-making. Am J Infect Control. 2022;50:20–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8511871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34653527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandani S, Jani D, Sahu PK, Kataria U, Suryawanshi S, Khubchandani J, et al. COVID-19 vaccination hesitancy in India: State of the nation and priorities for research. Brain Behav Immun Health. 2021;18:100375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8523306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34693366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padhi BK, Satapathy P, Rajagopal V, Rustagi N, Vij J, Jain L, et al. Parents' perceptions and intention to vaccinate their children against covid-19: Results from a cross-sectional national survey in India. Front Med. 2022;9:806702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9159272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35665354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohan R, Pandey V, Kumar A, Gangadevi P, Goel AD, Joseph J, et al. Acceptance and attitude of parents regarding covid-19 vaccine for children: A cross-sectional study. Cureus. 2022;14:e24518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9138809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35651474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarkar P, Chandrasekaran V, Gunasekaran D, Chinnakali P. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy among health care worker-parents (HCWP) in Puducherry, India and its implications on their children: A cross sectional descriptive study. Vaccine. 2022;40:5821–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9420929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36064669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Himanshi, Kadam KS, Uttarwar PU. Covid-19 vaccine hesitancy for children in parents: A cross-sectional survey among health-care professionals in India. Asian J Pharm Clin Res. 2022;15:41–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus J, Wyka K, White T, Picchio C, Gostin L, Larson H, et al. A survey of COVID-19 vaccine acceptance across 23 countries in 2022. Nat Med. 2023;29:366–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36624316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X, Wang S, Zhang K, Chen S, Chan PS, Fang Y, et al. Changes in parents' covid-19 vaccine hesitancy for children aged 3-17 years before and after the rollout of the national childhood covid-19 vaccination program in china: Repeated cross-sectional surveys. Vaccines (Basel) 2022;10:1478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9502861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36146556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shati AA, Al-Qahtani SM, Alsabaani AA, Mahmood SE, Alqahtani YA, AlQahtani KM, et al. Perceptions of Parents towards COVID-19 Vaccination in Children, Aseer Region, Southwestern Saudi Arabia. Vaccines. 2022;10:1222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9414894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36016110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yigit M, Ozkaya-Parlakay A, Senel E. Evaluation of covid-19 vaccine refusal in parents. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2021;40:e134–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33410650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karol S, Thakare MM. Strengthening Immunization Services in India through Digital Transformation from Co-WIN to U-WIN: A review. Prev Med Res Rev. 2024;1:25–8.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>