<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469488</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2504-3145</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Portuguese journal of public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Port J Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 Pandemic and Hospitalizations due to Abortion among 10- to 14-Year-Old Girls in Brazil.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>23</StartPage><EndPage>32</EndPage><MedlinePgn>23-32</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1159/000535227</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Various non-pharmacological interventions to prevent coronavirus dissemination were implemented during the COVID-19 pandemic, including school closures. The effect of these interventions on particular aspects of people's lives such as sexual and reproductive health outcomes has not been adequately discussed. The objective of the study was to compare the monthly hospital admission rates due to abortion before and during school closure.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We used an interrupted time series (IES) design to estimate the hospital admission rates before and during the school closure (intervention in March 2020) period. The analysis was performed considering all girls from age groups of interest and by stratifying the age groups according to skin color (white and non-white) in which the non-white category comprised both the black and mixed ethnicity together. Coefficients and 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) were calculated using segmented linear regression models.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The results showed positive and statistically significant coefficients, suggesting post-intervention trend changes both in the population as a whole (coefficient: 0.07; 95% CI: 0.02; 0.11) and the non-white population group (coefficient: 0.07; 95% CI: 0.03; 0.11), indicating that the monthly hospital admission rates increased over the post-intervention period compared to baseline pre-intervention period. The ITS analysis did not detect statistically significant trend changes (coefficient: 0.02; 95% CI: -0.01; 0.05) in abortion admission rates in the white girl population group.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The hospitalizations in Brazil due to abortions in 10- to 14-year-old girls increased during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020 compared to 2019, and the number of abortions was higher in the non-white population than the white population. Furthermore, recognizing that the implementation of school closure has affected the minority population differentially can help develop more effective actions to face other future similar situations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by S. Karger AG, Basel on behalf of NOVA National School of Public Health.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>do Nascimento</LastName><ForeName>Maria Isabel</ForeName><Initials>MI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculdade de Medicina, Departamento de Cirurgia Geral e Especializada, Universidade Federal Fluminense, Niterói, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rabelo Silva</LastName><ForeName>Thalys Gabriel</ForeName><Initials>TG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculdade de Medicina. Universidade Federal Fluminense, Niterói, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Aguiar Mello Nascimento</LastName><ForeName>Victor Joshua</ForeName><Initials>VJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculdade de Medicina. Universidade Federal Fluminense, Niterói, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ortiz Flores</LastName><ForeName>Luis Patricio</ForeName><Initials>LP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculdade de Economia, Contábeis e Atuária, Pontifícia Universidade Católica de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McBenedict</LastName><ForeName>Billy</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculdade de Medicina. Universidade Federal Fluminense, Niterói, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Port J Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101719507</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2504-3145</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19: abortion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hospitalization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Interrupted time series analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reproductive health</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare for this study.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11499666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000535227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">535227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Riley T, Sully E, Ahmed Z, Biddlecom A. Estimates of the potential impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on sexual and reproductive health in low- and middle-income countries. Int Perspect Sex Reprod Health. 2020;46:73–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32343244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilecco FB, McCallum CA, Almeida MDCC, Alves FJO, Rocha ADS, Ortelan N, et al. . Abortion and the COVID-19 pandemic: insights for Latin America. Cad Saúde Pública. 2021;37(6):e00322320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34231763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization; World Health Organization . Mitigating the direct and indirect consequences of COVID-19 on the health and well-being of young people in the Americas. Washington, DC: Pan American Health Organization. World Health Organization; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>School closures and teenage pregnancy. Bull World Health Organ. 2021;99(1):6–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7924898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33658730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chavez Villegas C, Peirolo S, Rocca M, Ipince A, Bakrania S. Impacts of health-related school closures on child protection outcomes: a review of evidence from past pandemics and epidemics and lessons learned for COVID-19. Int J Educ Dev. 2021;84:102431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8132744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34025016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karp C, Moreau C, Sheehy G, Anjur-Dietrich S, Mbushi F, Muluve E, et al. . Youth relationships in the Era of COVID-19: a mixed-methods study among adolescent girls and young women in Kenya. J Adolesc Health. 2021;69(5):754–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8460286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34465510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
World Health Organization . Abortion: fact sheets [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2023. [cited 2023 Apr 25]. Available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/abortion.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
UNESCO . Global monitoring of school closures caused by COVID-19 [Internet]. Paris: United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization; 2023. [cited 2021 Sep 11]. Available from: https://en.unesco.org/covid19/educationresponse#schoolclosures.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoumaker B, Sánchez-Páez DA. La fécondité des filles de moins de 15 ans dans le monde. Popul Soc. 2022;N°601(6):1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borges AL, Chofakian CB, Sato AP, Fujimori E, Duarte LS, Gomes MN. Fertility rates among very young adolescent women: temporal and spatial trends in Brazil. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2016;16:57. Erratum in: BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2016;16(1):204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4797224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26992396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dehlendorf C, Harris LH, Weitz TA. Disparities in abortion rates: a public health approach. Am J Public Health. 2013;103(10):1772–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3780732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23948010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernal JL, Cummins S, Gasparrini A. Interrupted time series regression for the evaluation of public health interventions: a tutorial. Int J Epidemiol. 2017;46(1):348–55. Erratum in: Int J Epidemiol. 2020;49(4):1414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5407170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27283160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasil. Ministério da Saúde. Departamento de Informática do Sistema Único de Saúde. Health Information: vital Statistics: overall Mortality [Internet]. Brasília-DF: DATASUS; 2021. [cited 2021 Aug 20]. Available from: http://www2.datasus.gov.br/DATASUS/index.php.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasil. Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística. Population: Statistics of Population [Internet]. Brasília-DF: IBGE; 2021. [cited 2021 Aug 21]. Available from: https://www.ibge.gov.br/estatisticas/sociais/populacao/9109-projecao-da-populacao.html?=&amp;t=o-que-e.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
R Core Team . R: a language and environment for statistical computing [Internet]. Vienna: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2013. [cited 2021 Aug 21]. Available from: https://www.R-project.org/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durbin J, Watson GS. Testing for serial correlation in least squares regression. II. Biometrika. 1951;38(1/2):159–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14848121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagner AK, Soumerai SB, Zhang F, Ross-Degnan D. Segmented regression analysis of interrupted time series studies in medication use research. J Clin Pharm Ther. 2002;27(4):299–309.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12174032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fulcher IR, Onwuzurike C, Goldberg AB, Cottrill AA, Fortin J, Janiak E. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on abortion care utilization and disparities by age. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2022;226(6):819 e1–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8802456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35114184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandell K, Vanbenschoten H, Parachini M, Gomperts R, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Telemedicine as an alternative way to access abortion in Italy and characteristics of requests during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMJ Sex Reprod Health. 2022;48(4):252–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34697044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Pan American Health Organization; World Health Organization . COVID-19 situation reports [Internet]. Washington, DC: Pan American Health Organization. World Health Organization; 2021. [cited 2021 Sep 29]. Available from: https://www.paho.org/en/covid-19-situation-reports.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaabane S, Doraiswamy S, Chaabna K, Mamtani R, Cheema S. The impact of COVID-19 school closure on child and adolescent health: a rapid systematic review. Children. 2021;8(5):415.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8159143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34069468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Vision International . COVID-19 aftershocks: access denied: teenage pregnancy threatens to block a million girls across Sub-Saharan Africa from returning to school. World Vision International; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan W. School closures were over-weighted against the mitigation of COVID-19 transmission: a literature review on the impact of school closures in the United States. Medicine. 2021;100(30):e26709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8322504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34397701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
World Health Organization . Adolescent pregnancy: key facts: 31 january 2020 [Internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020. [cited 2021 Sep 18]. Available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/adolescent-pregnancy.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndlovu CCC, Makoni P, Gundani HV. COVID-19 lockdown related teenage pregnancy: concept analysis. Int J Adv Res Nurs. 2021;4(1):101–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zauche LH, Wallace B, Smoots AN, Olson CK, Oduyebo T, Kim SY, et al. . Receipt of mRNA Covid-19 vaccines and risk of spontaneous abortion. N Engl J Med. 2021;385(16):1533–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8451181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34496196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kharbanda EO, Haapala J, DeSilva M, Vazquez-Benitez G, Vesco KK, Naleway AL, et al. . Spontaneous abortion following COVID-19 vaccination during pregnancy. JAMA. 2021;326(16):1629–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8427483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34495304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Digitale JC, Stojanovski K, McCulloch CE, Handley MA. Study designs to assess real-world interventions to prevent COVID-19. Front Public Health. 2021;9:e657976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8353119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34386470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>