<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464500</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1643-8876</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Przeglad menopauzalny = Menopause review</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Prz Menopauzalny</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 phobia, personality traits and menopausal symptoms in women in the climacteric period.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>133</StartPage><EndPage>139</EndPage><MedlinePgn>133-139</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5114/pm.2024.143468</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Menopausal symptoms in women are influenced by personality traits as well as physical and psychological characteristics. The effects of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) phobia on personality traits and menopausal symptoms in premenopausal and postmenopausal women were examined in this study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIAL AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The study was conducted in a cross-sectional and descriptive design with 410 women. The data were collected using a descriptive data form, the COVID-19 phobia scale, the menopause rating scale, and the Cervantes personality scale.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In this study, 46.8% of the women were premenopausal and 53.2% were postmenopausal. The mean age was 42.9 ±1.97 years in premenopausal women and 50.9 ±2.94 years in postmenopausal women. The psychological, social, and total COVID-19 phobia scores were found to be higher in postmenopausal women than premenopausal women. Postmenopausal women showed more introverted personality traits than premenopausal women. COVID-19 phobia affected postmenopausal women more than premenopausal women in terms of psychological, social and all menopausal symptoms. As COVID-19 phobia increased, neurotic personality traits increased in premenopausal women, and introverted and neurotic personality traits increased in postmenopausal women (p &lt; 0.05). Menopausal symptoms increased with neurotic personality traits in premenopausal women and with introverted personality traits in postmenopausal women (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.001).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">COVID-19 phobia affected both groups in terms of menopausal symptoms and personality traits. For the management of menopausal symptoms, it is recommended to consider neurotic personality traits in premenopausal women and introverted personality traits in postmenopausal women.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Termedia.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Özberk</LastName><ForeName>Hülya</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dokuz Eylül University, Izmir, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bilgiç</LastName><ForeName>Dilek</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dokuz Eylül University, Izmir, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tepecik Training and Research Hospital, Izmir, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arı</LastName><ForeName>Fatma Gül</ForeName><Initials>FG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tepecik Training and Research Hospital, Izmir, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Özeren</LastName><ForeName>Mehmet</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tepecik Training and Research Hospital, Izmir, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Başoğlu</LastName><ForeName>Melih</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dokuz Eylül University, Izmir, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Poland</Country><MedlineTA>Prz Menopauzalny</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101263235</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1643-8876</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">climacteric</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">personality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">postmenopause</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">premenopause</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>None.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/pm.2024.143468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">54873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rees M, Abernethy K, Bachmann G, et al. . The essential menopause curriculum for healthcare professionals: A European Menopause and Andropause Society (EMAS) position statement. Maturitas 2022; 158: 70-77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35115178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kekäläinen T, Hietavala EM, Hakamäki M, et al. . Personality traits and changes in health behaviors and depressive symptoms during the COVID-19 pandemic: a longitudinal analysis from pre-pandemic to onset and end of the initial emergency conditions in Finland. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2021; 18: 7732.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8345535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34360025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ak Sözer G, Güdül Öz, H, Yangın H. Relationship between menopausal symptoms and perceived stress during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Women Aging 2022; 34: 675-686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34661513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nacar G, Timur Tashan S. Eating attitudes, depressive symptoms, physical activity levels and menopausal symptoms of postmenopausal women diagnosed with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a case-control study. Women Health 2022; 62: 223-233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35291922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grochans E, Szkup M, Kotwas A, et al. . Analysis of sociodemographic, psychological, and genetic factors contributing to depressive symptoms in pre-, peri-and postmenopausal women. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2018; 15: 712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5923754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29642625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afshar H, Roohafza HR, Keshteli AH, et al. . The association of personality traits and coping styles according to stress level. J Res Med Sci 2015; 20: 353-358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4468450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26109990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa PT, McCrae RR. Personality disorders and the five-factor model of personality. J Pers Disord 1990; 4: 362-371.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldberg LR. An alternative “description of personality”: the big-five factor structure. J Pers Soc Psychol 1990; 59: 1216-29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2283588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Augoulea A, Moros M, Kokras N, et al. . Association of menopausal symptoms with sociodemographic factors and personality traits. Prz Menopauz 2019; 18: 191-197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7045358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32132882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi N, Delavar MA, Mashayekh-Amiri S, et al. . Exploring the relationship between depression on menopausal symptoms and personality trails. Community Health Equity Res Policy 2023; 43: 125-131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33818209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arpacı I, Karatas K, Baloglu M. The development and initial tests for the psychometric properties of the COVID-19 phobia scale (C19P-S). Pers Individ Differ 2020; 164: 110108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7211675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32394993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider HPG, Heinemann LAJ, Rosemeier HP, et al. . The menopause rating scale (MRS): comparison with Kupperman index and quality-of-life scale SF-36. Climacteric 2000; 3: 50-58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11910610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurkan OC. Reliability and validity of the Turkish form of the menopause symptoms assessment scale [Turkish]. J Nurs Forum 2005; 3: 30-35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castelo-Branco C, Palacios S, Ferrer-Barriendos J, et al. . Understanding how personality factors may influence quality of life: development and validation of the Cervantes personality scale. Menopause 2008; 15: 914-918.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18467964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bal Demirgöz M, Sahin Hotun N. Adaptation of Cervantes personality scale into Turkish: validity and reliability study [Turkish]. J Edu Res Nurs 2011; 8: 39-45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Pan R, Wan X, et al. . Immediate psychological responses and associated factors during the initial stage of the 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) epidemic among the general population in China. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2020; 17: 1729.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7084952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32155789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierce M, Hope H, Ford T, et al. . Mental health before and during the COVID-19 pandemic: a longitudinal probability sample survey of the UK population. Lancet Psychiatry 2020; 7: 883-892.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7373389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32707037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudenstine S, McNeal K, Schulder T, et al. . Depression and anxiety during the COVID-19 pandemic in an urban, low-income public university sample. J Trauma Stress 2021; 34: 12-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7675401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33045107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monterrosa-Blanco A, Monterrosa-Castro Á, González-Sequeda A. Online assessment of the perception of loneliness and associated factors in Colombian climacteric women during the COVID-19 pandemic: a cross-sectional study. Health Promot Perspect 2021; 11: 230-239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8233672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34195047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamauchi T, Suka M, Yanagisawa H. Personality traits, media exposure, and deterioration of psychological wellbeing in Japan during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Nerv Ment Dis 2022; 210: 83-90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34570060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stephan Y, Boiché J, Canada B, et al. . Association of personality with physical, social, and mental activities across the lifespan: findings from US and French samples. Br J Psychol 2014; 105: 564-580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24182200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ormel J, Jeronimus BF, Kotov R, et al. . Neuroticism and common mental disorders: meaning and utility of a complex relationship. Clin Psychol Rev 2013; 33: 686-697.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4382368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23702592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orhan Ergin I, Yağmur Y. The correlation between menopausal complaints and personality traits. Perspect Psychiatr Care 2018; 54: 365-370.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29427508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>