<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39463025</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1582-4934</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>28</Volume><Issue>20</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of cellular and molecular medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Cell Mol Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Old disease-New reflections: Gaucher, immunity, and inflammation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70087</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70087</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70087</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jcmm.70087</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Gaucher disease (GD) is the most common lysosomal storage disease. It is a multisystemic metabolic disease caused by GBA pathogenic mutations. Although the general symptoms have been known for a long time, new treatment possibilities, the detection of different biomarkers, and innovations in diagnosis and follow-up have paved the way for further studies. Recent studies have shown that the immune system has become an essential factor associated with disease progression. The role of Gaucher cells in the disease is well characterized. In addition to phagocytic macrophage cells, lymphocytes, complement system, and inflammatory pathway elements are also implicated in GD as they were shown to be the underlying factors causing associated pathologies such as Parkinson's. In this article, the relationship between the GD and the immune system has been examined and reviewed in light of new findings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine published by Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Şoroğlu</LastName><ForeName>Can Veysel</ForeName><Initials>CV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Acıbadem Mehmet Ali Aydınlar University, Institute of Health Sciences, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berkay</LastName><ForeName>Ezgi Gizem</ForeName><Initials>EG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1967-705X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Basic Sciences, Dentistry Faculty, Istanbul Kent University, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Cell Mol Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101083777</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1582-1838</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.2.1.45</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D005962">Glucosylceramidase</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005776" MajorTopicYN="Y">Gaucher Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007249" MajorTopicYN="Y">Inflammation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005962" MajorTopicYN="N">Glucosylceramidase</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007109" MajorTopicYN="N">Immunity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gaucher disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Glucocerebrosidase</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neuroinflammation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcmm.70087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11513444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Jmoudiak M, Futerman AH. Gaucher disease: pathological mechanisms and modern management. Br J Haematol. 2005;129:178‐188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15813845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong K, Sidransky E, Verma A, et al. Neuropathology provides clues to the pathophysiology of Gaucher disease. Mol Genet Metab. 2004;82:192‐207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15234332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nilsson O, Svennerholm L. Accumulation of glucosylceramide and Glucosylsphingosine (Psychosine) in cerebrum and cerebellum in infantile and juvenile Gaucher disease. J Neurochem. 1982;39:709‐718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7097276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith L, Mullin S, Schapira AHV. Insights into the structural biology of Gaucher disease. Exp Neurol. 2017;298:180‐190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28923368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tjoa STS, De Vries TJ, Schoenmaker T, Kelder A, Loos BG, Everts V. Formation of osteoclast‐like cells from peripheral blood of periodontitis patients occurs without supplementation of macrophage colony‐stimulating factor. J Clin Periodontol. 2008;35:568‐575.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18435789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilan Y. β‐Glycosphingolipids as mediators of both inflammation and immune tolerance: a manifestation of randomness in biological systems. Front Immunol. 2019;10:1143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6538797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31178868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braudeau C, Graveleau J, Rimbert M, et al. Altered innate function of plasmacytoid dendritic cells restored by enzyme replacement therapy in Gaucher disease. Blood Cells Mol Dis. 2013;50:281‐288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23357793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistry PK, Liu J, Yang M, et al. Glucocerebrosidase gene‐deficient mouse recapitulates Gaucher disease displaying cellular and molecular dysregulation beyond the macrophage. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2010;107:19473‐19478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2984187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20962279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taddei TH, Kacena KA, Yang M, et al. The underrecognized progressive nature of N370S Gaucher disease and assessment of cancer risk in 403 patients. Am J Hematol. 2009;84:208‐214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3008404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19260119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott CC, Vacca F, Gruenberg J. Endosome maturation, transport and functions. Semin Cell Dev Biol. 2014;31:2‐10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24709024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aflaki E, Borger DK, Grey RJ, et al. Efferocytosis is impaired in Gaucher macrophages. Haematologica. 2017;102:656‐665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5395106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28011901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Grabowski GA. Impaired autophagosomes and lysosomes in neuronopathic Gaucher disease. Autophagy. 2010;6:648‐649.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20458183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Liou B, Ran H, et al. Neuronopathic Gaucher disease in the mouse: viable combined selective saposin C deficiency and mutant glucocerebrosidase (V394L) mice with glucosylsphingosine and glucosylceramide accumulation and progressive neurological deficits. Hum Mol Genet. 2010;19:1088‐1097.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2830832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20047948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osellame LD, Rahim AA, Hargreaves IP, et al. Mitochondria and quality control defects in a mouse model of Gaucher disease—links to Parkinson's disease. Cell Metab. 2013;17:941‐953.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3678026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23707074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Xu K, Sun Y, et al. Multiple pathogenic proteins implicated in neuronopathic Gaucher disease mice. Hum Mol Genet. 2014;23:3943‐3957.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4082362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24599400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farfel‐Becker T, Vitner EB, Kelly SL, et al. Neuronal accumulation of glucosylceramide in a mouse model of neuronopathic Gaucher disease leads to neurodegeneration. Hum Mol Genet. 2014;23:843‐854.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3900102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24064337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinghorn KJ, Grönke S, Castillo‐Quan JI, et al. A drosophila model of neuronopathic Gaucher disease demonstrates lysosomal‐autophagic defects and altered mTOR signalling and is functionally rescued by rapamycin. J Neurosci. 2016;36:11654‐11670.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5125225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27852774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee RE, Balcerzak SP, Westerman MP. Gaucher's disease. A morphologic study and measurements of iron metabolism. Am J Med. 1967;42:891‐898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6067457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bitton A, Etzell J, Grenert JP, Wang E. Erythrophagocytosis in Gaucher cells. Arch Pathol Lab Med. 2004;128:1191‐1192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15387692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naito M, Takahashi K, Hojo H. An ultrastructural and experimental study on the development of tubular structures in the lysosomes of Gaucher cells. Lab Investig. 1988;58:590‐598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3367638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machaczka M, Klimkowska M, Regenthal S, Hägglund H. Gaucher disease with foamy transformed macrophages and erythrophagocytic activity. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2011;34:233‐235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21113739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gholamreza B, Ghasem M‐A. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis syndrome associated with Gaucher disease type 2. Turk J Haematol. 2014;31:307‐308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4287034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25330526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aflaki E, Moaven N, Borger DK, et al. Lysosomal storage and impaired autophagy lead to inflammasome activation in Gaucher macrophages. Aging Cell. 2016;15:77‐88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4717273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26486234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klionsky DJ, Abdelmohsen K, Abe A, et al. Guidelines for the use and interpretation of assays for monitoring autophagy (3rd edition). Autophagy. 2016;12:1‐222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4835977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26799652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barak V, Acker M, Nisman B, et al. Cytokines in Gaucher's disease. Eur Cytokine Netw. 1999;10:205‐210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10400826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balreira A, Lacerda L, Miranda CS, Arosa FA. Evidence for a link between sphingolipid metabolism and expression of CD1d and MHC‐class II: monocytes from Gaucher disease patients as a model. Br J Haematol. 2005;129:667‐676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15916690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lecourt S, Vanneaux V, Cras A, et al. Bone marrow microenvironment in an in vitro model of Gaucher disease: consequences of glucocerebrosidase deficiency. Stem Cells Dev. 2012;21:239‐248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21867425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mucci JM, Scian R, De Francesco PN, et al. Induction of osteoclastogenesis in an in vitro model of Gaucher disease is mediated by T cells via TNF‐α. Gene. 2012;509:51‐59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23010424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lecourt S, Mouly E, Freida D, et al. A prospective study of bone marrow hematopoietic and mesenchymal stem cells in type 1 Gaucher disease patients. PLoS One. 2013;8:e69293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3723887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23935976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crivaro A, Bondar C, Mucci JM, et al. Gaucher disease‐associated alterations in mesenchymal stem cells reduce osteogenesis and favour adipogenesis processes with concomitant increased osteoclastogenesis. Mol Genet Metab. 2020;130:274‐282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32536424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondar C, Mucci J, Crivaro A, et al. In vitro osteoclastogenesis from Gaucher patients' cells correlates with bone mineral density but not with chitotriosidase. Bone. 2017;103:262‐269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28736246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mucci JM, Cuello MF, Kisinovsky I, Larroude M, Delpino MV, Rozenfeld PA. Proinflammatory and proosteoclastogenic potential of peripheral blood mononuclear cells from Gaucher patients: implication for bone pathology. Blood Cells Mol Dis. 2015;55:134‐143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26142329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed MC, Bauernfreund Y, Cunningham N, Beaton B, Mehta AB, Hughes DA. Generation of osteoclasts from type 1 Gaucher patients and correlation with clinical and genetic features of disease. Gene. 2018;678:196‐206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30099023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinreb NJ, Charrow J, Andersson HC, et al. Effectiveness of enzyme replacement therapy in 1028 patients with type 1 Gaucher disease after 2 to 5 years of treatment: a report from the Gaucher registry. Am J Med. 2002;113:112‐119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12133749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gervas‐Arruga J, Cebolla JJ, De BI, et al. The influence of genetic variability and proinflammatory status on the development of bone disease in patients with Gaucher disease. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0126153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4433334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25978039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campeau PM, Rafei M, Boivin M‐N, Sun Y, Grabowski GA, Galipeau J. Characterization of Gaucher disease bone marrow mesenchymal stromal cells reveals an altered inflammatory secretome. Blood. 2009;114:3181‐3190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2925728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19587377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alcalay RN, Dinur T, Quinn T, et al. Comparison of Parkinson risk in Ashkenazi Jewish patients with Gaucher disease and GBA heterozygotes. JAMA Neurol. 2014;71:752‐757.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4082726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24756352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chérin P, Rose C, de Roux‐Serratrice C, et al. The neurological manifestations of Gaucher disease type 1: the French observatoire on Gaucher disease (FROG). J Inherit Metab Dis. 2010;33:331‐338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20532983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miklossy J, Doudet DD, Schwab C, Yu S, McGeer EG, McGeer PL. Role of ICAM‐1 in persisting inflammation in Parkinson disease and MPTP monkeys. Exp Neurol. 2006;197:275‐283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16336966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brochard V, Combadière B, Prigent A, et al. Infiltration of CD4+ lymphocytes into the brain contributes to neurodegeneration in a mouse model of Parkinson disease. J Clin Invest. 2009;119:182‐192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2613467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19104149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabatino JJ, Pröbstel A‐K, Zamvil SS. B cells in autoimmune and neurodegenerative central nervous system diseases. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2019;20:728‐745.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31712781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hallett PJ, Huebecker M, Brekk OR, et al. Glycosphingolipid levels and glucocerebrosidase activity are altered in normal aging of the mouse brain. Neurobiol Aging. 2018;67:189‐200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6015735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29735433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belarbi K, Cuvelier E, Bonte M‐A, et al. Glycosphingolipids and neuroinflammation in Parkinson's disease. Mol Neurodegener. 2020;15:59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7568394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahran AM, Youssef MAM, Shafik EA, et al. Downregulation of B regulatory cells and upregulation of T helper 1 cells in children with Gaucher disease undergoing enzyme replacement therapy. Immunol Res. 2020;68:73‐80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32524332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dondurmacı M, Canda E, Köse M, et al. Higher levels of CD19+ leukocytes in Gaucher disease patients as a potential marker for malignancy. J Clin Anal Med. 2018;9:56‐60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vardi A, Ben‐Dor S, Cho SM, Kalinke U, Spanier J, Futerman AH. Mice defective in interferon signaling help distinguish between primary and secondary pathological pathways in a mouse model of neuronal forms of Gaucher disease. J Neuroinflammation. 2020;17:265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7487497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32892753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melamed S, Avraham R, Rothbard DE, et al. Innate immune response in neuronopathic forms of Gaucher disease confers resistance against viral‐induced encephalitis. Acta Neuropathol Commun. 2020;8:144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7443817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32831144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey MK, Burrow TA, Rani R, et al. Complement drives glucosylceramide accumulation and tissue inflammation in Gaucher disease. Nature. 2017;543:108‐112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28225753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strainic MG, Liu J, Huang D, et al. Locally produced complement fragments C5a and C3a provide both costimulatory and survival signals to naive CD4+ T cells. Immunity. 2008;28:425‐435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2646383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18328742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahran AM, Eltayeb AA, Elsayh KI, Saad K, Ahmad FA, Ibrahim AIM. Activated and memory T lymphocytes in children with Gaucher disease. Arch Immunol Ther Exp (Warsz). 2017;65:263‐269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27638481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boven LA, van Meurs M, Boot RG, et al. Gaucher cells demonstrate a distinct macrophage phenotype and resemble alternatively activated macrophages. Am J Clin Pathol. 2004;122:359‐369.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15362365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mucci JM, Rozenfeld P. Pathogenesis of bone alterations in Gaucher disease: the role of immune system. J Immunol Res. 2015;2015:192761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4433682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26064996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Limgala RP, Ioanou C, Plassmeyer M, et al. Time of initiating enzyme replacement therapy affects immune abnormalities and disease severity in patients with Gaucher disease. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0168135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5152900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27942037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahran AM, Saad K, Elsayh KI, et al. Upregulation of cytotoxic T‐cells in pediatric patients with Gaucher disease. Sci Rep. 2022;12:4977.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8942997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35323826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Halene S, Yang M, et al. Gaucher disease gene GBA functions in immune regulation. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2012;109:10018‐10023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3382552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22665763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shoenfeld Y, Beresovski A, Zharhary D, et al. Natural autoantibodies in sera of patients with Gaucher's disease. J Clin Immunol. 1995;15:363‐372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8576322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valle DL, Antonarakis S, Ballabio A, Beaudet AL, Mitchell GA. The Online Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease. OMMBID McGraw Hill Medical; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costello R, O'Callaghan T, Sébahoun G. Gaucher disease and multiple myeloma. Leuk Lymphoma. 2006;47:1365‐1368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16923570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitatani K, Wada M, Perry D, et al. Activation of p38 mitogen‐activated protein kinase in Gaucher's disease. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0136633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4552301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26312487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Ran H, Liou B, et al. Isofagomine in vivo effects in a neuronopathic Gaucher disease mouse. PLoS One. 2011;6:e19037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3080394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21533102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitatani K, Sheldon K, Rajagopalan V, et al. Involvement of acid β‐glucosidase 1 in the salvage pathway of ceramide formation. J Biol Chem. 2009;284:12972‐12978.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2676029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19279011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitatani K, Idkowiak‐Baldys J, Bielawski J, et al. Protein kinase C‐induced activation of a ceramide/protein phosphatase 1 pathway leading to dephosphorylation of p38 MAPK. J Biol Chem. 2006;281:36793‐36802.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17030510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eapen M, Hostetter M, Neglia JP. Massive splenomegaly and Epstein‐Barr virus‐associated infectious mononucleosis in a patient with Gaucher disease. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 1999;21:47‐49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10029812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey MK, Rani R, Zhang W, et al. Immunological cell type characterization and Th1‐Th17 cytokine production in a mouse model of Gaucher disease. Mol Genet Metab. 2012;106:310‐322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3382074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22595426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey MK, Grabowski GA. Immunological cells and functions in Gaucher disease. Crit Rev Oncog. 2013;18:197‐220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3661296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23510064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen G, Wu D, Guo W, et al. Clinical and immunological features of severe and moderate coronavirus disease 2019. J Clin Invest. 2020;130:2620‐2629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7190990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng Z, Diao B, Wang R, et al. The novel severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS‐CoV‐2) directly decimates human spleens and lymph nodes. medRxiv. 2020;20045427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trivedi VS, Magnusen AF, Rani R, et al. Targeting the complement–sphingolipid system in COVID‐19 and Gaucher diseases: evidence for a new treatment strategy. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23:14340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9695449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36430817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilavuz S, Kor D, Bulut FD, et al. Real‐world patient data on immunity and COVID‐19 status of patients with MPS, Gaucher, and Pompe diseases from Turkey. Arch Pediatr. 2022;29:415‐423.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9125140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35705384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan J, Hale VL, Lelieveld LT, et al. Gaucher disease protects against tuberculosis. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2023;120:e2217673120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7614233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36745788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>