<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39463713</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2008-9872</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>79</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Archives of Razi Institute</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Arch Razi Inst</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Predictors of the willingness to receive the third dose of COVID-19 vaccine based on the Health Belief Model: A cross-sectional study in South Khorasan province.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>403</StartPage><EndPage>410</EndPage><MedlinePgn>403-410</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.32592/ARI.2024.79.2.403</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infections have re-emerged in several countries due to reduced levels of antibodies provided by vaccines or the rapid emergence of viral variants, such as Alpha, Beta, Gamma, and Delta. A considerable supplementary intervention is recommended, including an additional dose of vaccination. The present study aimed to assess the predictors of the willingness to receive the third dose of the COVID-19 vaccine based on the Health Belief Model (HBM) constructs among people referring to health centers in South Khorasan province. In this cross-sectional-analytical study, 283 people over 18 years old in South Khorasan province were randomly selected using the multi-stage cluster sampling method. The data were collected using a researcher-made questionnaire, including demographic information and health status, knowledge about COVID-19, and the third dose of the vaccine, as well as a questionnaire according to the HBM constructs, which was completed through self-report methods. Finally, the data were analyzed using the Chi-square test and multivariate logistic regression analysis. The mean age of the study participants was 36.57±11.56 years (range of 18-55). The results of multivariate logistic regression analysis demonstrated that gender (<i>P</i>=0.012), marital status (<i>P</i>=0.038), occupation (<i>P</i>=0.013), perceived severity (<i>P</i>=0.005), and cues to action (<i>P</i>=0.018) had a significant direct effect, while perceived barriers (<i>P</i>=0.010) had a significant inverse effect on the willingness to accept the third dose of the vaccine. Moreover, the predictor variables explained about 67.7% of the willingness to receive the third dose of the vaccine. The current study suggested that enhancing the perceived severity of COVID-19, along with healthcare providers' recommendations to receive the vaccine and reducing perceived barriers, can effectively encourage individuals to receive the third dose of the COVID-19 vaccine. These findings can be utilized to develop interventions aimed at promoting the uptake of the booster dose of the COVID-19 vaccine.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khazir</LastName><ForeName>Z</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Tabas School of Nursing, Birjand University of Medical Sciences, Birjand, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Torbat Jam Faculty of Medical Sciences, Torbat Jam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kouhpeikar</LastName><ForeName>H</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Treatment Deputy of Torbat Heydarieh University of Medical sciences, Torbat Heydarieh, Razavi Province, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Javanmardi</LastName><ForeName>E</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MS of Biostatistics, Clinical Research Development Unit, "The Persian Gulf Martyrs" Hospital, Bushehr University of Medical Sciences, Bushehr, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zareipour</LastName><ForeName>M A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, School of Health, Khoy University of Medical Sciences, Khoy, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gholamian</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>BSC in Public Health, Tabas Health Center, Birjand University of Medical Sciences, Birjand, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Iran</Country><MedlineTA>Arch Razi Inst</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101549567</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0365-3439</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000083342" MajorTopicYN="Y">Health Belief Model</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007492" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Iran</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007722" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010342" MajorTopicYN="N">Patient Acceptance of Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Barriers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Booster</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest in this study</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11512177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.32592/ARI.2024.79.2.403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ARI-79-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>İpek S, Yurttutan S, Güllü UU, Dalkıran T, Acıpayam C, Doğaner A. Is N95 face mask linked to dizziness and headache? International Archives of Occupational and Environmental Health. 2021;94:1627–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7919621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33646335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Guan X, Wu P, Wang X, Zhou L, Tong Y, et al. Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus–infected pneumonia. New England journal of medicine. 2020;382(13):1199–207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7121484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31995857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiersinga WJ, Rhodes A, Cheng AC, Peacock SJ, Prescott HC. Pathophysiology, transmission, diagnosis, and treatment of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a review. Jama. 2020;324(8):782–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32648899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palacios R, Patiño EG, de Oliveira Piorelli R, Conde MTRP, Batista AP, Zeng G, et al. Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Phase III Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of treating Healthcare Professionals with the Adsorbed COVID-19 (Inactivated) Vaccine Manufactured by Sinovac–PROFISCOV: A structured summary of a study protocol for a randomised controlled trial. Trials. 2020;21:1–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7558252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33059771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polack FP, Thomas SJ, Kitchin N, Absalon J, Gurtman A, Lockhart S, et al. Safety and efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 vaccine. New England journal of medicine. 2020;383(27):2603–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7745181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergwerk M, Gonen T, Lustig Y, Amit S, Lipsitch M, Cohen C, et al. Covid-19 breakthrough infections in vaccinated health care workers. New England Journal of Medicine. 2021;385(16):1474–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8362591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34320281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaishya R, Sibal A, Malani A, Prasad KH. SARS-CoV-2 infection after COVID-19 immunization in healthcare workers: A retrospective, pilot study. The Indian Journal of Medical Research. 2021;153(5-6):550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8555595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34341227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naaber P, Tserel L, Kangro K, Sepp E, Jürjenson V, Adamson A, et al. Dynamics of antibody response to BNT162b2 vaccine after six months: a longitudinal prospective study. The Lancet Regional Health–Europe. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8418937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34514454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabetian G, Moghadami M, Hashemizadeh Fard Haghighi L, Shahriarirad R, Fallahi MJ, Asmarian N, et al. COVID-19 infection among healthcare workers: a cross-sectional study in southwest Iran. Virology journal. 2021;18:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7968574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33731169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng L, Wang X, Zhou C, Liu Q, Li S, Sun Q, et al. Analysis of the infection status of healthcare workers in Wuhan during the COVID-19 outbreak: a cross-sectional study. Clinical Infectious Diseases. 2020;71(16):2109–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7239233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32409825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen I-H, Ahorsu DK, Ko N-Y, Yen C-F, Lin C-Y, Griffiths MD, et al. Adapting the motors of influenza vaccination acceptance scale into the motors of COVID-19 vaccination acceptance scale: psychometric evaluation among mainland Chinese university students. Vaccine. 2021;39(32):4510–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8216877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34217571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong LP, Alias H, Wong P-F, Lee HY, AbuBakar S. The use of the health belief model to assess predictors of intent to receive the COVID-19 vaccine and willingness to pay. Human vaccines &amp; immunotherapeutics. 2020;16(9):2204–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32730103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hidayana I, Amir S, Pelupessy DC, Rahvenia Z. Using a health belief model to assess COVID-19 vaccine intention and hesitancy in Jakarta, Indonesia. PLOS Global Public Health. 2022;2(10):e0000934.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10021901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36962574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alobaidi S, Hashim A. Predictors of the Third (Booster) Dose of COVID-19 Vaccine Intention among the Healthcare Workers in Saudi Arabia: An Online Cross-Sectional Survey. Vaccines. 2022;10(7):987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9317226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35891150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin C, Wang R, Tao L, Liu M, Liu J. Acceptance of a third dose of COVID-19 vaccine and associated factors in China based on health belief model: a national cross-sectional study. Vaccines. 2022;10(1):89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8780099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35062750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rzymski P, Poniedziałek B, Fal A. Willingness to receive the booster COVID-19 vaccine dose in Poland. Vaccines. 2021;9(11):1286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8624071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34835217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abouzid M, Ahmed AA, El-Sherif DM, Alonazi WB, Eatmann AI, Alshehri MM, et al. Attitudes toward receiving COVID-19 booster dose in the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) region: A cross-sectional study of 3041 fully vaccinated participants. Vaccines. 2022;10(8):1270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9414713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36016158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai X, Zhu H, Wang J, Huang Y, Jing R, Lyu Y, et al. Public perceptions and acceptance of COVID-19 booster vaccination in China: A cross-sectional study. Vaccines. 2021;9(12):1461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8709447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34960208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Qerem W, Al Bawab AQ, Hammad A, Ling J, Alasmari F. Willingness of the Jordanian population to receive a COVID-19 booster dose: a cross-sectional study. Vaccines. 2022;10(3):410.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8950968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35335042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Y, Hu Z, Zhao Q, Alias H, Danaee M, Wong LP. Understanding COVID-19 vaccine demand and hesitancy: A nationwide online survey in China. PLoS neglected tropical diseases. 2020;14(12):e0008961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7775119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33332359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basch CH, Meleo-Erwin Z, Fera J, Jaime C, Basch CE. A global pandemic in the time of viral memes: COVID-19 vaccine misinformation and disinformation on TikTok. Human vaccines &amp; immunotherapeutics. 2021;17(8):2373–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8475621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33764283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain L, Vij J, Satapathy P, Chakrapani V, Patro B, Kar SS, et al. Factors influencing COVID-19 vaccination intentions among college students: a cross-sectional study in India. Frontiers in Public Health. 2021;9:735902.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8714761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34976911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang K, Fang Y, Chan PS-f, Cao H, Chen H, Hu T, et al. Behavioral intention to get a booster dose of COVID-19 vaccine among Chinese factory workers. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. 2022;19(9):5245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9099970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35564639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Li Q, Silver Tarimo C, Wang M, Gu J, Wei W, et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy among Chinese population: a large-scale national study. Frontiers in Immunology. 2021;12:781161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8666422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34912346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu R, Zhang Y, Nicholas S, Leng A, Maitland E, Wang J. COVID-19 vaccination willingness among Chinese adults under the free vaccination policy. Vaccines. 2021;9(3):292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8004171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33801136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>