<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39462800</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1550-5030</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Health care management review</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Health Care Manage Rev</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Improving joy at work and reducing burnout in health care workers in Victoria, Australia using the Institute for Healthcare Improvement joy in work framework: A mixed-methods study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/HMR.0000000000000420</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Burnout in health care workers (HCWs) has serious ramifications for individual well-being, patients, organizations, and health systems. Global evidence demonstrates the COVID-19 pandemic has amplified the risk of burnout. Scalable interventions to address burnout are critical to protect HCW well-being.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Underpinned by the Conservation of Resources theory, this study examines the impacts of a statewide improvement initiative (the Initiative), using the Institute for Healthcare Improvement Joy in Work (JiW) Framework, to reduce burnout and increase joy at work across participating health care organizations in Victoria, Australia.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODOLOGY/APPROACH" NlmCategory="METHODS">An impact evaluation was undertaken utilizing a mixed-methods design. Quantitative outcomes included burnout and joy at work measured using an adapted Mini Z tool. In-depth interviews with implementation teams sought insights into the effectiveness of interventions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Overall, 20 teams from 17 organizations across diverse health care settings and geographical locations participated. At a statewide level, outcomes in burnout and joy at work were inconclusive due to limited data. However, five out of eight teams reporting sufficient data achieved measurable improvements in one or more outcomes. Qualitative data revealed the Initiative increased workplace resources and supports such as providing "permission" for HCWs to prioritize well-being at work, improved communications between management and HCWs, and increased HCWs' teamwork and camaraderie, resulting in safer and more positive workplaces.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION AND PRACTICE IMPLICATIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The JiW Framework, implemented across diverse settings, provided organizations with a structured process to develop multifaceted improvements that resulted in enhanced resources that appeared to improve HCW well-being. Compared to individual well-being support, this approach offers organization-level change and scalability potential.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jordan</LastName><ForeName>Joanne E</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2625-7985</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garner</LastName><ForeName>Kerryn</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bones</LastName><ForeName>Kate</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McKenzie</LastName><ForeName>Lisa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Linzer</LastName><ForeName>Mark</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rathert</LastName><ForeName>Cheryl</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goelz</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McCall</LastName><ForeName>Jesse</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sawyer</LastName><ForeName>Eleanor</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baass</LastName><ForeName>Briana</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Herco</LastName><ForeName>Fiona</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Health Care Manage Rev</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7611530</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0361-6274</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39462800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/HMR.0000000000000420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00004010-990000000-00074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alvaro C., Lyons R. F., Warner G., Hobfoll S. E., Martens P. J., Labonté R., Brown E. R. (2010). Conservation of resources theory and research use in health systems. Implementation Science, 5(1), 79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakker A. B., Demerouti E., Sanz-Vergel A. (2023). Job demands–resources theory: Ten years later. Annual Review of Organizational Psychology and Organizational Behavior, 10(1), 25–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brady K. J. S., Ni P., Carlasare L., Shanafelt T. D., Sinsky C. A., Linzer M., Stillman M., Trockel M. T. (2022). Establishing crosswalks between common measures of burnout in US physicians. Journal of General Internal Medicine, 37(4), 777–784.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterjee S. S., Chakrabarty M., Banerjee D., Grover S., Chatterjee S. S., Dan U. (2021). Stress, sleep and psychological impact in healthcare workers during the early phase of COVID-19 in India: A factor analysis. Frontiers in Psychology, 12, 611314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dall'Ora C., Ball J., Reinius M., Griffiths P. (2020). Burnout in nursing: A theoretical review. Human Resources for Health, 18(1), 41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eatough V., Smith J. A. (2017). Interpretive phenomenological analysis. In C. Willig, W. Stainton-Rogers (Eds.), Handbook of qualitative psychology ( ed., pp. 193–211). Sage.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewais T., Hunt G., Munro J., Pun P., Hogan C., William L., Teodorczuk A. (2022). Schwartz rounds for staff in an Australian tertiary hospital: Protocol for a pilot uncontrolled trial. JMIR Research Protocols, 11(4), e35083.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halbesleben J. R. B., Neveu J. P., Paustian-Underdahl S. C., Westman M. (2014). Getting to the “COR”: Understanding the role of resources in conservation of resources theory. Journal of Management, 40(5), 1334–1364.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall L., Johnson J., Heyhoe J., Watt I., Anderson K., O’Connor D. B. (2020). Exploring the impact of primary care physician burnout and well-being on patient care: A focus group study. Journal of Patient Safety, 16(4), e278–e283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harry M. L., Sudak N. L., Engels M. J., Horn K. K., Dean K., Poplau S., Stillman M. J., Linzer M. (2024). Physician and advanced practice clinician burnout in rural and urban settings. Journal of American Board of Family Medicine, 37(1), 43–58. 10.3122/jabfm.2023.230233R1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2023.230233R1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobfoll S. E. (1989). Conservation of resources. A new attempt at conceptualizing stress. The American Psychologist, 44(3), 513–524.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huggins K., Peeters A., Holton S., Wynter K., Hutchnison A., Rasmussen B., LaMontagne A. (2022). Towards a thriving healthcare workforce. https://ahha.asn.au/sites/default/files/docs/policy-issue/perspectives_brief_no_24_towards_a_thriving_healthcare_workforce.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IHI. (2003). The breakthrough series: IHI's collaborative model for achieving breakthrough improvement. www.ihi.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IHI. (2023). IHI joy in work results-oriented learning network. https://www.ihi.org/Engage/collaboratives/joy-results/Pages/default.aspx</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koranne R., Williams E. S., Poplau S., Banks K. M., Sonneborn M., Britt H. R., Linzer M. (2022). Reducing burnout and enhancing work engagement among clinicians: The Minnesota experience. Health Care Management Review, 47(1), 49–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korman M. B., Steinberg R., Gagliardi L., Stewart B., Acero C. L., Davies J., Maunder R., Walker T., DasGupta T., DiProspero L., Sinyor M., Ellis J. (2022). Implementing the STEADY wellness program to support healthcare workers throughout the COVID-19 pandemic. Healthcare, 10(10), 1830.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langley G., Langley G., Moen R., Nolan K., Norman CL., Provost L. (2009). The improvement guide (2nd ed.). Jossey-Bass.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Scherer N., Felix L., Kuper H. (2021). Prevalence of depression, anxiety and post-traumatic stress disorder in health care workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One, 16(3), e0246454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linzer M., Jin J. O., Shah P., Stillman M., Brown R., Poplau S., Nankivil N., Cappelucci K., Sinsky C. A. (2022a). Trends in clinician burnout with associated mitigating and aggravating factors during the COVID-19 pandemic. JAMA Health Forum, 3(11), e224163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linzer M., McLoughlin C., Poplau S., Goelz E., Brown R., Sinsky C.; for the AMA-Hennepin Health System (HHS) Burnout Reduction Writing Team (2022b). The Mini Z Worklife and burnout reduction instrument: Psychometrics and clinical implications. Journal of General Internal Medicine, 37(11), 2876–2878.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linzer M., Poplau S., Grossman E., Varkey A., Yale S., Williams E., Hicks L., Brown R. L., Wallock J., Kohnhorst D., Barbouche M. (2015). A cluster randomized trial of interventions to improve work conditions and clinician burnout in primary care: Results from the healthy work place (HWP) study. Journal of General Internal Medicine, 30(8), 1105–1111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linzer M., Smith C. D., Hingle S., Poplau S., Miranda R., Freese R., Palamara K. (2020). Evaluation of work satisfaction, stress, and burnout among US internal medicine physicians and trainees. JAMA Network Open, 3(10), e2018758.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linzer M., Visser M. R., Oort F. J., Smets E. M., McMurray J., de Haes H. C.; Society of General Internal Medicine (SGIM) Career Satisfaction Study Group (CSSG) (2001). Predicting and preventing physician burnout: Results from the United States and the Netherlands. The American Journal of Medicine, 111(2), 170–175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucas D., Brient S., le Grand T., Dewitte J. D., Loddé B., Pougnet R., Eveillard B. (2022). Evolution of Global Health and psychosocial factors among hospital workers during first year of SARS-CoV-2 pandemic: A longitudinal study. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(22), 15260.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macaron M. M., Segun-Omosehin O. A., Matar R. H., Beran A., Nakanishi H., Than C. A., Abulseoud O. A. (2023). A systematic review and meta analysis on burnout in physicians during the COVID-19 pandemic: A hidden healthcare crisis. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 13, 1071397.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maslach C., Schaufeli W. B., Leiter M. P. (2001). Job burnout. Annual Review of Psychology, 52, 397–422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Brien N., Flott K., Bray O., Shaw A., Durkin M. (2022). Implementation of initiatives designed to improve healthcare worker health and wellbeing during the COVID-19 pandemic: Comparative case studies from 13 healthcare provider organisations globally. Globalization and Health, 18(1), 24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panagioti M., Geraghty K., Johnson J., Zhou A., Panagopoulou E., Chew-Graham C., Peters D., Hodkinson A., Riley R., Esmail A. (2018). Association between physician burnout and patient safety, professionalism, and patient satisfaction: A systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Internal Medicine, 178(10), 1317–1331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perla J., Provost L. P., Murray S. K. (2011). The run chart: A simple analytical tool for learning from variation in healthcare processes. BMJ Quality Safety, 20(1), 46–51. 10.1136/bmjqs.2009.037895</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjqs.2009.037895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perlo J., Balik B, Swensen S, Kabcenell A, Landsman J, Feeley D (2017). IHI framework for improving joy in work (IHI white paper). www.ihi.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perlo J., Feeley D. (2018). Why focusing on professional burnout is not enough. Journal of Healthcare Management, 63(2), 85–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Provost L. P. (2011). Analytical studies: A framework for quality improvement design and analysis. BMJ Quality Safety, 20(Suppl 1), i92–i96. 10.1136/bmjqs.2011.051557</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjqs.2011.051557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Provost L. P., Murray S. K. (2011). The health care data guide: Learning from data for improvement. Jossey-Bass.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rathert C., Williams E. S., Linhart H. (2018). Evidence for the quadruple aim: A systematic review of the literature on physician burnout and patient outcomes. Medical Care, 56(12), 976–984.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehder K., Adair K. C., Sexton J. B. (2021). The science of health care worker burnout: Assessing and improving health care worker well-being. Archives of Pathology &amp; Laboratory Medicine, 145(9), 1095–1109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rohland B. M., Kruse G. R., Rohrer J. E. (2004). Validation of a single-item measure of burnout against the Maslach burnout inventory among physicians. Stress and Health, 20(2), 75–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah A., Akhtar S., Ayers T., Bevan R., Cannon E., Milarski M., Souza R., Warby R. (2023). Increasing joy in work in UK healthcare teams: A national quality improvement collaborative. British Journal of Healthcare Management, 29(6), 1–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smallwood N., Karimi L., Bismark M., Putland M., Johnson D., Dharmage S. C., Barson E., Atkin N., Long C., Ng I., Holland A., Munro J. E., Thevarajan I., Moore C., McGillion A., Sandford D., Willis K. (2021). High levels of psychosocial distress among Australian frontline healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-sectional survey. General Psychiatry, 34(5), e100577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watkins P. C., Emmons R. A., Greaves M. R., Bell J. (2018). Joy is a distinct positive emotion: Assessment of joy and relationship to gratitude and well-being. The Journal of Positive Psychology, 13(5), 522–539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>West C. P., Dyrbye L. N., Shanafelt T. D. (2018). Physician burnout: Contributors, consequences and solutions. Journal of Internal Medicine, 283(6), 516–529.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilkinson H., Whittington R., Perry L., Eames C. (2017). Examining the relationship between burnout and empathy in healthcare professionals: A systematic review. Burnout Research, 6, 18–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zemni I., Dhouib W., Sakly S., et al. (2023). Burnout syndrome among health care workers during the COVID-19 pandemic. A cross sectional study in Monastir, Tunisia. PLoS One, 18(3), e0282318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zung G., Schooler J. W., Wang Y., Tao M. (2018). Research on the relationship between positive emotions, psychological capital and job burnout in enterprises' employees: Based on the broaden-and-build theory of positive emotions. Canadian Social Science, 14(5), 42–48.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>