<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39465219</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2055-2076</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jan-Dec</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Digital health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Digit Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Characteristics, utilization of reproductive health services and AI prediction among Taiwanese adolescent mothers during the COVID-19 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>20552076241292675</StartPage><MedlinePgn>20552076241292675</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">20552076241292675</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/20552076241292675</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Although adolescent birth rates have declined globally, the sexual and reproductive health of adolescent mothers remains an area of specific concern, and these were impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic. This study investigates characteristics, utilization of reproductive health services (RHS) and artificial intelligence (AI) prediction during the pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We conducted an exploratory study using data for 2020-2022 from the Taipei City Government Health Bureau. Adolescent mothers under the age of 20 received post-birth telephone-based RHS, covering contraception, abortion, postpartum care, and social welfare support. The data analysis included descriptive statistics, and various machine learning techniques were employed, including random forest, SVM, KNN, logistic regression, and Bayesian network analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Of 112 participants, most were aged 17 to 19 (80.4%) and married (58.0%). The majority had full-term deliveries (86.6%) with healthy infants. A high percentage had not used contraception before conception (60.7%), and some had had earlier abortion or termination experiences (13.4%). In the examination of eight influential factors, the machine learning models, specifically the random forest and Bayesian network analyses, exhibited the highest accuracy, achieving 90.91% and 89%, respectively, in predicting service acceptance. The key determinants identified were abortion experience and marital status, directly influencing the acceptance of services.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The COVID-19 pandemic reduced hospital visits for adolescent mothers, but the RHS provided timely guidance. Telemedicine consultations and internet-based psychological consultations may play a crucial role in facilitating such services in the future.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Ching Hsuan</ForeName><Initials>CH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Taipei City Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">38010</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hsiao</LastName><ForeName>Ching Hua</ForeName><Initials>CH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Taipei City Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">38010</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liao</LastName><ForeName>Pei Hung</ForeName><Initials>PH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, National Taipei University of Nursing and Health Sciences, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">38028</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Hsiang Wei</ForeName><Initials>HW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Technology and Device Research Laboratories, Industrial Technology Research Institute, Hsinchu, Taiwan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">427095</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wei</LastName><ForeName>Shiow-Jing</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, National Taipei University of Nursing and Health Sciences, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">38028</Identifier></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>* Current affiliation: Department of Information and Communications Research Laboratories, Industrial Technology Research Institute, Hsinchu, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Shu Wen</ForeName><Initials>SW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0044-5750</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, National Taipei University of Nursing and Health Sciences, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">38028</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Digit Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101690863</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2055-2076</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AI prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent birth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">reproductive health services</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20552076241292675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_20552076241292675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO. Adolescent pregnancy. 2022. 
https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/adolescent-pregnancy
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wado YD, Sully EA, Mumah JN. Pregnancy and early motherhood among adolescents in five East African countries: a multi-level analysis of risk and protective factors. BMC Pregn Childb 2019; 19: 1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6366026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30727995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zulaika G, Bulbarelli M, Nyothach E, et al. Impact of COVID-19 lockdowns on adolescent pregnancy and school dropout among secondary schoolgirls in Kenya. BMJ Global Health 2022; 7: e007666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8761596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35027438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Branje S, Morris AS. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on adolescent emotional, social, and academic adjustment. J Res Adolesc 2021; 31: 486–499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34448306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serlachius A, Badawy SM, Thabrew H. Psychosocial challenges and opportunities for youth with chronic health conditions during the COVID-19 pandemic. JMIR Pediatr Parent 2020; 3: e23057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33001834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cousins S. COVID-19 has “devastating” effect on women and girls. Lancet 2020; 396: 301–302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32738942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sezgin AU, Punamäki R-L. Impacts of early marriage and adolescent pregnancy on mental and somatic health: the role of partner violence. Arch Women’s Ment Health 2020; 23: 155–166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7183488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30955087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diabelková J, Rimárová K, Dorko E, et al. Adolescent pregnancy outcomes and risk factors. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2023; 20: 4113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10002018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36901128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macedo TC, Montagna E, Trevisan CM, et al. Prevalence of preeclampsia and eclampsia in adolescent pregnancy: a systematic review and meta-analysis of 291,247 adolescents worldwide since 1969. Eur J Obstetr Gynecol Reprod Biol 2020; 248: 177–186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32283429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeMarco N, Twynstra J, Ospina MB, et al. Prevalence of low birth weight, premature birth, and stillbirth among pregnant adolescents in Canada: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Pediatr Adolesc Gynecol 2021; 34: 530–537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33727190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marvin-Dowle K, Soltani H. A comparison of neonatal outcomes between adolescent and adult mothers in developed countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur J Obstetr Gynecol Reprod Biol: X 2020; 6: 100109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7152816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32300758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eliner Y, Gulersen M, Kasar A, et al. Maternal and neonatal complications in teen pregnancies: a comprehensive study of 661,062 patients. J Adolesc Health 2022; 70: 922–927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35165030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karaçam Z, Çakaloz DK, Demir R. The impact of adolescent pregnancy on maternal and infant health in Turkey: systematic review and meta-analysis. J Gynecol Obstetr Human Reprod 2021; 50: 102093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33592347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunthorn W, Thapinta D, Panuthai Set al. et al. Factors explaining postpartum depression among Thai adolescent mothers. Pac Rim Int J Nurs Res Thail 2021; 25: 48–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budak MS, Akgol S. Investigation of adolescent pregnancy outcomes and postpartum depression frequency and risk factors: prospective case control study. Gynecol Obstetr Reprod Med 2020; 26: 94–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangsawang B, Wacharasin C, Sangsawang N. Interventions for the prevention of postpartum depression in adolescent mothers: a systematic review. Arch Womens Ment Health 2019; 22: 215–228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30116896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hymas R, Girard L-C. Predicting postpartum depression among adolescent mothers: a systematic review of risk. J Affect Disord 2019; 246: 873–885.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30795494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekonnen T, Dune T, Perz J. Maternal health service utilisation of adolescent women in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic scoping review. BMC Pregn Childb 2019; 19: 1–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6805384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31638927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adu PA, Stallwood L, Adebola SO, et al. The direct and indirect impact of COVID-19 pandemic on maternal and child health services in Africa: a scoping review. Global Health Res Policy 2022; 7: 1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9296365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35854345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justice M. The legal age of adulthood has been lowered to 18 years old. 2023. https://www.moj.gov.tw/2204/2795/2796/134595/post.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiang T. Health Care Reform. Health Care Policy in East Asia: A World Scientific Reference: Volume 4: Health Care System Reform and Policy Research in Taiwan: World Scientific; 2020. pp.15–30. 1995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Administration HP. Maternal Health Handbook. Taipei, Taiwan: Health Promotion Administration; 2022. https://www.hpa.gov.tw/File/Attach/16398/File_20261.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Household Registration Affairs. Fertility rates of childbearing age women Taipei. Taipei, Taiwan: Department of Household Registration Affairs, MOI, 2023. 
https://www.ris.gov.tw/app/portal/346
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of the Interior T. Fertility Rates of Childbearing Age Women: Dept. of Household Registration; 2023. https://www.ris.gov.tw/app/en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Promotion Administration. 2022 statistics of birth reporting system. Taipei, Taiwan: Ministry of Health and Welfare, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CJ, Ng CY, Brook RH. Response to COVID-19 in Taiwan: big data analytics, new technology, and proactive testing. JAMA 2020; 323: 1341–1342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32125371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao S-C, Chang Y-S, Chien L-Y. The maternity response to COVID-19: an example from one maternity unit in Taiwan. Midwifery 2020; 88: 102756.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7235558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32591236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang M-T, Liang Y-L, Chen T-S, et al. Setting up a specialized maternity unit in a tertiary hospital: an oasis for pregnant women with COVID-19 during the pandemic. Taiwan J Obstet Gynecol 2023; 62: 823–829.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38008500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kons K, Biney AA, Sznajder K. Factors associated with adolescent pregnancy in sub-Saharan Africa during the COVID-19 pandemic: a review of socioeconomic influences and essential interventions. Int J Sex Health 2022; 34: 386–396.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10903609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38596281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramaiya A, Chandra-Mouli V, Both R, et al. Assessing the health, social, educational and economic impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on adolescents in low- and middle-income countries: a rapid review of the literature. Sex Reprod Health Matters 2023; 31: 2187170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10062253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36987980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szucs LE, Pampati S, Li J, et al. Role of the COVID-19 pandemic on sexual behaviors and receipt of sexual and reproductive health services among US high school students—youth risk behavior survey, United States, 2019–2021. MMWR Suppl 2023; 72: 55–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10156159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37104536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oppong FB, Logo DD, Agbedra SY, et al. Determinants of contraceptive use among sexually active unmarried adolescent girls and young women aged 15–24 years in Ghana: a nationally representative cross-sectional study. BMJ Open 2021; 11: e043890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7925931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33550261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machira K, Palamuleni ME. Health care factors influencing teen mothers’ use of contraceptives in Malawi. Ghana Med J 2017; 51: 88–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5611910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28955105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Der AD, Anaman-Torgbor JA, Charles-Unadike VOet al. et al. Predictors of intention to use modern contraceptives among female senior secondary school students in the Kpando Municipality, Ghana. Afr Health Sci 2021; 21: 1375–1384.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8843303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35222603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Household Registration Affairs. Birth number based on maternal age and parity. Taipei, Taiwan: Department of Household Registration Affairs, MOI, 2021. 
https://www.ris.gov.tw/app/portal/346
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shikuku DN, Nyaoke IK, Nyaga LNet al. et al. Early indirect impact of COVID-19 pandemic on utilisation and outcomes of reproductive, maternal, newborn, child and adolescent health services in Kenya: a cross-sectional study. Afr J Reprod Health 2021; 25: 76–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37585823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li SH, Beames JR, Newby JM, et al. The impact of COVID-19 on the lives and mental health of Australian adolescents. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry 2022; 31: 1465–1477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8080862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33913036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rose SB, Garrett SM, McKinlay EMet al. et al. Access to sexual healthcare during New Zealand’s COVID-19 lockdown: cross-sectional online survey of 15–24-year-olds in a high deprivation region. BMJ Sex Reprod Health 2021; 47: 277–284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33737316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buzzi C, Tucci M, Ciprandi R, et al. The psycho-social effects of COVID-19 on Italian adolescents’ attitudes and behaviors. Ital J Pediatr 2020; 46: –7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7245982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32448323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen YJ. Analysis of the causes and risk factors of infant death in Taiwan. Hualien, Taiwan: Tzu Chi University, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karataşlı V, Kanmaz AG, İnan AH, et al. Maternal and neonatal outcomes of adolescent pregnancy. J Gynecol Obstetr Human Reprod 2019; 48: 347–350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30794955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siu WHS, Li PR, See LC. Rate of condom use among sexually active adolescents: a nationwide cross-sectional study in Taiwan from 2012 to 2016. BMJ Open 2021; 11: e047727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8372875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34404704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SH, Yen CH, Wu WYet al. et al. A review on adolescent childbearing in Taiwan: its characteristics, outcomes and risks. Asia Pacific J Public Health 2007; 19: 40–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17784658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma CM. The relationship between social support and life satisfaction among Chinese and ethnic minority adolescents in Hong Kong: the mediating role of positive youth development. Child Indic Res 2020; 13: 659–679.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee FC, Chen YY. A study of the adolescent experience in induced abortion. Formosan J Sex 2006; 12: 25–40.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>