<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469435</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2813-0146</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in health services</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Health Serv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multi-level barriers and facilitators to implementing evidence-based antipsychotics in the treatment of early-phase schizophrenia.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1385398</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1385398</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1385398</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/frhs.2024.1385398</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Long-acting injectable (LAI) antipsychotic medications and clozapine are effective yet underutilized medical therapies in early intervention services. The purpose of this study was to conduct a pre-implementation evaluation of contextual determinants of early intervention programs to implement innovations optimizing LAI antipsychotic and clozapine use within a shared decision-making model.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Semi-structured interviews explored barriers and facilitators to implementing LAI antipsychotics and clozapine in early intervention services. Participants were: prescribers (<i>n</i> = 2), non-prescribing clinicians (<i>n</i> = 5), administrators (<i>n</i> = 3), clients (<i>n</i> = 3), and caregivers (<i>n</i> = 3). Interviews were structured and analyzed using the Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research (CFIR 2.0).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Participants were supportive of using LAI antipsychotics, despite barriers (e.g., transportation, insurance coverage), while most were unfamiliar with clozapine (Innovation). Critical incidents (e.g., COVID-19) did not interfere with implementation, while barriers included lack of performance measures; stigma affecting willingness to take medication; and clozapine considered to be a "last resort" (Outer Setting). Treatment culture was described as client-centered and collaborative, and most participants indicated LAI antipsychotic use was compatible with clinic workflows, but some were in need of resources (e.g., individuals trained to administer LAI antipsychotics; Inner Setting). Participants on the healthcare team expressed confidence in their roles. Family education and collaborative decision-making were recommended to improve client/family engagement (Individuals). Participants related the importance of tracking medication compliance, addressing client concerns, and providing prescribers with updated guidelines on evidence-based treatment (Implementation Process).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Results may guide implementation strategy selection for future programs seeking to optimize the use of LAI antipsychotics and clozapine for early-phase schizophrenia, when appropriate.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Carroll, Robinson, Kane, Kordon, Bannon, Walunas and Brown.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carroll</LastName><ForeName>Allison J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences and Center for Dissemination and Implementation Science, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Robinson</LastName><ForeName>Delbert G</ForeName><Initials>DG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Behavioral Science, Feinstein Institutes for Medical Research, Northwell Health, Manhasset, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Psychiatry and of Molecular Medicine, The Donald and Barbara Zucker School of Medicine at Hofstra/Northwell, Hempstead, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kane</LastName><ForeName>John M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Behavioral Science, Feinstein Institutes for Medical Research, Northwell Health, Manhasset, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Psychiatry and of Molecular Medicine, The Donald and Barbara Zucker School of Medicine at Hofstra/Northwell, Hempstead, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kordon</LastName><ForeName>Avram</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bannon</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Health Information Partnerships, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walunas</LastName><ForeName>Theresa L</ForeName><Initials>TL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine and Center for Health Information Partnerships, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brown</LastName><ForeName>C Hendricks</ForeName><Initials>CH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences and Center for Dissemination and Implementation Science, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Health Serv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918334887706676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2813-0146</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antipsychotic medication</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">consolidated framework for implementation research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coordinated specialty care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">implementation determinants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">patient perspective</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">schizophrenia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">stakeholder engagement</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11513390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/frhs.2024.1385398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Correll CU, Galling B, Pawar A, Krivko A, Bonetto C, Ruggeri M, et al. Comparison of early intervention services vs treatment as usual for early-phase psychosis: a systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression. JAMA Psychiatry. (2018) 75(6):555–65. 10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2018.0623</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2018.0623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6137532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29800949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nordentoft M, Rasmussen JØ, Melau M, Hjorthøj CR, Thorup AAE. How successful are first episode programs? A review of the evidence for specialized assertive early intervention. Curr Opin Psychiatry. (2014) 27(3):167–72. 10.1097/YCO.0000000000000052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/YCO.0000000000000052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24662959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keepers GA, Fochtmann LJ, Anzia JM, Benjamin S, Lyness JM, Mojtabai R, et al. The American psychiatric association practice guideline for the treatment of patients with Schizophrenia. Am J Psychiatry. (2020) 177(9):868–72. 10.1176/appi.ajp.2020.177901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2020.177901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32867516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kane JM, Schooler NR, Marcy P, Correll CU, Achtyes ED, Gibbons RD, et al. Effect of long-acting injectable antipsychotics vs usual care on time to first hospitalization in early-phase schizophrenia: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Psychiatry. (2020) 77(12):1217–24. 10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2020.2076</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2020.2076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7364341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32667636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirson NY, Weiden PJ, Yermakov S, Huang W, Samuelson T, Offord SJ, et al. Efficacy and effectiveness of depot versus oral antipsychotics in schizophrenia: synthesizing results across different research designs. J Clin Psychiatry. (2013) 74(6):568–75. 10.4088/JCP.12r08167</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.12r08167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23842008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin D, Thompson-Leduc P, Ghelerter I, Nguyen H, Lafeuille M-H, Benson C, et al. Real-world evidence of the clinical and economic impact of long-acting injectable versus oral antipsychotics among patients with schizophrenia in the United States: a systematic review and meta-analysis. CNS Drugs. (2021) 35(5):469–81. 10.1007/s40263-021-00815-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40263-021-00815-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8144083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33909272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kane JM, Schooler NR, Marcy P, Achtyes ED, Correll CU, Robinson DG. Patients with early-phase schizophrenia will accept treatment with sustained-release medication (long-acting injectable antipsychotics): results from the recruitment phase of the PRELAPSE trial. J Clin Psychiatry. (2019) 80(3):18m12546. 10.4088/JCP.18m12546</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.18m12546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31050233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernardo M, San L, Olivares JM, Dilla T, Polavieja P, Gilaberte I, et al. Treatment patterns and health care resource utilization in a 1-year observational cohort study of outpatients with schizophrenia at risk of nonadherence treated with long-acting injectable antipsychotics. Patient Prefer Adherence. (2011) 5:601–10. 10.2147/PPA.S26253</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/PPA.S26253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3259075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22259237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcus SC, Zummo J, Pettit AR, Stoddard J, Doshi JA. Antipsychotic adherence and rehospitalization in schizophrenia patients receiving oral versus long-acting injectable antipsychotics following hospital discharge. J Manag Care Spec Pharm. (2015) 21(9):754–68. 10.18553/jmcp.2015.21.9.754</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18553/jmcp.2015.21.9.754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10398026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26308223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howes OD, McCutcheon R, Agid O, de Bartolomeis A, van Beveren NJ, Birnbaum ML, et al. Treatment-resistant schizophrenia: treatment response and resistance in psychosis (TRRIP) working group consensus guidelines on diagnosis and terminology. Am J Psychiatry. (2017) 174(3):216–29. 10.1176/appi.ajp.2016.16050503</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2016.16050503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6231547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27919182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thien K, Bowtell M, Eaton S, Bardell-Williams M, Downey L, Ratheesh A, et al. Clozapine use in early psychosis. Schizophr Res. (2018) 199:374–9. 10.1016/j.schres.2018.02.054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2018.02.054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29525463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams R, Malla A, Roy MA, Joober R, Manchanda R, Tibbo P, et al. What is the place of clozapine in the treatment of early psychosis in Canada? Can J Psychiatry. (2017) 62(2):109–14. 10.1177/0706743716651049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0706743716651049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5298522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27310245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi W, She S, Zhang J, Wu H, Zheng Y, Ning Y. Clozapine use in patients with early-stage schizophrenia in a Chinese psychiatric hospital. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. (2020) 16:2827–36. 10.2147/NDT.S261503</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/NDT.S261503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7699990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33262597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warnez S, Alessi-Severini S. Clozapine: a review of clinical practice guidelines and prescribing trends. BMC Psychiatry. (2014) 14:102. 10.1186/1471-244X-14-102</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-14-102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3999500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24708834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokes I, Griffiths SL, Jones R, Everard L, Jones PB, Fowler D, et al. Prevalence of treatment resistance and clozapine use in early intervention services. BJPsych Open. (2020) 6(5):e107. 10.1192/bjo.2020.89</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjo.2020.89</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7576650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32938513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz S, Carilli C, Mian T, Ruekert L, Kumar A. Attitudes and perceptions about the use of long-acting injectable antipsychotics among behavioral health practitioners. Ment Health Clin. (2022) 12(4):232–40. 10.9740/mhc.2022.08.232</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9740/mhc.2022.08.232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9405628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36071741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kane JM, McEvoy JP, Correll CU, Llorca PM. Controversies surrounding the use of long-acting injectable antipsychotic medications for the treatment of patients with schizophrenia. CNS Drugs. (2021) 35(11):1189–205. 10.1007/s40263-021-00861-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40263-021-00861-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8551124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34636025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma M, Grover S, Chakrabarti S, Dua D. Attitude towards and experience with clozapine of patients and their caregivers after three months of starting of clozapine. Nord J Psychiatry. (2021) 75(5):336–43. 10.1080/08039488.2020.1857832</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08039488.2020.1857832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33372832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parkes S, Mantell B, Oloyede E, Blackman G. Patients’ experiences of clozapine for treatment-resistant schizophrenia: a systematic review. Schizophr Bull Open. (2022) 3(1):sgac042. 10.1093/schizbullopen/sgac042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/schizbullopen/sgac042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11205966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39144802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung JG, Cusimano J, Gannon JM, Milgrom O, Valcourt SC, Stoklosa JB, et al. Addressing clozapine under-prescribing and barriers to initiation: a psychiatrist, advanced practice provider, and trainee survey. Int Clin Psychopharmacol. (2019) 34(5):247–56. 10.1097/YIC.0000000000000269</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/YIC.0000000000000269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31107831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nielsen J, Dahm M, Lublin H, Taylor D. Psychiatrists’ attitude towards and knowledge of clozapine treatment. J Psychopharmacol. (2010) 24(7):965–71. 10.1177/0269881108100320</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0269881108100320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19164499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oloyede E, Blackman G, Mantell B, Harris E, Williams J, Taylor D, et al. What are the barriers and facilitators of clozapine use in early psychosis? A survey of UK early intervention clinicians. Schizophrenia. (2023) 9(1):26. 10.1038/s41537-023-00353-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41537-023-00353-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10147630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moullin JC, Dickson KS, Stadnick NA, Albers B, Nilsen P, Broder-Fingert S, et al. Ten recommendations for using implementation frameworks in research and practice. Implement Sci Commun. (2020) 1(1):42. 10.1186/s43058-020-00023-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s43058-020-00023-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7427911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32885199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damschroder LJ, Reardon CM, Widerquist MAO, Lowery J. The updated consolidated framework for implementation research based on user feedback. Implement Sci. (2022) 17(1):75. 10.1186/s13012-022-01245-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13012-022-01245-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9617234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36309746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skolarus TA, Lehmann T, Tabak RG, Harris J, Lecy J, Sales AE. Assessing citation networks for dissemination and implementation research frameworks. Implement Sci. (2017) 12(1):97. 10.1186/s13012-017-0628-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13012-017-0628-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5534119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28754140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hennink M, Kaiser BN. Sample sizes for saturation in qualitative research: a systematic review of empirical tests. Soc Sci Med. (2022) 292:114523. 10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.114523</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.114523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34785096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton AB. Qualitative methods in rapid turn-around health services research. VA Womens Health Res Netw. (2013). Available online at: https://www.hsrd.research.va.gov/for_researchers/cyber_seminars/archives/video_archive.cfm?SessionID=780</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neal JW, Neal ZP, VanDyke E, Kornbluh M. Expediting the analysis of qualitative data in evaluation: a procedure for the rapid identification of themes from audio recordings (RITA). Am J Eval. (2015) 36(1):118–32. 10.1177/1098214014536601</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1098214014536601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oloyede E, Mantell B, Williams J, Lai S, Jauhar S, Taylor D, et al. Clozapine for treatment resistance in early psychosis: a survey of UK clinicians’ training, knowledge and confidence. Ther Adv Psychopharmacol. (2022) 12:20451253221141222. 10.1177/20451253221141222</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20451253221141222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9806412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36601352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farooq S, Choudry A, Cohen D, Naeem F, Ayub M. Barriers to using clozapine in treatment-resistant schizophrenia: systematic review. BJPsych Bull. (2019) 43(1):8–16. 10.1192/bjb.2018.67</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjb.2018.67</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6327301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30261942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakofsky JJ, Talbot TB, Dunlop BW. A virtual standardized patient–based assessment tool to evaluate psychiatric Residents’ psychopharmacology proficiency. Acad Psychiatry. (2020) 44(6):693–700. 10.1007/s40596-020-01286-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40596-020-01286-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7367158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32681418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizzo A, Thomas Koenig S, Talbot TB. Clinical results using virtual reality. J Technol Hum Serv. (2019) 37(1):51–74. 10.1080/15228835.2019.1604292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15228835.2019.1604292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizzo AS, Koenig ST, Talbot TB. Clinical virtual reality: emerging opportunities for psychiatry. FOCUS. (2018) 16(3):266–78. 10.1176/appi.focus.20180011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.focus.20180011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6493092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31975921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wheeler A, Humberstone V, Robinson E, Sheridan J, Joyce P. Impact of audit and feedback on antipsychotic prescribing in schizophrenia. J Eval Clin Pract. (2009) 15(3):441–50. 10.1111/j.1365-2753.2008.01032.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2753.2008.01032.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19366393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snider MDH, Boyd MR, Walker MR, Powell BJ, Lewis CC. Using audit and feedback to guide tailored implementations of measurement-based care in community mental health: a multiple case study. Implement Sci Commun. (2023) 4(1):94. 10.1186/s43058-023-00474-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s43058-023-00474-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10424451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37580815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilbourne AM, Geng E, Eshun-Wilson I, Sweeney S, Shelley D, Cohen DJ, et al. How does facilitation in healthcare work? Using mechanism mapping to illuminate the black box of a meta-implementation strategy. Implement Sci Commun. (2023) 4(1):53. 10.1186/s43058-023-00435-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s43058-023-00435-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10190070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37194084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. Practice Facilitation Rockville, MDContent last reviewed February 2023. Available online at:
https://www.ahrq.gov/evidencenow/practice-facilitation/index.html (Accessed February 01, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walunas TL, Ye J, Bannon J, Wang A, Kho AN, Smith JD, et al. Does coaching matter? Examining the impact of specific practice facilitation strategies on implementation of quality improvement interventions in the healthy hearts in the heartland study. Implement Sci. (2021) 16(1):33. 10.1186/s13012-021-01100-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13012-021-01100-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8011080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33789696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siantz E, Redline B, Henwood B. Practice facilitation in integrated behavioral health and primary care settings: a scoping review. J Behav Health Serv Res. (2021) 48(1):133–55. 10.1007/s11414-020-09709-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11414-020-09709-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32458281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>