<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39464416</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2214-9996</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>90</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Annals of global health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ann Glob Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Social and Behavioural Change Communication Challenges, Opportunities and Lessons from Past Public Health Emergencies and Disease Outbreaks: A Scoping Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>62</StartPage><MedlinePgn>62</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">62</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5334/aogh.4418</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><i>Background:</i> Documentation of social behavioural change communication (SBCC) regarding challenges, opportunities and lessons drawn from past public health emergencies is worthwhile to inform priorities for future response efforts. <i>Aim:</i> The aim of this review is to scope the evidence on social behavioural change communication regarding challenges, opportunities and lessons drawn from Ebola, coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), monkeypox and cholera outbreaks from studies published before March 2024, and suggest priorities for future response efforts. <i>Methods:</i> A Boolean strategy was used to search electronic databases for relevant published articles, complemented by relevant studies identified from reference lists. <i>Results:</i> The challenges, opportunities, lessons learnt and priorities for SBCC were consistent across study contexts, showing marked variations over time. The significance of technology, infodemic management, and behavioural data generation emerged more frequently and became increasingly important over time. Identified challenges were uptake hesitancy, limited capacity to undertake infodemic management, inadequate funding and human resources for SBCC, competing priorities, parallel or conflicting interventions due to inadequate coordination, difficulties evaluating SBCC programmes and missed opportunities for integration into routine programmes. Existing supportive structures for SBCC, strong political will and participation, as well as rapid information exchange enabled by technological advancement, represented opportunities for enhancing the effectiveness of SBCC programmes. Key lessons were that a multisectoral approach and coordination, partnership and active collaboration amongst stakeholders; building/strengthening trust, target population segmentation and localization of interventions, are important for enhancing the effectiveness of SBCC programmes. Political will, involvement and participation represent the core of social behavioural change (communication) interventions during a public health emergency. <i>Conclusion:</i> SBCC programming for future response to public health emergencies and disease outbreaks should consider the diverse assortment of benefits, threats/challenges and opportunities brought about by technology, infodemics and behavioural data generation to be more effective.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gonah</LastName><ForeName>Laston</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6070-2176</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Walter Sisulu University, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nomatshila</LastName><ForeName>Sibusiso Cyprian</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4130-0707</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Walter Sisulu University, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Ann Glob Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101620864</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2214-9996</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="Y">Public Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003142" MajorTopicYN="N">Communication</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004630" MajorTopicYN="N">Emergencies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012919" MajorTopicYN="N">Social Behavior</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cholera</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ebola</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Monkeypox</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health emergencies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social Behavioural Change (Communication)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11505028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5334/aogh.4418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Managing epidemics: Key facts about major deadly diseases. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obregón R, Lapsansky C. Building capacity in communication for development and health promotion. Handbook of Communication and Development. 2021:262.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matta G. Science communication as a preventative tool in the COVID19 pandemic. Humanit Soc Sci Commun. 2020;7(1):1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonah L, Kobie AG. Framework for risk communication and community engagement to improve vaccine uptake for COVID‑19 and other vaccine‑preventable diseases in low‑and middle‑income countries (LMIC). Ann Glob Health. 2021;87(1):123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8663749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34963879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonah L. Key considerations for successful risk communication and community engagement (RCCE) programmes during COVID‑19 pandemic and other public health emergencies. Ann Glob Health. 2020;86(1):146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7678561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33262935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samson D, Schoelles KM. Developing the topic and structuring systematic reviews of medical tests: Utility of PICOTS, analytic frameworks, decision trees, and other frameworks. Methods Guide for Medical Test Reviews [Internet]. 2012;27:11–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3364354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22648670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong WC, Cheung CS, Hart GJ. Development of a quality assessment tool for systematic reviews of observational studies (QATSO) of HIV prevalence in men having sex with men and associated risk behaviours. Emerg Themes Epidemiol. 2008;5:1–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2603000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19014686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher D, Liberati A, Tetzlaff J, Altman DG, PRISMA Group. Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta‑analyses: The PRISMA statement. Ann Intern Med. 2009;151(4):264–269. doi:10.7326/0003-4819-151-4-200908180-00135</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-151-4-200908180-00135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19622511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdulkareem SA, Augustijn EW, Filatova T, Musial K, Mustafa YT. Risk perception and behavioral change during epidemics: Comparing models of individual and collective learning. PloS one. 2020;15(1):e0226483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6944362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31905206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brainard J, Hunter PR. Misinformation making a disease outbreak worse: Outcomes compared for influenza, monkeypox, and norovirus. Simulation. 2020;96(4):365–374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8282656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34285423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickey C, Holzman E, Bedford J, et al. Behavioral communication strategies for global epidemics: An Innovative model for public health education and humanitarian response. Health Promot Pract. 2021;22(4):448–452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32295427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amaechi UA, Sodipo BO, Nnaji CA, et al. Social approaches to COVID‑19 pandemic response: Effectiveness and practicality in sub‑Saharan Africa. Pan Afr Med J. 2020;37(Suppl 1):2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7704349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33294103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt‑Sane M, Abbas S, Karam S, Palmer J. RCCE strategies for monkeypox response. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samhouri D, Aynsley TR, Hanna P, et al. Risk communication and community engagement capacity in the Eastern Mediterranean Region: A call for action. BMJ Global Health. 2024;7(Suppl 3):e008652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10910584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38423542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia‑Iglesias J, May T, Pickersgill M. Social media as a public health tool during the UK monkeypox outbreak: A qualitative study of stakeholders’ experiences. BMJ Public Health. 2023;1(1):e000407.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirani R, Noruzi K, Iqbal A, et al. A review of the past, present, and future of the monkeypox virus: Challenges, opportunities, and lessons from COVID‑19 for global health security. Microorganisms. 2023;11(11):2713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10673257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38004725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collins J, Westerveld R, Nelson KA, et al. ‘Learn from the lessons and don’t forget them’: identifying transferable lessons for COVID‑19 from meningitis A, yellow fever and Ebola virus disease vaccination campaigns. BMJ Glob Health. 2021;6(9):e006951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8450956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34535490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Song W, Wang Y, et al. Monkeypox knowledge investigation and knowledge gap analysis: An online cross‑sectional survey in China. Risk Manag Healthc Policy. 2023;16:2741–2756.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10725750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38107440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aduh U, Folayan MO, Afe A. Risk perception, public health interventions, and COVID‑19 pandemic control in sub‑Saharan Africa. J Public Health Africa. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardon A, Maisonnave E, Richard JB, et al. Rapid response to efficiently counter cholera: Lessons from a 45‑days intervention in Eastern DRC. PLoS One. 2018;13(5):1–5. Accessed 5 November 2022. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0266849</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0266849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White S, Mutula AC, Buroko MM, et al. How does handwashing behaviour change in response to a cholera outbreak? A qualitative case study in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. PloS One. 2022;17(4):e0266849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9004767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35413080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marston C, Renedo A, Miles S. Community participation is crucial in a pandemic. Lancet. 2020;395(10238):1676–1678.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7198202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32380042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awadi S, Al‑Shami K, Alkhoun H. A, Al‑Eitan S. F, Alsheikh A. M, Saeed A, Al Zoubi M. S. Human monkeypox virus in the shadow of the COVID‑19 pandemic. Journal of infection and public health. 2023;16(8):1149–1157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10182868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37269693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyekan AO. Conspiracy theories and pandemic management in Africa: Critical reflections on contexts, contradictions and challenges. Acta Academica. 2021;53(2):38–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lak A, Asl SS, Maher A. Resilient urban form to pandemics: Lessons from COVID‑19. Med J Islamic Repub Iran. 2020;34:71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7711032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33306051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owoyemi A, Okolie EA, Omitiran K. Importance of community‑level interventions during the COVID‑19 pandemic: Lessons from sub‑Saharan Africa. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2021;105(4):879–884.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8592170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34370697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tusabe F, Tahir IM, Akpa CI. Lessons learned from the Ebola virus disease and COVID‑19 preparedness to respond to the human monkeypox virus outbreak in low‑and middle‑income countries. Infect Drug Resist. 2022;15:6279–6286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9624151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36329989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lilleker D, Coman IA, Gregor M, et al. Political communication and COVID‑19: Governance and rhetoric in global comparative perspective. In Political Communication and COVID‑19. Routledge; 2021;333–350.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weintraub RL, Subramanian L, Karlage A, et al. COVID‑19 vaccine to vaccination: Why leaders must invest in delivery strategies now: Analysis describe lessons learned from past pandemics and vaccine campaigns about the path to successful vaccine delivery for COVID‑19. Health Aff. 2021;40(1):33–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33211554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kruk ME, Myers M, Varpilah ST, et al. What is a resilient health system? Lessons from Ebola. Lancet. 2015;385(9980):1910–1912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25987159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kieny MP, Dovlo D. Beyond Ebola: A new agenda for resilient health systems. Lancet. 2015;385(9963):91–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5513100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25706456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jedwab R, Khan AM, Russ J. Epidemics, pandemics, and social conflict: Lessons from the past and possible scenarios for COVID‑19. World Dev. 2021;147:105629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8633882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34866756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mphande FA. Equitable health response: Lessons from COVID‑19 and monkeypox. In Sustainable Health in Low and Middle Income Countries: Achieving SDG3 in the (Post) Pandemic World. Singapore: Springer Nature Singapore; 2023;95–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roess AA, Monroe BP, Kinzoni EA, et al. Assessing the effectiveness of a community intervention for monkeypox prevention in the Congo basin. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2011;5(10):e1356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3196471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22028942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lappan S, Malaivijitnond S, Radhakrishna S, et al. The human–primate interface in the new normal: Challenges and opportunities for primatologists in the COVID‐19 era and beyond. Am J Primatol. 2020;82(8):e23176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7404331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32686188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Legros D. Global cholera epidemiology: Opportunities to reduce the burden of cholera by 2030. J Infect Dis. 2018;218(suppl 3):S137–S140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6207143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30184102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautier L, Houngbedji KA, Uwamaliya J. Use of a community‑led prevention strategy to enhance behavioral changes towards Ebola virus disease prevention: A qualitative case study in Western Côte d’ivoire. Glob Health Res Policy. 2017;2(35):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5741877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29299536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basseal JM, Bennett CM, Collignon P, et al. Key lessons from the COVID‑19 public health response in Australia. Lancet Reg Health West Pac. 2023;30:100616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9549254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36248767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>