<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464477</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2470-1343</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>42</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ACS omega</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ACS Omega</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multiomics Reveals a Mechanism: Glycogen Synthesis, Galactose Metabolism, and Ethanol Degradation Pathways, the Durable Role of Neutralizing Antibodies in Preventing COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>42757</StartPage><EndPage>42765</EndPage><MedlinePgn>42757-42765</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acsomega.4c04047</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Since the emergence and rapid dissemination of Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), over 774 million individuals globally have achieved recovery to today. There is some case flashing into here and there all over the world. Neutralizing Antibody (NAb) against Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-Type 2 (SARS-CoV-2) play a paramount role in conferring effective and lasting protection for several months. This protective effect decreases with time thus increasing the chance of reinfection. Therefore, we can provide the body with a lasting protective effect by maintaining NAb level. However, how to maintain Nab level remains elusive. To address this question, we recruited 80 patients with confirmed COVID-19 and collected 480 consecutive blood samples and performed NAb testing six months after their recovery. The NAb level were categorized into two groups: a low-titer NAb group (≤20) and a high-titer NAb group (&gt;20). To achieve a comprehensive understanding of the changes in NAb level, 16 serum samples were randomly selected for an untargeted metabolomic analysis, whereas 9 samples were designated for a label-free proteomic analysis. We successfully identified differentially expressed 751 metabolites and 845 proteins. In both the low and high NAb titer groups, we identified three key differential proteins, phosphoglucose translocase 2(PGM2), UDP-Glc 4-epimerase (GALE), and alcohol dehydrogenase 1B (ADH1B), that play important roles in fluctuating NAb level through the glycogen synthesis, galactose metabolism and ethanol degradation pathways. These three key differential proteins may serve as potential biomarkers for maintaining NAb level and enhancing immune protection in patients recovering from COVID-19.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Huayu</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Gongli Hospital of Shanghai Pudong New Area, 219 Miao Pu Road, Shanghai 200135, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Changzhi Medical College Affiliated Heping Hospital, Changzhi, Shanxi Province 046000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fan</LastName><ForeName>Linrui</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Prevention &amp; Healthcare, Gongli Hospital of Shanghai Pudong New Area, 219 Miao Pu Road, Shanghai 200135, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cao</LastName><ForeName>Feng</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Prevention &amp; Healthcare, Gongli Hospital of Shanghai Pudong New Area, 219 Miao Pu Road, Shanghai 200135, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Tong</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Peking Union Medical College, Beijing 100144, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Yujie</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Gongli Hospital of Shanghai Pudong New Area, 219 Miao Pu Road, Shanghai 200135, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Tao</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Gongli Hospital of Shanghai Pudong New Area, 219 Miao Pu Road, Shanghai 200135, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Changzhi Medical College Affiliated Heping Hospital, Changzhi, Shanxi Province 046000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Dan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shanghai AB Sciex Analytical Instrument Trading Co., Ltd., Shanghai 200050, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Hongzheng</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0005-0241-0067</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Gongli Hospital of Shanghai Pudong New Area, 219 Miao Pu Road, Shanghai 200135, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ACS Omega</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101691658</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2470-1343</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11500150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsomega.4c04047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>de Araújo G. R.; de Castro P.; Ávila I. R.; Bezerra J. M. T.; Barbosa D. S. Effects of public health emergencies of international concern on disease control: a systematic review. Rev. Panam Salud Publica 2023, 47, e7410.26633/RPSP.2023.74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26633/RPSP.2023.74</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10120386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37089787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakadia B. M.; He F.; Souho T.; Lamboni L.; Ullah M. W.; Boni B. O.; Ahmed A. A. Q.; Mukole B. M.; Yang G. Prevention and treatment of COVID-19: Focus on interferons, chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine, azithromycin, and vaccine. Biomed Pharmacother 2021, 133, 111008.10.1016/j.biopha.2020.111008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2020.111008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7831445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33227708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salian V. S.; Wright J. A.; Vedell P. T.; Nair S.; Li C.; Kandimalla M.; Tang X.; Carmona Porquera E. M.; Kalari K. R.; Kandimalla K. K. COVID-19 Transmission, Current Treatment, and Future Therapeutic Strategies. Mol. Pharmaceutics 2021, 18 (3), 754–771. 10.1021/acs.molpharmaceut.0c00608.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.molpharmaceut.0c00608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33464914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez-Leon S.; Wegman-Ostrosky T.; Perelman C.; Sepulveda R.; Rebolledo P. A.; Cuapio A.; Villapol S. More than 50 long-term effects of COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Sci. Rep. 2021, 11 (1), 16144.10.1038/s41598-021-95565-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-95565-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8352980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34373540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Morales A. J.; Lopez-Echeverri M. C.; Perez-Raga M. F.; Quintero-Romero V.; Valencia-Gallego V.; Galindo-Herrera N.; López-Alzate S.; Sánchez-Vinasco J. D.; Gutiérrez-Vargas J. J.; Mayta-Tristan P.; Husni R.; Moghnieh R.; Stephan J.; Faour W.; Tawil S.; Barakat H.; Chaaban T.; Megarbane A.; Rizk Y.; Sakr R.; Escalera-Antezana J. P.; Alvarado-Arnez L. E.; Bonilla-Aldana D. K.; Camacho-Moreno G.; Mendoza H.; Rodriguez-Sabogal I. A.; Millán-Oñate J.; Lopardo G.; Barbosa A. N.; Cimerman S.; Chaves T.; Orduna T.; Lloveras S.; Rodriguez-Morales A. G.; Thormann M.; Zambrano P. G.; Perez C.; Sandoval N.; Zambrano L.; Alvarez-Moreno C. A.; Chacon-Cruz E.; Villamil-Gomez W. E.; Benites-Zapata V.; Savio-Larriera E.; Cardona-Ospina J. A.; Risquez A.; Forero-Peña D. A.; Henao-Martínez A. F.; Sah R.; Barboza J. J.; León-Figueroa D. A.; Acosta-España J. D.; Carrero-Gonzalez C. M.; Al-Tawfiq J. A.; Rabaan A. A.; Leblebicioglu H.; Gonzales-Zamora J. A.; Ulloa-Gutiérrez R. The global challenges of the long COVID-19 in adults and children. Travel Med. Infect Dis 2023, 54, 102606.10.1016/j.tmaid.2023.102606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2023.102606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10247301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37295581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frigerio R.; Marusic C.; Villani M. E.; Lico C.; Capodicasa C.; Andreano E.; Paciello I.; Rappuoli R.; Salzano A. M.; Scaloni A.; Baschieri S.; Donini M. Production of two SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies with different potencies in Nicotiana benthamiana. Front Plant Sci. 2022, 13, 956741.10.3389/fpls.2022.956741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.956741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9484322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36131799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Kaabi N.; Zhang Y.; Xia S.; Yang Y.; Al Qahtani M. M.; Abdulrazzaq N.; Al Nusair M.; Hassany M.; Jawad J. S.; Abdalla J.; Hussein S. E.; Al Mazrouei S. K.; Al Karam M.; Li X.; Yang X.; Wang W.; Lai B.; Chen W.; Huang S.; Wang Q.; Yang T.; Liu Y.; Ma R.; Hussain Z. M.; Khan T.; Saifuddin Fasihuddin M.; You W.; Xie Z.; Zhao Y.; Jiang Z.; Zhao G.; Zhang Y.; Mahmoud S.; ElTantawy I.; Xiao P.; Koshy A.; Zaher W. A.; Wang H.; Duan K.; Pan A.; Yang X. Effect of 2 Inactivated SARS-CoV-2 Vaccines on Symptomatic COVID-19 Infection in Adults: A Randomized Clinical Trial. Jama 2021, 326 (1), 35–45. 10.1001/jama.2021.8565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.8565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8156175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34037666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suthar M. S.; Zimmerman M. G.; Kauffman R. C.; Mantus G.; Linderman S. L.; Hudson W. H.; Vanderheiden A.; Nyhoff L.; Davis C. W.; Adekunle O.; Affer M.; Sherman M.; Reynolds S.; Verkerke H. P.; Alter D. N.; Guarner J.; Bryksin J.; Horwath M. C.; Arthur C. M.; Saakadze N.; Smith G. H.; Edupuganti S.; Scherer E. M.; Hellmeister K.; Cheng A.; Morales J. A.; Neish A. S.; Stowell S. R.; Frank F.; Ortlund E.; Anderson E. J.; Menachery V. D.; Rouphael N.; Mehta A. K.; Stephens D. S.; Ahmed R.; Roback J. D.; Wrammert J. Rapid Generation of Neutralizing Antibody Responses in COVID-19 Patients. Cell Rep. Med. 2020, 1 (3), 100040.10.1016/j.xcrm.2020.100040.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.xcrm.2020.100040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7276302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32835303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cromer D.; Steain M.; Reynaldi A.; Schlub T. E.; Wheatley A. K.; Juno J. A.; Kent S. J.; Triccas J. A.; Khoury D. S.; Davenport M. P. Neutralising antibody titres as predictors of protection against SARS-CoV-2 variants and the impact of boosting: a meta-analysis. Lancet Microbe 2022, 3 (1), e52–e61. 10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00267-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00267-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8592563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34806056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dan J. M.; Mateus J.; Kato Y.; Hastie K. M.; Yu E. D.; Faliti C. E.; Grifoni A.; Ramirez S. I.; Haupt S.; Frazier A.; Nakao C.; Rayaprolu V.; Rawlings S. A.; Peters B.; Krammer F.; Simon V.; Saphire E. O.; Smith D. M.; Weiskopf D.; Sette A.; Crotty S., Immunological memory to SARS-CoV-2 assessed for up to 8 months after infection. Science 2021, 371 ( (6529), ).10.1126/science.abf4063</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abf4063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7919858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33408181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen B.; Yi X.; Sun Y.; Bi X.; Du J.; Zhang C.; Quan S.; Zhang F.; Sun R.; Qian L.; Ge W.; Liu W.; Liang S.; Chen H.; Zhang Y.; Li J.; Xu J.; He Z.; Chen B.; Wang J.; Yan H.; Zheng Y.; Wang D.; Zhu J.; Kong Z.; Kang Z.; Liang X.; Ding X.; Ruan G.; Xiang N.; Cai X.; Gao H.; Li L.; Li S.; Xiao Q.; Lu T.; Zhu Y.; Liu H.; Chen H.; Guo T. Proteomic and Metabolomic Characterization of COVID-19 Patient Sera. Cell 2020, 182 (1), 59–72. 10.1016/j.cell.2020.05.032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.05.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7254001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32492406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bojkova D.; Klann K.; Koch B.; Widera M.; Krause D.; Ciesek S.; Cinatl J.; Münch C. Proteomics of SARS-CoV-2-infected host cells reveals therapy targets. Nature 2020, 583 (7816), 469–472. 10.1038/s41586-020-2332-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2332-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32408336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almagro Armenteros J. J.; Sønderby C. K.; Sønderby S. K.; Nielsen H.; Winther O. DeepLoc: prediction of protein subcellular localization using deep learning. Bioinformatics 2017, 33 (21), 3387–3395. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btx431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btx431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29036616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones P.; Binns D.; Chang H. Y.; Fraser M.; Li W.; McAnulla C.; McWilliam H.; Maslen J.; Mitchell A.; Nuka G.; Pesseat S.; Quinn A. F.; Sangrador-Vegas A.; Scheremetjew M.; Yong S. Y.; Lopez R.; Hunter S. InterProScan 5: genome-scale protein function classification. Bioinformatics 2014, 30 (9), 1236–40. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3998142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24451626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finn R. D.; Coggill P.; Eberhardt R. Y.; Eddy S. R.; Mistry J.; Mitchell A. L.; Potter S. C.; Punta M.; Qureshi M.; Sangrador-Vegas A.; Salazar G. A.; Tate J.; Bateman A. The Pfam protein families database: towards a more sustainable future. Nucleic Acids Res. 2016, 44 (D1), D279–85. 10.1093/nar/gkv1344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4702930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26673716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan S.; Chao R. An Exploration of Osteosarcoma Metastasis Diagnostic Markers Based on Tumor-Associated Neutrophils. Discov Med. 2023, 35 (176), 300–311. 10.24976/Discov.Med.202335176.31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.24976/Discov.Med.202335176.31</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37272097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shannon P.; Markiel A.; Ozier O.; Baliga N. S.; Wang J. T.; Ramage D.; Amin N.; Schwikowski B.; Ideker T. Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks. Genome Res. 2003, 13 (11), 2498–504. 10.1101/gr.1239303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/gr.1239303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC403769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14597658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C. J.; Chao T. L.; Chang T. Y.; Hsiao C. C.; Lu D. C.; Chiang Y. W.; Lai G. C.; Tsai Y. M.; Fang J. T.; Ieong S.; Wang J. T.; Chang S. Y.; Chang S. C. Neutralizing Monoclonal Antibodies Inhibit SARS-CoV-2 Infection through Blocking Membrane Fusion. Microbiol Spectr 2022, 10 (2), e018142110.1128/spectrum.01814-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.01814-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9045258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35293796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwamoto C.; Lesteberg K. E.; Lamb M. M.; Calvimontes D. M.; Guo K.; Barrett B. S.; Mickens K. L.; Duca L. M.; Monzon J.; Chard A. N.; Guzman G.; Barrios E.; Rojop N.; Arias K.; Gomez M.; Paiz C.; Bolanos G. A.; Edwards K. M.; Zielinski Gutierrez E.; Azziz-Baumgartner E.; Asturias E. J.; Santiago M. L.; Beckham J. D.; Olson D. High SARS-CoV-2 Seroprevalence and Rapid Neutralizing Antibody Decline among Agricultural Workers in Rural Guatemala, June 2020-March 2021. Vaccines (Basel) 2022, 10 (7), 1160.10.3390/vaccines10071160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10071160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9323551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35891324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinç H.; Demirci M.; Özdemir Y. E.; Sirekbasan S.; Aktaş A. N.; Karaali R.; Tuyji Tok Y.; Özbey D.; Akçin R.; Gareayaghi N.; Kuşkucu M. A.; Midilli K.; Aygün G.; Sarıbaş S.; Kocazeybek B. Anti-SARS-CoV-2 IgG and Neutralizing Antibody Levels in Patients with Past COVID-19 Infection: A Longitudinal Study. Balkan Med. J. 2022, 39 (3), 172–177. 10.4274/balkanmedj.galenos.2022.2021-8-131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4274/balkanmedj.galenos.2022.2021-8-131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9136548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35378574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J.; Chen C.; Chen W.; Huang L.; Fu Z.; Ye K.; Lv L.; Nong Z.; Zhou X.; Lu W.; Zhong M. Proteomics and metabonomics analyses of Covid-19 complications in patients with pulmonary fibrosis. Sci. Rep 2021, 11 (1), 14601.10.1038/s41598-021-94256-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-94256-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8285535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34272434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H.; Hui P.; Uemoto Y.; Ding Y.; Yin Z.; Bao W. Metabolomic and Proteomic Profiling of Porcine Intestinal Epithelial Cells Infected with Porcine Epidemic Diarrhea Virus. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2023, 24 (6), 5071.10.3390/ijms24065071.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms24065071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10049511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36982147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi J.; Li Y.; Zhou X.; Zhang Q.; Ye X.; Wu Z.; Jiang X.; Yu H.; Shao L.; Ai J. W.; Zhang H.; Xu B.; Sun F.; Zhang W. Lactate dehydrogenase and susceptibility to deterioration of mild COVID-19 patients: a multicenter nested case-control study. BMC Med. 2020, 18 (1), 168.10.1186/s12916-020-01633-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12916-020-01633-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7268591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32493370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnan S.; Nordqvist H.; Ambikan A. T.; Gupta S.; Sperk M.; Svensson-Akusjärvi S.; Mikaeloff F.; Benfeitas R.; Saccon E.; Ponnan S. M.; Rodriguez J. E.; Nikouyan N.; Odeh A.; Ahlén G.; Asghar M.; Sällberg M.; Vesterbacka J.; Nowak P.; Végvári Á.; Sönnerborg A.; Treutiger C. J.; Neogi U. Metabolic Perturbation Associated With COVID-19 Disease Severity and SARS-CoV-2 Replication. Mol. Cell Proteomics 2021, 20, 100159.10.1016/j.mcpro.2021.100159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mcpro.2021.100159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8490130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34619366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansone L.; Briviba M.; Silamikelis I.; Terentjeva A.; Perkons I.; Birzniece L.; Rovite V.; Rozentale B.; Viksna L.; Kolesova O.; Klavins K.; Klovins J. Amino Acid Metabolism is Significantly Altered at the Time of Admission in Hospital for Severe COVID-19 Patients: Findings from Longitudinal Targeted Metabolomics Analysis. Microbiol Spectr 2021, 9 (3), e003382110.1128/spectrum.00338-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.00338-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8653833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34878333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan X.; Liu Z.; Poulsen K. L.; Wu X.; Miyata T.; Dasarathy S.; Rotroff D. M.; Nagy L. E. Alcohol Consumption Is Associated with Poor Prognosis in Obese Patients with COVID-19: A Mendelian Randomization Study Using UK Biobank. Nutrients 2021, 13 (5), 1592.10.3390/nu13051592.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13051592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8152000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34068824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friske M. M.; Spanagel R. Chronic alcohol consumption and COVID-19 infection risk: A narrative review. Alcohol Clin Exp Res. (Hoboken) 2023, 47 (4), 629–639. 10.1111/acer.15041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/acer.15041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36851826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>