<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39465923</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0970-2113</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>41</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Lung India : official organ of Indian Chest Society</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lung India</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effectiveness of pulmonary rehabilitation in post-COVID-19 patients: A pre- and post-interventional study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>435</StartPage><EndPage>441</EndPage><MedlinePgn>435-441</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/lungindia.lungindia_368_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The need of pulmonary rehabilitation (PR) for COVID-19 patients with long-term effects was desperately felt. The study's objective was to measure the effect of PR on functional capacity and health-related quality of life (HRQOL) in patients with post COVID conditions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Pulmonary medicine department of a teaching hospital conducted this pre-experimental study. The patient underwent a pre and post-assessment, including a six-minute walk test (6MWT) measuring distance, oxygen desaturation, pulse rate, and HRQOL. The intervention had six components; education to patients and caregivers, breathlessness relieving exercises, postural correction, aerobic training, strength training, and stretching exercises. These activities were carried out twice a week for eight weeks, supervised, unsupervised in homes, and a combination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study enrolled 155 post-COVID patients (Males, 102 and female, 53), out of which 28 (18.1%) had mild, 55 (35.5%) had moderate and 72 (46.5%) had severe COVID. Paired t-test showed improvement in resting pulse rate (P = 0.001) and resting oxygen saturation (P &lt; 0.0001). Distance walking for six minutes increased after rehabilitation (P &lt; 0.0001). After eight weeks of pulmonary rehabilitation, there was an improvement (P &lt; 0.001) in all domains of quality of life, that is, mobility, self-care, pain and discomfort, usual activity, sleep, anxiety and depression.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Pulmonary rehabilitation is beneficial for post-COVID patients in improving their quality of life and six-minute walk test parameters, resulting in improved functional capacity and overall quality of life.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Copyright: © 2024 Indian Chest Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bargaje</LastName><ForeName>Medha Deepak</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Bharati Vidyapeeth Deemed University, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Priyasha</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiotherapy, Bharati Hospital and Research Centre, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Londhe</LastName><ForeName>Jyoti Deepak</ForeName><Initials>JD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiotherapy, Bharati Hospital and Research Centre, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patil</LastName><ForeName>Sanjeevani Vishwanath</ForeName><Initials>SV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Bharati Vidyapeeth Deemed University, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anokar</LastName><ForeName>Anita Tulsiramji</ForeName><Initials>AT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Bharati Vidyapeeth Deemed University, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Doke</LastName><ForeName>Purwa Prakash</ForeName><Initials>PP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of General Medicine, Bharati Vidyapeeth Deemed University, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oswal</LastName><ForeName>Jitendra Shankarlal</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Bharati Hospital and Research Centre, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Doke</LastName><ForeName>Prakash Prabhakarrao</ForeName><Initials>PP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Bharati Vidyapeeth Deemed University, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rayamane</LastName><ForeName>Kranti Laxman</ForeName><Initials>KL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cipla Foundation, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sule</LastName><ForeName>Nachiket Sandeep</ForeName><Initials>NS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cipla Foundation, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deshpande</LastName><ForeName>Aruna Bhimsen</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Bharati Vidyapeeth Deemed University, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Lung India</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8405380</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0970-2113</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/lungindia.lungindia_368_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">01408641-202411000-00007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Spruit MA, Singh SJ, Garvey C, Zu Wallack R, Nici L, Rochester C, et al. An official American thoracic society/European respiratory society statement:Key concepts and advances in pulmonary rehabilitation. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2013;188:e13–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holland AE, Spruit MA, Troosters T, Puhan MA, Pepin V, Saey D, et al. An official European respiratory society/American thoracic society technical standard:Field walking tests in chronic respiratory disease. Eur Respir J 2014;44:1428–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swaminathan N, Jiandani M, Surendran PJ, Jacob P, Bhise A, Baxi G, et al. Beyond COVID-19:Evidence-based consensus statement on the role of physiotherapy in pulmonary rehabilitation in the Indian context. J Assoc Physicians India 2020;68:82–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19):Post COVID-19 condition [Internet. World Health Organisation 2022:1 Available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-post-covid-19-condition .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajkumar Tripathi A, Pinto L. Long COVID:“And the fire rages on.”. Lung India 2021;38:564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). Support for Rehabilitation after COVID-19- Related Illness 2020;22 Available from: https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/support-for-rehabilitation-self-management-after-covid-19-related-illness .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GOI-MOHFW. National Comprehensive Guidelines for Management of Post-COVID Sequelae [for doctors] 2021:1–36 Available from: https://dghs.gov.in/WriteReadData/News/2021100103571503818885-RESPIRATORY_MODULE.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Curci C, Pisano F, Bonacci E, Camozzi DM, Ceravolo C, Bergonzi R, et al. Early rehabilitation in post-acute COVID-19 patients:Data from an Italian COVID-19 Rehabilitation Unit and proposal of a treatment protocol. Eur J Phys Rehabil Med 2020;56:633–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>. Ministry of Health and Family Welfare India. AIIMS/ICMR-COVID-19 National Task Force/Joint Monitoring Group (Dte GHS) Ministry of Health &amp;Family Welfare, Government of India Mild disease Severe disease, 2021 2021 Available from: https://dghs.gov.in/WriteRead Data/ Orders /202104231216553337715COVIDManagementAlgorithm_22Apr21.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>. EuroQol Research Foundation. EQ-5D-Y-5L User Guide 2024 Available from: https://euroqol.org/information-and-support/documentation/user-guides .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holland AE, Singh SJ, Casaburi R, Clini E, Cox NS, Galwicki M, et al. Defining modern pulmonary rehabilitation:An official American thoracic society workshop report. Ann Am Thorac Soc 2021;18:E12–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>. ATS Statement. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2002;166:111–7 doi:10.1164/ajrccm. 166.1.at1102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nici L, Donner C, Wouters E, Zuwallack R, Ambrosino N, Bourbeau J, et al. American thoracic society/European respiratory society statement on pulmonary rehabilitation. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2006;173:1390–413.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma BB, Singh V. Pulmonary rehabilitation:An overview. Lung India 2011;28:276–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tozato C, Ferreira BFC, Dalavina JP, Molinari CV, Dos Santos Alves VL. Cardiopulmonary rehabilitation in post-COVID-19 patients:Case series. Rev Bras Ter Intensiva 2021;33:167–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodwin VA, Allan L, Bethel A, Cowley A, Cross JL, Day J, et al. Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID- 19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aytür YK, Köseoglu BF, Taşkıran ÖÖ, Gökkaya NKO, Delialioğlu SÜ, Tur BS, et al. Pulmonary rehabilitation principles in SARS-COV-2 infection (COVID-19):The revised guideline for the acute, subacute, and post-COVID-19 rehabilitation. Turkish J Phys Med Rehabil 2021;67:129–45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Debeuf R, Swinnen E, Plattiau T, De Smedt A, De Waele E, Roggeman S, Schiltz M, Beckwee D, De Keersmaecker E. Effect of physical therapy on impairments in COVID-19 patients from intensive care to home rehabilitation:A rapid review. Journal of rehabilitation medicine 2022;54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uppal H, Rai S. Rehabilitation during COVID-19 pandemic:An Indian perspective. Disaster Med Public Health Prep 2022;16:409–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P, Goswami SK. Pulmonary tele-rehabilitation in patients (post Covid-19) with respiratory complications:A randomized controlled trial. Indian J Physiother Occup Ther 2022;16:182–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Büsching G, Zhang Z, Schmid JP, Sigrist T, Khatami R. Effectiveness of pulmonary rehabilitation in severe and critically ill COVID-19 patients:A controlled study. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2021;18:8956.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Chikhanie Y, Veale D, Schoeffler M, Pepin JL, Verges S, Hérengt F. Effectiveness of pulmonary rehabilitation in COVID-19 respiratory failure patients post-ICU. Respiratory physiology &amp;neurobiology 2021;287:103639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gloeckl R, Leitl D, Jarosch I, Schneeberger T, Nell C, Stenzel N, et al. Benefits of pulmonary rehabilitation in covid-19 –A prospective observational cohort study. ERJ Open Res 2021;7 doi:10.1183/23120541.00108-2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/23120541.00108-2021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zampogna E, Paneroni M, Belli S, Aliani M, Gandolfo A, Visca D, et al. Pulmonary rehabilitation in patients recovering from COVID-19. Respiration 2021;100:416–22.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>