<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469438</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2813-0146</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in health services</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Health Serv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Recommendations for implementing digital alcohol interventions in primary care: lessons learned from a Norwegian feasibility study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1343568</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1343568</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1343568</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/frhs.2024.1343568</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Excessive alcohol consumption is a leading global risk factor for ill-health and premature death. Digital alcohol interventions can be effective at reducing alcohol consumption, but their widespread adoption is lagging behind. This study aimed to identify factors promoting or inhibiting the implementation of a digital alcohol intervention in Norwegian primary care, by using Normalization Process Theory (NPT).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A mixed methods feasibility study combining quantitative and qualitative methods. A digital alcohol intervention called "Endre" was implemented across four GP practices in Stavanger and Oslo. Usage of the intervention was logged on the digital platform. General practitioners (GPs) reported their perceived uptake of the intervention via a web-based survey. The Normalization MeAsure Development (NoMAD) survey was used to measure support staff's perceived normalization of the intervention. Qualitative data were analyzed using the NPT framework, with quantitative data analyzed descriptively and using <i>χ</i> <sup>2</sup> and Wilcoxon signed-rank test for differences in current and future normalization.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Thirty-seven GPs worked in the clinics and could recruit patients for the digital intervention. Thirty-six patients registered for the intervention. Nine patients dropped out early and 25 completed the intervention as intended. Low normalization scores at follow-up (<i>n</i> = 27) indicated that Endre did not become fully embedded in and across practices. Nonetheless, staff felt somewhat confident about their use of Endre and thought it may become a more integral part of their work in the future. Findings from six semi-structured group interviews suggested that limited implementation success may have been due to a lack of tailored implementation support, staff's lack of involvement, their diminished trust in Endre, and a lack of feedback on intervention usage. The outbreak of the Covid-19 pandemic further limited opportunities for GPs to use Endre.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study investigated the real-world challenges of implementing a digital alcohol intervention in routine clinical practice. Future research should involve support staff in both the development and implementation of digital solutions to maximize compatibility with professional workflows and needs. Integration of digital solutions may further be improved by including features such as dashboards that enable clinicians to access and monitor patient progress and self-reported outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Potthoff, Brendryen, Bosnic, Njå, Finch and Lid.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Potthoff</LastName><ForeName>Sebastian</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Alcohol and Drug Research, Stavanger University Hospital, Stavanger, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social Work, Education and Community Wellbeing, Northumbria University, Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brendryen</LastName><ForeName>Håvar</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Alcohol and Drug Research, Stavanger University Hospital, Stavanger, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bosnic</LastName><ForeName>Haris</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Alcohol and Drug Research, Stavanger University Hospital, Stavanger, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Norwegian Reading Centre, Faculty of Arts and Education, University of Stavanger, Stavanger, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Njå</LastName><ForeName>Anne Lill Mjølhus</ForeName><Initials>ALM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Alcohol and Drug Research, Stavanger University Hospital, Stavanger, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Finch</LastName><ForeName>Tracy</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Midwifery and Health, Northumbria University, Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lid</LastName><ForeName>Torgeir Gilje</ForeName><Initials>TG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Alcohol and Drug Research, Stavanger University Hospital, Stavanger, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Stavanger, Stavanger, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Unit for General Practice, NORCE Norwegian Research Centre, Bergen, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Health Serv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918334887706676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2813-0146</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">alcohol</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">digital interventions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">eHealth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hazardous drinking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">implementation science</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">normalization process theory</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">primary care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risky drinking</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11514074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/frhs.2024.1343568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Organization WH. Global Status Report on Alcohol and Health 2018. World Health Organization. (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistisk sentralbyrå: Alkoholomsetning: Statistisk sentralbyrå. (2019). Available online at:
https://www.ssb.no/varehandel-og-tjenesteyting/statistikker/alkohol
(Accessed October 13, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaner EFS, Beyer FR, Muirhead C, Campbell F, Pienaar ED, Bertholet N, et al. Effectiveness of brief alcohol interventions in primary care populations. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. (2018) 2. 10.1002/14651858.CD004148.pub4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD004148.pub4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6491186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29476653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Donnell A, Schmidt CS, Beyer F, Schrietter M, Anderson P, Jane-Llopis E, et al. Effectiveness of digital interventions for people with comorbid heavy drinking and depression: a systematic review and narrative synthesis. J Affect Disord. (2022) 298:10–23. 10.1016/j.jad.2021.11.039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.11.039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34801605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beyer FR, Kenny RPW, Johnson E, Caldwell DM, Garnett C, Rice S, et al. Practitioner and digitally delivered interventions for reducing hazardous and harmful alcohol consumption in people not seeking alcohol treatment: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Addiction (Abingdon, England). (2023) 118(1):17–29. 10.1111/add.15999</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/add.15999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10087505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35815387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angus C, Latimer N, Preston L, Li J, Purshouse R. What are the implications for policy makers? A systematic review of the cost-effectiveness of screening and brief interventions for alcohol misuse in primary care. Front Psychiatry. (2014) 5:114. 10.3389/fpsyt.2014.00114</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2014.00114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4150206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25225487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramsey AT, Satterfield JM, Gerke DR, Proctor EK. Technology-based alcohol interventions in primary care: systematic review. J Med Internet Res. (2019) 21(4):e10859. 10.2196/10859</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/10859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6475823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30958270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quanbeck A, Gustafson DH, Marsch LA, Chih M-Y, Kornfield R, McTavish F, et al. Implementing a mobile health system to integrate the treatment of addiction into primary care: a hybrid implementation-effectiveness study. J Med Internet Res. (2018) 20(1):e37. 10.2196/jmir.8928</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.8928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5811649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29382624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quanbeck AR, Gustafson DH, Marsch LA, McTavish F, Brown RT, Mares M-L, et al. Integrating addiction treatment into primary care using mobile health technology: protocol for an implementation research study. Implement Sci. (2014) 9(1):65. 10.1186/1748-5908-9-65</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1748-5908-9-65</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4072605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24884976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaner EFS, Beyer FR, Garnett C, Crane D, Brown J, Muirhead C, et al. Personalised digital interventions for reducing hazardous and harmful alcohol consumption in community-dwelling populations. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. (2017) 9. 10.1002/14651858.CD011479.pub2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD011479.pub2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6483779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28944453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiluk BD, Ray LA, Walthers J, Bernstein M, Tonigan JS, Magill M. Technology-delivered cognitive-behavioral interventions for alcohol use: a meta-analysis. Alcohol Clin Exp Res. (2019) 43(11):2285–95. 10.1111/acer.14189</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/acer.14189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6824956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31566787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garnett C, Oldham M, Angus C, Beard E, Burton R, Field M, et al. Evaluating the effectiveness of the smartphone app. Drink Less, compared with the NHS alcohol advice webpage, for the reduction of alcohol consumption among hazardous and harmful adult drinkers in the UK at: 6, -month follow-up: protocol for a randomised controlled trial. Addiction. (2021) 116(2):412–25. 10.1111/add.15287</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/add.15287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8436762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33067856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attwood S, Parke H, Larsen J, Morton KL. Using a mobile health application to reduce alcohol consumption: a mixed-methods evaluation of the drink aware track &amp; calculate units application. BMC Public Health. (2017) 17(1):394. 10.1186/s12889-017-4358-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-017-4358-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5434584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28511698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bendtsen M, Åsberg K, McCambridge J. Effectiveness of a digital intervention versus alcohol information for online help-seekers in Sweden: a randomised controlled trial. BMC Med. (2022) 20(1):176. 10.1186/s12916-022-02374-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12916-022-02374-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9112593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35578276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auerbach AD. Evaluating digital health tools—prospective, experimental, and real world. JAMA Intern Med. (2019) 179(6):840–1. 10.1001/jamainternmed.2018.7229</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2018.7229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30801610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giebel GD, Speckemeier C, Abels C, Plescher F, Börchers K, Wasem J, et al. Problems and barriers related to the use of digital health applications: scoping review. J Med Internet Res. (2023) 25:e43808. 10.2196/43808</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/43808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10221513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37171838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabaeeian RA, Hajrahimi B, Khoshfetrat A. A systematic review of telemedicine systems use barriers: primary health care providers’ perspective. J Sci Technol Policy Manag. (2022) 15(3):610–35. 10.1108/jstpm-07-2021-0106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/jstpm-07-2021-0106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glass JE, Tiffany B, Matson TE, Lim C, Gundersen G, Kimbel K, et al. Approaches for implementing digital interventions for alcohol use disorders in primary care: a qualitative, user-centered design study. Implement Res Pract. (2022) 3:26334895221135264. 10.1177/26334895221135264</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/26334895221135264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9924279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37091101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huddlestone L, Turner J, Eborall H, Hudson N, Davies M, Martin G. Application of normalisation process theory in understanding implementation processes in primary care settings in the UK: a systematic review. BMC Fam Pract. (2020) 21(1):52. 10.1186/s12875-020-01107-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12875-020-01107-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7075013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32178624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Donnell A, Kaner E. Are brief alcohol interventions adequately embedded in UK primary care? A qualitative study utilising normalisation process theory. Int J Environ Res Public Health. (2017) 14(4):350. 10.3390/ijerph14040350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph14040350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5409551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28350364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nilsen P. Making sense of implementation theories, models and frameworks. Implement Sci. (2015) 10(1):53. 10.1186/s13012-015-0242-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13012-015-0242-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4406164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25895742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sturgiss E, Advocat J, Lam T, Nielsen S, Ball L, Gunatillaka N, et al. Multifaceted intervention to increase the delivery of alcohol brief interventions in primary care: a mixed-methods process analysis. Br J Gen Pract. (2023) 73(735):e778–88. 10.3399/bjgp.2022.0613</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/bjgp.2022.0613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10498380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37666514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skivington K, Matthews L, Simpson SA, Craig P, Baird J, Blazeby JM, et al. A new framework for developing and evaluating complex interventions: update of medical research council guidance. Br Med J. (2021) 374:n2061. 10.1136/bmj.n2061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n2061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8482308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34593508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creswell JW, Clark VLP, Gutmann ML, Hanson WE. Advanced mixed. In: Tashakkori A, editor. Handbook of Mixed Methods in Social &amp; Behavioral Research. Thousand Oaks, California: SAGE Publications, Inc. (2003). p. 209–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lid TG, Malterud K. General practitioners’ strategies to identify alcohol problems: a focus group study. Scand J Prim Health Care. (2012) 30(2):64–9. 10.3109/02813432.2012.679229</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/02813432.2012.679229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3378006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22643149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potthoff S, O’Donnell AJ, Karlsen AT, Brendryen H, Lid TG. Pragmatic approaches for addressing alcohol in general practice: development of a tailored implementation intervention. Front Health Serv. (2022) 2:940383. 10.3389/frhs.2022.940383</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/frhs.2022.940383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10012791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36925895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>May C, Finch T. Implementing, embedding, and integrating practices: an outline of normalization process theory. Sociology. (2009) 43(3):535–54. 10.1177/0038038509103208</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0038038509103208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holter MTS, Johansen A, Brendryen H. How a fully automated eHealth program simulates three therapeutic processes: a case study. J Med Internet Res. (2016) 18(6):e176. 10.2196/jmir.5415</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.5415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4942686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27354373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deci EL, Ryan RM. Self-determination theory: a macrotheory of human motivation, development, and health. Can Psycho/Psychologie Canadienne. (2008) 49(3):182. 10.1037/a0012801</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/a0012801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller WR, Rollnick S. Motivational Interviewing: Helping People Change. New York, NY: Guilford press; (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marlatt GA, George WH. Relapse prevention: introduction and overview of the model. Br J Addict. (1984) 79(4):261–73. 10.1111/j.1360-0443.1984.tb03867.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1360-0443.1984.tb03867.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6595020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friederichs SAH, Oenema A, Bolman C, Guyaux J, van Keulen HM, Lechner L. I move: systematic development of a web-based computer tailored physical activity intervention, based on motivational interviewing and self-determination theory. BMC Public Health. (2014) 14(1):212. 10.1186/1471-2458-14-212</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-14-212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3944675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24580802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barazzone N, Cavanagh K, Richards DA. Computerized cognitive behavioural therapy and the therapeutic alliance: a qualitative enquiry. Br J Clin Psychol. (2012) 51(4):396–417. 10.1111/j.2044-8260.2012.02035.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8260.2012.02035.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23078210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cahill J, Barkham M, Hardy G, Gilbody S, Richards D, Bower P, et al. A review and critical appraisal of measures of therapist-patient interactions in mental health settings. Health Technol Assess (Winchester, England). (2008) 12 (24):iii, ix-47. 10.3310/hta12240</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3310/hta12240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18510875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holter MT, Ness O, Johansen AB, Brendryen H. Getting change-space: a grounded theory study of automated eHealth therapy. Qual Rep. (2019) 24(7):1636–57. 10.46743/2160-3715/2019.3988</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.46743/2160-3715/2019.3988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holter MT, Ness O, Johansen AB, Brendryen H. Making come-alive and keeping un-alive: how people relate to self-guided web-based health interventions. Qual Health Res. (2020) 30(6):927–41. 10.1177/1049732320902456</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1049732320902456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7322942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32046613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bickmore T, Gruber A, Picard R. Establishing the computer-patient working alliance in automated health behavior change interventions. Patient Educ Couns. (2005) 59(1):21–30. 10.1016/j.pec.2004.09.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pec.2004.09.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16198215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michie S, Atkins L, West R. The behaviour change wheel: a guide to designing interventions. Needed Phys Leaders. (2014) 26(146). 10.1186/1748-5908-6-42</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1748-5908-6-42</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3096582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21513547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>May CR, Albers B, Bracher M, Finch TL, Gilbert A, Girling M, et al. Translational framework for implementation evaluation and research: a normalisation process theory coding manual for qualitative research and instrument development. Implement Sci. (2022) 17(1):19. 10.1186/s13012-022-01191-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13012-022-01191-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8861599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35193611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finch TL, Girling M, May CR, Mair FS, Murray E, Treweek S, et al. Improving the normalization of complex interventions: part 2-validation of the NoMAD instrument for assessing implementation work based on normalization process theory (NPT). BMC Med Res Methodol. (2018) 18(1):1–13. 10.1186/s12874-018-0591-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12874-018-0591-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6238372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30442094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapley T, Girling M, Mair FS, Murray E, Treweek S, McColl E, et al. Improving the normalization of complex interventions: part 1-development of the NoMAD instrument for assessing implementation work based on normalization process theory (NPT). BMC Med Res Methodol. (2018) 18(1):1–17. 10.1186/s12874-018-0590-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12874-018-0590-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6238361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30442093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ImpleMentAll consortium: Translation Guide (short version). (2018). Available online at:
https://www.implementall.eu/Translation%20Guide_NoMAD_IMAweb_wlogo.pdf (Accessed November 11, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol. (2006) 3(2):77–101. 10.1191/1478088706qp063oa</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1191/1478088706qp063oa</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King N. Qualitative organizational research: core methods and current challenges. In: Symon G, Cassell C, editors. London: SAGE Publications, Inc. (2012). 10.4135/9781526435620</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4135/9781526435620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker R, Camosso-Stefinovic J, Gillies C, Shaw EJ, Cheater F, Flottorp S, et al. Tailored interventions to address determinants of practice. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. (2015) 2015(4):Cd005470. 10.1002/14651858.CD005470.pub3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD005470.pub3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7271646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25923419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potthoff S, Finch T, Bührmann L, Etzelmüller A, van Genugten CR, Girling M, et al. Towards an implementation-STakeholder engagement model (I-STEM) for improving health and social care services. Health Expect. (2023) 26(5):1997–2012. 10.1111/hex.13808</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/hex.13808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10485327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37403248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smogeli Holter MT. Digital interventions could transform routine care but we need more research on how to achieve this. Acta Paediatr. (2023) 112(5):894–5. 10.1111/apa.16715</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apa.16715</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36864568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor MJ, McNicholas C, Nicolay C, Darzi A, Bell D, Reed JE. Systematic review of the application of the plan–do–study–act method to improve quality in healthcare. BMJ Qual Saf. (2014) 23(4):290–8. 10.1136/bmjqs-2013-001862</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjqs-2013-001862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3963536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24025320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lattie EG, Nicholas J, Knapp AA, Skerl JJ, Kaiser SM, Mohr DC. Opportunities for and tensions surrounding the use of technology-enabled mental health services in community mental health care. Adm Policy Mental Health Mental Health Serv Res. (2020) 47(1):138–49. 10.1007/s10488-019-00979-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10488-019-00979-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6946841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31535235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoare KJ, Mills J, Francis K. The role of government policy in supporting nurse-led care in general practice in the United Kingdom, New Zealand and Australia: an adapted realist review. J Adv Nurs. (2012) 68(5):963–80. 10.1111/j.1365-2648.2011.05870.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2011.05870.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22070658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raney L, Bergman D, Torous J, Hasselberg M. Digitally driven integrated primary care and behavioral health: how technology can expand access to effective treatment. Curr Psychiatry Rep. (2017) 19(11):86. 10.1007/s11920-017-0838-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11920-017-0838-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28965319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>