<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39464848</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1564-0604</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>102</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bull World Health Organ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Participatory development of training videos for respiratory equipment.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>828</StartPage><EndPage>833</EndPage><MedlinePgn>828-833</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2471/BLT.24.291816</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PROBLEM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">During the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, medical oxygen therapy was urgently needed for patients with hypoxaemia. Many low- and middle-income countries lacked the medical devices for oxygen therapy and experience in their use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="APPROACH" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In addition to providing medical devices for oxygen therapy for countries in need, the World Health Organization (WHO) and partners developed training videos to help local health workers select, use and maintain this equipment. Diverse health professionals, including engineers and clinicians from resource-constrained countries, collaborated in developing draft videos in their local settings. A production team refined these drafts and delivered the training videos through the platform OpenWHO.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LOCAL SETTING" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">OpenWHO is WHO's free open-access platform providing courses for health workers and others. The courses, based on WHO's scientific and operational guidance, can be easily adapted, contextualized and translated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RELEVANT CHANGES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The production team refined the drafts into 32 training videos. More than 17 505 health workers participated in the OpenWHO course on COVID-19 respiratory equipment between 28 February 2022 and 30 November 2023. Participants were from 189 countries and 38% (6027/16 047) were from low- and lower-middle-income countries.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LESSONS LEARNT" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Involving volunteer biomedical engineers and clinicians from low- and middle-income countries helped provide an appropriate training resource. WHO should continue to develop such training tools and offer them through OpenWHO, especially for emergencies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tim</LastName><ForeName>Joshua</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ministry of Health Botswana, Plot 54609, Amos Street, Government Enclave, PO Box 20172, Gaborone, Botswana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gentles</LastName><ForeName>Bill</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>BT Medical Technology Consulting, Peterborough, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Clark</LastName><ForeName>J Tobey</ForeName><Initials>JT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Collaborating Centre for Health Technology Management, Technical Services Partnership, University of Vermont, Burlington, United States of America (USA).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Relan</LastName><ForeName>Pryanka</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Integrated Health Services Department, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lado</LastName><ForeName>Marta</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Partners in Health, Freetown, Sierra Leone.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Hui-Ling</ForeName><Initials>HL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chang Gung University, Tao-Yuan, Taiwan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lipnick</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Collaborating Centre for Emergency, Critical and Operative Care, Department of Emergency Medicine, University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rauniyar</LastName><ForeName>Barun Kumar</ForeName><Initials>BK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Hazard Management Unit, WHO Regional Office for South-East Asia, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rodriguez</LastName><ForeName>Daniela Rodriguez</ForeName><Initials>DR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Devices and Diagnostics, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Velazquez Berumen</LastName><ForeName>Adriana</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Devices and Diagnostics, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Bull World Health Organ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7507052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0042-9686</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014944" MajorTopicYN="N">World Health Organization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006282" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Personnel</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000193" MajorTopicYN="N">education</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010102" MajorTopicYN="N">Oxygen Inhalation Therapy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003906" MajorTopicYN="N">Developing Countries</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014741" MajorTopicYN="N">Video Recording</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText Label="PROBLÈME" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Lors de la pandémie de coronavirus en 2019 (COVID-19), les patients atteints d’hypoxémie ont eu besoin d’une oxygénothérapie médicale d’urgence. De nombreux pays à revenus faibles ou intermédiaires manquaient alors de dispositifs médicaux pour assurer cette oxygénothérapie et d’expérience dans leur utilisation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="APPROCHE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">L’Organisation mondiale de la santé (OMS) et ses partenaires ont non seulement fourni des dispositifs médicaux d’oxygénothérapie aux pays qui en avaient besoin, mais ils ont également élaboré des vidéos de formation pour aider les professionnels de la santé locaux à sélectionner, utiliser et entretenir ce matériel. Différents professionnels de la santé, dont des ingénieurs et des cliniciens issus de pays aux ressources limitées, ont coopéré à l’élaboration de projets de vidéos dans leur environnement local. Une équipe de production a perfectionné ces projets et a diffusé les vidéos de formation par l’intermédiaire de la plateforme OpenWHO.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ENVIRONNEMENT LOCAL" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">OpenWHO est une plateforme gratuite et en accès libre de l’OMS qui propose des formations aux agents de santé et à d’autres personnes. Les formations, basées sur les orientations scientifiques et opérationnelles de l’OMS, peuvent être facilement adaptées, contextualisées et traduites.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CHANGEMENTS SIGNIFICATIFS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">L’équipe de production a perfectionné les projets et a réalisé 32 vidéos de formation à partir de ces projets. Plus de 17 505 agents de santé ont participé à la formation OpenWHO sur les appareils respiratoires dans le cadre de la pandémie de COVID-19 entre le 28 février 2022 et le 30 novembre 2023. Les participants étaient originaires de 189 pays, et 38% d’entre eux (6027/16 047) provenaient de pays à revenus faibles ou intermédiaires de la tranche inférieure.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LEÇONS TIRÉES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">La participation d’ingénieurs biomédicaux et de cliniciens volontaires issus de pays à revenus faibles ou intermédiaires a permis de fournir des ressources de formation appropriées. L’OMS devrait continuer à élaborer de tels outils de formation et les proposer sur la plateforme OpenWHO, en particulier pour les situations d’urgence.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText Label="SITUACIÓN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Durante la pandemia de la enfermedad por coronavirus de 2019 (COVID-19), se necesitó urgentemente oxigenoterapia médica para los pacientes con hipoxemia. Muchos países de ingresos bajos y medios carecían de los dispositivos médicos necesarios para la oxigenoterapia y de experiencia en su uso.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ENFOQUE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Además de proporcionar dispositivos médicos para oxigenoterapia a los países necesitados, la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) y sus asociados elaboraron vídeos de formación para ayudar al personal sanitario local a seleccionar, utilizar y mantener estos equipos. Varios profesionales sanitarios, entre ellos ingenieros y médicos de países con recursos limitados, colaboraron en la elaboración de los borradores de los vídeos en sus entornos locales. Un equipo de producción perfeccionó estos borradores y entregó los vídeos de formación a través de la plataforma OpenWHO.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MARCO REGIONAL" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">OpenWHO es la plataforma gratuita de libre acceso de la OMS que ofrece cursos para el personal sanitario y otras personas. Los cursos, basados en las orientaciones científicas y operativas de la OMS, pueden adaptarse, contextualizarse y traducirse fácilmente.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CAMBIOS IMPORTANTES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">El equipo de producción mejoró los borradores hasta convertirlos en 32 vídeos de formación. Más de 17 505 agentes de salud participaron en el curso OpenWHO sobre equipos respiratorios COVID-19 entre el 28 de febrero de 2022 y el 30 de noviembre de 2023. Los participantes procedían de 189 países y el 38% (6027/16 047) de países de ingresos bajos y medios bajos.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LECCIONES APRENDIDAS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">La participación de ingenieros biomédicos y médicos voluntarios de países de ingresos bajos y medios contribuyó a proporcionar un recurso de formación adecuado. La OMS debería seguir desarrollando estas herramientas de formación y ofrecerlas a través de OpenWHO, en especial para emergencias.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ara"><AbstractText Label="المشكلة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">أثناء جائحة مرض فيروس كورونا 2019 (كوفيد19)، كانت هناك حاجة شديدة للعلاج بالأكسجين الطبي للمرضى الذين يعانون من نقص التأكسج بالدم. وكانت العديد من الدول ذات الدخل المنخفض والدخل المتوسط في حاجة إلى الأجهزة الطبية للعلاج بالأكسجين فضلاً عن الخبرة في استخدامها.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الأسلوب" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">بالإضافة إلى توفير الأجهزة الطبية اللازمة للعلاج بالأكسجين في الدول التي تحتاج إلى هذه الأجهزة، قامت منظمة الصحة العالمية (WHO) وشركاؤها بتطوير مقاطع فيديو تدريبية لمساعدة العاملين في قطاع الصحة المحلي في انتقاء هذه المعدات واستخدامها وصيانتها. تعاون العديد من المتخصصين الصحيين، بما في ذلك المهندسون والأطباء من الدول ذات الموارد المحدودة، في تطوير مقاطع فيديو أولية في بيئاتهم المحلية. قام فريق الإنتاج بتنقيح هذه المقاطع الأولية، وتسليم مقاطع التدريب النهائية من خلال منصة OpenWHO.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="المواقع المحلية" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">إن OpenWHO هي المنصة مفتوحة المصدر والمجانية لمنظمة الصحة العالمية، وهي تقدم دورات تدريبية للعاملين في القطاع الصحي وغيرهم. يمكن بسهولة تكييف الدورات التدريبية، المستندة إلى التوجيهات العلمية والتشغيلية لمنظمة الصحة العالمية، وصياغتها وترجمتها.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="التغيّرات ذات الصلة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">قام فريق الإنتاج بتنقيح مقاطع الفيديو الأولية، وتحويلها إلى 32 مقطعًا من تدريبات الفيديو. شارك أكثر من 17505 من العاملين في القطاع الصحي في دورة OpenWHO التدريبية عن معدات التنفس الخاصة بكوفيد 19 في الفترة ما بين 28 فبراير/شباط 2022 و30 نوفمبر/تشرين ثاني 2023. وكان المشاركون من 189 دولة، بينما كان %38 منهم (6027/16047) من الدول ذات الدخل المنخفض، والدخل المتوسط المنخفض.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الدروس المستفادة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">إن اشتراك المهندسين والأطباء المتطوعين في مجال الطب الحيوي من الدول ذات الدخل المنخفض والدخل المتوسط، ساعد في توفير مورد تدريبي مناسب. يجب أن تستمر منظمة الصحة العالمية في تطوير مثل هذه الأدوات التدريبية، وطرحها من خلال منصة OpenWHO، وخاصة في حالات الطوارئ.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="chi"><AbstractText Label="问题" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">在新冠病毒 (COVID-19) 疫情期间，低氧血症患者急需接受医用氧疗。许多中低收入国家缺乏医用氧疗设备和相关使用经验。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="方法" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">除为有需要的国家提供医用氧疗设备外，世界卫生组织 (WHO) 及其合作伙伴还开发了培训视频，以帮助当地卫生工作者选择、使用和维护该设备。包括来自资源受限国家的生物医学工程师和临床医生在内的各种卫生专业人员合作，在当地开发了草拟培训视频。制作团队对这些草案进行了优化，并通过 OpenWHO 平台发布了这些培训视频。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="当地状况" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">OpenWHO 是 WHO 分享知识、为卫生工作者和类似人员提供线上课程的免费平台。这些课程以 WHO 的科学和操作指导为基础，很容易进行改编、情境化处理和翻译。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="相关变化" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">制作团队将优化后的草案剪辑成了 32 个培训视频。2022 年 2 月 28 日至 2023 年 11 月 30 日期间，有超过 17,505 名卫生工作者参加了 OpenWHO 上关于 COVID-19 呼吸设备的在线课程。参与者遍布 189 个国家，其中 38% (6027/16047) 来自中低收入国家。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="经验教训" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">让来自中低收入国家的志愿生物医学工程师和临床医生参与进来，有助于提供适用的培训资源。WHO 应继续致力于开发此类培训工具，并通过 OpenWHO 提供这些工具，特别是针对突发事件。.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="rus"><AbstractText Label="ПРОБЛЕМА" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Во время пандемии коронавирусной инфекции 2019 г. (COVID-19) пациентам с гипоксемией срочно требовалась терапия медицинским кислородом. Во многих странах с низким и средним уровнем дохода отсутствуют медицинские изделия для кислородной терапии и опыт их использования.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ПОДХОД" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Помимо поставки медицинских изделий для кислородной терапии в нуждающиеся страны, Всемирная организация здравоохранения (ВОЗ) и ее партнеры разработали обучающие видеоматериалы, направленные на оказание помощи местным медицинским работникам в выборе, использовании и обслуживании таких изделий. Различные специалисты в области здравоохранения, включая инженеров и клиницистов из стран с ограниченными ресурсами, сотрудничали при разработке проектов видеороликов в своих регионах. Производственная группа доработала эти проекты и передала учебные видеоматериалы через платформу OpenWHO.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="МЕСТНЫЕ УСЛОВИЯ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">OpenWHO – это бесплатная платформа ВОЗ с открытым доступом, на которой размещены курсы для работников здравоохранения и других специалистов. Курсы, основанные на научном и оперативном руководстве ВОЗ, могут быть легко адаптированы и переведены с учетом конкретных условий.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ОСУЩЕСТВЛЕННЫЕ ПЕРЕМЕНЫ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Производственная группа доработала пробные версии до 32 учебных видеороликов. В период с 28 февраля 2022 года по 30 ноября 2023 года более 17 505 медицинских работников прошли курс OpenWHO по использованию дыхательных устройств при лечении COVID-19. Участники представляли 189 стран, 38% (6027/16 047) – страны с низким и средненизким уровнем дохода.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ВЫВОДЫ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Привлечение добровольцев из числа инженеров по биомедицинскому оборудованию и клиницистов из стран с низким и средним уровнем дохода способствовало созданию соответствующего учебного ресурса. ВОЗ следует продолжать разработку подобных учебных пособий и предлагать их через OpenWHO, особенно в чрезвычайных ситуациях.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11500244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.24.291816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">BLT.24.291816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Clinical care for severe acute respiratory infection: toolkit, update 2022. COVID-19 adaptation. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/352851 [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Priority medical devices list for the COVID-19 response and associated technical specifications, interim guidance, 19 November 2020. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/336745 [cited 2023 Nov 7].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Solidarity Response Fund for the World Health Organization. impact report, January 1–March 31, 2021. New York: United Nations Foundation; 2021. Available from: https://s3.amazonaws.com/media.unfoundation.org/2021/05/C-Fund-impact-report-jan-march-21_Final.pdf [cited 2024 Mar 12].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medical equipment maintenance programme overview. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2011. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/44587 [cited 2023 Nov 7].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OpenWHO.org [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2024. Available from: https://openwho.org/ [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emergency global supply chain system (COVID-19) catalogue, August 2022. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. Available from: https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/emergency-global-supply-chain-system-covid-19-catalogue [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Looking back at a year that changed the world: WHO’s response to COVID-19; 22 January 2021. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2021. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/340321 [cited 2024 Apr 23].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OpenWHO. COVID-19 respiratory equipment [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. Available from: https://openwho.org/courses/respiratory-equipment [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OpenWHO. COVID-19 Module de formation sur les équipements respiratoires [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2023. Available from: https://openwho.org/courses/equipement-respiratoire [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OpenWHO. [Training course on the use of respiratory support equipment.] [internet].Geneva: World Health Organization; 2023. Russian. Available from: https://openwho.org/courses/respiratory-equipment-ru [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OpenWHO. Medical equipment electrical safety testing [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. Available from: https://openwho.org/courses/electrical-safety-testing [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IEC60601-1:2005. Medical electrical equipment – Part 1: General requirements for basic safety and essential performance. Geneva: International Electrotechnical Commission; 2005. Available from: https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/2606 [cited 2023 Nov 7].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank income group classification [internet]. Washington, DC: World Bank Group; 2024. Available from: https://datahelpdesk.worldbank.org/knowledgebase/articles/906519-world-bank-country-and-lending-groups [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trainings for medical devices [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2024. Available from: https://www.who.int/teams/health-product-policy-and-standards/assistive-and-medical-technology/medical-devices/management-use/trainings [cited 2024 Jan 16].</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>