<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39460501</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2574-173X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Neuropsychopharmacology reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Neuropsychopharmacol Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Real-world predictors of severe psychological distress during the COVID-19 pandemic in Japan: Insights from a large-scale internet-based cohort study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/npr2.12495</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The COVID-19 pandemic has had negative physical and psychological impacts worldwide. However, there has been a lack of real-world evidence concerning the predictors of severe psychological distress (SPD) among the general population in Japan during the COVID-19 pandemic. The aim of this study was to examine predictors of SPD during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We investigated the predictors of new-onset SPD in the general Japanese population using data from a large-scale internet-based cohort study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We included 16 489 study participants (age range = 16-81, mean age = 52.7, percentage of male = 50%) in the analysis. Over the course of 1 year from baseline, the estimated proportion of participants who experienced SPD was 5.2% with inverse probability weighting. The predictors of SPD included younger age, being never married, being unemployed, having a higher education background, scoring higher on the Fear of Coronavirus-19 Scale, experiencing more adverse childhood experiences, reporting poorer subjective health status, and COVID-19 with oxygen therapy. Our internet-based survey of the Japanese population may have selection bias, limiting the generalizability to other countries and cultures.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study revealed that being afflicted with COVID-19 requiring oxygen therapy is the most significant predictor of SPD. In addition, we found that vulnerability to social isolation, such as never being unmarried, anxiety toward COVID-19, and susceptibility to stress, are predictors of the emergence of SPD. Therefore, the implementation of online support systems and ensuring access to accurate information may protect against SPD during the COVID-19 pandemic in Japan.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Neuropsychopharmacology Reports published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of The Japanese Society of Neuropsychopharmacology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tokumitsu</LastName><ForeName>Keita</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6747-4348</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neuropsychiatry, Towada City Hospital, Towada, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dokkyo Medical University School of Medicine, Mibu, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sugawara</LastName><ForeName>Norio</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7058-664X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dokkyo Medical University School of Medicine, Mibu, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tabuchi</LastName><ForeName>Takahiro</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cancer Control Center, Osaka International Cancer Institute, Osaka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Graduate School of Medicine, Tohoku University, Miyagi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yasui-Furukori</LastName><ForeName>Norio</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4414-3770</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dokkyo Medical University School of Medicine, Mibu, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>19K13704</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>19H01073</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>19H01074</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>20H00040</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>20K10467</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>21H03203</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>21H04856</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>JPMJPF2017</GrantID><Agency>JST Grant</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>19FA1005</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>19FA1012</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>19FG2001</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>20F1005</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>20FA2001</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>20EA1017</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>21HA2016</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>22FA1001</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>22FA1002</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>22FA1010</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>22FA2001</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>22FA1005</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>23FA1004</GrantID><Agency>Health Labor Sciences Research Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>the intramural fund of the National Institute for Environmental Studies</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>the Tokyo Foundation for Policy Research</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Neuropsychopharmacol Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101719700</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2574-173X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Japan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">general population</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">predictors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychological distress</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39460501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/npr2.12495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Pokhrel S, Chhetri R. A literature review on impact of COVID‐19 pandemic on teaching and learning. High Educ Future. 2021;8(1):133–141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO Coronavirus (COVID‐19) Dashboard. Accessed 9 Aug 2024. https://covid19.who.int/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks SK, Webster RK, Smith LE, Woodland L, Wessely S, Greenberg N, et al. The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: rapid review of the evidence. Lancet. 2020;395(10227):912–920.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai J, Ma S, Wang Y, Cai Z, Hu J, Wei N, et al. Factors associated with mental health outcomes among health care workers exposed to coronavirus disease 2019. JAMA Netw Open. 2020;3(3):e203976.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shigemura J, Ursano RJ, Morganstein JC, Kurosawa M, Benedek DM. Public responses to the novel 2019 coronavirus (2019‐nCoV) in Japan: Mental health consequences and target populations. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2020;74(4):281–282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawryluck L, Gold WL, Robinson S, Pogorski S, Galea S, Styra R. SARS control and psychological effects of quarantine, Toronto, Canada. Emerg Infect Dis. 2004;10(7):1206–1212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu P, Fang Y, Guan Z, Fan B, Kong J, Yao Z, et al. The psychological impact of the SARS epidemic on hospital employees in China: exposure, risk perception, and altruistic acceptance of risk. Can J Psychiatr. 2009;54(5):302–311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lahav Y. Psychological distress related to COVID‐19 ‐ the contribution of continuous traumatic stress. J Affect Disord. 2020;277:129–137. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2020.07.141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID‐19 Mental Disorders Collaborators. Global prevalence and burden of depressive and anxiety disorders in 204 countries and territories in 2020 due to the COVID‐19 pandemic. Lancet. 2021;398(10312):1700–1712. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140‐6736(21)02143‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salanti G, Peter N, Tonia T, Holloway A, White IR, Darwish L, et al. The impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic and associated control measures on the Mental health of the general population: a systematic review and dose‐response meta‐analysis. Ann Intern Med. 2022;175(11):1560–1571. https://doi.org/10.7326/m22‐1507</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfefferbaum B, North CS. Mental health and the Covid‐19 pandemic. N Engl J Med. 2020;383(6):510–512. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMp2008017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubota T, Kuroda N, Sone D. Neuropsychiatric aspects of long COVID: a comprehensive review. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2023;77(2):84–93. https://doi.org/10.1111/pcn.13508</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braga J, Lepra M, Kish SJ, Rusjan PM, Nasser Z, Verhoeff N, et al. Neuroinflammation after COVID‐19 with persistent depressive and cognitive symptoms. JAMA Psychiatry. 2023;80(8):787–795. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2023.1321</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshioka T, Okubo R, Tabuchi T, Odani S, Shinozaki T, Tsugawa Y. Factors associated with serious psychological distress during the COVID‐19 pandemic in Japan: a nationwide cross‐sectional internet‐based study. BMJ Open. 2021;11(7):e051115. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen‐2021‐051115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabuchi T, Shinozaki T, Kunugita N, Nakamura M, Tsuji I. Study profile: the Japan "society and new tobacco" internet survey (JASTIS): a longitudinal internet cohort study of heat‐not‐burn tobacco products, electronic cigarettes, and conventional tobacco products in Japan. J Epidemiol. 2019;29(11):444–450. https://doi.org/10.2188/jea.JE20180116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hori A, Tabuchi T, Kunugita N. The spread of heated tobacco product (HTP) use across various subgroups during 2015‐16 and 2017‐18 in Japan. Environ Health Prev Med. 2023;28:5. https://doi.org/10.1265/ehpm.22‐00219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishimura M, Asai K, Tabuchi T, Toyokura E, Kawai T, Miyamoto A, et al. Association of combustible cigarettes and heated tobacco products use with SARS‐CoV‐2 infection and severe COVID‐19 in Japan: a JASTIS 2022 cross‐sectional study. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):1120. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐023‐28006‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Andrews G, Colpe LJ, Hiripi E, Mroczek DK, Normand SL, et al. Short screening scales to monitor population prevalences and trends in non‐specific psychological distress. Psychol Med. 2002;32(6):959–976.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furukawa TA, Kawakami N, Saitoh M, Ono Y, Nakane Y, Nakamura Y, et al. The performance of the Japanese version of the K6 and K10 in the world Mental health survey Japan. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2008;17(3):152–158. https://doi.org/10.1002/mpr.257</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakurai K, Nishi A, Kondo K, Yanagida K, Kawakami N. Screening performance of K6/K10 and other screening instruments for mood and anxiety disorders in Japan. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2011;65(5):434–441. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1440‐1819.2011.02236.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahorsu DK, Lin CY, Imani V, Saffari M, Griffiths MD, Pakpour AH. The fear of COVID‐19 scale: development and initial validation. Int J Ment Heal Addict. © The Author(s) 2020. 2022;3:1537–1545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin CY, Hou WL, Mamun MA, Aparecido da Silva J, Broche‐Pérez Y, Ullah I, et al. Fear of COVID‐19 scale (FCV‐19S) across countries: measurement invariance issues. Nurs Open. 2021;8(4):1892–1908. https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.855</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felitti VJ, Anda RF, Nordenberg D, Williamson DF, Spitz AM, Edwards V, et al. Relationship of childhood abuse and household dysfunction to many of the leading causes of death in adults. The adverse childhood experiences (ACE) study. Am J Prev Med. 1998;14(4):245–258. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0749‐3797(98)00017‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green JG, McLaughlin KA, Berglund PA, Gruber MJ, Sampson NA, Zaslavsky AM, et al. Childhood adversities and adult psychiatric disorders in the national comorbidity survey replication I: associations with first onset of DSM‐IV disorders. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2010;67(2):113–123. https://doi.org/10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.186</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujiwara T. Impact of adverse childhood experience on physical and mental health: a life‐course epidemiology perspective. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2022;76(11):544–551. https://doi.org/10.1111/pcn.13464</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Agency for Research on Cancer. IARC handbooks of cancer prevention tobacco control volume 13: evaluating the effectiveness of smoke‐free policies. Lyon: WHO Press; 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Little RJ, D'Agostino R, Cohen ML, Dickersin K, Emerson SS, Farrar JT, et al. The prevention and treatment of missing data in clinical trials. N Engl J Med. 2012;367(14):1355–1360. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMsr1203730</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabuchi T, Fujiwara T. Are secondhand smoke‐related diseases of children associated with parental smoking cessation? Determinants of parental smoking cessation in a population‐based cohort study. Prev Med. 2015;73:81–87. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2015.01.028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasaki N, Tabuchi T, Fujiwara T, Nishi D. Adverse childhood experiences and living in the socially deprived areas in adulthood: a cross‐sectional study of the nationwide data in Japan. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):1616. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889‐023‐16557‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schafer JL, Graham JW. Missing data: our view of the state of the art. Psychol Methods. 2002;7(2):147–177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanda Y. Investigation of the freely available easy‐to‐use software ‘EZR’ for medical statistics. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2013;48(3):452–458. https://doi.org/10.1038/bmt.2012.244</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomitaka S, Furukawa TA. Mathematical pattern of Kessler psychological distress distribution in the general population of the U.S. and Japan. BMC Psychiatry. 2021;21(1):188. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888‐021‐03198‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institutes of Health. COVID‐19 Treatment Guidelines Panel. Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Treatment Guidelines. Accessed 9 Aug, 2024. https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taquet M, Dercon Q, Luciano S, Geddes JR, Husain M, Harrison PJ. Incidence, co‐occurrence, and evolution of long‐COVID features: a 6‐month retrospective cohort study of 273,618 survivors of COVID‐19. PLoS Med. 2021;18(9):e1003773. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1003773</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng N, Zhao YM, Yan W, Li C, Lu QD, Liu L, et al. A systematic review and meta‐analysis of long term physical and mental sequelae of COVID‐19 pandemic: call for research priority and action. Mol Psychiatry. © 2022. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature Limited. 2023;1:423–433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khachatryan K, Beutel ME, Stöbel‐Richter Y, Zenger M, Berth H, Brähler E, et al. Are attitudes towards COVID‐19 pandemic related to subjective physical and Mental health? Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(21): 1–16. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph192114538</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isumi A, Fujiwara T. Association of adverse childhood experiences with shaking and smothering behaviors among Japanese caregivers. Child Abuse Negl. 2016;57:12–20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chiabu.2016.05.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resnick HS, Yehuda R, Pitman RK, Foy DW. Effect of previous trauma on acute plasma cortisol level following rape. Am J Psychiatry. 1995;152:1675–1677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yehuda R, Kahana B, Schmeidler J, Southwick SM, Wilson S, Giller EL. Impact of cumulative lifetime trauma and recent stress on current posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms in holocaust survivors. Am J Psychiatry. 1995;152(12):1815–1818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozer EJ, Best SR, Lipsey TL, Weiss DS. Predictors of posttraumatic stress disorder and symptoms in adults: a meta‐analysis. Psychol Bull. 2003;129(1):52–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breslau N, Peterson EL, Schultz LR. A second look at prior trauma and the posttraumatic stress disorder effects of subsequent trauma: a prospective epidemiological study. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2008;65(4):431–437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pietrabissa G, Simpson SG. Psychological consequences of social isolation during COVID‐19 outbreak. Front Psychol. 2020;11:2201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrow‐Howell N, Galucia N, Swinford E. Recovering from the COVID‐19 pandemic: a focus on older adults. J Aging Soc Policy. 2020;32(4–5):526–535. https://doi.org/10.1080/08959420.2020.1759758</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolen‐Hoeksema S, Ahrens C. Age differences and similarities in the correlates of depressive symptoms. Psychol Aging. 2002;17(1):116–124.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nkire N, Nwachukwu I, Shalaby R, Hrabok M, Vuong W, Gusnowski A, et al. COVID‐19 pandemic: influence of relationship status on stress, anxiety, and depression in Canada. Ir J Psychol Med. 2022;39(4):351–362. https://doi.org/10.1017/ipm.2021.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma R, Mann F, Wang J, Lloyd‐Evans B, Terhune J, al‐Shihabi A, et al. The effectiveness of interventions for reducing subjective and objective social isolation among people with mental health problems: a systematic review. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol. 2020;55(7):839–876. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00127‐019‐01800‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigues NG, Han CQY, Su Y, Klainin‐Yobas P, Wu XV. Psychological impacts and online interventions of social isolation amongst older adults during COVID‐19 pandemic: a scoping review. J Adv Nurs. 2022;78(3):609–644. https://doi.org/10.1111/jan.15063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rauschenberg C, Schick A, Goetzl C, Roehr S, Riedel‐Heller SG, Koppe G, et al. Social isolation, mental health, and use of digital interventions in youth during the COVID‐19 pandemic: a nationally representative survey. Eur Psychiatry. 2021;64(1):e20. https://doi.org/10.1192/j.eurpsy.2021.17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voitsidis P, Nikopoulou VA, Holeva V, Parlapani E, Sereslis K, Tsipropoulou V, et al. The mediating role of fear of COVID‐19 in the relationship between intolerance of uncertainty and depression. Psychol Psychother Theory Res Pract. 2021;94(3):884–893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del‐Valle MV, López‐Morales H, Andrés ML, Yerro‐Avincetto M, Gelpi Trudo R, Urquijo S, et al. Intolerance of COVID‐19‐related uncertainty and depressive and anxiety symptoms during the pandemic: a longitudinal study in Argentina. J Anxiety Disord. 2022;86:102531.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scales D, Gorman J, Jamieson KH. The Covid‐19 Infodemic—applying the epidemiologic model to counter misinformation. N Engl J Med. 2021;385(8):678–681. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMp2103798</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallotti R, Valle F, Castaldo N, Sacco P, De Domenico M. Assessing the risks of ‘infodemics’ in response to COVID‐19 epidemics. Nat Hum Behav. 2020;4(12):1285–1293. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562‐020‐00994‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung S. The impact of the COVID‐19 Infodemic on depression and sleep disorders: focusing on uncertainty reduction strategies and level of interpretation theory. JMIR Form Res. 2022;6(1):e32552. https://doi.org/10.2196/32552</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torales J, Barrios I, O'Higgins M, Almirón‐Santacruz J, Gonzalez‐Urbieta I, García O, et al. COVID‐19 infodemic and depressive symptoms: the impact of the exposure to news about COVID‐19 on the general Paraguayan population. J Affect Disord. 2022;298:599–603. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2021.11.036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakioğlu F, Korkmaz O, Ercan H. Fear of COVID‐19 and positivity: mediating role of intolerance of uncertainty, depression, anxiety, and stress. Int J Ment Heal Addict. 2021;19(6):2369–2382. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469‐020‐00331‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bjelland I, Krokstad S, Mykletun A, Dahl AA, Tell GS, Tambs K. Does a higher educational level protect against anxiety and depression? The HUNT study. Soc Sci Med. 2008;66(6):1334–1345. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2007.12.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman A, Tyrovolas S, Koyanagi A, Chatterji S, Leonardi M, Ayuso‐Mateos JL, et al. The role of socio‐economic status in depression: results from the COURAGE (aging survey in Europe). BMC Public Health. 2016;16:1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou M, Guo W. Subjective distress about COVID‐19 and its social correlates: empirical evidence from Hubei Province of China. J Affect Disord. 2021;289:46–54. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2021.04.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts T, Miguel Esponda G, Krupchanka D, Shidhaye R, Patel V, Rathod S. Factors associated with health service utilisation for common mental disorders: a systematic review. BMC Psychiatry. 2018;18(1):262. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888‐018‐1837‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters SE, Dennerlein JT, Wagner GR, Sorensen G. Work and worker health in the post‐pandemic world: a public health perspective. Lancet Public Health. 2022;7(2):e188–e194. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2468‐2667(21)00259‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shechter A, Diaz F, Moise N, Anstey DE, Ye S, Agarwal S, et al. Psychological distress, coping behaviors, and preferences for support among New York healthcare workers during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Gen Hosp Psychiatry. 2020;66:1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deguchi Y, Iwasaki S, Niki A, Kadowaki A, Hirota T, Shirahama Y, et al. Relationships between occupational stress, change in work environment during the COVID‐19 pandemic, and depressive and anxiety symptoms among non‐healthcare Workers in Japan: a cross‐sectional study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(2): 1–14. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19020983</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arakawa Y, Inoue K, Nishioka D, Nakagomi A, Tabuchi T, Kondo N. Remote communication and loneliness during the COVID‐19 pandemic: cross‐sectional study. J Med Internet Res. 2023;25:e45338. https://doi.org/10.2196/45338</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>