<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39466127</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-7027</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Health communication</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Health Commun</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Vicarious Acquisition of Learned Helplessness During the COVID-19 Campus Epidemics in China: Interactions Between Embodied and Mediated Experiences.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1</StartPage><EndPage>12</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1-12</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1080/10410236.2024.2421613</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Numerous universities nationwide announced urgent implementation of closed campus management due to the epidemics of COVID-19 in Chinese universities since March 2022, and a large number of students were under quarantine. This study aims to explore how embodied experiences (i.e., centralized quarantine and self-quarantine) and mediated experiences (i.e., exposure to media sources, pandemic information overload, and online help seeking) influence the acquisition of learned helplessness during the campus epidemics among the Chinese university students, besides, how do these two types of experiences interact with each other to elicit learned helplessness is another interested research question. The data was collected nationwide via an online survey platform from March 22nd to April 16 2022 immediately after the outbreak of campus epidemics. A total of 1267 valid student samples were retained. Hierarchical regression analysis showed that embodied experience of centralized quarantine is positively related to learned helplessness. Mediated experience of information access from friends on social media and government official media as well as online help seeking are negatively related to learned helplessness. Information access from overseas media and pandemic information overload are positively related to learned helplessness. Besides, the interaction between self-quarantine and pandemic information overload is positively related to learned helplessness. Theoretical contributions and intervention strategies aimed at enhancing authoritative communication and managing information overload during public health crisis were discussed.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Media and Communication, Shanghai Jiao Tong University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Cultural Innovation and Youth Development, Shanghai Jiao Tong University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Media and Communication, Shanghai Jiao Tong University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Cong</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Media and Communication, Shanghai Jiao Tong University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Cultural Innovation and Youth Development, Shanghai Jiao Tong University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Health Commun</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8908762</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1041-0236</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39466127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10410236.2024.2421613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>