<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469543</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2190-1678</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Diabetology international</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Diabetol Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Role of the receptor for advanced glycation end products in the severity of SARS-CoV-2 infection in diabetic patients.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>732</StartPage><EndPage>744</EndPage><MedlinePgn>732-744</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s13340-024-00746-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), caused by SARS-CoV-2, is a severe disease in older adults and in individuals with associated comorbidities such as diabetes mellitus. Patients with diabetes infected with SARS-CoV-2 are more likely to develop severe pneumonia, hospitalization, and mortality compared with infected non-diabetic patients<b>.</b> During diabetes, hyperglycemia contributes to the maintenance of a low-grade inflammatory state which has been implicated in the microvascular and macrovascular complications associated with this pathology. The receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE) is a multi-ligand pattern recognition receptor, expressed on a wide variety of cells, which participates as an important mediator of inflammatory responses in many diseases, including lung diseases. This review highlights the role of RAGE in the pathophysiology of COVID-19 with special emphasis on diabetic patients. These data could explain the severity of the disease, positioning it as a key therapeutic target in the clinical management of this infection.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Japan Diabetes Society 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pedreañez</LastName><ForeName>Adriana</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3937-0469</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cátedra de Inmunología, Escuela de Bioanálisis, Facultad de Medicina, Universidad del Zulia, Apartado Postal: 23, Maracaibo 4001-A, Maracaibo, Zulia Venezuela.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/04vy5s568</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411267.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2168 1114</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mosquera-Sulbaran</LastName><ForeName>Jesús A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1496-5511</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Investigaciones Clínicas "Dr. Américo Negrette", Facultad de Medicina, Universidad del Zulia, Maracaibo, Venezuela.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/04vy5s568</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411267.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2168 1114</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tene</LastName><ForeName>Diego</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1588-2005</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universidad Nacional del Chimborazo, Facultad de Ciencias de la Salud, Riobamba, Ecuador.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/059wmd288</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.442237.4</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0485 4812</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Japan</Country><MedlineTA>Diabetol Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101553224</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2190-1678</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hyperglycemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Inflammation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RAGE</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestThe authors have no competing interests to declare that are relevant to the content of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11512988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13340-024-00746-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO COVID-19 Dashboard. Accessed February 7, 2024. https://covid19.who.int/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Yu T, Du R, Fan G, Liu Y, Liu Z, Xiang J, Wang Y, Song B, Gu X, Guan L, Wei Y, Li H, Wu X, Xu J, Tu S, Zhang Y, Chen H, Cao B. Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020;395:1054–62. 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30566-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Diabetes Federation. IDF Diabetes Atlas. 10th ed (2021). Accessed 23 May 2022. Available from https://diabetesatlas.org/idfawp/resource-files/2021/07/IDF_Atlas_10th_Edition_2021.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W, Li M, Dong Y, Zhou H, Zhang Z, Tian C, Qin R, Wang H, Shen Y, Du K, Zhao L, Fan H, Luo S, Hu D. Diabetes is a risk factor for the progression and prognosis of COVID-19. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2020;36:e3319. 10.1002/dmrr.3319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7228407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32233013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AK, Gupta R, Ghosh A, Misra A. Diabetes in COVID-19: prevalence, pathophysiology, prognosis and practical considerations. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2020;14:303–10. 10.1016/j.dsx.2020.04.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32298981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piperi C, Goumenos A, Adamopoulos C, Papavassiliou AG. AGE/RAGE signalling regulation by miRNAs: associations with diabetic complications and therapeutic potential. Int J Biochem Cell Biol. 2015;60:197–201. 10.1016/j.biocel.2015.01.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25603271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosquera-Sulbarán JA, Hernández-Fonseca JP. Advanced glycation end products in diabetes. In: Patel VB, Preedy VR, editors. Biomarkers in diabetes, biomarkers in disease: methods, discoveries and applications. Springer Nature Switzerland; 2023. p. 171–94. 10.1007/978-3-031-08014-2_8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du C, Whiddett RO, Buckle I, Chen C, Forbes JM, Fotheringham AK. Advanced glycation end products and inflammation in type 1 diabetes development. Cells. 2022;11:3503. 10.3390/cells11213503.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9657002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36359899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angioni R, Bonfanti M, Caporale N, Sánchez-Rodríguez R, Munari F, Savino A, Pasqualato S, Buratto D, Pagani I, Bertoldi N, Zanon C, Ferrari P, Ricciardelli E, Putaggio C, Ghezzi S, Elli F, Rotta L, Scardua A, Weber J, Cecatiello V, Iorio F, Zonta F, Cattelan AM, Vicenzi E, Vannini A, Molon B, Villa CE, Viola A, Testa G. RAGE engagement by SARS-CoV-2 enables monocyte infection and underlies COVID-19 severity. Cell Rep Med. 2023;4:101266. 10.1016/j.xcrm.2023.101266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10694673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37944530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia J, Wang J, Ying L, Huang R, Zhang K, Zhang R, Tang W, Xu Q, Lai D, Zhang Y, Hu Y, Zhang X, Zang R, Fan J, Shu Q, Xu J. RAGE is a receptor for SARS-CoV-2 N protein and mediates N protein-induced acute lung injury. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol. 2023;69:508–20. 10.1165/rcmb.2022-0351OC.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10633841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37478333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutowska K, Czajkowski K, Kuryłowicz A. Receptor for the advanced glycation end products (RAGE) pathway in adipose tissue metabolism. Int J Mol Sci. 2023;24:10982. 10.3390/ijms241310982.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10341816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37446161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosquera JA. Role of the receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE) in inflammation. Invest Clin. 2010;51:257–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20928981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim ZA, Armour CL, Phipps S, Sukkar MB. RAGE and TLRs: Relatives, friends or neighbours? Mol Immunol. 2013;56:739–44. 10.1016/j.molimm.2013.07.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23954397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platnich JM, Muruve DA. NOD-like receptors and inflammasomes: a review of their canonical and non-canonical signaling pathways. Arch Biochem Biophys. 2019;670:4–14. 10.1016/j.abb.2019.02.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30772258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y, Deng J, Nan ML, Zhang J, Okekunle A, Li JY, Yu XQ, Wang PH. The interplay between pattern recognition receptors and autophagy in inflammation. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2019;1209:79–108. 10.1007/978-981-15-0606-2_6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31728866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brett J, Schmidt AM, Yan SD, Zhou YS, Weidmann E, Pinsky D, Nowygrod R, Neeper M, Przysiecki C, Dhaw A, Migheli A, Stern DM. Survey of the distribution of a newly characterized receptor for advanced glycation end products in tissue. Am J Pathol. 1993;143:1699–712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1887265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8256857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bierhaus A, Humpert PM, Morcos M, Wendt T, Chavakis T, Arnold B, Stern DM, Nawroth PP. Understanding RAGE, the receptor for advanced glycation end products. J Mol Med (Berl). 2005;83(11):876–86. 10.1007/s00109-005-0688-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16133426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fehrenbach H, Kasper M, Tschernig T, Shearman MS, Schuh D, Müller M. Receptor for advanced glycation endproducts (RAGE) exhibits highly differential cellular and subcellular localisation in rat and human lung. Cell Mol Biol (Noisy-le-grand). 1998;44:1147–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9846897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Twarda-Clapa A, Olczak A, Białkowska AM, Koziołkiewicz M. Advanced glycation end-products (AGEs): formation, chemistry, classification, receptors, and diseases related to AGEs. Cells. 2022;11:1312. 10.3390/cells11081312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9029922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35455991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue Q, Song Y, Liu Z, Zhang L, Yang L, Li J. Receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE): a pivotal hub in immune diseases. Molecules. 2022;27:4922. 10.3390/molecules27154922.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9370360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35956875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chellappa RC, Palanisamy R, Swaminathan K. RAGE isoforms, its ligands and their role in pathophysiology of Alzheimer’s disease. Curr Alzheimer Res. 2020;17:1262–79. 10.2174/156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33602095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palanissami G, Paul SFD. RAGE and its ligands: molecular interplay between glycation, inflammation, and hallmarks of cancer-a review. Horm Cancer. 2018;9:295–325. 10.1007/s12672-018-0342-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10355895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29987748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt AM, Stern DM. Receptor for age (RAGE) is a gene within the major histocompatibility class III region: implications for host response mechanisms in homeostasis and chronic disease. Front Biosci. 2001;6:D1151–60. 10.2741/Schmidt.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11578972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juranek J, Mukherjee K, Kordas B, Załęcki M, Korytko A, Zglejc-Waszak K, Szuszkiewicz J, Banach M. Role of RAGE in the pathogenesis of neurological disorders. Neurosci Bull. 2022;38:1248–62. 10.1007/s12264-022-00878-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9554177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35729453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalid M, Petroianu G, Adem A. Advanced glycation end products and diabetes mellitus: mechanisms and perspectives. Biomolecules. 2022;12:542. 10.3390/biom12040542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9030615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35454131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen CY, Lu CH, Wu CH, Li KJ, Kuo YM, Hsieh SC, Yu CL. The development of maillard reaction, and advanced glycation end product (AGE)-receptor for AGE (RAGE) signaling inhibitors as novel therapeutic strategies for patients with AGE-related diseases. Molecules. 2020;25:5591. 10.3390/molecules25235591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7729569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33261212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenga Ma Bonda W, Fournet M, Zhai R, Lutz J, Blondonnet R, Bourgne C, Leclaire C, Saint-Béat C, Theilliere C, Belville C, Bouvier D, Blanchon L, Berger M, Sapin V, Jabaudon M. Receptor for advanced glycation end-products promotes activation of alveolar macrophages through the nlrp3 inflammasome/TXNIP axis in acute lung injury. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23:11659. 10.3390/ijms231911659.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9569658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36232959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Killian KN, Kosanovich JL, Lipp MA, Empey KM, Oury TD, Perkins TN. RAGE contributes to allergen driven severe neutrophilic airway inflammation via NLRP3 inflammasome activation in mice. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1039997. 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1039997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9910358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36776857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaidt MM, Hornung V. The NLRP3 inflammasome renders cell death pro-inflammatory. J Mol Biol. 2018;430:133–41. 10.1016/j.jmb.2017.11.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29203171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma M, de Alba E. Structure, activation and regulation of NLRP3 and AIM2 inflammasomes. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22:872. 10.3390/ijms22020872.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7830601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33467177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao J, Sterling K, Wang Z, Zhang Y, Song W. The role of inflammasomes in human diseases and their potential as therapeutic targets. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2024;9:10. 10.1038/s41392-023-01687-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10766654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38177104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rathinam VA, Fitzgerald KA. Inflammasome complexes: emerging mechanisms and effector functions. Cell. 2016;165:792–800. 10.1016/j.cell.2016.03.046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5503689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27153493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paerewijck O, Lamkanfi M. The human inflammasomes. Mol Aspects Med. 2022;88:101100. 10.1016/j.mam.2022.101100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35696786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigues TS, de Sá KSG, Ishimoto AY, Becerra A, Oliveira S, Almeida L, Gonçalves AV, Perucello DB, Andrade WA, Castro R, Veras FP, Toller-Kawahisa JE, Nascimento DC, de Lima MHF, Silva CMS, Caetite DB, Martins RB, Castro IA, Pontelli MC, de Barros FC, do Amaral NB, Giannini MC, Bonjorno LP, Lopes MIF, Santana RC, Vilar FC, Auxiliadora-Martins M, Luppino-Assad R, de Almeida SCL, de Oliveira FR, Batah SS, Siyuan L, Benatti MN, Cunha TM, Alves-Filho JC, Cunha FQ, Cunha LD, Frantz FG, Kohlsdorf T, Fabro AT, Arruda E, de Oliveira RDR, Louzada-Junior P, Zamboni DS. Inflammasomes are activated in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection and are associated with COVID-19 severity in patients. J Exp Med. 2021;218:e20201707. 10.1084/jem.20201707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7684031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33231615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terpos E, Ntanasis-Stathopoulos I, Elalamy I, Kastritis E, Sergentanis TN, Politou M, Psaltopoulou T, Gerotziafas G, Dimopoulos MA. Hematological findings and complications of COVID-19. Am J Hematol. 2020;95:834–47. 10.1002/ajh.25829.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32282949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rayamajhi M, Zhang Y, Miao EA. Detection of pyroptosis by measuring released lactate dehydrogenase activity. Methods Mol Biol. 2013;1040:85–90. 10.1007/978-1-62703-523-1_7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3756820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23852598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin M, Marrone L, Peace CG, O'Neill LAJ. NLRP3, the inflammasome and COVID-19 infection .QJM. 2023;116:502–507. 10.1093/qjmed/hcad011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10382191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36661317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conigliaro P, Triggianese P, Ballanti E, Perricone C, Perricone R, Chimenti MS. Complement, infection, and autoimmunity. Curr Opin Rheumatol. 2019;31:532–41. 10.1097/BOR.0000000000000633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31192812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan BH, Li X, Winkler AR, Cunningham KM, Kuai J, Greco RM, Nocka KH, Fitz LJ, Wright JF, Pittman DD, Tan XY, Paulsen JE, Lin LL, Winkler DG. Complement C3a, CpG oligos, and DNA/C3a complex stimulate IFN-α production in a receptor for advanced glycation end product-dependent manner. J Immunol. 2010;185:4213–22. 10.4049/jimmunol.1000863.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20817881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Luo C, Chen J, Sun Y, Pu D, Lv A, Zhu S, Wu J, Wang M, Zhou J, Liao Z, Zhao K, Xiao Q. High glucose-induced complement component 3 up-regulation via RAGE-p38MAPK-NF-κB signalling in astrocytes: in vivo and in vitro studies. J Cell Mol Med. 2018;22:6087–98. 10.1111/jcmm.13884.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6237571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30246940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirtipal N, Bharadwaj S, Kang SG. From SARS to SARS-CoV-2, insights on structure, pathogenicity and immunity aspects of pandemic human coronaviruses. Infect Genet Evol. 2020;85:104502. 10.1016/j.meegid.2020.104502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7425554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32798769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang F, Deng L, Zhang L, Cai Y, Cheung CW, Xia Z. Review of the clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). J Gen Intern Med. 2020;35:1545–9. 10.1007/s11606-020-05762-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7088708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32133578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiersinga WJ, Rhodes A, Cheng AC, Peacock SJ, Prescott HC. Pathophysiology, transmission, diagnosis, and treatment of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a review. JAMA. 2020;324:782–93. 10.1001/jama.2020.12839.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32648899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothan HA, Byrareddy SN. The epidemiology and pathogenesis of coronavirus disease (COVID-19) outbreak. J Autoimmun. 2020;109: 102433. 10.1016/j.jaut.2020.102433.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32113704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M, Khan H, Khan S, Nawaz M. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease (COVID-19) cases at a screening clinic during the early outbreak period: a single-centre study. J Med Microbiol. 2020;69:1114–23. 10.1099/jmm.0.001231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7642977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32783802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu B, Huang S, Yin L. The cytokine storm and COVID-19. J Med Virol. 2021;93:250–6. 10.1002/jmv.26232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32592501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arya R, Kumari S, Pandey B, Mistry H, Bihani SC, Das A, Prashar V, Gupta GD, Panicker L, Kumar M. Structural insights into SARS-CoV-2 proteins. J Mol Biol. 2021;433:166725. 10.1016/j.jmb.2020.11.024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33245961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M, Kleine-Weber H, Schroeder S, Krüger N, Herrler T, Erichsen S, Schiergens TS, Herrler G, Wu NH, Nitsche A, Müller MA, Drosten C, Pöhlmann S. SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor. Cell. 2020;181:271-280.e8. 10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Chen J, Yu X, Lan HY. Signaling mechanisms of SARS-CoV-2 Nucleocapsid protein in viral infection, cell death and inflammation. Int J Biol Sci. 2022;18:4704–13. 10.7150/ijbs.72663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9305276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35874957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao T, Zhu L, Liu H, Zhang X, Wang T, Fu Y, Li H, Dong Q, Hu Y, Zhang Z, Jin J, Liu Z, Yang W, Liu Y, Jin Y, Li K, Xiao Y, Liu J, Zhao H, Liu Y, Li P, Song J, Zhang L, Gao Y, Kang S, Chen S, Ma Q, Bian X, Chen W, Liu X, Mao Q, Cao C. Highly pathogenic coronavirus N protein aggravates inflammation by MASP-2-mediated lectin complement pathway overactivation. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022;7:318. 10.1038/s41392-022-01133-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9470675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36100602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia J, Tang W, Wang J, Lai D, Xu Q, Huang R, Hu Y, Gong X, Fan J, Shu Q, Xu J. SARS-CoV-2 N protein induces acute lung injury in mice via NF-ĸB activation. Front Immunol. 2021;12:791753. 10.3389/fimmu.2021.791753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8688532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34950152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Ma L, Cai S, Zhuang Z, Zhao Z, Jin S, Xie W, Zhou L, Zhang L, Zhao J, Cui J. RNA-induced liquid phase separation of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid protein facilitates NF-κB hyper-activation and inflammation. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2021;6:167. 10.1038/s41392-021-00575-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8065320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33895773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan P, Shen M, Yu Z, Ge W, Chen K, Tian M, Xiao F, Wang Z, Wang J, Jia Y, Wang W, Wan P, Zhang J, Chen W, Lei Z, Chen X, Luo Z, Zhang Q, Xu M, Li G, Li Y, Wu J. SARS-CoV-2 N protein promotes NLRP3 inflammasome activation to induce hyperinflammation. Nat Commun. 2021;12:4664. 10.1038/s41467-021-25015-6. (Erratum.In:NatCommun12:5306).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8329225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34341353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Francesco EM, Vella V, Belfiore A. COVID-19 and diabetes: the importance of controlling RAGE. Front Endocrinol Lausanne. 2020;14:526. 10.3389/fendo.2020.00526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7375019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32760352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katsoulis O, Guo R, Singanayagam A. When it comes to COVID-19, inflammation is all the RAGE. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol. 2023;69:489–90. 10.1165/rcmb.2023-0227ED.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10633835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37489933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salehi M, Amiri S, Ilghari D, Hasham LFA, Piri H. The remarkable roles of the receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE) and its soluble isoforms in COVID-19: the importance of RAGE pathway in the lung injuries. Indian J Clin Biochem. 2023;38:159–71. 10.1007/s12291-022-01081-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9387879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35999871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthay ZA, Fields AT, Wick KD, Jones C, Lane HC, Herrera K, Nuñez-Garcia B, Gennatas E, Hendrickson CM, Kornblith AE, Matthay MA, Kornblith LZ. COVID-19 associated coagulopathy inflammation thrombosis (Co-ACIT) Study Group. Association of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid viral antigen and the receptor for advanced glycation end products with development of severe disease in patients presenting to the emergency department with COVID-19. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1130821. 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1130821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10070743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37026003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu M, Chen Y, Xia H, Wang C, Tan CY, Cai X, Liu Y, Ji F, Xiong P, Liu R, Guan Y, Duan Y, Kuang D, Xu S, Cai H, Xia Q, Yang D, Wang MW, Chiu IM, Cheng C, Ahern PP, Liu L, Wang G, Surana NK, Xia T, Kasper DL. Transcriptional and proteomic insights into the host response in fatal COVID-19 cases. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2020;117:28336–43. 10.1073/pnas.2018030117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7668053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33082228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L, Long X, Xu Q, Tan J, Wang G, Cao Y, Wei J, Luo H, Zhu H, Huang L, Meng F, Huang L, Wang N, Zhou X, Zhao L, Chen X, Mao Z, Chen C, Li Z, Sun Z, Zhao J, Wang D, Huang G, Wang W, Zhou J. Elevated serum levels of S100A8/A9 and HMGB1 at hospital admission are correlated with inferior clinical outcomes in COVID-19 patients. Cell Mol Immunol. 2020;17:992–4. 10.1038/s41423-020-0492-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7332851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32620787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aceti A, Margarucci LM, Scaramucci E, Orsini M, Salerno G, Di Sante G, Gianfranceschi G, Di Liddo R, Valeriani F, Ria F, Simmaco M, Parnigotto PP, Vitali M, Romano Spica V, Michetti F. Serum S100B protein as a marker of severity in Covid-19 patients. Sci Rep. 2020;10:18665. 10.1038/s41598-020-75618-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7596559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33122776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellani G, Laffey JG, Pham T, Fan E, Brochard L, Esteban A, Gattinoni L, van Haren F, Larsson A, McAuley DF, Ranieri M, Rubenfeld G, Thompson BT, Wrigge H, Slutsky AS, Pesenti A; LUNG SAFE Investigators; ESICM Trials Group. Epidemiology, Patterns of Care, and Mortality for Patients With Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome in Intensive Care Units in 50 Countries. JAMA. 2016;315(8):788–800. 10.1001/jama.2016.0291. Erratum in: JAMA. 2016 Jul 19;316(3):350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26903337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthay MA, McAuley DF, Ware LB. Clinical trials in acute respiratory distress syndrome: challenges and opportunities. Lancet Respir Med. 2017;5(6):524–34. 10.1016/S2213-2600(17)30188-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28664851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabaudon M, Berthelin P, Pranal T, Roszyk L, Godet T, Faure JS, Chabanne R, Eisenmann N, Lautrette A, Belville C, Blondonnet R, Cayot S, Gillart T, Pascal J, Skrzypczak Y, Souweine B, Blanchon L, Sapin V, Pereira B, Constantin JM. Receptor for advanced glycation end-products and ARDS prediction: a multicentre observational study. Sci Rep. 2018;8(1):2603. 10.1038/s41598-018-20994-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5805783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29422518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabaudon M, Blondonnet R, Roszyk L, Bouvier D, Audard J, Clairefond G, Fournier M, Marceau G, Déchelotte P, Pereira B, Sapin V, Constantin JM. Soluble receptor for advanced glycation end-products predicts impaired alveolar fluid clearance in acute respiratory distress syndrome. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2015;192(2):191–9. 10.1164/rccm.201501-0020OC.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25932660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapandji N, Yvin E, Devriese M, de Margerie-Mellon C, Moratelli G, Lemiale V, Jabaudon M, Azoulay E, Constantin JM, Dumas G. Importance of lung epithelial injury in COVID-19-associated acute respiratory distress syndrome: value of plasma soluble receptor for advanced glycation end-products. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2021;204(3):359–62. 10.1164/rccm.202104-1070LE.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8513587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34033529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mrozek S, Jabaudon M, Jaber S, Paugam-Burtz C, Lefrant JY, Rouby JJ, Asehnoune K, Allaouchiche B, Baldesi O, Leone M, Lu Q, Bazin JE, Roszyk L, Sapin V, Futier E, Pereira B, Constantin JM. Azurea network. Elevated plasma levels of sRAGE are associated with nonfocal CT-based lung imaging in patients with ards: a prospective multicenter study. Chest. 2016;150(5):998–1007. 10.1016/j.chest.2016.03.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27018314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradley BT, Maioli H, Johnston R, Chaudhry I, Fink SL, Xu H, Najafian B, Deutsch G, Lacy JM, Williams T, Yarid N, Marshall DA. Histopathology and ultrastructural findings of fatal COVID-19 infections in Washington state: a case series. Lancet. 2020;396(10247):320–332. 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31305-2. Epub 2020 Jul 16. Erratum in: Lancet. 2020 Aug 1;396(10247):312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7365650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32682491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim A, Radujkovic A, Weigand MA, Merle U. Soluble receptor for advanced glycation end products (sRAGE) as a biomarker of COVID-19 disease severity and indicator of the need for mechanical ventilation. ARDS mortality Ann Intensive Care. 2021;11:50. 10.1186/s13613-021-00836-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7983090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33751264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wick KD, Siegel L, Neaton JD, Oldmixon C, Lundgren J, Dewar RL, Lane HC, Thompson BT, Matthay MA. ACTIV-3/TICO study group. RAGE has potential pathogenetic and prognostic value in nonintubated hospitalized patients with COVID-19. JCI Insight. 2022;7(9):e157499. 10.1172/jci.insight.157499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9090244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35298440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jessop F, Schwarz B, Scott D, Roberts LM, Bohrnsen E, Hoidal JR, Bosio CM. Impairing RAGE signaling promotes survival and limits disease pathogenesis following SARS-CoV-2 infection in mice. JCI Insight. 2022;7:e155896. 10.1172/jci.insight.155896.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8855831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35076028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller LE, Bhattacharyya R, Miller AL. Diabetes mellitus increases the risk of hospital mortality in patients with Covid-19: systematic review with meta-analysis. Medicine (Baltimore). 2020;99:e22439. 10.1097/MD.0000000000022439.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7535849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33019426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts J, Pritchard AL, Treweeke AT, Rossi AG, Brace N, Cahill P, MacRury SM, Wei J, Megson IL. Why is COVID-19 more severe in patients with diabetes? the role of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2, endothelial dysfunction and the immunoinflammatory system. Front Cardiovasc Med. 2021;7:629933. 10.3389/fcvm.2020.629933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7886785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33614744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roncon L, Zuin M, Rigatelli G, Zuliani G. Diabetic patients with COVID-19 infection are at higher risk of ICU admission and poor short-term outcome. J Clin Virol. 2020;127:104354. 10.1016/j.jcv.2020.104354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32305882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafar N, Edriss H, Nugent K. The effect of short-term hyperglycemia on the innate immune system. Am J Med Sci. 2016;351:201–11. 10.1016/j.amjms.2015.11.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26897277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thimmappa PY, Vasishta S, Ganesh K, Nair AS, Joshi MB. Neutrophil (dys)function due to altered immuno-metabolic axis in type 2 diabetes: implications in combating infections. Hum Cell. 2023;36:1265–82. 10.1007/s13577-023-00905-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10284735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37115481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson BI, Lippman ME. Targeting RAGE signaling in inflammatory disease. Annu Rev Med. 2018;69:349–64. 10.1146/annurev-med-041316-085215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29106804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teissier T, Boulanger É. The receptor for advanced glycation end-products (RAGE) is an important pattern recognition receptor (PRR) for inflammaging. Biogerontology. 2019;20:279–301. 10.1007/s10522-019-09808-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30968282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuleta I, Frangogiannis NG. Diabetic fibrosis. Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Basis Dis. 2021;1867:166044. 10.1016/j.bbadis.2020.166044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7867637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33378699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kay AM, Simpson CL, Stewart JA Jr. The role of AGE/RAGE signaling in diabetes-mediated vascular calcification. J Diabetes Res. 2016;2016:6809703. 10.1155/2016/6809703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4980539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27547766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lien CF, Chen SJ, Tsai MC, Lin CS. Potential role of protein kinase c in the pathophysiology of diabetes-associated atherosclerosis. Front Pharmacol. 2021;12:716332. 10.3389/fphar.2021.716332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8283198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34276388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park S, Yoon SJ, Tae HJ, Shim CY. RAGE and cardiovascular disease. Front Biosci (Landmark Ed). 2011;16:486–97. 10.2741/3700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21196183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egaña-Gorroño L, López-Díez R, Yepuri G, Ramirez LS, Reverdatto S, Gugger PF, Shekhtman A, Ramasamy R, Schmidt AM. Receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE) and mechanisms and therapeutic opportunities in diabetes and cardiovascular disease: insights from human subjects and animal models. Front Cardiovasc Med. 2020;7:37. 10.3389/fcvm.2020.00037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7076074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32211423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bugger H, Abel ED. Molecular mechanisms of diabetic cardiomyopathy. Diabetologia. 2014;57:660–71. 10.1007/s00125-014-3171-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3969857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24477973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibb AA, Hill BG. Metabolic coordination of physiological and pathological cardiac remodeling. Circ Res. 2018;123:107–28. 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.118.312017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6023588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29929976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen CNS, Santerre M, Arjona SP, Ghaleb LJ, Herzi M, Llewellyn MD, Shcherbik N, Sawaya BE. SARS-CoV-2 causes lung inflammation through metabolic reprogramming and RAGE. Viruses. 2022;14:983. 10.3390/v14050983.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9143006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35632725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Ning J, Cao W, Wang S, Du T, Jiang J, Feng X, Zhang B. Research progress of TXNIP as a tumor suppressor gene participating in the metabolic reprogramming and oxidative stress of cancer cells in various cancers. Front Oncol. 2020;10:568574. 10.3389/fonc.2020.568574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7609813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33194655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesh GV, Mohanram RK. Metabolic reprogramming and immune regulation in viral diseases. Rev Med Virol. 2022;32:e2268. 10.1002/rmv.2268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34176174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han R, Liang J, Zhou B. Glucose metabolic dysfunction in neurodegenerative diseases-new mechanistic insights and the potential of hypoxia as a prospective therapy targeting metabolic reprogramming. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22:5887. 10.3390/ijms22115887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8198281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34072616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purdy JG, Luftig MA. Reprogramming of cellular metabolic pathways by human oncogenic viruses. Curr Opin Virol. 2019;39:60–9. 10.1016/j.coviro.2019.11.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6986357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31766001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katopodi T, Petanidis S, Anestakis D, Charalampidis C, Chatziprodromidou I, Floros G, Eskitzis P, Zarogoulidis P, Koulouris C, Sevva C, Papadopoulos K, Dagher M, Karakousis VA, Varsamis N, Theodorou V, Mystakidou CM, Vlassopoulos K, Kosmidis S, Katsios NI, Farmakis K, Kosmidis C. Tumor cell metabolic reprogramming and hypoxic immunosuppression: driving carcinogenesis to metastatic colonization. Front Immunol. 2024;14:1325360. 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1325360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10824957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38292487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polcicova K, Badurova L, Tomaskova J. Metabolic reprogramming as a feast for virus replication. Acta Virol. 2020;64:201–15. 10.4149/av_2020_210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32551788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandel NS. Glycolysis. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol. 2021;13:a040535. 10.1101/cshperspect.a040535.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8091952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33941515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warburg O. Versuche an überlebendem carcinom-gewebe. Klín Wochenschr. 1923;2:776–7. 10.1007/BF01712130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pascale RM, Calvisi DF, Simile MM, Feo CF, Feo F. The Warburg effect 97 years after its discovery. Cancers (Basel). 2020;12:2819. 10.3390/cancers12102819.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7599761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33008042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu L, She ZG, Cheng X, Qin JJ, Zhang XJ, Cai J, Lei F, Wang H, Xie J, Wang W, Li H, Zhang P, Song X, Chen X, Xiang M, Zhang C, Bai L, Xiang D, Chen MM, Liu Y, Yan Y, Liu M, Mao W, Zou J, Liu L, Chen G, Luo P, Xiao B, Zhang C, Zhang Z, Lu Z, Wang J, Lu H, Xia X, Wang D, Liao X, Peng G, Ye P, Yang J, Yuan Y, Huang X, Guo J, Zhang BH, Li H. Association of blood glucose control and outcomes in patients with COVID-19 and pre-existing type 2 diabetes. Cell Metab. 2020;31(6):1068-1077.e3. 10.1016/j.cmet.2020.04.021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7252168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bost P, Giladi A, Liu Y, Bendjelal Y, Xu G, David E, Blecher-Gonen R, Cohen M, Medaglia C, Li H, Deczkowska A, Zhang S, Schwikowski B, Zhang Z, Amit I. Host-viral infection maps reveal signatures of severe COVID-19 patients. Cell. 2020;181(7):1475-1488.e12. 10.1016/j.cell.2020.05.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7205692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32479746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codo AC, Davanzo GG, Monteiro LB, de Souza GF, Muraro SP, Virgilio-da-Silva JV, Prodonoff JS, Carregari VC, de Biagi Junior CAO, Crunfli F, Jimenez Restrepo JL, Vendramini PH, Reis-de-Oliveira G, Bispo Dos Santos K, Toledo-Teixeira DA, Parise PL, Martini MC, Marques RE, Carmo HR, Borin A, Coimbra LD, Boldrini VO, Brunetti NS, Vieira AS, Mansour E, Ulaf RG, Bernardes AF, Nunes TA, Ribeiro LC, Palma AC, Agrela MV, Moretti ML, Sposito AC, Pereira FB, Velloso LA, Vinolo MAR, Damasio A, Proença-Módena JL, Carvalho RF, Mori MA, Martins-de-Souza D, Nakaya HI, Farias AS, Moraes-Vieira PM. Elevated glucose levels favor SARS-CoV-2 infection and monocyte response through a HIF-1α/glycolysis-dependent axis. Cell Metab. 2020;32(3):437–446.e5. 10.1016/j.cmet.2020.07.007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleming N, Sacks LJ, Pham CT, Neoh SL, Ekinci EI. An overview of COVID-19 in people with diabetes: pathophysiology and considerations in the inpatient setting. Diabet Med. 2021;38(3):e14509. 10.1111/dme.14509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7883197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33377213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jana S, Heaven MR, Stauft CB, Wang TT, Williams MC, D’Agnillo F, Alayash AI. HIF-1α-dependent metabolic reprogramming, oxidative stress, and bioenergetic dysfunction in SARS-CoV-2-infected hamsters. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;24(1):558. 10.3390/ijms24010558.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9820273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36614003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian M, Liu W, Li X, Zhao P, Shereen MA, Zhu C, Huang S, Liu S, Yu X, Yue M, Pan P, Wang W, Li Y, Chen X, Wu K, Luo Z, Zhang Q, Wu J. HIF-1α promotes SARS-CoV-2 infection and aggravates inflammatory responses to COVID-19. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2021;6(1):308. 10.1038/s41392-021-00726-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8371950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34408131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bojkova D, Costa R, Reus P, Bechtel M, Jaboreck MC, Olmer R, Martin U, Ciesek S, Michaelis M, Cinatl J Jr. Targeting the pentose phosphate pathway for SARS-CoV-2 therapy. Metabolites. 2021;11:699. 10.3390/metabo11100699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8540749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34677415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Cohenford MA, Dutta U, Dain JA. In vitro nonenzymatic glycation of guanosine 5′-triphosphate by dihydroxyacetone phosphate. Anal Bioanal Chem. 2008;392:1189–96. 10.1007/s00216-008-2365-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18791706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Icard P, Lincet H, Wu Z, Coquerel A, Forgez P, Alifano M, Fournel L. The key role of Warburg effect in SARS-CoV-2 replication and associated inflammatory response. Biochimie. 2021;180:169–77. 10.1016/j.biochi.2020.11.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7659517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33189832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gul R, Kim UH, Alfadda AA. Renin-angiotensin system at the interface of COVID-19 infection. Eur J Pharmacol. 2021;890:173656. 10.1016/j.ejphar.2020.173656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7568848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33086029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Arif G, Khazaal S, Farhat A, Harb J, Annweiler C, Wu Y, Cao Z, Kovacic H, Abi Khattar Z, Fajloun Z, Sabatier JM. Angiotensin II type I receptor (AT1R): the gate towards COVID-19-associated diseases. Molecules. 2022;27:2048. 10.3390/molecules27072048.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9000463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35408447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedreanez A, Mosquera J, Munoz N, Robalino J, Tene D. Diabetes, heart damage, and angiotensin II. What is the relationship link between them? A minireview. Endocr Regul. 2022;56:55–65. 10.2478/enr-2022-0007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35180818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manigrasso MB, Juranek J, Ramasamy R, Schmidt AM. Unlocking the biology of RAGE in diabetic microvascular complications. Trends Endocrinol Metab. 2014;25:15–22. 10.1016/j.tem.2013.08.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3877224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24011512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim S, Lee ME, Jeong J, Lee J, Cho S, Seo M, Park S. sRAGE attenuates angiotensin II-induced cardiomyocyte hypertrophy by inhibiting RAGE-NFκB-NLRP3 activation. Inflamm Res. 2018;67:691–701. 10.1007/s00011-018-1160-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29796842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watson AM, Li J, Samijono D, Bierhaus A, Thomas MC, Jandeleit-Dahm KA, Cooper ME. Quinapril treatment abolishes diabetes-associated atherosclerosis in RAGE/apolipoprotein E double knockout mice. Atherosclerosis. 2014;235:444–8. 10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2014.05.945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24945577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ihara Y, Egashira K, Nakano K, Ohtani K, Kubo M, Koga J, Iwai M, Horiuchi M, Gang Z, Yamagishi S, Sunagawa K. Upregulation of the ligand-RAGE pathway via the angiotensin II type I receptor is essential in the pathogenesis of diabetic atherosclerosis. J Mol Cell Cardiol. 2007;43:455–64. 10.1016/j.yjmcc.2007.07.044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17761193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muñoz N, Pedreañez A, Mosquera J. Angiotensin II induces increased myocardial expression of receptor for advanced glycation end products, monocyte/macrophage infiltration and circulating endothelin-1 in rats with experimental diabetes. Can J Diabetes. 2020;30083–6. 10.1016/j.jcjd.2020.03.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32654973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pickering RJ, Tikellis C, Rosado CJ, Tsorotes D, Dimitropoulos A, Smith M, Huet O, Seeber RM, Abhayawardana R, Johnstone EK, Golledge J, Wang Y, Jandeleit-Dahm KA, Cooper ME, Pfleger KD, Thomas MC. Transactivation of RAGE mediates angiotensin-induced inflammation and atherogenesis. J Clin Invest. 2019;129:406–21. 10.1172/JCI99987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6307942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30530993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, Chen W, Zhang Z, Deng Y, Lian JQ, Du P, Wei D, Zhang Y, Sun XX, Gong L, Yang X, He L, Zhang L, Yang Z, Geng JJ, Chen R, Zhang H, Wang B, Zhu YM, Nan G, Jiang JL, Li L, Wu J, Lin P, Huang W, Xie L, Zheng ZH, Zhang K, Miao JL, Cui HY, Huang M, Zhang J, Fu L, Yang XM, Zhao Z, Sun S, Gu H, Wang Z, Wang CF, Lu Y, Liu YY, Wang QY, Bian H, Zhu P, Chen ZN. CD147-spike protein is a novel route for SARS-CoV-2 infection to host cells. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2020;5:283. 10.1038/s41392-020-00426-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7714896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33277466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guindolet D, Gabison EE. Role of CD147 (EMMPRIN/Basigin) in tissue remodeling. Anat Rec (Hoboken). 2020;303:1584–9. 10.1002/ar.24089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30768865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoud AM, Ali MM. High glucose and advanced glycation end products induce CD147-mediated MMP activity in human adipocytes. Cells. 2021;10:2098. 10.3390/cells10082098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8392673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34440867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdi A, Jalilian M, Sarbarzeh PA, Vlaisavljevic Z. Diabetes and COVID-19: a systematic review on the current evidences. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2020;166:108347. 10.1016/j.diabres.2020.108347.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7375314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32711003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wild S, Roglic G, Green A, Sicree R, King H. Global prevalence of diabetes: estimates for the year 2000 and projections for 2030. Diabetes Care. 2004;27:1047–53. 10.2337/diacare.27.5.1047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15111519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moskalev A, Stambler I, Caruso C. Innate and adaptive immunity in aging and longevity: the foundation of Resilience. Aging Dis. 2020;11:1363–73. 10.14336/AD.2020.0603.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7673842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33269094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monserrat-Mesquida M, Quetglas-Llabrés M, Capó X, Bouzas C, Mateos D, Pons A, Tur JA, Sureda A. Metabolic syndrome is associated with oxidative stress and proinflammatory state. Antioxidants (Basel). 2020;9:236. 10.3390/antiox9030236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7139344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32178436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raut SK, Khullar M. Oxidative stress in metabolic diseases: current scenario and therapeutic relevance. Mol Cell Biochem. 2023;478:185–96. 10.1007/s11010-022-04496-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35764861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng DL, Wu QR, Zeng P, Li SM, Cai YJ, Chen SZ, Luo XS, Kuang SJ, Rao F, Lai YY, Zhou MY, Wu FL, Yang H, Deng CY. Advanced glycation end products induce senescence of atrial myocytes and increase susceptibility of atrial fibrillation in diabetic mice. Aging Cell. 2022;21:e13734. 10.1111/acel.13734.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9741501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36278684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>St Sauver JL, Weston SA, Atkinson EJ, Mc Gree ME, Mielke MM, White TA, Heeren AA, Olson JE, Rocca WA, Palmer AK, Cummings SR, Fielding RA, Bielinski SJ, LeBrasseur NK. Biomarkers of cellular senescence and risk of death in humans. Aging Cell. 2023;22:e14006. 10.1111/acel.14006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10726868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37803875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franceschi C, Campisi J. Chronic inflammation (inflammaging) and its potential contribution to age-associated diseases. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2014;69:S4-9. 10.1093/gerona/glu057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24833586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedreañez A, Mosquera-Sulbaran J, Muñoz N. SARS-CoV-2 infection represents a high risk for the elderly: analysis of pathogenesis. Arch Virol. 2021;166:1565–74. 10.1007/s00705-021-05042-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7982908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33751241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daffu G, del Pozo CH, O'Shea KM, Ananthakrishnan R, Ramasamy R, Schmidt AM. Radical roles for RAGE in the pathogenesis of oxidative stress in cardiovascular diseases and beyond. Int J Mol Sci. 2013;14:19891–910. 10.3390/ijms141019891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3821592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24084731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dasu MR, Devaraj S, Park S, Jialal I. Increased toll-like receptor (TLR) activation and TLR ligands in recently diagnosed type 2 diabetic subjects. Diabetes Care. 2010;33:861–8. 10.2337/dc09-1799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2845042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20067962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>López-Díez R, Shekhtman A, Ramasamy R, Schmidt AM. Cellular mechanisms and consequences of glycation in atherosclerosis and obesity. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2016;1862:2244–52. 10.1016/j.bbadis.2016.05.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5101176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27166197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pleskovič A, Letonja MŠ, Vujkovac AC, Nikolajević Starčević J, Gazdikova K, Caprnda M, Gaspar L, Kruzliak P, Petrovič D. C-reactive protein as a marker of progression of carotid atherosclerosis in subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Vasa. 2017;46:187–92. 10.1024/0301-1526/a000614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28218562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>