<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39467825</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1478-5153</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nursing in critical care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nurs Crit Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical trial protocol for continuous glucose monitoring in critical care at Hospital Clinic of Barcelona (CGM-UCI23).</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/nicc.13198</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Hyperglycaemia is common in intensive care units (ICUs), with a prevalence of up to 86.2%, increasing mortality. Technology has evolved towards continuous glucose monitoring (CGM), and its use in ICUs began especially during the coronavirus pandemic (COVID-19). Various studies have evaluated the reliability of CGM, indicating that it is safe for use in critically ill patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The aim of this study was to compare the use of CGM with point-of-care glucose (POC-G) testing in ICU. Specific objectives include evaluating the glycaemic control, the frequency of POC-G measurements, the incidence of hyperglycaemia, hypoglycaemia and morbidity and mortality at 90 days.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">An experimental, controlled and randomized clinical trial with a single-blind design will be conducted at Hospital Clinic of Barcelona (HCB). A sample size of 376 participants will be recruited and randomly assigned to two groups: an experimental group, where glycaemic management will be based on CGM; and a control group, where glucose will be managed through POC-G testing, with a blinded CGM.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The primary variable considered will be time in range (TIR), with secondary outcomes including, time above range (TAR), time below range (TBR), number of POC-G measurements, incidence of hyperglycaemia and hypoglycaemia, and mortality. Hypothesis testing will use the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test to assess data normality, with appropriate statistical tests applied, considering a p-value &lt;.05.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RELEVANCE TO CLINICAL PRACTICE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The results obtained will help us understand the impact of CGM on critically ill patients. CGM could potentially reduce the workload of nurses and improve the efficiency of decision-making by the ICU team, enabling early identification and treatment of glucose complications, thereby enhancing safety. Patient safety, a reduction in patient fingerstick and a decreased care burden are the criteria that add value to this research.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Nursing in Critical Care published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of British Association of Critical Care Nurses.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pañero-Moreno</LastName><ForeName>Marc</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-9077-4350</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Critical Care Nurse, Hospital Clinic of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Barcelona Clinical Research Foundation - August Pi i Sunyer Biomedical Research Institute (FRCB-IDIBAPS), Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PhD Programme in Medicine and Translational Research, University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Fundamental and Clinical Nursing, University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guix-Comellas</LastName><ForeName>Eva Maria</ForeName><Initials>EM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9866-7265</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PhD Programme in Medicine and Translational Research, University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Fundamental and Clinical Nursing, University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Villamor-Ordozgoiti</LastName><ForeName>Alberto</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3108-349X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Barcelona Clinical Research Foundation - August Pi i Sunyer Biomedical Research Institute (FRCB-IDIBAPS), Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PhD Programme in Medicine and Translational Research, University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Fundamental and Clinical Nursing, University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>General Nursing Supervisior, Hospital Clinic of Barcelona, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>HOS-2023-021</GrantID><Agency>Dexcom</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>PR-687/2024</GrantID><Agency>Official College of Nurses of Barcelona (COIB)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Catalan Society of Intensive and Critical Medicine (SOCMIC)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Nurs Crit Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9808649</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1362-1017</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">continuous glucose monitoring</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">critical care nursing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">critical illness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hyperglycaemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intensive care</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39467825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nicc.13198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Ochoa PM. Historia y evolución de la medicina crítica: de los cuidados intensivos a la terapia cuidados intensivos y críticos. Acta Colomb Cuid Intensivo. 2017;17:258‐268. doi:10.1016/j.acci.2017.08.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ElSayed NA, Aleppo G, Aroda VR, et al. Diabetes care in the hospital: standards of care in diabetes—2023. Diabetes Care. 2023;46(suppl 1):S267‐S278. doi:10.2337/dc23‐S016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ammar MA, Ammar AA, Wee T, Deshpande R, Band M, Akhtar S. Relationship between glucose time in range in diabetic and non‐diabetic patients and mortality in critically ill patients. J Intensive Care Med. 2022;37(12):1625‐1633. doi:10.1177/08850666221098383</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Shebiny AA, Elewa GM, Gouda EAG, Hashim RM. Glucose intolerance in intensive care patients: incidence and outcome. Egypt J Anaesth. 2020;37(1):28‐34. doi:10.1080/11101849.2020.1864253</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vedantam D, Poman DS, Motwani L, Asif N, Patel A, Anne KK. Stress‐induced hyperglycemia: consequences and management. Cureus. 2022;14(7):e26714. doi:10.7759/cureus.26714</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazzeri C, Bonizzoli M, Cianchi G, Ciapetti M, Socci F, Peris A. The prognostic role of peak glycemia and glucose variability in trauma: a single‐center investigation. Acta Diabetol. 2020;57:931‐935. doi:10.1007/s00592‐020‐01493‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faust AC, Attridge RL, Ryan L. How low should you go? The limbo of glycemic control in intensive care units. Crit Care Nurse. 2011;31(4):e9‐e18. doi:10.4037/ccn2011188</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rijkenberg S, van Steen SC, DeVries JH, van der Voort PHJ. Accuracy and reliability of a subcutaneous continuous glucose monitoring device in critically ill patients. J Clin Monit Comput. 2018;32(5):953‐964. doi:10.1007/s10877‐017‐0086‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tingsarat W, Buranasupkajorn P, Khovidhunkit W, Boonchaya‐anant P, Laichuthai N. The accuracy of continuous glucose monitoring in the medical intensive care unit. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2022;16(6):1550‐1554. doi:10.1177/19322968211027590</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal S, Mathew J, Davis GM, et al. Continuous glucose monitoring in the intensive care unit during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Diabetes Care. 2021;44(3):847‐849. doi:10.2337/dc20‐2219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chow KW, Kelly DJ, Gupta R, Miller JD. Use of continuous glucose monitoring to assess parenteral nutrition–induced hyperglycemia in an adult patient with severe COVID‐19. J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2021;45:208‐211. doi:10.1002/jpen.2032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis GM, Faulds E, Walker T, et al. Remote continuous glucose monitoring with a computerized insulin infusion protocol for critically ill patients in a COVID‐19 medical ICU: proof of concept. Diabetes Care. 2021;44(4):1055‐1058. doi:10.2337/dc20‐2085</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumitrascu AG, Perry MF, Boone RJ, et al. Continuous glucose monitoring for patients with COVID‐19 pneumonia: initial experience at a tertiary care center. Endocr Pract. 2023;29(3):155‐161. doi:10.1016/j.eprac.2022.12.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadhu AR, Serrano IA, Xu J, et al. Continuous glucose monitoring in critically ill patients with COVID‐19: results of an emergent pilot study. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2020;14(6):1065‐1073. doi:10.1177/1932296820964264</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faulds ER, Boutsicaris A, Sumner L, et al. Use of continuous glucose monitor in critically ill COVID‐19 patients requiring insulin infusion: an observational study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2021;106(10):E4007‐E4016. doi:10.1210/clinem/dgab409</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pettus J, Edelman SV. Recommendations for using real‐time continuous glucose monitoring (rtCGM) data for insulin adjustments in type 1 diabetes. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2017;11:138‐147. doi:10.1177/1932296816663747</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parkes J, Slatin S, Pardo S, Ginsberg B. A new consensus error grid to evaluate the clinical significance of inaccuracies in the measurement of blood glucose. Diabetes Care. 2000;23(8):1143‐1148. doi:10.2337/diacare.23.8.1143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park E, Kim M. Clinical use of continuous glucose monitoring in critically ill pediatric patients with diabetic ketoacidosis. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2023;25(8):529‐537. doi:10.1089/dia.2023.0012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez‐Guzman MC, Duggan E, Gibanica S, et al. Continuous glucose monitoring in the operating room and cardiac intensive care unit. Diabetes Care. 2021;44:e50‐e52. doi:10.3803/enm.2021.201</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longo RR, Elias H, Khan M, Seley JJ. Use and accuracy of inpatient CGM during the COVID‐19 pandemic: an observational study of general medicine and ICU patients. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2022;16(5):1136‐1143. doi:10.1177/19322968211008446</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phongmekhin T, Wang R. Continuous glucose monitor accuracy during extracorporeal membrane oxygenation. Crit Care Resusc. 2024;26:58‐59. doi:10.1016/j.ccrj.2023.11.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battelino T, Danne T, Bergenstal RM, et al. Clinical targets for continuous glucose monitoring data interpretation: recommendations from the international consensus on time in range. Diabetes Care. 2019;42(8):1593‐1603. doi:10.2337/dci19‐0028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu M, Zuo Y, Guo J, Wen X, Kang Y. Continuous glucose monitoring system can improve the quality of glucose control and glucose variability compared with point‐of‐care measurement in critically ill patients: a randomized controlled trial. Medicine. 2018;97(36):e12187. doi:10.1097/md.0000000000012138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan A, Tetzlaff JM, Tzsche PC, et al. SPIRIT 2013 explanation and elaboration: guidance for protocols of clinical trials. BMJ. 2013;346:e7586. doi:10.1136/bmj.e7586</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO Data Set: 1.3. World Health Organization. (n.d.).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>