<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469109</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2352-0477</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European journal of radiology open</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur J Radiol Open</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A tri-light warning system for hospitalized COVID-19 patients: Credibility-based risk stratification for future pandemic preparedness.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100603</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100603</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100603</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ejro.2024.100603</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The novel coronavirus pneumonia (COVID-19) has continually spread and mutated, requiring a patient risk stratification system to optimize medical resources and improve pandemic response. We aimed to develop a conformal prediction-based tri-light warning system for stratifying COVID-19 patients, applicable to both original and emerging variants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We retrospectively collected data from 3646 patients across multiple centers in China. The dataset was divided into a training set (n = 1451), a validation set (n = 662), an external test set from Huoshenshan Field Hospital (n = 1263), and a specific test set for Delta and Omicron variants (n = 544). The tri-light warning system extracts radiomic features from CT (computed tomography) and integrates clinical records to classify patients into high-risk (red), uncertain-risk (yellow), and low-risk (green) categories. Models were built to predict ICU (intensive care unit) admissions (adverse cases in training/validation/Huoshenshan/variant test sets: n = 39/21/262/11) and were evaluated using AUROC ((area under the receiver operating characteristic curve)) and AUPRC ((area under the precision-recall curve)) metrics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The dataset included 1830 men (50.2 %) and 1816 women (50.8 %), with a median age of 53.7 years (IQR [interquartile range]: 42-65 years). The system demonstrated strong performance under data distribution shifts, with AUROC of 0.89 and AUPRC of 0.42 for original strains, and AUROC of 0.77-0.85 and AUPRC of 0.51-0.60 for variants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The tri-light warning system can enhance pandemic responses by effectively stratifying COVID-19 patients under varying conditions and data shifts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Chuanjun</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, the Second Hospital of Nanjing, Nanjing University of Chinese Medicine, Nanjing 210003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Qinmei</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Data Science (BMIR), Department of Medicine, Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94304, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, University of California Santa Cruz, Santa Cruze, CA 95064, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Mu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, Rutgers University, 110 Frelinghuysen Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xing</LastName><ForeName>Zijian</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Deepwise AI Lab, Deepwise Inc., Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Zhen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Deepwise AI Lab, Deepwise Inc., Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Danyang</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Changsheng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Imaging, Jinling Hospital, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Longjiang</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Imaging, Jinling Hospital, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Xiao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Imaging, Jinling Hospital, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhan</LastName><ForeName>Xianghao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bioengineering, Stanford University, Stanford 94305, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gevaert</LastName><ForeName>Olivier</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Data Science (BMIR), Department of Medicine, Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94304, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Guangming</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Imaging, Jinling Hospital, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Eur J Radiol Open</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101650225</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2352-0477</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Conformal prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multi-center study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multi-modal artificial intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Risk stratification</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Xiao Li reports financial support was provided by National Natural Science Foundation of China. NA reports a relationship with NA that includes:. NA has patent NA pending to NA. NA If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11513506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejro.2024.100603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2352-0477(24)00058-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>W. H. Organization, Covid-19 epidemiological update: Global overview and sars-cov-2 variants, 〈https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/covid-19-epidemiological-update-edition-167〉, 2024, accessed: 2024-05-17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaumdally S., Tomasicchio M., Pooran A., Esmail A., Kotze A., Meier S., Wilson L., Oelofse S., van der Merwe C., Roomaney A., et al. Frequency, kinetics and determinants of viable sars-cov-2 in bioaerosols from ambulatory covid-19 patients infected with the beta, delta or omicron variants. Nat. Commun. 2024;15(1):2003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10914788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38443359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mallick D., Singh A., Ng E.Y.-K., Arora V. Classifying chest x-rays for covid-19 through transfer learning: a systematic review. Multimed. Tools Appl. 2024:1–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turbow S., Walker T., Culler S., Ali M.K. Care fragmentation and readmission mortality and length of stay before and during the covid-19 pandemic: data from the national readmissions database, 2018–2020. BMC Health Serv. Res. 2024;24(1):622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11090805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38741088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imtiaz S., Batubara E.M., Abuelgasim M.H., Alabad M.M., Alyousef L.M., Alqahtani N.H., Sabbagh A.Y., Alharbi F.A., Ibrahim A.S. Long-term outcome of pulmonary involvement in patients with coronavirus disease 2019: The role of high-resolution computed tomography and functional status–a prospective single-center observational study. Ann. Thorac. Med. 2024;19(2):147–154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11100471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38766376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koyyada S.P., Singh T.P. A systematic survey of automatic detection of lung diseases from chest x-ray images: Covid-19, pneumonia, and tuberculosis. SN Comput. Sci. 2024;5(2):229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Q., Zhan X., Zhou Z., Li Y., Xie P., Zhang S., Li X., Yu Y., Zhou C., Zhang L., et al. Ai-based analysis of ct images for rapid triage of covid-19 patients. NPJ Digit. Med. 2021;4(1):1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8062628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33888856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H., Chen M.-J., Ling L.-Q., Yang J.-R., Huang H.-X., Zhou J.-J., Yang N., Zhang M.-J. A prediction model for clinical outcomes of covid-19 hospitalized patients: construction and accuracy assessment. Clin. Lab. 2024;70(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38469761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ergenc H., Ergenc Z., Araç S., Tor I.H., Alkılınç E. Predictors of disease severity, clinical course, and therapeutic outcome in covid-19 patients: our experience with 1700 patients. Author Prepr. 2024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36394767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farahat I.S., Sharafeldeen A., Ghazal M., Alghamdi N.S., Mahmoud A., Connelly J., van Bogaert E., Zia H., Tahtouh T., Aladrousy W., et al. An ai-based novel system for predicting respiratory support in covid-19 patients through ct imaging analysis. Sci. Rep. 2024;14(1):851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10774502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38191606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asteris P.G., Kokoris S., Gavriilaki E., Tsoukalas M.Z., Houpas P., Paneta M., Koutzas A., Argyropoulos T., Alkayem N.F., Armaghani D.J., et al. Early prediction of covid-19 outcome using artificial intelligence techniques and only five laboratory indices. Clin. Immunol. 2023;246</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9797218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36586431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vovk V., Gammerman A., Shafer G. Springer-Verlag; New York: 2005. Algorithmic Learning in a Random World.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/b106715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhan X., Wang Z., Yang M., Luo Z., Wang Y., Li G. An electronic nose-based assistive diagnostic prototype for lung cancer detection with conformal prediction. Measurement. 2020;158</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieslander H., Harrison P.J., Skogberg G., Jackson S., Fridén M., Karlsson J., Spjuth O., Wählby C. Deep learning with conformal prediction for hierarchical analysis of large-scale whole-slide tissue images. IEEE J. Biomed. Health Inform. 2020;25(2):371–380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32750907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Zhan, X. Guan, R. Wu, Z. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Luo, and G. Li, Online conformal prediction for classifying different types of herbal medicines with electronic nose, 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhan X., Wang F., Gevaert O. Reliably filter drug-induced liver injury literature with natural language processing and conformal prediction. IEEE J. Biomed. Health Inform. 2022;26(10):5033–5041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35877798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Zhan, Q. Xu, Y. Zheng, G. Lu, and O. Gevaert, Reliability-based cleaning of noisy training labels with inductive conformal prediction in multi-modal biomedical data mining, arXiv preprint arXiv:2309.07332, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Husnain A., Hussain H.K., Shahroz H.M., Ali M., Gill A., Rasool S. Exploring ai and machine learning applications in tackling covid-19 challenges. Rev. Esp. De. Doc. Cient. 2024;18(02):19–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Tamala, M.M. Rahmanb, M. Alhasimc, M.A. Mulhimd, and M. Derichee, Artificial intelligence (ai) based prediction of mortality, for covid-19 patients, arXiv preprint arXiv:2403.19355, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenda E.D., Henrina J., Setiadharma A., Aristy D.J., Romadhon P.Z., Thahadian H.F., Mahdi B.A., Adhikara I.M., Marfiani E., Suryantoro S.D., et al. Derivation and validation of novel integrated inpatient mortality prediction score for covid-19 (impact) using clinical, laboratory, and ai—processed radiological parameter upon admission: a multicentre study. Sci. Rep. 2024;14(1):2149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10810804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38272920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yildirim S., Sunecli O., Kirakli C. Mortality prediction with machine learning in covid-19 patients in intensive care units: a retrospective and prospective longitudinal study. J. Crit. Intensive Care-Vol. 2024;15(1):31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Holanda W.D., e Silva L.C., Sobrinho Á.A.d.C.C. Machine learning models for predicting hospitalization and mortality risks of covid-19 patients. Expert Syst. Appl. 2024;240</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hata T., Goto T., Yamanaka S., Matsumoto T., Yamamura O., Hayashi H. Prognostic value of initial serum sodium level in predicting disease severity in patients with covid-19: a multicenter retrospective study. J. Infect. Chemother. 2024;30(3):181–187.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37802152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramón A., Bas A., Herrero S., Blasco P., Suárez M., Mateo J. Personalized assessment of mortality risk and hospital stay duration in hospitalized patients with covid-19 treated with remdesivir: a machine learning approach. J. Clin. Med. 2024;13(7):1837.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11013017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38610602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei S., Xiaqin W., Liwei L., Fasu Z., Ying P., Pingping T., Furong Y. Analysis of risk factors for death in the coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) population: Data analysis from a large general hospital in anhui, china. Cureus. 2024;16(5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11089484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38741698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ince F.M., AlkanBilik O., Ince H. Evaluating mortality predictors in covid-19 intensive care unit patients: Insights into age, procalcitonin, neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio, platelet-to-lymphocyte ratio, and ferritin lactate index. Diagnostics. 2024;14(7):684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11011413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38611597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imzil A., Mansoury O., Oulahbib A., Latifa A., Hind S. Comparative study of the severity of covid-19 infection between female and male patients. Niger. Med. J. 2024;65(1):56–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11238169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39006174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi M.G., Joo Y.W., Kim M.-H., Park S., Shin Y.-Y., Chun E.M. Prognostic factors for predicting post-covid-19 condition in patients with covid-19 in an outpatient setting. J. Korean Med. Sci. 2024;39(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10789531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38225786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Y., Yu X., Zhao H., Wang H., Zhao R., Sheng J. Host susceptibility to severe covid-19 and establishment of a host risk score: findings of 487 cases outside wuhan. Crit. care. 2020;24(1):1–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7081524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32188484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucijanic M., Krecak I., Busic I., Atic A., Stojic J., Sabljic A., Soric E., Veic P., Marevic S., Derek L., et al. Estimated plasma volume status in covid-19 patients and its relation to comorbidities and clinical outcomes. J. Thromb. Thrombolysis. 2024;57(1):50–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37572182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyala N.J., Mboya I., Shao E., Sakita F., Kilonzo K.G., Shirima L., Sadiq A., Mkwizu E., Chamba N., Marandu A., et al. Neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio as a prognostic indicator in covid-19: evidence from a northern tanzanian cohort. medRxiv. 2024 2024–02. 2024–02.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najjar R., Hossain M.Z., Ahmed K.A., Hasan M.R. Exploring machine learning strategies in covid-19 prognostic modelling: A systematic analysis of diagnosis, classification and outcome prediction. medRxiv. 2024 2024–03. 2024–03.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji B., Kong L., Wang J., Liu C., Yuan K., Zhu L., Liang H. Predicting the prognosis of patients with mild covid-19 by chest ct based on machine learning. Chin. J. Acad. Radiol. 2024:1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang X., Shi F., Liu F., Wei Y., Li J., Wu J., Wang T., Lu J., Shao C., Bian Y. Tracheal computed tomography radiomics model for prediction of the omicron variant of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2. Die Radiol. 2024:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38695901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albataineh Z., Aldrweesh F., Alzubaidi M.A. Covid-19 ct-images diagnosis and severity assessment using machine learning algorithm. Clust. Comput. 2024;27(1):547–562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9871425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36712413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Yin, C. Xu, J. Zhu, Y. Xue, Y. Zhou, Y. He, J. Lin, L. Liu, J. Gao1, X. Liu, D. Shen, and C. Fu, Automated machine learning for the identification of asymptomatic covid-19 carriers based on chest ct images, 〈https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12880-024-01211-w〉, 2024, accessed: 2024-02-27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12880-024-01211-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10900643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38413923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhan X., Wang F., Gevaert O. Reliably filter drug-induced liver injury literature with natural language processing and conformal prediction. IEEE J. Biomed. Health Inform. 2022;26(10):5033–5041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35877798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drukker K., Chen W., Gichoya J., Gruszauskas N., Kalpathy-Cramer J., Koyejo S., Myers K., Sá R.C., Sahiner B., Whitney H., et al. Toward fairness in artificial intelligence for medical image analysis: identification and mitigation of potential biases in the roadmap from data collection to model deployment. J. Med. Imaging. 2023;10(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10129875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37125409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wynants L., Van Calster B., Collins G.S., Riley R.D., Heinze G., Schuit E., Bonten M.M., Dahly D.L., Damen J.A., Debray T.P., et al. Prediction models for diagnosis and prognosis of covid-19: systematic review and critical appraisal. bmj. 2020:369.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7222643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32265220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolff R.F., Moons K.G., Riley R.D., Whiting P.F., Westwood M., Collins G.S., Reitsma J.B., Kleijnen J., Mallett S., Group† P. Probast: a tool to assess the risk of bias and applicability of prediction model studies. Ann. Intern. Med. 2019;170(1):51–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30596875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasmy L., Nigo M., Kannadath B.S., Xie Z., Mao B., Patel K., Zhou Y., Zhang W., Ross A., Xu H., et al. Recurrent neural network models (covrnn) for predicting outcomes of patients with covid-19 on admission to hospital: model development and validation using electronic health record data. Lancet Digit. Health. 2022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9023005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35466079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamasoba D., Uriu K., Plianchaisuk A., Kosugi Y., Pan L., Zahradnik J., Ito J., Sato K. Virological characteristics of the sars-cov-2 omicron xbb. 1.16 variant. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10156138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37148902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang T., et al. Handbook of covid-19 prevention and treatment. First Affil. Hosp., Zhejiang Univ. Sch. Med. Compil. Clin. Exp. 2020;68</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tibshirani R., Hastie T., Narasimhan B., Chu G. Diagnosis of multiple cancer types by shrunken centroids of gene expression. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2002;99(10):6567–6572.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC124443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12011421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L., Zhan X., Yang X., Guan X., Wu R., Wang Z., Luo Z., Wang Y., Li G. Cpsc: Conformal prediction with shrunken centroids for efficient prediction reliability quantification and data augmentation, a case in alternative herbal medicine classification with electronic nose. IEEE Trans. Instrum. Meas. 2022;71:1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ke G., Meng Q., Finley T., Wang T., Chen W., Ma W., Ye Q., Liu T.-Y. Lightgbm: A highly efficient gradient boosting decision tree. Adv. Neural Inf. Process. Syst. 2017;30</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Collobert and S. Bengio, Links between perceptrons, mlps and svms, in Proceedings of the twenty-first international conference on Machine learning, 2004, 23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A.N. Angelopoulos and S. Bates, A gentle introduction to conformal prediction and distribution-free uncertainty quantification, arXiv preprint arXiv:2107.07511, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H., Zhan X., Liu L., Ullah A., Li H., Gao H., Wang Y., Hu R., Li G. Unsupervised cross-user adaptation in taste sensation recognition based on surface electromyography. IEEE Trans. Instrum. Meas. 2022;71:1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peacock T.P., Sheppard C.M., Brown J.C., Goonawardane N., Zhou J., Whiteley M., de Silva T.I., Barclay W.S., Consortium P.V., et al. The sars-cov-2 variants associated with infections in india, b. 1.617, show enhanced spike cleavage by furin. BioRxiv. 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar N., Quadri S., AlAwadhi A.I., AlQahtani M. Covid-19 recovery patterns across alpha (b. 1.1. 7) and delta (b. 1.617. 2) variants of sars-cov-2. Front. Immunol. 2022;379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8882843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35237265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A., Mojoli F., Pellegrinelli L., Ceriotti F., Valzano A., Grasselli G., Gismondo M.R., Micheli V., Castelli A., Farina C., et al. Impact of sars-cov-2 omicron and delta variants in patients requiring intensive care unit (icu) admission for covid-19, northern italy, december 2021 to january 2022. Respir. Med. Res. 2023;83</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9984278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36871459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dejnirattisai W., Huo J., Zhou D., Zahradník J., Supasa P., Liu C., Duyvesteyn H.M., Ginn H.M., Mentzer A.J., Tuekprakhon A., et al. Sars-cov-2 omicron-b. 1.1. 529 leads to widespread escape from neutralizing antibody responses. Cell. 2022;185(3):467–484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8723827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35081335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyngse F., Kirkeby C., Denwood M., Christiansen L., Mølbak K., Møller C., et al. Household transmission of sars-cov-2 omicron variant of concern subvariants ba. 1 and ba. 2 in denmark. Nat. Commun. 2022;13(1):5760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9524324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36180438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genc S., Taghizadehghalehjoughi A., Naldan M.E., Gülcü O., Caglayan C., Spanakis M., Nikolouzakis T.K., Alegakis A., Docea A.O., Drocas A.I., et al. Evaluation of various blood biomarkers associated with the outcomes of patients with covid-19 treated in intensive care units. Exp. Ther. Med. 2024;27(2):1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10809360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38274343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang W., Liang H., Ou L., Chen B., Chen A., Li C., Li Y., Guan W., Sang L., Lu J., et al. Development and validation of a clinical risk score to predict the occurrence of critical illness in hospitalized patients with covid-19. JAMA Intern. Med. 2020;180(8):1081–1089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7218676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32396163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty R., Achour N. Setting up a just and fair icu triage process during a pandemic: a systematic review. Healthcare. 2024;12(2):146. (MDPI)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10815731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38255035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>