<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463888</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0143-6228</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>171</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied geography (Sevenoaks, England)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Geogr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Spatial nonstationarity and the role of environmental metal exposures on COVID-19 mortality in New Mexico.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">103400</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.apgeog.2024.103400</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Worldwide, the COVID-19 pandemic has been influenced by a combination of environmental and sociodemographic drivers. To date, population studies have overwhelmingly focused on the impact of societal factors. In New Mexico, the rate of COVID-19 infection and mortality varied significantly among the state's geographically dispersed, and racially and ethnically diverse populations who are exposed to unique environmental contaminants related to resource extraction industries (e.g. fracking, mining, oil and gas exploration). By looking at local patterns of COVID-19 disease severity, we sought to uncover the spatially varying factors underlying the pandemic. We further explored the compounding role of potential long-term exposures to various environmental contaminants on COVID-19 mortality prior to widespread applications of vaccinations. To illustrate the spatial heterogeneity of these complex associations, we leveraged multiple modeling approaches to account for spatial non-stationarity in model terms. Multiscale geographically weighted regression (MGWR) results indicate that increased potential exposure to fugitive mine waste is significantly associated with COVID-19 mortality in areas of the state where socioeconomically disadvantaged populations were among the hardest hit in the early months of the pandemic. This relationship is paradoxically reversed in global models, which fail to account for spatial relationships between variables. This work contributes both to environmental health sciences and the growing body of literature exploring the implications of spatial nonstationarity in health research.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beene</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Community Environmental Health Program, College of Pharmacy, University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque, NM, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Geography &amp; Environmental Studies, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miller</LastName><ForeName>Curtis</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Community Environmental Health Program, College of Pharmacy, University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque, NM, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gonzales</LastName><ForeName>Melissa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Studies, Tulane University School of Public Health &amp; Tropical Medicine, New Orleans, LA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanda</LastName><ForeName>Deborah</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Comprehensive Cancer Center, University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque, NM, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Francis</LastName><ForeName>Isaiah</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Epidemiology and Response, New Mexico Department of Health, Santa Fe, NM, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Erdei</LastName><ForeName>Esther</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Community Environmental Health Program, College of Pharmacy, University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque, NM, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P30 ES032755</GrantID><Acronym>ES</Acronym><Agency>NIEHS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>P50 ES026102</GrantID><Acronym>ES</Acronym><Agency>NIEHS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Geogr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101085119</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0143-6228</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Simpson’s paradox</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">environmental exposure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiscale geographically weighted regression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rural areas</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. Declarations of interest: none.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS2023451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11501077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apgeog.2024.103400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">103400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahmed S, Moore SE, Kippler M, Gardner R, Hawlader MDH, Wagatsuma Y, Raqib R, and Vahter M. 2014. Arsenic Exposure and Cell-Mediated Immunity in Pre-School Children in Rural Bangladesh. Toxicological Sciences 141 (1):166–175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4833103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24924402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anselin L. 1995. Local indicators of spatial association—LISA. Geographical Analysis 27 (2):93–115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonić O, and Legović T. 1999. Estimating the direction of an unknown air pollution source using a digital elevation model and a sample of deposition. Ecological Modelling 124 (1):85–95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aranyi C, Bradof JN, O’Shea WJ, Graham JA, and Miller FJ 1985. Effects of arsenic trioxide inhalation exposure on pulmonary antibacterial defenses in mice. Journal of Toxicology and Environmental Health 15 (1):163–172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3884825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barber GM 1988. Elementary statistics for geographers. New York, NY: Guilford Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böhner J, and Antonić O. 2009. Chapter 8 Land-Surface Parameters Specific to Topo-Climatology. In Developments in Soil Science, Geomorphometry., eds. Hengl T. and Reuter HI, 195–226. Elsevier; 
http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0166248108000081 (last accessed 8 July 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brunsdon C, Fotheringham AS, and Charlton ME 1996. Geographically Weighted Regression: A Method for Exploring Spatial Nonstationarity. Geographical Analysis 28 (4):281–298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro LA, Shelley CD, Osthus D, Michaud I, Mitchell J, Manore CA, and Valle SYD 2021. How New Mexico leveraged a COVID-19 case forecasting model to preemptively address the health care needs of the state: Quantitative analysis. JMIR Public Health and Surveillance 7 (6):e27888.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen F, Leung Y, Wang Q, and Zhou Y. 2024. Spatial non-stationarity test of regression relationships in the multiscale geographically weighted regression model. Spatial Statistics :100846.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comber A, Brunsdon C, Charlton M, Dong G, Harris R, Lu B, Lü Y, Murakami D, Nakaya T, Wang Y, and Harris P. 2020. The GWR route map: a guide to the informed application of Geographically Weighted Regression. http://arxiv.org/abs/2004.06070 (last accessed 19 June 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dasgupta S, Bowen VB, Leidner A, Fletcher K, Musial T, Rose C, Cha A, Kang G, Dirlikov E, Pevzner E, Rose D, Ritchey MD, Villanueva J, Philip C, Liburd L, and Oster AM 2020. Association Between Social Vulnerability and a County’s Risk for Becoming a COVID-19 Hotspot — United States, June 1–July 25, 2020. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 69 (42):1535–1541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7583500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33090977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eicher CL, and Brewer CA 2001. Dasymetric Mapping and Areal Interpolation: Implementation and Evaluation. Cartography and Geographic Information Science 28 (2):125–138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdei E, Meltzer G, Avenbuan O, Awada C, Oyetade O, Blackman T, Kwon S, and Zelikoff J. 2020. Environmentally Marginalized Populations: the “perfect storm” for infectious disease pandemics, including COVID-19. The Journal of Health Disparities Research and Practice 13:68–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdei E, Qeadan F, Miller CP, Kanda DA, Luo L, Gonzales M, Lewis JL, and MacKenzie D. 2022. Environmental uranium exposures and cytokine profiles among mother-newborn baby pairs from the Navajo Βirth Cohort Study. Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology 456:116292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrigan TL, and Parker eds TS 2012. The Concentration of Poverty Is a Growing Rural Problem. Amber Waves: The Economics of Food, Farming, Natural Resources, and Rural America.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faruk MO, Rana Md. S., Jannat SN, Lisa F. Khanam, and Rahman Md. S. 2023. Impact of environmental factors on COVID-19 transmission: spatial variations in the world. International Journal of Environmental Health Research 33 (9):864–880.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35412402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fotheringham AS 2011. Geographically weighted regression. In The SAGE Handbook of Spatial Analysis, eds. Fotheringham A. and Rogerson P, 243–253. 1 Oliver’s Yard, 55 City Road, London England EC1Y 1SP United Kingdom: SAGE Publications, Ltd.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fotheringham AS, and Wong DWS 1991. The modifiable areal unit problem in multivariate statistical analysis. Environment and Planning A: Economy and Space 23 (7):1025–1044.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FracFocus.
2023. About Us. https://www.fracfocus.org/about-us (last accessed 16 November 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frenzel HN, Bloomer RR, Cline RB, Cys JM, Galley JE, Gibson WR, Hills JM, King WE, Seager WR, Kottlowski FE, Thompson III S, Luff GC, Pearson BT, and Siclen DCV 1988. The Permian Basin region. In Sedimentary Cover—North American Craton: U.S, ed. Sloss LL, 0. Geological Society of America; 10.1130/DNAG-GNA-D2.261 (last accessed 14 August 2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1130/DNAG-GNA-D2.261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaynor TS, and Wilson ME 2020. Social Vulnerability and Equity: The Disproportionate Impact of COVID-19. Public Administration Review 80 (5):832–838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32836465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilbert A, and Chakraborty J. 2011. Using geographically weighted regression for environmental justice analysis: Cumulative cancer risks from air toxics in Florida. Social Science Research 40 (1):273–286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorris ME, Shelley CD, Del Valle SY, and Manore CA 2021. A time-varying vulnerability index for COVID-19 in New Mexico, USA using generalized propensity scores. Health Policy OPEN 2:100052.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grineski SE, Collins TW, and Olvera HA 2015. Local variability in the impacts of residential particulate matter and pest exposure on children’s wheezing severity: a geographically weighted regression analysis of environmental health justice. Population and Environment 37 (1):22–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4627709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26527848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haley PJ, Bice DE, Muggenburg BA, Hann FF, and Benjamin SA 1987. Immunopathologic effects of nickel subsulfide on the primate pulmonary immune system. Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology 88 (1):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3564025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harmon ME, Lewis J, Miller C, Hoover J, Ali A-MS, Shuey C, Cajero M, Lucas S, Zychowski K, Pacheco B, Erdei E, Ramone S, Nez T, Gonzales M, and Campen MJ 2017. Residential proximity to abandoned uranium mines and serum inflammatory potential in chronically exposed Navajo communities. Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology 27 (4):365–371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5781233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28120833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatcher SM, Agnew-Brune C, Anderson M, Zambrano LD, Rose CE, Jim MA, Baugher A, Liu GS, Patel SV, Evans ME, Pindyck T, Dubray CL, Rainey JJ, Chen J, Sadowski C, Winglee K, Penman-Aguilar A, Dixit A, Claw E, Parshall C, Provost E, Ayala A, Gonzalez G, Ritchey J, Davis J, Warren-Mears V, Joshi S, Weiser T, Echo-Hawk A, Dominguez A, Poel A, Duke C, Ransby I, Apostolou A, and McCollum J. 2020. COVID-19 Among American Indian and Alaska Native Persons — 23 States, January 31–July 3, 2020. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 69 (34):1166–1169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7451969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32853193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirko KA, Kerver JM, Ford S, Szafranski C, Beckett J, Kitchen C, and Wendling AL 2020. Telehealth in response to the COVID-19 pandemic: Implications for rural health disparities. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association 27 (11):1816–1818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7337797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32589735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoover J, Gonzales M, Shuey C, Barney Y, and Lewis J. 2017. Elevated arsenic and uranium concentrations in unregulated water sources on the Navajo Nation, USA. Exposure and Health 9 (2):113–124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5425493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28553666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoover JH, Erdei E, Begay D, Gonzales M, NBCS Study Team, J. M. Jarrett P.-Y. Cheng, and Lewis J. 2020. Exposure to uranium and co-occurring metals among pregnant Navajo women. Environmental Research 190:109943.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu H, Chen E, Li Y, Xiaochun Zhu T. Zhang, and Xiaofang Zhu. 2018. Effects of Arsenic Trioxide on INF-gamma Gene Expression in MRL/lpr Mice and Human Lupus. Biological Trace Element Research 184 (2):391–397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29159556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Kwan M-P, Kan Z, Wong MS, Kwok CYT, and Yu X. 2020. Investigating the Relationship between the Built Environment and Relative Risk of COVID-19 in Hong Kong. ISPRS International Journal of Geo-Information 9 (11):624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jolliffe IT, and Cadima J. 2016. Principal component analysis: A review and recent developments. Philosophical transactions Series A, Mathematical, physical, and engineering sciences 374 (2065):20150202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karaye IM, and Horney JA 2020. The Impact of Social Vulnerability on COVID-19 in the U.S.: An Analysis of Spatially Varying Relationships. American Journal of Preventive Medicine 59 (3):317–325.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7318979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32703701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katzman JG, Tomedi LE, Thornton K, Menking P, Stanton M, Sosa N, Harkins M, Katzman N, Liu J, Archer GRD, and Arora S. 2021. Innovative COVID-19 programs to rapidly serve New Mexico: Project ECHO. Public Health Reports® 136 (1):39–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7856386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33216679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khazanchi R, Beiter ER, Gondi S, Beckman AL, Bilinski A, and Ganguli I. 2020. County-Level Association of Social Vulnerability with COVID-19 Cases and Deaths in the USA. Journal of General Internal Medicine 35 (9):2784–2787.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7311112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32578018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kucks RP
2005. Terrestrial Radioactivity and Gamma-ray Exposure in the United States and Canada: Gridded geographic images. https://mrdata.usgs.gov/metadata/narad.faq.html (last accessed 11 November 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwan M-P 2021. The stationarity bias in research on the environmental determinants of health. Health &amp; Place 70:102609.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Y, Hoover J, Beene D, Erdei E, and Liu Z. 2020. Environmental risk mapping of potential abandoned uranium mine contamination on the Navajo Nation, USA, using a GIS-based multi-criteria decision analysis approach. Environmental Science and Pollution Research 27 (24):30542–30557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7387200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32468361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindberg A-L, Ekström E-C, Nermell B, Rahman M, Lönnerdal B, Persson L-Å, and Vahter M. 2008. Gender and age differences in the metabolism of inorganic arsenic in a highly exposed population in Bangladesh. Environmental Research 106 (1):110–120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17900557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maier NK, Crown D, Liu J, Leppla SH, and Moayeri M. 2014. Arsenic Trioxide and Other Arsenical Compounds Inhibit the NLRP1, NLRP3, and NAIP5/NLRC4 Inflammasomes. The Journal of Immunology 192 (2):763–770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3884817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24337744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mason GT, and Arndt RE
1996. Mineral Resources Data System (MRDS). The Survey,. https://pubs.usgs.gov/publication/ds20 (last accessed 11 November 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng Y, Wong MS, Kwan M-P, and Zhu R. 2022. Association between Global Air Pollution and COVID-19 Mortality: A Study of Forty-Six Cities in the World. Annals of the American Association of Geographers 112 (6):1777–1793.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng Y, Wong MS, Xing H, Kwan M-P, and Zhu R. 2021. Assessing the Country-Level Excess All-Cause Mortality and the Impacts of Air Pollution and Human Activity during the COVID-19 Epidemic. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18 (13):6883.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8295924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34206915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak A, Islam SJ, Mehta A, Ko Y-A, Patel SA, Goyal A, Sullivan S, Lewis TT, Vaccarino V, Morris AA, and Quyyumi AA
2020. Impact of Social Vulnerability on COVID-19 Incidence and Outcomes in the United States. :2020.04.10.20060962. https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.04.10.20060962v2 (last accessed 16 November 2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2020.04.10.20060962v2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NOAA Physical Sciences Laboratory.
2023. NCEP North American Regional Reanalysis (NARR). https://psl.noaa.gov/data/gridded/data.narr.html (last accessed 11 November 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oak Ridge National Laboratory.
2020. LandScan. Documentation, LandScan. https://landscan.ornl.gov/documentation (last accessed 8 April 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Openshaw S. 1984. The modifiable areal unit problem. Concepts and Techniques in Modern Geography. https://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/10024464407/ (last accessed 16 December 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshan TM, Smith JP, and Fotheringham AS 2020. Targeting the spatial context of obesity determinants via multiscale geographically weighted regression. International Journal of Health Geographics 19 (1):11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7132879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32248807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmani K, Shavaleh R, Forouhi M, Disfani HF, Kamandi M, Oskooi RK, Foogerdi M, Soltani M, Rahchamani M, Mohaddespour M, and Dianatinasab M. 2022. The effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines in reducing the incidence, hospitalization, and mortality from COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Frontiers in Public Health
10. https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/public-health/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2022.873596/full (last accessed 19 June 2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.873596/full</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raqib R, Ahmed S, Ahsan KB, Kippler M, Akhtar E, Roy AK, Lu Y, Arifeen SE, Wagatsuma Y, and Vahter M. 2017. Humoral Immunity in Arsenic-Exposed Children in Rural Bangladesh: Total Immunoglobulins and Vaccine-Specific Antibodies. Environmental Health Perspectives 125 (6):067006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rifat SAA, and Liu W. 2022. One year into the pandemic: the impacts of social vulnerability on COVID-19 outcomes and urban–rural differences in the conterminous United States. International Journal of Environmental Health Research 32 (12):2601–2619.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34554860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Lonebear D, Barceló NE, Akee R, and Carroll SR 2020. American Indian reservations and COVID-19: Correlates of early infection rates in the pandemic. Journal of Public Health Management and Practice 26 (4):371–377.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7249493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32433389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan PH, LeMasters GK, Levin L, Burkle J, Biswas P, Hu S, Grinshpun S, and Reponen T. 2008. A land-use regression model for estimating microenvironmental diesel exposure given multiple addresses from birth through childhood. Science of The Total Environment 404 (1):139–147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18625514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sachdeva M, and Fotheringham AS 2023. A Geographical Perspective on Simpson’s Paradox. Journal of Spatial Information Science (26):1–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scammell MK, Sennett C, Laws RL, Rubin RL, Brooks DR, Amador JJ, López-Pilarte D, Ramirez-Rubio O, Friedman DJ, McClean MD, Cohort Study Team NB, Lewis J, and Erdei E. 2020. Urinary Metals Concentrations and Biomarkers of Autoimmunity among Navajo and Nicaraguan Men. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 17 (15):5263.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7432079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32707746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sequist TD
2020. The Disproportionate Impact of Covid-19 on Communities of Color. Catalyst nonissue content
1 (4). https://catalyst.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/CAT.20.0370 (last accessed 22 October 2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/CAT.20.0370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siordia C, Saenz J, and Tom SE 2012. An Introduction to Macro- Level Spatial Nonstationarity: a Geographically Weighted Regression Analysis of Diabetes and Poverty. Human geographies 6 (2):5–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4235967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25414731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sood A, Pollard C, Suer KL, Vlahovich K, and Walker J. 2021. Caring for miners during the Coronavirus Disease-2019 (COVID-19) Pandemic. The Journal of Rural Health 37 (1):165–168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32277775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soto Mas F, Iriart C, Pedroncelli R, Binder DS, Qualls CR, and Price B. 2019. Impact of Health Care and Socioeconomic Needs on Health Care Utilization and Disease Management: The University of New Mexico Hospital Care One Program. Population Health Management 22 (2):113–119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6459276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29969375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tieskens K, Patil P, Levy JI, Brochu P, Lane KJ, Fabian MP, Carnes F, Haley BM, Spangler KR, and Leibler JH 2021. Time-varying associations between COVID-19 case incidence and community-level sociodemographic, occupational, environmental, and mobility risk factors in Massachusetts. Research Square :rs.3.rs-237622.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Census Bureau.
2021. QuickFacts: New Mexico. QuickFacts. https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/NM (last accessed 6 March 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Census Bureau, U. C.
2021. Race and Ethnicity in the United States: 2010 Census and 2020 Census. Race and Ethnicity in the United States: 2010 Census and 2020 Census. https://www.census.gov/library/visualizations/interactive/race-and-ethnicity-in-the-united-state-2010-and-2020-census.html (last accessed 6 March 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Geological Survey.
2022. Elevation Derivatives for National Applications (EDNA) | U.S. Geological Survey
https://www.usgs.gov/special-topics/elevation-derivatives-for-national-applications (last accessed 11 November 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Paulson KR, Pease SA, Watson S, Comfort H, Zheng P, Aravkin AY, Bisignano C, Barber RM, Alam T, Fuller JE, May EA, Jones DP, Frisch ME, Abbafati C, Adolph C, Allorant A, Amlag JO, Bang-Jensen B, Bertolacci GJ, Bloom SS, Carter A, Castro E, Chakrabarti S, Chattopadhyay J, Cogen RM, Collins JK, Cooperrider K, Dai X, Dangel WJ, Daoud F, Dapper C, Deen A, Duncan BB, Erickson M, Ewald SB, Fedosseeva T, Ferrari AJ, Frostad JJ, Fullman N, Gallagher J, Gamkrelidze A, Guo G, He J, Helak M, Henry NJ, Hulland EN, Huntley BM, Kereselidze M, Lazzar-Atwood A, LeGrand KE, Lindstrom A, Linebarger E, Lotufo PA, Lozano R, Magistro B, Malta DC, Månsson J, Herrera AMM, Marinho F, Mirkuzie AH, Misganaw AT, Monasta L, Naik P, Nomura S, O’Brien EG, O’Halloran JK, Olana LT, Ostroff SM, Penberthy L, Jr RCR, Reinke G, Ribeiro ALP, Santomauro DF, Schmidt MI, Shaw DH, Sheena BS, Sholokhov A, Skhvitaridze N, Sorensen RJD, Spurlock EE, Syailendrawati R, Topor-Madry R, Troeger CE, Walcott R, Walker A, Wiysonge CS, Worku NA, Zigler B, Pigott DM, Naghavi M, Mokdad AH, Lim SS, Hay SI, Gakidou E, and Murray CJL 2022. Estimating excess mortality due to the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic analysis of COVID-19-related mortality, 2020–21. The Lancet 399 (10334):1513–1536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson V, and Mokhiber Z. 2016. 2016 ACS shows stubbornly high Native American poverty and different degrees of economic well-being for Asian ethnic groups. Bulgaria: Economic Policy Institute. https://policycommons.net/artifacts/1407215/2016-acs-shows-stubbornly-high-native-american-poverty-and-different-degrees-of-economic-well-being-for-asian-ethnic-groups/2021476/ (last accessed 24 January 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X, Nethery RC, Sabath MB, Braun D, and Dominici F. 2020. Air pollution and COVID-19 mortality in the United States: Strengths and limitations of an ecological regression analysis. Science Advances 6 (45):eabd4049.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia X, Lin S, and Zhou Y. 2007. Effects of arsenic trioxide on the autoimmunity and survival time in BXSB lupus mice. Zhongguo Zhong xi yi jie he za zhi Zhongguo Zhongxiyi jiehe zazhi = Chinese journal of integrated traditional and Western medicine 27 (2):138–141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17345664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yellow Horse AJ, Deschine Parkhurst NA, and Huyser KR 2020. COVID-19 in New Mexico tribal lands: Understanding the role of social vulnerabilities and historical racisms. Frontiers in Sociology 5:610355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Russell A, Mulholland J, and Huang Z. 2018. Using cell phone location to assess misclassification errors in air pollution exposure estimation. Environmental Pollution 233:261–266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29096298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>