<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39466617</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1550-5154</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Quality management in health care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Qual Manag Health Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19's Effect on Practice Quality Improvement and Transformation Activities: Practice Survey Results.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/QMH.0000000000000472</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The Transforming Clinical Practices Initiative (TCPI) was a 4-year, large-scale, collaborative, peer-based learning initiative for physician practices of all specialties with broad goals to improve the quality of patient care, spend health care dollars more wisely, and assist practices in being ready to succeed under value-based payment (VBP). We investigated whether the COVID-19 pandemic had erased or diminished practice transformation progress made during the TCPI program period, through a follow-up survey of participating practices fielded in October 2021.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In October 2021 to April 2022, we surveyed a probability sample of 2207 primary care and specialty practices that participated in the TCPI, receiving 610 responses. We asked about practice characteristics, financial and ownership stability, clinical performance, and quality improvement efforts, both now and prior to COVID-19. The COVID-19 content was part of a larger survey. Responses were weighted to account for sample selection, unknown eligibility status, and nonresponse. We generated weighted univariate descriptive statistics representative of practices with clinicians enrolled in TCPI. These estimated percentages have a 95% confidence interval of about ±5%. Multivariate analysis of unweighted data examined associations between practice characteristics and other variables of interest.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">For all but one of 13 practice transformation activities engaged in prior to the COVID-19 public health emergency, a majority of practices (at least 52%) reported that the progress on these activities were either not hurt or were helped by their COVID-19 experience. Compared to January 2020, only about 7% of practices reported that their quality of care or clinical performance was worse due to COVID-19, and 32% reported that their quality of care was better. More rural than urban practices reported that half or more of their transformation activities were hurt by COVID-19 (29% and 14%, respectively). Physician-owned practices were more likely to report quality is better today than prior to COVID-19 relative to practices with other ownership types such as hospitals or health systems (43% vs 24%).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Most practices have been able to recover from the deep stress of the COVID-19 pandemic and continue their efforts to improve patient care and performance to succeed under VBP. These results suggest a high perceived return on investment in value-readiness support along with emergency financial support in times of crisis, as well as room to continue preparation for any future pandemic and the national movement toward increased VBP, especially in rural settings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Felt-Lisk</LastName><ForeName>Suzanne</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Author Affiliations: Health Unit, Mathematica, Inc., Princeton, NJ (Ms Felt-Lisk, Drs Chandler and Merrill); and Centers for Clinical Standards and Quality, Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, Baltimore, MD (Ms Johnson, Drs Everhart and Flemming).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chandler</LastName><ForeName>Jesse</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Merrill</LastName><ForeName>Angela</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johnson</LastName><ForeName>Shawan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Everhart</LastName><ForeName>Damian</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Flemming</LastName><ForeName>Robert</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Qual Manag Health Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9306156</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1063-8628</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>None of the authors have any conflicts of interest to disclose. Funded by the US Department of Health &amp; Human Services, Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, under contracts HHSM-500-2014-00034I and HHSM[1]500-2014-000331.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39466617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QMH.0000000000000472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00019514-990000000-00093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Timmins L, Felt-Lisk S, Zhu W, et al. Practice transformation in the Transforming Clinical Practice Initiative was associated with reduced emergency department visits. Ann Fam Med 2024 (Accepted March 4, 2024, scheduled for the July/August issue).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filippi MK, Callen E, Wade A, et al. COVID-19’s financial impact on primary care clinicians and practices. J Am Board Fam Med. 2021;34(3):489–497. doi:10.3122/jabfm.2021.03.200502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2021.03.200502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services. Transforming Clinical Practice Initiative. Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services; n.d. Accessed February 14, 2024. https://www.cms.gov/priorities/innovation/innovation-models/transforming-clinical-practices</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zurovac Y, Barna M, Merrill A, et al. Transforming Clinical Practice Initiative boosted participation in Medicare alternative payment models. J Ambul Care Manage. 2022;45(3)150–160. doi:10.1097/JAC.0000000000000419</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/JAC.0000000000000419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin R. COVID-19’s crushing effects on medical practices, some of which might not survive. JAMA. 2020;324(4):321–323. doi:10.1001/jama.2020.11254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.11254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blumenthal D, Fowler EJ, Abrams M, Collins SR. Covid-19—implications for the health care system. N Engl J Med. 2020;383:1483–1488. doi:10.1056/NEJMsb2021088.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb2021088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satiani B, Zigrang TA, Bailey-Wheaton JL. COVID-19 financial resources for physicians. J Vasc Surg. 2020;72(4) :1161–1165. doi:10.1016/j.jvs.2020.04.482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2020.04.482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrotra A, Chernew ME, Linetsky D, Hatch H, Cutler DM, Schneider EC. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on outpatient care: visits return to prepandemic levels, but not for all providers and patients.2020.The Commonwealth Fund. doi: 10.26099/41xy-9m57</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charles M. COVID-19 and quality metrics: Why practices are struggling to rebound. Fam Pract Manag. 2022;29:37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterji P, Li Y. Effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on outpatient providers in the United States. Med Care. 2021;59(1):58–61. doi:10.1097/MLR.0000000000001448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim BS, Kojima N, Vangala S, et al. Impact of COVID-19 on primary care quality measures in an academic integrated health system. J Gen Intern. 2022;37:1161–1168. doi:10.1007/s11606-021-07193-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-021-07193-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Austin M, Kachalia A. The state of health care quality measurement in the era of COVID-19: the importance of doing better. JAMA. 2020;324(4):333–334. doi:10.1001/jama.2020.11461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.11461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bollen KA, Biemer PP, Karr AF, Tueller S, Berzofsky ME. Are survey weights needed? A review of diagnostic tests in regression analysis. Annu Rev Stat Appl. 2016;3:375–392. doi:10.1146/annurev-statistics-011516012958.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-statistics-011516012958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corlette S, Berenson R, Wengle E, Lucia K, Thomas T Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on primary care practices. February 2021. The Urban Institute. Accessed February 16, 2024 https://www.urban.org/sites/default/files/publication/103596/impact-of-the-covid-19-pandemic-on-primary-care-practices.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Larry A Green Center and Primary Care Collaborative. Quick COVID-19 Primary Care Survey Series 31 fielded September 10-14, 2021. Accessed February 16, 2024. https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5d7ff8184cf0e01e4566cb02/t/6171a03c49caaa47a3532dfe/1634836542339/C19_Series_31_National_Executive_Summary_vF.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holzmeuller CG, Wu AW, Pronovost PJ. A framework for encouraging patient engagement in medical decision making. J Patient Saf. 2012;8(4):161–164. doi:10.1097/PTS.0b13e318267c56e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PTS.0b13e318267c56e</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terry DL, Woo MJ. Burnout, job satisfaction, and work-family conflict among rural medical providers. Psychol Health Med. 2020;26(2):196–203. doi:10.1080/13548506.2020.1750663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13548506.2020.1750663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cromartie J, Dobis EA, Krumel TP, Mgranahan D, Pender J. Rural America at a Glance: 2020 Edition. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Economic Research Services Information Bulletin 221. December 2020. Accessed February 22, 2024. https://www.ers.usda.gov/webdocs/publications/100089/eib-221.pdf?v=7699.4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selee R, Zell E, Murthy BP, et al. Disparities in COVID-19 vaccination coverage between urban and rural counties—United States, December 14, 2020-January 31, 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep:71(9);2022. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7109a2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7109a2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USDA. E-Connectivity for all rural Americans is a modern-day necessity. n.d. Accessed February 19, 2024. https://www.usda.gov/broadband#:~:text=Unfortunately%2C%2022.3%20percent%20of%20Americans%20in%20rural%20areas,a%20recent%20report%20by%20the%20Federal%20Communications%20Commission.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pro G, Schumacher K, Hubach R, et al. US trends in mask wearing during the COVID-19 pandemic depend on rurality. Rural Remote Health. 2021;21(3):6596.doi:10.212605/RRH6596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.212605/RRH6596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The HealthSite.com Editorial Team. Logistics challenges in rural health care: how to bridge the gap. 30;2023. Accessed February 19, 2024https://www.thehealthsite.com/diseases-conditions/logistics-challenges-in-rural-healthcare-how-to-bridge-the-gap-981762/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards ST, Marino M, Solberg LI, et al. Cultural and structural features of zero-burnout primary care practices. Health Aff. 2021;40(6):928–936.doi:10.1377/hlthaff.2020.02391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2020.02391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewa CS, Loong D, Bonato S, Trojanowski L. The relationship between physician burnout and quality of healthcare in terms of safety and acceptability: a systematic review. BMJ Open. 2017;7(6). doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-015141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-015141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Larry A Green Center and Primary Care Collaborative. Quick COVID-19 Primary Care Survey Series 31 fielded September 10-14, 2021. Accessed February 16, 2024. https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5d7ff8184cf0e01e4566cb02/t/6171a03c49caaa47a3532dfe/1634836542339/C19_Series_31_National_Executive_Summary_vF.pdf</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>