<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39468402</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1522-2586</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of magnetic resonance imaging : JMRI</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Magn Reson Imaging</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Repeatability, Reproducibility, and Observer Variability of Cortical T1 Mapping for Renal Tissue Characterization.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmri.29602</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The global rise in kidney diseases underscores the need for reliable, noninvasive imaging biomarkers. Among these, renal cortical T1 has shown promise but further technical validation is still required.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To evaluate the repeatability, reproducibility, and observer variability of kidney cortical T1 mapping in human volunteers without known renal disease.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY TYPE" NlmCategory="METHODS">Prospective.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUBJECTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Three cohorts without renal disease: 1) 25 volunteers (median age 38 [interquartile range, IQR: 28-42] years, female N = 11) for scan-rescan assessments on GE 1.5 T and Siemens 1.5 T; 2) 29 volunteers (median age 29 [IQR: 24-40] years, female N = 15) for scan-rescan assessments on Siemens 3 T; and 3) 16 volunteers (median age 34 [IQR: 31-42] years, female N = 8) for cross-scanner reproducibility.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FIELD STRENGTH/SEQUENCES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">1.5 T and 3 T, a modified Look-Locker imaging (MOLLI) sequence with a balanced steady-state free precession (bSSFP) readout.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ASSESSMENT" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Kidney cortical T1 data was acquired on GE 1.5 T scanner, Siemens 1.5 T and 3 T scanners. Within-scanner repeatability and inter/intra-observer variability: GE 1.5 T and Siemens 1.5 T, and cross-scanner manufacturer reproducibility: Siemens 1.5 T-GE 1.5 T.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STATISTICAL TESTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Bland Altman analysis, coefficient of variation (CoV), intra-class coefficient (ICC), and repeatability coefficient (RC).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Renal cortical T1 mapping showed high repeatability and reliability across scanner field strengths and manufacturers (repeatability: CoV 1.9%-2.8%, ICC 0.79-0.88, pooled RC 73 msec; reproducibility: CoV 3.0%, ICC 0.75, RC 90 msec). The method also showed robust observer variability (CoV 0.6%-1.4%, ICC 0.93-0.98, RC 22-48 msec).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Kidney cortical T1 mapping is a highly repeatable and reproducible method across MRI manufacturers, field strengths, and observer conditions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="EVIDENCE LEVEL" NlmCategory="METHODS">2 TECHNICAL EFFICACY: Stage 2.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Perspectum. Journal of Magnetic Resonance Imaging published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nowak</LastName><ForeName>Magdalena</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6346-197X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Henningsson</LastName><ForeName>Markus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davis</LastName><ForeName>Tom</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chowdhury</LastName><ForeName>Najib</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dennis</LastName><ForeName>Andrea</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fernandes</LastName><ForeName>Carolina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thomaides Brears</LastName><ForeName>Helena</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Robson</LastName><ForeName>Matthew D</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5902-1012</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perspectum Ltd, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Magn Reson Imaging</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9105850</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1053-1807</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MOLLI</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">T1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">kidney</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">repeatability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">reproducibility</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39468402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmri.29602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Eknoyan G, Lameire N, Barsoum R, et al. The burden of kidney disease: Improving global outcomes. Kidney Int 2004;66(4):1310‐1314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamer RA, Nahas AME. The burden of chronic kidney disease. BMJ 2006;332(7541):563‐564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selby NM, Blankestijn PJ, Boor P, et al. Magnetic resonance imaging biomarkers for chronic kidney disease: A position paper from the European Cooperation in Science and Technology Action PARENCHIMA. Nephrol Dial Transplant 2018;33(suppl_2):ii4‐ii14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badrick T, Turner P. The uncertainty of the eGFR. Indian J Clin Biochem 2013;28(3):242‐247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porrini E, Ruggenenti P, Mogensen CE, et al. Non‐proteinuric pathways in loss of renal function in patients with type 2 diabetes. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol 2015;3(5):382‐391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hull KL, Adenwalla SF, Topham P, Graham‐Brown MP. Indications and considerations for kidney biopsy: An overview of clinical considerations for the non‐specialist. Clin Med (Lond) 2022;22(1):34‐40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francis ST, Selby NM, Taal MW. Magnetic resonance imaging to evaluate kidney structure, function, and pathology: Moving toward clinical application. Am J Kidney Dis 2023;82(4):491‐504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolf M, de Boer A, Sharma K, et al. Magnetic resonance imaging T1‐ and T2‐mapping to assess renal structure and function: A systematic review and statement paper. Nephrol Dial Transplant 2018;33(suppl_2):ii41‐ii50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Shi Z, Zhang Y, et al. Native T1 mapping in assessing kidney fibrosis for patients with chronic glomerulonephritis. Front Med 2021;8:772326. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmed.2021.772326.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham‐Brown MP, Singh A, Wormleighton J, et al. Association between native T1 mapping of the kidney and renal fibrosis in patients with IgA nephropathy. BMC Nephrol 2019;20(1):256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedli I, Crowe LA, Berchtold L, et al. New magnetic resonance imaging index for renal fibrosis assessment: A comparison between diffusion‐weighted imaging and T1 mapping with histological validation. Sci Rep 2016;6(1):30088.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peperhove M, Vo Chieu VD, Jang MS, et al. Assessment of acute kidney injury with T1 mapping MRI following solid organ transplantation. Eur Radiol 2018;28(1):44‐50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchanan CE, Mahmoud H, Cox EF, et al. Quantitative assessment of renal structural and functional changes in chronic kidney disease using multi‐parametric magnetic resonance imaging. Nephrol Dial Transplant 2020;35(6):955‐964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao W, Ding X, Ding Y, et al. Evaluation of interstitial fibrosis in chronic kidney disease by multiparametric functional MRI and histopathologic analysis. Eur Radiol 2023;33(6):4138‐4147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bachtiar V, Kelly MD, Wilman HR, et al. Repeatability and reproducibility of multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging of the liver. PLoS One 2019;14(4):e0214921.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox EF, Buchanan CE, Bradley CR, et al. Multiparametric renal magnetic resonance imaging: Validation, interventions, and alterations in chronic kidney disease. Front Physiol 2017;8:696.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dekkers IA, Paiman EHM, de Vries APJ, Lamb HJ. Reproducibility of native T1 mapping for renal tissue characterization at 3T. J Magn Reson Imaging 2019;49(2):588‐596.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kellman P, Hansen MS. T1‐mapping in the heart: Accuracy and precision. J Cardiovasc Magn Reson 2014;16(1):2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dekkers IA, de Boer A, Sharma K, et al. Consensus‐based technical recommendations for clinical translation of renal T1 and T2 mapping MRI. Magma 2020;33(1):163‐176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messroghli DR, Radjenovic A, Kozerke S, Higgins DM, Sivananthan MU, Ridgway JP. Modified Look‐Locker inversion recovery (MOLLI) for high‐resolution T1 mapping of the heart. Magn Reson Med 2004;52(1):141‐146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin ET. Comparison of four Region‐of‐Interest (ROI) placement methodologies for increased repeatability of renal T1. BIC‐ISMRM 2022 Annual Meeting, Cardiff, Wales; 2022. p 151‐159 Available from: https://bic‐ismrm.cubric.cf.ac.uk/static/downloads/BIC‐ISMRM%202022%20‐%20Abstract%20Book.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Euser AM, Dekker FW, le Cessie S. A practical approach to Bland‐Altman plots and variation coefficients for log transformed variables. J Clin Epidemiol 2008;61(10):978‐982.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bland JM, Altman DG. Statistical methods for assessing agreement between two methods of clinical measurement. Lancet 1986;1(8476):307‐310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bland JM, Altman DG. Applying the right statistics: Analyses of measurement studies. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol 2003;22(1):85‐93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raunig DL, McShane LM, Pennello G, et al. Quantitative imaging biomarkers: A review of statistical methods for technical performance assessment. Stat Methods Med Res 2015;24(1):27‐67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koo TK, Li MY. A guideline of selecting and reporting intraclass correlation coefficients for reliability research. J Chiropr Med 2016;15(2):155‐163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu MJ, Zhong WH, Liu YX, Miao HZ, Li YC, Ji MH. Sample size for assessing agreement between two methods of measurement by Bland‐Altman method. Int J Biostat 2016;12(2):20150039. https://doi.org/10.1515/ijb-2015-0039.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gillis KA, McComb C, Patel RK, et al. Non‐contrast renal magnetic resonance imaging to assess perfusion and corticomedullary differentiation in health and chronic kidney disease. Nephron 2016;133(3):183‐192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Boer A, Harteveld AA, Stemkens B, et al. Multiparametric renal MRI: An intrasubject test–retest repeatability study. J Magn Reson Imaging 2021;53(3):859‐873.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan BKC. Data analysis using R programming. In: Chan BKC, editor. Biostatistics for human genetic epidemiology [Internet]. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2018 [cited 2024 May 13]. p 47‐122. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-93791-5_2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makvandi K, Hockings PD, Jensen G, et al. Multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging allows non‐invasive functional and structural evaluation of diabetic kidney disease. Clin Kidney J 2022;15(7):1387‐1402.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bane O, Hectors SJ, Gordic S, et al. Multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging shows promising results to assess renal transplant dysfunction with fibrosis. Kidney Int 2020;97(2):414‐420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diamond C, Pansini M, Hamid A, et al. Quantitative imaging reveals steatosis and fibro‐inflammation in multiple organs in people with type 2 diabetes: A real‐world study. Diabetes 2024;73(8):1285‐1299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandaranayake N, Ankrah‐Tetteh T, Wijeratne S, Swaminathan R. Intra‐individual variation in creatinine and cystatin C. Clin Chem Lab Med 2007;45(9):1237‐1239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toffaletti JG, McDonnell EH. Variation of serum creatinine, cystatin C, and creatinine clearance tests in persons with normal renal function. Clin Chim Acta 2008;395(1–2):115‐119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keevil BG, Kilpatrick ES, Nichols SP, Maylor PW. Biological variation of cystatin C: Implications for the assessment of glomerular filtration rate. Clin Chem 1998;44(7):1535‐1539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cutajar M, Thomas DL, Banks T, Clark CA, Golay X, Gordon I. Repeatability of renal arterial spin labelling MRI in healthy subjects. Magma 2012;25(2):145‐153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Echeverria‐Chasco R, Martin‐Moreno PL, Garcia‐Fernandez N, et al. Multiparametric renal magnetic resonance imaging: A reproducibility study in renal allografts with stable function. NMR Biomed 2023;36(2):e4832.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rankin AJ, Allwood‐Spiers S, Lee MMY, et al. Comparing the interobserver reproducibility of different regions of interest on multi‐parametric renal magnetic resonance imaging in healthy volunteers, patients with heart failure and renal transplant recipients. Magma 2020;33(1):103‐112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasmussen CW, Bøgh N, Ringgaard S, et al. Daytime variation in kidney perfusion, oxygenation, and sodium concentration assessed by multiparametric MRI in healthy volunteers. J Magn Reson Imaging 2024;59(5):1603‐1611.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>