<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39467573</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-9064</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Seminars in thrombosis and hemostasis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Semin Thromb Hemost</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Laboratory Testing for ADAMTS13 for Thrombotic Thrombocytopenia Purpura and Beyond.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1055/s-0044-1792003</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>ADAMTS13 (a disintegrin and metalloproteinase with a thrombospondin type 1 motif, member 13), also called von Willebrand factor (VWF) cleaving protease, acts as a moderator of VWF activity. ADAMTS13 cleaves VWF multimers, thereby reducing VWF activity in blood. When ADAMTS13 is absent (e.g., in patients with TTP [thrombotic thrombocytopenia purpura]), accumulation of VWF in plasma can occur, particularly as "ultra-large" VWF multimers, with this leading to adverse outcomes such as thrombosis. Relative ADAMTS13 deficiencies also occur in several other conditions, including secondary thrombotic microangiopathies (TMA), cancer, and with severe infections such as in COVID-19 (coronavirus disease 2019). These situations might therefore be accompanied with relative loss of ADAMTS13, thereby potentially also leading to pathological VWF accumulation, with this then generating a prothrombotic milieu, thus contributing to enhance the risk of thrombosis. Laboratory testing for ADAMTS13 can aid in the diagnosis of such disorders (i.e., TTP, TMA), and help guide their management, with testing now accomplished using various assays. As most presentations of TTP reflect an acquired condition due to anti-ADAMTS13 antibodies, there may also be a need to test for these, as this will also influence clinical management. We herein provide an overview of TTP, note other conditions in which low levels of ADAMTS13 may be present, and then detail laboratory testing for both ADAMTS13 and associated inhibitors.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Thieme. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Favaloro</LastName><ForeName>Emmanuel J</ForeName><Initials>EJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2103-1661</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Sydney Centres for Thrombosis and Haemostasis, Institute of Clinical Pathology and Medical Research (ICPMR), Westmead Hospital, Westmead, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Dentistry and Medical Sciences, Faculty of Science and Health, Charles Sturt University, Wagga Wagga, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, University of Sydney, Westmead Hospital, Westmead, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pasalic</LastName><ForeName>Leonardo</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8237-6743</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Sydney Centres for Thrombosis and Haemostasis, Institute of Clinical Pathology and Medical Research (ICPMR), Westmead Hospital, Westmead, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Westmead Clinical School, University of Sydney, Westmead, Westmead Hospital, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lippi</LastName><ForeName>Giuseppe</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9523-9054</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of Clinical Biochemistry, University of Verona, Verona, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Semin Thromb Hemost</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0431155</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0094-6176</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>None declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39467573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0044-1792003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>