<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39462717</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-229X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical radiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Radiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Radiation dose to health care workers measured by thermoluminescent dosimetry.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0009-9260(24)00564-6</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.crad.2024.09.018</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To evaluate radiation dose among physicians, nurses, nuclear medicine (NM) technicians, and radiographers at a single institution and to compare the difference in the measured dose during COVID-19 with other periods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A retrospective analysis of the occupational radiation doses received by all workers in diagnostic radiography and NM departments at a single institution during a 5-year period (2018-2022) was performed. Dose measurements were recorded for 94 radiology personnel: radiographers, NM technicians, physicians, and nurses. In addition to descriptive statistics, the Mann-Whitney U-test was used to compare the average annual effective dose between male and female workers and between the periods before and during COVID-19. Kruskal-Wallis test was used to compare effective radiation doses from different quadrants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The annual average effective doses were found to be between 0.58 and 0.72 mSv for males and 0.68 and 0.85 mSv for females. All radiographers, 86% of nurses, and 69% of physicians have received annual average effective doses below 0.99 mSv. The average annual effective doses for all radiation workers were similar in the period before COVID-19 when compared to the period during COVID-19 except for nurses who had significantly lower (P&lt;0.05) doses before COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The average annual effective doses of radiation workers during 2018-2022 were well below the annual dose limit. A relatively higher average effective dose was received among NM technicians compared with other radiation occupational workers. While the caseload during the COVID-19 pandemic was lower due to government policies, the radiation dose to healthcare workers during the pandemic was similar to that before the pandemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Royal College of Radiologists. Published by Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alakhras</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan. Electronic address: mmalakhras@just.edu.jo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Mousa</LastName><ForeName>D S</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan; School of Dentistry and Health Sciences, Charles Sturt University, Wagga Wagga, NSW, Australia. Electronic address: dsalmusa@just.edu.jo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Mohammad</LastName><ForeName>B</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan. Electronic address: bmalmohammad@just.edu.jo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kleib</LastName><ForeName>I</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan. Electronic address: isklaib21@ams.just.edu.jo.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Radiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>1306016</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0009-9260</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39462717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.crad.2024.09.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0009-9260(24)00564-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>