<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39461355</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1474-4457</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Lancet. Infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Immunogenicity of a booster dose of a bivalent (Asp614Gly and omicron BA.4/5 variant) self-amplifying mRNA SARS-CoV-2 booster vaccine versus the BNT162b2 omicron BA.4/5 mRNA vaccine: a randomised phase 3 trial.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1473-3099(24)00565-6</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/S1473-3099(24)00565-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">We previously showed that ARCT-154, a self-amplifying mRNA COVID-19 vaccine, had improved immunogenicity and antibody persistence compared with conventional mRNA or adenovirus vector vaccines. In this study, we compared ARCT-2301, a bivalent self-amplifying mRNA vaccine (Asp614Gly and omicron BA.4/5 variant), with the bivalent Comirnaty omicron BA.4-5 vaccine, to determine whether this improved response persisted in bivalent formulations against different SARS-CoV-2 variants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This randomised, multicentre, phase 3, observer-masked, active-controlled comparative study was done at nine hospitals in Japan. Eligible participants were healthy Japanese adults, aged at least 18 years, who had previously received a full immunisation series of three to five doses of mRNA COVID-19 vaccines (Comirnaty or Spikevax [Moderna]), with the last dose received at least 3 months before screening for this trial. Participants were randomly assigned (1:1) to either ARCT-2301 or Comirnaty BA.4-5 mRNA vaccine using interactive computer-generated randomisation with a block size of four. Randomisation was stratified by gender (men vs women), age group (&lt;65 years vs ≥65 years), type of vaccine used for last vaccination (bivalent omicron BA.1 vs bivalent omicron BA.4/5), and time since last COVID-19 vaccination (&lt;5 months vs ≥5 months). ARCT-2301 was supplied in vials containing 100 μg lyophilised mRNA, 50 μg mRNA each coding for the full-length spike proteins of the ancestral Asp614Gly SARS-CoV-2 strain and omicron BA.4/5 variant. Immediately before use, each vial was reconstituted with 10 mL saline. The comparator original omicron BA.4/5 mRNA vaccine (Comirnaty BA.4-5) was supplied in ready-to-use vials containing a single dose of 30 μg mRNA in 0·3 mL volume. Both vaccines were administered by intramuscular injection in the deltoid of the non-dominant arm. The primary outcome of the study was to show non-inferiority of immunogenicity of ARCT-2301 versus Comirnaty BA.4-5 at day 29 as neutralising antibody geometric mean titres (GMT) and seroresponse rates against omicron BA.4/5. Primary analyses were done in a per-protocol manner. The trial is registered with the Japan Registry for Clinical Trials, jRCT2031230340.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Between Sept 29 and Nov 18, 2023, we enrolled 930 participants (451 men and 479 women) to receive a booster dose of ARCT-2301 (n=465) or Comirnaty BA.4-5 (n=465). The primary immunogenicity outcome to show that the antibody response at day 29 against omicron BA.4/5 elicited by ARCT-2301 was non-inferior to that elicited with Comirnaty BA.4-5 was achieved, both by GMT ratio (1·49, 95% CI 1·26-1·76) and difference in seroresponse rate (7·2%, 95% CI 0·6-13·7). Furthermore, the differences in antibody response between the groups showed superiority for ARCT-2301 against Wuhan-Hu-1 using both criteria, with a GMT ratio of 1·45 (95% CI 1·28-1·63) and a difference in seroresponse rate of 12·5% (95% CI 5·9-19·0), and omicron XBB.1.5, with a GMT ratio of 1·63 (95% CI 1·36-1·94) and a seroresponse rate difference of 16·7% (95% CI 10·1-23·2). Both vaccines were well-tolerated with mainly mild, transient solicited adverse events and no causally related severe or serious adverse events.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERPRETATION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Boosting mRNA-immunised adults with ARCT-2301 induced superior immunogenicity compared with Comirnaty BA.4-5 against both Wuhan-Hu-1 and omicron BA.4/5 variant COVID-19, and elicited a higher response against omicron XBB.1.5. Both vaccines had similar tolerability profiles. Self-amplifying mRNA vaccines could provide a substantial contribution to pandemic preparedness and response, inducing robust immune responses with a lower dose of mRNA to allow wider and more equitable distribution.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FUNDING" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Japanese Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare and Meiji Seika Pharma.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okada</LastName><ForeName>Yusuke</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumagai</LastName><ForeName>Yuji</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kitasato University Kitasato Institute Hospital, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okura</LastName><ForeName>Iori</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Otsuki</LastName><ForeName>Mako</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ishida</LastName><ForeName>Natsuki</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iwama</LastName><ForeName>Yasuhiro</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Minamida</LastName><ForeName>Takeshi</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yagi</LastName><ForeName>Yukihiro</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kurosawa</LastName><ForeName>Toru</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Meiji Seika Pharma, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Boxmeer</LastName><ForeName>Josephine</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSL Sequiris, Amsterdam, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Ye</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Arcturus Therapeutics, San Diego, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smolenov</LastName><ForeName>Igor</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSL Sequiris, Amsterdam, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walson</LastName><ForeName>Judd L</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Walson Consulting, Seattle, WA, USA. Electronic address: jwalson@walsonconsultingllc.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101130150</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1473-3099</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests YO, IO, MO, NI, YI, TM, and YY are full-time employees of and TK is a board member of the study sponsor (Meiji Seika Pharma). YK received fees from Meiji Seika Pharma for medical consultation during this study. IS and YZ are full-time employees of Arcturus Therapeutics, who developed the vaccine. JvB is a full-time employee of CSL Sequiris, which has a marketing agreement for the vaccine. JLW is an independent consultant working for Arcturus Therapeutics.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39461355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(24)00565-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1473-3099(24)00565-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>