<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39461208</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-5347</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>361</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Social science &amp; medicine (1982)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Soc Sci Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The effect of public tolerance towards corruptive behaviour on healthcare efficiency and equity - The case of the UK's COVID-19 vaccination programme.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>117180</StartPage><MedlinePgn>117180</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.socscimed.2024.117180</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0277-9536(24)00633-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Over the past four years, the COVID-19 pandemic has caused significant uncertainty, suffering, and economic disruption on a global scale. In response, governments have been under pressure to ensure equitable vaccine access while meeting vaccination targets quickly. These challenging circumstances created opportunities for nepotism and bribery, increasing attention to corruption risks associated with the pandemic response. This study investigates the relationship between public attitudes towards corruptive behaviour and the efficiency and equity of the UK's COVID-19 vaccination programme. It integrates primary data on public tolerance towards corruptive behaviour with secondary data on the efficiency of the vaccination program at the local authority level in England and Scotland. Employing a survival analysis approach, we estimate Cox Proportional Hazards Models to examine the time required to reach vaccination targets. Our findings suggest moderate tolerance towards corruptive behaviour among the British public, with 28% of survey participants considering monetary bribery and 34% considering nepotism/favouritism as acceptable means to secure early vaccination access. Notably, while public tolerance towards corruptive behaviour generally had a negative impact on the efficiency of the local rollout of the vaccination programme, it appeared to have accelerated its rollout in politically aligned local authorities governed by the Conservative and Unionist Party. However, this increase in efficiency seems to have come at the cost of reduced equity in vaccine distribution. These findings suggest a trade-off between efficiency and equity in vaccine distribution during public health crises, emphasising the need for balanced health policies that ensure fair and effective distribution of vaccines in the future.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sohns</LastName><ForeName>Franziska</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Economics, Finance, and Law, Anglia Ruskin University, Cambridge, UK. Electronic address: franziska.sohns@aru.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghinoi</LastName><ForeName>Stefano</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Communication and Economics, Università degli Studi di Modena e Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy; Department of Economics and Management, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Langosch</LastName><ForeName>Magdalena</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Imperial College Business School, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Soc Sci Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8303205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0277-9536</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Corruptive behaviour</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Healthcare</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Political alignment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">United Kingdom</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39461208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2024.117180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0277-9536(24)00633-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>