<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39467409</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-2518</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>26</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Vaccine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vaccine</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring risk factors for Raynaud's phenomenon post COVID-19 vaccination.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>126470</StartPage><MedlinePgn>126470</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.vaccine.2024.126470</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0264-410X(24)01152-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Raynaud's phenomenon (RP) has recently been observed in recipients of the COVID-19 vaccine. It is unclear whether RP is directly caused by the COVID-19 vaccine. This study aims to investigate the potential causation between RP and COVID-19 vaccination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this study, we searched PubMed, EMBASE, and Web of Science from January 1, 2020, to March 19, 2024. We included the articles with clinical related findings, specifically case reports and case series. Conference abstracts, editorial publications, preprint, and those not specifically related to COVID-19 vaccination are excluded. The refined selection process aimed to ensure a focused and clinically relevant analysis of the association between RP and COVID-19 vaccination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of six articles were ultimately included in this study, comprising five case reports and one case series involving 24 patients with RP after vaccination. Baseline characteristics of the studies showed the RP post COVID-19 vaccination frequently occurred with females compared to males (70.83 vs. 29.17 %). Of the patients with RP post COVID-19 vaccination, 87.5 % (21/24) had either a history or possible predisposing factors of RP. Among the patients with detailed information of vaccination (n = 20), the number of vaccine doses was not related to RP development (45 % (1st) vs. 30 % (2nd) vs. 25 % 3rd dose). For types of vaccine, 75 % of RP were found to have received the administration of mRNA vaccine (15/20).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The risk of bias was increased due to the uncontrolled study designs and small sample size, making it impossible to attribute causation between RP and COVID-19 vaccination. These few cases may have occurred independently of vaccination. However, physicians should still remain vigilant for RP following COVID-19 vaccination, particularly as the number of vaccinated individuals continues to rise.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ho</LastName><ForeName>Tzu-Chuan</ForeName><Initials>TC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Imaging and Radiological Sciences, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chuang</LastName><ForeName>Shih-Chang</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General and Digestive Surgery, Department of Surgery, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan; School of Medicine, College of Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hung</LastName><ForeName>Kuo-Chen</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General and Digestive Surgery, Department of Surgery, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chang</LastName><ForeName>Chin-Chuan</ForeName><Initials>CC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nuclear Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan; School of Medicine, College of Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chuang</LastName><ForeName>Kuo-Pin</ForeName><Initials>KP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate Institute of Animal Vaccine Technology, College of Veterinary Medicine, National Pingtung University of Science and Technology, Pingtung 912, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Cheng-Hui</ForeName><Initials>CH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mass Spectrometry Laboratory, Department of Chemistry, National University of Singapore, Singapore 119077, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Ming-Hui</ForeName><Initials>MH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of General and Digestive Surgery, Department of Surgery, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan. Electronic address: 1120439@kmuh.org.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tyan</LastName><ForeName>Yu-Chang</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Imaging and Radiological Sciences, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan; Graduate Institute of Animal Vaccine Technology, College of Veterinary Medicine, National Pingtung University of Science and Technology, Pingtung 912, Taiwan; Department of Medical Research, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan; Center for Tropical Medicine and Infectious Disease Research, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan; Center for Cancer Research, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung 807, Taiwan. Electronic address: yctyan@kmu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Vaccine</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8406899</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0264-410X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Autoimmune disorder</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Raynaud's phenomenon</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mRNA vaccination</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39467409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2024.126470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0264-410X(24)01152-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>