<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39465801</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-5964</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>41</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Medicine (Baltimore)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comprehending symmetry in epidemiology: A review of analytical methods and insights from models of COVID-19, Ebola, Dengue, and Monkeypox.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e40063</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e40063</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e40063</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MD.0000000000040063</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The challenge of developing comprehensive mathematical models for guiding public health initiatives in disease control is varied. Creating complex models is essential to understanding the mechanics of the spread of infectious diseases. We reviewed papers that synthesized various mathematical models and analytical methods applied in epidemiological studies with a focus on infectious diseases such as Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2, Ebola, Dengue, and Monkeypox. We address past shortcomings, including difficulties in simulating population growth, treatment efficacy and data collection dependability. We recently came up with highly specific and cost-effective diagnostic techniques for early virus detection. This research includes stability analysis, geographical modeling, fractional calculus, new techniques, and validated solvers such as validating solver for parametric ordinary differential equation. The study examines the consequences of different models, equilibrium points, and stability through a thorough qualitative analysis, highlighting the reliability of fractional order derivatives in representing the dynamics of infectious diseases. Unlike standard integer-order approaches, fractional calculus captures the memory and hereditary aspects of disease processes, resulting in a more complex and realistic representation of disease dynamics. This study underlines the impact of public health measures and the critical importance of spatial modeling in detecting transmission zones and informing targeted interventions. The results highlight the need for ongoing financing for research, especially beyond the coronavirus, and address the difficulties in converting analytically complicated findings into practical public health recommendations. Overall, this review emphasizes that further research and innovation in these areas are crucial for addressing ongoing and future public health challenges.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shanmugam</LastName><ForeName>Siva Nanthini</ForeName><Initials>SN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Digital Anti-Aging Healthcare (BK21), Inje University Medical Big Data Research Center, Inje University, Gimhae, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Byeon</LastName><ForeName>Haewon</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3363-390</Identifier></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NRF-2018R1D1A1B07041091, NRF-2021S1A5A8062526</GrantID><Agency>National Research Foundation of Korea</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Medicine (Baltimore)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985248R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0025-7974</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019142" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hemorrhagic Fever, Ebola</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003715" MajorTopicYN="Y">Dengue</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000090005" MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiological Models</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000040063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00005792-202410110-00019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11479419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mergenthaler C, Gurp M, Rood E, Bakker M. The study of spatial autocorrelation for infectious disease epidemiology decision-making: a systematized literature review. CABI Rev. 2022;17:10–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera-Serrano JE, Macías-Díaz JE, Medina-Ramírez IE, Guerrerof JA. An efficient nonstandard computer method to solve a compartmental epidemiological model for COVID-19 with vaccination and population migration. Comput Methods Programs Biomed. 2022;22:106–920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9164625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35687996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunasekar T, Manikandan M, Govindan V, et al. . Symmetry analyses of epidemiological model for Monkeypox virus with Atangana–Baleanu fractional derivative. Symmetry. 2023;15:160–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cacciapaglia G, Cot C, Hoffer AD, Hohenegger S, Sannino F, Vatani S. Epidemiological theory of virus variants. Physica A. 2022;59:127–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8848575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35185268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khairulbahri M. The SEIR model incorporating asymptomatic cases, behavioral measures, and lockdowns: lesson learned from the COVID-19 flow in Sweden. Biomed Signal Proc Control. 2023;81:104416–416.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9676179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36438783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonnet G, Pearson CAB, Torres-Rueda S, et al. . A scoping review &amp; taxonomy of epidemiological-macroeconomic models of COVID-19. Value Health. 2023;27:104–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37913921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markovic S, Rodic A, Salom I, Milicevic O, Djordjevic M, Djordjevic M. COVID-19 severity determinants inferred through ecological and epidemiological modeling. One Health. 2021;13:100355–355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8626896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34869819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekici R, Bozdogan B, Denkbaş E. Development of electrochemical biosensor platforms for determination of environmental viral structures. Appl Sci. 2022;12:12–97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav P, Jahan S, Nisar KS. Fractional order mathematical model of Ebola virus under Atangana–Baleanu–Caputo operator. Results Control Optim. 2023;13:100332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Champagne C, Paulc R, Lye S, Duong V, Leangg R, Cazellesa B. Dengue modeling in rural Cambodia: Statistical performance versus epidemiological relevance. Epidemics. 2019;26:43–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30206040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lizarralde-Bejaranoa DP, Gulbudak H, Kearfott RB, Puerta-Yepes ME. Modeling the uncertainty in epidemiological models through interval analysis considering actual data from two municipalities in Colombia affected by dengue. Appl Math Model. 2022;11:739–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aguiar M, Anam V, Blyussf KB, et al. . Mathematical models for dengue fever epidemiology: a 10-year systematic review. Phys Life Rev. 2022;40:65–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8845267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35219611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davydovych V, Dutka V, Cherniha R. Reaction–diffusion equations in mathematical models arising in epidemiology. Symmetry. 2023;15:2025–125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brauer F. Mathematical epidemiology: past, present, and future. Infect Dis Model. 2017;2:113–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6001967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29928732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiszewski A, Cleary EG, Jackson MJ, Ledley F. The role of NIH funding in vaccine readiness; foundational research and NIH funding underlying candidate SARS-CoV-2 vaccines. medRxiv. 2020;20187559. 10.1101/2020.09.08.20187559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2020.09.08.20187559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan A, Akgül A, Farman M, Chaudhry F, Sultan M, Sen MDL. Epidemiological analysis of symmetry in transmission of the Ebola virus with power law kernel. Symmetry. 2023;15:665–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adimy M, Chekroun A, Kuniya T. Traveling waves of a differential-difference diffusive Kermack-McKendrick epidemic model with age-structured protection phase. J Math Anal Appl. 2022;505:125464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kermack WO, McKendrick AG. A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics. Proc R Soc A: Math Phys Eng Sci. 1927;115:700–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatmawati F, Chukwu CW, Alqahtani RT, Alfiniyah C, Herdicho FF, Tasmi D. A Pontryagin’s maximum principle and optimal control model with cost-effectiveness analysis of the COVID-19 epidemic. Dec Anal J. 2023;8:100–273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu R, Luo Y, Wu J, et al. . Short-term forecasting of daily evapotranspiration from rice using a modified Priestley–Taylor model and public weather forecasts. Agric Water Manag. 2023;277:108123–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steindorf V, Srivastav AK, Stollenwerk N, Kooi BW, Aguiar M. Modeling secondary infections with temporary immunity and disease enhancement factor: mechanisms for complex dynamics in simple epidemiological models. Chaos Solitons Fractals. 2022;164:112709.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bentout S, Tridane A, Djilali S, Touaoula TM. Age-structured modeling of COVID-19 epidemic in the USA, UAE and Algeria. Alexandria Eng J. 2021;60:401–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballesteros A, Blasco A, Gutierrez-Sagredo I. Hamiltonian structure of compartmental epidemiological models. Physica D. 2020;413:132656–656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7375975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falco ID, Cioppa AD, Scafuri U, Tarantino E. Differential evolution to estimate the parameters of a SEIAR model with dynamic social distancing: the case of COVID-19 in Italy. Data Sci COVID-19. 2021:75–90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maki K. Analytical tool for COVID-19 using an SIR model equivalent to the chain reaction equation of infection. Biosystems. 2023;233:105029–129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37690531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klement RJ, Walach H. SEIR models in the light of Critical Realism – a critique of exaggerated claims about the effectiveness of Covid 19 vaccinations. Futures. 2023;148:103119–119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9922436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36819658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chekroun A, Kuniya T. Global threshold dynamics of an infection age-structured SIR epidemic model with diffusion under the Dirichlet boundary condition. J Differ Equ. 2020;269:117–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klemm S, Ravera L. On SIR-type epidemiological models and population heterogeneity effects. Physica A. 2023;624:128928–928.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borri A, Palumbo P, Papaa F, Possieri C. Optimizing restrictions in epidemics via piecewise time-varying SIRD models: application to the COVID-19 Italian emergency. Eur J Control. 2024;75:100902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith MJ, Phillips RV, Luque-Fernandez MA, Maringe C. Application of targeted maximum likelihood estimation in public health and epidemiological studies: a systematic review. Ann Epidemiol. 2023;86:34–48.e28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37343734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Zhong J, Ji Y, Yang F. A new SEIAR model on small-world networks to assess the intervention measures in the COVID-19 pandemics. Results Phys. 2021;25:104283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8105129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33996400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanzas C, Jara M, Tucker R, Curtis S. A review of epidemiological models of Clostridioides difficile transmission and control (2009–2021). Anaerobe. 2022;74:102–541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35217149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arif MS, Abodayeh K, Nawaz Y. Precision in disease dynamics: finite difference solutions for stochastic epidemics with treatment cure and partial immunity. Partial Differ Equ Appl Math. 2024;9:100660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arif MS, Abodayeh K, Nawaz Y. A reliable computational scheme for stochastic reaction–diffusion nonlinear chemical model. Axioms. 2023;12:460–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cobey S. Modeling infectious disease dynamics. Science. 2020;368:713–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32332062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shatanawi W, Raza A, Shoaib Arif M, Abodayeh K, Rafiq M, Bibi M. An effective numerical method for the solution of a stochastic coronavirus (2019-nCovid) pandemic model. Comput Mater Continua. 2021;66:1121–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shatanawi W, Raza A, Shoaib Arif M, Rafiq M, Bibi M. Essential features preserving dynamics of stochastic dengue model. Comput Model Eng Sci. 2021;126:201–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Samreen S, Ullah S, Khan IU, AlQahtani SA, Hassan AM. Numerical assessment of multiple vaccinations to mitigate the transmission of COVID-19 via a new epidemiological modeling approach. Results Phys. 2023;52:106–889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massonis G, Banga JR, Villaverde AF. Structural identifiability and observability of compartmental models of the COVID-19 pandemic. Annu Rev Control. 2021;51:441–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7752088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33362427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Issaka A, Paradies Y, Cameron AJ, Stevenson C. The association between body weight indices, behavioral factors, and type 2 diabetes mellitus in Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis of population-based epidemiological studies. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2023;2:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38016892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ataide VN, Pradela-Filho LA, Ameku WA, et al. . Paper-based electrochemical biosensors for the diagnosis of viral diseases. Microchim Acta. 2023;190:190–276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37368054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pujante-Otalora L, Canovas-Segura B, Campos M, Juarez JM. The use of networks in spatial and temporal computational models for outbreak spread in epidemiology: a systematic review. J Biomed Inform. 2023;143:104422–422.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37315830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acedo L. ed. Mathematical epidemiology in medicine and social sciences. Symmetry. 2019;11:1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Bedi T, Lehmann CU, Xiao G, Xie Y. Evaluating short-term forecasting of COVID-19 cases among different epidemiological models under a Bayesian framework. GigaScience. 2021;10:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7928884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33604654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dankwa EA, Brouwer AF, Donnelly CA. Structural identifiability of compartmental models for infectious disease transmission is influenced by data type. Epidemics. 2022;41:100643–643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9772104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36308994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maleki M, Mahmoudi MR, Heydari MH, Phoe K. Modeling and forecasting the spread and death rate of coronavirus (COVID-19) in the world using time series models. Chaos Solitons Fractals. 2020;14:110–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7381941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li F, Günay B, Nisar KS, Alharthi MS. Incorporating fractional operators into interaction dynamics studies: an eco-epidemiological model. Results Phys. 2023;47:106385–385.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>