<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39465238</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1738-3684</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>21</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Psychiatry investigation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Psychiatry Investig</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhancing Sleep and Reducing Occupational Stress Through Forest Therapy: A Comparative Study Across Job Groups.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1120</StartPage><EndPage>1128</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1120-1128</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.30773/pi.2024.0118</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19) pandemic radically shifted occupational patterns, leading to increased telecommuting and related stressors. Healthcare providers, among the most impacted group, faced heightened risks and workplace changes. Our study examined the efficacy of forest therapy in alleviating work-induced stress across various professions, exploring the need for profession-specific stress-relief strategies in the post-pandemic workplace.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">To examine the impact of COVID-19 on professionals, 62 participants were recruited, consisting of 20 healthcare providers, 21 information technology (IT) specialists, and 21 teachers. Instruments such as Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index and Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale, along with salivary tests for cortisol and melatonin, were used to assess the participants' sleep and stress levels. A specialized forest healing program was implemented among these participants. Data analysis was conducted using SPSS Win Ver. 22.0, utilizing paired t-tests and a repeated measures analysis of variance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Significant improvements were observed in the participants' sleep metrics, depression scales, and stress levels after the forest healing program. Physiological measures indicated an increase in melatonin and a decline in cortisol and dehydroepiandrosterone sulfate levels, with only cortisol changes being statistically significant. Teachers, participating during school vacations, exhibited minimal stress-related physiological changes. Overall, the program demonstrated widespread health benefits regardless of occupation or gender.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study showed that forest therapy reduced stress equally across professions, including healthcare providers, IT specialists, and teachers. Individual physiological responses may play a greater role in stress relief than the specific occupation.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kweon</LastName><ForeName>Juhye</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, International St. Mary's Hospital, College of Medicine, Catholic Kwandong University, Incheon, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Yunsoo</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, College of Medicine, Catholic Kwandong University, Gangneung, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choi</LastName><ForeName>Heeyong</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Convergence Institute of Healthcare and Medical Science, College of Medicine, Catholic Kwandong University, Incheon, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Im</LastName><ForeName>Wooyoung</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Konyang University Hospital, Daejeon, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Hyeyun</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Sleep Medicine Research Center, International St. Mary's Hospital, College of Medicine, Catholic Kwandong University, Incheon, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2021389B10-2323-0102</GrantID><Agency>Korea Forest Service</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Psychiatry Investig</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101242994</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1738-3684</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Forest healing programs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Occupational stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sleep quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Work–life balance</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>
<b>Conflicts of Interest</b>
. The authors have no potential conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30773/pi.2024.0118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">pi.2024.0118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11513866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Vasic M. Challenges of teleworking during the COVID-19 pandemic. Anali Ekonomskog fakulteta U Subotici. 2020;56:63–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deguchi Y, Iwasaki S, Niki A, Kadowaki A, Hirota T, Shirahama Y, et al. Relationships between occupational stress, change in work environment during the COVID-19 pandemic, and depressive and anxiety symptoms among non-healthcare workers in Japan: a cross-sectional study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:983.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8775764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35055803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irawanto DW, Novianti KR, Roz K. Work from home: measuring satisfaction between work–life balance and work stress during the COVID-19 pandemic in Indonesia. Economies. 2021;9:96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosoda M. Telework amidst the COVID-19 pandemic: effects on work style reform in Japan. Corporate Governance. 2021;21:1059–1071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai J, Ma S, Wang Y, Cai Z, Hu J, Wei N, et al. Factors associated with mental health outcomes among health care workers exposed to coronavirus disease 2019. JAMA Netw Open. 2020;3:e203976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7090843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32202646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo FL, Yang PH, Hsu HT, Su CY, Chen CH, Yeh IJ, et al. Survey on perceived work stress and its influencing factors among hospital staff during the COVID-19 pandemic in Taiwan. Kaohsiung J Med Sci. 2020;36:944–952.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7461417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32815248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madero Gómez S, Ortiz Mendoza OE, Ramírez J, Olivas-Luján MR. Stress and myths related to the COVID-19 pandemic’s effects on remote work. Management Research. 2020;18:401–420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burdorf A, Porru F, Rugulies R. The COVID-19 (coronavirus) pandemic: consequences for occupational health. Scand J Work Environ Health. 2020;46:229–230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32356896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benjet C. Stress management interventions for college students in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. Clin Psychol (New York) 2023;30:448–449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32837028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kar N, Kar B, Kar S. Stress and coping during COVID-19 pandemic: result of an online survey. Psychiatry Res. 2021;295:113598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7688436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33264677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song C, Ikei H, Miyazaki Y. Physiological effects of nature therapy: a review of the research in Japan. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2016;13:781.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4997467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27527193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adevi AA, Mårtensson F. Stress rehabilitation through garden therapy: the garden as a place in the recovery from stress. Urban For Urban Green. 2013;12:230–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajoo KS, Karam DS, Abdullah MZ. The physiological and psychosocial effects of forest therapy: a systematic review. Urban For Urban Green. 2020;54:126744.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee I, Choi H, Bang KS, Kim S, Song M, Lee B. Effects of forest therapy on depressive symptoms among adults: a systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2017;14:321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5369157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28335541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung WH, Woo JM, Ryu JS. Effect of a forest therapy program and the forest environment on female workers’ stress. Urban For Urban Green. 2015;14:274–281.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han JW, Choi H, Jeon YH, Yoon CH, Woo JM, Kim W. The effects of forest therapy on coping with chronic widespread pain: physiological and psychological differences between participants in a forest therapy program and a control group. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2016;13:255.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4808918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26927141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim Y, Choi Y, Kim H. Positive effects on emotional stress and sleep quality of forest healing program for exhausted medical workers during the COVID-19 outbreak. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:3130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8910265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35270820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Flynn J. Confronting the big challenges of our time: making a difference during and after COVID-19. Public Manag Rev. 2020;23:961–980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gajendran RS, Harrison DA. The good, the bad, and the unknown about telecommuting: meta-analysis of psychological mediators and individual consequences. J Appl Psychol. 2007;92:1524–1541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18020794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakker AB, Demerouti E. The job demands‐resources model: state of the art. J Manag Psychol. 2007;22:309–328.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bratman GN, Daily GC, Levy BJ, Gross JJ. The benefits of nature experience: improved affect and cognition. Landsc Urban Plan. 2015;138:41–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim HC, Koo CD. Effect of five senses activities in the forest on young children’s daily stress. J People Plants Environ. 2019;22:99–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim H, Lee YW, Ju HJ, Jang BJ, Kim YI. An exploratory study on the effects of forest therapy on sleep quality in patients with gastrointestinal tract cancers. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16:2449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6678486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31295818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim H, Kim J, Ju HJ, Jang BJ, Wang TK, Kim YI. Effect of forest therapy for menopausal women with insomnia. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:6548.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7558331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32916805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaplan S. The restorative benefits of nature: toward an integrative framework. J Environ Psychol. 1995;15:169–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashmi K, Kataria A. Work–life balance: a systematic literature review and bibliometric analysis. Int J Sociol Soc Policy. 2022;42:1028–1065.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirmohammadi M, Chan Au W, Beigi M. Antecedents and outcomes of work-life balance while working from home: a review of the research conducted during the COVID-19 pandemic. Hum Resour Dev Rev. 2022;21:473–516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniel CO. Effects of job stress on employee’s performance. Int J Bus Manag Soc Res. 2019;6:375–382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Semmer NK. Job stress interventions and the organization of work. Scand J Work Environ Health. 2006;32:515–527.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17173207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taris TW, van der Wal I, Kompier MAJ. In: Contemporary occupational health psychology: global perspectives on research and practice, volume 1. Houdmont J, Leka S, editors. West Sussex: Wiley Blackwell; 2010. Large-scale job stress interventions: the Dutch experience; pp. 77–97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JH. A meta-analysis of effects of job stress management interventions (SMIs) J Korean Acad Nurs. 2007;37:529–539.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17615474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amaranto E, Steinberg J, Castellano C, Mitchell R. Police stress interventions. Brief Treat Crisis Interv. 2003;3:47–53.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>