<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39465432</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2524-4655</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>6</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>One health outlook</Title><ISOAbbreviation>One Health Outlook</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Launching Austria's One Health network: paving the way for transdisciplinary collaborations.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>23</StartPage><MedlinePgn>23</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">23</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s42522-024-00116-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In the post-COVID-19 era, stakeholders, including policymakers, funders, and the public, are increasingly seeking for a cross-sectoral systems-based approach to health risks extending beyond conventional measures. Anchored on three health pillars -human, animal, and environmental- One Health offers a promising framework to effectively address this demand. While some nations have already implemented national One Health strategic plans, European countries, in general, are lagging behind the global agenda. On 22 February 2024, an initiative was launched in Austria toward addressing this gap, bringing together multiple sectors and disciplines, marking the initial step in creating a national One Health network. The workshop emphasized the importance of enhancing One Health education and addressed key topics, such as incorporating the environmental pillar of One Health as well as socio-economic and cultural drivers to further our understanding of outbreaks, and establishing trusted communication channels, including data sharing, between disciplines and sectors. Identified challenges encompassed the need for more funding of transdisciplinary research. Opportunities for advancement include initiating local One Health projects and showcasing their positive impacts. Moving forward, efforts will focus on establishing a mature and globally connected One Health framework in Austria and supporting the integration of One Health aspects into education curricula, research programs, and policies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Desvars-Larrive</LastName><ForeName>Amélie</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7671-696X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Department for Farm Animals and Food System Science, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria. amelie.desvars@vetmeduni.ac.at.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Complexity Science Hub, Josefstaedter Strasse, Vienna, 1080, Austria. amelie.desvars@vetmeduni.ac.at.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burger</LastName><ForeName>Pamela</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Interdisciplinary Life Sciences, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Savoyenstraße 1, Vienna, 1160, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khol</LastName><ForeName>Johannes Lorenz</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Department for Farm Animals and Food System Science, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Posautz</LastName><ForeName>Annika</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vice-Rectorate for Study Affairs and Clinical Veterinary Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schernhammer</LastName><ForeName>Eva</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Medical University of Vienna, Kinderspitalgasse 15, Vienna, 1090, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kutalek</LastName><ForeName>Ruth</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, Medical University of Vienna, Kinderspitalgasse 15, Vienna, 1090, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Puspitarani</LastName><ForeName>Gavrila Amadea</ForeName><Initials>GA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Department for Farm Animals and Food System Science, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Complexity Science Hub, Josefstaedter Strasse, Vienna, 1080, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schlippe Justicia</LastName><ForeName>Lia</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Interdisciplinary Life Sciences, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Savoyenstraße 1, Vienna, 1160, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Springer</LastName><ForeName>David Niklas</ForeName><Initials>DN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Virology, Medical University of Vienna, Kinderspitalgasse 15, Vienna, 1090, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ernst</LastName><ForeName>Damien</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Department for Farm Animals and Food System Science, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sohm</LastName><ForeName>Cynthia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Department for Farm Animals and Food System Science, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pontel de Almeida</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Department for Farm Animals and Food System Science, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences and Pathobiology, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schobesberger</LastName><ForeName>Hermann</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Department for Farm Animals and Food System Science, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Veterinaerplatz 1, Vienna, 1210, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Knauf</LastName><ForeName>Sascha</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of International Animal Health/One Health, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Federal Research Institute for Animal Health, Südufer 10, Greifswald - Insel Riems, 17493, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Animal Health, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Justus Liebig University, Frankfurter Strasse 106, Giessen, 35392, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walzer</LastName><ForeName>Chris</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Interdisciplinary Life Sciences, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Savoyenstraße 1, Vienna, 1160, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wildlife Conservation Society, 2300 Southern Boulevard Bronx, New York, 10460, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016422">Letter</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>One Health Outlook</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101769253</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2524-4655</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Austria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Network</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">One Health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Workshop</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s42522-024-00116-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s42522-024-00116-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11514587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adisasmito WB, Almuhairi S, Behravesh CB, Bilivogui P, Bukachi SA, Casas N, et al. One Health: a new definition for a sustainable and healthy future. PLoS Pathog. 2022;18(6):e1010537. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1010537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9223325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35737670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan MS, Rothman-Ostrow P, Spencer J, Hasan N, Sabirovic M, Rahman-Shepherd A, et al. The growth and strategic functioning of One Health networks: a systematic analysis. Lancet Planet Health. 2018;2(6):e264–73. 10.1016/S2542-5196(18)30084-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29880158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwatondo A, Rahman-Shepherd A, Hollmann L, Chiossi S, Maina J, Kurup KK, et al. A global analysis of One Health Networks and the proliferation of One Health collaborations. Lancet. 2023;401(10376):605–16. 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01596-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36682370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi BC, Pak AW. Multidisciplinarity, interdisciplinarity and transdisciplinarity in health research, services, education and policy: 1. Definitions, objectives, and evidence of effectiveness. Clin Invest Med. 2006;29(6):351–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17330451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rigolot C. Transdisciplinarity as a discipline and a way of being: complementarities and creative tensions. Humanit Soc Sci Commun. 2020;7(1):100. 10.1057/s41599-020-00598-5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salunke S, Lal DK. Multisectoral approach for promoting public health. Indian J Public Health. 2017;61(3):163–8. 10.4103/ijph.IJPH_220_17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28928298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alemanno A. The European response to COVID-19: from regulatory emulation to regulatory coordination? Eur J Risk Regul. 2020;11(2):307–16. 10.1017/err.2020.44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sipido KR, Antoñanzas F, Celis J, Degos L, Frackowiak R, Fuster V, et al. Overcoming fragmentation of health research in Europe: lessons from COVID-19. Lancet. 2020;395(10242):1970–1. 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31411-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32559417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bicher M, Zuba M, Rainer L, Bachner F, Rippinger C, Ostermann H, et al. Supporting COVID-19 policy-making with a predictive epidemiological multi-model warning system. Commun Med. 2022;2(1):157. 10.1038/s43856-022-00219-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9729177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36476987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sikkema R, Koopmans M. One Health training and research activities in Western Europe. Infect Ecol Epidemiol. 2016;6:33703. 10.3402/iee.v6.33703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5131506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27906121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control. Antimicrobial resistance surveillance in Europe 2022 – 2020 data. WHO Europe, ECDC; 2022. https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/sites/default/files/documents/Joint-WHO-ECDC-AMR-report-2022.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bundesministerium für Soziales, Gesundheit, Pflege und Konsumentenschutz. Resistenzbericht Österreich–AURES 2021. Bundesministerium für Soziales, Gesundheit, Pflege und Konsumentenschutz; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeleff M, Haddad C, Kutalek R. Between superimposition and local initiatives: Making sense of ‘implementation gaps’ as a governance problem of antimicrobial resistance. SSM Qual Res Health. 2023;4:100332. 10.1016/j.ssmqr.2023.100332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnold KE, Laing G, McMahon BJ, Fanning S, Stekel DJ, Pahl O, et al. The need for One Health systems-thinking approaches to understand multiscale dissemination of antimicrobial resistance. Lancet Planet Health. 2024;8(2):e124–33. 10.1016/S2542-5196(23)00278-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38331529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desvars-Larrive A, Vogl AE, Puspitarani GA, Yang L, Joachim A, Käsbohrer A. A One Health framework for exploring zoonotic interactions demonstrated through a case study. Nat Commun. 2024;15(1):5650. 10.1038/s41467-024-49967-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11250852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39009576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riebenbauer K, Czerny S, Egg M, Urban N, Kinaciyan T, Hampel A, et al. The changing epidemiology of human leishmaniasis in the non-endemic country of Austria between 2000 to 2021, including a congenital case. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2024;18(1):e0011875. 10.1371/journal.pntd.0011875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10805284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38198499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heger F, Schindler S, Pleininger S, Fueszl A, Blaschitz M, Lippert K, et al. Three Cases of Tickborne Francisella tularensis Infection, Austria, 2022. Emerg Infect Dis. 2023;29(11):2349. 10.3201/eid2911.230460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10617340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37877608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trimmel NE, Walzer C. Infectious wildlife diseases in Austria–a literature review from 1980 until 2017. Front Vet Sci. 2020;7. 10.3389/fvets.2020.00003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7046627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32154271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leth C, Revilla-Fernández S, Fink M, Hofer E, Schmoll F. Bovine tuberculosis in the Austrian alpine region. Int J Infect Dis. 2019;79:62. 10.1016/j.ijid.2018.11.161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nigsch A, Glawischnig W, Bagó Z, Greber N. Mycobacterium caprae infection of red deer in Western Austria–optimized use of pathology data to infer infection dynamics. Front Vet Sci. 2019;5. 10.3389/fvets.2018.00350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6348259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30719435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang Y, Hartemink N, Byrne AW, Gormley E, McGrath G, Tratalos JA, et al. Inferring bovine tuberculosis transmission between cattle and badgers via the environment and risk mapping. Front Vet Sci. 2023;10:1233173. 10.3389/fvets.2023.1233173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10572351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37841461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatlauf J, Bayer K, Trouwborst A, Hackländer K. New rules or old concepts? The golden jackal (Canis aureus) and its legal status in Central Europe. Eur J Wildl Res. 2021;67(2):25. 10.1007/s10344-020-01454-2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camp JV, Schmon E, Krause R, Sixl W, Schmid D, Aberle SW. Genetic Diversity of Puumala orthohantavirus in Rodents and Human Patients in Austria, 2012–2019. Viruses. 2021;13(4):640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8069475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33918083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jonsson CB, Figueiredo LT, Vapalahti O. A global perspective on hantavirus ecology, epidemiology, and disease. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2010;23(2):412–41. 10.1128/cmr.00062-09.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2863364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20375360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan S, Brown J. The World Café in Singapore: Creating a Learning Culture Through Dialogue. J Appl Behav Sci. 2005;41(1):83–90. 10.1177/0021886304272851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>One Health Commission. 2024. https://www.onehealthcommission.org/en/resources__services/one_health_strategic_action_plans/. Accessed 2 May 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeleff M, Lehner L, Giles-Vernick T, Dückers MLA, Napier AD, Jirovsky-Platter E, et al. Vulnerability and One Health assessment approaches for infectious threats from a social science perspective: a systematic scoping review. Lancet Planet Health. 2022;6(8):e682–93. 10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00097-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35932788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nadal D. Rabies in the Streets: Interspecies Camaraderie in Urban India. Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania State University Press; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Locke P, Muenster U. Multispecies Ethnography. 2015. https://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/display/document/obo-9780199766567/obo-9780199766567-0130.xml. Accessed 26 Apr 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernstein AS, Ando AW, Loch-Temzelides T, Vale MM, Li BV, Li H, et al. The costs and benefits of primary prevention of zoonotic pandemics. Sci Adv. 2022;8(5):eabl4183. 10.1126/sciadv.abl4183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8816336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35119921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burger PA. Integrating One Health into systems science. One Health. 2024:100701. 10.1016/j.onehlt.2024.100701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10926283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38468609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, United Nations Environment Programme, World Organisation for Animal Health. A guide to implementing the One Health Joint Plan of Action at national level. WHO, FAO, UNEP, WOAH; 2023. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240082069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greer SL, Rozenblum S, Falkenbach M, Löblová O, Jarman H, Williams N, et al. Centralizing and decentralizing governance in the COVID-19 pandemic: the politics of credit and blame. Health Policy. 2022;126(5):408–17. 10.1016/j.healthpol.2022.03.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8913406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35331575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desson Z, Lambertz L, Peters JW, Falkenbach M, Kauer L. Europe’s COVID-19 outliers: German, Austrian and Swiss policy responses during the early stages of the 2020 pandemic. Health Policy Technol. 2020;9(4):405–18. 10.1016/j.hlpt.2020.09.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33520639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thal DA, Groschup MH, Leendertz F, Ludwig S, Jansen F, Suchsland R, et al. One Health Platform: Eine Plattform für die vernetzte One Health-Forschung in Deutschland. Deut Tierärzteblatt. 2024;72(5):573–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Essack SY. Environment: the neglected component of the One Health triad. Lancet Planet Health. 2018;2(6):e238–9. 10.1016/S2542-5196(18)30124-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7129022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29880152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page SE. Diversity and complexity. Princeton University Press; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emerson K. Collaborative governance of public health in low- and middle-income countries: lessons from research in public administration. BMJ Global Health. 2018;3(Suppl 4):e000381. 10.1136/bmjgh-2017-000381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6195133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30364438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humboldt-Dachroeden S. A governance and coordination perspective - Sweden’s and Italy’s approaches to implementing One Health. SSM Qual Res Health. 2022;2:100198. 10.1016/j.ssmqr.2022.100198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, United Nations Environment Programme, World Health Organization, World Organisation for Animal Health. Global Plan of Action on One Health. Towards a more comprehensive One Health, approach to global health threats at the human-animal-environment interface. FAO, UNEP WHO, WOAH; 2022. 10.4060/cc2289en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Rome Declaration on World Food Security and World Food Summit Plan of Action: World Food Summit, 13-17 November 1996, Rome, Italy. FAO; 1996. http://digitallibrary.un.org/record/195568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Zero draft of the WHO CA+ for the consideration of the Intergovernmental Negotiating Body at its fourth meeting. Fourth Meeting of the Intergovernmental Negotiating Body to draft and negociate a WHO Convention, Agreement or other International Instrument on Pandemic Prevention, Preparedness and Response - Provisional agenda item 3. WHO; 2023. https://apps.who.int/gb/inb/pdf_files/inb4/A_INB4_3-en.pdf.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>