<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39462338</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2731-4553</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>25</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC primary care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Prim Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Virtual practice facilitation as an implementation strategy for launching opioid safety committees for quality improvement in primary care: feasibility, acceptability, and intervention fidelity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>384</StartPage><MedlinePgn>384</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">384</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12875-024-02632-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Practice facilitation (PF) is an evidence-based multicomponent in-person implementation strategy. COVID-19-related lockdowns caused many implementation initiatives to rapidly shift to virtual settings, but there is limited evidence on PF deployed exclusively using virtual meeting platforms. Our objective was to assess the feasibility and acceptability of virtual PF used in a primary care setting to implement interdisciplinary opioid safety committees (OSCs) to improve care for patients using opioid medicines for persistent pain and reduce high-dose opioid prescribing. We also describe alignment of virtual PF with the core functions of PF and fidelity of participating clinics to the OSC intervention.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We applied qualitative and quantitative methods to evaluate virtual PF used to implement a quality improvement project at Kaiser Permanente Washington, an integrated health system in Washington State. We established interdisciplinary OSCs in primary care clinics using virtual PF. OSCs were tasked with promoting opioid safety and high-quality pain care through population management and chart reviews. We used administrative data to calculate feasibility measures including attendance and retention. Acceptability data came from interviews with OSC members conducted by evaluators. Measures of fidelity to the OSC intervention were abstracted from meeting notes and administrative data. We used qualitative methods to assess the adherence of virtual PF to the core functions of PF.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Facilitators carried out a comprehensive PF approach virtually and demonstrated adherence to the core functions of PF. We established OSCs in eight clinics and conducted an average of 17.5 virtual PF meetings over eight months of PF for each clinic. Average attendance was 75% and we had 84% retention. OSC members were highly satisfied with virtual PF. Facilitators effectively supported teams through implementation and technical challenges and OSC members gained skills through virtual PF. We implemented OSCs with high fidelity, suggesting virtual PF is an effective implementation strategy.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">We found virtual PF is a feasible and acceptable implementation strategy for this intervention and identified strategies to support care teams through challenges. Our findings can help inform future implementation efforts, especially those hoping to engage geographically dispersed clinics or remote clinical staff.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="TRIAL REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Not applicable.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mogk</LastName><ForeName>Jessica</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, 1730 Minor Ave, Ste 1600, Seattle, WA, 98101, USA. Jessica.M.Mogk@kp.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Allen</LastName><ForeName>Claire L</ForeName><Initials>CL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, 1730 Minor Ave, Ste 1600, Seattle, WA, 98101, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Levitz</LastName><ForeName>Carly E</ForeName><Initials>CE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, 1730 Minor Ave, Ste 1600, Seattle, WA, 98101, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stefanik-Guizlo</LastName><ForeName>Kelsey</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, 1730 Minor Ave, Ste 1600, Seattle, WA, 98101, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bourcier</LastName><ForeName>Emily</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, 1730 Minor Ave, Ste 1600, Seattle, WA, 98101, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Trapp Petty</LastName><ForeName>Melissa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, 1730 Minor Ave, Ste 1600, Seattle, WA, 98101, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lozano</LastName><ForeName>Paula</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, 1730 Minor Ave, Ste 1600, Seattle, WA, 98101, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Prim Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918300889006676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2731-4553</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000701">Analgesics, Opioid</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058996" MajorTopicYN="Y">Quality Improvement</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011320" MajorTopicYN="Y">Primary Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000701" MajorTopicYN="Y">Analgesics, Opioid</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005240" MajorTopicYN="Y">Feasibility Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014861" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Washington</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Implementation facilitation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Interdisciplinary chart review</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Opioid safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pain management</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Persistent pain</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Practice coaching</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Practice facilitation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quality improvement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virtual practice facilitation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39462338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12875-024-02632-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12875-024-02632-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Baskerville NB, Liddy C, Hogg W. Systematic review and Meta-analysis of Practice Facilitation within Primary Care settings. Ann Fam Med. 2012;10(1):63–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3262473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22230833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagykaldi Z, Mold JW, Aspy CB. Practice facilitators: a review of the literature. Fam Med. 2005;37(8):581–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16145629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen AM, Cuthel A, Padgett DK, Niles P, Rogers E, Pham-Singer H, et al. How practice facilitation strategies Differ by Practice Context. J Gen Intern Med. 2020;35(3):824–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7080927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31637651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sweeney SM, Baron A, Hall JD, Ezekiel-Herrera D, Springer R, Ward RL, et al. Effective facilitator strategies for supporting primary care practice change: a mixed methods study. Ann Fam Med. 2022;20(5):414–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9512557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36228060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perry CK, Lindner S, Hall J, Solberg LI, Baron A, Cohen DJ. How type of practice ownership affects participation with Quality Improvement External Facilitation: findings from EvidenceNOW. J Gen Intern Med. 2022;37(4):793–801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8904707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34981342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor EF, Machta RM, Meyers DS, Genevro J, Peikes DN. Enhancing the Primary Care Team to provide redesigned care: the roles of Practice facilitators and Care managers. Ann Fam Med. 2013;11(1):80–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3596023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23319510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagykaldi Z, Mold JW, Robinson A, Niebauer L, Ford A. Practice facilitators and practice-based Research Networks. J Am Board Fam Med. 2006;19(5):506–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16951300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SM, Mulcahy AC, Lange TM, Eldridge MR, Weidenbacher HJ, Jackson GL, et al. Rolling out PRIDE in all who served: barriers and facilitators for sites implementing an LGBTQ + Health Education Group for Military Veterans. J Gen Intern Med. 2023;38(3):849–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10356690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37340269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jortberg B, Wearner R, Kirchner S. Making a rapid transition to virtual practice facilitation: Tales of facilitation during COVID-19. Ann Fam Med [Internet]. 2022 Apr 1 [cited 2023 Sep 28];20(Supplement 1). https://www.annfammed.org/content/20/Supplement_1/2764</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webel B, North American Primary Care Research Group International Conference on Practice Facilitation. Pivoting to Virtual Practice Facilitation [Internet].; 2021 Aug 6 [cited 2022 Aug 29]; Virtual. https://napcrg.org/conferences/icpf/icpf21-poster-hall/posteronresearchinprogress/3093/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatch BA, Ferrara L, Dickinson C, Stock I, Carney PA, Fagnan LJ. The Importance of Practice Facilitation in Primary Care when Pandemic takes hold: relationships of Resilience. J Prim Care Community Health. 2021;12:21501327211014093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8114255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33928813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mogk JM, Stefanik-Guizlo K, Allen CL, Lozano PM. Technology and Strategies for Overcoming Challenges in Virtual Practice Facilitation., North American Primary Care Research Group International Conference on Practice Facilitation. Savannah, GA. [Internet]. North American Primary Care Research Group International Conference on Practice Facilitation, Savannah GA. https://www.act-center.org/application/files/4216/6481/4051/ACT-Center_Virtual-PF-Presentation_ICPF2022.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ritchie MJ, Kirchner JE, Townsend JC, Pitcock JA, Dollar KM, Liu CF. Time and Organizational Cost for Facilitating Implementation of Primary Care Mental Health Integration. J Gen Intern Med. 2020;35(4):1001–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7174254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31792866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AN, Sanchez V, Kenzie ES, Sullivan E, McCormack JL, Hiebert Larson J, et al. Improving screening, treatment, and intervention for unhealthy alcohol use in primary care through clinic, practice-based research network, and health plan partnerships: protocol of the ANTECEDENT study. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(6):e0269635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9239445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35763485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noël PH, Barnard JM, Leng M, Penney LS, Bharath PS, Olmos-Ochoa TT, et al. The Coordination Toolkit and Coaching Project: Cluster-Randomized Quality Improvement Initiative to improve patient experience of Care Coordination. J Gen Intern Med. 2022;37(1):95–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8739408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34109545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pimentel CB, Mills WL, Palmer JA, Dillon K, Sullivan JL, Wewiorski NJ, et al. Blended Facilitation as an effective implementation strategy for quality improvement and research in nursing homes. J Nurs Care Qual. 2019;34(3):210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6685683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30480614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gold R, Bunce A, Cowburn S, Davis JV, Nelson JC, Nelson CA, et al. Does increased implementation support improve community clinics’ guideline-concordant care? Results of a mixed methods, pragmatic comparative effectiveness trial. Implement Sci. 2019;14(1):100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6894475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31805968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vest BM, York TRM, Sand J, Fox CH, Kahn LS. Chronic kidney Disease Guideline implementation in primary care: a qualitative report from the TRANSLATE CKD Study. J Am Board Fam Med. 2015;28(5):624–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4815897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26355134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang ET, Oberman RS, Cohen AN, Taylor SL, Gumm E, Mardian AS, et al. Increasing Access to medications for Opioid Use Disorder and complementary and Integrative Health Services in Primary Care. J Gen Intern Med. 2020;35(Suppl 3):918–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7728925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33145686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yano EM, Darling JE, Hamilton AB, Canelo I, Chuang E, Meredith LS, et al. Cluster randomized trial of a multilevel evidence-based quality improvement approach to tailoring VA Patient Aligned Care Teams to the needs of women veterans. Implement Sci IS. 2016;11:101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4950741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27435723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adler RN, Ferguson WJ, Antar H, Steinkrauss M, Bjoern B, Konar V, et al. Transformation Support provided remotely to a National Cohort of Optometry practices. Ann Fam Med. 2019;17(Suppl 1):S33–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6827673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31405874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damush TM, Miech EJ, Rattray NA, Homoya B, Penney LS, Cheatham A, et al. Implementation evaluation of a Complex intervention to improve timeliness of Care for veterans with transient ischemic attack. J Gen Intern Med. 2021;36(2):322–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7878645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33145694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang A, Pollack T, Kadziel LA, Ross SM, McHugh M, Jordan N, et al. Impact of Practice Facilitation in Primary Care on Chronic Disease Care processes and outcomes: a systematic review. J Gen Intern Med. 2018;33(11):1968–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6206351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30066117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Austin EJ, Briggs ES, Ferro L, Barry P, Heald A, Curran GM, et al. Integrating routine screening for opioid use disorder into primary care settings: experiences from a National Cohort of clinics. J Gen Intern Med. 2023;38(2):332–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9132563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35614169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis MM, Coury J, Larson JH, Gunn R, Towey EG, Ketelhut A, et al. Improving colorectal cancer screening in rural primary care: preliminary effectiveness and implementation of a collaborative mailed fecal immunochemical test pilot. J Rural Health off J Am Rural Health Assoc Natl Rural Health Care Assoc. 2023;39(1):279–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9969840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35703582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baum RA, Hoholik S, Maciejewski H, Ramtekkar U. Using practice facilitation to improve Depression Management in Rural Pediatric Primary Care practices. Pediatr Qual Saf. 2020;5(3):e295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7297391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32656464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behling EM, Garris T, Blankenship V, Wagner S, Ramsey D, Davis R, et al. Improvement in hypertension control among adults seen in federally qualified Health Center clinics in the Stroke Belt: implementing a program with a dashboard and process Metrics. Health Equity. 2023;7(1):89–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9982137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36876238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romer A, North American Primary Care Research Group International Conference on Practice Facilitation. Strategies and Best Practices in Virtual Facilitation [Internet].; 2021 Aug 6 [cited 2022 Aug 29]; Virtual. https://napcrg.org/conferences/icpf/pastconferences/2021/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartmann CW, Engle RL, Pimentel CB, Mills WL, Clark VA, Keleher VC, et al. Virtual external implementation facilitation: successful methods for remotely engaging groups in quality improvement. Implement Sci Commun. 2021;2(1):66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8218278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34158115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat A, Bennett IM, Bauer AM, Beidas RS, Eriksen W, Barg FK, et al. Longitudinal remote coaching for implementation of Perinatal Collaborative Care: a mixed-methods analysis. Psychiatr Serv. 2020;71(5):518–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7196015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31996114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ike B, Baldwin LM, Sutton S, Borkulo NV, Packer C, Parchman ML. Staff and clinician work-life perceptions after Implementing systems-based improvements to Opioid Management. J Am Board Fam Med. 2019;32(5):715–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7549504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31506367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parchman ML, Penfold RB, Ike B, Tauben D, Von Korff M, Stephens M, et al. Team-based Clinic Redesign of Opioid Medication Management in Primary Care: Effect on Opioid Prescribing. Ann Fam Med. 2019;17(4):319–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6827656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31285209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivich J, McCauliff J, Schroeder A. Impact of multidisciplinary chart reviews on opioid dose reduction and monitoring practices. Addict Behav. 2018;86:40–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29752012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Six Building Blocks – A Team-. Based Approach to Improving Opioid Management in Primary Care [Internet]. [cited 2023 Dec 28]. https://familymedicine.uw.edu/improvingopioidcare/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coleman K, Austin BT, Brach C, Wagner EH. Evidence on the Chronic Care Model in the new millennium. Health Aff Proj Hope. 2009;28(1):75–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5091929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19124857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagner EH. Chronic disease management: what will it take to improve care for chronic illness? Eff Clin Pract ECP. 1998;1(1):2–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10345255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center for Accelerating Care Transformation (ACT Center). | Homepage [Internet]. [cited 2023 Dec 28]. https://www.act-center.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen C, Coleman K, Mettert K, Lewis C, Westbrook E, Lozano P. A roadmap to operationalize and evaluate impact in a learning health system. Learn Health Syst. 2021;5(4):e10258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8512726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34667878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinnock H, Barwick M, Carpenter CR, Eldridge S, Grandes G, Griffiths CJ, et al. Standards for reporting implementation studies (StaRI) Statement. BMJ. 2017;356:i6795.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5421438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28264797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A, Sainsbury P, Craig J. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): a 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. Int J Qual Health Care J Int Soc Qual Health Care. 2007;19(6):349–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proctor E, Silmere H, Raghavan R, Hovmand P, Aarons G, Bunger A, et al. Outcomes for implementation research: conceptual distinctions, Measurement challenges, and Research Agenda. Adm Policy Ment Health. 2011;38(2):65–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3068522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20957426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson N, Naylor PJ, Ashe MC, Fernandez M, Yoong SL, Wolfenden L. Guidance for conducting feasibility and pilot studies for implementation trials. Pilot Feasibility Stud. 2020;6(1):167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7603668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33292770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowell LS, Norris JM, White DE, Moules NJ. Thematic analysis: striving to meet the trustworthiness Criteria. Int J Qual Methods. 2017;16(1):160940691773384.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ATLAS.ti Scientific Software Development GmbH [Internet]. 2023. Available from: https://atlasti.com.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutton KF, Richman EL, Rees JR, Pugh-Nicholson LL, Craft MM, Peaden SH, et al. Implementing practice facilitation in research: how facilitators spend their time guiding practices to improve blood pressure control. Implement Sci Commun. 2023;4:89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10388449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37525267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonnell MM, Elder NC, Stock R, Wolf M, Steeves-Reece A, Graham T. Project ECHO Integrated within the Oregon Rural Practice-based Research Network (ORPRN). J Am Board Fam Med. 2020;33(5):789–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32989075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danquah IH, Tolstrup JS. Standing meetings are feasible and effective in reducing sitting time among Office workers—walking meetings are not: mixed-methods results on the feasibility and effectiveness of active meetings based on data from the take a stand! Study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(5):1713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7084221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32151044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith B, Hendrick P, Bateman M, Moffatt F, Rathleff M, Selfe J et al. A loaded self-managed exercise programme for patellofemoral pain: a mixed methods feasibility study. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2019;20(1):129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6438027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30917806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>