<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464730</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2347-3584</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>35</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virusdisease</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virusdisease</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Genome sequencing of SARS-Co-V-2 reveals mutations including F559I and V781D in S protein and LI123-124L in the nsp6 in 21K and 21L clades.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>400</StartPage><EndPage>419</EndPage><MedlinePgn>400-419</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s13337-024-00876-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Contagious and virulent virus variants like B.1.1.529 have complicated the 2019 global COVID-19 pandemic from Wuhan, China. Omicron, with extensive mutations and high transmissibility, is replacing Delta in some regions. Remarkably, Omicron exhibits reduced disease severity and resistance to certain vaccines and treatments. Our research sought to identify Egypt-specific variants of concern (VOCs) and their mutation patterns, aiming to provide critical insights for tailored public health strategies. We also looked at vaccine compatibility with these VOCs, as well as the efficacy of current treatments against new SARS-CoV-2 variants<b>.</b> We collected 103 PCR-confirmed COVID-19 cases from an Egyptian army hospital and used next-generation sequencing technology to sequence the entire viral genome. The viral genome was then assembled and reconstructed. Nextclade tools aided in clade assignment and Phylogenetic analysis, allowing classification, and understanding of these genomes' Phylogenetic relationships. Our findings reveal that the dominant VOCs in Egypt are the 21K clade, mainly Pango lineages BA.1 (34%), BA.1.1 (30.1%), and BA.1.17 (6.8%), and the 21L clade represented by Pango lineages BA.2. We also identified novel mutations, including F559I in the S protein (consistent in the 21K clade), V781D in the S protein (present in &gt; 50% of both 21K and 21L clades), and LI123-124L in the nsp6 gene (found in both 21K and 21L clades). Finally, our research provides important insights into Egypt's evolving COVID-19 landscape, allowing for tailored responses and risk mitigation strategies for emerging variants in the region.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Indian Virological Society 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seadawy</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed G</ForeName><Initials>MG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6102-723X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biodefense Center for Infectious and Emerging Diseases, Ministry of Defense, Cairo, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Military Medical Academy, Cairo, Egypt.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/04szvwj50</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.489816.a</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0452 2383</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marei</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed I</ForeName><Initials>MI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biodefense Center for Infectious and Emerging Diseases, Ministry of Defense, Cairo, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohanad</LastName><ForeName>Marwa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biochemistry Department, College of Pharmaceutical Sciences and Drug Manufacturing, Misr University for Science and Technology, 6th of October City, Egypt.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/05debfq75</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.440875.a</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 1765 2064</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hmed</LastName><ForeName>Ahmed A</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Botany and Microbiology Department, Faculty of Science, Al-Azhar University, Nasr City, Cairo, 11884 Egypt.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/05fnp1145</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411303.4</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2155 6022</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sofy</LastName><ForeName>Ahmed R</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Botany and Microbiology Department, Faculty of Science, Al-Azhar University, Nasr City, Cairo, 11884 Egypt.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/05fnp1145</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411303.4</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2155 6022</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Virusdisease</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101624144</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2347-3584</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">F559I</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mitigation strategies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Next-generation sequencing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">V781D</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestThe authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11502607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13337-024-00876-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abavisani M, Rahimian K, Mahdavi B, Tokhanbigli S, Siasakht MM, Farhadi A, Kodori M, Mahmanzar M, Meshkat Z. Mutations in SARS-CoV-2 structural proteins: a global analysis. Virol J. 2022;19:1–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9759450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36528612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aksamentov I, Roemer C, Hodcroft EB, Neher RA. Nextclade: clade assignment, mutation calling and quality control for viral genomes. J Open Sour Softw. 2021;6:3773.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almalki SSR, Izhari MA, Alyahyawi HE, Alatawi SK, Klufah F, Ahmed WAM, Alharbi R. Mutational analysis of circulating omicron sars-cov-2 lineages in the Al-Baha region of Saudi Arabia. J Multidiscip Healthc. 2023;16:2117–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10389082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37529147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee S, Seal S, Dey R, Mondal KK, Bhattacharjee P. Mutational spectra of SARS-CoV-2 orf1ab polyprotein and signature mutations in the United States of America. J Med Virol. 2021;93:1428–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7436414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32779784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty C, Bhattacharya M, Sharma AR, Dhama K, Lee S-S. The rapid emergence of multiple sublineages of Omicron (B. 1.1. 529) variant: dynamic profiling via molecular phylogenetics and mutational landscape studies. J Infect Public Health. 2022;15:1234–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36270226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desingu PA, Nagarajan K. Omicron BA. 2 lineage spreads in clusters and is concentrated in Denmark. J Med Virol. 2022;94:2360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9088308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35150013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Mazouri S, Essabbar A, Aanniz T, Eljaoudi R, Belyamani L, Ibrahimi A, Ouadghiri M. Genetic diversity and evolutionary dynamics of the Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 in Morocco. Pathog Glob Health. 2023. 10.1080/20477724.2023.2250942.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11221468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37635364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y, Yang H, Ji W, Weidong Wu, Chen S, Zhang W, Duan G. Virology, epidemiology, pathogenesis, and control of COVID-19. Viruses. 2020;12:372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7232198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32230900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim J-S, Jang J-H, Kim J-M, Chung Y-S, Yoo C-K, Han M-G. Genome-wide identification and characterization of point mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 genome. Osong Pub Health Res Perspect. 2020;11:101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7282418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32528815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Karuppanan K, Subramaniam G. Omicron (BA.1) and sub-variants (BA.1.1, BA.2, and BA.3) of SARS-CoV-2 spike infectivity and pathogenicity: a comparative sequence and structural-based computational assessment. J Med Virol. 2022;94:4780–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9347785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35680610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Karuppanan K, Subramaniam G. Omicron (BA. 1) and sub-variants (BA. 1.1, BA. 2, and BA. 3) of SARS-CoV-2 spike infectivity and pathogenicity: a comparative sequence and structural-based computational assessment. J Med Virol. 2022;94:4780–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9347785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35680610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee RA, Herigon JC, Benedetti A, Pollock NR, Denkinger CM. Performance of saliva, oropharyngeal swabs, and nasal swabs for SARS-CoV-2 molecular detection: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Microbiol. 2021. 10.1128/jcm.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8091856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33504593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y-D, Chi W-Y, Jun-Han Su, Ferrall L, Hung C-F, Wu T-C. Coronavirus vaccine development: from SARS and MERS to COVID-19. J Biomed Sci. 2020;27:1–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7749790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33341119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lino A, Cardoso MA, Martins-Lopes P, Gonçalves HMR. Omicron–the new SARS-CoV-2 challenge? Rev Med Virol. 2022;32:e2358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9111063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35445774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomari M, Mohammad NR, Omidi-Ardali H, Arab SS. Insight into molecular characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein following D614G point mutation, a molecular dynamics study. J Biomol Struct Dyn. 2022;40:5634–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33475020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mingaleeva RN, Nigmatulina NA, Sharafetdinova LM, Romozanova AM, Gabdoulkhakova AG, Filina YV, Shavaliyev RF, Rizvanov AA, Miftakhova RR. Biology of the SARS-CoV-2 Coronavirus. Biochem Mosc. 2022;87:1662–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9839213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36717455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naqvi AA, Turab KF, Mohammad T, Fatima U, Singh IK, Singh A, Atif SM, Hariprasad G, Hasan GM, Hassan MI. Insights into SARSCoV2 genome, structure, evolution, pathogenesis and therapies: structural genomics approach. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) Mol Basis Dis. 2020;1866:165878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7293463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32544429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicot F, Trémeaux P, Latour J, Carcenac R, Demmou S, Jeanne N, Ranger N, De Smet C, Raymond S, Dimeglio C. Whole-genome single molecule real-time sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron. J Med Virol. 2023;95:e28564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36756931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ou J, Lan W, Xiaowei Wu, Zhao T, Duan B, Yang P, Ren Yi, Quan L, Zhao W, Seto D. Tracking SARS-CoV-2 Omicron diverse spike gene mutations identifies multiple inter-variant recombination events. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022;7:138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9039610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35474215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pondé RAA. Physicochemical effect of the N501Y, E484K/Q, K417N/T, L452R and T478K mutations on the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein RBD and its influence on agent fitness and on attributes developed by emerging variants of concern. Virology. 2022;572:44–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9096574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35580380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramaiah A, Khubbar M, Akinyemi K, Bauer A, Carranza F, Weiner J, Bhattacharyya S, Payne D, Balakrishnan N. Genomic surveillance reveals the rapid expansion of the XBB lineage among circulating SARS-CoV-2 Omicron lineages in Southeastern Wisconsin, USA. Viruses. 2023;15:1940.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10535685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37766346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeghi K, Zadheidar S, Zebardast A, Nejati A, Faraji M, Ghavami N, Kalantari S, Salimi V, Yavarian J, Abedi A. Genomic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 strains circulating in Iran during six waves of the pandemic. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2023;17:e13135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10106497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37078070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sixto-López Y, Correa-Basurto J, Bello M, Landeros-Rivera B, Garzón-Tiznado JA, Montaño S. Structural insights into SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and its natural mutants found in Mexican population. Sci Rep. 2021;11:4659.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7907372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33633229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taherizadeh M, Tabibzadeh A, Panahi M, Tameshkel FS, Golahdooz M, Niya MHK. An introduction to SARS coronavirus 2; comparative analysis with MERS and SARS coronaviruses: a brief review. Iran J Public Health. 2020;49:30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8266008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34268203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teymouri M, Mollazadeh S, Mortazavi H, Ghale-Noie ZN, Keyvani V, Aghababaei F, Hamblin MR, Abbaszadeh-Goudarzi G, Pourghadamyari H, Hashemian SMR. Recent advances and challenges of RT-PCR tests for the diagnosis of COVID-19. Pathol Res Pract. 2021;221:153443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8045416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33930607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uraki R, Kiso M, Iida S, Imai M, Takashita E, Kuroda M, Halfmann PJ, Loeber S, Maemura T, Yamayoshi S. Characterization and antiviral susceptibility of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA. 2. Nature. 2022;607:119–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10579982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35576972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilar S, Isom DG. One year of SARS-CoV-2: How much has the virus changed? Biology. 2021;10:91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7911924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33530355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolf JM, Wolf LM, Bello GL, Maccari JG, Nasi LA. Molecular evolution of SARS-CoV-2 from December 2019 to August 2022. J Med Virol. 2023;95: e28366.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9877913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36458547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Operational considerations for COVID-19 surveillance using GISRS: interim guidance, 26 March 2020. World Health Organization; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin C. Genotyping coronavirus SARS-CoV-2: methods and implications. Genomics. 2020;112:3588–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32353474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zekri ARN, Mohanad M, Hafez MM, Soliman HK, Hassan ZK, Abouelhoda M, Amer KE, Seadawy MG, Ahmed OS. Genome sequencing of SARSCoV2 in a cohort of Egyptian patients revealed mutation hotspots that are related to clinical outcomes. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta BBA Mol Basis Dis. 2021;1867:166154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8079944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33932525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng W, Liu G, Ma H, Zhao D, Yang Y, Liu M, Mohammed A, Zhao C, Yang Y, Xie J. Biochemical characterization of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid protein. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2020;527:618–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7190499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32416961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>