<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469408</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Factors Associated With the Suspension of Domiciliary Dental Care for Older Adults During the First Wave of the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Pandemic: A Comparative Study in the Japanese Local Government.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70376</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70376</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70376</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.70376</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Objective The novel coronavirus has reduced the availability of dental services, including domiciliary dental care. The suspension of dental treatment worsens the dental condition. However, the impact on domiciliary dental care during the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic remains unclear. Therefore, the aim of this study is to determine the impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on domiciliary dental care and associated factors. Materials and methods This comparative study used Japanese prefectural claims data, including data from older adults who utilized domiciliary dental care. We compared the suspension of dental treatment during the firstwave of the COVID-19 pandemic with that before the COVID-19 pandemic. The outcome was the completion of four consecutive months of treatment. The chi-squared test, t-test, and logistic regression were applied. Result Approximately 23.4% of participants suspended home dental services during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, whereas 11.7% suspended these services before COVID-19. Logistic regression clarified the effect of the following variables (during the first wave of COVID-19 vs. before COVID-19): care need level of long-term care was 1-5 (=severe) (odds ratio (OR): 0.92 vs. no significance (NS)), visit by hospital dentists (OR: 1.83 vs. NS), volume of patients in the visited place (2-9 people, OR: NS vs. 0.72; over 10 people, OR: 0.58 vs. 0.32), planned physicians' visit (OR: 0.71 vs. 0.77), and taxed income per population (OR: NS vs. 1.00). Discussion Domiciliary dental care, especially those in care facilities, were a vulnerable population during the pandemic. This may contribute to the delivery of domiciliary dental care during any future pandemics.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Egashira et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Egashira</LastName><ForeName>Yuki</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Innovation, Kanagawa University of Human Services, Kanagawa, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kubota</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Innovation, Kanagawa University of Human Services, Kanagawa, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Watanabe</LastName><ForeName>Ryo</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Innovation, Kanagawa University of Human Services, Kanagawa, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adherence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">claims data</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">domiciliary dental care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">older adults</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ethics Committee of Kanagawa University of Human Services issued approval SHI No. 68. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515946</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.70376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO Director-General's opening remarks at the media briefing on COVID-19 - 11 March 2020.  [
May;
2022 
]. 2020. https://www.who.int/director-general/speeches/detail/who-director-general-s-opening-remarks-at-the-media-briefing-on-covid-19---11-march-2020 https://www.who.int/director-general/speeches/detail/who-director-general-s-opening-remarks-at-the-media-briefing-on-covid-19---11-march-2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on hospital admissions in the United States. Birkmeyer JD, Barnato A, Birkmeyer N, Bessler R, Skinner J. Health Aff (Millwood) 2020;39:2010–2017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7769002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32970495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Surgical activity in England and Wales during the COVID-19 pandemic: a nationwide observational cohort study. Dobbs TD, Gibson JA, Fowler AJ, et al. Br J Anaesth. 2021;127:196–204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8277602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34148732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Older adults used fewer home care services during the COVID-19 pandemic: findings from a secondary analysis of an urgent survey in Japan. Matsumoto H, Kawagoe M, Hotta S. Ann Geriatr Med Res. 2021;25:286–293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8749038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34748695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukuda H. Research to strengthen the dental care delivery system in the community based on the response to new coronavirus infection [in Japanese]  [
Nov;
2023 
]. 2021. https://mhlw-grants.niph.go.jp/system/files/download_pdf/2020/202006074A.pdf https://mhlw-grants.niph.go.jp/system/files/download_pdf/2020/202006074A.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oral environment status and related factors among older adult home care patients who use visiting nursing services [in Japanese] Noguchi K, Ochiai R, Watabe S. Japanese Journal of Infection Prevention and Control. 2021;36:321–328.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oral health care status of homebound elderly in Japan. Morishita M, Takaesu Y, Miyatake K, Shinsho F, Fujioka M. J Oral Rehabil. 2001;28:717–720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11556951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Challenges in providing special care dentistry during COVID-19 pandemic: a survey of public dental care services in Italy. Buttiglieri S, Spirito F, Della Ferrera F, Lo Muzio L, Ricotti A, Magi M, Appendino P. Minerva Dent Oral Sci. 2022;71:324–328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36760202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health service experiences and preferences of frail home care clients and their family and friend caregivers during the COVID-19 pandemic. Weeks LE, Nesto S, Hiebert B, Warner G, Luciano W, Ledoux K, Donelle L. BMC Res Notes. 2021;14:271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8278184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34261523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Persistent oral health problems associated with comorbidity and impaired diet quality in older adults. Bailey RL, Ledikwe JH, Smiciklas-Wright H, Mitchell DC, Jensen GL. J Am Diet Assoc. 2004;104:1273–1276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15281046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Relationship between oral health and mortality rate. Jansson L, Lavstedt S, Frithiof L. J Clin Periodontol. 2002;29:1029–1034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12472996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oral health, general health, and quality of life in older people. Kandelman D, Petersen PE, Ueda H. Spec Care Dentist. 2008;28:224–236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19068063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Outbreak of a patient with pneumonia associated with a novel coronavirus (1st case)  [
Feb;
2024 
]. 2020. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/newpage_08906.html https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/newpage_08906.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Consequences of the early phase of the COVID-19 pandemic for home-healthcare recipients in Norway: a nursing perspective. Melby L, Lyngstad M, Ose SO. Healthcare (Basel) 2023;11:346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9914130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36766920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The oral healthcare system in Japan. Zaitsu T, Saito T, Kawaguchi Y. Healthcare (Basel) 2018;6:79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6163272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29996547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trends in prevalence of non-valvular atrial fibrillation and anticoagulation therapy in a Japanese region - analysis using the National Health Insurance Database. Narita N, Okumura K, Kinjo T, et al. Circ J. 2020;84:706–713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32213724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higher medical costs for CKD patients with a rapid decline in eGFR: a cohort study from the Japanese general population. Nagai K, Iseki C, Iseki K, et al. PLoS One. 2019;14:0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ICD-10 version:2019.  [
Aug;
2024 
]. 2019. https://icd.who.int/browse10/2019/en https://icd.who.int/browse10/2019/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domiciliary dental care among homebound older adults: a nested case-control study in Japan. Ishimaru M, Ono S, Morita K, Matsui H, Yasunaga H. Geriatr Gerontol Int. 2019;19:679–683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31037823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors for the promotion of home dental care in home dental care support clinics [in Japanese] Tsuneishi M, Yamamoto T, Hosono J, Hirata S, Maki Y, Hirata Y, Ishii T. Ronen Shika Igaku. 2011;26:423–433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on urgent dental care delivery in a Swiss university center for dental medicine. Eggmann F, Haschemi AA, Doukoudis D, et al. Clin Oral Investig. 2021;25:5711–5721.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Physician visits and medication prescriptions for major chronic diseases during the COVID-19 pandemic in Japan: retrospective cohort study. Osawa I, Goto T, Asami Y, Itoh N, Kaga Y, Yamamoto Y, Tsugawa Y. BMJ Open. 2021;11:0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19-related factors delaying dental visits of workers in Japan. Suzuki S, Ohyama A, Yoshino K, Eguchi T, Kamijo H, Sugihara N. Int Dent J. 2022;72:716–724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9085458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35680437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence and determinants of dental visits among older adults: findings of a nationally representative longitudinal study. Spinler K, Aarabi G, Valdez R, Kofahl C, Heydecke G, König HH, Hajek A. BMC Health Serv Res. 2019;19:590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6702718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31429740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perceived vulnerability to coronavirus infection: impact on dental practice. González-Olmo MJ, Ortega-Martínez AR, Delgado-Ramos B, Romero-Maroto M, Carrillo-Diaz M. Braz Oral Res. 2020;34:0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Why did home care personal support service volumes drop during the COVID-19 pandemic? The contributions of client choice and personal support worker availability. King EC, Zagrodney KA, Rabeenthira P, Van Belle TA, McKay SM. Health Serv Insights. 2023;16:11786329231210692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10644723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38028120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Expert group on countermeasures to combat new coronavirus infections.  [
Jan;
2024 
]. 2020. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/seisakunitsuite/bunya/0000121431_senmonkakaigi.html https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/seisakunitsuite/bunya/0000121431_senmonkakaigi.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disparity between medical and dental care of institutionalised elderly in Singapore. Soh G. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/1624205/ Int Dent J. 1992;42:97–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1624205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the utilization of medical and dental services in Taiwan: a cohort study. Lee YL, Hu HY, Yen YF, et al. J Dent Sci. 2021;16:1233–1240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7887450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33613855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unmet health care needs of older people: prevalence and predictors in a French cross-sectional survey. Herr M, Arvieu JJ, Aegerter P, Robine JM, Ankri J. Eur J Public Health. 2014;24:808–813.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4168041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24287029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Functional ability and oral health among older people: a longitudinal study from age 75 to 80. Avlund K, Holm-Pedersen P, Schroll M. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2001;49:954–962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11527488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>