<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39469754</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1399-0012</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>38</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical transplantation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Transplant</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Lessons Learned From Extracorporeal Life Support Practice and Outcomes During the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e15482</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e15482</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/ctr.15482</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation is increasingly being used to support patients with hypoxemic respiratory failure and cardiogenic shock. During the COVID-19 pandemic, consensus guidance recommended extracorporeal life support for patients with COVID-19-related cardiopulmonary disease refractory to optimal conventional therapy, prompting a substantial expansion in the use of this support modality. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation was particularly integral to the bridging of COVID-19 patients to heart or lung transplantation. Limited human and physical resources precluded widespread utilization of mechanical support during the COVID-19 pandemic, necessitating careful patient selection and optimal management by expert healthcare teams for judicious extracorporeal membrane oxygenation use. This review outlines the evidence supporting the use of extracorporeal life support in COVID-19, describes the practice and outcomes of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID-19-related respiratory failure and cardiogenic shock, and proposes lessons learned for the implementation of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation as a bridge to transplantation in future public health emergencies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 John Wiley &amp; Sons A/S. Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gill</LastName><ForeName>George</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6673-5841</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology, Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Connor</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anesthesia and Critical Care, University of Chicago Medicine, Chicago, Illinois, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nunnally</LastName><ForeName>Mark E</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology, Perioperative Care and Pain Medicine, New York University Langone Health, New York, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Combes</LastName><ForeName>Alain</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service de Médecine Intensive-Réanimation, Sorbornne Université, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harper</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Critical Care, Medstar Washington Hospital Center, Washington, District of Columbia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baran</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7754-9953</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Advanced Heart Failure, Transplant and Mechanical Circulatory Support, Cleveland Clinic Heart, Vascular and Thoracic Institute, Weston, Florida, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Avila</LastName><ForeName>Mary</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Northwell Health, New York, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pisani</LastName><ForeName>Barbara</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Section of Cardiovascular Medicine, Atrium Wake Forest Baptist, Winston-Salem, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Copeland</LastName><ForeName>Hannah</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3753-5194</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiovascular and Thoracic Surgery, Lutheran Health Physicians, Fort Wayne, Indiana, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nurok</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8920-1380</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology, Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Denmark</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Transplant</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8710240</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0902-0063</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015199" MajorTopicYN="Y">Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012131" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Insufficiency</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012770" MajorTopicYN="N">Shock, Cardiogenic</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">heart disease: infectious</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lung disease: infectious</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ctr.15482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, Weekly Epidemiological Update on COVID‐19 ‐ 25 May 2023, World Health Organization, published May 25, 2023, accessed May 30, 2023, https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/weekly‐epidemiological‐update‐on‐covid‐19—25‐may‐2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Yuki, M. Fujiogi, and S. Koutsogiannaki, “COVID‐19 Pathophysiology: A Review,” Clinical Immunology 215 (2020): 108427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Badulak, M. V. Antonini, C. M. Stead, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for COVID‐19: Updated 2021 Guidelines From the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization,” Asaio Journal 67, no. 5 (2021): 485–495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Davies, D. Jones, M. Bailey, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for 2009 Influenza A(H1N1) Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome,” JAMA 302, no. 17 (2009): 1888–1895.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Patroniti, A. Zangrillo, F. Pappalardo, et al., “The Italian ECMO Network Experience During the 2009 Influenza A(H1N1) Pandemic: Preparation for Severe respiratory Emergency Outbreaks,” Intensive Care Medicine 37, no. 9 (2011): 1447–1457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Pham, A. Combes, H. Rozé, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Pandemic influenza A(H1N1)‐Induced Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome: A Cohort Study and Propensity‐Matched Analysis,” American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 187, no. 3 (2013): 276–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. P. Barbaro, G. MacLaren, P. S. Boonstra, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for COVID‐19: Evolving Outcomes From the International Extracorporeal Life Support Organization Registry,” Lancet 398, no. 10307 (2021): 1230–1238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. C. Milewski, S. Chatterjee, H. Merritt‐Genore, et al., “ECMO During COVID‐19: A Society of Thoracic Surgeons/Extracorporeal Life Support Organization Survey,” Annals of Thoracic Surgery Short Reports 1, no. 1 (2023): 168–173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Brodie, A. S. Slutsky, and A. Combes, “Extracorporeal Life Support for Adults With Respiratory Failure and Related Indications: A Review,” JAMA 322, no. 6 (2019): 557–568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Combes, M. Schmidt, C. L. Hodgson, et al., “Extracorporeal Life Support for Adults With Acute respiratory Distress Syndrome,” Intensive Care Medicine 46, no. 12 (2020): 2464–2476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. J. Peek, M. Mugford, R. Tiruvoipati, et al., “Efficacy and Economic Assessment of Conventional Ventilatory Support Versus Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Severe Adult respiratory Failure (CESAR): A Multicentre Randomised Controlled Trial,” Lancet 374, no. 9698 (2009): 1351–1363.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Combes, D. Hajage, G. Capellier, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Severe Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome,” New England Journal of Medicine 378, no. 21 (2018): 1965–1975.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. C. Goligher, G. Tomlinson, D. Hajage, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Severe Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome and Posterior Probability of Mortality Benefit in a Post Hoc Bayesian Analysis of a Randomized Clinical Trial,” JAMA 320, no. 21 (2018): 2251–2259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Combes, G. J. Peek, D. Hajage, et al., “ECMO for Severe ARDS: Systematic Review and Individual Patient Data Meta‐Analysis,” Intensive Care Medicine 46, no. 11 (2020): 2048–2057.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Munshi, A. Walkey, E. Goligher, et al., “Venovenous Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 7, no. 2 (2019): 163–172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Aoyama, K. Uchida, K. Aoyama, et al., “Assessment of Therapeutic Interventions and Lung Protective Ventilation in Patients With Moderate to Severe Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome: A Systematic Review and Network Meta‐Analysis,” JAMA Network Open 2, no. 7 (2019): e198116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Nishikimi, D. Jafari, N. Singh, et al., “Mortality of Mechanically Ventilated COVID‐19 Patients in Traditional Versus Expanded Intensive Care Units in New York,” Annals of the American Thoracic Society 19, no. 8 (2022): 1346–1354.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, Clinical Management of COVID‐19: Interim Guidance, World Health Organization, published May 27, 2020, accessed May 30, 2023, https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/332196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. H. Bartlett, M. T. Ogino, D. Brodie, et al., “Initial ELSO Guidance Document: ECMO for COVID‐19 Patients With Severe Cardiopulmonary Failure,” Asaio Journal 66, no. 5 (2020): 472–474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. P. Barbaro, G. MacLaren, P. S. Boonstra, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Support in COVID‐19: An International Cohort Study of the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization Registry,” Lancet 396, no. 10257 (2020): 1071–1078.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Lebreton, M. Schmidt, M. Ponnaiah, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Network Organisation and Clinical Outcomes During the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Greater Paris, France: A Multicentre Cohort Study,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 9, no. 8 (2021): 851–862.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Shaefi, S. K. Brenner, S. Gupta, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation in Patients With Severe Respiratory Failure From COVID‐19,” Intensive Care Medicine 47, no. 2 (2021): 208–221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Saeed, A. J. Tatooles, M. Farooq, et al., “Characteristics and Outcomes of Patients With COVID‐19 Supported by Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation: A Retrospective Multicenter Study,” Journal of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery 163, no. 6 (2022): 2107–2116. e6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Herrmann, C. Lotz, C. Karagiannidis, et al., “Key Characteristics Impacting Survival of COVID‐19 Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation,” Critical Care (London, England) 26, no. 1 (2022): 190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Lorusso, M. E. De Piero, S. Mariani, et al., “In‐Hospital and 6‐Month Outcomes in Patients With COVID‐19 Supported With Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (EuroECMO‐COVID): A Multicentre, Prospective Observational Study,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 11, no. 2 (2023): 151–162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Chommeloux, S. Valentin, H. Winiszewski, et al., “One‐Year Mental and Physical Health Assessment in Survivors After Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for COVID‐19‐Related Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome,” American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 207, no. 2 (2023): 150–159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Schmidt, E. Zogheib, H. Rozé, et al., “The PRESERVE Mortality Risk Score and Analysis of Long‐Term Outcomes After Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Severe Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome,” Intensive Care Medicine 39, no. 10 (2013): 1704–1713.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. L. Hodgson, A. M. Higgins, M. J. Bailey, et al., “Incidence of Death or Disability at 6 Months After Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation in Australia: A Prospective, Multicentre, Registry‐Embedded Cohort Study,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 10, no. 11 (2022): 1038–1048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. D. Kanji, A. Chouldechova, S. Harris‐Fox, et al., “Quality of Life and Functional Status of Patients Treated With Venovenous Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation at 6 Months,” Journal of Critical Care 66 (2021): 26–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Huang, Q. Yao, X. Gu, et al., “1‐year Outcomes in Hospital Survivors With COVID‐19: A Longitudinal Cohort Study,” Lancet 398, no. 10302 (2021): 747–758.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. A. Hall, J. P. Jacobs, A. H. Stammers, et al., “Multi‐Institutional Analysis of 505 Patients With Coronavirus Disease‐2019 Supported With Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation: Predictors of Survival,” Annals of Thoracic Surgery 114, no. 1 (2022): 61–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Prodhan, M. Stroud, N. El‐Hassan, et al., “Prolonged Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenator Support Among Neonates With Acute Respiratory Failure: A Review of the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization Registry,” Asaio Journal 60, no. 1 (2014): 63–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Mustafa, P. J. Alexander, D. J. Joshi, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Patients with COVID‐19 in Severe Respiratory Failure,” JAMA Surgery 155, no. 10 (2020): 990–992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. K. Gurnani, L. A. Michalak, D. Tabachnick, et al., “Outcomes of Extubated COVID and Non‐COVID Patients Receiving Awake Venovenous Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation,” Asaio Journal 68, no. 4 (2022): 478–485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Kurihara, A. Manerikar, M. Querrey, et al., “Clinical Characteristics and Outcomes of Patients With COVID‐19‐Associated Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Who Underwent Lung Transplant,” JAMA 327, no. 7 (2022): 652–661.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Bharat, T. N. Machuca, M. Querrey, et al., “Early Outcomes After Lung Transplantation for Severe COVID‐19: A Series of the First Consecutive Cases From Four Countries,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 9, no. 5 (2021): 487–497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. B. Hawkins, J. H. Mehaffey, E. J. Charles, et al., “Lung Transplantation for Severe Post‐Coronavirus Disease 2019 Respiratory Failure,” Transplantation 105, no. 6 (2021): 1381–1387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Lang, P. Jaksch, M. A. Hoda, et al., “Lung Transplantation for COVID‐19‐Associated Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome in a PCR‐Positive Patient,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 8, no. 10 (2020): 1057–1060.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Y. Chen, K. Qiao, F. Liu, et al., “Lung Transplantation as Therapeutic Option in Acute respiratory Distress Syndrome for Coronavirus Disease 2019‐Related Pulmonary Fibrosis,” Chinese Medical Journal 133, no. 12 (2020): 1390–1396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Roach, J. Chikwe, P. Catarino, et al., “Lung Transplantation for Covid‐19‐Related Respiratory Failure in the United States,” New England Journal of Medicine 386, no. 12 (2022): 1187–1188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Okumura, S. Jyothula, T. Kaleekal, and A. Dhand, “One‐Year Outcomes of Lung Transplantation for COVID‐19 Associated End Stage Lung Disease in the United States,” Clinical Infectious Diseases 76, no. 12 (2023): 2140–2147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. A. Hayanga, H. K. Hayanga, S. D. Holmes, et al., “Mechanical Ventilation and Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation as a Bridge to Lung Transplantation: Closing the Gap,” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 38, no. 10 (2019): 1104–1111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Benazzo, S. Schwarz, F. Frommlet, et al., “Twenty‐Year Experience With Extracorporeal Life Support as Bridge to Lung Transplantation,” Journal of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery 157, no. 6 (2019): 2515–2525. e10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. H. Hakim, U. Ahmad, K. R. McCurry, et al., “Contemporary Outcomes of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Used as Bridge to Lung Transplantation,” Annals of Thoracic Surgery 106, no. 1 (2018): 192–198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Hoetzenecker, L. Donahoe, J. C. Yeung, et al., “Extracorporeal Life Support as a Bridge to Lung Transplantation‐Experience of a High‐volume Transplant Center,” Journal of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery 155, no. 3 (2018): 1316–1328. e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Inci, S. Klinzing, D. Schneiter, et al., “Outcome of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation as a Bridge to Lung Transplantation: An Institutional Experience and Literature Review,” Transplantation 99, no. 8 (2015): 1667–1671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. M. Todd, S. Biswas Roy, A. S. Hashimi, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation as a Bridge to Lung Transplantation: A Single‐center Experience in the Present Era,” Journal of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery 154, no. 5 (2017): 1798–1809.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. M. Patterson, A. Shah, J. Rabin, et al., “Extracorporeal Life Support as a Bridge to Lung Transplantation: Where Are We Now?” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 41, no. 11 (2022): 1547–1555.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. E. Leard, A. M. Holm, M. Valapour, et al., “Consensus Document for the Selection of Lung Transplant Candidates: An Update From the International Society for Heart and Lung Transplantation,” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 40, no. 11 (2021): 1349–1379.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Furfaro, E. B. Rosenzweig, L. Shah, et al., “Lung Transplantation Disparities Based on Diagnosis for Patients Bridging to Transplant on Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation,” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 40, no. 12 (2021): 1641–1648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Tipograf, M. Salna, E. Minko, et al., “Outcomes of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation as a Bridge to Lung Transplantation,” Annals of Thoracic Surgery 107, no. 5 (2019): 1456–1463.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Biscotti, W. D. Gannon, C. Agerstrand, et al., “Awake Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation as Bridge to Lung Transplantation: A 9‐Year Experience,” Annals of Thoracic Surgery 104, no. 2 (2017): 412–419.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Langer, P. Aliyev, H. J. Schäfers, et al., “Improving Outcomes in Bridge‐to‐Transplant: Extended Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Support to Obtain Optimal Donor Lungs for Marginal Recipients,” Asaio Journal 65, no. 5 (2019): 516–521.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Crotti, G. A. Iotti, A. Lissoni, et al., “Organ Allocation Waiting Time During Extracorporeal Bridge to Lung Transplant Affects Outcomes,” Chest 144, no. 3 (2013): 1018–1025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. K. Oh, S. B. Hong, T. S. Shim, et al., “Effects of the Duration of Bridge to Lung Transplantation With Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation,” PLoS ONE 16, no. 7 (2021): e0253520.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Cypel and S. Keshavjee, “When to Consider Lung Transplantation for COVID‐19,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 8, no. 10 (2020): 944–946.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Doglietto, M. Vezzoli, F. Gheza, et al., “Factors Associated With Surgical Mortality and Complications Among Patients With and Without Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) in Italy,” JAMA Surgery 155, no. 8 (2020): 691–702.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Shi, M. Qin, B. Shen, et al., “Association of Cardiac Injury With Mortality in Hospitalized Patients With COVID‐19 in Wuhan, China,” JAMA Cardiology 5, no. 7 (2020): 802–810.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Guo, Y. Fan, M. Chen, et al., “Cardiovascular Implications of Fatal Outcomes of Patients With Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19),” JAMA Cardiology 5, no. 7 (2020): 811–818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Ruan, K. Yang, W. Wang, et al., “Clinical Predictors of Mortality Due to COVID‐19 Based on an Analysis of Data of 150 Patients From Wuhan, China,” Intensive Care Medicine 46, no. 5 (2020): 846–848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Ammirati, L. Lupi, M. Palazzini, et al., “Prevalence, Characteristics, and Outcomes of COVID‐19‐Associated Acute Myocarditis,” Circulation 145, no. 15 (2022): 1123–1139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Akhmerov and E. Marbán, “COVID‐19 and the Heart,” Circulation Research 126, no. 10 (2020): 1443–1455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Barhoum, M. Pineton de Chambrun, K. Dorgham, et al., “Phenotypic Heterogeneity of Fulminant COVID‐19–Related Myocarditis in Adults,” Journal of the American College of Cardiology 80, no. 4 (2022): 299–312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. M. Becher, B. Schrage, C. R. Sinning, et al., “Venoarterial Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Cardiopulmonary Support,” Circulation 138, no. 20 (2018): 2298–2300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. J. Geller, S. S. Sinha, N. K. Kapur, et al., “Escalating and De‐Escalating Temporary Mechanical Circulatory Support in Cardiogenic Shock: A Scientific Statement from the,” American Heart Association Circulation 146, no. 6 (2022): e50–e68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Ostadal, R. Rokyta, J. Karasek, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation in the Therapy of Cardiogenic Shock: Results of the ECMO‐CS Randomized Clinical Trial,” Circulation 147, no. 6 (2023): 454–464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Thiele, U. Zeymer, I. Akin, et al., “Extracorporeal Life Support in Infarct‐Related Cardiogenic Shock,” New England Journal of Medicine 389, no. 14 (2023): 1286–1297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. Zeymer, A. Freund, M. Hochadel, et al., “Venoarterial Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation in Patients With Infarct‐Related Cardiogenic Shock: An Individual Patient Data Meta‐Analysis of Randomised Trials,” Lancet 402, no. 10410 (2023): 1338–1346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Brunner, S. P. W. Guenther, K. Lackermair, et al., “Extracorporeal Life Support in Cardiogenic Shock Complicating Acute Myocardial Infarction,” Journal of the American College of Cardiology 73, no. 18 (2019): 2355–2357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. S. Banning, M. Sabaté, M. Orban, et al., “Venoarterial Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation or Standard Care in Patients With Cardiogenic Shock Complicating Acute Myocardial Infarction: The Multicentre, Randomised EURO SHOCK Trial,” EuroIntervention 19, no. 6 (2023): 482–492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. T. Pham, H. Toeg, R. De Paulis, et al., “Establishment and Management of Mechanical Circulatory Support During the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” Circulation 142, no. 1 (2020): 10–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Combes, S. Price, A. S. Slutsky, et al., “Temporary Circulatory Support for Cardiogenic Shock,” Lancet 396, no. 10245 (2020): 199–212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. E. Tonna, C. S. Tan, K. Hryniewicz, et al., “Outcomes After Extracorporeal Life Support for COVID‐19 Myocarditis: An Analysis of the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization Registry,” Critical Care (London, England) 26, no. 1 (2022): 235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Gill, A. Roach, G. Rowe, et al., “Heart Transplantation for COVID‐19 Myopathy in the United States,” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 42, no. 4 (2023): 447–450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Mastoris, J. E. Tonna, J. Hu, et al., “Use of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation as Bridge to Replacement Therapies in Cardiogenic Shock: Insights From the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization,” Circulation: Heart Failure 15, no. 1 (2022): e008777.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Kilic, M. A. Mathier, G. W. Hickey, et al., “Evolving Trends in Adult Heart Transplant With the 2018 Heart Allocation Policy Change,” JAMA Cardiology 6, no. 2 (2021): 159–167.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organ Procurement &amp; Transplantation Network. Adult Heart Allocation, OPTN, accessed May 30, 2023, https://optn.transplant.hrsa.gov/professionals/by‐organ/heart‐lung/adult‐heart‐allocation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Moonsamy, A. L. Axtell, N. E. Ibrahim, et al., “Survival After Heart Transplantation in Patients Bridged With Mechanical Circulatory Support,” Journal of the American College of Cardiology 75, no. 23 (2020): 2892–2905.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Y. Yin, O. Wever‐Pinzon, M. R. Mehra, et al., “Post‐Transplant Outcome in Patients Bridged to Transplant With Temporary Mechanical Circulatory Support Devices,” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 38, no. 8 (2019): 858–869.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Fukuhara, K. Takeda, P. A. Kurlansky, Y. Naka, and H. Takayama, “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation as a Direct Bridge to Heart Transplantation in Adults,” Journal of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery 155, no. 4 (2018): 1607–1618. e6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Tsyganenko, T. W. Gromann, F. Schoenrath, et al., “Predictors of Mid‐Term Outcomes in Patients Undergoing Implantation of a Ventricular Assist Device Directly After Extracorporeal Life Support,” European Journal of Cardio‐Thoracic Surgery 55, no. 4 (2019): 773–779.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Malas, Q. Chen, A. Akhmerov, et al., “Does Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Duration as a Bridge to Total Artificial Heart Affect Outcomes,” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 42, no. 4 (2023): S67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Urban, A. Siddique, H. Merritt‐Genore, and J. Um, “What Are the Results of Venoarterial Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Bridging to Heart Transplantation?,” Interdisciplinary CardioVascular and Thoracic Surgery 29, no. 4 (2019): 632–634.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Combes, D. Brodie, R. Bartlett, et al., “Position Paper for the Organization of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Programs for Acute Respiratory Failure in Adult Patients,” American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 190, no. 5 (2014): 488–496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. P. Barbaro, F. O. Odetola, K. M. Kidwell, et al., “Association of Hospital‐Level Volume of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Cases and Mortality. Analysis of the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization Registry,” American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 191, no. 8 (2015): 894–901.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Nasa, E. Azoulay, A. K. Khanna, et al., “Expert Consensus Statements for the Management of COVID‐19‐Related Acute Respiratory Failure Using a Delphi Method,” Critical Care (London, England) 25, no. 1 (2021): 106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. E. Tonna, D. Abrams, D. Brodie, et al., “Management of Adult Patients Supported With Venovenous Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (VV ECMO): Guideline From the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization (ELSO),” Asaio Journal 67, no. 6 (2021): 601–610.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Lorusso, K. Shekar, G. MacLaren, et al., “ELSO Interim Guidelines for Venoarterial Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation in Adult Cardiac Patients,” Asaio Journal 67, no. 8 (2021): 827–844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Karagiannidis, A. S. Slutsky, T. Bein, W. Windisch, S. Weber‐Carstens, and D. Brodie, “Complete Countrywide Mortality in COVID Patients Receiving ECMO in Germany Throughout the First Three Waves of the Pandemic,” Critical Care (London, England) 25, no. 1 (2021): 413.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. C. Yeung, M. Cypel, C. Chaparro, and S. Keshavjee, “Lung Transplantation for Acute COVID‐19: The Toronto Lung Transplant Program Experience,” CMAJ 193, no. 38 (2021): E1494–E1497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Schmidt, D. Hajage, M. Landoll, et al., “Comparative Outcomes of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for COVID‐19 Delivered in Experienced European Centres During Successive SARS‐CoV‐2 Variant Outbreaks (ECMO‐SURGES): An International, Multicentre, Retrospective Cohort Study,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 11, no. 2 (2023): 163–175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Hajage, A. Combes, C. Guervilly, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Severe Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Associated With COVID‐19: An Emulated Target Trial Analysis,” American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 206, no. 3 (2022): 281–294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Wunsch, D. C. Angus, D. A. Harrison, et al., “Variation in Critical Care Services Across North America and Western Europe,” Critical Care Medicine 36, no. 10 (2008): 2787–2793. e1‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. S. Kadri, J. Sun, A. Lawandi, et al., “Association Between Caseload Surge and COVID‐19 Survival in 558 U.S. Hospitals, March to August 2020,” Annals of Internal Medicine 174, no. 9 (2021): 1240–1251.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Nurok, Rethinking ICU Allocation in Times of Crisis, HealthAffairs, published March 30, 2021, accessed May 30, 2023, https://www.healthaffairs.org/content/forefront/rethinking‐icu‐allocation‐times‐crisis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Schmidt, M. Bailey, J. Sheldrake, et al., “Predicting Survival After Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Severe Acute Respiratory Failure. The Respiratory Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Survival Prediction (RESP) Score,” American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 189, no. 11 (2014): 1374–1382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Wengenmayer, D. Duerschmied, E. Graf, et al., “Development and Validation of a Prognostic Model for Survival in Patients Treated With Venoarterial Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation: The PREDICT VA‐ECMO Score,” European Heart Journal – Acute CardioVascular Care 8, no. 4 (2019): 350–359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Hofmann, M. J. Gmelin, D. Metz, et al., “Cardiac Surgery Score (CASUS) Improves Outcome Prediction in Patients Treated With Extracorporal Life Support (ECLS),” Perfusion 33, no. 1 (2018): 36–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Moyon, M. Pineton de Chambrun, G. Lebreton, et al., “Validation of Survival Prediction Models for ECMO in Sars‐CoV‐2‐Related Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome,” Critical Care (London, England) 26, no. 1 (2022): 187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. C. Schneider, A. Shah, M. M. Doty, R. Tikkanen, K. Fields, and R. D. Williams II, Mirror, Mirror 2021: Reflecting Poorly: Health Care in the U.S. Compared to Other High‐Income Countries, The Commonwealth Fund, published August 4, 2021, accessed May 30, 2023, https://www.commonwealthfund.org/publications/fund‐reports/2021/aug/mirror‐mirror‐2021‐reflecting‐poorly.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Parekh, D. Abrams, C. Agerstrand, et al., “The Use of Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for COVID‐19: Lessons Learned,” Clinics in Chest Medicine 44, no. 2 (2023): 335–346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. B. White, L. Villarroel, and J. L. Hick, “Inequitable Access to Hospital Care—Protecting Disadvantaged Populations During Public Health Emergencies,” New England Journal of Medicine 385, no. 24 (2021): 2211–2214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Miller, L. R. Wherry, and B. Mazumder, “Estimated Mortality Increases During the COVID‐19 Pandemic by Socioeconomic Status, Race, and Ethnicity,” Health Affairs (Project Hope) 40, no. 8 (2021): 1252–1260.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Guillon, E. Laurent, L. Godillon, et al., “Inter‐Regional Transfers for Pandemic Surges Were Associated With Reduced Mortality Rates,” Intensive Care Medicine 47, no. 7 (2021): 798–800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Schmidt, D. Hajage, G. Lebreton, et al., “Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for Severe Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Associated With COVID‐19: A Retrospective Cohort Study,” Lancet Respiratory Medicine 8, no. 11 (2020): 1121–1131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Bréchot, C. Mastroianni, M. Schmidt, et al., “Retrieval of Severe Acute Respiratory Failure Patients on Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation: Any Impact on Their Outcomes?,” Journal of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery 155, no. 4 (2018): 1621–1629.e2.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>