<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463908</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association Between the Use of Proton Pump Inhibitors and Severe Clinical Outcomes in COVID-19 Patients: A Retrospective Observational Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e72385</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e72385</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e72385</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.72385</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background Proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) increase the risk of pneumonia secondary to PPI-induced hypochlorhydria. We aim to investigate the association between PPI and disease severity in coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)-positive patients and the risk of hospitalizations in Muscat, Oman. Methodology COVID-19-positive patients aged 18 years and above at the time of diagnosis were included in this retrospective observational study. The details of the patients were retrieved from the electronic health records of the Al Shifa Hospital Information Management System and Tarassud. The composite primary endpoint was COVID-19 admission to a government tertiary hospital ward or intensive care within 14 days of diagnosis. Results A total of 506 COVID-19-positive patients were identified during the specified period. The mean age was 44 ± 15 years. The majority of the patients were Omani, and a female preponderance was observed. Overall, 104 (20.4%) patients were current PPI users. Admission due to COVID-19 was significantly associated with the presence of comorbid conditions such as diabetes mellitus (p = 0.001), hypertension (p = 0.001), and chronic kidney disease (p &lt; 0.001). However, current PPI use (p = 0.140) was not significantly associated with an increased risk of hospitalization. Conclusions This data suggests that the use of PPIs during COVID-19 infection did not increase the risk of severe COVID-19 infection and poor outcomes leading to hospitalization in Muscat, Oman. However, the presence of other medical comorbidities, such as diabetes and hypertension, was associated with a higher risk of adverse clinical symptoms that resulted in hospitalization.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Pinto et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pinto</LastName><ForeName>Sharon</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Primary Healthcare, Ministry of Health, Muscat, OMN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, James Cook University Hospital, Middlesbrough, GBR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Lawati</LastName><ForeName>Hadia</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Family Medicine, Ministry of Health, Muscat, OMN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Raisi</LastName><ForeName>Marwa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Family Medicine, Ministry of Health, Muscat, OMN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maawali</LastName><ForeName>Balqees Al</ForeName><Initials>BA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Primary Healthcare, Ministry of Health, Muscat, OMN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">comorbid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diabetes mellitus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hypertension</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">omani</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">proton pump inhibitors</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Directorate General of Health Services, Muscat issued approval MOH/CSR/21/24311. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11510648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.72385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>COVID-19: immunopathology and its implications for therapy. Cao X. Nat Rev Immunol. 2020;20:269–270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7143200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32273594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronavirus disease 2019: what we know? He F, Deng Y, Li W. J Med Virol. 2020;92:719–725.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7228340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32170865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mortality in COVID-19 patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome and corticosteroids use: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Hasan SS, Capstick T, Ahmed R, Kow CS, Mazhar F, Merchant HA, Zaidi ST. Expert Rev Respir Med. 2020;14:1149–1163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7544968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32734777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology of COVID-19 infection in Oman: analysis of the first 1304 cases. Khamis F, Al Rashidi B, Al-Zakwani I, Al Wahaibi AH, Al Awaidy ST. Oman Med J. 2020;35:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7335452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32647593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trilogy of ACE2: a peptidase in the renin-angiotensin system, a SARS receptor, and a partner for amino acid transporters. Kuba K, Imai Y, Ohto-Nakanishi T, Penninger JM. Pharmacol Ther. 2010;128:119–128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20599443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evidence for gastrointestinal infection of SARS-CoV-2. Xiao F, Tang M, Zheng X, Liu Y, Li X, Shan H. Gastroenterology. 2020;158:1831–1833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7130181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effects of acupressure on fatigue of lung cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy: an experimental pilot study. Tang WR, Chen WJ, Yu CT, Chang YC, Chen CM, Wang CH, Yang SH. Complement Ther Med. 2014;22:581–591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25146059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gastrointestinal manifestations in COVID-19. Kariyawasam JC, Jayarajah U, Riza R, Abeysuriya V, Seneviratne SL. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2021;115:1362–1388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7989191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33728439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence, mechanism, and implications of gastrointestinal symptoms in COVID-19. Zeb S, Almani K, Arshad I, et al. Pak J Med Health Sci. 2021;15:2206–2209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Severe clinical outcomes of COVID-19 associated with proton pump inhibitors: a nationwide cohort study with propensity score matching. Lee SW, Ha EK, Yeniova AÖ, et al. Gut. 2021;70:76–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32732368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pre-hospitalization proton pump inhibitor use and clinical outcomes in COVID-19. Ramachandran P, Perisetti A, Gajendran M, Jean-Louis F, Bansal P, Dwivedi AK, Goyal H. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2022;34:137–141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33252418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The physiology of the gastric parietal cell. Engevik AC, Kaji I, Goldenring JR. Physiol Rev. 2020;100:573–602.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7327232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31670611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The potential therapeutic role of proton pump inhibitors in COVID-19: hypotheses based on existing evidences. Ray A, Sharma S, Sadasivam B. Drug Res (Stuttg) 2020;70:484–488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7672704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32877948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proton pump inhibitor use is associated with increased risk of severity and mortality from coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infection. Hariyanto TI, Prasetya IB, Kurniawan A. Dig Liver Dis. 2020;52:1410–1412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7538064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33092998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proton pump inhibitor use and risk of pneumonia: a self-controlled case series study. Maret-Ouda J, Panula J, Santoni G, Xie S, Lagergren J. J Gastroenterol. 2023;58:734–740.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10366235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37314495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proton-pump inhibitor use is not associated with severe COVID-19-related outcomes: a propensity score-weighted analysis of a national veteran cohort. Shah S, Halvorson A, McBay B, et al. Gut. 2022;71:1447–1450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9013721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34663578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Use of proton-pump inhibitor is not associated with adverse clinical outcomes in COVID-19 patients: a territory-wide cohort study. Yip TC, Chan FK, Lui GC, et al. GastroHep. 2022;13:1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proton pump inhibitor therapy usage and associated hospitalization rates and critical care outcomes of COVID-19 patients. Shupp B, Mehta SV, Chirayath S, et al. Sci Rep. 2022;12:7596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9084256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35534666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of proton pump inhibitors on the in-hospital outcome of COVID-19 patients: a retrospective study. Yao H, Li H, Ma Z, et al. Therap Adv Gastroenterol. 2022;15:17562848221104365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9201367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35721837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical features, laboratory characteristics and risk factors for mortality of COVID-19 patients in a secondary hospital in Oman during the first wave of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. Almayahi ZK, Raveendran AV, Al Malki R, et al. Bull Natl Res Cent. 2022;46:139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9108686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35601475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical characteristics of confirmed cases of COVID-19 admitted at Al Nahdha Hospital, Oman: a cross-sectional descriptive study. Al Harthi S, Al Osali M, Al Ismaili R, et al. Cureus. 2021;13:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8451160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34567884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association of asthma and its genetic predisposition with the risk of severe COVID-19. Zhu Z, Hasegawa K, Ma B, Fujiogi M, Camargo CA Jr, Liang L. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2020;146:327–329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7423602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32522462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Predictors of mortality in patients with coronavirus disease 2019: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Shi C, Wang L, Ye J, et al. BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21:663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8264491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34238232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incidence and outcomes of COVID-19 in people with CKD: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Chung EY, Palmer SC, Natale P, et al. Am J Kidney Dis. 2021;78:804–815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8339603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34364906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Associations between body-mass index and COVID-19 severity in 6·9 million people in England: a prospective, community-based, cohort study. Gao M, Piernas C, Astbury NM, Hippisley-Cox J, O'Rahilly S, Aveyard P, Jebb SA. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2021;9:350–359.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8081400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33932335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 disease severity and mortality determinants: a large population-based analysis in Oman. Al Wahaibi A, Al Rawahi B, Patel PK, Al Khalili S, Al Maani A, Al-Abri S. Travel Med Infect Dis. 2021;39:101923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7678429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33227503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>