<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39467655</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0386-300X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>78</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Acta medica Okayama</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acta Med Okayama</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Phenotypic and Genetic Characteristics of Carbapenemase-Producing Enterobacterales Isolates at Okayama University Hospital.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>371</StartPage><EndPage>376</EndPage><MedlinePgn>371-376</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.18926/AMO/67657</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Spread of carbapenemase-producing Enterobacterales (CPE) is an ongoing public health issue worldwide, including in Japan. In this study, we investigated the phenotypic and genetic characteristics of CPE isolates at Okayama University Hospital over the 5 years (2013-2018) prior to the outbreak of the 2019 coronavirus pandemic. Of 24 carbapenem-resistant Enterobacterales isolated during the study period, we identified 8 CPE isolates harboring blaIMP-1 (5 isolates) and blaIMP-6 genes (3 isolates). Bacterial species and carbapenem susceptibility patterns exhibited diversity. Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of meropenem were generally higher than those of imipenem and biapenem. Results of pulsed-field gel electrophoresis demonstrated that neither clonal nor plasmid-mediated outbreaks of blaIMP-harboring CPE isolates have developed at our hospital. One Klebsiella oxytoca isolate showed a high MIC (128 μg/mL) of meropenem, which could be explained by the high plasmid copy number. Subsequent analysis of this isolate may elucidate the intricacies of carbapenem resistance profiles among CPE isolates. Collectively, our findings underscore the necessity for ongoing genetic surveillance of CPE, complemented by tailored approaches for infection prevention and control.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gotoh</LastName><ForeName>Kazuyoshi</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bacteriology, Okayama University Graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceutical Sciences.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miyoshi</LastName><ForeName>Makoto</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Science, Graduate School of Health Sciences, Okayama University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>I Putu Bayu Mayura</LastName><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Microbiology, Faculty of Medicine, Udayana University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsuji</LastName><ForeName>Shuma</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Science, Graduate School of Health Sciences, Okayama University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iio</LastName><ForeName>Koji</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microbiology Division, Clinical Laboratory, Okayama University Hospital.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fukushima</LastName><ForeName>Shinnosuke</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bacteriology, Okayama University Graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceutical Sciences.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Matsushita</LastName><ForeName>Osamu</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bacteriology, Okayama University Graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceutical Sciences.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hagiya</LastName><ForeName>Hideharu</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Okayama University Hospital.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Japan</Country><MedlineTA>Acta Med Okayama</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0417611</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0386-300X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.5.2.6</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D001618">beta-Lactamases</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D001426">Bacterial Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.5.2.6</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C063912">carbapenemase</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D015780">Carbapenems</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001618" MajorTopicYN="Y">beta-Lactamases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007564" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Japan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008826" MajorTopicYN="Y">Microbial Sensitivity Tests</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001426" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bacterial Proteins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006785" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hospitals, University</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="Y">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004756" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterobacteriaceae Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073182" MajorTopicYN="N">Carbapenem-Resistant Enterobacteriaceae</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010641" MajorTopicYN="N">Phenotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004755" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterobacteriaceae</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015780" MajorTopicYN="N">Carbapenems</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Silent pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial resistance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">carbapenemase-producing enterobacterales</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">carbapenemase-resistant enterobacterales</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">whole genome sequence</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39467655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18926/AMO/67657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Meletis G: Carbapenem resistance: overview of the problem and future perspectives. Ther Adv Infect Dis (2016) 3: 15-21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antimicrobial Resistance Collaborators: Global burden of bacterial antimicrobial resistance in 2019: a systematic analysis. Lancet (2022) 399: 629-655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logan LK and Weinstein RA: The Epidemiology of Carbapenem-Resistant Enterobacteriaceae: The Impact and Evolution of a Global Menace. J Infect Dis (2017) 215: S28-36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto N, Asada R, Kawahara R, Hagiya H, Akeda Y, Shanmugakani RK, Yoshida H, Yukawa S, Yamamoto K, Takayama Y, Ohnishi H, Taniguchi T, Matsuoka T, Matsunami K, Nishi I, Kase T, Hamada S and Tomono K: Prevalence of, and risk factors for, carriage of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae among hospitalized patients in Japan. J Hosp Infect (2017) 97: 212-217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yano H, Kuga A, Okamoto R, Kitasato H, Kobayashi T and Inoue M: Plasmid-encoded metallo-beta-lactamase (IMP-6) conferring resistance to carbapenems, especially meropenem. Antimicrob Agents Chemother (2001) 45: 1343-1348.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishio H, Komatsu M, Shibata N, Shimakawa K, Sueyoshi N, Ura T, Satoh K, Toyokawa M, Nakamura T, Wada Y, Orita T, Kofuku T, Yamasaki K, Sakamoto M, Kinoshita S, Aihara M and Arakawa Y: Metallo-beta-lactamase-producing gram-negative bacilli: laboratory-based surveillance in cooperation with 13 clinical laboratories in the Kinki region of Japan. J Clin Microbiol (2004) 42: 5256-5263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohno Y, Nakamura A, Hashimoto E, Matsutani H, Abe N, Fukuda S, Hisashi K, Komatsu M and Nakamura F: Molecular epidemiology of carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae in a primary care hospital in Japan, 2010-2013. J Infect Chemother (2017) 23: 224-229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan JJ, Hsueh PR, Ko WC, Luh KT, Tsai SH, Wu HM and Wu JJ: Metallo-beta-lactamases in clinical Pseudomonas isolates in Taiwan and identification of VIM-3, a novel variant of the VIM-2 enzyme. Antimicrob Agents Chemother (2001) 45: 2224-2228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López-Cánovas L, Higginson D, Orozco E and Riverón AM: Rapid Non-Enzymatic DNA Deproteinization in Agarose Miniplugs. Analytical Letters (1996) 29: 2079-2084.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arakawa Y, Shibata N, Shibayama K, Kurokawa H, Yagi T, Fujiwara H and Goto M: Convenient test for screening metallo-beta-lactamase-producing gram-negative bacteria by using thiol compounds. J Clin Microbiol (2000) 38: 40-43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugawara Y, Hagiya H, Akeda Y, Takeuchi D, Sakamoto N, Matsumoto Y, Motooka D, Nishi I, Tomono K and Hamada S: Community spread and acquisition of clinically relevant Escherichia coli harbouring blaNDM among healthy Japanese residents of Yangon, Myanmar. J Antimicrob Chemother (2021) 76: 1448-1454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akram F, Imtiaz M and Haq IU: Emergent crisis of antibiotic resistance: A silent pandemic threat to 21st century. Microb Pathog (2023) 174: 105923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salam MA, Al-Amin MY, Salam MT, Pawar JS, Akhter N, Rabaan AA and Alqumber MAA: Antimicrobial Resistance: A Growing Serious Threat for Global Public Health. Healthcare (Basel) (2023) 11: 1946.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segawa T, Sekizuka T, Suzuki S, Shibayama K, Matsui M and Kuroda M: The plasmid-encoded transcription factor ArdK contributes to the repression of the IMP-6 metallo-β-lactamase gene blaIMP-6, leading to a carbapenem-susceptible phenotype in the blaIMP-6-positive Escherichia coli strain A56-1S. PLoS One (2018) 13: e0208976.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute: Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing. CLSI Document M100-S33 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto N, Kawahara R, Akeda Y, Shanmugakani RK, Yoshida H, Hagiya H, Hara N, Nishi I, Yukawa S, Asada R, Sasaki Y, Maeda K, Sakamoto N, Hamada S and Tomono K: Development of selective medium for IMP-type carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae in stool specimens. BMC Infect Dis (2017) 17: 229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dierikx C, Börjesson S, Perrin-Guyomard A, Haenni M, Norström M, Divon HH, Ilag HK, Granier SA, Hammerum A, Kjeldgaard JS, Pauly N, Randall L, Anjum MF, Smialowska A, Franco A, Veldman K and Slettemeås JS: A European multicenter evaluation study to investigate the performance on commercially available selective agar plates for the detection of carbapenemase producing Enterobacteriaceae. J Microbiol Methods (2022) 193: 106418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Göttig S, Walker SV, Saleh A, Koroska F, Sommer J, Stelzer Y, Steinmann J and Hamprecht A: Comparison of nine different selective agars for the detection of carbapenemase-producing Enterobacterales (CPE). Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis (2020) 39: 923-927.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Qin J, Xiang G, Wang C, Wang Q, Qin J, Wang H and Shen Z: Nosocomial dissemination of blaIMP-4 among Klebsiella pneumoniae by horizontal gene transfer and clonal spread: the epidemic IncN plasmids and the emerging high-risk IMP-4-producing ST101 clone. J Antimicrob Chemother (2023): dkad326.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eda R, Nakamura M, Takayama Y, Maehana S, Nakano R, Yano H and Kitasato H: Trends and molecular characteristics of carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae in Japanese hospital from 2006 to 2015. J Infect Chemother (2020) 26: 667-671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shigemoto N, Kuwahara R, Kayama S, Shimizu W, Onodera M, Yokozaki M, Hisatsune J, Kato F, Ohge H and Sugai M: Emergence in Japan of an imipenem-susceptible, meropenem-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae carrying blaIMP-6. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis (2012) 72: 109-112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aoki K, Harada S, Yahara K, Ishii Y, Motooka D, Nakamura S, Akeda Y, Iida T, Tomono K, Iwata S, Moriya K and Tateda K: Molecular Characterization of IMP-1-Producing Enterobacter cloacae Complex Isolates in Tokyo. Antimicrob Agents Chemother (2018) 62: e02091-17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kayama S, Shigemoto N, Kuwahara R, Oshima K, Hirakawa H, Hisatsune J, Jové T, Nishio H, Yamasaki K, Wada Y, Ueshimo T, Miura T, Sueda T, Onodera M, Yokozaki M, Hattori M, Ohge H and Sugai M: Complete nucleotide sequence of the IncN plasmid encoding IMP-6 and CTX-M-2 from emerging carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae in Japan. Antimicrob Agents Chemother (2015) 59: 1356-1359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen Z, Zhang H, Gao Q, Qin J, Zhang C, Zhu J and Li M: Increased Plasmid Copy Number Contributes to the Elevated Carbapenem Resistance in OXA-232-Producing Klebsiella pneumoniae. Microb Drug Resist (2020) 26: 561-568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abe R, Akeda Y, Sugawara Y, Matsumoto Y, Motooka D, Kawahara R, Yamamoto N, Tomono K, Iida T and Hamada S: Enhanced Carbapenem Resistance through Multimerization of Plasmids Carrying Carbapenemase Genes. MBio (2021) 12: e0018621.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koh TH, Sng LH, Babini GS, Woodford N, Livermore DM and Hall LM: Carbapenem-Resistant Klebsiella Pneumoniae in Singapore Producing IMP-1 β-Lactamase and Lacking an Outer Membrane Protein. Antimicrob Agents Chemother (2001) 45: 1939-1940.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abubakar U, Al-Anazi M, Alanazi Z and Rodríguez-Baño J: Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on multidrug resistant gram positive and gram negative pathogens: A systematic review. J Infect Public Health (2023) 16: 320-331.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>