<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39189386</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-0801</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biomedical chromatography : BMC</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biomed Chromatogr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dissipation pattern and dietary risk assessment of chlorfenapyr and methomyl in corn under Egyptian field conditions.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e5992</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e5992</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/bmc.5992</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Corn is the second most widely farmed grain for human consumption. Low corn productivity due to damage caused by pests has led to using pesticides to control pest infestations. However, the uncontrolled application of pesticides on corn harms both environmental and human health. Accordingly, field experiments followed good agricultural practices to investigate the dissipation pattern and terminal residues of chlorfenapyr and methomyl in corn and compare the values with established safety limits. Gas chromatography-tandem mass spectrometer coupled with the quick, easy, cheap, effective, rugged, and safe technique was used to analyze residues of chlorfenapyr and methomyl in corn. The average recoveries varied from 94% to 105%, with relative standard deviations (RSDs) of 8%-13% for chlorfenapyr and from 99% to 111%, with RSDs of 10-16% for methomyl. Chlorfenapyr and methomyl residues degraded in corn following a first-order kinetic model, with an estimated half-life (t<sub>1/2</sub>) of 3.9 and 2.8 days, respectively, and significant degradation (91.4%-98.1.5%, respectively) after 14 days. Although the maximum residue limits of chlorfenapyr and methomyl for corn are yet to be formulated in Egypt, the long-term dietary risk for those pesticides was acceptable, with arisk quotient &lt; 100%, according to the national assessments. These findings are required to guide the correct and safe application of these insecticides in Egypt.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Biomedical Chromatography published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saber</LastName><ForeName>El-Sayed</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide Residues and Environmental Pollution Department, Central Agricultural Pesticide Laboratory, Agricultural Research Center, Dokki, Giza, 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malhat</LastName><ForeName>Farag</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide Residues and Environmental Pollution Department, Central Agricultural Pesticide Laboratory, Agricultural Research Center, Dokki, Giza, 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saber</LastName><ForeName>Ayman N</ForeName><Initials>AN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9651-3780</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide Residues and Environmental Pollution Department, Central Agricultural Pesticide Laboratory, Agricultural Research Center, Dokki, Giza, 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Analytical Chemistry, Institute of Chemistry for Energy and the Environment, University of Córdoba, Cordoba, 14071, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heikal</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide Department, Faculty of Agriculture, Menofiya University, Shebien El-Kom, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hussien</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, King Khalid University, Abha, 61413, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pesticide Formulation, Central Agricultural Pesticide Laboratory, Agricultural Research Center, Dokki, Giza, 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Biomed Chromatogr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8610241</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0269-3879</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">GC–MS/MS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">QuEChERS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">corn</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">residue distribution</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39189386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bmc.5992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdallah, O. I., Almaz, M. M., Arief, M. H., &amp; Abd El‐Aleem, A. H. (2014). Dissipation behavior of chlorfenapyr and difenoconazole residues in/on grapes (Vitis vinifera L.). Journal of Nature and Science, 12, 49–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel Ghani, S. B., &amp; Abdallah, O. I. (2016). Method validation and dissipation dynamics of chlorfenapyr in squash and okra. Food Chemistry, 194, 516–521. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.08.053</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agricultural Pesticide Committee. (2023). The approved recommendations for agricultural pest control — Egyptian agricultural pesticides Commit_tee. http://www.apc.gov.eg/en/default.aspx</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anastassiades, M., Lehotay, S. J., Štajnbaher, D., &amp; Schenck, F. J. (2003). Fast and easy multiresidue method employing acetonitrile extraction/partitioning and “dispersive solid‐phase extraction” for the determination of pesticide residues in produce. Journal of AOAC International, 86, 412–431. https://doi.org/10.1093/jaoac/86.2.412</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atalla, S. M. M., Abdel‐Kader, M. M., El‐Gamal, N. G., &amp; El‐Mougy, N. S. (2020). Using maize wastes, fermented by co‐cultures of Trichoderma harzianum and Pseudomonas fluorescens, as grain dressing against m maize diseases under field conditions. Egyptian Journal of Biological Pest Control, 30, 37. https://doi.org/10.1186/s41938-020-00236-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakry, M. M. S., &amp; Abdel‐Baky, N. F. (2023). Population density of the fall armyworm, Spodoptera frugiperda (smith) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) and its response to some ecological phenomena in maize crop. Brazilian Journal of Biology, 83. https://doi.org/10.1590/1519-6984.271354</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, Y., Chen, J., Wang, Y., Liang, J., Chen, L., &amp; Lu, Y. (2005). HPLC/UV analysis of chlorfenapyr residues in cabbage and soil to study the dynamics of different formulations. Science of the Total Environment, 350, 38–46. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2005.01.031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, T., Yu, X., Tian, X., Hu, J., Chen, Y., Long, G., Xu, H., &amp; Yang, G. F. (2022). Study on the environmental fate of three insecticides in garlic by in vivo sampling rate calibrated‐solid phase microextraction‐gas chromatography‐mass spectrometry. Food Chemistry, 367, 130740. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130740</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codex Alimentarius Commission. (1993). Standard for honey, ref. no. CL 1993/14, SH. FAO/WHO.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dasika, R., Tangirala, S., &amp; Naishadham, P. (2012). Pesticide residue analysis of fruits and vegetables. Journal of Environmental Chemistry and Ecotoxicology, 4, 19–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Groote, H., Kimenju, S. C., Munyua, B., Palmas, S., Kassie, M., &amp; Bruce, A. (2020). Spread and impact of fall armyworm (Spodoptera frugiperda J.E. Smith) in maize production areas of Kenya. Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment, 292, 106804. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agee.2019.106804</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deshmukh, S. S., Kiran, S., Naskar, A., Pradeep, P., Kalleshwaraswamy, C. M., &amp; Sharath, K. N. (2021). First record of a parasitoid, Megaselia (M) scalaris (Diptera: Phoridae) of fall armyworm, Spodoptera frugiperda (J. E. Smith) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) from India. Egyptian Journal of Biological Pest Control, 31, 0–3. https://doi.org/10.1186/s41938-021-00439-w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ditya, P., Das, S. P., Sarkar, P. K., &amp; Bhattacharyya, A. (2010). Degradation dynamics of chlorfenapyr residue in chili, cabbage and soil. Bulletin of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, 84, 602–605. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00128-010-9994-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Shamy, N. (2023). Indicators of productivity and economic efficiency of maize in Egypt. Assiut Journal of Agricultural Sciences, 54, 284–297. https://doi.org/10.21608/ajas.2023.188059.1222</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El‐Hefny, D., Abdallah, I., Helmy, R., &amp; Mahmoud, H. (2019). Dissipation of methomyl residues in tomato fruits, soil and water using LC‐MS/MS. Journal of Plant Protection Research, 59, 355–361. https://doi.org/10.24425/jppr.2019.129742</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EN 15662. (2018). Foods of plant origin ‐ multimethod for the determination of pesticide residues using GC‐ and LC‐based analysis following acetonitrile extraction/partitioning and clean‐up by dispersive SPE ‐ modular QuEChERS‐method Brussels: ILNAS‐EN 15662. https://iln</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, Y., Zhang, G., Zhang, A., Zhou, L., Bian, Y., Pan, J., Yang, S., Han, J., Ma, X., Qi, X., Liang, L., &amp; Zuo, B. (2022). Dissipation, residue, and dietary risk assessment of methoxyfenozide, chlorantraniliprole, indoxacarb, lufenuron, and chlorfenapyr in spinach using a modified QuEChERS method combined with a tandem mass spectrometry technique. Agronomy, 12, 3173. https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy12123173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galietta, G., Egaña, E., Gemelli, F., Maeso, D., Casco, N., Conde, P., &amp; Nuñez, S. (2010). Pesticide dissipation curves in peach, pear and tomato crops in Uruguay*. Journal of Environmental Science and Health, Part B, 46, 35–40. https://doi.org/10.1080/03601234.2010.515504</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García‐Lara, S., &amp; Serna‐Saldivar, S. O. (2019). Corn History and Culture. In Corn (pp. 1–18). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-811971-6.00001-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, J. X., Liu, C. Y., Lu, D. H., Chen, J. J., Deng, Y. C., &amp; Wang, F. H. (2015). Residue behavior and risk assessment of mixed formulation of imidacloprid and chlorfenapyr in chieh‐qua under field conditions. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 187, 650. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10661-015-4846-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IEDI. (2014). In: IEDI calculations for FAO/WHO acute dietary intake assessment.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IIMR. (2021). World maize scenario. Retrieved July 26, 2021, from https://iimr.icar.gov.in/world-maze-scenario/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kareem, K. T., Anjorin, F. B., Odeyemi, O. O., &amp; Akinbode, O. A. (2022). Fall armyworm (Spodoptera frugiperda) (J. E. Smith) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) infestation: Maize yield depression and physiological basis of tolerance. Journal of Plant Protection Research, 62, 12–21. https://doi.org/10.24425/jppr.2022.140294</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasoma, C., Shimelis, H., Laing, M., Shayanowako, A. I. T., &amp; Mathew, I. (2020). Screening of inbred lines of tropical maize for resistance to fall armyworm, and for yield and yield‐related traits. Crop Protection, 136, 105218. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cropro.2020.105218</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Chen, X., &amp; Hu, J. (2019). Dissipation behavior, residue distribution and dietary risk assessment of chlorfenapyr and clothianidin in leek using RRLC‐QqQ‐MS/MS technique. Chinese Chemical Letters, 30, 107–110. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cclet.2018.02.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loutfy, N., Malhat, F., Kamel, E., &amp; Saber, A. (2015). Residual pattern and dietary intake of iprodione on grapes under Egyptian field conditions: A prelude to risk assessment profile. Human and Ecological Risk Assessment, 21, 265–279. https://doi.org/10.1080/10807039.2014.909206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozowicka, B., Jankowska, M., Hrynko, I., &amp; Kaczynski, P. (2016). Removal of 16 pesticide residues from strawberries by washing with tap and ozone water, ultrasonic cleaning and boiling. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 188, 51. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10661-015-4850-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malhat, F., Hegazy, A., Barakat, D. A., Ibrahim, E.‐D., Hussien, M., Saber, E.‐S., &amp; Saber, A. N. (2024). Sulfoxaflor residues and exposure risk assessment in grape under Egyptian field conditions. Environmental Science and Pollution Research. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-024-34523-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malhat, F., Mahmoud, M., Barakat, D. A., Ibrahim, E. D., Elgammal, H., Hussien, M., &amp; Saber, A. N. (2024). Dissipation behavior, residue distribution, and exposure risk assessment of tebufenpyrad and milbemectin acaricides in strawberries under open field conditions. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 31, 35194–35205. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-024-33200-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malhat, F., Watanabe, H., &amp; Youssef, A. (2015). Degradation profile and safety evaluation of methomyl residues in tomato and soil. Hellenic Plant Protection Journal, 8, 55–62. https://doi.org/10.1515/hppj-2015-0008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martín‐Pozo, L., Arena, K., Cacciola, F., Dugo, P., &amp; Mondello, L. (2023). Development and validation of a multi‐class analysis of pesticides in corn products by comprehensive two‐dimensional liquid chromatography‐tandem mass spectrometry. Journal of Chromatography. A, 1701, 464064. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2023.464064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng, L., Zhong, Y., Guo, L., Wang, Z., Chen, K., &amp; Guo, Z. (2018). Recovery of cu and Zn from waste printed circuit boards using super‐gravity separation. Waste Management, 78, 559–565. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2018.06.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nottingham, L. B., &amp; Kuhar, T. P. (2021). Ambient moisture causes methomyl residues on corn plants to rapidly lose toxicity to the pest slug, Arion subfuscus, Müller (Gastropoda, Stylommatophora). Crop Protection, 147, 105709. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cropro.2021.105709</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ou, X.‐M., Huang, M.‐Z., Wang, X.‐G., &amp; Fan, D. (2006). Dissipation of chlorfenapyr residue in pakchoi and soil. Bulletin of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, 77, 810–815. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00128-006-1216-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patra, S., Ganguly, P., Barik, S. R., &amp; Samanta, A. (2018). Dissipation kinetics and risk assessment of chlorfenapyr on tomato and cabbage. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 190, 71. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10661-017-6457-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Payá, P., Anastassiades, M., Mack, D., Sigalova, I., Tasdelen, B., Oliva, J., &amp; Barba, A. (2007). Analysis of pesticide residues using the quick easy cheap effective rugged and safe (QuEChERS) pesticide multiresidue method in combination with gas and liquid chromatography and tandem mass spectrometric detection. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 389, 1697–1714. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216-007-1610-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman, M. M., Choi, J., Abd El‐Aty, A. M., Park, J. H., Park, J. Y., Im, G. J., &amp; Shim, J. H. (2012). Determination of chlorfenapyr in leek grown under greenhouse conditions with GC‐μECD and confirmation by mass spectrometry. Biomedical Chromatography, 26, 172–177. https://doi.org/10.1002/bmc.1643</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saber, A., Malhat, F., Anagnostopoulos, C., &amp; Kasiotis, K. M. (2020). Evaluation of dissipation, unit–unit‐variability and terminal residue of etoxazole residues in strawberries from two different parts in Egypt. Journal of Consumer Protection and Food Safety, 15, 229–236. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00003-019-01266-w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saber, A. N., Malhat, F. M., Badawy, H. M. A., &amp; Barakat, D. A. (2016). Dissipation dynamic, residue distribution and processing factor of hexythiazox in strawberry fruits under open field condition. Food Chemistry, 196, 1108–1116. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.10.052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SANTE/11312/2021. (2021). Guidance document on analytical quality control and method validation procedures for pesticide residues and analysis in food and feed. 1–57. Accessible at: https://www.eurl-pesticides.eu/docs/public/tmplt_article.asp?CntID=727</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sdeek, F. A., Morsy, A. R., Arafa, H. M., &amp; Kamel, E. (2016). Dissipation behavior of chlorfenapyr on citrus and tomato in Egypt. International Journal of Innovation and Applied Studies, 18, 131–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, K., Li, L., Yuan, L., Li, W., &amp; Liu, F. (2016). Residues and risk assessment of bifenthrin and chlorfenapyr in eggplant and soil under open ecosystem conditions. International Journal of Environmental Analytical Chemistry, 96, 173–184. https://doi.org/10.1080/03067319.2015.1137908</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sosan, M. B., Adeleye, A. O., Oyekunle, J. A. O., Udah, O., Oloruntunbi, P. M., Daramola, M. O., &amp; Saka, W. T. (2020). Dietary risk assessment of organochlorine pesticide residues in maize‐based complementary breakfast food products in Nigeria. Heliyon, 6, e05803. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05803</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veiga‐del‐Baño, J. M., Cuenca‐Martínez, J. J., Andreo‐Martínez, P., Andreo‐Martínez, P., Cámara, M. Á., Oliva, J., &amp; Motas, M. (2023). Uncertainty and associated risks in the analysis of pesticides in homogeneous paprika samples. Food Chemistry, 429, 136963. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.136963</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan, J., Huang, C., Li, C., Zhou, H. X., Ren, Y. L., Li, Z. Y., Xing, L. S., Zhang, B., Xi, Q. I., Bo, L. I., &amp; Liu, C. H. (2021). Biology, invasion and management of the agricultural invader: Fall armyworm, Spodoptera frugiperda (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae). Journal of Integrative Agriculture, 20, 646–663. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2095-3119(20)63367-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. (2003). GEMS/foodregionaldiets (regionalpercapitaconsumptionofrawandsemiprocesse_dagriculturalcommodities).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. (2013). Global environment monitoring system — Food contamination monitoring and GEMS/food. Assessment Programme.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, J., Luo, F., Zhou, L., Sun, H., Yu, H., Wang, X., Zhang, X., Yang, M., Lou, Z., &amp; Chen, Z. (2020). Residue reduction and risk evaluation of chlorfenapyr residue in tea planting, tea processing, and tea brewing. Science of the Total Environment, 738, 139613. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.139613</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z., Zhang, C., Liu, X., &amp; Hong, X. (2006). Dynamics of pesticide residues in the autumn Chinese cabbage (Brassica chinensis L.) grown in open fields. Pest Management Science, 62, 350–355. https://doi.org/10.1002/ps.1174</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, H., &amp; Hu, J. (2022). Total residue levels and risk assessment of flufenacet and its four metabolites in corn. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis, 106, 104268. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfca.2021.104268</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, Y., Adoley, A. T. N., Fateh, B., Wu, W., Hu, G., Qiu, L., &amp; Chen, J. (2020). Determination of methomyl residues in Bohe by ultrahigh‐performance liquid chromatography‐tandem mass spectrometry (UPLC‐MS). International Journal of Analytical Chemistry, 2020, 4–7. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/8817964</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>