<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39194906</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2309-608X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of fungi (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Fungi (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Mechanisms of Cadmium Stress Mitigation by Fungal Endophytes from Maize Grains.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">581</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/jof10080581</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Maize is a crucial staple crop that ensures global food security by supplying essential nutrients. However, heavy metal (HM) contamination inhibits maize growth, reduces output, and affects food security. Some endophytic fungi (EFs) in maize seeds have the potential to enhance growth and increase dry biomass, offering a solution to mitigate the negative effect of HM contamination. Using these functional EFs could help maintain crop production and ensure food safety in HM-contaminated areas. In the present study, the diversity of EFs in corn grains from various HM-contaminated areas in China was studied through culture-dependent and culture-independent methods. We tested the plant growth-promoting (PGP) traits of several dominant culturable isolates and evaluated the growth-promoting effects of these twenty-one isolates through pot experiments. Both studies showed that HM contamination increased the diversity and richness of corn grain EFs and affected the most dominant endophytes. <i>Nigrospora</i> and <i>Fusarium</i> were the most prevalent culturable endophytes in HM-contaminated areas. Conversely, <i>Cladosporium</i> spp. were the most isolated endophytes in non-contaminated areas. Different from this, <i>Saccharomycopsis</i> and <i>Fusarium</i> were the dominant EFs in HM-contaminated sites, while <i>Neofusicoccum</i> and <i>Sarocladium</i> were dominant in non-contaminated sites, according to a culture-independent analysis. PGP trait tests indicated that 70% of the tested isolates (forty-two) exhibited phosphorus solubilization, IAA production, or siderophore production activity. Specifically, 90% of the tested isolates from HM-contaminated sites showed better PGP results than 45% of the isolates from non-contaminated sites. The benefit of the twenty-one isolates on host plant growth was further studied through pot experiments, which showed that all the isolates could improve host plant growth. Among them, strains derived from HM-contaminated sites, including AK18 (<i>Nigrospora</i>), AK32 (<i>Beauveria</i>), SD93 (<i>Gibberellia</i>), and SD64 (<i>Fusarium</i>), had notable effects on enhancing the dry biomass of shoots and roots of maize under Cd stress. We speculate that the higher ratio of PGP EFs in corn grains from HM-contaminated areas may explain their competitiveness in such extreme environments. <i>Fusarium</i> and <i>Cladosporium</i> isolates show high PGP properties, but they can also be phytopathogenic. Therefore, it is essential to evaluate their pathogenic properties and safety for crops before considering their practical use in agriculture.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Awais</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Environmental Science and Engineering, Medical School, Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming 650500, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiang</LastName><ForeName>Yingying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Affiliated Yanan Hospital of Kunming Medical University, Kunming 650051, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Dian</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Environmental Science and Engineering, Medical School, Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming 650500, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lai</LastName><ForeName>Yibin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Environmental Science and Engineering, Medical School, Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming 650500, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cai</LastName><ForeName>Fenglian</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Environmental Science and Engineering, Medical School, Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming 650500, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shah</LastName><ForeName>Naila</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Botany, Gardan Campus, Abdul Wali Khan University Mardan, Mardan 23200, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Majid</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Cotton Research, Chinese Academy of Agriculture Sciences, Anyang 455000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Haiyan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7041-3199</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Environmental Science and Engineering, Medical School, Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming 650500, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>KUST-AN2023006Y</GrantID><Agency>Kunming University of Science and Technology Plan Project (Medical Joint Special Project)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>42267059</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SKLEG2023216</GrantID><Agency>State Key Laboratory of Environmental Geochemistry</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>J Fungi (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101671827</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2309-608X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cd tolerance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Zea mays</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">corn grains</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">heavy metal contamination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">plant growth promotion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pot experiment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">seed endophytes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39194906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11355786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jof10080581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">jof10080581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Erenstein O., Jaleta M., Sonder K., Mottaleb K., Prasanna B. Global maize production, consumption and trade: Trends and R&amp;D implications. Food Secur. 2022;14:1295–1319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahzad A., Siddique A., Ferdous S., Amin M.A., Qin M., Aslam U., Naeem M., Bashir T., Shakoor A. Heavy metals mitigation and growth promoting effect of endophytic Agrococcus terreus (MW 979614) in maize plants under zinc and nickel contaminated soil. Front. Microbiol. 2023;14:1255921. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2023.1255921.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1255921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10668838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38029198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albahri G., Alyamani A.A., Badran A., Hijazi A., Nasser M., Maresca M., Baydoun E. Enhancing essential grains yield for sustainable food security and bio-safe agriculture through latest innovative approaches. Agronomy. 2023;13:1709. doi: 10.3390/agronomy13071709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agronomy13071709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman Z., Singh V.P. The relative impact of toxic heavy metals (THMs)(arsenic (As), cadmium (Cd), chromium (Cr)(VI), mercury (Hg), and lead (Pb)) on the total environment: An overview. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2019;191:419. doi: 10.1007/s10661-019-7528-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-019-7528-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31177337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashid A., Schutte B.J., Ulery A., Deyholos M.K., Sanogo S., Lehnhoff E.A., Beck L. Heavy metal contamination in agricultural soil: Environmental pollutants affecting crop health. Agronomy. 2023;13:1521. doi: 10.3390/agronomy13061521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agronomy13061521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J., Sun Z. Evaluation of shallow groundwater contamination and associated human health risk in an alluvial plain impacted by agricultural and industrial activities, mid-west China. Expo. Health. 2016;8:311–329. doi: 10.1007/s12403-015-0170-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12403-015-0170-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Wang P., Gojenko B., Yu J., Wei L., Luo D., Xiao T. A review of water pollution arising from agriculture and mining activities in Central Asia: Facts, causes and effects. Environ. Pollut. 2021;291:118209. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34563852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou D., O’Connor D., Igalavithana A.D., Alessi D.S., Luo J., Tsang D.C., Sparks D.L., Yamauchi Y., Rinklebe J., Ok Y.S. Metal contamination and bioremediation of agricultural soils for food safety and sustainability. Nat. Rev. Earth Environ. 2020;1:366–381. doi: 10.1038/s43017-020-0061-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43017-020-0061-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma M. Bioremediation and Biotechnology, Volume 2: Degradation of Pesticides and Heavy Metals. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2020. Ecotoxicology of heavy metals: Sources, effects and toxicity; pp. 13–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H., Zhao Y., Wang Z., Liu Y. Distribution characteristics, bioaccumulation and trophic transfer of heavy metals in the food web of grassland ecosystems. Chemosphere. 2021;278:130407. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.130407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.130407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33823346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sonone S.S., Jadhav S., Sankhla M.S., Kumar R. Water contamination by heavy metals and their toxic effect on aquaculture and human health through food Chain. Lett. Appl. NanoBioScience. 2020;10:2148–2166.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey P., Tripathi A., Dwivedi S., Lal K., Jhang T. Deciphering the mechanisms, hormonal signaling, and potential applications of endophytic microbes to mediate stress tolerance in medicinal plants. Front. Plant Sci. 2023;14:1250020. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2023.1250020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2023.1250020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10684941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38034581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govindasamy V., George P., Raina S.K., Kumar M., Rane J., Annapurna K. Advances in Crop Environment Interaction. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2018. Plant-associated microbial interactions in the soil environment: Role of endophytes in imparting abiotic stress tolerance to crops; pp. 245–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam B., Lǐ J., Gě Q., Khan M.A., Gōng J., Mehmood S., Yuán Y., Gǒng W. Endophytic fungi: From symbiosis to secondary metabolite communications or vice versa? Front. Plant Sci. 2021;12:791033. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2021.791033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2021.791033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8718612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34975976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J.-L., Sun X., Zheng Y., Lü P.-P., Wang Y.-L., Guo L.-D. Diversity and community of culturable endophytic fungi from stems and roots of desert halophytes in northwest China. MycoKeys. 2020;62:75. doi: 10.3897/mycokeys.62.38923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3897/mycokeys.62.38923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7010840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32076383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fontana D.C., de Paula S., Torres A.G., de Souza V.H.M., Pascholati S.F., Schmidt D., Dourado Neto D. Endophytic fungi: Biological control and induced resistance to phytopathogens and abiotic stresses. Pathogens. 2021;10:570. doi: 10.3390/pathogens10050570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens10050570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8151296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34066672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baron N.C., Rigobelo E.C. Endophytic fungi: A tool for plant growth promotion and sustainable agriculture. Mycology. 2022;13:39–55. doi: 10.1080/21501203.2021.1945699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21501203.2021.1945699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8856089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35186412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S., Kaushik N. Endophytic fungi isolated from oil-seed crop Jatropha curcas produces oil and exhibit antifungal activity. PLoS ONE. 2013;8:e56202. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0056202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3568098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23409154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabbasum I., Ali A., Shafique U., Bibi I., Khalid B., Ijaz N., Naseer M.U. Role of endophytic fungal species in plant growth promotion and in sustainable agricultural productions: A review. J. Microbiol. Mol. Genet. 2022;3:1–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao M., Xiong C., Gao C., Tsui C.K., Wang M.-M., Zhou X., Zhang A.-M., Cai L. Disease-induced changes in plant microbiome assembly and functional adaptation. Microbiome. 2021;9:187. doi: 10.1186/s40168-021-01138-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40168-021-01138-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8444440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34526096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi X., Zhao Y., Xu M., Ma L., Adams J.M., Shi Y. Insight into Plant-Microbe Interactions in rhizosphere for Sustainable Agriculture in the New Crops Era. New Crops. 2024;1:100004. doi: 10.1016/j.ncrops.2023.11.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ncrops.2023.11.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li T., Yang W., Wu S., Selosse M.-A., Gao J. Progress and prospects of mycorrhizal fungal diversity in orchids. Front. Plant Sci. 2021;12:646325. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2021.646325.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2021.646325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8138444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34025694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander H.M. Disease in natural plant populations, communities, and ecosystems: Insights into ecological and evolutionary processes. Plant Dis. 2010;94:492–503. doi: 10.1094/PDIS-94-5-0492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PDIS-94-5-0492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30754479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma K.-W., Niu Y., Jia Y., Ordon J., Copeland C., Emonet A., Geldner N., Guan R., Stolze S.C., Nakagami H. Coordination of microbe–host homeostasis by crosstalk with plant innate immunity. Nat. Plants. 2021;7:814–825. doi: 10.1038/s41477-021-00920-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41477-021-00920-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8208891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34031541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv G.-H., Li Y.-Q., Chen J.-J., Wu Z.-X., Wu W.-M., Wu X.-H., Lin H.-J., Wang T. ZmHMA3 enhances heavy mental Zn stress tolerance and mediates Zn transport in Maize. Res. Sq. 2023. priprint .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-2970282/v1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrović S., Mitov D., Mrmošanin J., Arsić B., Pavlović A., Tošić S. The national maize hybrid as a potential mediator in the contamination of the food chain with heavy metals. Int. J. Environ. Anal. Chem. 2023:1–14. doi: 10.1080/03067319.2023.2230145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03067319.2023.2230145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Li Z., Zhang G., Liang X., Hu L., Li Y., He Y., Zhan F. Dark septate endophyte Exophiala pisciphila promotes maize growth and alleviates cadmium toxicity. Front. Microbiol. 2023;14:1165131. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2023.1165131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1165131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10126344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37113231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamaji K., Watanabe Y., Masuya H., Shigeto A., Yui H., Haruma T. Root fungal endophytes enhance heavy-metal stress tolerance of Clethra barbinervis growing naturally at mining sites via growth enhancement, promotion of nutrient uptake and decrease of heavy-metal concentration. PLoS ONE. 2016;11:e0169089. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0169089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0169089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5193448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28030648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Silva J.A.T., Winarto B., Dobránszki J., Cardoso J.C., Zeng S. Tissue disinfection for preparation of culture. Folia Hortic. 2016;28:57–75. doi: 10.1515/fhort-2016-0008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/fhort-2016-0008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geisen S., Kostenko O., Cnossen M.C., Ten Hooven F.C., Vreš B., van Der Putten W.H. Seed and root endophytic fungi in a range expanding and a related plant species. Front. Microbiol. 2017;8:1645. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2017.01645.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5581836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28900420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fouda A.H., Hassan S.E.-D., Eid A.M., Ewais E.E.-D. Biotechnological applications of fungal endophytes associated with medicinal plant Asclepias sinaica (Bioss.) Ann. Agric. Sci. 2015;60:95–104. doi: 10.1016/j.aoas.2015.04.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aoas.2015.04.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salem-Bango Z., Price T.K., Chan J.L., Chandrasekaran S., Garner O.B., Yang S. Fungal whole-genome sequencing for species identification: From test development to clinical utilization. J. Fungi. 2023;9:183. doi: 10.3390/jof9020183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jof9020183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9965959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36836298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao H., Sun X., He C., Maitra P., Li X.-C., Guo L.-D. Phyllosphere epiphytic and endophytic fungal community and network structures differ in a tropical mangrove ecosystem. Microbiome. 2019;7:57. doi: 10.1186/s40168-019-0671-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40168-019-0671-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6456958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30967154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan K., Pei Z., Meng L., Zheng Y., Wang L., Feng R., Li Q., Liu Y., Zhao X., Wei Q. Determination of community structure and diversity of seed-vectored endophytic fungi in Alpinia zerumbet. Front. Microbiol. 2022;13:814864. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2022.814864.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.814864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8918987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35295292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhayanithy G., Subban K., Chelliah J. Diversity and biological activities of endophytic fungi associated with Catharanthus roseus. BMC Microbiol. 2019;19:22. doi: 10.1186/s12866-019-1386-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12866-019-1386-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6341747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30665368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellemain E., Carlsen T., Brochmann C., Coissac E., Taberlet P., Kauserud H. ITS as an environmental DNA barcode for fungi: An in silico approach reveals potential PCR biases. BMC Microbiol. 2010;10:189. doi: 10.1186/1471-2180-10-189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-10-189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2909996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20618939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y., Xiong Z., Wu G., Bai W., Zhu Z., Gao Y., Parmar S., Sharma V.K., Li H. Fungal endophytic communities of two wild Rosa varieties with different powdery mildew susceptibilities. Front. Microbiol. 2018;9:2462. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2018.02462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.02462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6198141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30386316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling L., Feng L., Li Y., Yue R., Wang Y., Zhou Y. Endophytic Fungi Volatile Organic Compounds as Crucial Biocontrol Agents Used for Controlling Fruit and Vegetable Postharvest Diseases. J. Fungi. 2024;10:332. doi: 10.3390/jof10050332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jof10050332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11122075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38786687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attia M.S., Salem M.S., Abdelaziz A.M. Endophytic fungi Aspergillus spp. reduce fusarial wilt disease severity, enhance growth, metabolism and stimulate the plant defense system in pepper plants. Biomass Convers. Biorefinery. 2022;14:16603–16613. doi: 10.1007/s13399-022-03607-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13399-022-03607-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez J., Wang K. A sterilization protocol for field-harvested maize mature seed used for in vitro culture and genetic transformation. Maize Genet. Coop. Newsl. 2009;83:2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah N., Irshad M., Hussain A., Qadir M., Murad W., Khan A., Awais M., Alrefaei A.F., Ali S. EDTA and IAA Ameliorates Phytoextraction Potential and Growth of Sunflower by Mitigating Cu-Induced Morphological and Biochemical Injuries. Life. 2023;13:759. doi: 10.3390/life13030759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/life13030759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10051917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36983913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilal S., Shahzad R., Imran M., Jan R., Kim K.M., Lee I.-J. Synergistic association of endophytic fungi enhances Glycine max L. resilience to combined abiotic stresses: Heavy metals, high temperature and drought stress. Ind. Crops Prod. 2020;143:111931. doi: 10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.111931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.111931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma A., Shameem N., Jatav H.S., Sathyanarayana E., Parray J.A., Poczai P., Sayyed R. Fungal endophytes to combat biotic and abiotic stresses for climate-smart and sustainable agriculture. Front. Plant Sci. 2022;13:953836. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2022.953836.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.953836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9294639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35865289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizaludin M.S., Stopnisek N., Raaijmakers J.M., Garbeva P. The Chemistry of Stress: Understanding the ‘Cry for Help’ of Plant Roots. Metabolites. 2021;11:357. doi: 10.3390/metabo11060357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/metabo11060357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8228326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34199628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phour M., Sehrawat A., Sindhu S.S., Glick B.R. Interkingdom signaling in plant-rhizomicrobiome interactions for sustainable agriculture. Microbiol. Res. 2020;241:126589. doi: 10.1016/j.micres.2020.126589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2020.126589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32927204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Passarini M.R.Z., Ottoni J.R., Costa P.E.d.S., Hissa D.C., Falcão R.M., Melo V.M.M., Balbino V.Q., Mendonça L.A.R., Lima M.G.d.S., Coutinho H.D.M. Fungal community diversity of heavy metal contaminated soils revealed by metagenomics. Arch. Microbiol. 2022;204:255. doi: 10.1007/s00203-022-02860-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00203-022-02860-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35412096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang W., Gong W., Xiao R., Mao W., Zhao L., Song J., Awais M., Ji X., Li H. Endophytic fungal community of Stellera chamaejasme L. and its possible role in improving host plants’ ecological flexibility in degraded grasslands. J. Fungi. 2023;9:465. doi: 10.3390/jof9040465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jof9040465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10146894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37108919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y., Huang Y., Hou J., Wu L., Christie P., Liu W. Microbial community assembly of the hyperaccumulator plant Sedum plumbizincicola in two contrasting soil types with three levels of cadmium contamination. Sci. Total Environ. 2023;863:160917. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.160917.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.160917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36529394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah N., Qadir M., Irshad M., Hussain A., Hamayun M., Murad W., Khan A., Al-Harrasi A. Enhancement of Cadmium Phytoremediation Potential of Helianthus annuus L. with Application of EDTA and IAA. Metabolites. 2022;12:1049. doi: 10.3390/metabo12111049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/metabo12111049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9692325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36355131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah N., Irshad M., Hussain A., Mehmood A., Murad W., Qadir M., Awais M., Shah M., Khan N. The deteriorating effects of cadmium accumulation on the yield and quality of maize crops. S. Afr. J. Bot. 2023;160:732–738. doi: 10.1016/j.sajb.2023.07.050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2023.07.050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gadd G.M. Metals, minerals and microbes: Geomicrobiology and bioremediation. Microbiology. 2010;156:609–643. doi: 10.1099/mic.0.037143-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/mic.0.037143-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20019082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romano-Armada N., Yañez-Yazlle M.F., Irazusta V.P., Rajal V.B., Moraga N.B. Potential of Bioremediation and PGP Traits in Streptomyces as Strategies for Bio-Reclamation of Salt-Affected Soils for Agriculture. Pathogens. 2020;9:117. doi: 10.3390/pathogens9020117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens9020117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7169405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32069867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gowtham H., Hema P., Murali M., Shilpa N., Nataraj K., Basavaraj G., Singh S.B., Aiyaz M., Udayashankar A., Amruthesh K.N. Fungal Endophytes as Mitigators against Biotic and Abiotic Stresses in Crop Plants. J. Fungi. 2024;10:116. doi: 10.3390/jof10020116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jof10020116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10890593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38392787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng J., Xie X., Li C., Wang H., Yu Y., Huang B. Regulation mechanism of plant response to heavy metal stress mediated by endophytic fungi. Int. J. Phytoremediat. 2023;25:1596–1613. doi: 10.1080/15226514.2023.2176466.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15226514.2023.2176466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36786203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui J., Nie F., Zhao Y., Zhang D., Zhou D., Wu J., Qu L., Xiao L., Liu L. A review on plant endophytes in response to abiotic stress. Environ. Pollut. Bioavailab. 2024;36:2323123. doi: 10.1080/26395940.2024.2323123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/26395940.2024.2323123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S., Walker R., Schicklberger M., Nico P.S., Fox P.M., Karaoz U., Chakraborty R., Brodie E.L. Microbial phosphorus mobilization strategies across a natural nutrient limitation gradient and evidence for linkage with iron solubilization traits. Front. Microbiol. 2021;12:572212. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2021.572212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.572212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8261140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34248859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qadir M., Hussain A., Shah M., Lee I.J., Iqbal A., Irshad M., Ismail, Sayyed A., Husna, Ahmad A., et al. Comparative assessment of chromate bioremediation potential of Pantoea conspicua and Aspergillus niger. J. Hazard. Mater. 2022;424:127314. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.127314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.127314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34600376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva L.I.d., Pereira M.C., Carvalho A.M.X.d., Buttrós V.H., Pasqual M., Dória J. Phosphorus-solubilizing microorganisms: A key to sustainable agriculture. Agriculture. 2023;13:462. doi: 10.3390/agriculture13020462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agriculture13020462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain R., Bhardwaj P., Pandey S.S., Kumar S. Arnebia euchroma, a plant species of cold desert in the Himalayas, harbors beneficial cultivable endophytes in roots and leaves. Front. Microbiol. 2021;12:696667. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2021.696667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.696667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8322769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34335527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen K.B.T., Phan T.H.T. Application of plant endophytic microorganisms (Endophytes) in the treatment of heavy metal pollution in Soils; Proceedings of the International Conference on Geo-Spatial Technologies and Earth Resources; Hanoi, Vietnam. 13–14 October 2022; pp. 199–221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goryluk-Salmonowicz A.D., Myczka A., Popowska M. Antibiotic and heavy metal resistant endophytes inhabit Armeria maritima hyperaccumulator. Plant Soil. 2023;495:57–76. doi: 10.1007/s11104-023-06320-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11104-023-06320-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zakaria L. Fusarium species associated with diseases of major tropical fruit crops. Horticulturae. 2023;9:322. doi: 10.3390/horticulturae9030322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/horticulturae9030322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stępień Ł. Plant-pathogenic Fusarium species. J. Fungi. 2022;9:13. doi: 10.3390/jof9010013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jof9010013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9866786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36675834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hafez M., Telfer M., Chatterton S., Aboukhaddour R. Plant-Pathogen Interactions. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2023. Specific Detection and Quantification of Major Fusarium spp. Associated with Cereal and Pulse Crops; pp. 1–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37249881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimi Tamandegani P., Zafari D. Evaluation of different Fusarium species–wheat interactions effect on Cd biosorption by wheat seedlings. Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2019;16:1873–1884. doi: 10.1007/s13762-017-1621-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13762-017-1621-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jedidi I., Mateo E.M., Marín P., Jiménez M., Said S., González-Jaén M.T. Contamination of wheat, barley, and maize seeds with toxigenic Fusarium species and their mycotoxins in Tunisia. J. AOAC Int. 2021;104:959–967. doi: 10.1093/jaoacint/qsab020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jaoacint/qsab020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33576795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang F.-H., Li X.-Q., Duan L.-Y., Chen Y., Ji M.-F., Zhang H., Han H., Chen Z.-J. High-Throughput Sequencing Combined with Metabonomics to Analyze the Effect of Heavy Metal Contamination on Farmland Soil Microbial Community and Function. Huan Jing Ke Xue = Huanjing Kexue. 2022;43:4333–4341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35971729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Hafez S.I., Ismail M.A., Hussein N.A., Abdel-Hameed N.A. Fusarium species and other fungi associated with some seeds and grains in Egypt, with 2 newly recorded Fusarium species. J. Biol. Earth Sci. 2014;4:B120–B129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oller-López J.L., Avalos J., Barrero A.F., Oltra J.E. Improved GA1 production by Fusarium fujikuroi. Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2003;63:282–285. doi: 10.1007/s00253-003-1376-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-003-1376-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12827323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilal L., Asaf S., Hamayun M., Gul H., Iqbal A., Ullah I., Lee I.-J., Hussain A. Plant growth promoting endophytic fungi Asprgillus fumigatus TS1 and Fusarium proliferatum BRL1 produce gibberellins and regulates plant endogenous hormones. Symbiosis. 2018;76:117–127. doi: 10.1007/s13199-018-0545-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13199-018-0545-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>