<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39194372</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1477-092X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of oncology pharmacy practice : official publication of the International Society of Oncology Pharmacy Practitioners</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Oncol Pharm Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Cellular therapy site-preparedness: Inpatient pharmacy implementation at a large academic medical center.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>10781552241279025</StartPage><MedlinePgn>10781552241279025</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/10781552241279025</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">With the recent Food &amp; Drug Administration (FDA) approval of cellular therapy that requires product manipulation prior to administration in combination with a short stability window, the need was identified for local dose preparation within the pharmacy rather than the off-site stem cell processing laboratory. This approval gave rise to assessment of regulatory standards surrounding cellular therapy, evaluation and revision of current standard operating procedures and policies with formal process validation, assessment of occupational exposure mitigation and safety considerations, and development of staff training and education.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To describe and provide insight into the stepwise process of FACT validation and onboarding of commercially available cellular therapy products that require sterile compounding manipulation within a pharmacy prior to administration.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">A multidisciplinary effort is required to attain FACT certification and implement pharmacist compounding of cellular therapy products.<sup>1</sup> Local preparation within a pharmacy facilitates a sound operational workflow and provides a pathway to perform aseptic manipulations of cellular therapy products safely and efficiently.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Safe and successful administration of cellular therapies handled and compounded by pharmacy department staff along with program validation requires a preemptive review utilizing a multidisciplinary approach for process development. This manuscript will provide a foundation based on consistency and transparency in effective cellular therapy sterile compounding and aseptic manipulation, proper handling and disposal procedures, increased communication through creation and optimization of treatment plans and order-sets, standardized medical center staff education, and development of policies and standard operating procedures for the entire health care team.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martino</LastName><ForeName>Janine G</ForeName><Initials>JG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8781-962X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, UC San Diego Health, Jacobs Medical Center, La Jolla, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McConnell</LastName><ForeName>Kim</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Investigational Drug Service, UC San Diego Health, Jacobs Medical Center, La Jolla, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Greathouse</LastName><ForeName>Lorraine</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Blood and Marrow Transplant, UC San Diego Health, Moores Cancer Center, La Jolla, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rosario</LastName><ForeName>Brent Del</ForeName><Initials>BD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, UC San Diego Health, Jacobs Medical Center, La Jolla, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jaskowiak</LastName><ForeName>Jaclyn M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, UC San Diego Health, Jacobs Medical Center, La Jolla, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Oncol Pharm Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9511372</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1078-1552</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cellular therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FACT validation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inpatient pharmacy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lisocabtagene maraleucel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sterile compounding</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of conflicting interestsThe authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39194372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/10781552241279025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>