<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39195345</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-6535</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical pharmacology and therapeutics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Pharmacol Ther</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessing Post-Marketing Requirements for Orphan Drugs: A Cross-Sectional Analysis of FDA and EMA Oversight.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/cpt.3397</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the European Medicines Agency (EMA) oversee pharmaceutical regulations, including orphan drugs targeting rare diseases with limited patient populations. Post-marketing studies are crucial for monitoring safety and efficacy, with post-marketing requirements (PMRs) mandated by the regulatory agencies to ensure compliance. This study aims to compare PMR statuses, objectives, and pivotal trial characteristics of orphan drugs approved by the FDA (n = 154) and EMA (n = 79) from 2008 to 2018, shedding light on regulatory differences and their impact on drug development. Contrary to expectations, our analysis found no significant disparity in the proportion of orphan drugs with and without PMRs approved by both the FDA (48.1%) and EMA (55.7%). Safety concerns surrounding orphan drugs post-approval, attributed partly to pivotal trial design, underscore the need for robust post-marketing surveillance. While the FDA primarily focuses on post-marketing safety (36.1%), the EMA places a higher emphasis on both efficacy and safety (47.1%), reflecting distinct approaches to PMR management between the two regulatory bodies. The observed trend of delayed PMRs at the EMA (47.1%) highlights the importance of effective cooperation between regulators and pharmaceutical companies to ensure the timely completion of PMRs and enhance drug safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Clinical Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American Society for Clinical Pharmacology and Therapeutics.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Jae Hyeon</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, Daegu Catholic University, Gyeongsan, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Sangwon</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3862-9491</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Hanyang University, College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacology and Therapeutics, Hanyang University Seoul Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Yoon Jung</ForeName><Initials>YJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, Daegu Catholic University, Gyeongsan, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Won Young</ForeName><Initials>WY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, Daegu Catholic University, Gyeongsan, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Min Jung</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, Daegu Catholic University, Gyeongsan, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Yun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9809-7351</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, Daegu Catholic University, Gyeongsan, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Pharmacol Ther</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0372741</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0009-9236</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39195345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cpt.3397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Fan, M. et al. Postmarketing safety of orphan drugs: a longitudinal analysis of the US Food and Drug Administration database between 1999 and 2018. Orphanet J. Rare Dis. 17, 3 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giannuzzi, V. et al. Orphan medicinal products in Europe and United States to cover needs of patients with rare diseases: an increased common effort is to be foreseen. Orphanet J. Rare Dis. 12, 64 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Althobaiti, H., Seoane‐Vazquez, E., Brown, L.M., Fleming, M.L. &amp; Rodriguez‐Monguio, R. Disentangling the cost of orphan drugs marketed in the United States. Healthcare (Basel) 11, 558 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Micallef, J. &amp; Blin, O. Orphan drug designation in Europe: a booster for the research and development of drugs in rare diseases. Therapie 75, 133–139 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, R. et al. Trends in rare disease drug development. Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 23, 168–169 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tambuyzer, E. et al. Therapies for rare diseases: therapeutic modalities, progress and challenges ahead. Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 19, 93–111 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maier, W.C., Christensen, R.A. &amp; Anderson, P. Post‐approval studies for rare disease treatments and orphan drugs. Adv. Exp. Med. Biol. 1031, 197–205 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson, L.S., Loh, M. &amp; Perrone, J. Assuring safety of inherently unsafe medications: the FDA risk evaluation and mitigation strategies. J. Med. Toxicol. 10, 165–172 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA. Postmarketing Studies and Clinical Trials—Implementation of Section 505(o)(3) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act Guidance for Industry &lt;https://www.fda.gov/regulatory‐information/search‐fda‐guidance‐documents/postmarketing‐studies‐and‐clinical‐trials‐implementation‐section‐505o3‐federal‐food‐drug‐and&gt; (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall, A.K. &amp; Carlson, M.R. The current status of orphan drug development in Europe and the US. Intractable Rare Dis Res 3, 1–7 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EMA. Guideline on good pharmacovigilance practices (GVP); Module VIII – Post‐authorisation safety studies (Rev 3) &lt;https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/scientific‐guideline/guideline‐good‐pharmacovigilance‐practices‐gvp‐module‐viii‐post‐authorisation‐safety‐studies‐rev‐3_en.pdf&gt; (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller, K.L., Fermaglich, L.J. &amp; Maynard, J. Using four decades of FDA orphan drug designations to describe trends in rare disease drug development: substantial growth seen in development of drugs for rare oncologic, neurologic, and pediatric‐onset diseases. Orphanet J. Rare Dis. 16, 265 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin, E.Y., Hong, Y.J., Lim, K.M., Kim, T.H. &amp; Lee, J.H. International comparison of availability for orphan drugs: focused on approved orphan drugs in South Korea. J Pharm Policy Pract 17, 2354299 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michaeli, D.T., Michaeli, T., Albers, S., Boch, T. &amp; Michaeli, J.C. Special FDA designations for drug development: orphan, fast track, accelerated approval, priority review, and breakthrough therapy. Eur. J. Health Econ. 11, 1–19 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teixeira, T., Kweder, S.L. &amp; Saint‐Raymond, A. Are the European medicines agency, US Food and Drug Administration, and other international regulators talking to each other? Clin. Pharmacol. Ther. 107, 507–513 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA. Postmarketing Requirements and Commitments: Status and Fulfillment Categories &lt;https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket‐requirements‐and‐commitments/postmarketing‐requirements‐and‐commitments‐status‐and‐fulfillment‐categories&gt; (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherla, A., Mossialos, E., Salcher‐Konrad, M., Kesselheim, A.S. &amp; Naci, H. Post‐marketing requirements for cancer drugs approved by the European medicines agency, 2004–2014. Clin. Pharmacol. Ther. 112, 846–852 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onakpoya, I.J., Spencer, E.A., Thompson, M.J. &amp; Heneghan, C.J. Effectiveness, safety and costs of orphan drugs: an evidence‐based review. BMJ Open 5, e007199 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell, S.A. &amp; Tudur Smith, C. A comparison of interventional clinical trials in rare versus non‐rare diseases: an analysis of ClinicalTrials.Gov. Orphanet J. Rare Dis. 9, 170 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michaeli, T., Jurges, H. &amp; Michaeli, D.T. FDA approval, clinical trial evidence, efficacy, epidemiology, and price for non‐orphan and ultra‐rare, rare, and common orphan cancer drug indications: cross sectional analysis. BMJ 381, e073242 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kesselheim, A.S., Myers, J.A. &amp; Avorn, J. Characteristics of clinical trials to support approval of orphan vs nonorphan drugs for cancer. JAMA 305, 2320–2326 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naci, H. et al. Design characteristics, risk of bias, and reporting of randomised controlled trials supporting approvals of cancer drugs by European medicines agency, 2014‐16: cross sectional analysis. BMJ 366, l5221 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dechartres, A., Trinquart, L., Boutron, I. &amp; Ravaud, P. Influence of trial sample size on treatment effect estimates: meta‐epidemiological study. BMJ 346, f2304 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dauner, D.G., Dauner, K.N. &amp; Peterson, A.L.H. FDA's unimproved enforcement of Postmarketing requirements and commitments: implications for providers and patients. Res. Social Adm. Pharm. 16, 844–847 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maeda, K., Kaneko, M., Narukawa, M. &amp; Arato, T. Points to consider: efficacy and safety evaluations in the clinical development of ultra‐orphan drugs. Orphanet J. Rare Dis. 12, 143 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monge, A.N., Sigelman, D.W., Temple, R.J. &amp; Chahal, H.S. Use of US Food and Drug Administration expedited drug development and review programs by orphan and nonorphan novel drugs approved from 2008 to 2021. JAMA Netw. Open 5, e2239336 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kesselheim, A.S., Wang, B., Franklin, J.M. &amp; Darrow, J.J. Trends in utilization of FDA expedited drug development and approval programs, 1987–2014: cohort study. BMJ 351, h4633 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward, L.M., Chambers, A., Mechichi, E., Wong‐Rieger, D. &amp; Campbell, C. An international comparative analysis of public reimbursement of orphan drugs in Canadian provinces compared to European countries. Orphanet J. Rare Dis. 17, 113 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichler, H.G. et al. The risks of risk aversion in drug regulation. Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 12, 907–916 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller, J.E. et al. Evaluation of drug trials in high‐, middle‐, and low‐income countries and local commercial availability of newly approved drugs. JAMA Netw. Open 4, e217075 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalali, R., Nogueira‐Rodrigues, A., Das, A., Sirohi, B. &amp; Panda, P.K. Drug development in low‐ and middle‐income countries: opportunity or exploitation? Am. Soc. Clin. Oncol. Educ. Book 42, 1–8 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller, K.L. &amp; Lanthier, M. Orphan drug label expansions: analysis of subsequent rare and common indication approvals. Health Aff (Millwood) 43, 18–26 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chambers, J.D., Clifford, K.A., Enright, D.E. &amp; Neumann, P.J. Follow‐on indications for orphan drugs related to the inflation reduction act. JAMA Netw. Open 6, e2329006 (2023).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>