<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39196834</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1524-4725</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>50</Volume><Issue>9S</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Dermatologic surgery : official publication for American Society for Dermatologic Surgery [et al.]</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Dermatol Surg</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>RimabotulinumtoxinB: An Update.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>S52</StartPage><EndPage>S57</EndPage><MedlinePgn>S52-S57</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/DSS.0000000000004253</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Botulinum type-A toxin is a well established aesthetic and medical treatment. While the usage of type-B toxin is less common, there is a growing interest in using type-B toxin, especially in those who are treatment resistant.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To evaluate the primary FDA-approved clinical applications of rimabotulinumtoxinB, along with established and emerging off-label clinical indications.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIAL AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Articles were reviewed from PubMed database and Food and Drug Adminstration guidelines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Facial rhytids tend to use a higher conversion ratio between type A and type B toxin, due to type B toxin's weaker affinity to muscles and higher affinity for sweat glands. Specially, a 1:100 to 1:50 ratio was utilized for glabellar rhytids, a 1:25 to 1:50 ratio for periocular rhytids, a 1:50 to 1:66.6 ratio for cervical dystonia, a 1:20 to 1:50 ratio for hyperhidrosis, and a 1:25 to 30 ratio for sialorrhea.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Type B toxin has demonstrated its safety and efficacy in treating facial rhytids, cervical dystonia, sialorrhea and hyperhidrosis, with potential for novel applications under investigation. Regardless of injection location and clinical applications, dry mouth and dysphagia remained the most common side effects. Across all indications, type B toxin appeared to have a faster onset of action, a dose-dependent clinical duration, and a dose-dependent adverse effect profile.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 by the American Society for Dermatologic Surgery, Inc. Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Teresa</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Marmur Medical, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, The Mount Sinai Hospital, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marmur</LastName><ForeName>Ellen S</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Marmur Medical, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, The Mount Sinai Hospital, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Dermatol Surg</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9504371</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1076-0512</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.4.24.69</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D019274">Botulinum Toxins, Type A</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0Y70779M1F</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C096323">rimabotulinumtoxinB</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D009465">Neuromuscular Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019274" MajorTopicYN="Y">Botulinum Toxins, Type A</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006945" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hyperhidrosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003357" MajorTopicYN="N">Cosmetic Techniques</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012798" MajorTopicYN="N">Sialorrhea</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014103" MajorTopicYN="N">Torticollis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009465" MajorTopicYN="N">Neuromuscular Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D056687" MajorTopicYN="N">Off-Label Use</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015595" MajorTopicYN="N">Skin Aging</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39196834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/DSS.0000000000004253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00042728-202409001-00012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aoki KR, Guyer B. Botulinum toxin type A and other botulinum toxin serotypes: a comparative review of biochemical and pharmacological actions. Eur J Neurol 2001;8(Suppl 5):21–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BOTOX (OnabotulinumtoxinA) Label—accessdata.fda.gov; 2010. Available from: https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2011/103000s5236lbl.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spiegel LL, Ostrem JL, Bledsoe IO. FDA approvals and consensus guidelines for botulinum toxins in the treatment of dystonia. Toxins (Basel) 2020;12:332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith TJ, Lou J, Geren IN, Forsyth CM, et al. Sequence variation within botulinum neurotoxin serotypes impacts antibody binding and neutralization. Infect Immun 2005;73:5450–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myobloc (rimabotulinumtoxinB) Injection—accessdata.fda.gov; 2009. Available from: https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2009/103846s5120lbl.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker TJ, Dayan SH. Comparison and overview of currently available neurotoxins. J Clin Aesthet Dermatol 2014;7:31–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann L, Slezinger A, Halem M, Vujevich J, et al. Pilot study of the safety and efficacy of Myobloc (botulinum toxin type B) for treatment of axillary hyperhidrosis. Int J Dermatol. 2005;44:418–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spencer JM, Gordon M, Goldberg DJ. Botulinum B treatment of the glabellar and frontalis regions: a dose response analysis. J Cosmet Laser Ther 2002;4:19–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botulinum toxin advancement. In: Dermatology Times; 2001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann L, Black L. Botulinum toxin type B (Myobloc). Dermatol Surg. 2003;29:496–500; discussion 500.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowe NJ, Yamauchi PS, Lask GP, Patnaik R, et al. Botulinum toxins types A and B for brow furrows: preliminary experiences with type B toxin dosing. J Cosmet Laser Ther 2002;4:15–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimstad O, Kvammen BO, Swartling C. Botulinum toxin type B for hidradenitis suppurativa: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled pilot study. Am J Clin Dermatol 2020;21:741–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos JI, Swensen P, Glasgow LA. Potentiation of Clostridium botulinum toxin aminoglycoside antibiotics: clinical and laboratory observations. Pediatrics 1981;68:50–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myobloc Prescribing Information; 2021. Available from: https://www.myobloc.com/files/Myobloc-Prescribing-Information.pdf. Accessed February 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadick NS, Faacs. Botulinum toxin type B for glabellar wrinkles: a prospective open-label response study. Dermatol Surg 2002;28:817–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadick NS. Prospective open-label study of botulinum toxin type B (Myobloc) at doses of 2,400 and 3,000 U for the treatment of glabellar wrinkles. Dermatol Surg 2003;29:501–7; discussion 507.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carruthers A, Carruthers J, Flynn TC, Leong MS. Dose-finding, safety, and tolerability study of botulinum toxin type B for the treatment of hyperfunctional glabellar lines. Dermatol Surg 2007;33:S60–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matarasso SL. Comparison of botulinum toxin types A and B: a bilateral and double-blind randomized evaluation in the treatment of canthal rhytides. Dermatol Surg 2003;29:7–13; discussion 13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann L, Slezinger A, Vujevich J, Halem M, et al. A double-blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled pilot study of the safety and efficacy of Myobloc (botulinum toxin type B)-purified neurotoxin complex for the treatment of crow's feet: a double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial. Dermatol Surg 2003;29:508–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hefter H, Samadzadeh S, Moll M. Transient improvement after switch to low doses of RimabotulinumtoxinB in patients resistant to AbobotulinumtoxinA. Toxins (Basel) 2020;12:677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comella CL, Jankovic J, Shannon KM, Tsui J, et al. Comparison of botulinum toxin serotypes A and B for the treatment of cervical dystonia. Neurology 2005;65:1423–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pappert EJ, Germanson T, Myobloc/Neurobloc European Cervical Dystonia Study Group. Botulinum toxin type B vs. type A in toxin-naive patients with cervical dystonia: randomized, double-blind, noninferiority trial. Mov Disord 2008;23:510–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marques RE, Duarte GS, Rodrigues FB, Castelão M, et al. Botulinum toxin type B for cervical dystonia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016;2016:CD004315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berman B, Seeberger L, Kumar R. Long-term safety, efficacy, dosing, and development of resistance with botulinum toxin type B in cervical dystonia. Mov Disord 2005;20:233–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinnapongse RB, Lew MF, Ferreira JJ, Gullo KL, et al. Immunogenicity and long-term efficacy of botulinum toxin type B in the treatment of cervical dystonia: report of 4 prospective, multicenter trials. Clin Neuropharmacol 2012;35:215–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brin MF, Lew MF, Adler CH, Comella CL, et al. Safety and efficacy of NeuroBloc (botulinum toxin type B) in type A-resistant cervical dystonia. Neurology 1999;53:1431–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaji R, Endo A, Sugawara M, Ishii M. Efficacy of botulinum toxin type B (rimabotulinumtoxinB) in patients with cervical dystonia previously treated with botulinum toxin type A: a post-marketing observational study in Japan. eNeurologicalSci 2021;25:100374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duarte GS, Castelao M, Rodrigues FB, Marques RE, et al. Botulinum toxin type A versus botulinum toxin type B for cervical dystonia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016;10:CD004314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tintner R, Gross R, Winzer UF, Smalky KA, et al. Autonomic function after botulinum toxin type A or B: a double-blind, randomized trial. Neurology 2005;65:765–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isaacson SH, Ondo W, Jackson CE, Trosch RM, et al. Safety and efficacy of RimabotulinumtoxinB for treatment of sialorrhea in adults: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Neurol 2020;77:461–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinnapongse R, Gullo K, Nemeth P, Zhang Y, et al. Safety and efficacy of botulinum toxin type B for treatment of sialorrhea in Parkinson's disease: a prospective double-blind trial. Mov Disord 2012;27:219–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dashtipour K, Bhidayasiri R, Chen JJ, Jabbari B, et al. RimabotulinumtoxinB in sialorrhea: systematic review of clinical trials. J Clin Mov Disord 2017;4:9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hecht MJ, Birklein F, Winterholler M. Successful treatment of axillary hyperhidrosis with very low doses of botulinum toxin B: a pilot study. Arch Dermatol Res. 2004;295:318–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann LS, Halem ML. Botulinum toxin-B and the management of hyperhidrosis. Clin Dermatol 2004;22:60–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dressler D, Adib Saberi F, Benecke R. Botulinum toxin type B for treatment of axillar hyperhidrosis. J Neurol 2002;249:1729–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson L, Bachoo P, Holmes J. Botulinum toxin type B: a new therapy for axillary hyperhidrosis. Br J Plast Surg. 2005;58:228–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frasson E, Brigo F, Acler M, Didone G, et al. Botulinum toxin type A vs type B for axillary hyperhidrosis in a case series of patients observed for 6 months. Arch Dermatol 2011;147:122–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann L, Slezinger A, Halem M, Vujevich J, et al. Double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled pilot study of the safety and efficacy of Myobloc (botulinum toxin type B) for the treatment of palmar hyperhidrosis. Dermatol Surg 2005;31:263–70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basciani M, Di Rienzo F, Bizzarrini M, Zanchi M, et al. Efficacy of botulinum toxin type B for the treatment of primary palmar hyperhidrosis: a prospective, open, single-blind, multi-centre study. Arch Dermatol Res 2014;306:497–503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan AM, Chappell AG, Boyd RM, Joshi C, et al. The use of botulinum toxin to prevent anastomotic thrombosis and promote flap survival: a bridge to developing clinical studies. Ann Plast Surg 2021;87:222–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson DM, Hallett M, Ashman EJ, Comella CL, et al. Practice guideline update summary: botulinum neurotoxin for the treatment of blepharospasm, cervical dystonia, adult spasticity, and headache: report of the Guideline Development Subcommittee of the American Academy of Neurology. Neurology 2016;86:1818–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campanati A, Diotallevi F, Radi G, Martina E, et al. Efficacy and safety of botulinum toxin B in focal hyperhidrosis: a narrative review. Toxins (Basel). 2023;15:147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho WWS, Albrecht P, Calderon PE, Corduff N, et al. Emerging trends in botulinum neurotoxin A resistance: an international multidisciplinary review and consensus. Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open 2022;10:e4407.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadick NS, Matarasso SL. Comparison of botulinum toxins A and B in the treatment of facial rhytides. Dermatol Clin 2004;22:221–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bentivoglio AR, Del Grande A, Petracca M, Ialongo T, et al. Clinical differences between botulinum neurotoxin type A and B. Toxicon 2015;107:77–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strotmeier J, Willjes G, Binz T, Rummel A. Human synaptotagmin-II is not a high affinity receptor for botulinum neurotoxin B and G: increased therapeutic dosage and immunogenicity. FEBS Lett 2012;586:310–3.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>