<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39203297</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1996-1944</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>17</Volume><Issue>16</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Materials (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Materials (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Investigation of Releasing Chamomile Essential Oil from Inserts with Cellulose Agar and Microcrystalline Cellulose Agar Films Used in Biotextronics Systems for Lower Urinary Tract Inflammation Treatment.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">4119</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/ma17164119</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Lower urinary tract inflammation is a very common problem which occurs particularly in women. That is why the idea of a biotextronics system for preventive and supportive treatment came to be. The system is a kind of a therapeutic clothing in the form of underwear integrated with a four-layer pantiliner with biological active compounds (from chamomile essential oil) immobilized on the insert with a cellulose agar or microcrystalline cellulose agar film. In this research, the outer part of the insert was investigated for its ability to release compounds with antibacterial and anti-inflammatory activity under the temperature of the treatment (40 °C). The research was conducted on the day of the insert preparation (day 0) and also after 7, 14, 28, and 56 days to test the ability of the insert to be stored without changing its properties. The results showed that even after 56 days of storage, there are compounds released that are known to have antibacterial activity, such as <i>α</i>-bisabolol. The system requires further tests involving bacteria; however, chamomile essential oil seems to be good substrate for biotextronics systems for preventive and supportive treatment of lower urinary tract inflammations.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frydrysiak</LastName><ForeName>Emilia</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Natural Products and Cosmetics, Faculty of Biotechnology and Food Sciences, Lodz University of Technology, ul. Stefanowskiego 2/22, 90-537 Lodz, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Śmigielski</LastName><ForeName>Krzysztof</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Biotechnology, Faculty of Biotechnology and Food Sciences, Lodz University of Technology, ul. Wólczańska 171/173, 90-530 Lodz, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kunicka-Styczyńska</LastName><ForeName>Alina</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4611-9109</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sugar Industry and Food Safety Management, Faculty of Biotechnology and Food Sciences, Lodz University of Technology, ul. Wólczańska 171/173, 90-530 Lodz, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frydrysiak</LastName><ForeName>Michał</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6004-8976</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Materials Science of Textiles and Polymer Composites, Faculty of Material Technologies and Textile Design, Lodz University of Technology, ul. Żeromskiego 116, 90-543 Lodz, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>MNISW/2017/DIR/32</GrantID><Agency>National Science Center</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Materials (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101555929</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1996-1944</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">GC–MS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SPME</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">agar film</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biotextronics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cellulose</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chamomile essential oil</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">insert</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lower urinary tract inflammation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microcrystalline cellulose</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. The funders had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript; or in the decision to publish the results.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39203297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11356156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma17164119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ma17164119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Frydrysiak E., Kunicka-Styczyńska A., Śmigielski K., Frydrysiak M. The Impact of Selected Essential Oils Applied to Non-Woven Viscose on Bacteria That Cause Lower Urinary Tract Infections—Preliminary Studies. Molecules. 2021;26:6854. doi: 10.3390/molecules26226854.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26226854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8619585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34833945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Czajkowski K., Broś-Konopielko M., Teliga-Czajkowska J. Urinary Tract Infection in Women. Przeglad Menopauzalny. 2021;20:40–47. doi: 10.5114/pm.2021.105382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/pm.2021.105382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8077804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33935619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abelson B., Sun D., Que L., Nebel R.A., Baker D., Popiel P., Amundsen C.L., Chai T., Close C., Disanto M., et al. Sex differences in lower urinary tract biology and physiology. Biol. Sex Differ. 2018;9:45. doi: 10.1186/s13293-018-0204-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13293-018-0204-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6196569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30343668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zakażenia Układu Moczowego (ZUM) (Eng. Urinary Tract Inflammations (UTI)). Materiały dla Studentów (Eng. Materials for Students)  [(accessed on 15 September 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.umed.wroc.pl/sites/default/files/mikrobiologia/files/stomatologia/ZUM.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamkiewicz K., Borkowski A., Krzeski T., Leńko J., Marczyńska A., Mazurek L., Stolarczyk J., Zieliński J. Choroby pęcherza moczowego (Eng. Bladder diseases) In: Leńko J., editor. Urologia Podręcznik dla Studentów Medycyny (Eng. Urology Textbook for Medical Students) Państwowy Zakład Wydawnictw Lekarskich (Eng. National Medical Publishing Institute); Warsaw, Poland: 1982. pp. 186–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holecki M., Hryniewicz W., Pawlik K., Wanke-Rytt M., Duława J., Imiela J., Klinger M. Rekomendacje Diagnostyki, Terapii i Profilaktyki Zakażeń Układu Moczowego u Dorosłych (Eng. Recommendations for the Diagnosis, Treatment and Prevention of Urinary Tract Infections in Adults) Narodowy Instytut Leków (Eng. National Institute of Medicines); Warsaw, Poland: 2015. pp. 7–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawecki D. Infekcje w układzie moczowym. In: Gajkowska J., editor. Uroginekologia, Schorzenia Dna Miednicy (Eng. Urogynecology, Pelvic Floor Disorders) Via Medica; Gdańsk, Poland: 2017. pp. 399–406.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamkiewicz K., Borkowski A., Krzeski T., Leńko J., Marczyńska A., Mazurek L., Stolarczyk J., Zieliński J. Zapalenie pęcherza moczowego (Eng. Bladder inflammation) In: Leńko J., editor. Urologia Podręcznik dla Studentów Medycyny (Eng. Urology Textbook for Medical Students) Państwowy Zakład Wydawnictw Lekarskich (Eng. National Medical Publishing Institute); Warsaw, Poland: 1987. pp. 130–133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh P.C., Retik A.B., Campbell M.F. Campbell’s Urology. 8th ed. W.B. Saunders; Philadelphia, PA, USA: 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Head K.A. Natural approaches to prevention and treatment of infections of the lower urinary tract. Altern. Med. Rev. 2008;13:227–244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18950249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulipati S., Babu P.S., Narasu M.L. An overview on urinary tract infections and effective natural remedies. J. Med. Plants Stud. 2017;5:50–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loose M., Pilger E., Wagenlehner F. Anti-bacterial effects of essential oils against uropathogenic bacteria. Antibiotics. 2020;9:358. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics9060358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9060358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7344393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32630444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stan M.S., Chirila L., Popescu A., Radulescu D.M., Radulescu D.E., Dinischiotu A. Essential oil microcapsules immobilized on textiles and certain induced effects. Materials. 2019;12:2029. doi: 10.3390/ma12122029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma12122029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6630941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31242556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Yin C., You J., Li R., Zhang J., Cheng Y., Wang Y., Zhang J. Cellulose-based ultralong room-temperature phosphorescence nanomaterials with tunable color and high quantum yield via nano-surface confining effect. Research. 2023;6:0029. doi: 10.34133/research.0029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34133/research.0029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10076006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37040512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ioleovich M. Cellulose: Nanostructured Natural Polymer. Lambert Academic Publishing; Saarbrücken, Germany: 2014. pp. 4–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shokri J., Adibkia K. Cellulose-Medical, Pharmaceutical and Electronic Applications. InTechOpen; Rijeka, Croatia: 2013. Application of cellulose and cellulose derivatives in pharmaceutical industries.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5772/55178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Góra J., Lis A. Olejek rumiankowy. In: Wakarecy I., editor. Najcenniejsze Olejki Eteryczne. 4th ed. Wydawnictwo Politechniki Łódzkiej (Eng. Lodz University of Technology Publishing House); Lodz, Poland: 2019. pp. 237–249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khattab A., Abou-shoer M., Harraz F.M., El-Ghazouly M.G. Hiearchiral clustering of commercial chamomile oil, a quality assessment approach. Egypt. J. Biomed. Sci. 2010;34:1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharafzadeh S., Alizadeh O. German and Roman chamomile. J. Appl. Pharm. Sci. 2011;1:1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amiri S., Sharafzadeh S. Essential oil components of German chamomile cultivated in Firoozabad, Iran. Orient. J. Chem. 2014;30:365–367. doi: 10.13005/ojc/300151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13005/ojc/300151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardiner P. Chamomile (Matricaria recutita, Anthemis nobilis). The Longwood Herbal Task Force. 1999.  [(accessed on 17 April 2020)]. pp. 1–21. Available online:  https://dpointernational.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/Chamomile-Matricaria-recutita-Anthemis-nobilis.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das M. Chamomile Medicinal, Biochemical and Agricultural Aspects. 1st ed. CRC Press; Boca Raton, FL, USA: 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghasemi M., Jelodar N.B., Modarresi M., Bagheri N., Jamali A. Increase of chamazulene and α-bisabolol contents of the essential oil of German chamomile (Matricaria chamomilla L.) using salicylic acid treatments under normal and heat stress conditions. Foods. 2016;5:56. doi: 10.3390/foods5030056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods5030056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5302395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28231151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djilani A., Dicko A. Nutrition, Well-Being and Health. InTech; Vienna, Austria: 2012. The therapeutic benefits of essential oils; pp. 157–178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5772/25344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao J., Liu T., Xia K., Liu X., Zhang X. Preparation and application of edible agar-based composite films modified by cellulose nanocrystals. Food Packag. Shelf Life. 2022;34:100936. doi: 10.1016/j.fpsl.2022.100936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fpsl.2022.100936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeug A., Zimmermann J., Röder B., Lagoriob M.G., San Románb E. Microcrystalline cellulose as a carrier for hydrophobic photosensitizers in water. Photochem. Photobiol. Sci. 2002;3:198–203. doi: 10.1039/b109592g.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/b109592g</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12659517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mrozińska Z., Kudzin M.H., Ponczek M.B., Kaczmarek A., Król P., Lisiak-Kucińska A., Żyłła R., Walawska A. Biochemical approach to poly(lactide)–copper composite—Impact on blood coagulation processes. Materials. 2024;17:608. doi: 10.3390/ma17030608.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma17030608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10856769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38591465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Pharmacopoeia 7. European Directorate for the Quality of Medicines &amp; HealthCare of the Council of Europe (EDQM); Strasbourg, France: 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Mihyaoui A., Esteves Da Silva J.C.G., Charfi S., Castillo M.E.C., Lamarti A., Arnao M.B. Chamomile (Matricaria chamomilla L.): A review of ethnomedicinal use, phytochemistry and pharmacological uses. Life. 2022;12:479. doi: 10.3390/life12040479.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/life12040479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9032859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35454969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcuello C., Foulon L., Chabbert B., Aguié-Béghin V., Molinari M. Atomic force microscopy reveals how relative humidity impacts the Young’s modulus of lignocellulosic polymers and their adhesion with cellulose nanocrystals at the nanoscale. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2020;147:1064–1075. doi: 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.10.074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.10.074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31743709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aziz T., Farid A., Haq F., Kiran M., Ullah A., Zhang K., Li C., Ghazanfar S., Sun H., Ullah R., et al. A Review on the Modification of Cellulose and Its applications. Polymers. 2022;14:3206. doi: 10.3390/polym14153206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym14153206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9371096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35956720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An Z., Feng X., Sun M., Wang Y., Wang H., Gong Y. Chamomile essential oil: Chemical constituents and antitumor activity in MDA-MB-231 cells through PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling pathway. Chem. Biodivers. 2023;20:e202200523. doi: 10.1002/cbdv.202200523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cbdv.202200523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36941224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolenwar P. Fragrance Finishing of Textiles.  [(accessed on 13 May 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.fibre2fashion.com/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh M.K., Varun V.K., Behera B.K. Cosmetotextiles: State of art. Fibres Text. East. Eur. 2011;19:27–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamowicz E., Śmigielski K., Frydrysiak M. Microencapsulation of active substances and fragrances in textile material applications. Tekstil. 2015;64:128–132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng S.Y., Yuen C.W.M., Kan C.W., Cheuk K.K.L. Development of cosmetic textiles using microencapsulation technology. Res. J. Text. Appar. 2008;12:41–51. doi: 10.1108/RJTA-12-04-2008-B005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/RJTA-12-04-2008-B005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S., Boyter H., Qian L. UV curing for encapsulated aroma finish on cotton. J. Text. Inst. 2005;96:407–411. doi: 10.1533/joti.2005.0116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1533/joti.2005.0116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teixeira C.S.N.R. Ph.D. Thesis. University of Porto; Porto, Portugal: 2010. Microencapsulation of perfumes for application in textile industry; pp. 3–165.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson G. Application of microencapsulation in textiles. Int. J. Pharm. 2002;242:55–62. doi: 10.1016/S0378-5173(02)00141-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0378-5173(02)00141-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12176225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkataraman D., Shabani E., Park J.H. Advancement of Nonwoven Fabrics in Personal Protective Equipment. Materials. 2023;16:3964. doi: 10.3390/ma16113964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma16113964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10253991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37297096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachowiak-Wencek A., Prądzyński W. The effect of temperature on the emission of volatile organic compounds from furniture coatings. Ann. Wars. Univ. Life Sci. SGGW. For. Wood Technol. 2013;84:310–314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shuvo I.I., Shah A., Dagdeviren C. Electronic textile sensors for decoding vital body signals: State-of-the-art review on characterizations and recommendations. Adv. Intell. Syst. 2022;4:2100223. doi: 10.1002/aisy.202100223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/aisy.202100223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boncel S., Jędrysiak R.G., Czerw M., Kolanowska A., Blacha A.W., Imielski M., Jóźwiak B., Dzida M.H., Greer H.F., Sobotnicki A. Paintable carbon nanotube coating-based textronics for sustained holter-type electrocardiography. ACS Appl. Nano Mater. 2022;5:15762–15774. doi: 10.1021/acsanm.2c03904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsanm.2c03904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9623549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36338322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhry N.A., Arnold L., Rasheed A., Khan I.A., Wang L. Textronics—A review of textile-based wearable electronics. Adv. Eng. Mater. 2021;23:2100469. doi: 10.1002/adem.202100469.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adem.202100469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korzeniewska E., Szczęsny A., Lipiński P., Dróżdż T., Kiełbasa P., Miernik A. Prototype of a Textronic Sensor Created with a Physical Vacuum Deposition Process for Staphylococcus aureus Detection. Sensors. 2021;21:183. doi: 10.3390/s21010183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s21010183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7794882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33383934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>