<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39200012</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2079-6382</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Antibiotics (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Antibiotics (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>On-Site Inactivation for Disinfection of Antibiotic-Resistant Bacteria in Hospital Effluent by UV and UV-LED.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">711</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/antibiotics13080711</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The problem of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is not limited to the medical field but is also becoming prevalent on a global scale in the environmental field. Environmental water pollution caused by the discharge of wastewater into aquatic environments has caused concern in the context of the sustainable development of modern society. However, there have been few studies focused on the treatment of hospital wastewater, and the potential consequences of this remain unknown. This study evaluated the efficacy of the inactivation of antimicrobial-resistant bacteria (AMRB) and antimicrobial resistance genes (AMRGs) in model wastewater treatment plant (WWTP) wastewater and hospital effluent based on direct ultraviolet (UV) light irradiation provided by a conventional mercury lamp with a peak wavelength of 254 nm and an ultraviolet light-emitting diode (UV-LED) with a peak emission of 280 nm under test conditions in which the irradiance of both was adjusted to the same intensity. The overall results indicated that both UV- and UV-LED-mediated disinfection effectively inactivated the AMRB in both wastewater types (&gt;99.9% after 1-3 min of UV and 3 min of UV-LED treatment). Additionally, AMRGs were also removed (0.2-1.4 log<sub>10</sub> for UV 254 nm and 0.1-1.3 log<sub>10</sub> for UV 280 nm), and notably, there was no statistically significant decrease (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) in the AMRGs between the UV and UV-LED treatments. The results of this study highlight the importance of utilizing a local inactivation treatment directly for wastewater generated by a hospital prior to its flow into a WWTP as sewage. Although additional disinfection treatment at the WWTP is likely necessary to remove the entire quantity of AMRB and AMRGs, the present study contributes to a significant reduction in the loads of WWTP and urgent prevention of the spread of infectious diseases, thus alleviating the potential threat to the environment and human health risks associated with AMR problems.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azuma</LastName><ForeName>Takashi</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9625-0631</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Osaka Medical and Pharmaceutical University, Takatsuki 569-1094, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Usui</LastName><ForeName>Masaru</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1624-1469</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Microbiology and Food Safety, Department of Health and Environmental Sciences, School of Veterinary Medicine, Rakuno Gakuen University, Ebetsu 069-8501, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hasei</LastName><ForeName>Tomohiro</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Osaka Medical and Pharmaceutical University, Takatsuki 569-1094, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hayashi</LastName><ForeName>Tetsuya</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Osaka Medical and Pharmaceutical University, Takatsuki 569-1094, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>20H02289, 23H03553, and 24K15322</GrantID><Agency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>21HA1002 and 24HA1003</GrantID><Agency>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare of Japan</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>JP22fk0108131 and JP23fk0108666</GrantID><Agency>Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development (AMED)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Antibiotics (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101637404</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2079-6382</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UV lamp</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial resistance genes (AMRGs)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial-resistant bacteria (AMRB)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disinfection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hospital wastewater</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">river environment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ultraviolet-light emitting diode (UV-LED)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">wastewater treatment plant (WWTP)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The funding agencies had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or manuscript preparation. The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39200012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11350808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics13080711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">antibiotics13080711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Khan N.A., Vambol V., Vambol S., Bolibrukh B., Sillanpaa M., Changani F., Esrafili A., Yousefi M. Hospital effluent guidelines and legislation scenario around the globe: A critical review. J. Environ. Chem. Eng. 2021;9:105874. doi: 10.1016/j.jece.2021.105874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jece.2021.105874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cameron A., Esiovwa R., Connolly J., Hursthouse A., Henriquez F. Antimicrobial resistance as a global health threat: The need to learn lessons from the COVID-19 pandemic. Glob. Policy. 2022;13:179–192. doi: 10.1111/1758-5899.13049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1758-5899.13049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9111155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35601654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Han Y., Li L., Liu J., Yan X. Distribution, sources, and potential risks of antibiotic resistance genes in wastewater treatment plant: A review. Environ. Pollut. 2022;310:119870. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119870.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35921944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Antimicrobial Resistance: Global Report on Surveillance 2014. World Health Organization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2014. pp. 1–232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Antibiotic Resistance Threats in the United States. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; Atlanta, GA, USA: 2019. pp. 1–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jim O.N. Antimicrobial resistance: Tackling a crisis for the health and wealth of nations. Rev. Antimicrob. Resist. 2014:1–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray C.J.L., Ikuta K.S., Sharara F., Swetschinski L., Robles Aguilar G., Gray A., Han C., Bisignano C., Rao P., Wool E., et al. Global burden of bacterial antimicrobial resistance in 2019: A systematic analysis. Lancet. 2022;399:629–655. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02724-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02724-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8841637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35065702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Government of Japan . National Action Plan on Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), 2016. The Government of Japan; Tokyo, Japan: 2016. pp. 1–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Government of Japan . National Action Plan on Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), 2023. The Government of Japan; Tokyo, Japan: 2023. pp. 1–90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Salah D.M.M., Ngweme G.N., Laffite A., Otamonga J.P., Mulaji C., Poté J. Hospital wastewaters: A reservoir and source of clinically relevant bacteria and antibiotic resistant genes dissemination in urban river under tropical conditions. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 2020;200:110767. doi: 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.110767.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.110767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32470679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassoun-Kheir N., Stabholz Y., Kreft J.U., de la Cruz R., Romalde J.L., Nesme J., Sørensen S.J., Smets B.F., Graham D., Paul M. Comparison of antibiotic-resistant bacteria and antibiotic resistance genes abundance in hospital and community wastewater: A systematic review. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;743:140804. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.140804.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.140804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32758846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekizuka T., Tanaka R., Hashino M., Yatsu K., Kuroda M. Comprehensive genome and plasmidome analysis of antimicrobial resistant bacteria in wastewater treatment plant effluent of Tokyo. Antibiotics. 2022;11:1283. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics11101283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11101283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9598598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36289941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muraki Y., Kitamura M., Maeda Y., Kitahara T., Mori T., Ikeue H., Tsugita M., Tadano K., Takada K., Akamatsu T., et al. Nationwide surveillance of antimicrobial consumption and resistance to Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolates at 203 Japanese hospitals in 2010. Infection. 2013;41:415–423. doi: 10.1007/s15010-013-0440-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s15010-013-0440-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23471823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Boeckel T.P., Gandra S., Ashok A., Caudron Q., Grenfell B.T., Levin S.A., Laxminarayan R. Global antibiotic consumption 2000 to 2010: An analysis of national pharmaceutical sales data. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2014;14:742–750. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(14)70780-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(14)70780-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25022435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stefani S., Chung D.R., Lindsay J.A., Friedrich A.W., Kearns A.M., Westh H., MacKenzie F.M. Meticillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA): Global epidemiology and harmonisation of typing methods. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2012;39:273–282. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2011.09.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2011.09.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22230333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lakhundi S., Zhang K. Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus: Molecular characterization, evolution, and epidemiology. Clin. Microbiol. Rev. 2018;31:e00018–e00020. doi: 10.1128/CMR.00020-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00020-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6148192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30209034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee A.S., de Lencastre H., Garau J., Kluytmans J., Malhotra-Kumar S., Peschel A., Harbarth S. Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus. Nature Rev. Dis. Primers. 2018;4:18033. doi: 10.1038/nrdp.2018.33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2018.33</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29849094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiozaki Y. The action for the antimicobial resistance issue in Japan. Jpn. Assoc. Infect. Dis. 2018;91:915–923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M.T., Shah I.A., Ihsanullah I., Naushad M., Ali S., Shah S.H.A., Mohammad A.W. Hospital wastewater as a source of environmental contamination: An overview of management practices, environmental risks, and treatment processes. J. Water Proc. Eng. 2021;41:101990. doi: 10.1016/j.jwpe.2021.101990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jwpe.2021.101990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verlicchi P. Trends, new insights and perspectives in the treatment of hospital effluents. Curr. Opin. Environ. Sci. Health. 2021;19:100217. doi: 10.1016/j.coesh.2020.10.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coesh.2020.10.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7571420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33103011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pariente M.I., Segura Y., Álvarez-Torrellas S., Casas J.A., de Pedro Z.M., Diaz E., García J., López-Muñoz M.J., Marugán J., Mohedano A.F., et al. Critical review of technologies for the on-site treatment of hospital wastewater: From conventional to combined advanced processes. J. Environ. Manag. 2022;320:115769. doi: 10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.115769.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.115769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35944316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pruden A., Vikesland P.J., Davis B.C., de Roda Husman A.M. Seizing the moment: Now is the time for integrated global surveillance of antimicrobial resistance in wastewater environments. Curr. Opin. Microbiol. 2021;64:91–99. doi: 10.1016/j.mib.2021.09.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2021.09.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34655936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekizuka T., Itokawa K., Tanaka R., Hashino M., Yatsu K., Kuroda M. Metagenomic analysis of urban wastewater treatment plant effluents in tokyo. Infect. Drug Resist. 2022;15:4763–4777. doi: 10.2147/IDR.S370669.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S370669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9419991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36039320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rekhate C.V., Srivastava J.K. Recent advances in ozone-based advanced oxidation processes for treatment of wastewater- A review. Chem. Eng. J. Adv. 2020;3:100031. doi: 10.1016/j.ceja.2020.100031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ceja.2020.100031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhandari G., Chaudhary P., Gangola S., Gupta S., Gupta A., Rafatullah M., Chen S. A review on hospital wastewater treatment technologies: Current management practices and future prospects. J. Water Proc. Eng. 2023;56:104516. doi: 10.1016/j.jwpe.2023.104516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jwpe.2023.104516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adeoye J.B., Tan Y.H., Lau S.Y., Tan Y.Y., Chiong T., Mubarak N.M., Khalid M. Advanced oxidation and biological integrated processes for pharmaceutical wastewater treatment: A review. J. Environ. Manag. 2024;353:120170. doi: 10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.120170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.120170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38308991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin N., Foster T., Shimki N.T., Willetts J. Hospital wastewater (HWW) treatment in low- and middle-income countries: A systematic review of microbial treatment efficacy. Sci. Total Environ. 2024;921:170994. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.170994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.170994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38365018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saravanan A., Deivayanai V.C., Kumar P.S., Rangasamy G., Hemavathy R.V., Harshana T., Gayathri N., Alagumalai K. A detailed review on advanced oxidation process in treatment of wastewater: Mechanism, challenges and future outlook. Chemosphere. 2022;308:136524. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.136524.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.136524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36165838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal J., Shah N.S., Ali Khan J., Naushad M., Boczkaj G., Jamil F., Khan S., Li L., Murtaza B., Han C. Pharmaceuticals wastewater treatment via different advanced oxidation processes: Reaction mechanism, operational factors, toxicities, and cost evaluation—A review. Sep. Purif. Technol. 2024;347:127458. doi: 10.1016/j.seppur.2024.127458.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.seppur.2024.127458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X., Cai M., Wang L., Niu F., Yang D., Zhang G. Evaluation survey of microbial disinfection methods in UV-LED water treatment systems. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;659:1415–1427. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.12.344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.12.344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31096352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan U., Hill K., Deere D. Review of generic screening level assumptions for quantitative microbial risk assessment (qmra) for estimating public health risks from australian drinking water sources contaminated with Cryptosporidium by recreational activities. Water Res. 2022;220:118659. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2022.118659.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2022.118659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35635918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matafonova G., Batoev V. Recent advances in application of UV light-emitting diodes for degrading organic pollutants in water through advanced oxidation processes: A review. Water Res. 2018;132:177–189. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2017.12.079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2017.12.079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29331640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen T.M.H., Suwan P., Koottatep T., Beck S.E. Application of a novel, continuous-feeding ultraviolet light emitting diode (UV-LED) system to disinfect domestic wastewater for discharge or agricultural reuse. Water Res. 2019;153:53–62. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2019.01.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2019.01.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6382465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30690218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song K., Mohseni M., Taghipour F. Application of ultraviolet light-emitting diodes (UV-LEDs) for water disinfection: A review. Water Res. 2016;94:341–349. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2016.03.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2016.03.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26971809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelayo D., Rivero M.J., Santos G., Gómez P., Ortiz I. Techno-economic evaluation of UV light technologies in water remediation. Sci. Total Environ. 2023;868:161376. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.161376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.161376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36621496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li G.Q., Wang W.L., Huo Z.Y., Lu Y., Hu H.Y. Comparison of UV-LED and low pressure UV for water disinfection: Photoreactivation and dark repair of Escherichia coli. Water Res. 2017;126:134–143. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2017.09.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2017.09.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28941399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyangaresi P.O., Qin Y., Chen G., Zhang B., Lu Y., Shen L. Comparison of UV-LED photolytic and UV-LED/TiO2 photocatalytic disinfection for escherichia coli in water. Catal. Today. 2019;335:200–207. doi: 10.1016/j.cattod.2018.11.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cattod.2018.11.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan Q., Cao R., Wen G., Xu X., Xia Y., Wu G., Li Y., Wang J., Xu H., Lin Y., et al. Efficacy of UV-LED based advanced disinfection processes in the inactivation of waterborne fungal spores: Kinetics, photoreactivation, mechanism and energy requirements. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;803:150107. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34525763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dulin D., Mill T. Development and evaluation of sunlight actinometers. Environ. Sci. Technol. 1982;16:815–820. doi: 10.1021/es00105a017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es00105a017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22299793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J., Loeb S., Kim J.H. Led revolution: Fundamentals and prospects for UV disinfection applications. Environ. Sci. Water Res. Technol. 2017;3:188–202. doi: 10.1039/C6EW00241B.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C6EW00241B</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma B., Seyedi S., Wells E., McCarthy D., Crosbie N., Linden K.G. Inactivation of biofilm-bound bacterial cells using irradiation across UVC wavelengths. Water Res. 2022;217:118379. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2022.118379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2022.118379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35429876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bae J.Y., Kim Y., Kim H., Kim Y., Jin J., Bae B.S. Ultraviolet light stable and transparent sol–gel methyl siloxane hybrid material for UV light-emitting diode (UV LED) encapsulant. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2015;7:1035–1039. doi: 10.1021/am507132a.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/am507132a</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25564875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Z.C., Lin Y.L., Xu B., Xia Y., Hu C.Y., Cao T.C., Zou X.Y., Gao N.Y. Evaluating iopamidol degradation performance and potential dual-wavelength synergy by UV-LED irradiation and UV-LED/chlorine treatment. Chem. Eng. J. 2019;360:806–816. doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2018.12.022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2018.12.022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai A., Deng J., Ye C., Zhu T., Ling X., Shen S., Guo H., Li X. Highly efficient removal of deet by UV-LED irradiation in the presence of iron-containing coagulant. Chemosphere. 2022;286:131613. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.131613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.131613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34315080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song K., Taghipour F., Mohseni M. Microorganisms inactivation by wavelength combinations of ultraviolet light-emitting diodes (UV-LEDs) Sci. Total Environ. 2019;665:1103–1110. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30893742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou X.Y., Lin Y.L., Xu B., Cao T.C., Tang Y.L., Pan Y., Gao Z.C., Gao N.-Y. Enhanced inactivation of E. coli by pulsed UV-LED irradiation during water disinfection. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;650:210–215. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.08.367.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.08.367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30196221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pousty D., Hofmann R., Gerchman Y., Mamane H. Wavelength-dependent time–dose reciprocity and stress mechanism for UV-LED disinfection of Escherichia coli. J. Photochem. Photobiol. B. 2021;217:112129. doi: 10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2021.112129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2021.112129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33713893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerchman Y., Mamane H., Friedman N., Mandelboim M. UV-LED disinfection of coronavirus: Wavelength effect. J. Photochem. Photobiol. B. 2020;212:112044. doi: 10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2020.112044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2020.112044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7521879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33022467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inagaki H., Saito A., Kaneko C., Sugiyama H., Okabayashi T., Fujimoto S. Rapid inactivation of SARS-CoV-2 variants by continuous and intermittent irradiation with a deep-ultraviolet light-emitting diode (DUV-LED) device. Pathogens. 2021;10:754. doi: 10.3390/pathogens10060754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens10060754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8232135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34203643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verlicchi P. Hospital Wastewaters: Characteristics, Management, Treatment and Environmental Risks. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2017. pp. 1–243.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan N.A., Ahmed S., Farooqi I.H., Ali I., Vambol V., Changani F., Yousefi M., Vambol S., Khan S.U., Khan A.H. Occurrence, sources and conventional treatment techniques for various antibiotics present in hospital wastewaters: A critical review. Trends Anal. Chem. 2020;129:115921. doi: 10.1016/j.trac.2020.115921.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trac.2020.115921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatimazahra S., Latifa M., Laila S., Monsif K. Review of hospital effluents: Special emphasis on characterization, impact, and treatment of pollutants and antibiotic resistance. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2023;195:393. doi: 10.1007/s10661-023-11002-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-023-11002-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9923651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36780024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haeusser S., Weber M., Mauer C., Linnemann V., Pfannstiel A., Pinnekamp J., Wintgens T., Klümper C., Beier S. On-site treatment of hospital wastewater in a full-scale treatment plant in Germany: SARS-CoV-2 and treatment performance. Water Sci. Technol. 2023;87:1747–1763. doi: 10.2166/wst.2023.088.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wst.2023.088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37051795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutierrez M., Mutavdžić Pavlović D., Stipaničev D., Repec S., Avolio F., Zanella M., Verlicchi P. A thorough analysis of the occurrence, removal and environmental risks of organic micropollutants in a full-scale hybrid membrane bioreactor fed by hospital wastewater. Sci. Total Environ. 2024;914:169848. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.169848.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.169848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38190908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu S.Y., Xie Z.H., Wu X., Zheng Y.Z., Shi Y., Xiong Z.K., Zhou P., Liu Y., He C.-S., Pan Z.C., et al. Review of advanced oxidation processes for treating hospital sewage to achieve decontamination and disinfection. Chin. Chem. Lett. 2024;35:108714. doi: 10.1016/j.cclet.2023.108714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cclet.2023.108714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azuma T., Uchiyama T., Zhang D., Usui M., Hayashi T. Distribution and characteristics of carbapenem-resistant and extended-spectrum β-lactamase (ESBL) producing Escherichia coli in hospital effluents, sewage treatment plants, and river water in an urban area of Japan. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;839:156232. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.156232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.156232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35623520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Japan Meteorological Agency  Weather Statistics.  [(accessed on 23 July 2024)].  Available online:  http://www.jma.go.jp/jma/index.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng J., Su C., Zhou J., Xu L., Qian Y., Chen H. Effects and mechanisms of ultraviolet, chlorination, and ozone disinfection on antibiotic resistance genes in secondary effluents of municipal wastewater treatment plants. Chem. Eng. J. 2017;317:309–316. doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2017.02.076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2017.02.076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunkin N., Weng S., Coulter C.G., Jacangelo J.G., Schwab K.J. Impacts of virus processing on human norovirus GI and GII persistence during disinfection of municipal secondary wastewater effluent. Water Res. 2018;134:1–12. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2018.01.053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2018.01.053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29407643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyangaresi P.O., Qin Y., Chen G., Zhang B., Lu Y., Shen L. Effects of single and combined UV-LEDs on inactivation and subsequent reactivation of E.coli in water disinfection. Water Res. 2018;147:331–341. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2018.10.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2018.10.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30317042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keshavarzfathy M., Malayeri A.H., Mohseni M., Taghipour F. UV-LED fluence determination by numerical method for microbial inactivation studies. J. Photochem. Photobiol. A. 2020;392:112406. doi: 10.1016/j.jphotochem.2020.112406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jphotochem.2020.112406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Fate, Transport and Transformation: Test Guidelines OPPTS 835.2210. U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA); Washington, DC, USA: 1998. pp. 1–35. Direct Photolysis Rate in Water by Sunlight.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Fate, Transport and Transformation: Test Guidelines OPPTS 835.2240. U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA); Washington, DC, USA: 1998. pp. 1–4. Photodegradation in Water.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD . Phototransformation of Chemicals in Water-Direct Photolysis, OECD Guideline for the Testing of Chemicals No. 316. OECD; Paris, France: 2008. pp. 1–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Japan Sewage Works Association . Statistics of Sewerage. Japan Sewage Works Association; Tokyo, Japan: 2022. (In Japanese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azuma T., Hayashi T. Effects of natural sunlight on antimicrobial-resistant bacteria (AMRB) and antimicrobial-susceptible bacteria (AMSB) in wastewater and river water. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;766:142568. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142568.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33066962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hijnen W.A.M., Beerendonk E.F., Medema G.J. Inactivation credit of UV radiation for viruses, bacteria and protozoan (oo)cysts in water: A review. Water Res. 2006;40:3–22. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2005.10.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2005.10.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16386286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He H., Zhou P., Shimabuku K.K., Fang X., Li S., Lee Y., Dodd M.C. Degradation and deactivation of bacterial antibiotic resistance genes during exposure to free chlorine, monochloramine, chlorine dioxide, ozone, ultraviolet light, and hydroxyl radical. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2019;53:2013–2026. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.8b04393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b04393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30712343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Global Action Plan on Antimicrobial Resistance. World Health Organization (WHO); Geneva, Switzerland: 2015. pp. 1–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO)  Antibiotic-Resistant “Priority Pathogens”—A Catalogue of 12 Families of Bacteria that Pose the Greatest Threat to Human Health.  [(accessed on 23 July 2024)].  Available online:  http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2017/bacteria-antibiotics-needed/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alekshun M.N., Levy S.B. Molecular mechanisms of antibacterial multidrug resistance. Cell. 2007;128:1037–1050. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2007.03.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2007.03.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17382878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulani M.S., Kamble E.E., Kumkar S.N., Tawre M.S., Pardesi K.R. Emerging strategies to combat eskape pathogens in the era of antimicrobial resistance: A review. Front. Microbiol. 2019;10:539. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2019.00539.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6452778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30988669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azuma T., Usui M., Hayashi T. Inactivation of antibiotic-resistant bacteria in wastewater by ozone-based advanced water treatment processes. Antibiotics. 2022;11:210. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics11020210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11020210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8868322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35203813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>bioMérieux (France)  Manufacturer’s Protocol for chromIDTM Chromogenic Media.  [(accessed on 23 July 2024)].  Available online:  http://www.biomerieux.fr/diagnostic-clinique/milieux-de-culture.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamba M., Graham D.W., Ahammad S.Z. Hospital wastewater releases of carbapenem-resistance pathogens and genes in urban India. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2017;51:13906–13912. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.7b03380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.7b03380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28949542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glady-Croue J., Niu X.Z., Ramsay J.P., Watkin E., Murphy R.J.T., Croue J.P. Survival of antibiotic resistant bacteria following artificial solar radiation of secondary wastewater effluent. Sci. Total Environ. 2018;626:1005–1011. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.01.101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.01.101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29898509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haller L., Chen H., Ng C., Le T.H., Koh T.H., Barkham T., Sobsey M., Gin K.Y.H. Occurrence and characteristics of extended-spectrum β-lactamase- and carbapenemase- producing bacteria from hospital effluents in singapore. Sci. Total Environ. 2018;615:1119–1125. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.09.217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.09.217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29751417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azuma T., Otomo K., Kunitou M., Shimizu M., Hosomaru K., Mikata S., Ishida M., Hisamatsu K., Yunoki A., Mino Y., et al. Environmental fate of pharmaceutical compounds and antimicrobial-resistant bacteria in hospital effluents, and contributions to pollutant loads in the surface waters in Japan. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;657:476–484. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.11.433.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.11.433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30550911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serna-Galvis E.A., Vélez-Peña E., Osorio-Vargas P., Jiménez J.N., Salazar-Ospina L., Guaca-González Y.M., Torres-Palma R.A. Inactivation of carbapenem-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae by photo-Fenton: Residual effect, gene evolution and modifications with citric acid and persulfate. Water Res. 2019;161:354–363. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2019.06.024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2019.06.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31220761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sauter D., Stange C., Schumacher V., Tiehm A., Gnirss R., Wintgens T. Impact of ozonation and biological post-treatment of municipal wastewater on microbiological quality parameters. Environ. Sci. Water Res. Technol. 2021;7:1643–1656. doi: 10.1039/D1EW00312G.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1EW00312G</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sib E., Voigt A.M., Wilbring G., Schreiber C., Faerber H.A., Skutlarek D., Parcina M., Mahn R., Wolf D., Brossart P., et al. Antibiotic resistant bacteria and resistance genes in biofilms in clinical wastewater networks. Int. J. Hyg. Environ. Health. 2019;222:655–662. doi: 10.1016/j.ijheh.2019.03.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijheh.2019.03.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30905579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schreiber C., Zacharias N., Essert S.M., Wasser F., Müller H., Sib E., Precht T., Parcina M., Bierbaum G., Schmithausen R.M., et al. Clinically relevant antibiotic-resistant bacteria in aquatic environments—An optimized culture-based approach. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;750:142265. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33182186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsunoda R., Usui M., Tagaki C., Fukuda A., Boonla C., Anomasiri W., Sukpanyatham N., Akapelwa M.L., Nakajima C., Tamura Y., et al. Genetic characterization of coliform bacterial isolates from environmental water in Thailand. J. Infect. Chemother. 2021;27:722–728. doi: 10.1016/j.jiac.2020.12.023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2020.12.023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33468426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The eDNA Society . Environmental DNA Sampling and Experiment Manual Ver. 2.1. The eDNA Society; Otsu, Japan: 2021. pp. 1–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katada S., Fukuda A., Nakajima C., Suzuki Y., Azuma T., Takei A., Takada H., Okamoto E., Kato T., Tamura Y., et al. Aerobic composting and anaerobic digestion decrease the copy numbers of antibiotic-resistant genes and the levels of lactose-degrading Enterobacteriaceae in dairy farms in Hokkaido, Japan. Front. Microbiol. 2021;12:737420. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2021.737420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.737420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8515179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34659165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y., Xing S., Chen Y., Wu R., Wu Y., Wang Y., Mi J., Liao X. Profiles of bacteria/phage-comediated args in pig farm wastewater treatment plants in China: Association with mobile genetic elements, bacterial communities and environmental factors. J. Hazard. Mater. 2021;404:124149. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saladin M., Cao V.T.B., Lambert T., Donay J.L., Herrmann J.L., Ould-Hocine Z., Verdet C., Delisle F., Philippon A., Arlet G. Diversity of CTX-M β-lactamases and their promoter regions from Enterobacteriaceae isolated in three parisian hospitals. FEMS Microbiol. Lett. 2002;209:161–168. doi: 10.1016/S0378-1097(02)00484-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0378-1097(02)00484-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12007800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kojima A., Ishii Y., Ishihara K., Esaki H., Asai T., Oda C., Tamura Y., Takahashi T., Yamaguchi K. Extended-spectrum-β-lactamase-producing Escherichia coli strains isolated from farm animals from 1999 to 2002: Report from the Japanese veterinary antimicrobial resistance monitoring program. Antimicrob. Age. Chemother. 2005;49:3533. doi: 10.1128/AAC.49.8.3533-3537.2005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AAC.49.8.3533-3537.2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1196269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16048977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei T., Miyanaga K., Tanji Y. Persistence of antibiotic-resistant and -sensitive Proteus mirabilis strains in the digestive tract of the housefly (Musca domestica) and green bottle flies (Calliphoridae) Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2014;98:8357–8366. doi: 10.1007/s00253-014-5846-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-014-5846-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24903814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laffite A., Al Salah D.M.M., Slaveykova V.I., Otamonga J.P., Poté J. Impact of anthropogenic activities on the occurrence and distribution of toxic metals, extending-spectra β-lactamases and carbapenem resistance in sub-Saharan African urban rivers. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;727:138129. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32498199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang K., Chen Q.L., Chen M.L., Li H.Z., Liao H., Pu Q., Zhu Y.G., Cui L. Temporal dynamics of antibiotic resistome in the plastisphere during microbial colonization. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2020;54:11322–11332. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.0c04292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.0c04292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32812755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ávila C., García-Galán M.J., Borrego C.M., Rodríguez-Mozaz S., García J., Barceló D. New insights on the combined removal of antibiotics and args in urban wastewater through the use of two configurations of vertical subsurface flow constructed wetlands. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;755:142554. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33059136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S., Yao Q., Liu J., Yu Z., Li Y., Jin J., Liu X., Wang G. Liming mitigates the spread of antibiotic resistance genes in an acid black soil. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;817:152971. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.152971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.152971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35016930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Pei M., Zhang B., He Y., Zhong Y. Changes of antibiotic resistance genes and bacterial communities in the advanced biological wastewater treatment system under low selective pressure of tetracycline. Water Res. 2021;207:117834. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117834.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34763281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohore O.E., Wei Y., Wang Y., Nwankwegu A.S., Wang Z. Tracking the influence of antibiotics, antibiotic resistomes, and salinity gradient in modulating microbial community assemblage of surface water and the ecological consequences. Chemosphere. 2022;305:135428. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.135428.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.135428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35760129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y., Li H., Wei Y., Chen Z., Chen T., Liang Y., Yin J., Yang D., Yang Z., Shi D., et al. Comprehensive insights into profiles and bacterial sources of intracellular and extracellular antibiotic resistance genes in groundwater. Environ. Pollut. 2022;307:119541. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35623567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flach C.F., Hutinel M., Razavi M., Åhrén C., Larsson D.G.J. Monitoring of hospital sewage shows both promise and limitations as an early-warning system for carbapenemase-producing Enterobacterales in a low-prevalence setting. Water Res. 2021;200:117261. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34082263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu S., Liu Y., Wang R., Zhang T., Lu W. Behaviors of antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) and metal resistance genes (mrgs) during the pilot-scale biophysical drying treatment of sewage sludge: Reduction of args and enrichment of mrgs. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;809:152221. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34890650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watts G.S., Youens-Clark K., Slepian M.J., Wolk D.M., Oshiro M.M., Metzger G.S., Dhingra D., Cranmer L.D., Hurwitz B.L. 16s RNA gene sequencing on a benchtop sequencer: Accuracy for identification of clinically important bacteria. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2017;123:1584–1596. doi: 10.1111/jam.13590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.13590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5765505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28940494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson J.S., Spakowicz D.J., Hong B.-Y., Petersen L.M., Demkowicz P., Chen L., Leopold S.R., Hanson B.M., Agresta H.O., Gerstein M., et al. Evaluation of 16s rrna gene sequencing for species and strain-level microbiome analysis. Nature Commun. 2019;10:5029. doi: 10.1038/s41467-019-13036-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-13036-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6834636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31695033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng M., Chen J., Gou J., Hou J., Li D., He X. The effect of different carbon sources on water quality, microbial community and structure of biofloc systems. Aquaculture. 2018;482:103–110. doi: 10.1016/j.aquaculture.2017.09.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2017.09.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quartaroli L., Silva C.M., Silva L.C.F., Lima H.S., de Paula S.O., Dias R.S., Carvalho K.B., Souza R.S., Bassin J.P., da Silva C.C. Effect of the gradual increase of salt on stability and microbial diversity of granular sludge and ammonia removal. J. Environ. Manag. 2019;248:109273. doi: 10.1016/j.jenvman.2019.109273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2019.109273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31336338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Z., Li G., Wang C., Jing Y., Zhu Y., Zhang S., Liu Y. Community dynamics of prokaryotic and eukaryotic microbes in an estuary reservoir. Sci. Rep. 2014;4:6966. doi: 10.1038/srep06966.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep06966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4225533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25382138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu P., Sun Y., Huang Z., Zhu F., Sun Y., Jiang L. The effects of ectomycorrhizal fungi on heavy metals’ transport in pinus massoniana and bacteria community in rhizosphere soil in mine tailing area. J. Hazard. Mater. 2020;381:121203. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.121203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.121203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31561121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azuma T., Hayashi T. Disinfection of antibiotic-resistant bacteria in sewage and hospital effluent by ozonation. Ozone Sci. Eng. 2021;43:413–426. doi: 10.1080/01919512.2021.1906095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01919512.2021.1906095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An X.L., Su J.Q., Li B., Ouyang W.Y., Zhao Y., Chen Q.L., Cui L., Chen H., Gillings M.R., Zhang T., et al. Tracking antibiotic resistome during wastewater treatment using high throughput quantitative pcr. Environ. Int. 2018;117:146–153. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2018.05.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.05.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29751164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogwugwa V.H., Oyetibo G.O., Amund O.O. Taxonomic profiling of bacteria and fungi in freshwater sewer receiving hospital wastewater. Environ. Res. 2021;192:110319. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2020.110319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng J.H., Tang X.Y., Guan Z., Liu C. Occurrence of antibiotic resistome in farmland soils near phosphorus chemical industrial area. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;796:149053. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.149053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.149053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34328884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai C., Hui X., Yang W., Hua Y., Liu H., Dai X. Implications for mitigation of antibiotic resistance: Differential response of intracellular and extracellular antibiotic resistance genes to sludge fermentation coupled with thermal hydrolysis. Water Res. 2022;209:117876. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34864623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wasserstein R.L., Lazar N.A. The ASA statement on p-values: Context, process, and purpose. Am. Stat. 2016;70:129–133. doi: 10.1080/00031305.2016.1154108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00031305.2016.1154108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agathokleous E. Environmental pollution impacts: Are p values over-valued? Sci. Total Environ. 2022;850:157807. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.157807.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.157807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35934042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee O.M., Kim H.Y., Park W., Kim T.H., Yu S. A comparative study of disinfection efficiency and regrowth control of microorganism in secondary wastewater effluent using UV, ozone, and ionizing irradiation process. J. Hazard. Mater. 2015;295:201–208. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2015.04.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2015.04.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25955959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ofori I., Maddila S., Lin J., Jonnalagadda S.B. Ozone initiated inactivation of Escherichia coli and Staphylococcus aureus in water: Influence of selected organic solvents prevalent in wastewaters. Chemosphere. 2018;206:43–50. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.04.164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.04.164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29730564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torii S., Itamochi M., Katayama H. Inactivation kinetics of waterborne virus by ozone determined by a continuous quench flow system. Water Res. 2020;186:116291. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2020.116291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2020.116291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32836147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Guidelines for Environmental Infection Control in Health-Care Facilities Recommendations of CDC and the Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committee (HICPAC) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; Atlanta, GA, USA: 2013. pp. 1–241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12836624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia A.B., Vinuela-Prieto J.M., Lopez-Gonzalez L., Candel F.J. Correlation between resistance mechanisms in Staphylococcus aureus and cell wall and septum thickening. Infect. Drug Resist. 2017;10:353–356. doi: 10.2147/IDR.S146748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S146748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5655128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29089777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azuma T., Hayashi T. On-site chlorination responsible for effective disinfection of wastewater from hospital. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;776:145951. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.145951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.145951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33647640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi Y., He H., Dodd M.C., Lee Y. Degradation kinetics of antibiotic resistance gene mecA of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) during water disinfection with chlorine, ozone, and ultraviolet light. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;55:2541–2552. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.0c05274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.0c05274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33499587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Bu L., Wu Y., Sun J., Li G., Zhou S. Disinfection profiles and mechanisms of E. coli, S. aureus, and B. subtilis in UV365/chlorine process: Inactivation, reactivation, and DBP formation. Sep. Purif. Technol. 2022;287:120584. doi: 10.1016/j.seppur.2022.120584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.seppur.2022.120584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torii S., David S.C., Larivé O., Cariti F., Kohn T. Observed kinetics of enterovirus inactivation by free chlorine are host cell-dependent. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2023;57:18483–18490. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.2c07048.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c07048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36649532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao Z., Ye Y., Chang P.H., Thirunarayanan D., Wigginton K.R. Nucleic acid photolysis by UV254 and the impact of virus encapsidation. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2018;52:10408–10415. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.8b02308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b02308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30106282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X., Hu J.Y. Effect of DNA sizes and reactive oxygen species on degradation of sulphonamide resistance sul1 genes by combined UV/free chlorine processes. J. Hazard. Mater. 2020;392:122283. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.122283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.122283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32086093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He H., Choi Y., Wu S.J., Fang X., Anderson A.K., Liou S.Y., Roberts M.C., Lee Y., Dodd M.C. Application of nucleotide-based kinetic modeling approaches to predict antibiotic resistance gene degradation during UV- and chlorine-based wastewater disinfection processes: From bench- to full-scale. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2022;56:15141–15155. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.2c00567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c00567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36098629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward C.P., Bowen J.C., Freeman D.H., Sharpless C.M. Rapid and reproducible characterization of the wavelength dependence of aquatic photochemical reactions using light-emitting diodes. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2021;8:437–442. doi: 10.1021/acs.estlett.1c00172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.estlett.1c00172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M., Ateia M., Awfa D., Yoshimura C. Regrowth of bacteria after light-based disinfection—What we know and where we go from here. Chemosphere. 2021;268:128850. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33187648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lennon J.T., Muscarella M.E., Placella S.A., Lehmkuhl B.K., Zhou J. How, when, and where relic DNA affects microbial diversity. mBio. 2018;9:e00618–e00637. doi: 10.1128/mBio.00637-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.00637-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6016248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29921664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burkert A., Douglas Thomas A., Waldrop Mark P., Mackelprang R., Atomi H. Changes in the active, dead, and dormant microbial community structure across a pleistocene permafrost chronosequence. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2019;85:e02646-18. doi: 10.1128/AEM.02646-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02646-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6585489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30683748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison C., Atkinson A., Zamyadi A., Kibuye F., McKie M., Hogard S., Mollica P., Jasim S., Wert E.C. Critical review and research needs of ozone applications related to virus inactivation: Potential implications for SARS-CoV-2. Ozone Sci. Eng. 2021;43:2–20. doi: 10.1080/01919512.2020.1839739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01919512.2020.1839739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epelle E.I., Macfarlane A., Cusack M., Burns A., Okolie J.A., Mackay W., Rateb M., Yaseen M. Ozone application in different industries: A review of recent developments. Chem. Eng. J. 2023;454:140188. doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2022.140188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2022.140188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9637394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36373160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeb B.L. Ozone: A valuable tool for addressing today’s environmental issues. A review of forty-five years of Ozone: Science &amp; Engineering. Ozone Sci. Eng. 2024;46:2–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R., Ji M., Zhai H., Guo Y., Liu Y. Occurrence of antibiotics and antibiotic resistance genes in wwtp effluent-receiving water bodies and reclaimed wastewater treatment plants. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;796:148919. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148919.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34273824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei Z., Feng K., Wang Z., Zhang Y., Yang M., Zhu Y.G., Virta M.P.J., Deng Y. High-throughput single-cell technology reveals the contribution of horizontal gene transfer to typical antibiotic resistance gene dissemination in wastewater treatment plants. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;55:11824–11834. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.1c01250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c01250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34415164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raza S., Shin H., Hur H.G., Unno T. Higher abundance of core antimicrobial resistant genes in effluent from wastewater treatment plants. Water Res. 2022;208:117882. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117882.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34837814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y.H., Liu Y., Du P.-P., Zeng L.J., Mo C.H., Li Y.W., Lü H., Cai Q.Y. Occurrence and distribution of antibiotics and antibiotic resistant genes in water and sediments of urban rivers with black-odor water in Guangzhou, South China. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;670:170–180. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.03.168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.03.168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30903891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng X., Xu J., Smith G., Zhang Y. Metagenomic insights into dissemination of antibiotic resistance across bacterial genera in wastewater treatment. Chemosphere. 2021;271:129563. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7969412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33453487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang X., Liu L., Chen J., Fan X., Xie S., Huang J., Yu G. Antibiotic resistance genes and mobile genetic elements in a rural river in southeast China: Occurrence, seasonal variation and association with the antibiotics. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;778:146131. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33721645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenni P. Antimicrobial resistance in rivers: A review of the genes detected and new challenges. Environ. Toxicol. Chem. 2022;41:687–714. doi: 10.1002/etc.5289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/etc.5289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35191071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stange C., Sidhu J.P.S., Toze S., Tiehm A. Comparative removal of antibiotic resistance genes during chlorination, ozonation, and UV treatment. Int. J. Hyg. Environ. Health. 2019;222:541–548. doi: 10.1016/j.ijheh.2019.02.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijheh.2019.02.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30738743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Bruggen A.H.C., Goss E.M., Havelaar A., van Diepeningen A.D., Finckh M.R., Morris J.G. One health—Cycling of diverse microbial communities as a connecting force for soil, plant, animal, human and ecosystem health. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;664:927–937. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30769316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Booton R.D., Meeyai A., Alhusein N., Buller H., Feil E., Lambert H., Mongkolsuk S., Pitchforth E., Reyher K.K., Sakcamduang W., et al. One health drivers of antibacterial resistance: Quantifying the relative impacts of human, animal and environmental use and transmission. One Health. 2021;12:100220. doi: 10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7892992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33644290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auguet O., Pijuan M., Borrego C.M., Rodriguez-Mozaz S., Triadó-Margarit X., Giustina S.V.D., Gutierrez O. Sewers as potential reservoirs of antibiotic resistance. Sci. Total Environ. 2017;605–606:1047–1054. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.06.153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.06.153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28709370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He P., Zhou Y., Shao L., Huang J., Yang Z., Lü F. The discrepant mobility of antibiotic resistant genes: Evidence from their spatial distribution in sewage sludge flocs. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;697:134176. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31491625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Li R. Variation and distribution of antibiotic resistance genes and their potential hosts in microbial electrolysis cells treating sewage sludge. Bioresour. Technol. 2020;315:123838. doi: 10.1016/j.biortech.2020.123838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2020.123838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32693346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J., Jeon J.H., Shin J., Jang H.M., Kim S., Song M.S., Kim Y.M. Quantitative and qualitative changes in antibiotic resistance genes after passing through treatment processes in municipal wastewater treatment plants. Sci. Total Environ. 2017;605–606:906–914. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.06.250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.06.250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28686994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narciso-da-Rocha C., Rocha J., Vaz-Moreira I., Lira F., Tamames J., Henriques I., Martinez J.L., Manaia C.M. Bacterial lineages putatively associated with the dissemination of antibiotic resistance genes in a full-scale urban wastewater treatment plant. Environ. Int. 2018;118:179–188. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2018.05.040.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.05.040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29883764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gwenzi W., Musiyiwa K., Mangori L. Sources, behaviour and health risks of antimicrobial resistance genes in wastewaters: A hotspot reservoir. J. Environ. Chem. Eng. 2020;8:102220. doi: 10.1016/j.jece.2018.02.028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jece.2018.02.028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Quantitative Microbial Risk Assessment, Application for Water Safety Management. World Health Organization (WHO); Geneva, Switzerland: 2016. pp. 1–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Page G., Gunnarsson L., Snape J., Tyler C.R. Integrating human and environmental health in antibiotic risk assessment: A critical analysis of protection goals, species sensitivity and antimicrobial resistance. Environ. Int. 2017;109:155–169. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2017.09.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2017.09.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28964562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pepper I.L., Brooks J.P., Gerba C.P. Antibiotic resistant bacteria in municipal wastes: Is there reason for concern? Environ. Sci. Technol. 2018;52:3949–3959. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.7b04360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.7b04360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29505255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schages L., Wichern F., Kalscheuer R., Bockmühl D. Winter is coming—Impact of temperature on the variation of beta-lactamase and mcr genes in a wastewater treatment plant. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;712:136499. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.136499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.136499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31945531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoen M.E., Jahne M.A., Garland J., Ramirez L., Lopatkin A.J., Hamilton K.A. Quantitative microbial risk assessment of antimicrobial resistant and susceptible Staphylococcus aureus in reclaimed wastewaters. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;55:15246–15255. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.1c04038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c04038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8721656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34699171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Ye C., Guo L., Chen C., Kong X., Chen Y., Shu L., Wang P., Yu X., Fang J. Assessment of the UV/chlorine process in the disinfection of Pseudomonas aeruginosa: Efficiency and mechanism. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;55:9221–9230. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.1c00645.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c00645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34138551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iakovides I.C., Manoli K., Karaolia P., Michael-Kordatou I., Manaia C.M., Fatta-Kassinos D. Reduction of antibiotic resistance determinants in urban wastewater by ozone: Emphasis on the impact of wastewater matrix towards the inactivation kinetics, toxicity and bacterial regrowth. J. Hazard. Mater. 2021;420:126527. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.126527.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.126527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34329111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Espinoza J.D., Robles I., Durán-Moreno A., Godínez L.A. Photo-assisted electrochemical advanced oxidation processes for the disinfection of aqueous solutions: A review. Chemosphere. 2021;274:129957. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129957.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8121763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33979920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H., Dechesne A., He Z., Jensen M.M., Song H.L., Smets B.F. Electrochemical disinfection may increase the spread of antibiotic resistance genes by promoting conjugal plasmid transfer. Sci. Total Environ. 2023;858:159846. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159846.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36328265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiejza D., Kotowska U., Polińska W., Karpińska J. Peracids—New oxidants in advanced oxidation processes: The use of peracetic acid, peroxymonosulfate, and persulfate salts in the removal of organic micropollutants of emerging concern—A review. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;790:148195. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34380254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahulka S.Q., Bhattarai B., Bhattacharjee A.S., Tanner W., Mahar R.B., Goel R. Differences in chlorine and peracetic acid disinfection kinetics of Enterococcus faecalis and Escherichia fergusonii and their susceptible strains based on gene expressions and genomics. Water Res. 2021;203:117480. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117480.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34392043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo L.W., Wu Y.H., Chen G.Q., Wang H.B., Wang Y.H., Tong X., Bai Y., Xu Y.Q., Zhang Z.-W., Ikuno N., et al. Chlorine-resistant bacteria (CRB) in the reverse osmosis system for wastewater reclamation: Isolation, identification and membrane fouling mechanisms. Water Res. 2022;209:117966. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117966.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34952485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R., Alamin M., Tsuji S., Hara-Yamamura H., Hata A., Zhao B., Ihara M., Honda R. Removal performance of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater treatment by membrane bioreactor, anaerobic-anoxic-oxic, and conventional activated sludge processes. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;851:158310. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9411102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36030862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Z., Tran P.Q., Kieft K., Anantharaman K. Genome diversification in globally distributed novel marine proteobacteria is linked to environmental adaptation. ISME J. 2020;14:2060–2077. doi: 10.1038/s41396-020-0669-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41396-020-0669-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7367891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32393808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niestępski S., Harnisz M., Ciesielski S., Korzeniewska E., Osińska A. Environmental fate of Bacteroidetes, with particular emphasis on Bacteroides fragilis group bacteria and their specific antibiotic resistance genes, in activated sludge wastewater treatment plants. J. Hazard. Mater. 2020;394:122544. doi: 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.122544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.122544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32224375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallace M.J., Jean S., Wallace M.A., Burnham C.A.D., Dantas G. Comparative genomics of Bacteroides fragilis group isolates reveals species-dependent resistance mechanisms and validates clinical tools for resistance prediction. mBio. 2022;13:e03603-21. doi: 10.1128/mbio.03603-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mbio.03603-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8764542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35038926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander J., Knopp G., Dötsch A., Wieland A., Schwartz T. Ozone treatment of conditioned wastewater selects antibiotic resistance genes, opportunistic bacteria, and induce strong population shifts. Sci. Total Environ. 2016;559:103–112. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.03.154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.03.154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27058129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Czekalski N., Imminger S., Salhi E., Veljkovic M., Kleffel K., Drissner D., Hammes F., Bürgmann H., von Gunten U. Inactivation of antibiotic resistant bacteria and resistance genes by ozone: From laboratory experiments to full-scale wastewater treatment. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2016;50:11862–11871. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.6b02640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.6b02640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27775322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomi R., Matsuda T., Yamamoto M., Chou P.H., Tanaka M., Ichiyama S., Yoneda M., Matsumura Y. Characteristics of carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae in wastewater revealed by genomic analysis. Antimicrob. Age. Chemother. 2018;62:e02501–e02517. doi: 10.1128/AAC.02501-17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AAC.02501-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5923170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29483120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekizuka T., Yatsu K., Inamine Y., Segawa T., Nishio M., Kishi N., Kuroda M. Complete genome sequence of a blakpc-2-positive Klebsiella pneumoniae strain isolated from the effluent of an urban sewage treatment plant in Japan. mSphere. 2018;3:e00314–e00318. doi: 10.1128/mSphere.00314-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00314-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6147131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30232165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekizuka T., Inamine Y., Segawa T., Kuroda M. Characterization of NDM-5- and CTX-M-55-coproducing Escherichia coli GSH8M-2 isolated from the effluent of a wastewater treatment plant in Tokyo Bay. Infect. Drug Resist. 2019;12:2243–2249. doi: 10.2147/IDR.S215273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S215273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6662510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31413601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teixeira P., Tacão M., Pureza L., Gonçalves J., Silva A., Cruz-Schneider M.P., Henriques I. Occurrence of carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae in a portuguese river: blaNDM, blaKPC and blaGES among the detected genes. Environ. Pollut. 2020;260:113913. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2020.113913.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.113913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31972417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiller C.X., Hübner U., Fajnorova S., Schwartz T., Drewes J.E. Antibiotic microbial resistance (AMR) removal efficiencies by conventional and advanced wastewater treatment processes: A review. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;685:596–608. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.05.315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.05.315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31195321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pazda M., Kumirska J., Stepnowski P., Mulkiewicz E. Antibiotic resistance genes identified in wastewater treatment plant systems –A review. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;697:134023. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31479900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piña B., Bayona J.M., Christou A., Fatta-Kassinos D., Guillon E., Lambropoulou D., Michael C., Polesel F., Sayen S. On the contribution of reclaimed wastewater irrigation to the potential exposure of humans to antibiotics, antibiotic resistant bacteria and antibiotic resistance genes—NEREUS COST Action ES1403 position paper. J. Environ. Chem. Eng. 2020;8:102131. doi: 10.1016/j.jece.2018.01.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jece.2018.01.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>