<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39208836</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2213-2619</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Lancet. Respiratory medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet Respir Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of elexacaftor-tezacaftor-ivacaftor treatment in individuals with cystic fibrosis and CFTR<sup>N1303K</sup> in the USA: a prospective, multicentre, open-label, single-arm trial.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2213-2600(24)00205-4</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/S2213-2600(24)00205-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">CFTR modulators are approved for approximately 90% of people with cystic fibrosis in the USA and provide substantial clinical benefit. N1303K (Asn1303Lys), one of the most common class 2 CFTR defects, has not been approved for these therapies by any regulatory agency. Preclinical investigation by our laboratories showed N1303K CFTR activation with elexacaftor-tezacaftor-ivacaftor (ETI). In this trial, we evaluate whether ETI improves CFTR function, measured by sweat chloride and other clinical outcomes, in people with cystic fibrosis and CFTR<sup>N1303K</sup>.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this prospective, open-label, single-arm trial, participants aged 12 years or older with cystic fibrosis encoding at least one N1303K variant and at least one CFTR<sup>N1303K</sup> allele who were ineligible for modulator therapy by US Food and Drug Administration labelling were given ETI for 28 days followed by a 28-day washout period at two cystic fibrosis centres in the USA. Participants received two orally administered pills of 100 mg elexacaftor, 50 mg tezacaftor, and 75 mg ivacaftor once daily in the morning, and 150 mg ivacaftor once daily in the evening. The primary endpoint was mean change in sweat chloride from baseline up to day 28 compared with mixed-effects models. Secondary endpoints were changes in percentage of predicted FEV<sub>1</sub> (ppFEV<sub>1</sub>), Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R) respiratory domain, BMI, and weight after ETI therapy. Safety was assessed in all participants who received at least one dose of the study drug and primary and secondary analyses were performed in all participants who took the study drug per protocol. The trial was registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT03506061) and remains open for reporting purposes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Between June 7, 2022, and Oct 20, 2023, 20 participants (ten male and ten female) were enrolled and received ETI treatment. One participant was lost to follow-up but was included in intention-to-treat analyses. At 28 days, the mean sweat chloride reduction was -1·1 mmol/L (95% CI -5·3 to 3·1; p=0·61) with only one participant showing a sweat chloride decrease greater than 15 mmol/L. There was a mean increase in ppFEV<sub>1</sub> from baseline at day 28 of 9·5 percentage points (6·7-12·3; p&lt;0·0001) with 15 (75%) participants showing at least a 5% increase in ppFEV<sub>1</sub>. Improvements were also identified in mean CFQ-R respiratory domain score (20·8 increase [95% CI 11·9-29·8]; p&lt;0·0001), BMI (0·4 kg/m<sup>2</sup> increase [0·2-0·7]; p=0·0017), and weight (1·0 kg increase [0·4-1·7]; p=0·0020) after 28 days of ETI treatment. 14 (70%) of 20 participants had adverse events (12 [60%] mild, one [5%] moderate), with one (5%) serious adverse event of hospitalisation attributed to pneumonia. No deaths were recorded in the study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERPRETATION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Individuals with CFTR<sup>N1303K</sup> showed no change in sweat chloride after 28 days of treatment with ETI. However, there were improvements in secondary clinical endpoints, which suggest clinical efficacy. Our approach provides support for the use of in vitro model systems to inform clinical trials for rare CFTR variants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FUNDING" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The Cystic Fibrosis Foundation and the US National Institutes of Health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Solomon</LastName><ForeName>George M</ForeName><Initials>GM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA. Electronic address: gsolomon@uabmc.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Linnemann</LastName><ForeName>Rachel W</ForeName><Initials>RW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA; Children's Healthcare of Atlanta, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rich</LastName><ForeName>Rachel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Streby</LastName><ForeName>Ashleigh</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Buehler</LastName><ForeName>Brian</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hunter</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vijaykumar</LastName><ForeName>Kadambari</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hunt</LastName><ForeName>William R</ForeName><Initials>WR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brewington</LastName><ForeName>John J</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cincinnati Children's Hospital, Cincinnati, OH, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rab</LastName><ForeName>Andras</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bai</LastName><ForeName>Shasha P</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Westbrook</LastName><ForeName>Adrianna L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McNicholas-Bevensee</LastName><ForeName>Carmel</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hong</LastName><ForeName>Jong</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manfredi</LastName><ForeName>Candela</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barilla</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA; University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suzuki</LastName><ForeName>Shingo</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA; University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davis</LastName><ForeName>Brian R</ForeName><Initials>BR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA; University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sorscher</LastName><ForeName>Eric J</ForeName><Initials>EJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA; Children's Healthcare of Atlanta, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT03506061</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet Respir Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101605555</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2213-2600</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of interest GMS reports funding from the National Institutes of Health (NIH), the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation, the COPD Foundation, and the PCD Foundation; reports grants for clinical trials from Renovion, Vertex, Electromed, Insmed Pharmaceuticals, 4DMT, AstraZeneca, and BiomX for clinical trials; is a paid consultant for Insmed, Electromed, and Genetech; is on the steering committees for clinical trials for AstraZeneca, GlaxoSmithKline, and Genentech; is a member of the steering committee for the Bronchiectasis and NTM Research Registry; and has contracts for laboratory work from Renovion and ReCode, unrelated to the current manuscript. RWL reports grants paid to her institution from the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation and Vertex Pharmaceuticals; consulting fees from Vertex Pharmaceuticals; and support for travel to an investigator meeting from Vertex Pharmaceuticals. AS and EH report funding from the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation. WRH reports funding from NIH and the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation. JJB reports funding from NIH, the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation, and Cure Cystic Fibrosis, and has previously received honoraria for invited lectures from Vertex Pharmaceuticals. AR reports research support from NIH (HL-139876) and the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation. SPB reports grant funding from NIH and the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation. CM-B is a collaborator on the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation grant that funded this work. SS participates and has a key role in studies funded by the NIH and Cystic Fibrosis Foundation, and is an inventor on US Patent number 11 401 510 for the generation of airway basal stem cells from human pluripotent stem cells (issue date Aug 2, 2022). CB participates and has a key role in studies funded by NIH and the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation, and is an inventor on US Patent number 11 401 510. BRD has grants from NIH and the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation, and is an inventor on US Patent number 11 401 510. EJS reports funding from NIH (HL139876), the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation, and the Marcus Foundation; received an honorarium from the University of Iowa (Iowa City, IA, USA) for a talk regarding CFTR theratyping analysis; is working on novel compounds for treatment of cystic fibrosis that are not described or mentioned in this study but might have a future role against many CFTR mutations, including N1303K; and is a non-voting member of the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation board of directors (a not-for-profit organisation with no competing interests with this study). RR, BB, KV, ALW, JH, and CM declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39208836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(24)00205-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2213-2600(24)00205-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>