<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39206637</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1745-5065</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>20</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jan-Dec</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Women's health (London, England)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Womens Health (Lond)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Nutrition knowledge among pregnant women in Lebanon: A cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>17455057241272216</StartPage><MedlinePgn>17455057241272216</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">17455057241272216</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/17455057241272216</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Women's knowledge of the nutritional guidelines during pregnancy can affect the health and nutritional status of both mother and child. Having good nutritional information related to maternal dietary intake and healthy lifestyles is therefore of great importance. However, there is limited published research that demonstrates pregnant women's knowledge of the nutritional guidelines during pregnancy in Lebanon.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To assess the knowledge on food sources and energy recommendations as well as food safety practices and diet-health relationship among women during pregnancy in Lebanon.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A cross-sectional study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The study was conducted at prenatal care clinics in Lebanon, and all pregnant women present, regardless of nationality, were invited to complete the self-administered nutrition knowledge questionnaire. The study assessed five different nutrition knowledge domains (food sources of nutrients, dietary behaviors, food safety knowledge, micronutrients for fetal development, and energy requirements and weight gain) and the demographic characteristics of pregnant women who completed a multidimensional online survey based on validated and existing measures.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Four-hundred and ten responses were obtained. Approximately half of respondents (47%) held a university degree, for 42% of women this was their first pregnancy, and 71% had a planned pregnancy. Among the different nutrition knowledge domains, the highest levels of knowledge were for the behaviors that can minimize the effect of nausea/vomiting, heartburn, and constipation during pregnancy (63.9%) and the lowest levels of knowledge was for the importance of iodine and omega-3 fatty acids in pregnancy (28.4%). Most of females knew about food safety practices during pregnancy (72.9%) but less than half were knowledgeable about listeriosis contamination (45.9%), and the types of fish that are the safest to select during pregnancy (47.8%).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Despite the fact that pregnant women had an adequate level of knowledge in different nutrition-related areas, there was inadequate level of awareness related to critical nutrients and behaviors that can have adverse effects on mother and/or baby. Therefore, there is a need to focus on specific maternal nutrition aspects such as iron-rich foods, listeriosis food contamination, and nutrients that aid in fetal brain and retina development.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rizk</LastName><ForeName>Jessy</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-4714-4544</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, University of Nicosia, Nicosia, Cyprus.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andreou</LastName><ForeName>Eleni</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, University of Nicosia, Nicosia, Cyprus.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hileti</LastName><ForeName>Dona</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, University of Nicosia, Nicosia, Cyprus.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghaddar</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Science, Lebanese International University, Beirut, Lebanon.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Research Group, University of Alicante, Alicante, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zampelas</LastName><ForeName>Antonis</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, University of Nicosia, Nicosia, Cyprus.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Dietetics and Quality of Life, Department of Food Science and Human Nutrition, Agricultural University of Athens, Athens, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Womens Health (Lond)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101271249</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1745-5057</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011247" MajorTopicYN="N">Pregnancy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007861" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Lebanon</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007722" MajorTopicYN="Y">Health Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D037841" MajorTopicYN="Y">Pregnant Women</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004032" MajorTopicYN="N">Diet</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011295" MajorTopicYN="N">Prenatal Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009752" MajorTopicYN="N">Nutritional Status</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText><b>Nutrition knowledge among pregnant women in Lebanon</b>Women who adopt healthy dietary patterns during pregnancy are more likely to prevent adverse birth outcomes. Pregnant women from the Middle East have limited knowledge of the dietary guidelines for healthy eating during pregnancy. Yet there are no studies on nutritional knowledge of pregnant women residing in the Middle East. This study aimed to investigate the nutrition knowledge of pregnant women in Lebanon, which includes food sources of nutrients, diet–health relationships, food safety, and energy requirements during pregnancy. The highest levels of nutrition knowledge were for the behaviors that can reduce the effect of nausea and vomiting, heartburn, and constipation during pregnancy and the lowest levels of knowledge were for the importance of iodine and omega-3 fatty acids in pregnancy. The level of awareness related to critical nutrients and behaviors that can have adverse effects on mother and/or baby is inadequate. Lebanese women need to obtain their information from reliable sources such as their healthcare providers. Collaboration between healthcare providers and dietitians is essential to ensure that pregnant women receive comprehensive and accurate nutritional advice throughout their pregnancy journey.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diet</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">knowledge</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutrition</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pregnancy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">women</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39206637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11363051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/17455057241272216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abu-Saad K, Fraser D. Maternal nutrition and birth outcomes. Epidemiol Rev 2010; 32: 5–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20237078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsegaye B, Kassa A. Prevalence of adverse birth outcome and associated factors among women who delivered in Hawassa town governmental health institutions, south Ethiopia, in 2017. Reprod Health 2018; 15:193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6260556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30477512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chia AR, Chen LW, Lai JS, et al.. Maternal dietary patterns and birth outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Adv Nutr 2019; 10: 685–695.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6628847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31041446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowensohn RI, Stadler DD, Naze C. Current concepts of maternal nutrition. Obstet Gynecol Surv 2016; 71: 413–426.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4949006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27436176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danielewicz H, Myszczyszyn G, Dębińska A, et al.. Diet in pregnancy-more than food. Eur J Pediatr 2017; 176: 1573–1579.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5682869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29101450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Y, Feng C, Bédard B, et al.. Diet quality during pregnancy and its association with social factors: 3D cohort study (design, develop, discover). Matern Child Nutr 2022; 18: e13403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9480933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35821643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kocyłowski R, Lewicka I, Grzesiak M, et al.. Assessment of dietary intake and mineral status in pregnant women. Arch Gynecol Obstet 2018; 297: 1433–1440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5945726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29541858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee A, Belski R, Radcliffe J, et al.. What do pregnant women know about the healthy eating guidelines for pregnancy? A web-based questionnaire. Matern Child Health J 2016; 20: 2179–2188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27395383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jersey SJ, Nicholson JM, Callaway LK, et al.. An observational study of nutrition and physical activity behaviours, knowledge, and advice in pregnancy. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth 2013; 13: 115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3663720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23688111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malek L, Umberger W, Makrides M, et al.. Adherence to the Australian dietary guidelines during pregnancy: evidence from a national study. Public Health Nutr 2016; 19: 1155–1163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10271122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26228526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aoun A, Faddoul L, El Jabbour F, et al.. Are the level of knowledge and practices of pregnant women regarding folic acid supplementation still inadequate? A cross-sectional study in a middle eastern urban setting. J Diet Suppl 2018; 15: 692–703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29131701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan AS, Al-Kharusi BM. Knowledge and use of folic acid among pregnant Arabian women residing in Qatar and Oman. Int J Food Sci Nutr 2008; 59: 70–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18097845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazloomymahmoodabad SS, Sadeghi S, Khodayarian M, et al.. Exploring the nutritional beliefs of pregnant women in Yazd city. J Prev Med Hyg 2021; 61: E545–E552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7888392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33628959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Daour R, Osaili TM, Hashim M, et al.. Food safety knowledge among pregnant women in the United Arab Emirates amid the COVID-19 pandemic. PLoS One 2022; 17: e0279810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9803218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36584141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwalla N, Al Dhaheri AS, Radwan H, et al.. The prevalence of micronutrient deficiencies and inadequacies in the middle east and approaches to interventions. Nutrients 2017; 9: 229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sari SA, Al-Khaldi YM, Surrati AM, et al.. Knowledge, attitude, and practice of pregnant women regarding the possible effects of obesity on maternal and fetal health. Middle East J Fam Med 2022; 20: 110–116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alshahrani MS, Alqahtani NS, Alqahtani AM, et al.. Awareness of pregnant women about effect of obesity on mother and neonates at maternity and children’s hospital, Najran, Saudi Arabia. Int J Med Sci Public Health 2018; 7: 322–328.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondarianzadeh D, Yeatman H, Condon-Paoloni D. Listeria education in pregnancy: lost opportunity for health professionals. Aust N Z J Public Health 2007; 31: 468–474.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17931296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skouteris H, McPhie S, Hill B, et al.. Health coaching to prevent excessive gestational weight gain: a randomized-controlled trial. Br J Health Psychol 2016; 21: 31–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26227112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendrie GA, Coveney J, Cox D. Exploring nutrition knowledge and the demographic variation in knowledge levels in an Australian community sample. Public Health Nutr 2008; 11: 1365–1371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18671887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Worsley A, Wang WC, Byrne S, et al.. Different patterns of Australian adults’ knowledge of foods and nutrients related to metabolic disease risk. J Nutr Sci 2014; 3: e14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4153087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25191606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoerr SL, Horodynski MA, Lee SY, et al.. Predictors of nutritional adequacy in mother-toddler dyads from rural families with limited incomes. J Am Diet Assoc 2006; 106: 1766–1773.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17081827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bookari K., Yeatman H, Williamson M. Exploring Australian women’s level of nutrition knowledge during pregnancy: a cross-sectional study. Int J Womens Health 2016; 8: 405–419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4993554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27574470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jarvis S, Nelson-Piercy C. Management of nausea and vomiting in pregnancy. BMJ 2011; 342: d3606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21685438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papežová K, Kapounová Z, Zelenková V, et al.. Nutritional health knowledge and literacy among pregnant women in the Czech Republic: analytical cross-sectional study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023; 20: 3931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10001919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36900942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee A, Newton M, Radcliffe J, et al.. Pregnancy nutrition knowledge and experiences of pregnant women and antenatal care clinicians: a mixed methods approach. Women Birth 2018; 31: 269–277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29126796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blondin JH, LoGiudice JA. Pregnant women’s knowledge and awareness of nutrition. Appl Nurs Res 2018; 39: 167–174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29422153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aktaç S, Sabuncular G, Kargin D, et al.. Evaluation of nutrition knowledge of pregnant women before and after nutrition education according to sociodemographic characteristics. Ecol Food Nutr 2018; 57: 441–455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30421984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adjei-Banuah NY, Aduah VA, Ziblim SD, et al.. Nutrition knowledge is associated with the consumption of iron rich foods: a survey among pregnant women from a rural district in Northern Ghana. Nutr Metab Insights 2021; 14: 11786388211039427.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8411617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34483667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jouanne M, Oddoux S, Noël A, et al.. Nutrient requirements during pregnancy and lactation. Nutrients 2021; 13: 692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7926714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33670026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan RG. Prenatal omega-3 fatty acids: review and recommendations. J Midwifery Womens Health 2010; 55: 520–528.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20974414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khresheh R. Strategies used by Jordanian women to alleviate heartburn during pregnancy. Midwifery 2011; 27: 603–606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21146263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahimi N, Maltepe C, Einarson A. Optimal management of nausea and vomiting of pregnancy. Int J Womens Health 2010; 2: 241–248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2990891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21151729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Assessment of iodine deficiency disorders and monitoring their elimination: a guide for programme managers. 3rd ed. 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearce EN, Lazarus JH, Moreno-Reyes R, et al.. Consequences of iodine deficiency and excess in pregnant women: an overview of current knowns and unknowns. Am J Clin Nutr 2016; 104(Suppl 3): 918S–923S.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5004501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27534632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garnweidner-Holme L, Aakre I, Lilleengen AM, et al.. Knowledge about iodine in pregnant and lactating women in the Oslo area, Norway. Nutrients 2017; 9: 493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5452223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28505075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinheiro C, Xavier Moreira N, Ferreira P, et al.. Iodine knowledge is associated with iodine status in Portuguese pregnant women: results from the IoMum cohort study. Br J Nutr 2021; 126: 1331–1339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33461643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinikovic DS, Yeatman HR, Cameron D, et al.. Women’s awareness of the importance of long-chain omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid consumption during pregnancy: knowledge of risks, benefits and information accessibility. Public Health Nutr 2009; 12: 562–569.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18507886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Troxell H, Anderson J, Auld G, et al.. Omega-3 for baby and me: material development for a WIC intervention to increase DHA intake during pregnancy. Matern Child Health J 2005; 9: 189–197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15965625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryant J, Waller A, Cameron E, et al.. Diet during pregnancy: women’s knowledge of and adherence to food safety guidelines. Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol 2017; 57: 315–322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27624518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jevšnik M, Česen A, Šantić M, et al.. Food safety knowledge and practices of pregnant women and postpartum mothers in Slovenia. Foods 2021; 10: 2412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8535543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34681461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Downs DS, Savage JS, Rauff EL. Falling short of guidelines? Nutrition and weight gain knowledge in pregnancy. J Womens Health Care. 2014; 3: 1000184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4293543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25599012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>