<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39205510</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Rapid detection of murine-derived ingredients in meat products using real-time enzymatic recombinase amplification.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13841</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Accurate identification of meat species is critical to prevent economic fraud and safeguard public health. The use of inappropriate meat sources, such as murine, poses significant health risks because of potential contamination with pathogens and allergens, leading to foodborne illnesses. The present study aimed to develop a novel real-time enzymatic recombinase amplification (ERA) method for the rapid and specific detection of murine DNA in meat products.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A novel ERA primer and probe set was designed, targeting a murine-specific single-copy nuclear gene identified through bioinformatics analysis. The assay demonstrates high specificity, showing no amplification in commonly consumed meats, other animals or major crops. Additionally, it exhibits remarkable sensitivity, detecting as few as five copies of murine genomic DNA. For practical application, the ERA method could effectively identify mouse DNA in laboratory-prepared samples at concentrations as low as 0.5% and also quantify samples with mouse DNA content as low as 5%. It also accurately detects the presence of murine-derived ingredients in commercially available meat products. The detection process is straightforward, utilizing a simple isothermal device for incubation, blue light excitation and a smartphone camera for result interpretation. This rapid analysis can be completed within 20 min.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The newly developed real-time ERA method provides a valuable tool for standardizing meat trade practices, promoting food safety and enhancing consumer confidence in the authenticity of meat products. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Qingqing</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Zhifei</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liang</LastName><ForeName>Qianqian</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaohui</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Qiquan</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cai</LastName><ForeName>Wenyu</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lei</LastName><ForeName>Jiawen</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Guojun</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2381-9345</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Key Laboratory for Protection and Application of Special Plant Germplasm in Wuling Area of China, College of Life Science, South-Central Minzu University, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Academic Innovation Teams of South-Central Minzu University (Grant Number: XTZ24022)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food authenticity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">murine DNA detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rapid detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">real‐time enzymatic recombinase amplification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">single‐copy nuclear gene</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39205510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Hossain MAM, Ali ME, Sultana S, Asing, Bonny SQ, Kader MA et al., Quantitative Tetraplex real‐time polymerase chain reaction assay with TaqMan probes discriminates cattle, Buffalo, and porcine materials in food chain. J Agric Food Chem 65:3975–3985 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agnoli L, Capitello R, De Salvo M, Longo A and Boeri M, Food fraud and consumers' choices in the wake of the horsemeat scandal. Br Food J 118:1898–1913 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Septiani T and Pendrianto P, Detection of mice DNA in meatballs using real time – PCR. J Envisci 2:63–67 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>China Daily, 'Rat's head in canteen’ incident creates lasting stir (2023). Available: https://www.chinadaily.com.cn/a/202306/12/WS648668d9a31033ad3f7bba98.html [3 June 2024].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali ME, Ahamad MNU, Asing, Hossain MAM and Sultana S, Multiplex polymerase chain reaction‐restriction fragment length polymorphism assay discriminates of rabbit, rat and squirrel meat in frankfurter products. Food Control 84:148–158 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woolfe M and Primrose S, Food forensics: using DNA technology to combat misdescription and fraud. Trends Biotechnol 22:222–226 (2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Jin W, Yang Y, Ma H, Liu H, Lei J et al., CRISPR/Cas12a‐mediated enzymatic recombinase amplification for rapid visual quantitative authentication of halal food. Anal Chim Acta 1255:341144 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain MAM, Ali ME, Abd Hamid SB, Asing, Mustafa S, Mohd Desa MN et al., Double gene targeting multiplex polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism assay discriminates beef, buffalo, and pork substitution in frankfurter products. J Agric Food Chem 64:6343–6354 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Liu J, Zhang Q, Zhou X and Liu B, Multiplex PCR assay for identification and quantification of bovine and equine in minced meats using novel specific nuclear DNA sequences. Food Control 105:29–37 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nesvadbova M, Kralik P, Dziedzinska R, Dufkova M and Borilova G, An integrated system of four multiplex qPCR assays for the precise and sensitive identification of animal species in food and feed. Food Control 135:108781 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu N, Ren J, Huang W, Xing R, Deng T and Chen Y, An effective analytical droplet digital PCR approach for identification and quantification of fur‐bearing animal meat in raw and processed food. Food Chem 355:129525 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim M‐J, Suh S‐M, Kim S‐Y, Qin P, Kim H‐R and Kim H‐Y, Development of a real‐time PCR assay for the detection of donkey (Equus asinus) meat in meat mixtures treated under different processing conditions. Foods 9:130 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarlak Z, Shojaee‐Aliabadi S, Rezvani N, Hosseini H, Rouhi M and Dastafkan Z, Development and validation of TaqMan real‐time PCR assays for quantification of chicken adulteration in hamburgers. J Food Compos Anal 106:104302 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q, Cai Y, Ning X, Yang L, Xu Z, Zhao L et al., Inter‐laboratory validation of real‐time PCR assays for goat‐, horse‐ and donkey‐derived material in meat products. Agric Biotechnol 10:69–74 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S‐Z, Zeng S‐L, Wu Y, Zheng G‐D, Chu C, Yin Q et al., Cultivar differentiation of Citri Reticulatae Pericarpium by a combination of hierarchical three‐step filtering metabolomics analysis, DNA barcoding and electronic nose. Anal Chim Acta 1056:62–69 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mottola A, Piredda R, Lorusso L, Armani A and Di Pinto A, Preliminary study on species authentication in poultry meat products by next‐generation sequencing. Food Control 145:109459 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahama S, Chebako H, Sirikwanpong S, Mahamad P, Santiworakul NY, Suksuwan A et al., Simultaneous identification of four meat species (cattle, chicken, fish, and pig) using next generation sequencing (NGS). IHSATEC 14:182–193 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piredda R, Mottola A, Cipriano G, Carlucci R, Ciccarese G and Di Pinto A, Next generation sequencing (NGS) approach applied to species identification in mixed processed seafood products. Food Control 133:108590 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zia Q, Alawami M, Mokhtar NFK, Nhari RMHR and Hanish I, Current analytical methods for porcine identification in meat and meat products. Food Chem 324:126664 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Zhang X, Liao G, Shang Y, Ge C, Chen R et al., Species‐specific TM‐LAMP and trident‐like lateral flow biosensor for on‐site authenticity detection of horse and donkey meat. Sensor Actuat B‐Chem 301:127039 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kissenkötter J, Böhlken‐Fascher S, Forrest MS and Piepenburg O, Czerny C‐P and Abd El Wahed a, recombinase polymerase amplification assays for the identification of pork and horsemeat. Food Chem 322:126759 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji C, He Y, Xu X, Liu J, Liu W, Wang X et al., Development of reference material for the detection of rat ingredient in meat by quantitative real‐time PCR. Food Biosci 53:102800 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang X and Zhang C, Detection of adulterated murine components in meat products by TaqMan© real‐time PCR. Food Chem 192:485–490 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali ME, Razzak MA, Hamid SBA, Rahman MM, Amin MA, Rashid NRA et al., Multiplex PCR assay for the detection of five meat species forbidden in Islamic foods. Food Chem 177:214–224 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wibowo T, Cahyadi M, Pramono A and Volkandari SD, Evaluation of commercial meat product food label conformity using multiplex PCR assay. Food Control 149:109712 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary P and Kumar Y, Recent advances in multiplex molecular techniques for meat species identification. J Food Compos Anal 110:104581 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou B, Meng X, Zhang L, Guo J, Li S and Jin H, Development of a sensitive and specific multiplex PCR method for the simultaneous detection of chicken, duck and goose DNA in meat products. Meat Sci 101:90–94 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin P, Qiao D, Xu J, Song Q, Yao L, Lu J et al., Rapid visual sensing and quantitative identification of duck meat in adulterated beef with a lateral flow strip platform. Food Chem 294:224–230 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang L, Huang P, Liu J, Fu C, Liu W, Gao Y et al., Real‐time PCR method based on single‐copy nuclear DNA sequences for the quantitative detection of pork adulteration in processed beef products. Food Control 163:110518 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li T, Wang J, Wang Z, Qiao L, Liu R, Li S et al., Quantitative determination of mutton adulteration with single‐copy nuclear genes by real‐time PCR. Food Chem 344:128622 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Fu M, Zhang Q, Zhen Y, Liu J, Xiang S et al., A novel quantitative real‐time PCR method for the detection of mammalian and poultry species based on a shared single‐copy nuclear DNA sequence. Food Chem 341:128170 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Wang Y, Hu J, Bao Z and Wang M, Rapid detection of white spot syndrome virus in Penaeus vannamei based on real‐time enzymatic recombinase amplification. Aquaculture 566:739196 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Q, Wang Y, Hu J, Bao Z and Wang M, Development of a real‐time enzymatic recombinase amplification assay (RT‐ERA) and an ERA combined with lateral flow dipsticks (LFD) assay (ERA‐LFD) for rapid detection of acute hepatopancreatic necrosis disease (AHPND) in shrimp Penaeus vannamei. Aquaculture 566:739205 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Wang X, Xu L and Zhang B, A new rapid method for extraction of high quality of genomic DNA from animal tissues. Chin J Zool 6:27–29 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Andreo M, Lugo L, Garrido‐Pertierra A, Prieto MI and Puyet A, Identification and quantitation of species in complex DNA mixtures by real‐time polymerase chain reaction. Anal Biochem 339:73–82 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Wang X, Wei T, Zhang Q, Zhou X and Liu B, A multiplex real‐time PCR approach for identification and quantification of sheep/goat, fox and murine fractions in meats using nuclear DNA sequences. Food Control 126:108035 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ENGL (European Network of GMO Laboratories), European Commission, Definition of minimum performance requirements for analytical methods of GMO testing (2015). Available: http://gmo-crl.jrc.ec.europa.eu/doc/MPR%20Report%20Application%2020_10_2015.pdf [3 June 2024].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie R, Zhang J, Wen S, Zhao R, Wang N and Chen A, Rapid identification of escolar (Lepidocybium flavobrunneum) and oilfish (Ruvettus pretiosus) species based on recombinase polymerase amplification. Food Control 144:109352 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Sui X, Ma Y, Li M, Zhang X, Fei D et al., Real‐time reverse transcription recombinase polymerase amplification for rapid detection of murine hepatitis virus. Front Microbiol 13:1067694 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou C, Liu L, Xiang J, Fu Q, Wang J, Wang K et al., Identification of horse, donkey and pig ingredients by species‐specific ERA‐based methods to assess the authenticity of meat products. Food Biosci 53:102827 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin L, Zheng Y, Huang H, Zhuang F, Chen H, Zha G et al., A visual method to detect meat adulteration by recombinase polymerase amplification combined with lateral flow dipstick. Food Chem 354:129526 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crannell ZA, Rohrman B and Richards‐Kortum R, Quantification of HIV‐1 DNA using real‐time recombinase polymerase amplification. Anal Chem 86:5615–5619 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Wang Q, Bergmann SM, Li Y, Li B, Lv Y et al., Development and comparative evaluation of real‐time PCR and real‐time RPA assays for detection of tilapia lake virus. Mol Cell Probes 60:101776 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y, Wang Y, Fan Z, Zhao X, Bergmann SM, Dong H et al., Establishment and evaluation of qPCR and real‐time recombinase‐aided amplification assays for detection of largemouth bass ranavirus. J Fish Dis 45:1033–1043 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li K, Luo Y, Huang K, Yang Z, Wan Y and Xu W, Single universal primer recombinase polymerase amplification‐based lateral flow biosensor (SUP‐RPA‐LFB) for multiplex detection of genetically modified maize. Anal Chim Acta 1127:217–224 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JY and Lee J‐L, Development of a multiplex real‐time recombinase polymerase amplification (RPA) assay for rapid quantitative detection of campylobacter coli and jejuni from eggs and chicken products. Food Control 73:1247–1255 (2017).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>