<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39218992</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>89</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Characterization of ultrasonic-assisted antifungal film loaded with fermented walnut meal on Rosa roxburghii Tratt during near-freezing temperature storage.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>6539</StartPage><EndPage>6552</EndPage><MedlinePgn>6539-6552</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17328</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Fermented walnut meal (FW) has antifungal activity against Penicillium victoriae, a fungus responsible for Rosa roxbughii Tratt spoilage. This study characterized and applied ultrasonic-assisted antifungal film loaded with FW to preserve R. roxbughii Tratt during near-freezing temperature (NFT). Results showed that O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> transmission rates decreased by 80.02% and 29.05%, respectively, and antimicrobial properties were improved with ultrasound at 560 W for 5 min and 1% FW. Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy and X-ray diffraction results revealed ultrasound improved hydrogen bonds and inductive effect via ─NH, ─OH, and C═O bonds. The addition of FW led to the formation of CMCS-GL-FW polymer via C═O bond. Thermogravimetric analysis and transmission electron microscope results demonstrated thermal degradation process was decomposed by ultrasound, and the internal structure of P. victoriae was accelerated by the addition of FW. Compared to the U-CMCS/GL group, the vitamin C content, peroxidase, and catalase activities of U-CMCS/GL/FW were enhanced by 4.24%, 8.52%, and 14.3% during NFT (-0.8 to -0.4°C), respectively. Particularly, the fungal count of the U-CMCS/GL/FW group did not exceed 10<sup>5</sup> CFU g<sup>-1</sup> at the end of storage, and the relative abundance of P. victoriae decreased to 0.007%. Our findings provide an effective route for agricultural waste as natural antifungal compounds in the active packaging industry. PRACTICAL APPLICATION: In this study, the barrier and antimicrobial properties of film were successfully improved by ultrasonic treatment and loaded fermented walnut meal. The ultrasonic-assisted antifungal film loaded with fermented walnut meal effectively delayed the degradation of nutrients and reduced microbial invasion of Rosa roxburghii Tratt. These results provide a theoretical basis for the application of agricultural waste in the food packaging industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Yue</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Efficient Production of Forest Resources, Beijing Key Laboratory of Food Processing and Safety in Forestry, Department of Food Science and Engineering, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wan</LastName><ForeName>Shuangju</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Efficient Production of Forest Resources, Beijing Key Laboratory of Food Processing and Safety in Forestry, Department of Food Science and Engineering, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Ruijie</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Efficient Production of Forest Resources, Beijing Key Laboratory of Food Processing and Safety in Forestry, Department of Food Science and Engineering, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cao</LastName><ForeName>Lisha</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Efficient Production of Forest Resources, Beijing Key Laboratory of Food Processing and Safety in Forestry, Department of Food Science and Engineering, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fu</LastName><ForeName>Chengxin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Efficient Production of Forest Resources, Beijing Key Laboratory of Food Processing and Safety in Forestry, Department of Food Science and Engineering, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Di Feng</ForeName><Initials>DF</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5813-2792</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Efficient Production of Forest Resources, Beijing Key Laboratory of Food Processing and Safety in Forestry, Department of Food Science and Engineering, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2020133135</GrantID><Agency>National promotion project of scientific and technological achievements in forestry and grassland</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000935">Antifungal Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D031324" MajorTopicYN="Y">Juglans</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000935" MajorTopicYN="Y">Antifungal Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D027826" MajorTopicYN="Y">Rosa</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005285" MajorTopicYN="Y">Fermentation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D061353" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Storage</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005519" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Preservation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010407" MajorTopicYN="N">Penicillium</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003080" MajorTopicYN="N">Cold Temperature</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018857" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Packaging</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014465" MajorTopicYN="N">Ultrasonics</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009754" MajorTopicYN="N">Nuts</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017550" MajorTopicYN="N">Spectroscopy, Fourier Transform Infrared</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rosa roxburghii Tratt</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antifungal film</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fermented walnut meal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">postharvest preservation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ultrasound</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39218992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abral, H., Basri, A., Muhammad, F., Fernando, Y., Hafizulhaq, F., Mahardika, M., Sugiarti, E., Sapuan, S. M., Ilyas, R. A., &amp; Stephane, I. (2019). A simple method for improving the properties of the sago starch films prepared by using ultrasonication treatment. Food Hydrocolloids, 93(8), 276–283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahrami, A., Rezaei Mokarram, R., Sowti Khiabani, M., Ghanbarzadeh, B., &amp; Salehi, R. (2019). Physico‐mechanical and antimicrobial properties of tragacanth/hydroxypropyl methylcellulose/beeswax edible films reinforced with silver nanoparticles. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 129, 1103–1112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benettayeb, A., Guibal, E., Morsli, A., &amp; Kessas, R. (2017). Chemical modification of alginate for enhanced sorption of Cd(II), Cu(II) and Pb(II). Chemical Engineering Journal, 316, 704–714.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borah, P. P., Das, P., &amp; Badwaik, L. S. (2017). Ultrasound treated potato peel and sweet lime pomace based biopolymer film development. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 36, 11–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chemat, F., Rombaut, N., Sicaire, A.‐G., Meullemiestre, A., Fabiano‐Tixier, A.‐S., &amp; Abert‐Vian, M. (2016). Ultrasound assisted extraction of food and natural products. Mechanisms, techniques, combinations, protocols and applications. A review. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 34, 540–560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dammak, I., De Carvalho, R. A., Trindade, C. S. F., Lourenço, R. V., &amp; Do Amaral Sobral, P. J. (2017). Properties of active gelatin films incorporated with rutin‐loaded nanoemulsions. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 98, 39–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evranos, B., Aycan, D., &amp; Alemdar, N. (2019). Production of ciprofloxacin loaded chitosan/gelatin/bone ash wound dressing with improved mechanical properties. Carbohydrate Polymers, 222, 115007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falguera, V., Quintero, J. P., Jim´enez, A., Munoz, J. A., &amp; Ibarz, A. (2011). Edible films and coatings: Structures, active functions and trends in their use. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 22(6), 292–303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghanbarzadeh, B., Almasi, H., &amp; Entezami, A. A. (2010). Physical properties of edible modified starch/carboxymethyl cellulose films. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 11, 697–702.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gul, O., Saricaoglu, F. T., Besir, A., Atalar, I., &amp; Yazici, F. (2018). Effect of ultrasound treatment on the properties of nano‐emulsion films obtained from hazelnut meal protein and clove essential oil. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 41, 466–474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haghighi, H., Biard, S., Bigi, F., De Leo, R., Bedin, E., Pfeifer, F., Siesler, H. W., Licciardello, F., &amp; Pulvirenti, A. (2019). Comprehensive characterization of active chitosan‐gelatin blend films enriched with different essential oils. Food Hydrocolloids, 95, 33–42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halim, A. L. L. A., Kamari, A., &amp; Phillip, E. (2018). Chitosan, gelatin and methylcellulose films incorporated with tannic acid for food packaging. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 120, 1119–1126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou, Z., Zhao, L., Wang, Y., &amp; Liao, X. (2019). Effects of high pressure on activities and properties of superoxide dismutase from chestnut rose. Food Chemistry, 294, 557–564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, H., Wu, J., Li‐Chan, E. C. Y., Zhu, L., Zhang, F., Xu, X., Fan, G., Wang, L., Huang, X., &amp; Pan, S. (2013). Effects of ultrasound on structural and physical properties of soy protein isolate dispersions. Food Hydrocolloids, 30, 647–655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Y., Ling, Y., Qin, Z., Huang, J., Jian, L., &amp; Ren, D. F. (2024). Isolation, identification, and synergistic mechanism of a novel antimicrobial peptide and phenolic compound from fermented walnut meal and their application in Rosa roxbughii Tratt spoilage fungus. Food Chemistry, 433, 137333.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kong, J., Zhang, Y., Ju, J., Xie, Y., Guo, Y., Cheng, Y., Qian, H., Quek, S. Y., &amp; Yao, W. (2019). Antifungal effects of thymol and salicylic acid on cell membrane and mitochondria of rhizopus stolonifer and their application in postharvest preservation of tomatoes. Food Chemistry, 285, 380–388.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Fang, W., Wang, Z., &amp; Chen, Y. (2022). Physicochemical, biological properties, and flavour profile of Rosa roxburghii Tratt, Pyracantha fortuneana, and Rosa laevigata Michx fruits: A comprehensive review. Food Chemistry, 366, 130509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima, G., De Curtis, F., &amp; De Cicco, V. (2008). Interaction of microbial biocontrol agents and fungicides in the control of postharvest diseases. Stewart Postharvest Review, 4, 1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, P., Gao, W., Zhang, X., Wang, B., Zou, F., Yu, B., Lu, L., Fang, Y., Wu, Z., Yuan, C., &amp; Cui, B. (2021). Effects of ultrasonication on the properties of maize starch/stearic acid/sodium carboxymethyl cellulose composite film. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 72, 105447.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, P., Kang, X., Cui, B., Wang, R., &amp; Wu, Z. (2019). Effects of glycerides with different molecular structures on the properties of maize starch and its film forming capacity. Industrial Crops and Products, 129, 512–517.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, R., Du, J., Zhang, Z., Li, H., Lu, J., Cheng, Y., Lv, Y., &amp; Wang, H. (2019). Preparation of polyacrylic acid‐grafted‐acryloyl/hemicellulose (PAA‐g‐AH) hybrid films with high oxygen barrier performance. Carbohydrate Polymers, 205(10), 83–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molenda, P., Jugenheimer, A., Haefner, C., Oechsle, O., &amp; Karat, R. (2019). Methodology for the visualization, analysis and assessment of information processes in manufacturing companies. Procedia CIRP, 84, 5–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao, C., Ma, X., Zhang, J., &amp; Yao, J. (2017). Molecular interactions in gelatin/chitosan composite films. Food Chemistry, 235, 45–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahari, J., Sapuan, S. M., Zainudin, E. S., &amp; Maleque, M. A. (2013). Thermo‐mechanical behaviors of thermoplastic starch derived from sugar palm tree (Arenga pinnata). Carbohydrate Polymers, 92, 1711–1716.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanzani, S. M., Reverberi, M., &amp; Geisen, R. (2016). Mycotoxins in harvested fruits and vegetables: Insights in producing fungi, biological role, conducive conditions, and tools to manage postharvest contamination. Postharvest Biology and Technology, 122, 95–105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soria, A. C., &amp; Villamiel, M. (2010). Effect of ultrasound on the technological properties and bioactivity of food: A review. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 21(7), 323–331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Y., &amp; Ye, X. (2013). Enhancement or reduction of sonochemical activity of pulsed ultrasound compared to continuous ultrasound at 20 k Hz. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 18(5), 4858–4867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Ding, J., Fang, Y., Pan, X., Fan, F., Li, P., &amp; Hu, Q. (2020). Effect of ultrasonic power on properties of edible composite films based on rice protein hydrolysates and chitosan. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 65(3), 105049.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Wu, M., &amp; Liu, H.‐M. (2017). Emulsifying and physicochemical properties of soy hullhemicelluloses‐soy protein isolate conjugates. Carbohydrate Polymers, 163, 181–190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, C., Tian, J., Li, S., Wu, T., Hu, Y., Chen, S., Sugawara, T., &amp; Ye, X. (2016). Structural properties of films and rheology of film‐forming solutions of chitosan gallate for food packaging. Carbohydrate Polymers, 146, 10–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing, Y., Li, X., Xu, Q., Yun, J., Lu, Y., &amp; Tang, Y. (2011). Effects of chitosan coating enriched with cinnamon oil on qualitative properties of sweet pepper (Capsicum annuum L). Food Chemistry, 124(4), 1443–1450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, F. Z., Cheng, S. J., &amp; Jameson, P. E. (2017). A rapid and cost effective protocol for plant genomic DNA isolation using regenerated silica columns in combination with CTAB extraction. Journal of Integrative Agriculture, 16, 1682–1688.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, C., Yang, Z., Shi, J., Zou, X., Zhai, X., Huang, X., Li, Z., Holmes, M., Daglia, M., &amp; Xiao, J. (2021). Physical properties and bioactivities of chitosan/gelatin‐based films loaded with tannic acid and its application on the preservation of fresh‐cut apples. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 144, 111223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, F., Du, G., &amp; Huang, Y. (2022). Exploring the use of Near‐infrared spectroscopy as a tool to predict quality attributes in prickly pear (Rosa roxburghii Tratt) with chemometrics variable strategy. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis, 105(10), 104225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, H., Shu, C., Fan, X., Cao, J., &amp; Jiang, W. (2018). Near‐freezing temperature storage prolongs storage period and improves quality and antioxidant capacity of nectarines. Scientia Horticulturae, 228, 196–203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, M., Zhou, H., Chen, L., Hao, L., Chen, H., &amp; Zhou, X. (2020). Carboxymethyl chitosan grafted trisiloxane surfactant nanoparticles with pH sensitivity for sustained release of pesticide. Carbohydrate Polymers, 243, 116433.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>