<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39217524</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Transplanting network pharmacology technology into food science research: A comprehensive review on uncovering food-sourced functional factors and their health benefits.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13429</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13429</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.13429</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Network pharmacology is an emerging interdisciplinary research method. The application of network pharmacology to reveal the nutritional effects and mechanisms of active ingredients in food is of great significance in promoting the development of functional food, facilitating personalized nutrition, and exploring the mechanisms of food health effects. This article systematically reviews the application of network pharmacology in the field of food science using a literature review method. The application progress of network pharmacology in food science is discussed, and the mechanisms of functional factors in food on the basis of network pharmacology are explored. Additionally, the limitations and challenges of network pharmacology are discussed, and future directions and application prospects are proposed. Network pharmacology serves as an important tool to reveal the mechanisms of action and health benefits of functional factors in food. It helps to conduct in-depth research on the biological activities of individual ingredients, composite foods, and compounds in food, and assessment of the potential health effects of food components. Moreover, it can help to control and enhance their functionality through relevant information during the production and processing of samples to guarantee food safety. The application of network pharmacology in exploring the mechanisms of functional factors in food is further analyzed and summarized. Combining machine learning, artificial intelligence, clinical experiments, and in vitro validation, the achievement transformation of functional factor in food driven by network pharmacology is of great significance for the future development of network pharmacology research.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Qing</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Clinical Research, Institute of Seafood, Zhejiang Gongshang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Panvascular Diseases Research Center, The Quzhou Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Quzhou People's Hospital, Quzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ge</LastName><ForeName>Lijun</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Clinical Research, Institute of Seafood, Zhejiang Gongshang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Weibo</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Clinical Research, Institute of Seafood, Zhejiang Gongshang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Huixiang</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Clinical Research, Institute of Seafood, Zhejiang Gongshang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Quzhou Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Quzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ningbo Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang Chinese Medical University, Ningbo, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Oushan</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaoxing Second Hospital, Shaoxing, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Muhammad</LastName><ForeName>Imran</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6871-1763</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Clinical Research, Institute of Seafood, Zhejiang Gongshang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Panvascular Diseases Research Center, The Quzhou Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Quzhou People's Hospital, Quzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Yeshun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Panvascular Diseases Research Center, The Quzhou Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Quzhou People's Hospital, Quzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Si-Wei</ForeName><Initials>SW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Panvascular Diseases Research Center, The Quzhou Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Quzhou People's Hospital, Quzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Xi-Xi</ForeName><Initials>XX</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Panvascular Diseases Research Center, The Quzhou Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Quzhou People's Hospital, Quzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xue</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0004-4487-1489</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Clinical Research, Institute of Seafood, Zhejiang Gongshang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Keyun</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Panvascular Diseases Research Center, The Quzhou Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Quzhou People's Hospital, Quzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Ningbo Medical &amp; Health Leading Academic Discipline Project (2022-Z03)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Science and Technology Project of Zhejiang Provincial Drug Administration (2021016)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Zhejiang Provincial TCM Science and Technology Project (2023ZL734)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Quzhou City Science and Technology Project (2023K163 and 2023K128)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>State and Provincial Joint Key Project of TCM Science and Technology (GZY-ZJ-KJ-24047)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>LTGY23H020001</GrantID><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055951" MajorTopicYN="Y">Functional Food</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000091484" MajorTopicYN="Y">Network Pharmacology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005524" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Technology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059022" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Safety</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069550" MajorTopicYN="N">Machine Learning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biological activities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">functional factors in food</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mechanisms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">network pharmacology</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39217524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.13429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Afzal, S., Abdul Manap, A. S., Attiq, A., Albokhadaim, I., Kandeel, M., &amp; Alhojaily, S. M. (2023). From imbalance to impairment: The central role of reactive oxygen species in oxidative stress‐induced disorders and therapeutic exploration. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 14, 1269581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aguilera, J. M. (2019). The food matrix: Implications in processing, nutrition and health. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 59(22), 3612–3629.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akter, S., Moni, A., Faisal, G. M., Uddin, M. R., Jahan, N., Hannan, M. A., Rahman, A., &amp; Uddin, M. J. (2022). Renoprotective effects of mangiferin: pharmacological advances and future perspectives. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(3), 1864.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Mijan, M., &amp; Lim, B. O. (2018). Diets, functional foods, and nutraceuticals as alternative therapies for inflammatory bowel disease: Present status and future trends. World Journal of Gastroenterology, 24(25), 2673.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almutairi, R., Basson, A. R., Wearsh, P., Cominelli, F., &amp; Rodriguez‐Palacios, A. (2022). Validity of food additive maltodextrin as placebo and effects on human gut physiology: Systematic review of placebo‐controlled clinical trials. European Journal of Nutrition, 61(6), 2853–2871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alongi, M., &amp; Anese, M. (2021). Re‐thinking functional food development through a holistic approach. Journal of Functional Foods, 81, 104466.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alt, K. W., Al‐Ahmad, A., &amp; Woelber, J. P. (2022). Nutrition and Health in Human Evolution–Past to Present. Nutrients, 14(17), 3594.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambati, R. R., Phang, S.‐M., Ravi, S., &amp; Aswathanarayana, R. G. (2014). Astaxanthin: Sources, extraction, stability, biological activities and its commercial applications—A review. Marine Drugs, 12(1), 128–152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amit, S. K., Uddin, M. M., Rahman, R., Islam, S. R., &amp; Khan, M. S. (2017). A review on mechanisms and commercial aspects of food preservation and processing. Agriculture &amp; Food Security, 6, 1–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azevedo, L., Granato, D., Maltarollo, V. G., &amp; Gonçalves, J. E. (2023). A mosaic‐structured framework applied in the healthy food design: Insights from integrated in silico and in vitro approaches. Current Opinion in Food Science, 52, 101047.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azevedo, L., Serafim, M. S. M., Maltarollo, V. G., Grabrucker, A. M., &amp; Granato, D. (2022). Atherosclerosis fate in the era of tailored functional foods: Evidence‐based guidelines elicited from structure‐and ligand‐based approaches. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 128, 75–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbosa, J. R., &amp; de Carvalho Junior, R. N. (2021). Polysaccharides obtained from natural edible sources and their role in modulating the immune system: Biologically active potential that can be exploited against COVID‐19. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 108, 223–235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basak, S., &amp; Gokhale, J. (2022). Immunity boosting nutraceuticals: Current trends and challenges. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 46(3), e13902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bharate, S. S., Mignani, S., &amp; Vishwakarma, R. A. (2018). Why are the majority of active compounds in the CNS domain natural products? A critical analysis. Journal of Medicinal Chemistry, 61(23), 10345–10374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat, A. H., Dar, K. B., Anees, S., Zargar, M. A., Masood, A., Sofi, M. A., &amp; Ganie, S. A. (2015). Oxidative stress, mitochondrial dysfunction and neurodegenerative diseases; a mechanistic insight. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy, 74, 101–110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilal, Z., Akhmetsadykova, S., Baubekova, A., Tormo, H., Faye, B., &amp; Konuspayeva, G. (2024). The main features and microbiota diversity of fermented camel milk. Foods, 13(13), 1985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calabrese, V., Schmitz‐Afonso, I., Prevost, C., Afonso, C., &amp; Elomri, A. (2022). Molecular networking and collision cross section prediction for structural isomer and unknown compound identification in plant metabolomics: A case study applied to Zhanthoxylum heitzii extracts. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 414(14), 4103–4118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, X., Shi, K., Xu, Y., Zhang, P., Zhang, H., &amp; Pan, S. (2023). Integrated metabolomics and network pharmacology to reveal antioxidant mechanisms and potential pharmacological ingredients of citrus herbs. Food Research International, 174, 113514.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, Y., Huang, J., Sun, M., Shui, W., Huang, T., &amp; Huang, M. (2023). Network pharmacology and molecular docking combined to investigate the mechanism of duck‐derived active peptides in preventing hypertension. International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology, 58(10), e12–e25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carr, A. C., &amp; Maggini, S. (2017). Vitamin C and immune function. Nutrients, 9(11), 1211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakrabarti, S., Guha, S., &amp; Majumder, K. (2018). Food‐derived bioactive peptides in human health: Challenges and opportunities. Nutrients, 10(11), 1738.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan, E. W. C., Wong, C. W., Tan, Y. H., Foo, J. P. Y., Wong, S. K., &amp; Chan, H. T. (2019). Resveratrol and pterostilbene: A comparative overview of their chemistry, biosynthesis, plant sources and pharmacological properties. Journal of Applied Pharmaceutical Science, 9(7), 124–129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chautard, E., Thierry‐Mieg, N., &amp; Ricard‐Blum, S. (2009). Interaction networks: From protein functions to drug discovery. A review. Pathologie Biologie, 57(4), 324–333.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, G., Huang, C., Shi, P., Xu, H., Gao, S., Luo, D., Chen, T., Xie, Y., Huang, R., &amp; Song, H. (2021). Mechanism of Chinese yam for the treatment of aging‐related diseases based on network pharmacology. European Journal of Integrative Medicine, 41, 101254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Zhou, Z., Li, P., Ye, S., Li, W., Li, M., Zhu, L., &amp; Ding, Y. (2023). Investigation of the potential phlorotannins and mechanism of six brown algae in treating type II diabetes mellitus based on biological activity, UPLC‐QE‐MS/MS, and network pharmacology. Foods, 12(16), 3000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, S., Wu, S., Li, W., Chen, X., Dong, X., Tan, G., Zhang, H., Hong, Z., Zhu, Z., &amp; Chai, Y. (2014). Investigation of the therapeutic effectiveness of active components in Sini decoction by a comprehensive GC/LC–MS based metabolomics and network pharmacology approaches. Molecular BioSystems, 10(12), 3310–3321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Ren, B., Chen, M., Wang, Q., Zhang, L., &amp; Yan, G. (2016). NLLSS: Predicting synergistic drug combinations based on semi‐supervised learning. PLoS Computational Biology, 12(7), e1004975.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Xu, X., Lv, J., Huang, J., Lyu, L., &amp; Liu, L. (2023). Potential mechanisms of Perilla folium against COVID‐19: A network pharmacology approach. Journal of Medicinal Food, 26(6), 401–415.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y., Liao, W., Zhu, Z., Chen, J., Yang, Q., Zheng, Y., Zhang, X., Limsila, B., Lu, M., &amp; Fu, S. (2021). Essential oil from the raw and vinegar‐processed Rhizoma Curcumae ameliorate CCl4‐induced liver fibrosis: Integrating network pharmacology and molecular mechanism evaluation. Food &amp; Function, 12(9), 4199–4220.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhury, A., Singh, P. A., Bajwa, N., Dash, S., &amp; Bisht, P. (2023). Pharmacovigilance of herbal medicines: Concerns and future prospects. Journal of Ethnopharmacology, 309, 116383.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, N., Liu, S., Zheng, Z., Pi, Z., Liu, Z., &amp; Song, F. (2022). The chemical profile of Fubai Chrysanthemum (Fubaiju) and its mechanism in preventing cataract based on ultrahigh‐performance liquid chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry and network pharmacology. Journal of Separation Science, 45(13), 2406–2414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D'Angelo, S., Motti, M. L., &amp; Meccariello, R. (2020). ω‐3 and ω‐6 polyunsaturated fatty acids, obesity and cancer. Nutrients, 12(9), 2751.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Pasquale, V., Quiccione, M. S., Tafuri, S., Avallone, L., &amp; Pavone, L. M. (2021). Heparan sulfate proteoglycans in viral infection and treatment: A special focus on SARS‐CoV‐2. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 22(12), 6574.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, J., Du, H., Tan, H., Li, J., Wang, L., Li, L., Zhang, Y., &amp; Liu, Y. (2023). Optimization of protein removal process of Lonicera japonica polysaccharide and its immunomodulatory mechanism in cyclophosphamide‐induced mice by metabolomics and network pharmacology. Food Science &amp; Nutrition, 11(1), 364–378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, M., Li, Z., Yu, X.‐A., Zhang, D., Li, J., Wang, H., He, J., Gao, X.‐M., &amp; Chang, Y.‐X. (2018). A network pharmacology‐integrated metabolomics strategy for clarifying the difference between effective compounds of raw and processed Farfarae flos by ultra high‐performance liquid chromatography‐quadrupole‐time of flight mass spectrometry. Journal of Pharmaceutical and Biomedical Analysis, 156, 349–357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, W., Liang, X., Wang, S., Lee, P., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2020). The underlying mechanism of Paeonia lactiflora pall. in parkinson's disease based on a network pharmacology approach. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 11, 581984.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan, X., Li, J., Cui, J., Wen, H., Xin, X., &amp; Aisa, H. A. (2022). A network pharmacology strategy combined with in vitro experiments to investigate the potential anti‐inflammatory mechanism of Prunus cerasifera Ehrhart. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 46(12), e14396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eid, S., Sas, K. M., Abcouwer, S. F., Feldman, E. L., Gardner, T. W., Pennathur, S., &amp; Fort, P. E. (2019). New insights into the mechanisms of diabetic complications: Role of lipids and lipid metabolism. Diabetologia, 62, 1539–1549.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elasbali, A. M., Al‐Soud, W. A., Mousa Elayyan, A. E., Al‐Oanzi, Z. H., Alhassan, H. H., Mohamed, B. M., Alanazi, H. H., Ashraf, M. S., Moiz, S., &amp; Patel, M. (2023). Integrating network pharmacology approaches for the investigation of multi‐target pharmacological mechanism of 6‐shogaol against cervical cancer. Journal of Biomolecular Structure and Dynamics, 41(23), 14135–14151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El‐Behery, H., Attia, A. F., El‐Fishawy, N., &amp; Torkey, H. (2021). Efficient machine learning model for predicting drug‐target interactions with case study for Covid‐19. Computational Biology and Chemistry, 93, 107536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elkhalifa, A. E. O., Banu, H., Khan, M. I., &amp; Ashraf, S. A. (2023). Integrated network pharmacology, molecular docking, molecular simulation, and in vitro validation revealed the bioactive components in soy‐fermented food products and the underlying mechanistic pathways in lung cancer. Nutrients, 15(18), 3949.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espitia‐Hernández, P., Chavez Gonzalez, M. L., Ascacio‐Valdés, J. A., Dávila‐Medina, D., Flores‐Naveda, A., Silva, T., Ruelas Chacon, X., &amp; Sepúlveda, L. (2022). Sorghum (Sorghum bicolor L.) as a potential source of bioactive substances and their biological properties. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 62(8), 2269–2280.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, J., Wang, L., Wu, T., Yang, C., Gao, L., Cai, H., Liu, J., Fang, S., Chen, Y., &amp; Tan, W. (2017). Network pharmacology‐based study on the mechanism of action for herbal medicines in Alzheimer treatment. Journal of Ethnopharmacology, 196, 281–292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foudah, A. I., Shakeel, F., Yusufoglu, H. S., Ross, S. A., &amp; Alam, P. (2020). Simultaneous determination of 6‐shogaol and 6‐gingerol in various ginger (Zingiber officinale Roscoe) extracts and commercial formulations using a green RP‐HPTLC‐densitometry method. Foods, 9(8), 1136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, Y., Fang, Y., Gong, S., Xue, T., Wang, P., She, L., &amp; Huang, J. (2022). Deep learning‐based network pharmacology for exploring the mechanism of licorice for the treatment of COVID‐19 (preprint). Scientific Reports, 13(1), 5844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallo, M., Ferrara, L., Calogero, A., Montesano, D., &amp; Naviglio, D. (2020). Relationships between food and diseases: What to know to ensure food safety. Food Research International, 137, 109414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galvão, I., Sugimoto, M. A., Vago, J. P., Machado, M. G., &amp; Sousa, L. P. (2018). Mediators of inflammation. Immunopharmacology and Inflammation, 3–32. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-77658-3_1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gangadharan, A., Choi, S. E., Hassan, A., Ayoub, N. M., Durante, G., Balwani, S., Kim, Y. H., Pecora, A., Goy, A., &amp; Suh, K. S. (2017). Protein calorie malnutrition, nutritional intervention and personalized cancer care. Oncotarget, 8(14), 24009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, X., Zhang, Y., Li, T., Li, J., Su, Y., Wang, H., Yan, Z., &amp; Qin, K. (2023). Uncovering the molecular mechanisms of Fructus Choerospondiatis against coronary heart disease using network pharmacology analysis and experimental pharmacology. Analytical Biochemistry, 675, 115214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ge, C., &amp; He, Y. (2020). In silico prediction of molecular targets of astragaloside IV for alleviation of COVID‐19 hyperinflammation by systems network pharmacology and bioinformatic gene expression analysis. Frontiers in pharmacology, 11, 556984.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geng, Z., Guo, M., Zhou, Q., &amp; Pan, L. (2022). The mechanism of crocetin targeting cardiovascular disease based on network pharmacology constrained by spectral experiments. Chemistry &amp; Biodiversity, 19(11), e202200685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghallab, D. S., Shawky, E., Ghareeb, D. A., Abdulmalek, S. A., El‐Din, S. M. M., Mohyeldin, M. M., &amp; Ibrahim, R. S. (2022). Exploring the anti‐inflammatory bioactive metabolites of some marine algae through integration of metabolomics, network pharmacology and molecular docking analyses. Food Bioscience, 50, 102091.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gheda, S., Naby, M. A., Mohamed, T., Pereira, L., &amp; Khamis, A. (2021). Antidiabetic and antioxidant activity of phlorotannins extracted from the brown seaweed Cystoseira compressa in streptozotocin‐induced diabetic rats. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 28, 22886–22901.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giri, B., Dey, S., Das, T., Sarkar, M., Banerjee, J., &amp; Dash, S. K. (2018). Chronic hyperglycemia mediated physiological alteration and metabolic distortion leads to organ dysfunction, infection, cancer progression and other pathophysiological consequences: An update on glucose toxicity. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy, 107, 306–328.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong, Y., Chen, K., Yu, S.‐Q., Liu, H.‐R., &amp; Qi, M.‐Y. (2012). Protective effect of terpenes from Fructus Corni on the cardiomyopathy in alloxan‐induced diabetic mice. Zhongguo Ying Yong Sheng Li Xue Za Zhi = Zhongguo Yingyong Shenglixue Zazhi = Chinese Journal of Applied Physiology, 28(4), 378–380.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González, D., Hincapié, S., Londoño‐Londoño, J., &amp; Jiménez‐Cartagena, C. (2017). The profile of bioactive substances in ten vegetable and fruit by‐products from a food supply chain in Colombia. Sustainable Production and Consumption, 9, 37–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granato, D., Barba, F. J., Bursać Kovačević, D., Lorenzo, J. M., Cruz, A. G., &amp; Putnik, P. (2020). Functional foods: Product development, technological trends, efficacy testing, and safety. Annual Review of Food Science and Technology, 11, 93–118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gudalwar, B. R., Nimbalwar, M. G., Panchale, W. A., Wadekar, A. B., Manwar, J. V., &amp; Bakal, R. L. (2021). Allium sativum, a potential phytopharmacological source of natural medicine for better health. GSC Advanced Research and Reviews, 6(3), 220–232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guimarães, V. H. D., Lelis, D. d. F., Oliveira, L. P., Borém, L. M. A., Guimarães, F. A. D., Farias, L. C., de Paula, A. M. B., Guimarães, A. L. S., &amp; Santos, S. H. S. (2023). Comparative study of dietary fat: Lard and sugar as a better obesity and metabolic syndrome mice model. Archives of Physiology and Biochemistry, 129(2), 449–459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulcin, İ. (2020). Antioxidants and antioxidant methods: An updated overview. Archives of Toxicology, 94(3), 651–715.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gwon, S. Y., Ahn, J. Y., Kim, T. W., &amp; Ha, T. Y. (2012). Zanthoxylum piperitum DC ethanol extract suppresses fat accumulation in adipocytes and high fat diet‐induced obese mice by regulating adipogenesis. Journal of Nutritional Science and Vitaminology, 58(6), 393–401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamdi, Y., Abdeljaoued‐Tej, I., Zatchi, A. A., Abdelhak, S., Boubaker, S., Brown, J. S., &amp; Benkahla, A. (2021). Cancer in Africa: The untold story. Frontiers in Oncology, 11, 650117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higuera‐Ciapara, I., Felix‐Valenzuela, L., &amp; Goycoolea, F. (2006). Astaxanthin: A review of its chemistry and applications. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 46(2), 185–196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoang, S. H., Dao, H., &amp; Lam, E. M. (2023). A network pharmacology approach to elucidate the anti‐inflammatory effects of ellagic acid. Journal of Biomolecular Structure and Dynamics, 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1080/07391102.2023.2240417</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins, A. L. (2007). Network pharmacology. Nature Biotechnology, 25(10), 1110–1111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins, A. L. (2008). Network pharmacology: The next paradigm in drug discovery. Nature Chemical Biology, 4(11), 682–690.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Y., Liu, L., Wang, Z., Jiang, C. P., Zhu, Z., Li, H., Zeng, Q., Xue, Y., Wu, Y., &amp; Wang, Y. (2022). Network pharmacology, molecular docking and in vivo and in vitro experiments to explore the molecular mechanism of licorice green tea beverage to scavenge oxygen free radicals. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 46(10), e14315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Y., Liu, T., Zheng, G., Zhou, L., Ma, K., Xiong, X., Zheng, C., Li, J., Zhu, Y., &amp; Bian, W. (2023). Mechanism exploration of 6‐gingerol in the treatment of atherosclerosis based on network pharmacology, molecular docking and experimental validation. Phytomedicine, 115, 154835.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim, R. S., &amp; El‐Banna, A. A. (2021). Network pharmacology‐based analysis for unraveling potential cancer‐related molecular targets of Egyptian propolis phytoconstituents accompanied with molecular docking and in vitro studies. RSC Advances, 11(19), 11610–11626.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jang, S., Chapa‐Dubocq, X. R., Parodi‐Rullán, R. M., Fossati, S., &amp; Javadov, S. (2022). Beta‐amyloid instigates dysfunction of mitochondria in cardiac cells. Cells, 11(3), 373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jensen, K., Ni, Y., Panagiotou, G., &amp; Kouskoumvekaki, I. (2015). Developing a molecular roadmap of drug‐food interactions. PLOS Computational Biology, 11(2), e1004048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, L., Lu, J., Qin, Y., Jiang, W., &amp; Wang, Y. (2020). Antitumor effect of guava leaves on lung cancer: A network pharmacology study. Arabian Journal of Chemistry, 13(11), 7773–7797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, S., Huang, C., Wang, S., Huang, B., Wu, D., Zheng, G., &amp; Cai, Y. (2022). Network pharmacology‐based strategy for predicting therapy targets of Citri Reticulatae Pericarpium on myocardial hypertrophy. BioMed Research International, 2022, 4293265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiashuo, W., Zhang, F., Zhuangzhuang, L., Weiyi, J., &amp; Yue, S. (2022). Integration strategy of network pharmacology in traditional Chinese medicine: A narrative review. Journal of Traditional Chinese Medicine, 42(3), 479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiran, S., Rohini, P., &amp; Bhagyasree, P. (2017). Flavonoid: A review on Naringenin. Journal of Pharmacognosy and Phytochemistry, 6(5), 2778–2783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kong, F., Li, Y., Zhang, Y., Zeng, Q., &amp; Guo, X. (2022). Elucidation of the potential antioxidant compound and mechanism of mung bean using network pharmacology and in vitro anti‐oxidative activity. Frontiers in Sustainable Food Systems, 6, 1000916.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovačević, D. B., Maras, M., Barba, F. J., Granato, D., Roohinejad, S., Mallikarjunan, K., Montesano, D., Lorenzo, J. M., &amp; Putnik, P. (2018). Innovative technologies for the recovery of phytochemicals from Stevia rebaudiana bertoni leaves: A review. Food Chemistry, 268, 513–521.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, D., Liu, L., Yang, S., Xing, Y., Pan, L., Zhao, R., Zhao, Y., Huang, G., &amp; Wu, M. (2021). Exploring the therapeutic mechanisms of huzhang–shanzha herb pair against coronary heart disease by network pharmacology and molecular docking. Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 2021, 5569666.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Gao, L., Shao, H., Li, B., Zhang, C., Sheng, H., &amp; Zhu, L. (2022). Elucidation of active ingredients and mechanism of action of hawthorn in the prevention and treatment of atherosclerosis. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 46(12), e14457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Zhao, L., Zhang, B., Jiang, Y., Wang, X., Guo, Y., Liu, H., Li, S., &amp; Tong, X. (2014). A network pharmacology approach to determine active compounds and action mechanisms of ge‐gen‐qin‐lian decoction for treatment of type 2 diabetes. Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 2014, 495840.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Zhang, Y., Liu, S., Li, W., Sun, Y., Cao, H., Wang, S., &amp; Meng, J. (2023). A network pharmacology integrated pharmacokinetics strategy to investigate the pharmacological mechanism of absorbed components from crude and processed Zingiberis Rhizoma on deficiency‐cold and hemorrhagic syndrome. Journal of Ethnopharmacology, 301, 115754.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, L., Liu, Y., Yu, H., Li, Z., Lin, H., Wu, F., Tan, L., Wang, C., Li, P., &amp; Liu, J. (2022). Comprehensive phytochemicals analysis and anti‐myocardial ischemia activity of total saponins of American ginseng berry. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 46(2), e14042.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Q., Hong, X., Zheng, X., Xu, Y., Lai, X., Teng, C., Wu, W., Huang, J., &amp; Liu, Z. (2022). Characterization of key aroma compounds and core functional microorganisms in different aroma types of Liupao tea. Food Research International, 152, 110925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, R., Guo, C., Li, Y., Liang, X., Yang, L., &amp; Huang, W. (2020). Therapeutic target and molecular mechanism of vitamin C‐treated pneumonia: A systematic study of network pharmacology. Food &amp; Function, 11(5), 4765–4772.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, S., Fan, T. P., Jia, W., Lu, A., &amp; Zhang, W. (2014). Network pharmacology in traditional Chinese medicine. Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: EcaM, 2014, 138460.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, S., Wang, Y., Li, C., Yang, N., Yu, H., Zhou, W., Chen, S., Yang, S., &amp; Li, Y. (2021). Study on hepatotoxicity of Rhubarb based on metabolomics and network pharmacology. Drug Design, Development and Therapy, 15, 1883–1902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, S., Wang, Z., Zhou, Z., Gao, Z., Liu, Y., Li, J., Gao, X., Liu, J., Liu, H., &amp; Xu, Q. (2023). Molecular mechanism of the role of apigenin in the treatment of hyperlipidemia: A network pharmacology approach. Chemistry &amp; Biodiversity, 20(2), e202200308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, T., Wang, L., Wu, L., Xie, Y., Chang, M., Wang, D., Yi, L., Zhu, X., &amp; Mi, M. (2023). Integrated metabolomics and network pharmacology investigation of cardioprotective effects of myricetin after 1‐week high‐intensity exercise. Nutrients, 15(6), 1336.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Guo, X., Sha, M., Gao, W., &amp; Li, X. (2022). Combining network pharmacology with chromatographic fingerprinting and multicomponent quantitative analysis for the quality evaluation of Astragali Radix. Biomedical Chromatography, 36(4), e5319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Tang, L., Lin, Y. F., &amp; Xie, G. F. (2018). Role of vitamin C in wound healing after dental implant surgery in patients treated with bone grafts and patients with chronic periodontitis. Clinical Implant Dentistry and Related Research, 20(5), 793–798.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Yang, M., Lin, H., Yan, W., Deng, G., Ye, H., Shi, H., Wu, C., Ma, G., &amp; Xu, S. (2022). Limonin alleviates non‐alcoholic fatty liver disease by reducing lipid accumulation, suppressing inflammation and oxidative stress. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 12, 801730.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, B., Zhang, X.‐X., &amp; Gu, N. (2020). Virtual screening and network pharmacology‐based synergistic mechanism identification of multiple components contained in Guanxin V against coronary artery disease. BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies, 20(1), 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao, F., Yousif, M., Huang, R., Qiao, Y., &amp; Hu, Y. (2023). Network pharmacology‐and molecular docking‐based analyses of the antihypertensive mechanism of Ilex kudingcha. Frontiers in Endocrinology, 14, 1216086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, C.‐Y., Lee, J.‐Y., Huang, S.‐H., Hsu, Y.‐C., Hsu, N.‐Y., &amp; Yang, J.‐M. (2020). FooDisNET: A database of food‐compound‐protein‐disease associations. In 2020 IEEE 20th International Conference on Bioinformatics and Bioengineering (BIBE) (pp. 190–195). IEEE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liss, M. A., Dursun, F., Hackman, G. L., Gadallah, M. I., Saha, A., Friedman, C. A., Rathore, A. S., Chandra, P., White, J. R., Tiziani, S., &amp; DiGiovanni, J. (2024). Phase 1 clinical trial evaluating safety, bioavailability, and gut microbiome with a combination of curcumin and ursolic acid in lipid enhanced capsules. Journal of Traditional and Complementary Medicine, 00, 00–00. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtcme.2024.03.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, H., Zhang, H., Nie, J., Yu, Y., Li, Q., Lv, C., &amp; Lu, J. (2023). Systematic analysis of the material basis and mechanism of total saponins of mountain cultivated ginseng against doxorubicin‐induced cardiotoxicity based on integrating network pharmacology and in vivo substance profiling. Phytochemical Analysis, 34(7), 755–771.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, L., Jiao, Y., Yang, M., Wu, L., Long, G., &amp; Hu, W. (2023). Network pharmacology, molecular docking and molecular dynamics to explore the potential immunomodulatory mechanisms of deer antler. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 24(12), 10370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Q., Nan, Y., Yang, Y., Li, X., Jiang, W., Jiao, T., Li, J., Jia, X., Ye, M., Niu, Y., &amp; Yuan, L. (2023). Exploring the role of Lycium barbarum polysaccharide in corneal injury repair and investigating the relevant mechanisms through in vivo and in vitro experiments. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 29(1), 49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, X., Wu, J., Zhang, D., Wang, K., Duan, X., Meng, Z., &amp; Zhang, X. (2018). Network pharmacology‐based approach to investigate the mechanisms of Hedyotis diffusa willd. In the treatment of gastric cancer. Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 2018(1), 7802639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Z., Niu, X., &amp; Wang, J. (2022). Naringenin as a natural immunomodulator against T cell‐mediated autoimmune diseases: Literature review and network‐based pharmacology study. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 63(32), 11026–11043.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long, S., Ji, S., Xue, P., Xie, H., Ma, Y., &amp; Zhu, S. (2022). Network pharmacology and molecular docking analysis reveal insights into the molecular mechanism of shiliao decoction in the treatment of cancer‐associated malnutrition. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, 985991.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, C., Wang, L., Wu, Y., Liu, M., Chen, B., Lu, Y., Zhang, Y., Fu, C., &amp; Liu, X. (2023). Protective effect and possible mechanisms of geniposide for ischemia‐reperfusion injury: A systematic review with meta‐analysis and network pharmacology of preclinical evidence. Heliyon, 9, e20114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv, L., Wang, X., &amp; Wu, H. (2023). Assessment of palmitic acid toxicity to animal hearts and other major organs based on acute toxicity, network pharmacology, and molecular docking. Computers in Biology and Medicine, 158, 106899.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, J., Li, Y., Ji, X., Wang, A., Lan, Y., &amp; Ma, L. (2023). Integrating network pharmacology and experimental verification to explore the mechanisms of salidroside against myocardial fibrosis. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, 677, 38–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, X., Meng, Y., Wang, P., Tang, Z., Wang, H., &amp; Xie, T. (2020). Bioinformatics‐assisted, integrated omics studies on medicinal plants. Briefings in Bioinformatics, 21(6), 1857–1874.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansour, S., Moustafa, M., Saad, B., Hamed, R., &amp; Moustafa, A.‐R. (2021). Impact of diet on human gut microbiome and disease risk. New Microbes and New Infections, 41, 100845.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcelino, G., Machate, D. J., Freitas, K. d. C., Hiane, P. A., Maldonade, I. R., Pott, A., Asato, M. A., Candido, C. J., &amp; Guimarães, R. d. C. A. (2020). β‐Carotene: Preventive role for type 2 diabetes mellitus and obesity: A review. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 25(24), 5803.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcillo‐Parra, V., Anaguano, M., Molina, M., Tupuna‐Yerovi, D. S., &amp; Ruales, J. (2021). Characterization and quantification of bioactive compounds and antioxidant activity in three different varieties of mango (Mangifera indica L.) peel from the Ecuadorian region using HPLC‐UV/VIS and UPLC‐PDA. NFS Journal, 23, 1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez‐García, M., &amp; Hernández‐Lemus, E. (2022). Data integration challenges for machine learning in precision medicine. Frontiers in Medicine, 8, 784455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martiz, R. M., Patil, S. M., Abdulaziz, M., Babalghith, A., Al‐Areefi, M., Al‐Ghorbani, M., Mallappa Kumar, J., Prasad, A., Mysore Nagalingaswamy, N. P., &amp; Ramu, R. (2022). Defining the role of isoeugenol from Ocimum tenuiflorum against diabetes mellitus‐linked Alzheimer's disease through network pharmacology and computational methods. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 27(8), 2398.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michailidis, P. A., &amp; Krokida, M. K. (2014). Drying and dehydration processes in food preservation and processing. Conventional and Advanced Food Processing Technologies, 1–32. https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118406281.ch1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mills, K. T., Stefanescu, A., &amp; He, J. (2020). The global epidemiology of hypertension. Nature Reviews Nephrology, 16(4), 223–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra, U. N., Jena, D., Sahu, C., Devi, R., Kumar, R., Jena, R., Irondi, E. A., Rout, S., Tiwari, R. K., &amp; Lal, M. K. (2022). Nutrigenomics: An inimitable interaction amid genomics, nutrition and health. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 82, 103196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mondal, S., Soumya, N. P. P., Mini, S., &amp; Sivan, S. K. (2021). Bioactive compounds in functional food and their role as therapeutics. Bioactive Compounds in Health and Disease, 4(3), 24–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mu, C., Sheng, Y., Wang, Q., Amin, A., Li, X., &amp; Xie, Y. (2021). Potential compound from herbal food of Rhizoma Polygonati for treatment of COVID‐19 analyzed by network pharmacology: Viral and cancer signaling mechanisms. Journal of Functional Foods, 77, 104149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathan, C. (2002). Points of control in inflammation. Nature, 420(6917), 846–852.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu, B., Xie, X., Xiong, X., &amp; Jiang, J. (2022). Network pharmacology‐based analysis of the anti‐hyperglycemic active ingredients of roselle and experimental validation. Computers in Biology and Medicine, 141, 104636.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu, X., Zhang, J., Ni, J., Wang, R., Zhang, W., Sun, S., Peng, Y., Bai, M., &amp; Zhang, Z. (2018). Network pharmacology‐based identification of major component of Angelica sinensis and its action mechanism for the treatment of acute myocardial infarction. Bioscience Reports, 38(6), BSR20180519.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noor, F., Asif, M., Ashfaq, U. A., Qasim, M., &amp; Tahir ul Qamar, M. (2023). Machine learning for synergistic network pharmacology: A comprehensive overview. Briefings in Bioinformatics, 24(3), bbad120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh, K. K., Adnan, M., &amp; Cho, D. H. (2021). A network pharmacology analysis on drug‐like compounds from Ganoderma lucidum for alleviation of atherosclerosis. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 45(9), e13906.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh, K.‐K., Gupta, H., Min, B.‐H., Ganesan, R., Sharma, S. P., Won, S.‐M., Jeong, J.‐J., Lee, S.‐B., Cha, M.‐G., &amp; Kwon, G.‐H. (2022). Elucidation of prebiotics, probiotics, postbiotics, and target from gut microbiota to alleviate obesity via network pharmacology study. Cells, 11(18), 2903.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan, W., Li, W., Wu, H., Xie, X., Xie, M., Nie, Q., Liu, Z., &amp; Cai, S. (2023). Aging‐accelerated mouse prone 8 (SAMP8) mice experiment and network pharmacological analysis of aged liupao tea aqueous extract in delaying the decline changes of the body. Antioxidants, 12(3), 685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pei, H., He, Z., Chen, W., Zhao, Y., Li, J., Wang, R., Zong, Y., &amp; Du, R. (2023). Network pharmacology and molecular docking analysis on the mechanism of Cordyceps militaris polysaccharide regulating immunity through TLR4/TNF‐α pathways. Journal of Biochemical and Molecular Toxicology, 37(6), e23345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierantonelli, I., &amp; Svegliati‐Baroni, G. (2019). Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: Basic pathogenetic mechanisms in the progression from NAFLD to NASH. Transplantation, 103(1), e1–e13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pizzino, G., Irrera, N., Cucinotta, M., Pallio, G., Mannino, F., Arcoraci, V., Squadrito, F., Altavilla, D., &amp; Bitto, A. (2017). Oxidative stress: Harms and benefits for human health. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity, 2017, 8416763.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plumb, J., Pigat, S., Bompola, F., Cushen, M., Pinchen, H., Nørby, E., Astley, S., Lyons, J., Kiely, M., &amp; Finglas, P. (2017). Ebasis (bioactive substances in food information systems) and bioactive intakes: Major updates of the bioactive compound composition and beneficial bioeffects database and the development of a probabilistic model to assess intakes in Europe. Nutrients, 9(4), 320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poljsak, B., Kovač, V., &amp; Milisav, I. (2021). Antioxidants, food processing and health. Antioxidants, 10(3), 433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poornima, P., Kumar, J. D., Zhao, Q., Blunder, M., &amp; Efferth, T. (2016). Network pharmacology of cancer: From understanding of complex interactomes to the design of multi‐target specific therapeutics from nature. Pharmacological Research, 111, 290–302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman, M. M., Vadrev, S. M., Magana‐Mora, A., Levman, J., &amp; Soufan, O. (2022). A novel graph mining approach to predict and evaluate food‐drug interactions. Scientific Reports, 12(1), 1061.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rarison, R. H., Truong, V.‐L., Yoon, B.‐H., Park, J.‐W., &amp; Jeong, W.‐S. (2023). Antioxidant and anti‐inflammatory mechanisms of lipophilic fractions from Polyscias fruticosa leaves based on network pharmacology, in silico, and in vitro approaches. Foods, 12(19), 3643.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reza, A. A., Rashid, M. M., Islam, M. S., Hossen, M. A., Ahmed, A. A., Haque, M. A., Nasrin, M. S., Uddin, M. N., Khan, J., &amp; Rahman, M. A. (2023). Polyphenolics of purple devil fruits potentiate anti‐inflammatory action by regulating the expression of inflammatory cytokines and apoptotic signaling molecules evident in extensive and combined experimental models. Journal of Functional Foods, 106, 105610.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubinic, I., Kurtov, M., Rubinic, I., Likic, R., Dargan, P. I., &amp; Wood, D. M. (2023). Artificial intelligence in clinical pharmacology: A case study and scoping review of large language models and bioweapon potential. British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology, 90, 620–628.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo, G. L., Siani, A., Fogliano, V., Geleijnse, J. M., Giacco, R., Giampaoli, S., Iacoviello, L., Kromhout, D., Lionetti, L., &amp; Naska, A. (2021). The mediterranean diet from past to future: Key concepts from the second “Ancel Keys” international seminar. Nutrition, Metabolism and Cardiovascular Diseases, 31(3), 717–732.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saeedi, P., Petersohn, I., Salpea, P., Malanda, B., Karuranga, S., Unwin, N., Colagiuri, S., Guariguata, L., Motala, A. A., &amp; Ogurtsova, K. (2019). Global and regional diabetes prevalence estimates for 2019 and projections for 2030 and 2045: Results from the International Diabetes Federation Diabetes Atlas. Diabetes Research and Clinical Practice, 157, 107843.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarkar, T., Bharadwaj, K. K., Salauddin, M., Pati, S., &amp; Chakraborty, R. (2021). Phytochemical characterization, antioxidant, anti‐inflammatory, anti‐diabetic properties, molecular docking, pharmacokinetic profiling, and network pharmacology analysis of the major phytoconstituents of raw and differently dried Mangifera indica (Himsagar cultivar): An in vitro and in silico investigations. Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology, 194, 950–987.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schelbert, E. B., Piehler, K. M., Zareba, K. M., Moon, J. C., Ugander, M., Messroghli, D. R., Valeti, U. S., Chang, C. C. H., Shroff, S. G., &amp; Diez, J. (2015). Myocardial fibrosis quantified by extracellular volume is associated with subsequent hospitalization for heart failure, death, or both across the spectrum of ejection fraction and heart failure stage. Journal of the American Heart Association, 4(12), e002613.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah, B. R., Li, B., Al Sabbah, H., Xu, W., &amp; Mráz, J. (2020). Effects of prebiotic dietary fibers and probiotics on human health: With special focus on recent advancement in their encapsulated formulations. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 102, 178–192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shang, X., Dai, L., He, J., Yang, X., Wang, Y., Li, B., Zhang, J., Pan, H., &amp; Gulnaz, I. (2022). A high‐value‐added application of the stems of Rheum palmatum L. as a healthy food: The nutritional value, chemical composition, and anti‐inflammatory and antioxidant activities. Food &amp; Function, 13(9), 4901–4913.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao, L., &amp; Zhang, B. (2013). Traditional Chinese medicine network pharmacology: Theory, methodology and application. Chinese Journal of Natural Medicines, 11(2), 110–120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, R., Jadhav, M., Choudhary, N., Kumar, A., Rauf, A., Gundamaraju, R., AlAsmari, A. F., Ali, N., Singla, R. K., &amp; Sharma, R. (2022). Deciphering the impact and mechanism of Trikatu, a spices‐based formulation on alcoholic liver disease employing network pharmacology analysis and in vivo validation. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, 1063118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, P., Chen, J., Ge, W., Liu, Z., Han, N., &amp; Yin, J. (2023). Antichilblain components in eggplant based on network pharmacology and biological evaluation. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 71(30), 11442–11453.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, X., Capanoglu, E., Simal‐Gandara, J., Chen, F., &amp; Xiao, J. (2022). Different food processing technologies: A general background. In Retention of bioactives in food processing (pp. 37–89). Springer International Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su, M., Guo, C., Liu, M., Liang, X., &amp; Yang, B. (2019). Therapeutic targets of vitamin C on liver injury and associated biological mechanisms: A study of network pharmacology. International Immunopharmacology, 66, 383–387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, X., Ji, Y., Tahir, A., &amp; Kang, J. (2020). Network pharmacology combined with transcriptional analysis to unveil the biological basis of astaxanthin in reducing the oxidative stress induced by diabetes mellitus. Diabetes, Metabolic Syndrome and Obesity, 13, 4281–4295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Y., Wang, Z., Dai, J., Sha, R., Mao, J., Mao, Y., &amp; Cui, Y. (2023). Improved antioxidant capacity of Akebia trifoliata fruit inoculated fermentation by Plantilactobacillus plantarum, mechanism of anti‐oxidative stress through network pharmacology, molecular docking and experiment validation by HepG2 cells. Fermentation, 9(5), 432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, L., Gao, J., Li, X., Cao, X., &amp; Zhou, B. (2022). Molecular mechanisms of luteolin against atopic dermatitis based on network pharmacology and in vivo experimental validation. Drug Design Development and Therapy, 16, 4205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, L., Zhang, S., Zhang, M., Wang, P. J., Liang, G. Y., &amp; Gao, X. L. (2022). Analysis of protective effects of Rosa Roxburghii Tratt fruit polyphenols on lipopolysaccharide‐induced acute lung injury through network pharmacology and metabolomics. Food Science &amp; Nutrition, 10(12), 4258–4269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakur, K. T., Albanese, E., Giannakopoulos, P., Jette, N., Linde, M., Prince, M. J., Steiner, T. J., &amp; Dua, T. (2016). Neurological disorders. In Disease control priorities (Vol. 4, pp. 87–107). The World Bank.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian, D., Yang, Y., Yu, M., Han, Z.‐Z., Wei, M., Zhang, H.‐W., Jia, H.‐M., &amp; Zou, Z.‐M. (2020). Anti‐inflammatory chemical constituents of Flos Chrysanthemi Indici determined by UPLC‐MS/MS integrated with network pharmacology. Food &amp; Function, 11(7), 6340–6351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timmis, A., Vardas, P., Townsend, N., Torbica, A., Katus, H., De Smedt, D., Gale, C. P., Maggioni, A. P., Petersen, S. E., &amp; Huculeci, R. (2022). European society of cardiology: Cardiovascular disease statistics 2021. European Heart Journal, 43(8), 716–799.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topolska, K., Florkiewicz, A., &amp; Filipiak‐Florkiewicz, A. (2021). Functional food—Consumer motivations and expectations. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 18(10), 5327.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsoupras, A., Zabetakis, I., &amp; Lordan, R. (2023). Functional foods: Growth, evolution, legislation, and future perspectives. In Functional foods and their implications for health promotion (pp. 367–377). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ugwor, E. I., James, A. S., Amuzat, A. I., Ezenandu, E. O., Ugbaja, V. C., &amp; Ugbaja, R. N. (2022). Network pharmacology‐based elucidation of bioactive compounds in propolis and putative underlying mechanisms against type‐2 diabetes mellitus. Pharmacological Research‐Modern Chinese Medicine, 5, 100183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan, Y., Xu, L., Liu, Z., Yang, M., Jiang, X., Zhang, Q., &amp; Huang, J. (2019). Utilising network pharmacology to explore the underlying mechanism of Wumei Pill in treating pancreatic neoplasms. BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 19, 1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, C.‐R., Chen, H.‐W., Li, Y., Zhou, M.‐Y., Wong, V. K.‐W., Jiang, Z.‐H., &amp; Zhang, W. (2021). Network pharmacology exploration reveals anti‐apoptosis as a common therapeutic mechanism for non‐alcoholic fatty liver disease treated with blueberry leaf polyphenols. Nutrients, 13(11), 4060.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Liang, Q., Zhang, Y., Liu, F., Sun, Y., Wang, S., Cao, H., &amp; Meng, J. (2021). iTRAQ‐based quantitative proteomics and network pharmacology revealing hemostatic mechanism mediated by Zingiberis Rhizome Carbonisata in deficiency‐cold and Hemorrhagic Syndrome rat models. Chemico‐Biological Interactions, 343, 109465.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Wang, X., Xia, M., Yang, L., Cheng, W., &amp; Song, Q. (2022). Combining network pharmacology with chromatographic fingerprinting and multicomponent quantitative analysis for the quality evaluation of Moutan Cortex. Biomedical Chromatography, 36(10), e5434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, W., Wang, S., Liu, T., Ma, Y., Huang, S., Lei, L., Wen, A., &amp; Ding, Y. (2020). Resveratrol: Multi‐targets mechanism on neurodegenerative diseases based on network pharmacology. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 11, 694.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, W., Yang, L., Hu, M., Yang, Y., Ma, Q., &amp; Chen, J. (2023). Network pharmacology to reveal the molecular mechanisms of rutaceous plant‐derived limonin ameliorating non‐alcoholic steatohepatitis. Critical Reviews™ in Immunology, 43(5), 11–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, W.‐X., Zhang, Y.‐R., Luo, S.‐Y., Zhang, Y.‐S., Zhang, Y., &amp; Tang, C. (2022). Chlorogenic acid, a natural product as potential inhibitor of COVID‐19: Virtual screening experiment based on network pharmacology and molecular docking. Natural Product Research, 36(10), 2580–2584.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X., Li, X., Li, L., Yang, X., Wang, J., Liu, X., Chen, J., Liu, S., Zhang, N., &amp; Li, J. (2022). Hawthorn fruit extract ameliorates H2O2‐induced oxidative damage in neuronal PC12 cells and prolongs the lifespan of Caenorhabditis elegans via the IIS signaling pathway. Food &amp; Function, 13(20), 10680–10694.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Chen, S., Mo, J., Chen, X., Yang, Y., Zhang, K., Chen, Z., &amp; Zhang, C. X. (2022). Investigate the metabolic profile and potential active compounds of Fructus Corni in the treatment of heart failure by applying ultra‐performance liquid chromatography with quadrupole time‐of‐flight mass spectrometry and network pharmacology. Journal of Separation Science, 45(24), 4348–4363.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Li, Y., Ding, Y., Du, X., &amp; Zhu, J. (2024). Identification of quality markers in Schisandra chinensis (Turcz.) Baill. using UPLC‐Q‐extractive orbitrap/MS, chemometric analysis, and network pharmacology. Separations, 11(3), 88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Liang, Z., Shen, F., Zhou, W., Manaer, T., Jiaerken, D., &amp; Nabi, X. (2023). Exploring the immunomodulatory effects and mechanisms of Xinjiang fermented camel milk‐derived bioactive peptides based on network pharmacology and molecular docking. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 13, 1038812.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Yang, S. H., Zhong, K., Jiang, T., Zhang, M., Kwan, H. Y., &amp; Su, T. (2020). Network pharmacology‐based strategy for the investigation of the anti‐obesity effects of an ethanolic extract of Zanthoxylum bungeanum Maxim. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 11, 572387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen, J., Zou, W., Wang, R., Liu, H., Yang, Y., Li, H., Wei, S., Li, R., Cai, H., &amp; Wang, J. (2019). Cardioprotective effects of Aconiti Lateralis Radix Praeparata combined with Zingiberis Rhizoma on doxorubicin‐induced chronic heart failure in rats and potential mechanisms. Journal of Ethnopharmacology, 238, 111880.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen, J.‐X., Li, R.‐S., Wang, J., Hao, J.‐J., Qin, W.‐H., Yang, T., Wang, R.‐L., Wei, S.‐Z., Liu, X.‐Y., &amp; Li, H.‐T. (2020). Therapeutic effects of Aconiti Lateralis Radix Praeparata combined with Zingiberis Rhizoma on doxorubicin‐induced chronic heart failure in rats based on an integrated approach. Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmacology, 72(2), 279–293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, J., Zhao, Y., Wang, X., Kong, L., Johnston, L. J., Lu, L., &amp; Ma, X. (2022). Dietary nutrients shape gut microbes and intestinal mucosa via epigenetic modifications. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 62(3), 783–797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, S., Chen, R., Chen, J., Yang, N., Li, K., Zhang, Z., &amp; Zhang, R. (2023). Study of the anti‐inflammatory mechanism of β‐carotene based on network pharmacology. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 28(22), 7540.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, Y., Wang, Y., Liu, X., Jiang, L., Guli, A., Sailike, J., Sun, X., Abuduwaili, N., Tuoliuhan, H., &amp; Maney, K. (2020). Ziziphora clinopodioides flavonoids based on network pharmacology attenuates atherosclerosis in rats induced by high‐fat emulsion combined with vitamin D3 by down‐regulating VEGF/AKT/NF‐κB signaling pathway. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy, 129, 110399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, Z., Li, W., Liu, G., &amp; Tang, Y. (2018). Network‐based methods for prediction of drug‐target interactions. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 9, 1134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, T., Fang, B., Kang, C., Zhao, Y., Qiang, X., Zhang, X., Wang, Y., Zhong, T., Xiao, J., &amp; Wang, M. (2022). Hepatoprotective mechanism of ginsenoside rg1 against alcoholic liver damage based on gut microbiota and network pharmacology. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity, 2022, 5025237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, T., Xiong, Z., Sun, X., Chen, J., Wang, C., Chen, Y., &amp; Zheng, D. (2023). Metabolomic profiles and health‐promoting functions of Camellia drupifera mature‐seeds were revealed relate to their geographical origins using comparative metabolomic analysis and network pharmacology approach. Food Chemistry, 426, 136619.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiang, W., Suo, T. C., Yu, H., Li, A. P., Zhang, S. Q., Wang, C. H., Zhu, Y., &amp; Li, Z. (2018). A new strategy for choosing “Q‐markers” via network pharmacology, application to the quality control of a Chinese medical preparation. Journal of Food and Drug Analysis, 26(2), 858–868.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, P., Guo, M., Xie, J.‐B., Xiao, M.‐Y., Qi, Y.‐S., Duan, Y., Li, F.‐F., &amp; Piao, X.‐L. (2022). Effects of heat‐processed Gynostemma pentaphyllum on high‐fat diet‐fed mice of obesity and functional analysis on network pharmacology and molecular docking strategy. Journal of Ethnopharmacology, 294, 115335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing, J., Luo, X., Jia, K., Liu, S., Chen, S., Qiao, G., Zhang, C., &amp; Yi, J. (2023). Integrating network pharmacology and experimental verification to explore the pharmacological mechanisms of asparagus against polycystic ovary syndrome. Journal of Ovarian Research, 16(1), 128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, L., Zuo, S.‐M., Liu, M., Wang, T., Li, Z., Yun, Y.‐H., &amp; Zhang, W. (2023). Integrated analysis of metabolomics combined with network pharmacology and molecular docking reveals the effects of processing on metabolites of Dendrobium officinale. Metabolites, 13(8), 886.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, L., Li, H., Yang, M., Zhang, W., Li, M., Xu, Y., Li, J., Kang, J., Zhang, J., &amp; Guo, S. (2020). Exploration in the mechanism of kaempferol for the treatment of gastric cancer based on network pharmacology. BioMed Research International, 2020, 5891016. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/5891016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, L., Wang, H., Song, S., Xu, H., Chen, Y., Tian, S., Zhang, Y., &amp; Zhang, Q. (2022). Systematic understanding of anti‐aging effect of coenzyme Q10 on oocyte through a network pharmacology approach. Frontiers in Endocrinology, 13, 813772.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, L., Xiong, H., Li, X., Li, Y., Zhou, H., Lin, X., Chan, T. F., Li, R., Lai, K. P., &amp; Chen, X. (2022). Network pharmacology and comparative transcriptome reveals biotargets and mechanisms of curcumol treating lung adenocarcinoma patients with COVID‐19. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, 870370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Q., Li, B., Chen, S., Tang, J., Li, Y., Li, Y., Zhang, S., Shi, C., Zhang, Y., &amp; Mou, M. (2021). MMEASE: Online meta‐analysis of metabolomic data by enhanced metabolite annotation, marker selection and enrichment analysis. Journal of Proteomics, 232, 104023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao, Z., Fu, S., Ren, B., Ma, L., &amp; Sun, D. (2022). Based on network pharmacology and gut microbiota analysis to investigate the mechanism of the laxative effect of pterostilbene on loperamide‐induced slow transit constipation in mice. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 13, 913420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yong, C., Zhang, Z., Huang, G., Yang, Y., Zhu, Y., Qian, L., Tian, F., Liu, L., Wu, Q., &amp; Xu, Z. (2021). Exploring the critical components and therapeutic mechanisms of Perilla frutescens L. in the treatment of chronic kidney disease via network pharmacology. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 12, 717744.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, X., Zhang, P., Tang, K., Shen, G., Chen, H., Zhang, Z., Zhao, W., Shang, Q., Zhu, G., &amp; Tan, R. (2021). Network pharmacology integrated with molecular docking explores the mechanisms of naringin against osteoporotic fracture by regulating oxidative stress. Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 2021, 1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan, G., Shi, S., Jia, Q., Shi, J., Shi, S., Zhang, X., Shou, X., Zhu, X., &amp; Hu, Y. (2021). Use of network pharmacology to explore the mechanism of Gegen (Puerariae lobatae Radix) in the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus associated with hyperlipidemia. Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 2021, 1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue, K., Liu, Z., Pi, Z., Li, H., Wang, Y., Song, F., &amp; Liu, Z. (2022). Network pharmacology combined with metabolomics approach to investigate the toxicity mechanism of paclobutrazol. Chemical Research in Toxicology, 35(4), 626–635.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhan, Q., Zhao, J., Liu, L., Wang, B., Hui, J., Lin, Q., Qin, Y., Xue, B., &amp; Xu, F. (2023). Integrated network pharmacology and molecular docking analyses of the mechanisms underlying the antihypertensive effects of lotusine. European Journal of Pharmacology, 945, 175622.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, A., Fang, H., Wang, Y., Yan, G., Sun, H., Zhou, X., Wang, Y., Liu, L., &amp; Wang, X. (2017). Discovery and verification of the potential targets from bioactive molecules by network pharmacology‐based target prediction combined with high‐throughput metabolomics. RSC Advances, 7(81), 51069–51078.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, A., Sun, H., Han, Y., Yan, G., Yuan, Y., Song, G., Yuan, X.‐X., Xie, N., &amp; Wang, X.‐J. (2013). Ultraperformance liquid chromatography–mass spectrometry based comprehensive metabolomics combined with pattern recognition and network analysis methods for characterization of metabolites and metabolic pathways from biological data sets. Analytical Chemistry, 85(15), 7606–7612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, C., Guan, D., Jiang, M., Liang, C., Li, L., Zhao, N., Zha, Q., Zhang, W., Lu, C., &amp; Zhang, G. (2019). Efficacy of leflunomide combined with ligustrazine in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis: Prediction with network pharmacology and validation in a clinical trial. Chinese Medicine, 14(1), 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, F. X., Cui, S. S., Li, M., Tan, X., Qiu, Z. C., &amp; Li, R. M. (2021). Dissection of the potential pharmacological function of neohesperidin dihydrochalcone–a food additive–by in vivo substances profiling and network pharmacology. Food &amp; Function, 12(10), 4325–4336.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Chen, Y., Wang, Z., Zhou, W., Ullah, H., Cao, J., Liu, Y., &amp; Cheng, G. (2023). The protective effect and mechanism of mangiferin on d‐galactose‐induced oxidative stress and cognitive impairment in aging mice by an integrated network pharmacology and experimental validation strategy. Food Frontiers, 4(4), 1927–1945.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, S.‐S., Hou, Y.‐F., Liu, S.‐J., Guo, S., Ho, C.‐T., &amp; Bai, N.‐S. (2022). Exploring active ingredients, beneficial effects, and potential mechanism of Allium tenuissimum L. flower for treating T2DM mice based on network pharmacology and gut microbiota. Nutrients, 14(19), 3980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Bao, X., Zhu, Y., Dai, Z., Shen, Q., &amp; Xue, Y. (2024). Advances in machine learning screening of food bioactive compounds. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 150, 104578.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, J., Yang, J., Tian, S., &amp; Zhang, W. (2019). A survey of web resources and tools for the study of TCM network pharmacology. Quantitative Biology, 7(1), 17–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, L., Zhu, D., Shafik, W., Matinkhah, S. M., Ahmad, Z., Sharif, L., &amp; Craig, A. (2022). Artificial intelligence analysis in cyber domain: A review. International Journal of Distributed Sensor Networks, 18(4), 15501329221084882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, L., Zhou, Y., Yan, T., Gong, Z., Li, Y., Chen, S., Huang, S., &amp; Chi, M. (2022). Quality control of Oleum Cinnamomi assisted by network pharmacology strategy. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 27(19), 6391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, M., Ren, G., Zhang, B., Ma, F., Fan, J., &amp; Qiu, Z. (2022). Screening and identification of a novel antidiabetic peptide from collagen hydrolysates of Chinese giant salamander skin: Network pharmacology, inhibition kinetics and protection of IR‐HepG2 cells. Food &amp; Function, 13(6), 3329–3342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, W., Wang, Y., Lu, A., &amp; Zhang, G. (2016). Systems pharmacology in small molecular drug discovery. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 17(2), 246.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, Y., Wang, C., Kou, J., Wang, M., Rong, X., Pu, X., Xie, X., Han, G., &amp; Pang, X. (2021). Chrysanthemi Flos extract alleviated acetaminophen‐induced rat liver injury via inhibiting oxidative stress and apoptosis based on network pharmacology analysis. Pharmaceutical Biology, 59(1), 1376–1385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, Z., Chen, B., Chen, S., Lin, M., Chen, Y., Jin, S., Chen, W., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2020). Applications of network pharmacology in traditional Chinese medicine research. Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 2020(1), 1646905.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, N., Huang, B., &amp; Jiang, W. (2021). Targets of vitamin C with therapeutic potential for cardiovascular disease and underlying mechanisms: A study of network pharmacology. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 11, 591337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, X., Liu, S., Pei, H., Chen, W., Zong, Y., Zhao, Y., Li, J., Du, R., &amp; He, Z. (2023). Study on dihydromyricetin improving aflatoxin induced liver injury based on network pharmacology and molecular docking. Toxics, 11(9), 760.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>