<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39220534</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2470-1343</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>34</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ACS omega</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ACS Omega</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring Electrochemical Sensing for Fungicide Detection: Utilization of Newly Synthesized Oligomers.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>36622</StartPage><EndPage>36634</EndPage><MedlinePgn>36622-36634</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acsomega.4c04959</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The determination of thiabendazole is crucial for ensuring food safety, environmental protection, and compliance with regulatory standards. Accurate detection helps prevent harmful exposure, ensuring the safety of agricultural products and safeguarding public health. Therefore, this study investigates the electrochemical sensing capabilities of newly synthesized oligo 3-amino-5-mercapto-1,2,4-triazole (oligo AMTa) using hydrogen tetrachloroaurate (III) (HAuCl<sub>4</sub>) as an oxidizing agent at room temperature for thiabendazole (TBZ) detection, employing a simple electrode fabrication process. The prepared oligo AMTa was thoroughly characterized using UV-visible spectroscopy, scanning electron microscopy (SEM), Energy Dispersive X-ray Analysis (EDAX), X-ray diffraction (XRD), X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS), high-resolution mass spectroscopy (HR-MS), and Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy (FT-IR) to confirm its oligomerization structure and properties. The IR spectrum of oligo AMTa reveals a new peak at 1449 cm<sup>-1</sup>, indicating the conversion of -NH<sub>2</sub> groups to -N=N- groups during oligomerization, unlike AMTa. Additionally, the disappearance of the -SH group peak at 2615 cm<sup>-1</sup> in oligo AMTa suggests an S-S linkage involvement in the oligomerization process. In the oligo AMTa XPS spectrum, the presence of C=N is displayed by a small peak at 287.3 eV, and oligomerization via -NH and N=N is confirmed by the lack of a 284.0 eV peak for C-C or C=C. Gold nanoparticle formation is not demonstrated by the 84.8 eV peak, which implies that the gold atom is not in the Au<sup>0</sup> state. The HR-MS spectrum of oligo AMTa shows a peak at <i>m</i>/<i>z</i> 564.08, indicating a chain of five monomers, and another peak at <i>m</i>/<i>z</i> 435.03, confirming the presence of a tetrameric form of AMTa. After that, the GC electrode was directly linked to the oligo AMTa by the potentiodynamic method. SEM, electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS), and cyclic voltammetry (CV) were all employed to confirm the fabrication of oligo AMTa. The SEM image illustrates the formation of a particlelike structure with a uniform size of the oligomer after cycling in 0.1 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. After electrocycling, the size of the oligomer was reduced from 2.6 μm to 30 nm. The oligo AMTa-modified electrode possesses the highest electroactive surface area and electrical conductivity due to several key factors. First, the presence of amino (-NH<sub>2</sub>) and thiol (-SH) functional groups in AMTa enhances the surface coverage and density of electroactive sites, increasing the electroactive surface area. Additionally, the conjugated structure of AMTa facilitates efficient electron transfer, resulting in enhanced electrical conductivity compared to unmodified electrodes. Eventually, the electrochemical oxidation of TBZ occurred using the fabricated electrodes. The GC/oligo AMTa electrode exhibited a four-fold increase in oxidation current for TBZ compared to unmodified GC electrodes. This enhancement is due to the improved surface properties from the oligo AMTa modification, which significantly boosts TBZ adsorption through strong interactions like hydrogen bonding and π-π stacking. These interactions, along with the increased surface area and catalytic properties, facilitate effective electron transfer, resulting in a higher oxidation current. As an outcome, the film was employed to determine the sensitivity level of TBZ, and a LOD of 1.8 × 10<sup>-11</sup> M (S/N = 3) was found. The straightforward method's practical utility was proven by measuring TBZ in tap water, water spinach, and pear juice samples. The comprehensive characterization of oligo AMTa provided insights into its interaction mechanisms with thiabendazole, contributing to the development of a reliable, cost-effective, and efficient sensor.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mangala Gowri</LastName><ForeName>Veeramani</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10900, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, The Gandhigram Rural Institute, Gandhigram, 624 302 Dindigul, Tamilnadu, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chanpuang</LastName><ForeName>Pontagarn</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10900, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bunrueang</LastName><ForeName>Warit</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10900, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Imboon</LastName><ForeName>Tanawat</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10900, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khamboonrueang</LastName><ForeName>Dusadee</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Science and Technology, Nakhon Sawan Rajabaht University, Mueang District, Nakhon Sawan 60000, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Issro</LastName><ForeName>Chaisak</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Burapha University, Chonburi 10131, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shima</LastName><ForeName>Mutsuhiro</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Materials Science and Processing, Graduate School of Natural Science and Technology, Gifu University, Yanagida, Gifu 501-1193, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thongmee</LastName><ForeName>Sirikanjana</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8294-9997</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10900, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ACS Omega</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101691658</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2470-1343</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39220534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11359631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsomega.4c04959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Namsheer K.; Rout C. S. Conducting Polymers: A Comprehensive Review on Recent Advances in Synthesis Properties and Applications. RSC Adv. 2021, 11, 5659.10.1039/D0RA07800J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0RA07800J</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9133880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35686160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding H.; Hussein A. M.; Ahmad I.; Latef R.; Abbas J. K.; Ali A. T. A.; Saeed S. M.; Abdulwahid A. S.; Ramadan M. F.; Rasool H. A.; Elawady A. Conducting Polymers in Industry: A Comprehensive Review on The Characterization, Synthesis and Application. Alex. Eng. J. 2024, 88, 253.10.1016/j.aej.2024.01.029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aej.2024.01.029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poddar A. K.; Patel S. S.; Patel H. D. Synthesis, Characterization and Applications of Conductive Polymers: A Brief Review. Polym. Adv. Technol. 2021, 32, 4616.10.1002/pat.5483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pat.5483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar D.; Sharma R. C. Advances in Conductive Polymers. Eur. Polym. J. 1998, 34, 1053.10.1016/S0014-3057(97)00204-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0014-3057(97)00204-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajika S.; Beitollahi H.; Nejadc F. G.; Shoaiec I. S.; Khalilzadeh M. A.; Asle M. S.; Le Q. V.; Zhangg K.; Jang H. W.; Shokouhimehr M. Recent Developments in Conducting Polymers: Applications for Electrochemistry. RSC Adv. 2020, 10, 37834.10.1039/D0RA06160C.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0RA06160C</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9057190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35515168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattam L. B.; Bijoy A.; Thadathil D. A.; George L.; Varghese A. Conducting Polymers: A Versatile Material for Biomedical Applications. ChemistrySelect 2022, 7, e20220176510.1002/slct.202201765.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/slct.202201765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin S.; Wu Q.; Lu Y. Recent Progress of The Application of Electropolymerization in Batteries and Supercapacitors: Specific Design of Functions in Electrodes. ChemElectroChem. 2024, 11, e20230077610.1002/celc.202300776.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/celc.202300776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maziza A.; Ozgur E.; Bergauda C.; Uzun L. Progress in Conducting Polymers for Biointerfacing and Biorecognition Applications. Sens. Actuators Rep. 2021, 3, 100003510.1016/j.snr.2021.100035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snr.2021.100035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lakard B. Electrochemical Biosensors Based on Conducting Polymers: A Review. Appl. Sci. 2020, 10, 6614.10.3390/app10186614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app10186614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tran V. V.; Lee S.; Lee D.; Le H. Recent Developments and Implementations of Conductive Polymer-Based Flexible Devices in Sensing Applications. Polymer 2022, 14, 3730.10.3390/polym14183730.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym14183730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9504310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36145876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B.; Chen J.; Liu B.; Tang D.; Dass P. M. Amplified Electrochemical Sensing of Lead Ion Based on DNA-Mediated Self-Assembly-Catalyzed Polymerization. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2015, 69, 230.10.1016/j.bios.2015.02.041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2015.02.041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25747508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tadesse M. G.; Ahmmed A. S.; Lubben J. F. Review on Conductive Polymer Composites for Supercapacitor Applications. J. Compos. Sci. 2024, 8, 53.10.3390/jcs8020053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcs8020053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen S.; Yu Z.; Wang Y.; Tang J.; Zeng Y.; Liu X.; Tang D. Block-Polymer-Restricted Sub-nanometer Pt Nanoclusters Nanozyme-Enhanced Immunoassay for Monitoring of Cardiac Troponin I. Anal. Chem. 2023, 95, 14494.10.1021/acs.analchem.3c03249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.3c03249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37707360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luong J. H. T.; Narayan T.; Solanki S.; Malhotra B. D. Recent Advances of Conducting Polymers and Their Composites for Electrochemical Biosensing Applications. J. Funct. Biomater. 2020, 11, 71.10.3390/jfb11040071.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jfb11040071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7712382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32992861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh N.; Riaz U. Recent Trends on Synthetic Approaches and Application Studies of Conducting Polymers and Copolymers: A Review. Polym. Bull. 2022, 12, 10377.10.1007/s00289-021-03987-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00289-021-03987-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marjanovic G. I. Recent Advances in Polyaniline Research: Polymerization Mechanisms, Structural Aspects, Properties and Applications. Synth. Met. 2013, 177, 1.10.1016/j.synthmet.2013.06.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.synthmet.2013.06.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murad A. R.; Iraqi A.; Aziz S. B.; Abdullah S. N.; Brza M. A. Conducting Polymers for Optoelectronic Devices and Organic Solar Cells: A Review. Polymer 2020, 12, 2627.10.3390/polym12112627.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym12112627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7695322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33182241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esfahani N. N.; Dastan D.; Alizadeh A.; Shirvanisamani P.; Rozati M.; Ricciardi E.; Lewis B.; Aphale A.; Toghraie D. A Critical Review on Intrinsic Conducting Polymers and Their Applications. J. Ind. Eng. Chem. 2023, 125, 14.10.1016/j.jiec.2023.05.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiec.2023.05.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng R.; Luo Z.; Zhang L.; Tang D. Platinum Nanozyme-Catalyzed Gas Generation for Pressure-Based Bioassay Using Polyaniline Nanowires-Functionalized Graphene Oxide Framework. Anal. Chem. 2018, 90, 12299.10.1021/acs.analchem.8b03889.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.8b03889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30220197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu J.; Qiu Z.; Tang D. Self-Referenced Smartphone Imaging for Visual Screening of H2S Using CuxO-Polypyrrole Conductive Aerogel Doped with Graphene Oxide Framework. Anal. Chem. 2018, 90, 9691.10.1021/acs.analchem.8b03011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.8b03011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30051716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu J.; Qiu Z.; Lv S.; Zhang K.; Tang D. Cu2+ Doped SnO2 Nanograin/Polypyrrole Nanospheres with Synergic Enhanced Properties for Ultrasensitive Room-Temperature H2S Gas Sensing. Anal. Chem. 2017, 89, 11135.10.1021/acs.analchem.7b03491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.7b03491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28948772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paramshetti S.; Angolkar M.; Garg A.; Ravi G.; Fatease A. A.; Alshahrani S. M.; Osmani R. A. Revolutionizing Drug Delivery and Therapeutics: The Biomedical Applications of Conductive Polymers and Composites-Based Systems. Pharmaceutics 2023, 15, 1204.10.3390/pharmaceutics15041204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics15041204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10145001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37111689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le C. V.; Yoon H. Advances in the Use of Conducting Polymers for Healthcare Monitoring. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2024, 25, 1654.10.3390/ijms25031564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms25031564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10855550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38338846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beygisangchin M.; Rashid S. A.; Shafie S.; Sadrolhosseini A. R.; Lim H. N. Preparations, Properties, And Applications of Polyaniline and Polyaniline Thin Films—A Review. Polymer 2021, 13, 2003.10.3390/polym13122003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym13122003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8234317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34207392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji W. F.; Chu C. M.; Hsu S. C.; Lu Y. D.; Yu Y. C.; Santiago K. S.; Yeh J. M. Synthesis and Characterization of Organo-Soluble Aniline Oligomer Based Electroactive Doped with Gold Nanoparticles, and Application to Electrochemical Sensing of Ascorbic Acid. Polymer 2017, 128, 218.10.1016/j.polymer.2017.09.034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.polymer.2017.09.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majeed A. H.; Mohammed L. A.; Hammoodi O. G.; Sehgal S.; Alheety M. A.; Saxena K. K.; Dadoosh S. A.; Mohammed K.; Jasim M. M.; Salmaan N. U. A Review on Polyaniline: Synthesis, Properties, Nanocomposites, and Electrochemical Applications. Int. J. Polym. Sci. 2022, 2022, 904755410.1155/2022/9047554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/9047554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sumdani G.; Islam M. R.; Yahaya A. N. A.; Safie S. Recent Advancements in Synthesis, Properties, and Applications of Conductive Polymers for Electrochemical Energy Storage Devices: A Review. Polym. Eng. Sci. 2021, 62, 269.10.1002/pen.25859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pen.25859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biyikogulu M.; Ciftci H. Chemical Synthesis and Characterization of Soluble Conducting Poly(2-Aminothiazole). Polym. Bull. 2013, 70, 2843.10.1007/s00289-013-0992-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00289-013-0992-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari M.; Gupta S.; Prakash R. One Pot Synthesis of Coordination Polymer 2,5-Dimercapto-1,3,4-Thiadiazole–Gold and Its Application in Voltammetric Sensing of Resorcinol. RSC Adv. 2014, 4, 25675.10.1039/C4RA02983F.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C4RA02983F</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang S.; Ma C.; Li C.; Min C.; Du P.; Xia Y.; Yang C.; Huang Q. Facile Synthesis, Characterization of Poly-2-Mercapto-1,3,4-Thiadiazole Nanoparticles for Rapid Removal of Mercury and Silver Ions from Aqueous Solutions. Polymer 2018, 10, 150.10.3390/polym10020150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym10020150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6415195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30966186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savateev A.; Pronkin S.; Epping J. D.; Willinger M. G.; Antoniettia M.; Dontsova D. Synthesis of An Electronically Modified Carbon Nitride from a Processable Semiconductor, 3-Amino-1,2,4-Triazole Oligomer, via a Topotactic-Like Phase Transition. J. Mater. Chem. A 2017, 5, 8394.10.1039/C7TA01714F.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C7TA01714F</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yildirim M.; Kaya I. A Comparative Study of Aminothiazole-Based Polymers Synthesized by Chemical Oxidative Polymerization. Synth. Met. 2012, 162, 436.10.1016/j.synthmet.2012.01.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.synthmet.2012.01.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solamaz R.; Kardas G. Electrochemical Synthesis and Characterization of Poly-2-Aminothiazole. Prog. Org. Coat. 2009, 64, 81.10.1016/j.porgcoat.2008.07.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.porgcoat.2008.07.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamanna M. E.; Horra E.; Jacobo S.; Accorso N. B. Synthesis of an Organic Semiconductor by Polymerization of 3-Amino-1,2,4-Triazole. React. Funct. Polym. 2009, 69, 759.10.1016/j.reactfunctpolym.2009.06.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.reactfunctpolym.2009.06.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalimuthu P.; John S. A. Electropolymerized Film of Functionalized Thiadiazole on Glassy Carbon Electrode for The Simultaneous Determination of Ascorbic Acid Dopamine and Uric Acid. Bioelectrochemistry 2009, 77, 13.10.1016/j.bioelechem.2009.04.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bioelechem.2009.04.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19467620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalimuthu P.; John S. A. Simultaneous Determination of Ascorbic Acid, Dopamine, Uric Acid and Xanthine Using a Nanostructured Polymer Film Modified Electrode. Talanta 2010, 80, 1686.10.1016/j.talanta.2009.10.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2009.10.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20152397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalimuthu P.; John S. A. Simultaneous Determination of Epinephrine, Uric Acid and Xanthine in The Presence of Ascorbic Acid Using an Ultrathin Polymer Film Of 5-Amino-1,3,4-Thiadiazole-2-Thiol Modified Electrode. Anal. Chim. Acta 2009, 647, 97.10.1016/j.aca.2009.05.036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2009.05.036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19576392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revin S. B.; John S. A. Electropolymerization of 3-Amino-5-Mercapto-1,2,4-Triazole on Glassy Carbon Electrode and Its Electrocatalytic Activity Towards Uric Acid. Electrochim. Acta 2011, 56, 8934.10.1016/j.electacta.2011.07.125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2011.07.125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin L.; Peng Z.; Yang C. L.; Wang M. Y.; Zha Y. B.; Liu L. L.; Zeng S. D. Determination of imidacloprid, carbendazim and thiabendazole residues in vegetables and fruits by HPLC. Adv. Mater. Res. 2013, 781, 1392.10.4028/www.scientific.net/AMR.781-784.1392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4028/www.scientific.net/AMR.781-784.1392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Razman A. Determination of Thiabendazole in Citrus Fruits by Ultraviolet Spectrophotometry. Analyst 1974, 99, 120.10.1039/AN9749900120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/AN9749900120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4825971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes J. F. G.; Martinez E. J. L.; Barrales P. O.; Diaz A. M. Determination of Thiabendazole Residues in Citrus Fruits Using a Multicommuted Fluorescence-Based Optosensor. Anal. Chim. Acta 2006, 557, 95.10.1016/j.aca.2005.10.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2005.10.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Llorent-Martínez E. J.; Fernández-de Córdova M. L.; Ruiz-Medina A.; Ortega-Barrales P. Fluorimetric Determination of Thiabendazole Residues in Mushrooms Using Sequential Injection Analysis. Talanta 2012, 96, 190.10.1016/j.talanta.2011.12.072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2011.12.072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22817949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Q. W.; Sun H.; Wang K.; He H. B.; Feng Y. Q. Monitoring of Carbendazim and Thiabendazole in Fruits and Vegetables by Sio2@Nio-Based Solid-Phase Extraction Coupled to High-Performance Liquid Chromatography-Fluorescence Detector, Food Anal. Methods 2017, 10, 2892.10.1007/s12161-017-0837-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-017-0837-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi S. I.; Han X.; Lee S. J.; Men X.; Oh G.; Lee D. S.; Lee O. H. Validation of an Analytical Method for The Determination of Thiabendazole in Various Food Matrices. Sep. 2022, 9, 135.10.3390/separations9060135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/separations9060135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khrushchev A. Y.; Akmaev E. R.; Belozerova O. A.; Shmygarev V. I.; Gulyaeva A. Y. Determination of Trace Amounts of Thiabendazole in Fruit Juices Using Internal Standard-Based SERS Method. Vib. Spectrosc. 2023, 127, 10354410.1016/j.vibspec.2023.103544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vibspec.2023.103544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budetic M.; Kopf D.; Dandic A.; Samardzic M. Review of Characteristics and Analytical Methods for Determination of Thiabendazole. Mol. 2023, 28, 3926.10.3390/molecules28093926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28093926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10179875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37175335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noori J. S.; Mortensen J.; Geto A. Recent Development on The Electrochemical Detection of Selected Pesticides: A Focused Review. Sens. 2020, 20, 2221.10.3390/s20082221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s20082221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7218881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32326400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J. C.; Zhang D. F.; Wang L. L.; Long N.; Zhang M. H.; Zhang L.; An L. Electrochemical Method for High Sensitive Detection of Thiabendazole and Its Interaction with Human Serum Albumin. Food Anal. Methods 2015, 8, 507.10.1007/s12161-014-9919-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-014-9919-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong Y.; Yang L.; Zhang L. Simultaneous Electrochemical Detection of Benzimidazole Fungicides Carbendazim and Thiabendazole Using a Novel Nano-Hybrid Material Modified Electrode. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2017, 65, 727.10.1021/acs.jafc.6b04675.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.6b04675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28068083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J.; Ma X.; Zhang M.; Li D.; Yuan Y.; Fan Y.; Xie X.; Guo L.; Zeng G. Preparation of Molecularly Imprinted Polymer Sensor on Electrochemically Reduced Graphene Oxide Modified Electrode for Selective Probing of Thiabendazole. J. Electrochem. Soc. 2019, 166, B84.10.1149/2.0671902jes.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1149/2.0671902jes</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng F.; Liao X.; Huang Z.; Xu L.; Zhou Y.; Zhang X. Highly Sensitive Detection of Thiabendazole Residues in Food Samples Based on Multiwall Carbon Nanotubes Decorated Two-Dimensional Layered Molybdenum Disulfide. Food Anal. Methods 2020, 13, 811.10.1007/s12161-019-01698-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-019-01698-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribeiro F. W. P.; Oliveira R. C.; Oliveira A. G.; Nascimento R. F.; Beckerb H.; Neto P. L.; Correia A. N. Electrochemical Sensing of Thiabendazole in complex samples using boron-doped diamond electrode. J. Electroanal. Chem. 2020, 866, 11417910.1016/j.jelechem.2020.114179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jelechem.2020.114179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kannan P.; John S. A. Fabrication of Conducting Polymer-Gold Nanoparticles Film on Electrodes Using Monolayer Protected Gold Nanoparticles and Its Electrocatalytic Application. Electrochim. Acta 2011, 56, 7029.10.1016/j.electacta.2011.06.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2011.06.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gowri V. M.; Ajith A.; John S. A. Systematic Study on Morphological, Electrochemical Impedance, and Electrocatalytic Activity of Graphitic Carbon Nitride Modified on a Glassy Carbon Substrate from Sequential Exfoliation in Water. Langmuir 2021, 37, 10538.10.1021/acs.langmuir.1c01550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.langmuir.1c01550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34432473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gowri V. M.; Ajith A.; John S. A. Different Modes of Attachment of Graphitic Carbon Nitrides on Glassy Carbon Electrode and Their Electrocatalytic Activity. Microchem. J. 2023, 191, 10881810.1016/j.microc.2023.108818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2023.108818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García Rojas L. M.; Huerta-Aguilar C. A.; Navarrete E.; Llobet E.; Thangarasu P. Enhancement of the CO2 Sensing/Capture through High Cationic Charge in M-ZrO2 (Li+, Mg2+, or Co3+): Experimental and Theoretical Studies. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2023, 15, 25952.10.1021/acsami.3c02997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.3c02997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37200218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tecuapa-Flores E. D.; Hernandez J. G.; Roquero-Tejeda P.; Arenas-Alatorre J. A.; Thangarasu P. Rapid Electrochemical Recognition of Trimethoprim in Human Urine Samples Using New Modified Electrodes (CPE/Ag/Au Nps) Analysing Tunable Electrode Properties: Experimental and Theoretical Studies. Analyst 2021, 146, 7653.10.1039/D1AN01408K.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1AN01408K</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34806723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tecuapa-Flores E. D.; Palacios-Cabrera C. B.; Santiago-Cuevas A. J.; Hernandez J. G.; Narayanan J.; Thangarasu P. Simultaneous Recognition of Dopamine and Uric Acid in Real Samples Through Highly Sensitive New Electrode Fabricated Using ZnO/Carbon Quantum Dots: Bio-Imaging and Theoretical Studies. Analyst 2024, 149, 108.10.1039/D3AN01467C.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D3AN01467C</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37982410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng R.; Qiu M.; Wan Q.; Huang Z.; Liu X.; Tang D.; Knopp D. Smartphone-Based Electrochemical Immunoassay for Point-of-Care Detection of SARS-CoV-2 Nucleocapsid Protein. Anal. Chem. 2022, 94, 15155.10.1021/acs.analchem.2c03606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.2c03606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36251341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv S.; Zhang K.; Zhu L.; Tang D.; Niessner R.; Knopp D. H2-Based Electrochemical Biosensor with Pd Nanowires@ZIF-67 Molecular Sieve Bilayered Sensing Interface for Immunoassay. Anal. Chem. 2019, 91, 12055.10.1021/acs.analchem.9b03177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.9b03177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31436433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>