<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39224501</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2196-5226</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>GMS hygiene and infection control</Title><ISOAbbreviation>GMS Hyg Infect Control</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Medical associations and expert committees urge that ethanol be approved as a virucidal active substance for use in hand antiseptics under the European Biocidal Products Regulation, without a CMR classification.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>Doc40</StartPage><MedlinePgn>Doc40</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">Doc40</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3205/dgkh000495</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Since 2007, the classification of ethanol under the Biocidal Products Regulation has paradoxically remained unresolved due to conflicting views among experts and authorities. Initially, there was a discussion about classifying ethanol as carcinogenic. The current proposal to extend its harmonized classification includes, among other things, categorizing it as reproductive toxicity category 2 ("suspected to have CMR potential for humans"; carcinogenic, mutagenic, reprotoxic). If ethanol were classified under reproductive toxicity category 2, it would mean that the only active ingredient in hand antiseptics effective against non-enveloped viruses would no longer be available.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SCIENTIFIC ASSESSMENT OF THE SAFETY OF ETHANOL-BASED HAND RUBS EBHR" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Available epidemiological studies do not confirm an increased risk for cancer from EBHR in exposed individuals, except under uncommon or unlikely routes or levels of exposure.The evidence for ethanol's reprotoxic effect originates from the consumption of alcoholic beverages by pregnant women, where ethanol uptake is incomparably higher. The amount of transdermal ethanol absorption during hand antisepsis is up to ten times lower than the oral intake of beverages containing hidden ethanol, such as apple juice, kefir, or non-alcoholic beer. Blood alcohol levels after using EBHR remain within the physiological range associated with food intake.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">There is no epidemiological evidence of toxicity for workers handling ethanol-containing products in industry or using EBHR in healthcare settings. Given that the classification of EBHR as reproductive toxicity category 2 is not supported by current scientific research and that no alternative biocidal active substance in hand rubs is effective against non-enveloped viruses, medical associations and expert committees from Europe, the USA, Canada, the Asia-Pacific region, and the World Society for Virology unequivocally recommend, with the highest priority, that EBHR be approved as an active substance for PT1 biocides and not be classified as a reproductive toxicant in category 2.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Kramer et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kramer</LastName><ForeName>Axel</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Hygiene and Environmental Medicine, University Medicine Greifswald, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pittet</LastName><ForeName>Didier</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infection Control Programme, Faculty of Medicine, University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Exner</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Hygiene and Public Health, University Clinics Bonn, Bonn, Germany; VAH - Association for Applied Hygiene c/o Institute for Hygiene and Public Health, Bonn, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wendt</LastName><ForeName>Constanze</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MVZ Labor Dr. Limbach, Department of Hygiene, Heidelberg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>GMS Hyg Infect Control</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101609519</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2196-5226</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ger"><AbstractText Label="EINLEITUNG" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Seit 2007 ist die Einstufung von Ethanol im Rahmen der Biozid-Verordnung paradoxerweise aufgrund widersprüchlicher Ansichten von Experten und Behörden ungelöst geblieben. Ursprünglich war diskutiert worden, Ethanol als krebserregend einzustufen. Die derzeitige Absicht, die harmonisierte Einstufung zu erweitern, sieht u.a. eine Einstufung als Reproduktionstoxizität der Kategorie 2 („Verdacht auf CMR-Potenzial für den Menschen“; carcinogen, mutagen, reproduktionstoxisch) vor. Die Einstufung von Ethanol in die Reproduktionstoxizitätskategorie 2 hätte zur Folge, dass der einzige Wirkstoff in Händedesinfektionsmitteln mit Wirksamkeit gegen unbehüllte Viren nicht mehr verfügbar wäre.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="WISSENSCHAFTLICHE BEWERTUNG DER UNBEDENKLICHKEIT VON ETHANOL-BASIERTEN HÄNDEDESINFEKTIONSMITTELN EBHD" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Die verfügbaren epidemiologischen Studien bestätigen kein erhöhtes Krebsrisiko bei mit EBHD exponierten Menschen. Die vorliegenden Erkenntnisse deuten nicht darauf hin, dass der Wirkstoff beim Menschen wahrscheinlich Krebs verursacht, außer bei ungewöhnlichen oder unwahrscheinlichen Expositionswegen oder -höhen. Die Evidenz für eine reproduktionstoxische Wirkung von Ethanol beruht auf dem Konsum von alkoholischen Getränken durch schwangere Frauen mit einer unvergleichlich höheren Ethanol-Aufnahme als durch Einsatz von EBHD. Die transdermale Ethanolaufnahme bei der Händedesinfektion ist bis zu zehnmal geringer als die orale Aufnahme von Getränken mit verstecktem Ethanolgehalt wie Apfelsaft, Kefir oder alkoholfreiem Bier. Der Blutspiegel liegt nach Händedesinfektion mit EBHD im physiologischen Bereich der Nahrungsaufnahme.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SCHLUSSFOLGERUNG" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Es gibt keine epidemiologischen Hinweise auf eine Toxizität für Arbeitnehmer beim Umgang mit ethanolhaltigen Produkten in der Industrie oder bei der Verwendung von EBHD in Gesundheitseinrichtungen. In Anbetracht der Tatsache, dass die Einstufung von EBHD in die Reproduktionstoxizitätskategorie 2 durch die aktuelle wissenschaftliche Forschung nicht bestätigt wird, und es keinen bioziden Ersatzwirkstoff zur Händedesinfektion mit Wirksamkeit gegen unbehüllte Viren gibt, empfehlen medizinische Fachverbände und Expertenausschüsse aus Europa, den USA, Kanada, der Asia-Pacific Region und die Weltgesellschaft für Virologie unmissverständlich und mit höchster Priorität, EBHD als Wirkstoff für PT1-Biozide zuzulassen und nicht in die Reproduktionstoxizitätskategorie 2 einzustufen.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Kramer et al.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biocid classifying</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ethanol-based handrubs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">no carcinogenic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">no fetotoxic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">no mutagenic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">toxicological harmlessness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transdermal absorption</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">virucidal efficacy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39224501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11367556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3205/dgkh000495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">dgkh000495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kramer A, Benkhai H, Jäkel C, Zwicker P. Ethanol is indispensable for virucidal hand antisepsis and without toxic risks in daily use. GMS Hyg Infect;18:Doc02. doi: 10.3205/dgkh000428.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3205/dgkh000428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9978451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36875333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer A, Arvand M, Christiansen B, Dancer S, Eggers M, Exner M, Müller D, Mutters NT, Schwebke I, Pittet D. Ethanol is indispensable for virucidal hand antisepsis: memorandum from the alcohol-based hand rub (ABHR) Task Force, WHO Collaborating Centre on Patient Safety, and the Commission for Hospital Hygiene and Infection Prevention (KRINKO), Robert Koch Institute, Berlin, Germany. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control. 2022 Jul;11(1):93. doi: 10.1186/s13756-022-01134-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13756-022-01134-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9257567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35794648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. Commission Implementing Decision (EU) 2016/904 of 8 June 2016 pursuant to Article 3(3) of Regulation (EU) No 528/2012 of the European Parliament and of the Council on propan-2-ol containing products used for hand disinfection. Off J Eur Union. 2016 J;59:L152/45. Available from:  http://data.europa.eu/eli/dec_impl/2016/904/oj.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. Regulation (EU) No 528/2012 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 May 2012 concerning the making available on the market and use of biocidal products. Off J Eur Union. 2012;55:L167/1. doi: 10.3000/19770677.L_2012.167.eng.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3000/19770677.L_2012.167.eng</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/407 of 11 March 2015 approving propan-2-ol as an active substance for use in biocidal products for product-types 1, 2 and 4. Off J Eur Union. 2015;58:L67/15. Available from:  https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg_impl/2015/407/oj.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2017/2001 of 8 November 2017 approving propan-1-ol as an existing active substance for use in biocidal products of product-type 1, 2 and 4. Off J Eur Union. 2017;60:L290/1. Available from:  https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg_impl/2017/2001/oj.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IBM Watson Health, editor. Ethanol. Greenwood Village, CO: IBM Corporation; 2021.  Available from:  https://www.micromedexsolutions.com/home/dispatch.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadi HA, Hill JA, Castillo RA. Alcohol and reproductive function: a review. Obstet Gynecol Surv. 1987 Feb;42(2):69–74. doi: 10.1097/00006254-198742020-00001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00006254-198742020-00001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3547207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission for Hospital Hygiene and Infection Prevention (KRINKO) Hygiene requirements for cleaning and disinfection of surfaces: recommendation of the Commission for Hospital Hygiene and Infection Prevention (KRINKO) at the Robert Koch Institute. GMS Hyg Infect Control. 2024;19:Doc13. doi: 10.3205/dgkh000468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3205/dgkh000468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11035912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38655122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrović T, D’Agostino M. Viral contamination of food. Antimicrobial Food Packaging. 2016:65–79. doi: 10.1016/B978-0-12-800723-5.00005-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-800723-5.00005-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Food Code. 2022 Recommendations of the Unit.  Available from:  https://www.fda.gov/media/164194/download?attachment.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scallan E, Hoekstra RM, Angulo FJ, Tauxe RV, Widdowson MA, Roy SL, Jones JL, Griffin PM. Foodborne illness acquired in the United States – major pathogens. Emerg Infect Dis. 2011 Jan;17(1):7–15. doi: 10.3201/eid1701.p11101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1701.p11101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3375761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21192848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirk MD, Pires SM, Black RE, Caipo M, Crump JA, Devleesschauwer B, Döpfer D, Fazil A, Fischer-Walker CL, Hald T, Hall AJ, Keddy KH, Lake RJ, Lanata CF, Torgerson PR, Havelaar AH, Angulo FJ. Correction: World Health Organization Estimates of the Global and Regional Disease Burden of 22 Foodborne Bacterial, Protozoal, and Viral Diseases, 2010: A Data Synthesis. PLoS Med. 2015 Dec;12(12):e1001940. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1001940.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4668831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26633831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer A. Ethanol is indispensable for virucidal hand antisepsis and harmless – a classification of ethanol based hand rubs (EBHR) as carcinogenic, mutagenic, or reprotoxic by the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) would be an disaster and lacks any scientific basis. 9th edition of Innovations in Food Science and Human Nutrition; 2024 Jun 26-27; Prague, Czech Republic.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tartari E, Bellissimo-Rodrigues F, Pires D, Fankhauser C, Lotfinejad N, Saito H, Suchomel M, Kramer A, Allegranzi B, Boyce J, Sax H, Stewardson AJ, Pittet D ICPIC Alcohol-Based Handrub Task Force. Updates and future directions regarding hand hygiene in the healthcare setting: insights from the 3rd ICPIC alcohol-based handrub (ABHR) task force. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control. 2024 Feb;13(1):26. doi: 10.1186/s13756-024-01374-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13756-024-01374-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10905912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38424571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verbund für Angewandte Hygiene (VAH) VAH: Ethanol ist als biozider Wirkstoff zur hygienischen Händedesinfektion unverzichtbar.  [As a biocidal active substance, ethanol is indispensable for hygienic hand disinfection]. HygMed. 2020;45(11):194–200. (Ger). Available from:  https://vah-online.de/files/download/vah-mitteilungen/VAH_Ethanol_ZT_6_20_354_359_en.pdf.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>