<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39223008</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1539-6924</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Risk analysis : an official publication of the Society for Risk Analysis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Risk Anal</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Combating foodborne disease through household food handling behavior improvement: A comparison between education and price interventions.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/risa.17642</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Foodborne disease cases are increasingly occurring in home kitchens because of improper food handling behavior. Human factors are considered major determinants of such behavior, although economic factors, which have attracted little attention, may also be important influencers. Taking the service time of kitchen towels as an example, we construct a theoretical model to analyze food handling behavior under an economic framework and empirically explore its economic determinants. Empirically, we use a randomized controlled trial (RCT) coupled with pre- and postsurveys in rural China. The RCT intervention includes information with tips for proper kitchen towel use and in-kind subsidies of one, two, or three packs of kitchen towels, which is regarded as a price intervention. We find that information alone and information plus one pack of towels are not enough to stimulate behavior improvement, whereas information plus two or three packs is sufficient. This implies that the quantity of kitchen towels used increases only as the towel price drops below a certain threshold. As an early attempt, we indicate that food handling behavior is economically driven, suggesting that a well-designed policy should combine educational campaigns and appropriate economic incentives to improve such behavior to reduce the risk of foodborne disease.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society for Risk Analysis.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Meng</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6604-1604</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food and Strategic Reserves, Nanjing University of Finance &amp; Economics, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>H Holly</ForeName><Initials>HH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6929-4201</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agriculture, Food, and Resource Economics, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bai</LastName><ForeName>Junfei</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0153-6793</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Economics and Management, China Agricultural University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Beijing Food Safety Policy &amp; Strategy Research Base, China Agricultural University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>72333003</GrantID><Agency>Key Program of the National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>The 2115 Talent Development Program of China Agricultural University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>23YJA790097</GrantID><Agency>Humanities and Social Sciences Research Planning Fund Project of the Ministry of Education of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2024SJYB0215</GrantID><Agency>General Project of Philosophy and Social Sciences Research in Universities, Jiangsu Provincial Department of Education</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Risk Anal</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8109978</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0272-4332</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">economic incentive</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety behavior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">information intervention</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">price intervention</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39223008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/risa.17642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Augustin, J. C., Kooh, P., Bayeux, T., Guillier, L., Meyer, T., Jourdan‐Da Silva, N., Villena, I., Sanaa, M., &amp; Cerf, O., &amp; Anses Working Group on Consumer Information on Foodborne Biological Risks. (2020). Contribution of foods and poor food‐handling practices to the burden of foodborne infectious diseases in France. Foods, 9(11), 1644. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods9111644</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai, L., Tang, J., Yang, Y., &amp; Gong, S. (2014). Hygienic food handling intention. An application of the theory of planned behavior in the Chinese cultural context. Food Control, 42, 172–180. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2014.02.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee, A. V., &amp; Duflo, E. (2009). The experimental approach to development economics. Annual Review of Economics, 1(1), 151–178. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.economics.050708.143235</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee, A. V., Duflo, E., Glennerster, R., &amp; Kothari, D. (2010). Improving immunisation coverage in rural India: Clustered randomised controlled evaluation of immunisation campaigns with and without incentives. BMJ, 340, c2220. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.c2220</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bates, M. A., Glennerster, R., Gumede, K., &amp; Duflo, E. (2012). The price is wrong. Field Actions Science Reports, 4(Special issue 4), 30–37. http://journals.openedition.org/factsreports/1554</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker, G. S. (1965). A theory of the allocation of time. The Economic Journal, 75(299), 493–517. https://doi.org/10.2307/2228949</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berger, N., Koch, S., Jungnickel, K., &amp; Böl, G. F. (2023). Food safety in the aging population: Qualitative findings on what to communicate and how. Risk Analysis, 43(9), 1843–1854. https://doi.org/10.1111/risa.14069</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisht, A., Kamble, M. P., Choudhary, P., Chaturvedi, K., Kohli, G., Juneja, V. K., Sehgal, S., &amp; Taneja, N. K. (2021). A surveillance of food borne disease outbreaks in India: 2009–2018. Food Control, 121, 107630. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107630</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogevska, Z., Berjan, S., El Bilali, H., Allahyari, M. S., Radosavac, A., &amp; Davitkovska, M. (2022). Exploring food shopping, consumption and waste habits in North Macedonia during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Socio‐Economic Planning Sciences, 82, 101150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seps.2021.101150</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cameron, L., Olivia, S., &amp; Shah, M. (2019). Scaling up sanitation: Evidence from an RCT in Indonesia. Journal of Development Economics, 138, 1–16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jdeveco.2018.12.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrieri, V., &amp; Principe, F. (2022). WHO and for how long? An empirical analysis of the consumers’ response to red meat warning. Food Policy, 108, 102231. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodpol.2022.102231</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, H., &amp; Feng, Y. (2021). Moving forward to the future: A review of microbial food safety education in China. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease, 18(8), 547–566. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2020.2889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Zhang, R., Qi, X., Zhou, B., Wang, J., Chen, Y., &amp; Zhang, H. (2017). Epidemiology of foodborne disease outbreaks caused by Vibrio parahaemolyticus during 2010–2014 in Zhejiang Province, China. Food Control, 77, 110–115. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.02.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen, J., &amp; Dupas, P. (2010). Free distribution or cost‐sharing? Evidence from a randomized malaria prevention experiment. The Quarterly Journal of Economics, 125(1), 1–45. https://doi.org/10.1162/qjec.2010.125.1.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colen, L., Gomez y Paloma, S., Latacz‐Lohmann, U., Lefebvre, M., Préget, R., &amp; Thoyer, S. (2016). Economic experiments as a tool for agricultural policy evaluation: Insights from the European CAP. Canadian Journal of Agricultural Economics, 64(4), 667–694. https://doi.org/10.1111/cjag.12107</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Courtemanche, C. J., &amp; Zapata, D. (2014). Does universal coverage improve health? The Massachusetts experience. Journal of Policy Analysis and Management, 33(1), 36–69. https://doi.org/10.1002/pam.21737</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Cunha, D. T., De Rosso, V. V., Pereira, M. B., &amp; Stedefeldt, E. (2019). The differences between observed and self‐reported food safety practices: A study with food handlers using structural equation modeling. Food Research International, 125, 108637. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2019.108637</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Freitas, R. S. G., Da Cunha, D. T., &amp; Stedefeldt, E. (2020). Work conditions, social incorporations, and foodborne diseases risk: Reflections about the (non) compliance of food safety practices. Risk Analysis, 40(5), 926–938. https://doi.org/10.1111/risa.13453</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dupas, P. (2014a). Getting essential health products to their end users: Subsidize, but how much? Science, 345(6202), 1279–1281. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1256973</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dupas, P. (2014b). Short‐run subsidies and long‐run adoption of new health products: Evidence from a field experiment. Econometrica, 82(1), 197–228. https://doi.org/10.3982/ECTA9508</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dupas, P., Hoffmann, V., Kremer, M., &amp; Zwane, A. P. (2016). Targeting health subsidies through a nonprice mechanism: A randomized controlled trial in Kenya. Science, 353(6302), 889–895. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aaf6288</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeSerpa, A. C. (1971). A theory of the economics of time. The Economic Journal, 81(324), 828–846.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ernawati, K., Nadhifah, Q., Muslikha, A., Hidayat, M., Soesilo, T. E., Jannah, F., &amp; Widianti, D. (2021). Relationship of knowledge and attitude with food handling practices: A systematic review. International Journal of Public Health Science, 10(2), 336–347. https://doi.org/10.11591/ijphs.v10i2.20665</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer, A. R. H., Jong, A. E. I. D., Asselt, E. D. V., Jonge, R. D., Frewer, L. J., &amp; Nauta, M. J. (2007). Food safety in the domestic environment: An interdisciplinary investigation of microbial hazards during food preparation. Risk Analysis, 27(4), 1065–1082. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1539‐6924.2007.00944.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freivogel, C., Lehmann, S. H., &amp; Visschers, V. H. (2022). Tailoring can improve consumers’ hygienic food‐handling behavior to reduce the transmission risk of antimicrobial‐resistant bacteria through food. European Journal of Investigation in Health, Psychology and Education, 12(2), 169–192. https://doi.org/10.3390/ejihpe12020014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grossman, M. (1972). On the concept of health capital and the demand for health. Journal of Political Economy, 80(2), 223–255. https://doi.org/10.1086/259880</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, Z., &amp; Bai, L. (2024). The effect of online versus offline interventions on food safety and handling knowledge of household food handlers: A continuous experimental design. Food Control, 159, 110280. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110280</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamory, J., Miguel, E., Walker, M., Kremer, M., &amp; Baird, S. (2021). Twenty‐year economic impacts of deworming. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 118(14), e2023185118. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2023185118</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann, S., Ashton, L., &amp; Ahn, J. W. (2021). Food safety: A policy history and introduction to avenues for economic research. Applied Economic Perspectives and Policy, 43(2), 680–700. https://doi.org/10.1002/aepp.13158</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann, V., Moser, C., &amp; Saak, A. (2019). Food safety in low and middle‐income countries: The evidence through an economic lens. World Development, 123, 104611. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.worlddev.2019.104611</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu, C. L., &amp; Lin, J. C. C. (2015). What drives purchase intention for paid mobile apps?–An expectation confirmation model with perceived value. Electronic Commerce Research and Applications, 14(1), 46–57. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.elerap.2014.11.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kariuki, S. W., &amp; Hoffmann, V. (2022). Can information drive demand for safer food? Impact of brand‐specific recommendations and test results on product choice. Agricultural Economics, 53(3), 454–467. https://doi.org/10.1111/agec.12685</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kendall, H., Kaptan, G., Stewart, G., Grainger, M., Kuznesof, S., Naughton, P., Clark, B., Hubbard, C., Raley, M., Marvin, H. J. P., &amp; Frewer, L. J. (2018). Drivers of existing and emerging food safety risks: Expert opinion regarding multiple impacts. Food Control, 90, 440–458. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.02.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koch, S., Lohmann, M., Geppert, J., Stamminger, R., Epp, A., &amp; Böl, G. F. (2021). Kitchen hygiene in the spotlight: How cooking shows influence viewers’ hygiene practices. Risk Analysis, 41(1), 131–140. https://doi.org/10.1111/risa.13584</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kremer, M., &amp; Glennerster, R. (2011). Improving health in developing countries: Evidence from randomized evaluations. In M. V. Pauly, T. G. McGuire, &amp; P. P. Barros (Eds.), Handbook of health economics (Vol. 2, pp. 201–315). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐444‐53592‐4.00004‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, W., Pires, S. M., Liu, Z., Ma, X., Liang, J., Jiang, Y., Chen, J., Liang, J., Wang, S., Wang, L., Wang, Y., Meng, C., Huo, X., Lan, Z., Lai, S., Liu, C., Han, H., Liu, J., Fu, P., &amp; Guo, Y. (2020). Surveillance of foodborne disease outbreaks in China, 2003–2017. Food Control, 118, 107359. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107359</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, N., &amp; Roberts, K. R. (2020). Using the theory of planned behavior to predict food safety behavioral intention: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. International Journal of Hospitality Management, 90, 102612. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijhm.2020.102612</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao, X. (2010). Epidemiological characteristics and disease burden of bacterial foodborne diseases in China from 2003 to 2008 (PhD dissertation) (In Chinese). Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malcolm, T. T. H., San Chang, W., Loo, Y. Y., Cheah, Y. K., Radzi, C. W. J. W. M., Kantilal, H. K., Nishibuchi, M., &amp; Son, R. (2018). Simulation of improper food hygiene practices: A quantitative assessment of Vibrio parahaemolyticus distribution. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 284, 112–119. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.08.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manipis, K., Mulhern, B., Haywood, P., Viney, R., &amp; Goodall, S. (2023). Estimating the willingness‐to‐pay to avoid the consequences of foodborne illnesses: A discrete choice experiment. The European Journal of Health Economics, 24(5), 831–852. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10198‐022‐01512‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Møretrø, T., Almli, V. L., Åsli, A. W., Kummen, C., Galler, M., &amp; Langsrud, S. (2022). Kitchen cloths: Consumer practices, drying properties and bacterial growth and survival. Food Control, 142, 109195. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109195</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Møretrø, T., Moen, B., Almli, V. L., Teixeira, P., Ferreira, V. B., Åsli, A. W., Nilsen, C., &amp; Langsrud, S. (2021). Dishwashing sponges and brushes: Consumer practices and bacterial growth and survival. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 337, 108928. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2020.108928</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanli̇er, N., Sormaz, Ü., &amp; Güneş, E. (2020). The effect of food safety education on food safety knowledge, attitudes, behaviors of individuals who work in food and beverage departments in Turkey. International Journal of Gastronomy and Food Science, 22, 100259. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijgfs.2020.100259</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unnevehr, L. J. (2022). Addressing food safety challenges in rapidly developing food systems. Agricultural Economics, 53(4), 529–539. https://doi.org/10.1111/agec.12724</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Votinov, M., Aso, T., Fukuyama, H., &amp; Mima, T. (2016). A neural mechanism of preference shifting under zero price condition. Frontiers in Human Neuroscience, 10, 177. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnhum.2016.00177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vu, H. T., Tran, D., Goto, D., &amp; Kawata, K. (2020). Does experience sharing affect farmers’ pro‐environmental behavior? A randomized controlled trial in Vietnam. World Development, 136, 105062. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105062</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M., Bai, L., Gong, S., &amp; Huang, L. (2020). Determinants of consumer food safety self‐protection behavior–An analysis using grounded theory. Food Control, 113, 107198. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107198</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M., Gong, S., Bai, L., Liang, L., Weng, Z., &amp; Tang, J. (2023). Analytic and heuristic process for prudent antimicrobial use in animals: What are triggers and how do they work? Risk Analysis, 44(4), 757–773. https://doi.org/10.1111/risa.14208</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M., Huang, L., Liang, X., &amp; Bai, L. (2021). Consumer knowledge, risk perception and food‐handling behaviors—A national survey in China. Food Control, 122, 107789. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107789</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M., Huang, L., Pan, C., &amp; Bai, L. (2021). Adopt proper food‐handling intention: An application of the health belief model. Food Control, 127, 108169. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108169</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2016). WHO's first ever global estimates of foodborne diseases find children under 5 account for almost one third of deaths. Saudi Medical Journal, 37(1), 109–110. https://www.who.int/en/news‐room/detail/03‐12‐2015‐who‐s‐first‐ever‐global‐estimates‐of‐foodborne‐diseases‐find‐children‐under‐5‐account‐for‐almost‐one‐third‐of‐deaths</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young, I., Waddell, L., Harding, S., Greig, J., Mascarenhas, M., Sivaramalingam, B., Pham, M. T., &amp; Papadopoulos, A. (2015). A systematic review and meta‐analysis of the effectiveness of food safety education interventions for consumers in developed countries. BMC Public Health [Electronic Resource], 15, 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889‐015‐2171‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young, I., Waddell, L. A., Wilhelm, B. J., &amp; Greig, J. (2020). A systematic review and meta‐regression of single group, pre‐post studies evaluating food safety education and training interventions for food handlers. Food Research International, 128, 108711. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2019.108711</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanin, L. M., Da Cunha, D. T., De Rosso, V. V., Capriles, V. D., &amp; Stedefeldt, E. (2017). Knowledge, attitudes and practices of food handlers in food safety: An integrative review. Food Research International, 100, 53–62. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2017.07.042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M., Lu, X., &amp; Bai, J. (2023). The effectiveness of information interventions to improve domestic food safety among rural consumers. International Journal of Consumer Studies, 47(2), 496–508. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijcs.12846</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M., Zhu, Q., &amp; Bai, J. (2022). The disparity between self‐reported and observed food safety behavior: A case involving consumers from rural China. Food Control, 138, 108981. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.108981</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z., Chen, Y. H., &amp; Wu, L. H. (2021). Effects of governmental intervention on foodborne disease events: Evidence from China. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 18(24), 13311. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph182413311</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>