<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39220920</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>16</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Activation of the l-fucose utilization cluster in <i>Campylobacter jejuni</i> induces proteomic changes and enhances Caco-2 cell invasion and fibronectin binding.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e34996</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e34996</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e34996</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e34996</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Most <i>Campylobacter jejuni</i> isolates carry the fucose utilization cluster (<i>Cj0480c-Cj0489</i>) that supports the metabolism of l-fucose and d-arabinose. In this study we quantified l-fucose and d-arabinose metabolism and metabolite production, and the impact on Caco-2 cell interaction and binding to fibronectin, using <i>C. jejuni</i> NCTC11168 and the closely related human isolate <i>C. jejuni</i> strain 286. When cultured with l-fucose and d-arabinose, both isolates showed increased survival and production of acetate, pyruvate and succinate, and the respective signature metabolites lactate and glycolic acid, in line with an overall upregulation of l-fucose cluster proteins. <i>In vitro</i> Caco-2 cell studies and fibronectin-binding experiments showed a trend towards higher invasion and a significantly higher fibronectin binding efficacy of <i>C. jejuni</i> NCTC11168 cells grown with l-fucose and d-arabinose, while no significant differences were found with <i>C. jejuni</i> 286. Both fibronectin binding proteins, CadF and FlpA, were detected in the two isolates, but were not significantly differentially expressed in l-fucose or d-arabinose grown cells. Comparative proteomics analysis linked the <i>C. jejuni</i> NCTC11168 phenotypes uniquely to the more than 135-fold upregulated protein Cj0608, putative TolC-like component MacC, which, together with the detected Cj0606 and Cj0607 proteins, forms the tripartite secretion system MacABC with putative functions in antibiotic resistance, cell envelope stress response and virulence in Gram negative pathogenic bacteria. Further studies are required to elucidate the role of the MacABC system in <i>C. jejuni</i> cell surface structure modulation and virulence.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Middendorf</LastName><ForeName>Pjotr S</ForeName><Initials>PS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Microbiology, Wageningen University and Research, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, Bilthoven, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wijnands</LastName><ForeName>Lucas M</ForeName><Initials>LM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, Bilthoven, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boeren</LastName><ForeName>Sjef</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Biochemistry, Wageningen University and Research, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zomer</LastName><ForeName>Aldert L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Department of Infectious Diseases and Immunology, Utrecht University, Utrecht, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Collaborating Center for Campylobacter/OIE Reference Laboratory for Campylobacteriosis, Utrecht, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jacobs-Reitsma</LastName><ForeName>Wilma F</ForeName><Initials>WF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, Bilthoven, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>den Besten</LastName><ForeName>Heidy M W</ForeName><Initials>HMW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Microbiology, Wageningen University and Research, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abee</LastName><ForeName>Tjakko</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Microbiology, Wageningen University and Research, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lipooligosaccharides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pathogen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Secretion system</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Survival</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39220920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11365321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e34996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)11027-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>EFSA, the European Union one health 2019 zoonoses report. EFSA J. 2021;19(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7913300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33680134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaakoush N.O., Castaño-Rodríguez N., Mitchell H.M., Man S.M. Global epidemiology of Campylobacter infection. Clin. Microbiol. Rev. 2015;28(3):687–720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4462680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26062576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Špačková M., Kolářová K., Gašpárek M. Incidence and analysis of campylobacteriosis cases in the Czech Republic in 1997-2017. Epidemiol. Mikrobiol. Imunol.: casopis Spolecnosti pro epidemiologii a mikrobiologii Ceske lekarske spolecnosti JE Purkyne. 2019;68(3):122–130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31914777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tack D.M., Marder E.P., Griffin P.M., Cieslak P.R., Dunn J., Hurd S., Scallan E., Lathrop S., Muse A., Ryan P. Preliminary incidence and trends of infections with pathogens transmitted commonly through food—foodborne Diseases Active Surveillance Network, 10 US Sites, 2015–2018. MMWR (Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep.) 2019;68(16):369.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6483286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31022166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark C.G., Lawrence Price R.A., Woodward D.L., Melito P.L., Rodgers F.G., Jamieson F., Ciebin B., Li A., Ellis A. Characterization of waterborne outbreak–associated Campylobacter jejuni, Walkerton, Ontario. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2003;9(10):1232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3033067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14609457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karagiannis I., Sideroglou T., Gkolfinopoulou K., Tsouri A., Lampousaki D., Velonakis E., Scoulica E., Mellou K., Panagiotopoulos T., Bonovas S. A waterborne Campylobacter jejuni outbreak on a Greek island. Epidemiol. Infect. 2010;138(12):1726–1734.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20836911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kenyon J., Inns T., Aird H., Swift C., Astbury J., Forester E., Decraene V. Campylobacter outbreak associated with raw drinking milk, North West England, 2016. Epidemiol. Infect. 2020:148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7019543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32000879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhn K.G., Falkenhorst G., Emborg H.-D., Ceper T., Torpdahl M., Krogfelt K., Ethelberg S., Mølbak K. Epidemiological and serological investigation of a waterborne Campylobacter jejuni outbreak in a Danish town. Epidemiol. Infect. 2017;145(4):701–709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9507752</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27903324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuusi M., Klemets P., Miettinen I., Laaksonen I., Sarkkinen H., Hänninen M.-L., Rautelin H., Kela E., Nuorti J. An outbreak of gastroenteritis from a non-chlorinated community water supply. J. Epidemiol. Community. 2004;58(4):273–277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1732716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15026434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montgomery M.P., Robertson S., Koski L., Salehi E., Stevenson L.M., Silver R., Sundararaman P., Singh A., Joseph L.A., Weisner M.B. Multidrug-resistant Campylobacter jejuni outbreak linked to puppy exposure—United States, 2016–2018. MMWR (Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep.) 2018;67(37):1032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6147421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30235182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blaser M.J. Epidemiologic and clinical features of Campylobacter jejuni infections. JID (J. Infect. Dis.) 1997;176(Supplement_2):S103–S105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9396691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansson I., Sandberg M., Habib I., Lowman R., Engvall E.O. Knowledge gaps in control of Campylobacter for prevention of campylobacteriosis. Transboundary and emerging diseases. 2018;65:30–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29663680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuki N., Taki T., Inagaki F., Kasama T., Takahashi M., Saito K., Handa S., Miyatake T. A bacterium lipopolysaccharide that elicits Guillain-Barré syndrome has a GM1 ganglioside-like structure. J. Exp. Med. 1993;178(5):1771–1775.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2191246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8228822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nachamkin I., Allos B.M., Ho T. Campylobacter species and Guillain-Barre syndrome. Clin. Microbiol. Rev. 1998;11(3):555–567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC88896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9665983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rees J., Soudain S., Gregson N., Hughes R. Infection and Guillain-Barre syndrome. N. Engl. J. Med. 1995;333:1374–1379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7477117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Black R.E., Levine M.M., Clements M.L., Hughes T.P., Blaser M.J. Experimental Campylobacter jejuni infection in humans. J. Infect. Dis. 1988;157(3):472–479.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3343522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson D. Infective dose of Campylobacter jejuni in milk. Br. Med. J. 1981;282(6276):1584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1505544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6786571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konkel M.E., Christensen J.E., Keech A.M., Monteville M.R., Klena J.D., Garvis S.G. Identification of a fibronectin‐binding domain within the Campylobacter jejuni CadF protein. Mol. Microbiol. 2005;57(4):1022–1035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16091041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brøndsted L., Andersen M.T., Parker M., Jørgensen K., Ingmer H. The HtrA protease of Campylobacter jejuni is required for heat and oxygen tolerance and for optimal interaction with human epithelial cells. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2005;71(6):3205–3212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1151804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15933023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashgar S.S., Oldfield N.J., Wooldridge K.G., Jones M.A., Irving G.J., Turner D.P., Ala'Aldeen D.A. CapA, an autotransporter protein of Campylobacter jejuni, mediates association with human epithelial cells and colonization of the chicken gut. J. Bacteriol. 2007;189(5):1856–1865.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1855769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17172331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchant J., Wren B., Ketley J. Exploiting genome sequence: predictions for mechanisms of Campylobacter chemotaxis. Trends Microbiol. 2002;10(4):155–159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11912013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konkel M.E., Talukdar P.K., Negretti N.M., Klappenbach C.M. Taking control: Campylobacter jejuni binding to fibronectin sets the stage for cellular adherence and invasion. Front. Microbiol. 2020;11:564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7161372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32328046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konkel M.E., Larson C.L., Flanagan R.C. Campylobacter jejuni FlpA binds fibronectin and is required for maximal host cell adherence. J. Bacteriol. 2010;192(1):68–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2798237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19880595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flanagan R.C., Neal-McKinney J.M., Dhillon A.S., Miller W.G., Konkel M.E. Examination of Campylobacter jejuni putative adhesins leads to the identification of a new protein, designated FlpA, required for chicken colonization. Infect. Immun. 2009;77(6):2399–2407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2687328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19349427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodcock D.J., Krusche P., Strachan N.J., Forbes K.J., Cohan F.M., Méric G., Sheppard S.K. Genomic plasticity and rapid host switching can promote the evolution of generalism: a case study in the zoonotic pathogen Campylobacter. Sci. Rep. 2017;7(1):9650.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5575054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28851932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheppard S.K., Didelot X., Meric G., Torralbo A., Jolley K.A., Kelly D.J., Bentley S.D., Maiden M.C., Parkhill J., Falush D. Genome-wide association study identifies vitamin B5 biosynthesis as a host specificity factor in Campylobacter. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2013;110(29):11923–11927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3718156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23818615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofreuter D. Defining the metabolic requirements for the growth and colonization capacity of Campylobacter jejuni. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 2014;4:137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4178425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25325018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garber J.M., Nothaft H., Pluvinage B., Stahl M., Bian X., Porfirio S., Enriquez A., Butcher J., Huang H., Glushka J. The gastrointestinal pathogen Campylobacter jejuni metabolizes sugars with potential help from commensal Bacteroides vulgatus. Commun. Biol. 2020;3(1):1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6946681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31925306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parsons C.M. Influence of caecectomy and source of dietary fibre or starch on excretion of endogenous amino acids by laying hens. Br. J. Nutr. 1984;51(3):541–548.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6326800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vorwerk H., Mohr J., Huber C., Wensel O., Schmidt‐Hohagen K., Gripp E., Josenhans C., Schomburg D., Eisenreich W., Hofreuter D. Utilization of host‐derived cysteine‐containing peptides overcomes the restricted sulphur metabolism of Campylobacter jejuni. Mol. Microbiol. 2014;93(6):1224–1245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25074326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwivedi R., Nothaft H., Garber J., Xin Kin L., Stahl M., Flint A., van Vliet A.H., Stintzi A., Szymanski C.M. L‐fucose influences chemotaxis and biofilm formation in Campylobacter jejuni. Mol. Microbiol. 2016;101(4):575–589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27145048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muraoka W.T., Zhang Q. Phenotypic and genotypic evidence for L-fucose utilization by Campylobacter jejuni. J. Bacteriol. 2011;193(5):1065–1075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3067607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21193610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stahl M., Friis L.M., Nothaft H., Liu X., Li J., Szymanski C.M., Stintzi A. L-fucose utilization provides Campylobacter jejuni with a competitive advantage. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2011;108(17):7194–7199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3084102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21482772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Hooft J.J., Alghefari W., Watson E., Everest P., Morton F.R., Burgess K.E., Smith D.G. Unexpected differential metabolic responses of Campylobacter jejuni to the abundant presence of glutamate and fucose. Metabolomics. 2018;14(11):1–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6208705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30830405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vegge C.S., Jansen van Rensburg M.J., Rasmussen J.J., Maiden M.C., Johnsen L.G., Danielsen M., MacIntyre S., Ingmer H., Kelly D.J. Glucose metabolism via the Entner-Doudoroff pathway in Campylobacter: a rare trait that enhances survival and promotes biofilm formation in some isolates. Front. Microbiol. 2016;7:1877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5118423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27920773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middendorf P.S., Jacobs-Reitsma W.F., Zomer A.L., den Besten H.M., Abee T. Comparative analysis of L-fucose utilization and its impact on growth and survival of Campylobacter isolates. Front. Microbiol. 2022;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9100392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35572645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas M.T., Shepherd M., Poole R.K., van Vliet A.H., Kelly D.J., Pearson B.M. Two respiratory enzyme systems in Campylobacter jejuni NCTC 11168 contribute to growth on L‐lactate. Environ. Microbiol. 2011;13(1):48–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20653766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luijkx Y.M., Bleumink N.M., Jiang J., Overkleeft H.S., Wösten M.M., Strijbis K., Wennekes T. Bacteroides fragilis fucosidases facilitate growth and invasion of Campylobacter jejuni in the presence of mucins. Cell Microbiol. 2020;22(12)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32827216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elmi A., Nasher F., Dorrell N., Wren B., Gundogdu O. Revisiting Campylobacter jejuni virulence and fitness factors: role in sensing, adapting, and competing. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 2021:895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7887314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33614526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mughini-Gras L., Pijnacker R., Coipan C., Mulder A.C., Veludo A.F., de Rijk S., van Hoek A.H., Buij R., Muskens G., Koene M. Sources and transmission routes of campylobacteriosis: a combined analysis of genome and exposure data. J. Infect. 2021;82(2):216–226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33275955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page A.J., Cummins C.A., Hunt M., Wong V.K., Reuter S., Holden M.T., Fookes M., Falush D., Keane J.A., Parkhill J. Roary: rapid large-scale prokaryote pan genome analysis. Bioinformatics. 2015;31(22):3691–3693.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4817141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26198102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wijnands L.M., Teunis P.F., Kuijpers A.F., Delfgou-Van Asch E.H., Pielaat A. Quantification of Salmonella survival and infection in an in vitro model of the human intestinal tract as proxy for foodborne pathogens. Front. Microbiol. 2017;8:1139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5491934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28713334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batth T.S., Tollenaere M.X., Rüther P., Gonzalez-Franquesa A., Prabhakar B.S., Bekker-Jensen S., Deshmukh A.S., Olsen J.V. Protein aggregation capture on microparticles enables multipurpose proteomics sample preparation. Mol. Cell. Proteomics. 2019;18(5):1027–1035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6495262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30833379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Tempelaars M.H., Boeren S., Alexeeva S., Smid E.J., Abee T. Extracellular vesicle formation in Lactococcus lactis is stimulated by prophage‐encoded holin–lysin system. Microb. Biotechnol. 2022;15(4):1281–1295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8966010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35229476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox J., Hein M.Y., Luber C.A., Paron I., Nagaraj N., Mann M. Accurate proteome-wide label-free quantification by delayed normalization and maximal peptide ratio extraction, termed MaxLFQ. Mol. Cell. Proteomics. 2014;13(9):2513–2526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4159666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24942700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyanova S., Temu T., Sinitcyn P., Carlson A., Hein M.Y., Geiger T., Mann M., Cox J. The Perseus computational platform for comprehensive analysis of (prote) omics data. Nat. Methods. 2016;13(9):731–740.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27348712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wösten M.M., van Dijk L., Parker C.T., Guilhabert M.R., van der Meer-Janssen Y.P., Wagenaar J.A., van Putten J.P. Growth phase-dependent activation of the DccRS regulon of Campylobacter jejuni. J. Bacteriol. 2010;192(11):2729–2736.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2876482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20348251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bravo V., Katz A., Porte L., Weitzel T., Varela C., Gonzalez-Escalona N., Blondel C.J. Genomic analysis of the diversity, antimicrobial resistance and virulence potential of clinical Campylobacter jejuni and Campylobacter coli strains from Chile. PLoS Neglected Trop. Dis. 2021;15(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7928456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33606689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu B., Zheng D., Jin Q., Chen L., Yang J. Vfdb 2019: a comparative pathogenomic platform with an interactive web interface. Nucleic Acids Res. 2019;47(D1):D687–D692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6324032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30395255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Redondo N., Carroll A., McNamara E. Molecular characterization of Campylobacter causing human clinical infection using whole-genome sequencing: virulence, antimicrobial resistance and phylogeny in Ireland. PLoS One. 2019;14(7)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6619736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31291319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dasti J.I., Tareen A.M., Lugert R., Zautner A.E., Groß U. Campylobacter jejuni: a brief overview on pathogenicity-associated factors and disease-mediating mechanisms. International Journal of Medical Microbiology. 2010;300(4):205–211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19665925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper K.K., Cooper M.A., Zuccolo A., Joens L.A. Re-sequencing of a virulent strain of Campylobacter jejuni NCTC11168 reveals potential virulence factors. Res. Microbiol. 2013;164(1):6–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23046762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panzenhagen P., Portes A.B., Dos Santos A.M., Duque S.d.S., Conte Junior C.A. The distribution of Campylobacter jejuni virulence genes in genomes worldwide derived from the NCBI pathogen detection database. Genes. 2021;12(10):1538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8535712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34680933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sałamaszyńska-Guz A., Rasmussen P.K., Murawska M., Douthwaite S. Campylobacter jejuni virulence factors identified by modulating their synthesis on ribosomes with altered rRNA methylation. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 2022:1390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8794745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35096652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taheri N., Mahmud A.F., Sandblad L., Fällman M., Wai S.N., Fahlgren A. Campylobacter jejuni bile exposure influences outer membrane vesicles protein content and bacterial interaction with epithelial cells. Sci. Rep. 2018;8(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6242867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30451931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du X., Kong K., Tang H., Tang H., Jiao X., Huang J. The novel protein Cj0371 inhibits chemotaxis of Campylobacter jejuni. Front. Microbiol. 2018;9:1904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6104132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30158919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao B., Vorwerk H., Huber C., Lara-Tejero M., Mohr J., Goodman A.L., Eisenreich W., Galán J.E., Hofreuter D. Metabolic and fitness determinants for in vitro growth and intestinal colonization of the bacterial pathogen Campylobacter jejuni. PLoS Biol. 2017;15(5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5438104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28542173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pascoe B., Williams L.K., Calland J.K., Meric G., Hitchings M.D., Dyer M., Ryder J., Shaw S., Lopes B.S., Chintoan-Uta C. Domestication of Campylobacter jejuni NCTC 11168. Microb. Genom. 2019;5(7)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6700657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31310201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flint A., Butcher J., Clarke C., Marlow D., Stintzi A. Use of a rabbit soft tissue chamber model to investigate Campylobacter jejuni–host interactions. Front. Microbiol. 2010;1:126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3109488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21687769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene N.P., Kaplan E., Crow A., Koronakis V. Antibiotic resistance mediated by the MacB ABC transporter family: a structural and functional perspective. Front. Microbiol. 2018;9:950.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5985334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29892271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogomolnaya L.M., Andrews K.D., Talamantes M., Maple A., Ragoza Y., Vazquez-Torres A., Andrews-Polymenis H. The ABC-type efflux pump MacAB protects Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium from oxidative stress. mBio. 2013;4(6) 00630-13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3809562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24169575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishino K., Latifi T., Groisman E.A. Virulence and drug resistance roles of multidrug efflux systems of Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium. Mol. Microbiol. 2006;59(1):126–141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16359323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guérin A., Sulaeman S., Coquet L., Ménard A., Barloy-Hubler F., Dé E., Tresse O. Membrane proteocomplexome of Campylobacter jejuni using 2-D blue native/SDS-PAGE combined to bioinformatics analysis. Front. Microbiol. 2020;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7717971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33329413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hameed A., Woodacre A., Machado L.R., Marsden G.L. An updated classification system and review of the lipooligosaccharide biosynthesis gene locus in Campylobacter jejuni. Front. Microbiol. 2020;11:677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7248181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32508756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burnham P.M., Hendrixson D.R. Campylobacter jejuni: collective components promoting a successful enteric lifestyle. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2018;16(9):551–565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29892020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szymanski C.M. Bacterial glycosylation, it's complicated. Front. Mol. Biosci. 2022:1089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9561416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36250013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alav I., Kobylka J., Kuth M.S., Pos K.M., Picard M., Blair J.M., Bavro V.N. Structure, assembly, and function of tripartite efflux and type 1 secretion systems in gram-negative bacteria. Chem. Rev. 2021;121(9):5479–5596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8277102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33909410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>