<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39222884</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1095-8304</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>203</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>31</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Appetite</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appetite</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Risk it for a biscuit: Food safety behaviours and food insecurity of older adults.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>107650</StartPage><MedlinePgn>107650</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.appet.2024.107650</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0195-6663(24)00453-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Foodborne disease presents a significant public health issue, costing the UK economy £9 billion annually, with many incidences being due to food-related behaviours in the home. Adults aged 60 and over account for around a quarter of the population in England and Wales and are at a greater risk of foodborne disease and may suffer a much higher burden. Research into risky food behaviours has previously focused on larger cohorts and typically treats the over 60's as one homogenous group. The current paper aims to identify the characteristics associated with risky food-related practices related to cooking, cleaning, chilling, cross-contamination, and use-by date adherence. The current research analysed data from the Official Statistics survey, Food and You 2: Wave 6 (2022-23). A series of binary logistic regression models examined the characteristics associated with risky food-related practices. We demonstrate that the characteristics associated with risky behaviours are not uniform, with different factors being associated with specific behaviours. We suggest that risky behaviours cannot be targeted efficiently with a one size fits all approach. This research provides an evidence base for policy makers to target risky food behaviours in this understudied vulnerable group.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Armstrong</LastName><ForeName>Beth</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Geography, The University of Sheffield, Winter Street, Sheffield, S10 2TN, UK. Electronic address: m.armstrong@sheffield.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Rachel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food and Nutritional Sciences, School of Chemistry, Food and Pharmacy, The University of Reading, Reading, RG6 6LA, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garratt</LastName><ForeName>Elisabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sheffield Methods Institute, The University of Sheffield, 2 Whitham Rd, Sheffield, S10 2AH, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>31</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Appetite</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8006808</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0195-6663</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest Dr Smith and Dr Garrett have no declarations of interest to disclose. Dr Armstrong has received research funding from the Food Standards Agency (FSA) to find her current fellowship position. The views express in this paper are her own and do not reflect the position of the FSA.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39222884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.appet.2024.107650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0195-6663(24)00453-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>