<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39230391</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A review of conditions influencing fate of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O157:H7 in leafy greens.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70013</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70013</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70013</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The accuracy of predictive microbial models used in quantitative microbial risk assessment (QMRA) relies on the relevancy of conditions influencing growth or inactivation. The continued use of log-linear models in studies remains widespread, despite evidence that they fail to accurately account for biphasic kinetics or include parameters to account for the effect of environmental conditions within the model equation. Although many experimental studies detail conditions of interest, studies that do not do so lead to uncertainty in QMRA modeling because the applicability of the predictive microbial models to the conditions in the risk scenarios is questionable or must be extrapolated. The current study systematically reviewed 65 articles that provided quantitative data and documented the conditions influencing the inactivation or growth of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) O157:H7 in leafy greens. The conditions were identified and categorized as environmental, biological, chemical, and/or processing. Our study found that temperature (n = 37 studies) and sanitizing and washing procedures (n = 12 studies) were the most studied conditions in the farm-to-table continuum of leafy greens. In addition, relative humidity was also established to affect growth and inactivation in more than one stage in the continuum. This study proposes the evaluation of the interactive effects of multiple conditions in processing and storage stages from controlled experiments as they relate to the fate of STEC O157:H7 in leafy greens for future quantitative analysis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Owade</LastName><ForeName>Joshua Ombaka</ForeName><Initials>JO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Human Nutrition, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biosystems and Agricultural Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bergholz</LastName><ForeName>Teresa M</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Human Nutrition, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mitchell</LastName><ForeName>Jade</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2199-4190</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biosystems and Agricultural Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>AM21SCBPCA1002</GrantID><Agency>U.S. Department of Agriculture's (USDA) Agricultural Marketing Service</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Center for Produce Safety</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019453" MajorTopicYN="Y">Escherichia coli O157</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013696" MajorTopicYN="N">Temperature</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014675" MajorTopicYN="N">Vegetables</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005511" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Handling</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018570" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054323" MajorTopicYN="N">Shiga-Toxigenic Escherichia coli</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">STEC O157:H7</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">conditions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">farm‐to‐table</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">growth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inactivation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lettuce</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39230391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdul‐Raouf, U. M., Beuchat, L. R., &amp; Ammar, M. S. (1993). Survival and growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on salad vegetables. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 59(7), 1999–2006. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.59.7.1999‐2006.1993</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abnavi, M. D., Kothapalli, C. R., Munther, D., &amp; Srinivasan, P. (2021). Chlorine inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in fresh produce wash process: Effectiveness and modeling. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 356, Article 109364. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2021.109364</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belias, A. M., Sbodio, A., Truchado, P., Weller, D., Pinzon, J., Skots, M., Allende, A., Munther, D., Suslow, T., Wiedmann, M., &amp; Ivanek, R. (2020). Effect of weather on the die‐off of Escherichia coli and attenuated Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium on preharvest leafy greens following irrigation with contaminated water. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 86(17), Article e00899‐20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bezanson, G., Delaquis, P., Bach, S., McKellar, R., Topp, E., Gill, A., Blais, B., &amp; Gilmour, M. (2012). Comparative examination of Escherichia coli O157:H7 survival on romaine lettuce and in soil at two independent experimental sites. Journal of Food Protection, 75(3), 480–487. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐11‐306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyacioglu, O., Sharma, M., Sulakvelidze, A., &amp; Goktepe, I. (2013). Biocontrol of Escherichia coli O157. Bacteriophage, 3(1), Article e24620. https://doi.org/10.4161/bact.24620</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer, A. F., Eisenberg, M. C., Remais, J. V., Collender, P. A., Meza, R., &amp; Eisenberg, J. N. S. (2017). Modeling biphasic environmental decay of pathogens and implications for risk analysis. Environmental Science and Technology, 51(4), 2186–2196. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.6b04030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cámara, M., Giner, R. M., González‐Fandos, E., López‐García, E., Mañes, J., Portillo, M. P., Rafecas, M., Domínguez, L., &amp; Martínez, J. A. (2021). Food‐based dietary guidelines around the world: A comparative analysis to update AESAN scientific committee dietary recommendations. Nutrients, 13(9), Article 3131. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13093131</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). (2022). National Outbreak Reporting System (NORS). Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. https://wwwn.cdc.gov/norsdashboard/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang, J. M., &amp; Fang, T. J. (2007). Survival of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella enterica serovars Typhimurium in iceberg lettuce and the antimicrobial effect of rice vinegar against E. coli O157:H7. Food Microbiology, 24(7–8), 745–751. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2007.03.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chase, J. A., Atwill, E. R., Partyka, M. L., Bond, R. F., &amp; Oryang, D. (2017). Inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on romaine lettuce when inoculated in a fecal slurry matrix. Journal of Food Protection, 80(5), 792–798. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐16‐307</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chase, J. A., Partyka, M. L., Bond, R. F., &amp; Atwill, E. R. (2019). Environmental inactivation and irrigation‐mediated regrowth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on romaine lettuce when inoculated in a fecal slurry matrix. PeerJ, 7, Article e6591. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.6591</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, S., Bang, J., Kim, H., Beuchat, L. R., &amp; Ryu, J.‐H. (2011). Survival and colonization of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on spinach leaves as affected by inoculum level and carrier, temperature and relative humidity. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 111(6), 1465–1472. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2672.2011.05175.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coulombe, G., Catford, A., Martinez‐Perez, A., &amp; Buenaventura, E. (2020). Outbreaks of Escherichia coli O157:H7 infections linked to Romaine Lettuce in Canada from 2008 to 2018: An analysis of food safety context. Journal of Food Protection, 83(8), 1444–1462. https://doi.org/10.4315/JFP‐20‐029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, H., Bai, M., Yuan, L., Surendhiran, D., &amp; Lin, L. (2018). Sequential effect of phages and cold nitrogen plasma against Escherichia coli O157:H7 biofilms on different vegetables. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 268, 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.01.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson, G. R., Kaminski, C. N., &amp; Ryser, E. T. (2014). Impact of organic load on Escherichia coli O157:H7 survival during pilot‐scale processing of iceberg lettuce with acidified sodium hypochlorite. Journal of Food Protection, 77(10), 1669–1681. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐14‐067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson, G. R., Kaminski‐Davidson, C. N., &amp; Ryser, E. T. (2017). Persistence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 during pilot‐scale processing of iceberg lettuce using flume water containing peroxyacetic acid‐based sanitizers and various organic loads. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 248, 22–31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2017.02.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dean, K., &amp; Mitchell, J. (2022). Meta‐analysis addressing the implications of model uncertainty in understanding the persistence of indicators and pathogens in natural surface waters. Environmental Science and Technology, 56(17), 12106–12115. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.1c07552</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delbeke, S., Ceuppens, S., Jacxsens, L., &amp; Uyttendaele, M. (2015). Survival of Salmonella and Escherichia coli O157:H7 on strawberries, basil, and other leafy greens during storage. Journal of Food Protection, 78(4), 652–660. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐14‐354</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz, C., &amp; Hotchkiss, J. H. (1996). Comparative growth of Escherichia coli 0157:H7, spoilage organisms and shelf‐life of shredded iceberg lettuce stored under modified atmospheres. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 70(4), 433–438. https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1097‐0010(199604)70:4&lt;433::AID‐JSFA518&gt;3.0.CO;2‐Q</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, T., Jin, Y., Rahman, S. M. E., Kim, J., Choi, K., Choi, G., &amp; Oh, D. (2009). Prediction of growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in lettuce treated with alkaline electrolyzed water at different temperatures. Journal of Food Hygiene and Safety, 24(3), 232–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinu, L. D., &amp; Bach, S. (2011). Induction of viable but nonculturable Escherichia coli O157:H7 in the phyllosphere of lettuce: A food safety risk factors. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 77(23), 8295–8302. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.05020‐11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dixit, A. R., Khodadad, C. L. M., Hummerick, M. E., Spern, C. J., Spencer, L. S. E., Fischer, J. A., Curry, A. B., Gooden, J. L., Maldonado Vazquez, G. J., Wheeler, R. M., Massa, G. D., &amp; Romeyn, M. W. (2021). Persistence of Escherichia coli in the microbiomes of red Romaine lettuce (Lactuca sativa cv. ‘Outredgeous’) and mizuna mustard (Brassica rapa var. japonica)—Does seed sanitization matter? BMC Microbiology, 21(1), Article 289. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866‐021‐02345‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doering, H. J., Harrison, M. A., Morrow, R. A., Hurst, W. C., &amp; Kerr, W. L. (2009). Use of the systems approach to determine the fate of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on fresh lettuce and spinach. Journal of Food Protection, 72(7), 1560–1568. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐72.7.1560</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ergönül, B. (2011). Survival characteristics of Salmonella Typhimurium and Escherichia coli O157:H7 in minimally processed lettuce during storage at different temperatures. Journal Fur Verbraucherschutz Und Lebensmittelsicherheit, 6(3), 339–342. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00003‐010‐0646‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erickson, M. C., Webb, C. C., Diaz‐Perez, J. C., Phatak, S. C., Silvoy, J. J., Davey, L., Payton, A. S., Liao, J., Ma, L., &amp; Doyle, M. P. (2010). Surface and internalized Escherichia coli O157: H7 on field‐grown spinach and lettuce treated with spray‐contaminated irrigation water. Journal of Food Protection, 73(6), 1023–1029. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐73.6.1023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO/WHO. (2019). Attributing illness caused by Shiga toxin‐producing Escherichia coli (STEC) to specific foods. Microbiological Risk Assessment Series 32. FAO and WHO. https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/326923/9789241516396‐eng.pdf?ua=1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francis, G. A., &amp; O'Beirne, D. (2001). Effects of vegetable type, package atmosphere and storage temperature on growth and survival of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Listeria monocytogenes. Journal of Industrial Microbiology and Biotechnology, 27(2), 111–116. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.jim.7000094</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franz, E., &amp; van Bruggen, A. H. C. (2008). Ecology of E. coli O157:H7 and Salmonella enterica in the primary vegetable production chain. Critical Reviews in Microbiology, 34(3–4), 143–161. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408410802357432</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gleeson, E., &amp; O'Beirne, D. (2005). Effects of process severity on survival and growth of Escherichia coli and Listeria innocua on minimally processed vegetables. Food Control, 16(8), 677–685. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2004.06.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton, A. J., Stagnitti, F., Premier, R., Boland, A. M., &amp; Hale, G. (2006). Quantitative microbial risk assessment models for consumption of raw vegetables irrigated with reclaimed water. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 72(5), 3284–3290. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.72.5.3284‐3290.2006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibekwe, A. M., Grieve, C. M., Papiernik, S. K., &amp; Yang, C.‐H. (2009). Persistence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on the rhizosphere and phyllosphere of lettuce. Letters in Applied Microbiology, 49(6), 784–790. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1472‐765X.2009.02745.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibekwe, A. M., Grieve, C. M., &amp; Yang, C.‐H. (2007). Survival of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in soil and on lettuce after soil fumigation. Canadian Journal of Microbiology, 53(5), 623–635. https://doi.org/10.1139/W07‐003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IFPA, PMA, UFFVA, &amp; WGA. (2006). Commodity specific food safety guidelines for the lettuce and leafy greens supply chain. http://www.fda.gov/downloads/Food/GuidanceRegulation/UCM169008.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ingram, D. T., Pate, J., &amp; Sharma, M. (2011). Effect of repeated irrigation with water containing varying levels of total organic carbon on the persistence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on baby spinach. Journal of Food Protection, 74(5), 709–717. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐10‐426</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Işık, H., Topalcengiz, Z., Güner, S., &amp; Aksoy, A. (2020). Generic and Shiga toxin‐producing Escherichia coli (O157:H7) contamination of lettuce and radish microgreens grown in peat moss and perlite. Food Control, 111, Article 107079. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.107079</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam, M., Doyle, M. P., Phatak, S. C., Millner, P., &amp; Jiang, X. (2004). Persistence of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli O157:H7 in soil and on leaf lettuce and parsley grown in fields treated with contaminated manure composts or irrigation water. Journal of Food Protection, 67(7), 1365–1370. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐67.7.1365</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam, M., Morgan, J., Doyle, M. P., &amp; Jiang, X. (2004). Fate of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in manure compost‐amended soil and on carrots and onions grown in an environmentally controlled growth chamber. Journal of Food Protection, 67(3), 574–578. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐67.3.574</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeamsripong, S., Chase, J. A., Jay‐Russell, M. T., Buchanan, R. L., &amp; Atwill, E. R. (2019). Experimental in‐field transfer and survival of Escherichia coli from animal feces to romaine lettuce in Salinas valley, California. Microorganisms, 7(10), Article 408. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms7100408</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalmpourtzidou, A., Eilander, A., &amp; Talsma, E. F. (2020). Global vegetable intake and supply compared to recommendations: A systematic review. Nutrients, 12(6), 22–29. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12061558</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalil, R. K. S. (2016). Effect of abusive storage temperatures on growth and survival of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on leafy salad vegetables in Egypt. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology, 65, 954–962. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2015.09.034</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J., Chung, H., Cho, J., &amp; Yoon, K. (2013). Evaluation of models describing the growth of nalidixic acid‐resistant E. coli O157:H7 in blanched spinach and iceberg lettuce as a function of temperature. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 10(7), 2857–2870. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph10072857</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kintz, E., Byrne, L., Jenkins, C., McCarthy, N., Vivancos, R., &amp; Hunter, P. (2019). Outbreaks of Shiga toxin–producing Escherichia coli linked to sprouted seeds, salad, and leafy greens: A systematic review. Journal of Food Protection, 82(11), 1950–1958. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐19‐014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koseki, S., &amp; Isobe, S. (2005). Prediction of pathogen growth on iceberg lettuce under real temperature history during distribution from farm to table. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 104(3), 239–248. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2005.02.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, S. Y., &amp; Baek, S. Y. (2008). Effect of chemical sanitizer combined with modified atmosphere packaging on inhibiting Escherichia coli O157:H7 in commercial spinach. Food Microbiology, 25(4), 582–587. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2008.02.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Brackett, R. E., Chen, J., &amp; Beuchat, L. R. (2001). Survival and growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 inoculated onto cut lettuce before or after heating in chlorinated water, followed by storage at 5 or 15°C. Journal of Food Protection, 64(3), 305–309. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐64.3.305</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Likotrafiti, E., Smirniotis, P., Nastou, A., &amp; Rhoades, J. (2013). Effect of relative humidity and storage temperature on the behavior of Listeria monocytogenes on fresh vegetables. Journal of Food Safety, 33(4), 545–551. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfs.12087</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luna‐Guevara, J. J., Arenas‐Hernandez, M. M. P., de la Peña, C. M., Silva, J. L., &amp; Luna‐Guevara, M. L. (2019). The role of pathogenic E. coli in fresh vegetables: Behavior, contamination factors, and preventive measures. International Journal of Microbiology, 2019, Article 2894328. https://doi.org/10.1155/2019/2894328</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, Y., He, Q., &amp; McEvoy, J. L. (2010). Effect of storage temperature and duration on the behavior of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on packaged fresh‐cut salad containing romaine and iceberg lettuce. Journal of Food Science, 75(7), M390–M397. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1750‐3841.2010.01722.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, Y., He, Q., McEvoy, J. L., &amp; Conway, W. S. (2009). Fate of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in the presence of indigenous microorganisms on commercially packaged baby spinach, as impacted by storage temperature and time. Journal of Food Protection, 72(10), 2038–2045. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐72.10.2038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madamba, T., Moreira, R. G., Castell‐Perez, E., Banerjee, A., &amp; da Silva, D. (2022a). Agent‐based simulation of cross‐contamination of Escherichia coli O157:H7 On lettuce during processing with temperature fluctuations during storage in a produce facility. Part 1: Model development. Journal of Food Process Engineering, 45(4), Article e14002. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpe.13983</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madamba, T., Moreira, R. G., Castell‐Perez, E., Banerjee, A., &amp; da Silva, D. (2022b). Agent‐based simulation of cross‐contamination of Escherichia coli O157:H7 On lettuce during processing with temperature fluctuations during storage in a produce facility. Part 2: Model development. Journal of Food Process Engineering, 45(4), Article e13983. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpe.14002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoud, B. S. M., &amp; Linton, R. H. (2008). Inactivation kinetics of inoculated Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella enterica on lettuce by chlorine dioxide gas. Food Microbiology, 25(2), 244–252. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2007.10.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markland, S. M., Shortlidge, K. L., Hoover, D. G., Yaron, S., Patel, J., Singh, A., Sharma, M., &amp; Kniel, K. E. (2013). Survival of pathogenic Escherichia coli on basil, lettuce, and spinach. Zoonoses and Public Health, 60(8), 563–571. https://doi.org/10.1111/zph.12033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKellar, R. C., Leblanc, D. I., Lu, J., &amp; Delaquis, P. (2012). Simulation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 behavior in fresh‐cut lettuce under dynamic temperature conditions during distribution from processing to retail. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease, 9(3), 239–244. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2011.1025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKellar, R. C., Peréz‐Rodríguez, F., Harris, L. J., Moyne, A. l., Blais, B., Topp, E., Bezanson, G., Bach, S., &amp; Delaquis, P. (2014). Evaluation of different approaches for modeling Escherichia coli O157:H7 survival on field lettuce. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 184, 74–85. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.04.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Min, S. C., Roh, S. H., Boyd, G., Sites, J. E., Uknalis, J., Fan, X., &amp; Niemira, B. A. (2017). Inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Aerobic Microorganisms in Romaine Lettuce Packaged in a Commercial Polyethylene Terephthalate Container Using Atmospheric Cold Plasma. Journal of Food Protection, 80(1), 35–43. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028x.jfp‐16‐148</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell, J., &amp; Akram, S. (2017). Pathogen specific persistence modeling data. In J. B. Rose &amp; B. Jiménez‐Cisneros (Eds.), Water and sanitation for the 21st century: Health and microbiological aspects of excreta and wastewater management (Global water pathogen project) (pp. 1–20). UNESCO. https://doi.org/10.14321/waterpathogens.53</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyne, A. L., Blessington, T., Williams, T. R., Koike, S. T., Cahn, M. D., Marco, M. L., &amp; Harris, L. J. (2020). Conditions at the time of inoculation influence survival of attenuated Escherichia coli O157:H7 on field‐inoculated lettuce. Food Microbiology, 85, Article 103274. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2019.103274</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyne, A. L., Harris, L. J., &amp; Marco, M. L. (2013). Assessments of total and viable Escherichia coli O157:H7 on field and laboratory grown lettuce. PLoS ONE, 8(7), Article e70643. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0070643</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyne, A. L., Sudarshana, M. R., Blessington, T., Koike, S. T., Cahn, M. D., &amp; Harris, L. J. (2011). Fate of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in field‐inoculated lettuce. Food Microbiology, 28(8), 1417–1425. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2011.02.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukhopadhyay, S., Sokorai, K., Ukuku, D. O., Jin, T., Fan, X., Olanya, O. M., Leng, J., &amp; Juneja, V. (2021). Effects of direct and in‐package pulsed light treatment on inactivation of E. coli O157:H7 and reduction of microbial loads in Romaine lettuce. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology, 139, Article 110710. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.110710</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munther, D. S., Carter, M. Q., Aldric, C. V., Ivanek, R., &amp; Brandl, M. T. (2020). Formation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 persister cells in the lettuce phyllosphere and application of differential equation models to predict their prevalence on lettuce plants in the field. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 86(2), Article e01602‐19. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01602‐19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neal, J. A., Cabrera‐Diaz, E., Márquez‐González, M., Maxim, J. E., &amp; Castillo, A. (2008). Reduction of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella on baby spinach, using electron beam radiation. Journal of Food Protection, 71(12), 2415–2420. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐71.12.2415</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noor, R., Malek, M., Rahman, S., Meghla, M., Acharjee, M., &amp; Rahman, M. M. (2015). Assessment of survival of pathogenic bacteria in fresh vegetables through in vitro challenge test. International Journal of Food Contamination, 2(1), Article 15. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40550‐015‐0021‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nou, X., Luo, Y., Hollar, L., Yang, Y., Feng, H., Millner, P., &amp; Shelton, D. (2011). Chlorine stabilizer T‐128 enhances efficacy of chlorine against cross‐contamination by E. coli O157:H7 and Salmonella in fresh‐cut lettuce processing. Journal of Food Science, 76(3), 218–224. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1750‐3841.2011.02046.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira, M., Usall, J., Solsona, C., Alegre, I., Viñas, I., &amp; Abadias, M. (2010). Effects of packaging type and storage temperature on the growth of foodborne pathogens on shredded “Romaine” lettuce. Food Microbiology, 27(3), 375–380. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2009.11.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Toole, G. A. (2016). Classic spotlight: Plate counting you can count on. Journal of Bacteriology, 198(23), 3127–3127. https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00711‐16</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ottoson, J. R., Nyberg, K., Lindqvist, R., &amp; Albihn, A. (2011). Quantitative microbial risk assessment for Escherichia coli O157 on lettuce, based on survival data from controlled studies in a climate chamber. Journal of Food Protection, 74(12), 2000–2007. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐10‐563</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page, M. J., McKenzie, J. E., Bossuyt, P. M., Boutron, I., Hoffmann, T. C., Mulrow, C. D., Shamseer, L., Tetzlaff, J. M., Akl, E. A., Brennan, S. E., Chou, R., Glanville, J., Grimshaw, J. M., Hróbjartsson, A., Lalu, M. M., Li, T., Loder, E. W., Mayo‐Wilson, E., McDonald, S., … Moher, D. (2021). The PRISMA 2020 statement: An updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. International Journal of Surgery, 88, Article 105906. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijsu.2021.105906</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang, H., Lambertini, E., Buchanan, R. L., Schaffner, D. W., &amp; Pradhan, A. K. (2017). Quantitative microbial risk assessment for Escherichia coli O157:H7 in fresh‐cut lettuce. Journal of Food Protection, 80(2), 302–311. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐16‐246</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parabhoi, L. (2017). How Mendeley helps to your research work? In M. K. Stanley (Ed.), National Conference of Agricultural Libraries &amp; User Community (NCALUC‐2017) on Libraries Beyond Borders: Navigating Towards Global Dissemination, January (pp. 64–70). BS Publication.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posada‐Izquierdo, G. D., Pérez‐Rodríguez, F., López‐Gálvez, F., Allende, A., Gil, M. I., &amp; Zurera, G. (2014). Modeling growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in fresh‐cut lettuce treated with neutral electrolyzed water and under modified atmosphere packaging. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 177, 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.12.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posada‐Izquierdo, G. D., Pérez‐Rodríguez, F., López‐Gálvez, F., Allende, A., Selma, M. V., Gil, M. I., &amp; Zurera, G. (2013). Modelling growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in fresh‐cut lettuce submitted to commercial process conditions: Chlorine washing and modified atmosphere packaging. Food Microbiology, 33(2), 131–138. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2012.08.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puerta‐Gomez, A. F., Moreira, R. G., Kim, J., &amp; Castell‐Perez, E. (2013). Modeling the growth rates of Escherichia coli spp. and Salmonella Typhimurium LT2 in baby spinach leaves under slow cooling. Food Control, 29(1), 11–17. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.05.070</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seidu, R., Sjølander, I., Abubakari, A., Amoah, D., Larbi, J. A., &amp; Stenström, T. A. (2013). Modeling the die‐off of E. coli and Ascaris in wastewater‐irrigated vegetables: Implications for microbial health risk reduction associated with irrigation cessation. Water Science and Technology, 68(5), 1013–1021. https://doi.org/10.2166/wst.2013.335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, M., Lakshman, S., Ferguson, S., Ingram, D. T., Luo, Y., &amp; Patel, J. (2011). Effect of modified atmosphere packaging on the persistence and expression of virulence factors of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on shredded iceberg lettuce. Journal of Food Protection, 74(5), 718–726. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐10‐427</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Söderqvist, K., Ahmed Osman, O., Wolff, C., Bertilsson, S., Vågsholm, I., &amp; Boqvist, S. (2017). Emerging microbiota during cold storage and temperature abuse of ready‐to‐eat salad. Infection Ecology and Epidemiology, 7(1), Article 1328963. https://doi.org/10.1080/20008686.2017.1328963</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon, E. B., Pang, H.‐J., &amp; Matthews, K. R. (2003). Persistence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on lettuce plants following spray irrigation with contaminated water. Journal of Food Protection, 66(12), 2198–2202. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐66.12.2198</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, Y. S., Stewart, D., Reineke, K., Wang, L., Ma, C., Lu, Y., Shazer, A., Deng, K., &amp; Tortorello, M. L. (2019). Effects of package atmosphere and storage conditions on minimizing risk of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in packaged fresh baby spinach. Journal of Food Protection, 82(5), 844–853. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐18‐337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theofel, C. G., &amp; Harris, L. J. (2009). Impact of preinoculation culture conditions on the behavior of Escherichia coli O157:H7 inoculated onto romaine lettuce (Lactuca sativa) plants and cut leaf surfaces. Journal of Food Protection, 72(7), 1553–1559. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐72.7.1553</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyagi, D., Kraft, A. L., Smith, S. L., Roof, S. E., Sherwood, J. S., Wiedmann, M., &amp; Bergholz, T. M. (2019). Pre‐harvest survival and post‐harvest chlorine tolerance of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli on lettuce. Toxins, 11(11), Article 675. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins11110675</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uzeh, R. E., &amp; Adepoju, A. (2013). Incidence and survival of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Listeria monocytogenes on salad vegetables. International Food Research Journal, 20(4), 1921–1925. https://www.scopus.com/inward/record.uri?eid=2‐s2.0‐84884676693&amp;partnerID=40&amp;md5=4c0054d2106a5c9d72df45d8a829543e</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veys, O., de Elias, S. O., Sampers, I., &amp; Tondo, E. C. (2016). Modelling the growth of salmonella spp. and escherichia coli o157 on lettuce. Procedia Food Science, 7, 168–172. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.profoo.2016.10.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Membré, J.‐M., Ha, S.‐D., Bahk, G.‐J., Chung, M.‐S., Chun, H.‐S., Hwang, I.‐G., &amp; Oh, D.‐H. (2012). Modeling the combined effect of temperature and relative humidity on Escherichia coli O157:H7 on lettuce. Food Science and Biotechnology, 21(3), 859–865. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10068‐012‐0111‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Wang, Y. H., Dai, P. G., Chen, D. X., Zhao, T. C., Li, X. L., &amp; Huang, Q. (2017). First report of tobacco bacterial leaf blight caused by Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. Brasiliense in China. Plant Disease, 101(5), Article 830. https://doi.org/10.1094/PDIS‐10‐16‐1438‐PDN</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, W., Vorst, K., Brown, W., Marks, B. P., Jeong, S., Pérez‐Rodríguez, F., &amp; Ryser, E. T. (2014). Growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Listeria monocytogenes in packaged fresh‐cut romaine mix at fluctuating temperatures during commercial transport, retail storage, and display. Journal of Food Protection, 77(2), 197–206. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐13‐117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, G., Ma, L., Beuchat, L. R., Erickson, M. C., Phelan, V. H., &amp; Doyle, M. P. (2009). Lack of internalization of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in lettuce (Lactuca sativa L.) after leaf surface and soil inoculation. Journal of Food Protection, 72(10), 2028–2037. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐72.10.2028</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>