<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39233700</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2239-7132</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Italian journal of food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ital J Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Microbiological safety of dry-aged meat: a critical review of data gaps and research needs to define process hygiene and safety criteria.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>12438</StartPage><MedlinePgn>12438</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">12438</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4081/ijfs.2024.12438</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Dry-aged meat is gaining popularity among food business operators and private consumers. The process is carried out in aerobic conditions by hanging beef carcasses or placing subprimal or primal cuts in a dedicated cabinet for several weeks or even months while controlling the environment through the management of process parameters such as temperature, relative humidity, and airflow. In this review, we present a critical evaluation of the literature to evaluate tools to manage the process to guarantee food safety and identify critical control points, as well as good hygiene and manufacturing practices. In controlled aging conditions, only <i>Listeria monocytogenes</i> and <i>Yersinia enterocolitica</i> can multiply, while a reduction in the number of <i>Salmonella</i> spp. and <i>Escherichia coli</i> O157:H7 is generally reported. <i>Enterobacteriaceae</i> usually decrease on the surface of the meat during maturation; thus, for the purpose of the hygiene evaluation of the production process, a count no higher than that of unmatured meat is expected. Besides, various studies report that the total bacterial count and the spoilage microorganisms significantly increase on the surface of the meat, up to 5-6 Log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g in the absence of visible spoilage. Bacteria of the <i>Pseudomonas</i> genus tend to progressively replace other microorganisms during maturation; thus, the total mesophilic or psychrophilic bacterial load is not a good indicator of process hygiene for matured meat. Critical parameters for the control of the process are temperature, relative humidity, and ventilation, which should be monitored during the process. For this reason, equipment designed and certified for dry-aging must be used, and the manufacturer must validate the process. Food business operators must apply general good manufacturing practices (GMP) and good hygiene practices (GHP) for meat processing and some GMP and GHP specific for dry-aging. Several research needs were identified, among them the evolution of the populations of <i>L. monocytogenes</i> and <i>Y. enterocolitica</i> and the microbiology of the inner parts of the dry-aged meat.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, the Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Savini</LastName><ForeName>Federica</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Indio</LastName><ForeName>Valentina</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giacometti</LastName><ForeName>Federica</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Medicine, Production and Health, University of Padova, Legnaro.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mekkonnen</LastName><ForeName>Yitagele Terefe</ForeName><Initials>YT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>De Cesare</LastName><ForeName>Alessandra</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prandini</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marrone</LastName><ForeName>Raffaele</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Production, University of Naples "Federico II", Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seguino</LastName><ForeName>Alessandro</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Di Paolo</LastName><ForeName>Marika</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Production, University of Naples "Federico II", Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vuoso</LastName><ForeName>Valeria</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Production, University of Naples "Federico II", Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tomasello</LastName><ForeName>Federico</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Serraino</LastName><ForeName>Andrea</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna, Ozzano dell'Emilia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Italy</Country><MedlineTA>Ital J Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101684120</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2239-7132</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dry-aged meat</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbiological criteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molds</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenic microorganism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spoilage microorganism</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interest: the authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39233700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11369755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/ijfs.2024.12438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahnström ML, Seyfert M, Hunt MC, Johnson DE, 2006. Dry aging of beef in a bag highly permeable to water vapour. Meat Sci 73:674-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22062568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Álvarez S, Mullen AM, Hamill R, O’Neill E, Álvarez C, 2021. Dry-aging of beef as a tool to improve meat quality. Impact of processing conditions on the technical and organoleptic meat properties. Adv Food Nutr Res 95:97-130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33745517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beach JC, Murano EA, Acuff GR, 2002. Prevalence of Salmonella and Campylobacter in beef cattle from transport to slaughter. J Food Prot 65:1687-93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12430687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berger J, Kim YHB, Legako JF, Martini S, Lee J, Ebner P, Zuelly SMS, 2018. Dry-aging improves meat quality attributes of grass-fed beef loins. Meat Sci 145:285-91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30007174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernardo APDS, Da Silva ACM, Ferreira FMS, Do Nascimento MDS, Pflanzer SB, 2021. The effects of time and relative humidity on dry-aged beef: traditional versus special bag. Food Sci Technol Int 27:626-34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33322928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brichta-Harhay DM, Guerini MN, Arthur TM, Bosilevac JM, Kalchayanand N, Shackelford SD, Wheeler TL, Koohmaraie M, 2008. Salmonella and Escherichia coli O157:H7 contamination on hides and carcasses of cull cattle presented for slaughter in the United States: an evaluation of prevalence and bacterial loads by immunomagnetic separation and direct plating methods. Appl Environ Microbiol 74:6289-97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2570275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18723661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks FT, Hansford CG, 1923. Mould growths upon cold-store meat. Trans Br Mycol Soc 8:113-42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchanan RL, Gorris LGM, Hayman MM, Jackson TC, Whiting RC, 2017. A review of Listeria monocytogenes: an update on outbreaks, virulence, dose-response, ecology, and risk assessments. Food Control 75:1-13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell RE, Hunt MC, Levis P, Chambers E, 2001. Dry-aging effects on palatability of beef longissimus muscle. J Food Sci 66:196-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capouya R, Mitchell T, Clark DI, Clark DL, Bass P, 2020. A survey of microbial communities on dry-aged beef in commercial meat processing facilities. Meat and Muscle Biology 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherroud S, Cachaldora A, Fonseca S, Laglaoui A, Carballo J, Franco I, 2014. Microbiological and physicochemical characterization of dry-cured Halal goat meat. Effect of salting time and addition of olive oil and paprika covering. Meat Sci 98:129-34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24950081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colle MJ, Richard RP, Killinger KM, Bohlscheid JC, Gray AR, Loucks WI, Day RN, Cochran AS, Nasados JA, Doumit ME, 2016. Influence of extended aging on beef quality characteristics and sensory perception of steaks from the biceps femoris and semimembranosus. Meat Sci 119:110-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27155799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission of the European Communities, 2005. Commission Regulation (EC) No. 2073/2005 of 15 November 2005 on microbiological criteria for foodstuffs. In: Official Journal, L 338/1, 22/12/2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva ACM, de Oliveira Pena P, Pflanzer SB, da Silva do Nascimento M, 2019. Effect of different dry aging temperatures on Listeria innocua as surrogate for Listeria monocytogenes. Meat Sci 157:107884.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31323452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva Bernardo AP, da Silva ACM, Francisco VC, Ribeiro FA, Nassu RT, Calkins CR, da Silva do Nascimento M, Pflanzer SB, 2020. Effects of freezing and thawing on microbiological and physical-chemical properties of dry-aged beef. Meat Sci 161:108003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31734467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dashdorj D, Tripathi VK, Cho S, Kim Y, Hwang I, 2016. Dry aging of beef; review. J Anim Sci Technol 58:20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4872334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27200180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeGeer SL, Hunt MC, Bratcher CL, Crozier-Dodson BA, Johnson DE, Stika JF, 2009. Effects of dry aging of bone-in and boneless strip loins using two aging processes for two aging times. Meat Sci 83:768-74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20416624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Paolo M, Ambrosio RL, Lambiase C, Vuoso V, Salzano A, Bifulco G, Barone CMA, Marrone R, 2023. Effects of the aging period and method on the physicochemical, microbiological and rheological characteristics of two cuts of charolais beef. Foods 12:531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9914319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36766061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA BIOHAZ Panel, Koutsoumanis K, Allende A, Alvarez-Ordóñez A, Bover-Cid S, Chemaly M, De Cesare A, Herman L, Hilbert F, Lindqvist R, Nauta M, Peixe L, Ru G, Simmons M, Skandamis P, Suffredini E, Blagojevic B, Van Damme I, Hempen M, Messens W, Bolton D, 2023. Microbiological safety of aged meat. EFSA J 21:e07745.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9850206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36698487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission, 2024. Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) No. 2024/1141 of 14 December 2023 amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No. 853/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards specific hygiene requirements for certain meat, fishery products, dairy products and eggs. In: Official Journal, L 2024/1141, 19/04/2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Parliament Council of the European Union, 2002. Regulation (EC) No. 178/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 28 January 2002 laying down the general principles and requirements of food law, establishing the European Food Safety Authority and laying down procedures in matters of food safety. In: Official Journal, L 031, 01/02/2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Parliament Council of the European Union, 2004. Regulation (EC) No. 853/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 laying down specific hygiene rules for food of animal origin. In: Official Journal, L 139/55, 30/04/2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gowda TKGM, De Zutter L, Van Royen G, Van Damme I, 2022. Exploring the microbiological quality and safety of dry-aged beef: a cross-sectional study of loin surfaces during ripening and dry-aged beef steaks from commercial meat companies in Belgium. Food Microbiol 102:103919.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34809945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gudjónsdóttir M, Gacutan MD, Mendes AC, Chronakis IS, Jespersen L, Karlsson AH, 2015. Effects of electrospun chitosan wrapping for dry-ageing of beef, as studied by microbiological, physicochemical and low-field nuclear magnetic resonance analysis. Food Chem 184:167-75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25872440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hulánková R, Kameník J, Saláková A, Závodský D, Borilova G, 2018. The effect of dry aging on instrumental, chemical and microbiological parameters of organic beef loin muscle. LWT 89:559-65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaballah S, Fhoula I, Boumaiza M, Najjari A, Mhajbi N, Boudabous A, Klibi N, Ouzari H, 2022. Prevalence and risk factors of potential pathogenic Yersinia enterocolitica in Tunisian frozen ground beef through a shelf life monitoring protocol validation. Food Process Preserv 46:e16360.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khazzar S, Segato S, Riuzzi G, Serva L, Garbin E, Gerardi G, Tenti S, Mirisola M, Catellani P, 2023. Influence of ageing time and method on beef quality and safety. Foods 12:3250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10486688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37685182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim S, Kim G, Moon C, Ko K, Choi Y, Choe J, Ryu Y, 2022. Effects of aging methods and periods on quality characteristics of beef. Food Sci Anim Resour 42:953-67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9647182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36415581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kozyrev I, Kozyrev I, Mittelshtein T, Mittelshtein T, Pchelkina V, Pchelkina V, Kuznetsova T, Kuznetsova T, Lisitsyn A, Lisitsyn A, 2018. Marbled beef quality grades under various ageing conditions. Foods and Raw Materials 6:429-37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knudsen GM, Sommer HM, Sørensen ND, Olsen JE, Aabo S, 2011. Survival of Salmonella on cuts of beef carcasses subjected to dry aging: Salmonella survival on beef carcasses. J Appl Microbiol 111:848-54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21714838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lancaster JM, Smart JH, Van Buren J, Buseman BJ, Weber TM, Insausti K, Nasados JA, Glaze B, Price WJ, Colle MJ, Bass PD, 2022. Assessment of dry-aged beef from commercial aging locations across the United States. Int J Gastron Food Sci 27:100466.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee HJ, Choe J, Kim KT, Oh J, Lee DG, Kwon KM, Choi YI, Jo C, 2017. Analysis of low-marbled Hanwoo cow meat aged with different dry-aging methods. Asian-Australas J Anim Sci 30:1733-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5666177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28728384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee HJ, Yoon JW, Kim M, Oh H, Yoon Y, Jo C, 2019. Changes in microbial composition on the crust by different air flow velocities and their effect on sensory properties of dry-aged beef. Meat Sci 153:152-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30953880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Chen H, Kingsley DH, 2013. The influence of temperature, pH, and water immersion on the high hydrostatic pressure inactivation of GI.1 and GII.4 human noroviruses. Int J Food Microbiol 167:138-43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24135670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meat and Livestock Australia, 2016. Dry aged beef – design and good manufacturing practices review. Available from: https://www.mla.com.au/contentassets/e4b4dbda8b5645f8b7d584700f2e332e/p.psh.0679_final_report.pdf. Accessed on: 09/05/2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikami N, Toyotome T, Yamashiro Y, Sugo K, Yoshitomi K, Takaya M, Han K-H, Fukushima M, Shimada K, 2021. Dryaged beef manufactured in Japan: microbiota identification and their effects on product characteristics. Food Res Int 140:110020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33648250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh H, Lee HJ, Lee J, Jo C, Yoon Y, 2019. Identification of microorganisms associated with the quality improvement of dry-aged beef through microbiome analysis and DNA sequencing, and evaluation of their effects on beef quality. J Food Sci 84:2944-54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31553057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezende de Souza JH, Cardello FAB, De Paula APM, Ribeiro FA, Calkins CR, Pflanzer SB, 2021. Profile of producers and production of dry-aged beef in Brazil. Foods 10:2447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8536073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34681496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhoades JR, Duffy G, Koutsoumanis K, 2009. Prevalence and concentration of verocytotoxigenic Escherichia coli, Salmonella enterica and Listeria monocytogenes in the beef production chain: A review. Food Microbiol 26:357-76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19376457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu S, Park MR, Maburutse BE, Lee WJ, Park DJ, Cho S, Hwang I, Oh S, Kim Y, 2018. Diversity and characteristics of the meat microbiological community on dry aged beef. J Microbiol Biotechnol 28:105-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29081086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu S, Shin M, Cho S, Hwang I, Kim Y, Oh S, 2020. Molecular characterization of microbial and fungal communities on dry-aged beef of hanwoo using metagenomic analysis. Foods 9:1571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7693710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33138191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott WJ, Vickery JR, 1939. Investigations on chilled beef. Part II. Cooling and storage in the meatworks. In: Empey WA, ed. Investigations on chilled beef. Government Printer, Melbourne, Australia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao L, Chen S, Wang Haodong, Zhang J, Xu X, Wang Huhu, 2021. Advances in understanding the predominance, phenotypes, and mechanisms of bacteria related to meat spoilage. Trends Food Sci Tech 118:822-32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Y, Zhang W, Zhou G, 2020. Effects of different moisture-permeable packaging on the quality of aging beef compared with wet aging and dry aging. Foods 9:649.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7278742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32443458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smaldone G, Marrone R, Vollano L, Peruzy MF, Barone CMA, Ambrosio RL, Anastasio A, 2019. Microbiological, rheological and physical-chemical characteristics of bovine meat subjected to a prolonged ageing period. Ital J Food Saf 8:8100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6784598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31632927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tittor AW, Tittor MG, Brashears MM, Brooks JC, Garmyn AJ, Miller MF, 2011. Effects of simulated dry and wet chilling and aging of beef fat and lean tissues on the reduction of Escherichia Coli O157:H7 and Salmonella. J Food Prot 74:289-93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21333151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomasello F, Pollesel M, Mondo E, Savini F, Scarpellini R, Giacometti F, Lorito L, Tassinari M, Cuomo S, Piva S, Serraino A, 2021. Effectiveness of alkaline electrolyzed water in reducing bacterial load on surfaces intended to come into contact with food. Ital J Food Saf 10:9988.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8513190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34733803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USDA, 2024. Food standards and labeling policy book. Available from: https://www.fsis.usda.gov/sites/default/files/ import/Labeling-Policy-Book.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USMEF, 2014. Guidelines for U.S. dry-aged beef for international markets.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Damme I, Varalakshmi S, De Zutter L, Vossen E, De Smet S, 2022. Decrease of Salmonella and Escherichia coli O157:H7 counts during dry-aging of beef but potential growth of Listeria monocytogenes under certain dry-aging conditions. Food Microbiol 104:104000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35287819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>