<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39234758</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1526-4998</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pest management science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pest Manag Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Design and synthesis of some novel structurally diverse thiochroman derivatives as fungicides against phytopathogenic fungi.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ps.8400</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Plant diseases infected by pathogenic fungi have a devastating effect on global agricultural and food industry yields. The development of novel, environmentally friendly, and efficient fungicides is an important technique for preventing and combatting phytopathogenic fungi.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Herein, 99 thiochroman-based derivatives containing hydroxyl, sulfoxide, sulfone, carbonyl, double bond, amino, imine, oxime, oxime ester, and amide moieties were synthesized. The antifungal activities of the target compounds against ten typical phytopathogenic fungi were also investigated. The bioassay results illustrated that most of the target compounds exhibited moderate to excellent antifungal effects against the tested fungi in vitro. Among these, thiochroman-oxime derivatives (12a-12m) exerted a promising inhibition effect, especially against Fusarium solani, Fusarium graminearum, Valsa mali, and Botrytis cinerea strains. Furthermore, the compounds 12f and 12g markedly suppressed the spore germination germ and tube growth. At the same time, they exerted excellent protective effects against potatoes infected by F. solani, making them superior to commercial fungicides Hymexazol and Chlorothalonil. Notably, the compounds 12d and 12f also showed excellent protective effects against cherry tomatoes infected by B. cinerea. Further mechanistic studies revealed that compound 12f exerted an antifungal effect by overtly altering the mycelium structure and remarkably increasing cell membrane permeability. Fortunately, the excellent bioactive compounds showed good safety against human hepatic cell lines (WRL-68). The preliminary structure-activity relationship analysis revealed that the introduction of hydroxyl or oxime fragments at the thiopyran ring might be significantly beneficial to antifungal activity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study provides thiochroman compounds that can be used in the development of novel botanical fungicides for the management of phytopathogenic fungi. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Wenjing</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liang</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Gaofeng</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jianta</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Wenzhang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Lei</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fan</LastName><ForeName>Lingling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5607-3813</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Guizhou Provincial Engineering Technology Research Center for Chemical Drug R&amp;D, Guizhou Medical University, Guiyang, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>32060627</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>22207021</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>the State Key Laboratory Breeding Base of Green Pesticide and Agricultural Bioengineering</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Key Laboratory of Ministry of Education</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>QianjiaoheKYzi[2022]362</GrantID><Agency>Guizhou University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>26222190618</GrantID><Agency>Special Research Project of Rural Economic Revitalization and Agricultural Industry Technology Project of Guizhou Medical University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>S202210660018</GrantID><Agency>College Student Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Pest Manag Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100898744</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1526-498X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antifungal activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phytopathogenic fungi</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">structure–activity relationship</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thiochroman derivatives</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39234758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ps.8400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Salvatore MM and Andolfi A, Phytopathogenic fungi and toxicity. Toxins 13:689 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang XK, Li BQ, Zhang ZQ, Chen Y and Tian SP, Antagonistic yeasts: a promising alternative to chemical fungicides for controlling postharvest decay of fruit. J Fungi 6:158 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pratap R and Ram VJ, Natural and synthetic chromenes, fused chromenes, and versatility of dihydrobenzo[h]chromenes in organic synthesis. Chem Rev 114:10476–10526 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Zhou Q, Zhou Y, Wang ZH, Wang J and Wang MF, Asymmetric synthesis of chiral (thio)chromanes and exploration on their structure–activity relationship in macrophages. RSC Adv 13:30391 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao L, Yu L, Li P, Chi J, Tang Z, Li J et al., Design, synthesis, and bioactivity evaluation of new thiochromanone derivatives containing a carboxamide moiety. Molecules 26:4391 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamboj S and Singh R, Chromanone‐a prerogative therapeutic scafold: an overview. Arab J Sci Eng 47:75–111 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinedo‐Rivilla C, Collado IG and Aleu J, Metabolism of antifungal thiochroman‐4‐ones by trichoderma viride and Botrytis cinerea. J Nat Prod 81:1036–1040 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu GY and Xiao T, Recent advances in the research of chromone and thiochromone derivatives as antifungal agents. Chin J Antibiot 36:481–486 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun XY, Feng JJ, Li SB, Feng SR, Liu ZM, Song YL et al., Design, synthesis, and antifungal activity of novel thiochromanone derivatives containing 1,3,4‐oxadiazole skeleton. Chin J Org Chem 39:1037–1043 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu H, Hu YK, Guo MB, Huang AS, Su X and Guo C, Design, synthesis and antifungal activity of novel selenochroman‐4‐one derivatives. Chem Pap 71:2455–2463 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li P, Chi JY, Xiao LL and Yu L, Synthesis and antibacterial and antifungal activities of novel thiochroman‐4‐one derivatives incorporating oxime ether and 1,3,4‐oxadiazole thioether moieties. Phosphorus Sulfur Silicon Relat Elem 197:1063–1068 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh L, Kumar PSV, Poornachandra Y, Kumar CG, Babu NJ and Chandramouli GVP, An expeditious four‐component domino protocol for the synthesis of novel thiazolo[3,2‐a]thiochromeno[4,3‐d]pyrimidine derivatives as antibacterial and antibiofilm agents. Bioorg Med Chem 24:3808–3817 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chouchene N, Toumi A, Boudriga S, Edziri H, Sobeh M, Abdelfattah MA et al., Antimicrobial activity and DFT studies of a novel set of spiropyrrolidines tethered with thiochroman‐4‐one/chroman‐4‐one scaffolds. Molecules 27:582 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao PL, Li J and Yang GF, Synthesis and insecticidal activity of chromanone and chromone analogues of diacylhydrazines. Bioorg Med Chem 15:1888–1895 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas E, Echeverri F, Vélez ID, Robledo SM and Quiñones W, Synthesis and evaluation of thiochroman‐4‐one derivatives as potential leishmanicidal agents. Molecules 22:2041 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur N, Kishore L and Singh R, Antidiabetic effect of new chromane isolated from Dillenia indica L. leaves in streptozotocin induced diabetic rats. J Funct Foods 22:547–555 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts BF, Iyamu ID, Lee S, Lee E, Ayong L, Kyle DE et al., Spirocyclic chromanes exhibit antiplasmodial activities and inhibit all intraerythrocytic life cycle stages. Int J Parasitol Drugs Drug Resist 6:85–92 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu WJ, Li Y, Fan JD, Tang L, Guo B, Xue W et al., Natural products‐based fungicides: synthesis and antifungal activity against plant pathogens of 2H‐chromene derivatives. Chem Biodivers 19:e202200802 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Luo BL, Luo ZF, Ma TG, Fan LL, Liu WJ et al., Design and synthesis of novel 2,2‐dimethylchromene derivatives as potential antifungal agents. Mol Divers 27:589–601 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai P, Luo K, Yu X, Yang WC, Wu L and Zhang WH, Tert‐butyl nitrite mediated expeditious methylsulfoxidation of tetrazole‐amines with DMSO: metal‐free synthesis of antifungal active methylsulfinyl‐1H‐tetrazole derivatives. Adv Synth Catal 360:468–473 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li P, Wang LJ and Wang X, Recent advances on the pesticidal activity evaluations of sulfone derivatives: a 2010 to 2020 decade in mini‐review. J Heterocyclic Chem 58:28–39 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang M, Duan WG, Lin GS, Li K and Hu Q, Synthesis and antifungal activity of novel 3‐caren‐5‐one oxime esters. Molecules 22:1538 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo B and Ning YL, Comprehensive overview of carboxamide derivatives as succinate dehydrogenase inhibitors. J Agric Food Chem 70:957–975 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Luo ZF, Luo BL, Lan Q, Fan JD, Xue W et al., Design, synthesis and antifungal activities of 6‐substituted 3‐butylphthalide derivatives against phytopathogenic fungi. Chem Biodivers 17:e2000435 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan LL, Luo ZF, Yang CF, Guo B, Miao J, Chen Y et al., Design and synthesis of small molecular 2‐aminobenzoxazoles as potential antifungal agents against phytopathogenic fungi. Mol Divers 26:981–992 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma TG, Zhong X, Yang Y, Liu WJ, Guo B, Fan JD et al., Synthesis and evaluation of imidazo[1,2‐a]quinoxaline derivatives as potential antifungal agents against phytopathogenic fungi. Mol Divers (2023). https://doi.org/10.1007/s11030-023-10739-y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu JK, Gao JM, Yang CJ, Shang XF, Zhao ZM, Lawoe RK et al., Design, synthesis, and antifungal evaluation of neocryptolepine derivatives against phytopathogenic fungi. J Agric Food Chem 68:2306–2315 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen YJ, Ma KY, Du SS, Zhang ZJ, Wu TL, Sun Y et al., Antifungal exploration of quinoline derivatives against phytopathogenic fungi inspired by quinine alkaloids. J Agric Food Chem 69:12156–12170 (2021).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>