<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39233703</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2239-7132</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Italian journal of food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ital J Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Low-frequency focused thermosonication for <i>Salmonella typhimurium</i> inactivation: an <i>in vitro</i> study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>12217</StartPage><MedlinePgn>12217</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">12217</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4081/ijfs.2024.12217</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Customer requests are addressed to safe products that best express their characteristics of "naturalness" and "freshness" for their entire shelf life; therefore, scientific research has been exploring the use of "non-thermal technologies". Thermosonication using low-frequency focused ultrasound determines bacterial inactivation through the phenomenon of "cavitation", guaranteeing high-quality standards of safety, nutrition, and freshness of the products. The present work aims to evaluate the effectiveness of the inactivation of <i>Salmonella typhimurium</i> in culture broth by low-frequency focused thermosonication with two different operational parameters: sublethal temperature (40°C, 50°C) and treatment time (5, 10, and 15 minutes). Treatment determined a bacterial load reduction compared to the negative control (untreated inoculum), which was statistically significant at the <i>t</i>-test (p&lt;0.05). Average decreases of 1.5 log and 3.5 CFU/mL were observed, respectively, after treatment and after 24 hours of storage at +4°C. Treatment at 50°C for 15 minutes was the most effective (average value: 3.06 log CFU/mL; minimum value: 2.13 log CFU/mL; maximum value: 4.59 log CFU/mL). However, strains have shown markable variability: one of them even showed an increase in the microbial load 24 hours after treatment at 40°C for 5 minutes (-0.20 log CFU/mL); however, the same treatment showed a reduction of bacterial charge in all the other strains (average value: 1.05 log CFU/mL; minimum value: -0.20 log CFU/mL; maximum value: 2.28 log CFU/mL). This study poses numerous perspectives on the use of low-frequency focused thermosonication treatment in the food industry as a sustainable and safe alternative to classic thermal treatments.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, the Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lauteri</LastName><ForeName>Carlotta</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine, School of Specialization in Inspection of Food of Animal Origin "G. Tiecco", University of Teramo, Località Piano D'Accio.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pennisi</LastName><ForeName>Luca</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine, School of Specialization in Inspection of Food of Animal Origin "G. Tiecco", University of Teramo, Località Piano D'Accio.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Di Clerico</LastName><ForeName>Daniele</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Next Cooking Generation Srl, Milano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pennisi</LastName><ForeName>Viola</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine, School of Specialization in Inspection of Food of Animal Origin "G. Tiecco", University of Teramo, Località Piano D'Accio.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vergara</LastName><ForeName>Alberto</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine, School of Specialization in Inspection of Food of Animal Origin "G. Tiecco", University of Teramo, Località Piano D'Accio.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Italy</Country><MedlineTA>Ital J Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101684120</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2239-7132</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella inactivation in food matrix</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella typhimurium</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">low frequency focused ultrasound</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thermosonication</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interest: the authors declare no potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39233703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11369753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/ijfs.2024.12217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Baumann AR, Martin SE, Feng H, 2005. Power ultrasound treatment of Listeria monocytogenes in apple cider. J Food Prot 68:2333-40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16300070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beitia E, Gkogka E, Chanos P, Hertel C, Heinz V, Valdramidis V, Aganovic K, 2023. Microbial decontamination assisted by ultrasound-based processing technologies in food and model systems: a review. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 22:2802-49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37184058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bi X, Wang X, Chen Y, Chen L, Xing Y, Che Z, 2020. Effects of combination treatments of lysozyme and high-power ultrasound on the Salmonella typhimurium inactivation and quality of liquid whole egg. Ultrason Sonochem 60:104763.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31539729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz-Cansino N, Reyes-Hernández I, Delgado-Olivares L, Jaramillo-Bustos DP, Ortega JAA, Ramírez-Moreno E, 2016. Effect of ultrasound on survival and growth of Escherichia coli in cactus pear juice during storage. Braz J Microbiol 47:431-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4874580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26991288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control, 2022. The European Union one health 2021 zoonoses report. EFSA J 20:e07666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9745727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36524203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferri G, Lauteri C, Scattolini M, Vergara A, 2023. Shelf life and safety of vacuum packed HPP- treated soaked cod fillets: effects of salt content and multilayer plastic film. Foods 12:179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9818557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36613395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferri G, Lauteri C, Vergara A, 2022. Antibiotic resistance in the finfish aquaculture industry: a review. Antibiotics (Basel) 11:1574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9686606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36358229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herceg Z, Rezek Jambrak A, Lelas V, Mededovic Thagard S, 2012. The effect of high intensity ultrasound treatment on the amount of Staphylococcus aureus and Escherichia coli in milk. Food Technol Biotechnol 50:46-52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horwood MP, Horton JP, Minch VA, 1951. Factors influencing bactericidal action of ultrasonic waves. J AWWA 43:153-60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang G, Chen S, Dai C, Sun L, Sun W, Tang Y, Xiong F, He R, Ma H, 2017. Effects of ultrasound on microbial growth and enzyme activity. Ultrason Sonochem 37:144-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28427617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamovi project, 2022. Jamovi (Version 2.3) Available from: https://www.jamovi.org.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauteri C, Ferri G, Piccinini A, Pennisi L, Vergara A, 2023. Ultrasound technology as inactivation method for foodborne pathogens: a review. Foods 12:1212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10048265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36981137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H, Li Z, Zhang X, Liu Y, Hu J, Yang C, Zhao X, 2021. The effects of ultrasound on the growth, nutritional quality and microbiological quality of sprouts. Trends Food Sci Technol 111:292-300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo W, Wang J, Chen Y, Wang Y, Li R, Tang J, Geng F, 2022. Quantitative proteomic analysis provides insight into the survival mechanism of Salmonella typhimurium under high-intensity ultrasound treatment. Curr Res Food Sci 5:1740-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9576580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36268134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musavian HS, Krebs NH, Nonboe U, Corry Janet EL, Purnell G, 2014. Combined steam and ultrasound treatment of broilers at slaughter: a promising intervention to significantly reduce numbers of naturally occurring campylobacters on carcasses. Int J Food Microbiol 176:23-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24561390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pennisi L, Di Clerico D, Costantini L, Festino AR, Vergara A, 2020. Ultrasonic decontamination in smoked salmon experimentally contaminated with Listeria monocytogenes: preliminary results. Ital J Food Saf 9:8398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7154597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32300563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pokhrel PR, Bermúdez-Aguirre D, Martínez-Flores HE, Garnica-Romo MG, Sablani S, Tang J, Barbosa-Cánovas GV, 2017. Combined effect of ultrasound and mild temperatures on the inactivation of E. coli in fresh carrot juice and changes on its physicochemical characteristics. J Food Sci 82:2343-50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28898409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suslick KS, 1988. Homogeneous sonochemistry. In: Suslick KS, ed. Ultrasound: its chemical, physical and biological effects. VCH Publishers, New York, NY, USA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Zhang W, Zhou G, 2019. Effects of ultrasound-assisted frying on the physiochemical properties and microstructure of fried meatballs. Int J Food Sci Technol 54:2915-26.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>