<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39230472</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2410-8650</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>40</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Kaohsiung journal of medical sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Kaohsiung J Med Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>In vitro and in vivo effects of Galectin-3 inhibitor TD139 on inflammation and ERK/JNK/p38 pathway in gestational diabetes mellitus.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>916</StartPage><EndPage>925</EndPage><MedlinePgn>916-925</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/kjm2.12890</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study aims to investigate the effects of the Galectin-3 (Gal-3) inhibitor TD139 on inflammation and the extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK)/c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK)/p38 pathway in gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM). Human placental tissues were treated with TD139 and TNF-α, assessing Gal-3, ERK/JNK/p38 activation, and inflammatory cytokines. GDM was induced in mice via subcutaneous injections of streptozotocin (STZ). After confirming GDM, mice were treated with 15 mg/kg TD139 on GD 10.5 12.5, 14.5, 16.5, and 18.5. Serum inflammatory cytokines were measured on GD 20.5, and post-delivery placental tissues were analyzed. Data were analyzed using one-way or two-way repeated measures ANOVA with post hoc tests. TD139 suppressed TNF-α-induced increases in Gal-3, IL-1β, IL-6, MCP-1, and ERK/JNK/p38 activation in placental tissues. In STZ-induced GDM mice, TD139 reduced glucose levels, weight loss, and food and water intake. TD139 significantly lowered TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and MCP-1 in serum and placental tissues and inhibited the ERK/JNK/p38 pathway. TD139 improved pup numbers in GDM mice compared to untreated ones. TD139 reduces inflammation and inhibits the ERK/JNK/p38 pathway in TNF-α stimulated placental tissues and STZ-induced GDM mice, suggesting its therapeutic potential for managing GDM-related placental inflammation and improving pregnancy outcomes. The study used TNF-α to mimic GDM in placental tissues and an STZ-induced GDM mouse model, which may not fully represent human GDM complexity. Future research should explore alternative models, and broader signaling pathways, and thoroughly evaluate TD139's safety in pregnancy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). The Kaohsiung Journal of Medical Sciences published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Kaohsiung Medical University.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xia</LastName><ForeName>Ji</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics, Hainan Branch, Shanghai Children's Medical Center, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Sanya, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics, Hainan Branch, Shanghai Children's Medical Center, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Sanya, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qi</LastName><ForeName>Bang-Ruo</ForeName><Initials>BR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0224-0548</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics, Hainan Branch, Shanghai Children's Medical Center, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Sanya, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>WSJK2024MS208</GrantID><Agency>Joint Program on Health Science &amp; Technology Innovation of Hainan Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021GXYL35</GrantID><Agency>Sanya Special Science and Technology Plan for Universities and Medical Institutions project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>821MS163</GrantID><Agency>Hainan Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>China (Republic : 1949- )</Country><MedlineTA>Kaohsiung J Med Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100960562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1607-551X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D037502">Galectin 3</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 2.7.11.24</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D048051">p38 Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinases</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014409">Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016207">Cytokines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>5W494URQ81</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D013311">Streptozocin</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011247" MajorTopicYN="N">Pregnancy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016640" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diabetes, Gestational</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010920" MajorTopicYN="Y">Placenta</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D037502" MajorTopicYN="Y">Galectin 3</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000037" MajorTopicYN="N">antagonists &amp; inhibitors</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020935" MajorTopicYN="Y">MAP Kinase Signaling System</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007249" MajorTopicYN="N">Inflammation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D048051" MajorTopicYN="N">p38 Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000037" MajorTopicYN="N">antagonists &amp; inhibitors</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014409" MajorTopicYN="N">Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016207" MajorTopicYN="N">Cytokines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="N">blood</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013311" MajorTopicYN="N">Streptozocin</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003921" MajorTopicYN="N">Diabetes Mellitus, Experimental</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Galectin 3</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gestational diabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inflammation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mitogen‐activated protein kinases (MAPKs)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tumor necrosis factor‐alpha (TNF‐α)</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39230472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/kjm2.12890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Govindarajah V, Sakabe M, Good S, Solomon M, Arasu A, Chen N, et al. Gestational diabetes in mice induces hematopoietic memory that affects the long‐term health of the offspring. J Clin Invest. 2024;134(2):e169730.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang L, Tang K, Magee LA, von Dadelszen P, Ekeroma A, Li X, et al. A global view of hypertensive disorders and diabetes mellitus during pregnancy. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2022;18(12):760–775.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spinelli P, Fields AM, Falcone S, Mesaros C, Susiarjo M. Susceptibility to low vitamin B6 diet‐induced gestational diabetes is modulated by strain differences in mice. Endocrinology. 2023;164(10):bqad130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed R, Anam K, Ahmed H. Development of Galectin‐3 targeting drugs for therapeutic applications in various diseases. Int J Mol Sci. 2023;24(9):8116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simeone P, Tripaldi R, Michelsen A, Ueland T, Liani R, Ciotti S, et al. Effects of liraglutide vs. lifestyle changes on soluble suppression of tumorigenesis‐2 (sST2) and galectin‐3 in obese subjects with prediabetes or type 2 diabetes after comparable weight loss. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2022;21(1):36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saksida T, Nikolic I, Vujicic M, Nilsson UJ, Leffler H, Lukic ML, et al. Galectin‐3 deficiency protects pancreatic islet cells from cytokine‐triggered apoptosis in vitro. J Cell Physiol. 2013;228(7):1568–1576.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamal R, Awasthi A, Pundir M, Thakur S. Healing the diabetic wound: unlocking the secrets of genes and pathways. Eur J Pharmacol. 2024;975:176645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang JY, Lu PH, Lin WW, Wei YH, Chiu LY, Chern SR, et al. Galectin‐3 regulates UVB‐induced inflammation in skin. J Dermatol Sci. 2020;98(2):119–127.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silverman AM, Nakata R, Shimada H, Sposto R, DeClerck YA. A galectin‐3‐dependent pathway upregulates interleukin‐6 in the microenvironment of human neuroblastoma. Cancer Res. 2012;72(9):2228–2238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Cheng K, Chen H, Tu J, Shen Y, Pang L, et al. Galectin‐3 knock down inhibits cardiac ischemia‐reperfusion injury through interacting with bcl‐2 and modulating cell apoptosis. Arch Biochem Biophys. 2020;694:108602.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H, Hwang SY, Lee SS. Role of galectin in cardiovascular conditions including cirrhotic cardiomyopathy. Pharmaceuticals. 2023;16(7):978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirani N, MacKinnon AC, Nicol L, Ford P, Schambye H, Pedersen A, et al. Target inhibition of galectin‐3 by inhaled TD139 in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Eur Respir J. 2021;57(5):2002559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Li T, Zhou Z, Xiao Y. Emerging roles of Galectin‐3 in diabetes and diabetes complications: a snapshot. Rev Endocr Metab Disord. 2022;23(3):569–577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Kang X, Guo Y, Zhang J, Xie J, Shao S, et al. Association of circulating galectin‐3 with gestational diabetes mellitus, progesterone, and insulin resistance. J Diabetes. 2021;13(1):54–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talmor‐Barkan Y, Chezar‐Azerrad C, Kruchin B, Leshem‐Lev D, Levi A, Hadar E, et al. Elevated galectin‐3 in women with gestational diabetes mellitus, a new surrogate for cardiovascular disease in women. PLoS One. 2020;15(6):e0234732.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heusler I, Biron‐Shental T, Farladansky‐Gershnabel S, Pasternak Y, Kidron D, Vulih‐Shuitsman I, et al. Enhanced expression of Galectin‐3 in gestational diabetes. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2021;31(6):1791–1797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatakrishnan V, Elmwall J, Lahiri T, Sundqvist M, Bergqvist L, Leffler H, et al. Novel inhibitory effect of galectin‐3 on the respiratory burst induced by Staphylococcus aureus in human neutrophils. Glycobiology. 2023;33(6):503–511.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen‐Ngo C, Salomon C, Quak S, Lai A, Willcox JC, Lappas M. Nobiletin exerts anti‐diabetic and anti‐inflammatory effects in an in vitro human model and in vivo murine model of gestational diabetes. Clin Sci. 2020;134(6):571–592.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arifin WN, Zahiruddin WM. Sample size calculation in animal studies using resource equation approach. Malays J Med Sci. 2017;24(5):101–105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serdar CC, Cihan M, Yucel D, Serdar MA. Sample size, power and effect size revisited: simplified and practical approaches in pre‐clinical, clinical and laboratory studies. Biochem Med. 2021;31(1):010502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosales‐Gomez CA, Martinez‐Carrillo BE, Guadarrama‐Lopez AL, Resendiz‐Albor AA, Arciniega‐Martinez IM, Aguilar‐Rodriguez E. Pharmacological induction of diabetes mellitus in pregnant female mice: a comparison of two doses and routes of administration. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2024;28(8):3275–3286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies MJ, Aroda VR, Collins BS, Gabbay RA, Green J, Maruthur NM, et al. Management of Hyperglycemia in type 2 diabetes, 2022. A consensus report by the American Diabetes Association (ADA) and the European Association for the Study of diabetes (EASD). Diabetes Care. 2022;45(11):2753–2786.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabel M, Wolf A, Szczepan M, Xu H, Jagle H, Moehle C, et al. Genetic targeting or pharmacological inhibition of galectin‐3 dampens microglia reactivity and delays retinal degeneration. J Neuroinflammation. 2022;19(1):229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed A, Aliyu IS, Manu M. Correlation between circulating level of tumor necrosis factor‐alpha and insulin resistance in Nigerian women with gestational diabetes mellitus. Ann Afr Med. 2018;17(4):168–171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen‐Ngo C, Perkins AV, Lappas M. Selenium prevents inflammation in human placenta and adipose tissue in vitro: implications for metabolic diseases of pregnancy associated with inflammation. Nutrients. 2022;14(16):3286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tran HT, Liong S, Lim R, Barker G, Lappas M. Resveratrol ameliorates the chemical and microbial induction of inflammation and insulin resistance in human placenta, adipose tissue and skeletal muscle. PLoS One. 2017;12(3):e0173373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udomsinprasert W, Ungsudechachai T, Wunthong S, Yuttanarad S, Jittikoon J, Honsawek S. Effect of galectin‐3 on synovial inflammation in knee osteoarthritis via stimulating phosphatidylinositol‐3‐kinase/Akt pathway. Int Immunopharmacol. 2023;122:110673.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu XN, Hong D, Shi ZR, Lu SY, Lai YX, Ren YL, et al. TNF‐alpha promotes CXCL‐1/8 production in keratinocytes by downregulating galectin‐3 through NF‐kappaB and hsa‐miR‐27a‐3p pathway to contribute psoriasis development. Immunopharmacol Immunotoxicol. 2023;45(6):692–700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayran Y, Alli N, Akpinar U, Oktem A, Yucel C, Firat Oguz E, et al. Serum galectin‐3 levels in patients with psoriasis. Int J Clin Pract. 2021;75(10):e14545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kandel M, Tong S, Walker SP, Cannon P, Nguyen TV, MacDonald TM, et al. Placental galectin‐3 is reduced in early‐onset preeclampsia. Front Physiol. 2022;13:1037597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen Y, Zhang W, Chang H, Li Z, Lin C, Zhang G, et al. Galectin‐3 modulates microglial activation and neuroinflammation in early brain injury after subarachnoid hemorrhage. Exp Neurol. 2024;377:114777.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volarevic V, Markovic BS, Bojic S, Stojanovic M, Nilsson U, Leffler H, et al. Gal‐3 regulates the capacity of dendritic cells to promote NKT‐cell‐induced liver injury. Eur J Immunol. 2015;45(2):531–543.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Zhao C, Meng J, Li N, Xu Z, Liu X, et al. Galectin‐3 regulates microglial activation and promotes inflammation through TLR4/MyD88/NF‐kB in experimental autoimmune uveitis. Clin Immunol. 2022;236:108939.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murthi P, Sarkis R, Lim R, Nguyen‐Ngo C, Pratt A, Liong S, et al. Endocan expression is increased in the placenta from obese women with gestational diabetes mellitus. Placenta. 2016;48:38–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz H, Celik HT, Ozdemir O, Kalkan D, Namuslu M, Abusoglu S, et al. Serum galectin‐3 levels in women with PCOS. J Endocrinol Invest. 2014;37(2):181–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrovic I, Pejnovic N, Ljujic B, Pavlovic S, Miletic Kovacevic M, Jeftic I, et al. Overexpression of galectin 3 in pancreatic beta cells amplifies beta‐cell apoptosis and islet inflammation in type‐2 diabetes in mice. Front Endocrinol. 2020;11:30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menini S, Iacobini C, Blasetti Fantauzzi C, Pesce CM, Pugliese G. Role of Galectin‐3 in obesity and impaired glucose homeostasis. Oxid Med Cell Longev. 2016;2016:9618092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baek JH, Kim SJ, Kang HG, Lee HW, Kim JH, Hwang KA, et al. Galectin‐3 activates PPARgamma and supports white adipose tissue formation and high‐fat diet‐induced obesity. Endocrinology. 2015;156(1):147–156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pejnovic NN, Pantic JM, Jovanovic IP, Radosavljevic GD, Milovanovic MZ, Nikolic IG, et al. Galectin‐3 deficiency accelerates high‐fat diet‐induced obesity and amplifies inflammation in adipose tissue and pancreatic islets. Diabetes. 2013;62(6):1932–1944.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>