<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39232188</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1740-634X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Neuropsychopharmacology : official publication of the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Neuropsychopharmacology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>GLP-1 receptor agonist exenatide uncouples food intake from hedonic and anticipatory regulation in non-human primates: insights from an operant meal schedule paradigm.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41386-024-01981-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1), a neuroendocrine signal of energy balance and satiety, has a major role in regulating food intake behaviour. Here we investigated the effects of the GLP-1 agonist exenatide on palatability-driven feeding regulation in adult male rhesus macaques (n = 5) using a novel operant food intake paradigm with four meal schedule conditions where two types of pellets with different palatability values were offered as meal in all combinations in two consecutive daily feeding sessions (S1 and S2). In control conditions, a strong, palatability-driven anticipatory effect was found in S1, followed by a complementary positive contrast effect in S2. After acute subcutaneous treatment with 1 µg/kg dose of exenatide 1 h before S1, food intake decreased to the same very low level in all meal schedule conditions in S1, completely erasing the previously observed anticipatory effect. Conversely, exenatide induced hypoglycaemia in an anticipatory meal schedule dependent pattern. Interestingly, the previously observed positive contrast effect was spared in S2, with a weaker residual effect specifically on the consumption of the more palatable pellet type. To conclude, the food intake reducing effects of exenatide may temporally evolve from strong anorectic to weak anhedonic modulations, where hedonic experience and anticipation during the early anorectic phase is conserved but uncoupled from food intake behaviour.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Knakker</LastName><ForeName>Balázs</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Grastyán E. Translational Research Centre, University of Pécs, Pécs, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Inkeller</LastName><ForeName>Judit</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Grastyán E. Translational Research Centre, University of Pécs, Pécs, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kovács</LastName><ForeName>Péter</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Drug Safety Research, Gedeon Richter Plc., Budapest, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>VRG Therapeutics, Füvészkert utca 3., Budapest, 1083, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lendvai</LastName><ForeName>Balázs</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Drug Safety Research, Gedeon Richter Plc., Budapest, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Richter Department, Semmelweis University, Budapest, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hernádi</LastName><ForeName>István</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7882-4817</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Grastyán E. Translational Research Centre, University of Pécs, Pécs, Hungary. hernadi@gamma.ttk.pte.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurobiology, Institute of Biology, Faculty of Sciences, University of Pécs, Pécs, Hungary. hernadi@gamma.ttk.pte.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Physiology, Medical School, University of Pécs, Pécs, Hungary. hernadi@gamma.ttk.pte.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Neuropsychopharmacology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8904907</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0893-133X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>39</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39232188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41386-024-01981-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41386-024-01981-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zheng H, Lenard NR, Shin AC, Berthoud H-R. Appetite control and energy balance regulation in the modern world: reward-driven brain overrides repletion signals. Int J Obes. 2009;33:S8–S13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ijo.2009.65</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lutter M, Nestler EJ. Homeostatic and hedonic signals interact in the regulation of food intake. J Nutr. 2009;139:629–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19176746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2714382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3945/jn.108.097618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayes MR, Skibicka KP, Grill HJ. Caudal brainstem processing is sufficient for behavioral, sympathetic, and parasympathetic responses driven by peripheral and hindbrain glucagon-like-peptide-1 receptor stimulation. Endocrinology. 2008;149:4059–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18420740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2488211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/en.2007-1743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brubaker PL, Drucker DJ. Minireview: glucagon-like peptides regulate cell proliferation and apoptosis in the pancreas, gut, and central nervous system. Endocrinology. 2004;145:2653–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15044356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/en.2004-0015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mojsov S, Kopczynski MG, Habener JF. Both amidated and nonamidated forms of glucagon-like peptide I are synthesized in the rat intestine and the pancreas. J Biol Chem. 1990;265:8001–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1692320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(19)39030-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vrang N, Larsen PJ. Preproglucagon derived peptides GLP-1, GLP-2 and oxyntomodulin in the CNS: role of peripherally secreted and centrally produced peptides. Prog Neurobiol. 2010;92:442–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20638440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2010.07.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGrath R, Glastras S, Hocking S, Tjoeng I, Krause M, Fulcher GR. Central Functions of Glucagon-like Peptide-1: Roles in Energy Regulation and Neuroprotection. J Steroids Horm Sci. 2015;6:152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayes MR, Mietlicki-Baase EG, Kanoski SE, De Jonghe BC. Incretins and amylin: neuroendocrine communication between the gut, pancreas, and brain in control of food intake and blood glucose. Annu Rev Nutr. 2014;34:237–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24819325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4458367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-nutr-071812-161201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merchenthaler I, Lane M, Shughrue P. Distribution of pre-pro-glucagon and glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor messenger RNAs in the rat central nervous system. J Comp Neurol. 1999;403:261–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9886047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19990111)403:2&lt;261::AID-CNE8&gt;3.0.CO;2-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holst JJ. Glucagon-like peptide-1, a gastrointestinal hormone with a pharmaceutical potential. Curr Med Chem. 1999;6:1005–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10519910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/092986730611220401163238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flint A, Raben A, Astrup A, Holst JJ. Glucagon-like peptide 1 promotes satiety and suppresses energy intake in humans. J Clin Investig. 1998;101:515–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9449682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">508592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1172/JCI990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drucker DJ. The biology of incretin hormones. Cell Metab. 2006;3:153–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16517403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2006.01.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nadkarni P, Chepurny OG, Holz GG. Regulation of Glucose Homeostasis by GLP-1. In: Tao Y-X, editor. Glucose Homeostatis and the Pathogenesis of Diabetes Mellitus, vol. 121, Academic Press; 2014. p. 23–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parkes D, Jodka C, Smith P, Nayak S, Rinehart L, Gingerich R, et al. Pharmacokinetic actions of exendin‐4 in the rat: Comparison with glucagon‐like peptide‐1. Drug Dev Res. 2001;53:260–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ddr.1195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautier J-F, Choukem S-P, Girard J. Physiology of incretins (GIP and GLP-1) and abnormalities in type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Metab. 2008;34:S65–S72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18640588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1262-3636(08)73397-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heppner KM, Perez-Tilve D. GLP-1 based therapeutics: simultaneously combating T2DM and obesity. Front Neurosci. 2015;9:92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25852463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4367528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnins.2015.00092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinnen D. Glucagon-like peptide 1 receptor agonists for type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Spectr. 2017;30:202–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28848315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5556578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/ds16-0026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards CMB, Stanley SA, Davis R, Brynes AE, Frost GS, Seal LJ, et al. Exendin-4 reduces fasting and postprandial glucose and decreases energy intake in healthy volunteers. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2001;281:E155–E161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11404233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.2001.281.1.E155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanoski SE, Fortin SM, Arnold M, Grill HJ, Hayes MR. Peripheral and central GLP-1 receptor populations mediate the anorectic effects of peripherally administered GLP-1 receptor agonists, liraglutide and exendin-4. Endocrinology. 2011;152:3103–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21693680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3138234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/en.2011-0174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mack CM, Moore CX, Jodka CM, Bhavsar S, Wilson JK, Hoyt JA, et al. Antiobesity action of peripheral exenatide (exendin-4) in rodents: effects on food intake, body weight, metabolic status and side-effect measures. Int J Obes. 2006;30:1332–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.ijo.0803284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams DL, Baskin DG, Schwartz MW. Evidence that intestinal glucagon-like peptide-1 plays a physiological role in satiety. Endocrinology. 2009;150:1680–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19074583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/en.2008-1045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott KA, Moran TH. The GLP-1 agonist exendin-4 reduces food intake in nonhuman primates through changes in meal size. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2007;293:R983–R987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17581835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00323.2007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Bloemendaal L, IJzerman RG, ten Kulve JS, Barkhof F, Konrad RJ, Drent ML, et al. GLP-1 receptor activation modulates appetite- and reward-related brain areas in humans. Diabetes. 2014;63:4186–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25071023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db14-0849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickson SL, Shirazi RH, Hansson C, Bergquist F, Nissbrandt H, Skibicka KP. The glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) analogue, exendin-4, decreases the rewarding value of food: a new role for mesolimbic GLP-1 receptors. J Neurosci. 2012;32:4812–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22492036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6620919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.6326-11.2012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhadeff AL, Rupprecht LE, Hayes MR. GLP-1 neurons in the nucleus of the solitary tract project directly to the ventral tegmental area and nucleus accumbens to control for food intake. Endocrinology. 2012;153:647–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22128031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/en.2011-1443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mietlicki-Baase EG, Ortinski PI, Rupprecht LE, Olivos DR, Alhadeff AL, Pierce RC, et al. The food intake-suppressive effects of glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor signaling in the ventral tegmental area are mediated by AMPA/kainate receptors. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2013;305:E1367–E1374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24105414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3882373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00413.2013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mietlicki-Baase EG, Ortinski PI, Reiner DJ, Sinon CG, McCutcheon JE, Pierce RC, et al. Glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor activation in the nucleus accumbens core suppresses feeding by increasing glutamatergic AMPA/Kainate signaling. J Neurosci. 2014;34:6985–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24828651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4019807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0115-14.2014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhadeff AL, Grill HJ. Hindbrain nucleus tractus solitarius glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor signaling reduces appetitive and motivational aspects of feeding. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2014;307:R465–R470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24944243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4137150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00179.2014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richard JE, Anderberg RH, Göteson A, Gribble FM, Reimann F, Skibicka KP. Activation of the GLP-1 receptors in the nucleus of the solitary tract reduces food reward behavior and targets the mesolimbic system. PLoS ONE. 2015;10:e0119034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25793511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4368564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stenlid R, Cerenius SY, Wen Q, Aydin BK, Manell H, Chowdhury A, et al. Adolescents with obesity treated with exenatide maintain endogenous GLP-1, reduce DPP-4, and improve glycemic control. Front Endocrinol. 2023;14:1293093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1293093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox CK, Clark JM, Rudser KD, Ryder JR, Gross AC, Nathan BM, et al. Exenatide for weight‐loss maintenance in adolescents with severe obesity: a randomized, placebo‐controlled trial. Obesity. 2022;30:1105–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35403350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/oby.23395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee PC, Dixon JB. Food for thought: reward mechanisms and hedonic overeating in obesity. Curr Obes Rep. 2017;6:353–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29052153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13679-017-0280-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaherty CF. Incentive relativity. New York, NY, US: Cambridge University Press; 1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inkeller J, Knakker B, Kovács P, Lendvai B, Hernádi I. Intrinsic anticipatory motives in non-human primate food consumption behaviour. iScience. 2024;27:109459.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38558930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10981109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2024.109459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Clinical Pharmacology and Biopharmaceutics Review(s). 2009; NDA 21-919. Retrieved from https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/nda/2009/021919s000pharmr.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bray GM. Exenatide. Am J Health-Syst Pharm. 2006;63:411–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16484515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2146/ajhp050459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gleitman H, Steinman F. Depression effect as a function of retention interval before and after shift in reward magnitude. J Comp Physiol Psychol. 1964;57:158–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14125081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/h0046320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez RC, Fernhoff D, David FG. Contrast, resistance to extinction, and forgetting in rats. J Comp Physiol Psychol. 1973;84:562–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/h0034882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hetherington MM, Caton S, Nekitsing C. Sensory‐Specific Satiation and Satiety. Time‐Dependent Measures of Perception in Sensory Evaluation, Wiley; 2017. p. 48–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Wang Y, Long Y, Wang L, Li Y, Gao F. et al. Alteration of sweet taste in high-fat diet induced obese rats after 4 weeks treatment with exenatide. Peptides. 2013;47:115–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23891652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.peptides.2013.07.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams DL, Hyvarinen N, Lilly N, Kay K, Dossat A, Parise E, et al. Maintenance on a high-fat diet impairs the anorexic response to glucagon-like-peptide-1 receptor activation. Physiol Behav. 2011;103:557–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21515295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3666166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2011.04.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mella R, Schmidt CB, Romagnoli P, Teske JA, Perez‐Leighton C. The food environment, preference, and experience modulate the effects of exendin‐4 on food intake and reward. Obesity. 2017;25:1844–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29086500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/oby.21939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandoval D, Barrera JG, Stefater MA, Sisley S, Woods SC, D’Alessio DD, et al. The Anorectic Effect of GLP-1 in Rats Is Nutrient Dependent. PLoS ONE. 2012;7:e51870.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23284795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3524167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Bloemendaal L, Veltman DJ, ten Kulve JS, Groot PFC, Ruhé HG, Barkhof F, et al. Brain reward‐system activation in response to anticipation and consumption of palatable food is altered by glucagon‐like peptide‐1 receptor activation in humans. Diabetes Obes Metab. 2015;17:878–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26094857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dom.12506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berridge KC. Wanting and liking: observations from the neuroscience and psychology laboratory. Inquiry. 2009;52:378</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20161627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00201740903087359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lapin BA, Gvozdik TE, Klots IN. Blood glucose levels in rhesus monkeys (Macaca mulatta) and cynomolgus macaques (Macaca fascicularis) under moderate stress and after recovery. Bull Exp Biol Med. 2013;154:497–500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23486590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10517-013-1986-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campfield LA, Smith FJ. Blood glucose dynamics and control of meal initiation: a pattern detection and recognition theory. Physiol Rev. 2003;83:25–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12506126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/physrev.00019.2002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ott V, Friedrich M, Prilop S, Lehnert H, Jauch-Chara K, Born J, et al. Food anticipation and subsequent food withdrawal increase serum cortisol in healthy men. Physiol Behav. 2011;103:594–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21550357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2011.04.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Power ML, Schulkin J. Anticipatory physiological regulation in feeding biology: Cephalic phase responses. Appetite. 2008;50:194–206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18045735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.appet.2007.10.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feldman M, Richardson CT. Role of thought, sight, smell, and taste of food in the cephalic phase of gastric acid secretion in humans. Gastroenterology. 1986;90:428–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3940915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0016-5085(86)90943-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaughan KL, Kaiser T, Peaden R, Anson RM, de Cabo R, Mattison JA. Caloric restriction study design limitations in rodent and nonhuman primate studies. J Gerontol Ser A. 2018;73:48–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/gerona/glx088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowland NE. Food or fluid restriction in common laboratory animals: balancing welfare considerations with scientific inquiry. Comp Med. 2007;57:149–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17536615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>