<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39238881</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2472-7245</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jul-Sep</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JB &amp; JS open access</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JB JS Open Access</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Robots on the Stage: A Snapshot of the American Robotic Total Knee Arthroplasty Market.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e24.00063</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2106/JBJS.OA.24.00063</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>» Computer-assisted robots aid orthopaedic surgeons in implant positioning and bony resection. Surgeons selecting a robot for their practice are faced with numerous options. This study aims to make the choice less daunting by reviewing the most commonly used Food and Drug Administration-approved robotic total knee arthroplasty platforms in the American arthroplasty market.» Modern total knee arthroplasty (TKA) robots use computer guidance to create a virtual knee model that serves as the surgeon's canvas for resection planning.» Most available robotic TKA (rTKA) systems are closed semiactive systems that restrict implant use to those of the manufacturer.» Each system has distinct imaging requirements, safety features, resection methods, and operating room footprints that will affect a surgeon's technique and practice.» Robots carry different purchase, maintenance, and equipment costs that will influence patient access across different socioeconomic groups.» Some studies show improved early patient-reported outcomes with rTKA, but long-term studies have yet to show clinical superiority over manual TKA.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Incorporated. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Inabathula</LastName><ForeName>Avinash</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0009-7546-3812</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northshore University Health System, Evanston, Illinois.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Semerdzhiev</LastName><ForeName>Dimitar I</ForeName><Initials>DI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8587-2902</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Arkansas College of Osteopathic Medicine, Fort Smith, Arkansas.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srinivasan</LastName><ForeName>Anand</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-0492-6820</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northshore University Health System, Evanston, Illinois.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amirouche</LastName><ForeName>Farid</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3002-4199</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northshore University Health System, Evanston, Illinois.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Puri</LastName><ForeName>Lalit</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-0066-7866</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northshore University Health System, Evanston, Illinois.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Piponov</LastName><ForeName>Hristo</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6965-609X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northshore University Health System, Evanston, Illinois.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>JB JS Open Access</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101726219</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2472-7245</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>Disclosure: The Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest forms are provided with the online version of the article (http://links.lww.com/JBJSOA/A659).</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39238881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11368221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2106/JBJS.OA.24.00063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JBJSOA-D-24-00063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Shah J, Vyas A, Vyas D. The history of robotics in surgical specialties. Am J Robotic Surg. 2014;1(1):12-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4677089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26677459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beyaz S. A brief history of artificial intelligence and robotic surgery in orthopedics &amp; traumatology and future expectations. Joint Dis Relat Surg. 2020;31(3):653-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7607941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32962606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mittelstadt B, Paul H, Kazanzides P, Zuhars J, Williamson B, Pettitt R, Cain P, Kloth D, Rose L, Musits B. Development of a surgical robot for cementless total hip replacement. Robotica. 1993;11(6):553-60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Joint Replacement Registry (AJRR). 2023 Annual Report. Rosemont, IL: American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons (AAOS), 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonios JK, Korber S, Sivasundaram L, Mayfield C, Kang HP, Oakes DA, Heckmann ND. Trends in computer navigation and robotic assistance for total knee arthroplasty in the United States: an analysis of patient and hospital factors. Arthroplast Today. 2019;5(1):88-95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6470347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31020030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mavrogenis AF, Savvidou OD, Mimidis G, Papanastasiou J, Koulalis D, Demertzis N, Papagelopoulos PJ. Computer-assisted navigation in orthopedic surgery. Orthopedics. 2013;36(8):631-42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23937743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacofsky DJ, Allen M. Robotics in arthroplasty: a comprehensive review. J Arthroplasty. 2016;31(10):2353-63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27325369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Ng N, Scott CEH, Blyth MJG, Haddad FS, Macpherson GJ, Patton JT, Clement ND. Robotic arm-assisted versus manual unicompartmental knee arthroplasty: a systematic review and meta-analysis of the MAKO robotic system. Bone Joint J. 2022;104-B(5):541-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9948441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35491572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell SW, Anthony I, Jones B, MacLean A, Rowe P, Blyth M. Improved accuracy of component positioning with robotic-assisted unicompartmental knee arthroplasty: data from a prospective, randomized controlled study. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2016;98(8):627-35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27098321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song E-K, Seon J-K, Yim J-H, Netravali NA, Bargar WL. Robotic-assisted TKA reduces postoperative alignment outliers and improves gap balance compared to conventional TKA. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2013;471(1):118-26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3528918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22669549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park SE, Lee CT. Comparison of robotic-assisted and conventional manual implantation of a primary total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2007;22(7):1054-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17920481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal N, To K, McDonnell S, Khan W. Clinical and radiological outcomes in robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Arthroplasty. 2020;35(11):3393-409.e2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32234326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thienpont E, Fennema P, Price A. Can technology improve alignment during knee arthroplasty. Knee. 2013;20(suppl 1):S21-28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24034591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scuderi GR, Tria AJ. Minimally Invasive Surgery in Orthopedics. New York, NY: Springer Science &amp; Business Media; 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim Y-H, Yoon S-H, Park J-W. Does robotic-assisted TKA result in better outcome scores or long-term survivorship than conventional TKA? A randomized, controlled trial. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2020;478(2):266-75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7438149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31389889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lang JE, Mannava S, Floyd AJ, Goddard MS, Smith BP, Mofidi A, Seyler TM, Jinnah RH. Robotic systems in orthopaedic surgery. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2011;93(10):1296-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21969424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen M, Jacofsky D. Evolution of robotics in arthroplasty. In: Lonner JH, ed. Robotics in Knee and Hip Arthroplasty. New York, NY: Springer International Publishing; 2019:13-25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas TL, Goh GS, Nguyen MK, Lonner JH. Pin-related complications in computer navigated and robotic-assisted knee arthroplasty: a systematic review. J Arthroplasty. 2022;37(11):2291-307.e2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35537611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Migliorini F, Cuozzo F, Oliva F, Eschweiler J, Hildebrand F, Maffulli N. Imageless navigation for primary total hip arthroplasty: a meta-analysis study. J Orthop Traumatol. 2022;23(1):21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9012775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35426527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith-Bindman R, Lipson J, Marcus R, Kim K-P, Mahesh M, Gould R, Berrington de González A, Miglioretti DL. Radiation dose associated with common computed tomography examinations and the associated lifetime attributable risk of cancer. Arch Intern Med. 2009;169(22):2078-86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4635397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20008690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Total knee arthroplasty using the THINK surgical robot. 2021. AAOS Orthopedic Video Theater. Available at: https://www.aaos.org/videos/video-detail-page/23038__Videos. Accessed February 18, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fehring TK. Rotational malalignment of the femoral component in total knee arthroplasty. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2000;380:72-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11064975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plaskos C, Hodgson AJ, Inkpen K, McGraw RW. Bone cutting errors in total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2002;17(6):698-705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12216022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liow MHL, Chin PL, Pang HN, Tay DK-J, Yeo S-J. THINK surgical TSolution-One (Robodoc) total knee arthroplasty. SICOT J. 2017;3:63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5663203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29087292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamara E, Berliner ZP, Hepinstall MS, Cooper HJ. Pin site complications associated with computer-assisted navigation in hip and knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2017;32(9):2842-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28522245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourne RB, Chesworth BM, Davis AM, Mahomed NN, Charron KDJ. Patient satisfaction after total knee arthroplasty: who is satisfied and who is not? Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2010;468(1):57-63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2795819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19844772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tompkins GS, Sypher KS, Li H-F, Griffin TM, Duwelius PJ. Robotic versus manual total knee arthroplasty in high volume surgeons: a comparison of cost and quality metrics. J Arthroplasty. 2022;37(8S):S782-S789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34952162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nogalo C, Meena A, Abermann E, Fink C. Complications and downsides of the robotic total knee arthroplasty: a systematic review. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc. 2023;31(3):736-50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9958158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35716186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>St Mart J-P, Goh EL. The current state of robotics in total knee arthroplasty. EFORT Open Rev. 2021;6(4):270-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8142057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34040804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoeffel D, Goldstein L, Intwala D, Kaindl L, Dineen A, Patel L, Mayle R. Systematic review and meta-analysis of economic and healthcare resource utilization outcomes for robotic versus manual total knee arthroplasty. J Robotic Surg. 2023;17(6):2899-910.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10678833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37819597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers EM, Havens AE. Predicting innovativeness. Sociological Inq. 1962;32(1):34-42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khlopas A, Sodhi N, Hozack WJ, Chen AF, Mahoney OM, Kinsey T, Orozco F, Mont MA. Patient-reported functional and satisfaction outcomes after robotic-arm-assisted total knee arthroplasty: early results of a prospective multicenter investigation. J Knee Surg. 2020;33(7):685-90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30959541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blum CL, Lepkowsky E, Hussein A, Wakelin EA, Plaskos C, Koenig JA. Patient expectations and satisfaction in robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty: a prospective two-year outcome study. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2021;141(12):2155-64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34283279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith AF, Eccles CJ, Bhimani SJ, Denehy KM, Bhimani RB, Smith LS, Malkani AL. Improved patient satisfaction following robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty. J Knee Surg. 2021;34(7):730-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31731324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffin J, Davis ET, Parsons H, Gemperle Mannion E, Khatri C, Ellard DR, Blyth MJ, Clement ND, Deehan D, Flynn N, Fox J, Grant NJ, Haddad FS, Hutchinson CE, Mason J, Mohindru B, Scott CEH, Smith TO, Skinner JA, Toms AD, Rees S, Underwood M, Metcalfe A. Robotic arthroplasty clinical and cost effectiveness randomised controlled trial (RACER-knee): a study protocol. BMJ Open. 2023;13(6):e068255.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10277111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37295832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joo PY, Chen AF, Richards J, Law TY, Taylor K, Marchand K, Clark G, Collopy D, Marchand RC, Roche M, Mont MA, Malkani AL. Clinical results and patient-reported outcomes following robotic-assisted primary total knee arthroplasty: a multicentre study. Bone Joint Open. 2022;3(8):589-95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9350694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35848995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchand KB, Moody R, Scholl LY, Bhowmik-Stoker M, Taylor KB, Mont MA, Marchand RC. Results of robotic-assisted versus manual total knee arthroplasty at 2-year follow-up. J Knee Surg. 2023;36(2):159-66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34187064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown ML, Javidan P, Early S, Bugbee W. Evolving etiologies and rates of revision total knee arthroplasty: a 10-year institutional report. Arthroplasty. 2022;4(1):39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9404596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36008846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirchner GJ, Stambough JB, Jimenez E, Nikkel LE. Robotic-assisted TKA is not associated with decreased odds of early revision: an analysis of the American Joint Replacement Registry. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2024;482(2):303-10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10776156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37962943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Li L, Fu J, Xu C, Ni M, Chai W, Hao L, Zhang G, Chen J. Early clinical and radiographic outcomes of robot-assisted versus conventional manual total knee arthroplasty: a randomized controlled study. Orthop Surg. 2022;14(9):1972-80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9483055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35848154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunaratne R, Pratt DN, Banda J, Fick DP, Khan RJK, Robertson BW. Patient dissatisfaction following total knee arthroplasty: a systematic review of the literature. J Arthroplasty. 2017;32(12):3854-60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28844632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiranaka T, Suda Y, Saitoh A, Tanaka A, Arimoto A, Koide M, Fujishiro T, Okamoto K. Current concept of kinematic alignment total knee arthroplasty and its derivatives. Bone Joint Open. 2022;3(5):390-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9134837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35532356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajan PV, Khlopas A, Klika A, Molloy R, Krebs V, Piuzzi NS. The cost-effectiveness of robotic-assisted versus manual total knee arthroplasty: a Markov model-based evaluation. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2022;30(4):168-76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35040808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Condon A. A breakdown of 7 robots in spine surgery; 2021. Available at: https://www.beckersspine.com/robotics/52042-a-breakdown-of-7-robots-in-spine-surgery.html. Accessed September 10, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walgrave S, Oussedik S. Comparative assessment of current robotic-assisted systems in primary total knee arthroplasty. Bone Joint Open. 2023;4(1):13-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9887337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36602297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brinkman JC, Christopher ZK, Moore ML, Pollock JR, Haglin JM, Bingham JS. Patient interest in robotic total joint arthroplasty is exponential: a 10-year Google trends analysis. Arthroplast Today. 2022;15:13-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8961076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35360676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peterman NJ, Pagani N, Mann R, Li RL, Gasienica J, Naik A, Sun D. Disparities in access to robotic knee arthroplasty: a geospatial analysis. J Arthroplasty. 2024;39(4):864-70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37852446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callahan LF, Cleveland RJ, Allen KD, Golightly Y. Racial/ethnic, socioeconomic, and geographic disparities in the epidemiology of knee and hip osteoarthritis. Rheum Dis Clin. 2021;47(1):1-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8248516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34042049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boylan M, Suchman K, Vigdorchik J, Slover J, Bosco J. Technology-assisted hip and knee arthroplasties: an analysis of utilization trends. J Arthroplasty. 2018;33(4):1019-23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29290333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deckey DG, Verhey JT, Rosenow CS, Doan MK, McQuivey KS, Joseph AM, Schwartz AJ, Clarke HD, Bingham JS. Robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty allows for trainee involvement and teaching without lengthening operative time. J Arthroplasty. 2022;37(6S):S201-S206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35184933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell J, Wang J, Bukowski B, Greiner J, Wolford B, Oyer M, Illgen RL. Relative clinical outcomes comparing manual and robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty at minimum 1-year follow-up. HSS J. 2021;17(3):267-73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8436347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34539266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolam SM, Tay ML, Zaidi F, Sidaginamale RP, Hanlon M, Munro JT, Monk AP. Introduction of ROSA robotic-arm system for total knee arthroplasty is associated with a minimal learning curve for operative time. J Exp Orthop. 2022;9(1):86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9427173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36042122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Z, Bhowmik-Stoker M, Palmer M, Coppolecchia A, Harder B, Mont MA, Marchand RC. Time-based learning curve for robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty: a multicenter study. J Knee Surg. 2023;36(8):873-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35255506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchand KB, Ehiorobo J, Mathew KK, Marchand RC, Mont MA. Learning curve of robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty for a high-volume surgeon. J Knee Surg. 2022;35(4):409-15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32838457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen TN, Anger JT, Shamash K, Cohen KA, Nasseri Y, Francis SE, Fimpler M, Avenido R, Gewertz BL, Shouhed D. Discovering the barriers to efficient robotic operating room turnover time: perceptions vs. reality. J Robotic Surg. 2020;14(5):717-24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31933120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souders CP, Catchpole KR, Wood LN, Solnik JM, Avenido RM, Strauss PL, Eilber KS, Anger JT. Reducing operating room turnover time for robotic surgery using a motor racing pit stop model. World J Surg. 2017;41(8):1943-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6010351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28357497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beldame J, Boisrenoult P, Beaufils P. Pin track induced fractures around computer-assisted TKA. Orthop Traumatol Surg Res. 2010;96(3):249-55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20488143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith TJ, Siddiqi A, Forte SA, Judice A, Sculco PK, Vigdorchik JM, Schwarzkopf R, Springer BD. Periprosthetic fractures through tracking pin sites following computer navigated and robotic total and unicompartmental knee arthroplasty: a systematic review. JBJS Rev. 2021;9(1):e20.00091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33502139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun AG, Qutami M, Pasko KBD. Do bicortical diaphyseal array pins create the risk of periprosthetic fracture in robotic-assisted knee arthroplasties? Arthroplasty. 2021;3(1):25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8796534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35236500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desai SS, Kunes JA, Held MB, Ren M, deMeireles AJ, Geller JA, Shah RP, Cooper HJ. A comparison of pin site complications between large and small pin diameters in robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty. J Exp Orthop. 2023;10(1):22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10006377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36897468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shetty T, Nguyen JT, Sasaki M, Wu A, Bogner E, Burge A, Cogsil T, Dalal A, Halvorsen K, Cummings K, Su EP, Lyman S. Risk factors for acute nerve injury after total knee arthroplasty. Muscle Nerve. 2018;57(6):946-50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5951729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29266269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beltran MJ, Collinge CA, Patzkowski JC, Masini BD, Blease RE, Hsu JR, Skeletal Trauma Research Consortium STReC. The safe zone for external fixator pins in the femur. J Orthop Trauma. 2012;26(11):643-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22473068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kayani B, Konan S, Pietrzak JRT, Haddad FS. Iatrogenic bone and soft tissue trauma in robotic-arm assisted total knee arthroplasty compared with conventional jig-based total knee arthroplasty: a prospective cohort study and validation of a new classification system. J Arthroplasty. 2018;33(8):2496-501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29699827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kayani B, Tahmassebi J, Ayuob A, Konan S, Oussedik S, Haddad FS. A prospective randomized controlled trial comparing the systemic inflammatory response in conventional jig-based total knee arthroplasty versus robotic-arm assisted total knee arthroplasty. Bone Joint J. 2021;103-B(1):113-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33380182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khlopas A, Sodhi N, Sultan AA, Chughtai M, Molloy RM, Mont MA. Robotic arm–assisted total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2018;33(7):2002-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29506926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan H, Dhillon K, Mahapatra P, Popat R, Zakieh O, Kim WJ, Nathwani D. Blood loss and transfusion risk in robotic-assisted knee arthroplasty: a retrospective analysis. Int J Med Robot. 2021;17(6):e2308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34288356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stimson LN, Steelman KR, Hamilton DA, Chen C, Darwiche HF, Mehaidli A. Evaluation of blood loss in conventional vs MAKOplasty total knee arthroplasty. Arthroplast Today. 2022;16:224-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9307488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35880226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarwala R. Tourniquet versus no tourniquet in total knee arthroplasty: we don't have a winner yet: commentary on article by Rahul Goel, MD, et al: “Tourniquet use does not affect functional outcomes or pain after total knee arthroplasty. A prospective, double-blinded, randomized controlled trial.” J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2019;101(20):e109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31626017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arthur JR, Spangehl MJ. Tourniquet use in total knee arthroplasty. J Knee Surg. 2019;32(8):719-29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30822788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tai T-W, Chang C-W, Lai K-A, Lin C-J, Yang C-Y. Effects of tourniquet use on blood loss and soft-tissue damage in total knee arthroplasty: a randomized controlled trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2012;94(24):2209-15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23318610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCarthy Deering E, Hu SY, Abdulkarim A. Does tourniquet use in TKA increase postoperative pain? A systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2019;477(3):547-58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6382207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30461513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MAKO Robotic Arm System User Guide. Ft Lauderdale, FL: Mako Surgical Corp; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roche M. The MAKO robotic-arm knee arthroplasty system. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2021;141(12):2043-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34757462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clatworthy M. Patient-specific TKA with the VELYSTM robotic-assisted solution. Surg Technology Int. 2022;40:315-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35325451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knapp PW, Nett MP, Scuderi GR. Optimizing total knee arthroplasty with ROSA® robotic technology. Surg Technol Int. 2022;40:289-96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35015900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ROSA Knee User Manual and Surgical Technique v1.4. Montreal, Canada: Zimmer CAS.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batailler C, Hannouche D, Benazzo F, Parratte S. Concepts and techniques of a new robotically assisted technique for total knee arthroplasty: the ROSA knee system. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2021;141(12):2049-58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34255173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real Intelligence. CORI for Knee Arthroplasty User Manual. Version 500185 REVB. Memphis, TN: Simth &amp; Nephew.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamska O, Modzelewski K, Szymczak J, Świderek J, Maciąg B, Czuchaj P, Poniatowska M, Wnuk A. Robotic-assisted total knee arthroplasty utilizing NAVIO, CORI imageless systems and manual TKA accurately restore femoral rotational alignment and yield satisfactory clinical outcomes: a randomized controlled trial. Medicina (Kaunas, Lithuania). 2023;59(2):236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9963242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36837438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>2300.6-GLBL-en-ROSA-Knee-System-User-Manual-and-Surg-Tech-digital1.pdf. Available at: https://www.zimmerbiomet.com/content/dam/zb-corporate/en/education-resources/surgical-techniques/specialties/robotics/2300.6-GLBL-en-ROSA-Knee-System-User-Manual-and-Surg-Tech-digital1.pdf. Accessed September 10, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>VELYS robotic-assisted solution operating dimensions. Raynham, MA: DePuy Synthes; 2021. p. 1-2. Report No.: 103723271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramkumar PN, Karnuta JM, Navarro SM, Haeberle HS, Scuderi GR, Mont MA, Krebs VE, Patterson BM. Deep learning preoperatively predicts value metrics for primary total knee arthroplasty: development and validation of an artificial neural network model. J Arthroplasty. 2019;34(10):2220-7.e1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31285089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>