<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39248187</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-1738</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>09</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food science and technology international = Ciencia y tecnologia de los alimentos internacional</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Sci Technol Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Advancing plant-based meat analogs: Composite blend of pulse protein reinforcing structure with fibrous mushroom, jackfruit seed powder and carboxymethyl cellulose.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>10820132241278958</StartPage><MedlinePgn>10820132241278958</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/10820132241278958</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In this study, Indian pulse proteins from cowpeas, yellow peas, green gram, and horse gram were used to create plant-based meatball analogs. The nutritional composition, molecular functional groups, color, and texture of meatball analogs T1, T2, and T3 and mutton meatballs were thoroughly analyzed. T1 had highest protein (51%) compared to control (19%), T2 (45%), and T3 (36%), but fiber content (1.26%) was less in T1 compared to control (2.86%), T2 (3.33%), and T3 (3.49%). The more is fibrous raw materials; lower will be the hardness of meat analogs. T1 had consistent fracturability, hardness, cohesiveness, and adhesiveness, and was superior in springiness, gumminess, resilience, and chewiness compared to T2, T3, and control. Sensory evaluation results reported that T1 was more consistent with control sample in terms of color, texture, juiciness, and overall acceptability and no significant difference was reported among the two (<i>p</i> &gt; .05). The L* and b* values of T1 were more consistent with control compared to other two. Potato starch, salt, spice mix, coriander leaves, beet root pulp, jackfruit seed powder, rose water, carboxy methyl cellulose and rehydrated mushrooms showed a positive impact on sensory and textural attributes. The Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectra revealed that the protein fractions were not affected by the processing conditions. FTIR results confirm the presence of secondary structural components such as α-helix, β-sheet, and β-turn. The interaction between the starchy fibrous material and protein fractions were identified clearly via FTIR. The T1 meat analog was superior in terms of color, organoleptic and textural properties compared to T2 and T3 and more close to mutton meatballs. These results will open up the new horizons in this area and pave the way for the large production and marketing of plant based meat analogs, which will reduces the health and sustainable raising issues from consumption of mutton meat.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Achinna</LastName><ForeName>Poshadri</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Processing Technology, Professor Jayashankar Telangana State Agricultural University, Hyderabad, India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">424093</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malleboina</LastName><ForeName>Penchalaraju</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7985-7207</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, School of Agricultural Sciences, Malla Reddy University, Hyderabad, India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">594979</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Joshi</LastName><ForeName>Anuprita Ashokrao</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Process Technology, College of Food Technology, Vasantrao Naik Marthwada Krishi Vidyapeethi, Parbhani, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Padmavathi</LastName><ForeName>T V N</ForeName><Initials>TVN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Safety and Quality Assurance, Professor Jayashankar Telangana State Agricultural University, Hyderabad, India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">424093</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Swaroopa</LastName><ForeName>Gugulothu</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering, College of Food Technology, Vasantrao Naik Marthwada Krishi Vidyapeethi, Parbhani, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nikkam</LastName><ForeName>Indra Teja</ForeName><Initials>IT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Microbiology and Safety, College of Food Technology, Vasantrao Naik Marthwada Krishi Vidyapeeth, Parbhani, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Anshul</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food chemistry and Nutrition, College of Food Technology, Vasantrao Naik Marthwada Krishi Vidyapeeth, Parbhani, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Food Sci Technol Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9889534</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1082-0132</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meatball analogs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adhesiveness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chewiness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gumminess</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hardness</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>DECLARATION OF CONFLICTING INTERESTSThe authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39248187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/10820132241278958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>