<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">39245919</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Concentration of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in bread and health risk assessment across the globe: A systematic review and meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13411</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13411</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.13411</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Although bread is the principal food in most countries, polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) may be present and pose a potential risk to consumers. The aim of this review is to provide a comprehensive report on the concentration and health risks associated with PAHs in bread around the world. Various databases, such as Scopus, PubMed, Science Direct, and Google Scholar, were searched from their beginnings until December 2023 for this systematic review, which included 34 potentially relevant articles with data relating to 1057 bread samples. Utilizing a multilevel regression modeling approach, the study evaluated various factors such as fuel type, bread type, and geographical location. Following the initial evaluation, in 26.47% and 20.28% of all studies, the levels of Bap and PAH4 were higher than the permissible limit values, respectively. Based on the isomer ratios, 55.88% of the studies associated the presence of PAHs in bread samples with pyrogenic/coal combustion sources. According to the carcinogenic risk results, bread consumers in all studies have been exposed to moderate or high levels of carcinogenicity. The most significant risk levels are associated with the consumption of bread in Egypt, Kuwait, Iran, and India. Moreover, meta-regression analysis demonstrated significantly higher toxicity equivalent quotient and cancer risk mean values in bread baked using fossil fuels compared to other sources (p &lt; .05). The high concentrations of PAHs, especially Benzo[a]pyrene, in bread pose a serious public health risk. Stringent regulations and monitoring are crucial to reduce contamination. Further research is necessary to develop safe processing methods to remove PAHs in bread.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asadi Touranlou</LastName><ForeName>Fateme</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9349-2398</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Toxicology Research Center, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, Faculty of Medicine, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hashemi</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9998-6727</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Toxicology Research Center, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, Faculty of Medicine, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghavami</LastName><ForeName>Vahid</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6358-0207</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, School of Health, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tavakoly Sany</LastName><ForeName>Seyedeh Belin</ForeName><Initials>SB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7891-4449</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health, Safety, Environment Management, School of Health Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Social Determinants of Health Research Center, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>402139</GrantID><Agency>Mashhad University of Medical Sciences</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011084">Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011084" MajorTopicYN="Y">Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001939" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bread</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018570" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bread</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health risk assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (pahs)</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39245919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.13411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdul‐Gafaru, O. (2017). Health risk assessment of PAH in bread [Master thesis, Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aghalari, Z., Dahms, H.‐U., &amp; Sillanpää, M. (2022). Evaluation of nutrients in bread: A systematic review. Journal of Health, Population and Nutrition, 41(1), 50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed, M. T., Hadi, E.‐S. A., El Samahy, S., &amp; Youssof, K. (2000). The influence of baking fuel on residues of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and heavy metals in bread. Journal of hazardous materials, 80(1–3), 1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akbari‐Adergani, B., Mahmood‐Babooi, K., Salehi, A., Khaniki, G. J., Shariatifar, N., Sadighara, P., &amp; Zeinali, T. (2021). GC–MS determination of the content of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in bread and potato Tahdig prepared with the common edible oil. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 193(8), 1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al‐Rashdan, A., Helaleh, M. I., Nisar, A., Ibtisam, A., &amp; Al‐Ballam, Z. (2010). Determination of the levels of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in toasted bread using gas chromatography mass spectrometry. International Journal of Analytical Chemistry, 2010, 821216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alinezhad, Z., Hashemi, M., &amp; Tavakoly Sany, S. B. (2024). Concentration of heavy metals in pasteurized and sterilized milk and health risk assessment across the globe: A systematic review. PLoS ONE, 19(2), e0296649.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alomirah, H., Al‐Zenki, S., Al‐Hooti, S., Zaghloul, S., Sawaya, W., Ahmed, N., &amp; Kannan, K. (2011). Concentrations and dietary exposure to polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) from grilled and smoked foods. Food Control, 22(12), 2028–2035.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsuhaibani, A. M. (2018). Rheological and nutritional properties and sensory evaluation of bread fortified with natural sources of calcium. Journal of Food Quality, 2018, 1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atsdr, U. S.. (1997). Agency for toxic substances and disease registry. Case Studies in environmental medicine. http://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/HEC/CSEM/csem.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asadi Touranlou, F., Raeesi, A., &amp; Rezaei, M. (2024). Health risk assessment of the concentration of heavy metals in Pistacia species: A global systematic review. Nutrition &amp; Food Science, 54(3), 468–482.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atwa, M. (2015). Determination of polycyclic aromatic of hydrocarbons (pahs) benzo [a] pyrene level in heat treated food from Egyptian market by GC and HPLC‐fluoresences detection. Journal of Agricultural Chemistry and Biotechnology, 6(6), 137–153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. (2007). Findings of the EFSA data collection on polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in food. EFSA Journal, 5(9), 33r.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. (2008). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in food‐scientific opinion of the panel on contaminants in the food chain. EFSA Journal, 6(8), 724.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bansal, V., &amp; Kim, K.‐H. (2015). Review of PAH contamination in food products and their health hazards. Environment International, 84, 26–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basaran, B. (2022). Comparison of heavy metal levels and health risk assessment of different bread types marketed in Turkey. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis, 108, 104443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basin, F. R. (2022). A critical appraisal of PAH ratios as indicators of PAH source and composition. Organic Geochemistry, 33(4), 489–515.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boadu, E. F., Wang, C. C., &amp; Sunindijo, R. Y. (2020). Characteristics of the construction industry in developing countries and its implications for health and safety: An exploratory study in Ghana. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17(11), 4110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chawda, S., Tarafdar, A., Sinha, A., &amp; Mishra, B. K. (2017). Profiling and health risk assessment of PAHs content in tandoori and tawa bread from India. Polycyclic Aromatic Compounds, 40, 21–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, B.‐H., Inbaraj, B. S., &amp; Hsu, K.‐C. (2022). Recent advances in the analysis of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in food and water. Journal of Food and Drug Analysis, 30(4), 494–522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheung, M. W.‐L. (2014). Modeling dependent effect sizes with three‐level meta‐analyses: A structural equation modeling approach. Psychological Methods, 19(2), 211–229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciecierska, M., &amp; Obiedziński, M. (2013). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in the bakery chain. Food Chemistry, 141(1), 1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cust, A., Skilton, M., Van Bakel, M., Halkjaer, J., Olsen, A., Agnoli, C., Psaltopoulou, T., Buurma, E., Sonestedt, E., &amp; Chirlaque, M. (2009). Total dietary carbohydrate, sugar, starch and fibre intakes in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition. European Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 63(4), S37–S60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalhina, N., Fedorenko, E., Sychik, S., &amp; Belysheva, L. (2020). Integral assessment of food products contamination with priority polyaromatic hydrocarbons. Health Risk Analysis, 2020(3), 77–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demaneche, S., Meyer, C., Micoud, J., Louwagie, M., Willison, J. C., &amp; Jouanneau, Y. (2004). Identification and functional analysis of two aromatic‐ring‐hydroxylating dioxygenases from a Sphingomonas strain that degrades various polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 70(11), 6714–6725.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demirtaş, B., Kaya, A., &amp; Dağıstan, E. (2018). Consumers ′bread consumption habits and waste status: Hatay/Turkey example. Turkish Journal of Agriculture‐Food Science and Technology, 6(11), 1653–1661.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dennis, M., Massey, R., Cripps, G., Venn, I., Howarth, N., &amp; Lee, G. (1991). Factors affecting the polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon content of cereals, fats and other food products. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants, 8(4), 517–530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domingo, J. L., &amp; Nadal, M. (2015). Human dietary exposure to polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons: A review of the scientific literature. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 86, 144–153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Einolghozati, M., Talebi‐Ghane, E., &amp; Amirsadeghi, S. (2022). Evaluation of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in processed cereals: A meta‐analysis study, systematic review, and health risk assessment. Heliyon, 8, e12168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). (2017). Benzo[a]pyrene (BaP) (CASRN 50‐32‐8 | DTXSID2020139). EPA. https://cfpub.epa.gov/ncea/iris2/chemicallanding.cfm?substance_nmbr=136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eslamizad, S., Kobarfard, F., Javidnia, K., Sadeghi, R., Bayat, M., Shahanipour, S., Khalighian, N., &amp; Yazdanpanah, H. (2016). Determination of benzo [a] pyrene in traditional, industrial and semi‐industrial breads using a modified QuEChERS extraction, dispersive SPE and GC–MS and estimation of its dietary intake. Iranian Journal of Pharmaceutical Research: IJPR, 15, (Suppl), 165–174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eslamizad, S., Kobarfard, F., Naderi, N., &amp; Yazdanpanah, H. (2021). Investigation of effective factors on the formation of acrylamide and benzo (a) pyrene in the baking process of different bread types traditional, semi‐industrial and industrial. Research and Innovation in Food Science and Technology, 10(1), 95–106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eslamizad, S., Yazdanpanah, H., Javidnia, K., Sadeghi, R., Bayat, M., Shahabipour, S., Khalighian, N., &amp; Kobarfard, F. (2016). Validation of an analytical method for determination of benzo [a] pyrene bread using QuEChERS method by GC–MS. Iranian Journal of Pharmaceutical Research: IJPR, 15(2), 465–474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fasano, E., Yebra‐Pimentel, I., Martinez‐Carballo, E., &amp; Simal‐Gándara, J. (2016). Profiling, distribution and levels of carcinogenic polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in traditional smoked plant and animal foods. Food Control, 59, 581–590.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes, A., Holland, J., Petch, R., Miller, M., Carlisle, S., Stewart, J., &amp; Rose, M. (2011). Survey for polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in cereals, cereal products, vegetables, vegetable products and traditionally‐smoked foods. Food and Environment Research Agency (FERA).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández‐Castilla, B., Beretvas, S. N., Onghena, P., &amp; Van den Noortgate, W. (2019). Multilevel models in meta‐analysis: A systematic review of their application and suggestions. In Research Synthesis 2019 incl. Pre‐Conference Symposium Big Data in Psychology. ZPID.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleming, P. S., Koletsi, D., &amp; Pandis, N. (2014). Blinded by PRISMA: Are systematic reviewers focusing on PRISMA and ignoring other guidelines? PLoS ONE, 9(5), e96407.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghasemi, S., Hashemi, M., Aval, M. G., Safarian, M., Khanzadi, S., Orooji, A., &amp; Sany, S. B. T. (2022). Effect of baking methods types on residues of heavy metals in the different breads produced with wheat flour in Iran: A case study of Mashhad. Journal of Chemical Health Risks, 12(1), 00–00.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gizaw, Z. (2019). Public health risks related to food safety issues in the food market: A systematic literature review. Environmental Health and Preventive Medicine, 24, 1–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrer, M., Cuijpers, P., Furukawa, T., &amp; Ebert, D. (2021). Doing meta‐analysis with R: A hands‐on guide. Chapman and Hall/CRC.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins, J. P., Thompson, S. G., Deeks, J. J., &amp; Altman, D. G. (2003). Measuring inconsistency in meta‐analyses. BMJ, 327(7414), 557–560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Igbiri, S., Udowelle, N. A., Ekhator, O. C., Asomugha, R. N., Igweze, Z. N., &amp; Orisakwe, O. E. (2017). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in edible mushrooms from Niger Delta, Nigeria: Carcinogenic and non‐carcinogenic health risk assessment. Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention: APJCP, 18(2), 437–447.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwegbue, C. M. (2016). Concentrations and hazards of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in hawked baked ready‐to‐eat foods in Nigeria. Acta Alimentaria, 45(2), 175–181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahed Khaniki, G., Ahmadi, M., Ahmadabadi, M., Shariatifar, N., Ahmadkhaniha, R., Rastkari, N., &amp; Sadighara, P. (2021). Assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in traditional breads consumed by people in Tehran city of Iran and the calculation of their daily intake. International Journal of Environmental Analytical Chemistry, 103, 1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahed Khaniki, G., Ahmadi, M., Ahmadabadi, M., Shariatifar, N., Ahmadkhaniha, R., Rastkari, N., &amp; Sadighara, P. (2023). Assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in traditional breads consumed by people in Tehran city of Iran and the calculation of their daily intake. International Journal of Environmental Analytical Chemistry, 103(11), 2533–2541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin, H., Yuan, W., Li, W., Yang, J., Zhou, Z., Zhao, L., Li, Y., &amp; Qi, F. (2023). Combustion chemistry of aromatic hydrocarbons. Progress in Energy and Combustion Science, 96, 101076.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kacmaz, S. (2016). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in cereal products on the Turkish market. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part B, 9(3), 191–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamalabadi, M., Kamankesh, M., Mohammadi, A., Hadian, Z., &amp; Ferdowsi, R. (2019). Contamination and daily intake of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in Iranian bread samples. Polycyclic Aromatic Compounds, 40(4), 1187–1195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karşı, M. B. B., Berberler, E., Kurhan, Ş., Bilaloğlu, K., Çakır, İ., &amp; Karakaş, D. (2021). Levels, dietary exposure, and health risk estimation of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in bread baked with different oven and fuel types. Polycyclic Aromatic Compounds, 1–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karşı, M. B. B., Berberler, E., Kurhan, Ş., Bilaloğlu, K., Çakır, İ., &amp; Karakaş, D. (2023). Levels, dietary exposure, and health risk estimation of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in bread baked with different oven and fuel types. Polycyclic Aromatic Compounds, 43(1), 811–825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kayali‐Sayadi, M., Rubio‐Barroso, S., Garcia‐Iranzo, R., &amp; Polo‐Diez, L. (2000). Determination of selected polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in toasted bread by supercritical fluid extraction and HPLC with fluorimetric detection. Journal of Liquid Chromatography and Related Technologies, 23, 1913–1925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kempf, K., Röhling, M., Kolb, H., &amp; Martin, S. (2023). Impact of a low‐insulin‐stimulating bread on weight development—A real life randomised controlled trial. Nutrients, 15, 1301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalili, F., Shariatifar, N., Dehghani, M. H., Yaghmaeian, K., Nodehi, R. N., Yaseri, M., &amp; Arabameri, M. (2022). The analysis and probabilistic health risk assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in cereal products. Environ Sci Pollut Res Int, 29, 31099–31109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanverdiluo, S., Talebi‐Ghane, E., &amp; Heshmati, A. (2021). The concentration of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in mother milk: A global systematic review, meta‐analysis and health risk assessment of infants. Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences, 28(12), 6869–6875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, W., Choi, J., Kang, H. J., Lee, J.‐W., Moon, B., Joo, Y.‐S., &amp; Lee, K.‐W. (2022). Monitoring and risk assessment of eight polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH8) in daily consumed agricultural products in South Korea. Polycyclic Aromatic Compounds, 42(4), 1141–1156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobets, T., Smith, B. P., &amp; Williams, G. M. (2022). Food‐borne chemical carcinogens and the evidence for human cancer risk. Foods, 11(18), 2828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kong, S., Shi, J., Lu, B., Qiu, W., Zhang, B., Peng, Y., Zhang, B., &amp; Bai, Z. (2011). Characterization of PAHs within PM10 fraction for ashes from coke production, iron smelt, heating station and power plant stacks in Liaoning province, China. Atmospheric Environment, 45(23), 3777–3785.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Köse, B. G., Pekmezci, H., &amp; Basaran, B. (2024). Bread consumption‐induced heavy metal exposures and health risk assessment of pregnant women: Turkey. Biological Trace Element Research, 202, 473–480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumosani, T. A., Moselhy, S. S., Asseri, A. M., &amp; Asseri, A. H. (2013). Detection of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in different types of processed foods. Toxicology and Industrial Health, 29(3), 300–304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawal, A. T. (2017). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons. A review. Cogent Environmental Science, 3(1), 1339841.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, G., Wu, S., Zeng, J., Wang, L., &amp; Yu, W. (2016). Effect of frying and aluminium on the levels and migration of parent and oxygenated PAHs in a popular Chinese fried bread youtiao. Food Chemistry, 209, 123–130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoudpour, M., Pilevar, Z., Javanmardi, F., Taram, F., &amp; Mousavi, M.‐M. (2018). PAHs in toasted bread: Determination using microwave‐assisted extraction and dispersive liquid–liquid microextraction followed by high‐performance liquid chromatography. Analytical Methods, 10(20), 2398–2404.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martorell, I., Perelló, G., Martí‐Cid, R., Castell, V., Llobet, J. M., &amp; Domingo, J. L. (2010). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) in foods and estimated PAH intake by the population of Catalonia, Spain: Temporal trend. Environment International, 36(5), 424–432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mollakhalili‐meybodi, N., Sheidaei, Z., Khorshidian, N., Nematollahi, A., &amp; Khanniri, E. (2023). Sensory attributes of wheat bread: A review of influential factors. Journal of Food Measurement and Characterization, 17(3), 2172–2181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moradi, M., Ghavami, V., Niazi, A., Shirvan, F. S., &amp; Rasa, S. (2023). The effect of Salvia officinalis on hot flashes in postmenopausal women: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. International Journal of Community Based Nursing and Midwifery, 11(3), 169–178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moradi, V., Ardabili, S. M. S., Shakoori, A., &amp; Hoseyni, S. E. (2020). Development of a GC–MS method for determination of various polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in Iranian traditional and semi‐industrial taftoon bread. Iranian Journal of Pharmaceutical Research: IJPR, 19(3), 183–194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munsif, R., Zubair, M., Aziz, A., &amp; Zafar, M. N. (2021). Industrial air emission pollution: Potential sources and sustainable mitigation. In Environmental emissions. IntechOpen.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namayandeh, S. M., Lotfi, M. H., Jafari, V., Dad, V., Biabani, J., Razi, M. H., &amp; Sangsefidi, Z. S. (2018). Salt content in traditional and nontraditional breads in Yazd city, Iran, 2015–2016. Journal of Nutrition and Food Security, 3(4), 185–192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nionelli, L., Wang, Y., Pontonio, E., Immonen, M., Rizzello, C., Maina, H., Katina, K., &amp; Coda, R. (2020). Antifungal effect of bioprocessed surplus bread as ingredient for bread‐making: Identification of active compounds and impact on shelf‐life. Food Control, 118, 107437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noori, S. M. A., Zadehdabagh, R., Najafi, N., Tishezan, L., Zerehpoush, M., Jazayeri, S. M. H. M., Hashemi, M., &amp; Sany, S. B. T. (2022). Measurement of the toxic trace elements in commercial wheat flours: Potential health risk via dietary intake. Journal of Chemical Health Risks, 12(4), 00–00.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odika, I. M., Nwanisobi, G. C., Nwankwo, N. V., Mmaduakor, E. C., &amp; Ikeh, O. A. (2023). Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons, PAHs Contamination Levels and Health Risks in Foods Consumed in Nigeria: A Review. Asian Journal of Food Research and Nutrition, 2, 558–570.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ofori, S. A., Cobbina, S. J., &amp; Doke, D. A. (2020). The occurrence and levels of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in African environments—A systematic review. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 27(26), 32389–32431.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orecchio, S., &amp; Papuzza, V. (2009). Levels, fingerprint and daily intake of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in bread baked using wood as fuel. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 164(2–3), 876–883.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2019). Meeting report: WHO technical consultation: nutrition‐related health products and the World Health Organization model list of essential medicines–practical considerations and feasibility: Geneva, Switzerland, 20–21 September 2018. WHO.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortiz, J. E., Sánchez‐Palencia, Y., Gallego, J. L., Borrego, Á. G., Baragaño, D., &amp; Torres, T. (2023). Deposition of atmospheric polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in rural areas: Current data and historical record from an ombrotrophic peatland. International Journal of Coal Geology, 268, 104199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacin, A., Bovier, E. C., Cano, G., Taglieri, D., &amp; Pezzani, C. H. (2010). Effect of the bread making process on wheat flour contaminated by deoxynivalenol and exposure estimate. Food Control, 21(4), 492–495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palade, L. M., Negoiță, M., Adascălului, A. C., &amp; Mihai, A. L. (2023). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon occurrence and formation in processed meat, edible oils, and cereal‐derived products: A review. Applied Sciences, 13(13), 7877.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peiravian, F., Shakoori, A., Moradi, V., Salamzadeh, J., &amp; Mahboubi, A. (2021). Simultaneous analysis of 10 priority PAHs in Iranian Sangak bread samples by developing a GC–MS method. Iranian Journal of Pharmaceutical Research: IJPR, 20(2), 433–440.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racovita, R. C., Secuianu, C., Ciuca, M. D., &amp; Israel‐Roming, F. (2020). Effects of smoking temperature, smoking time, and type of wood sawdust on polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon accumulation levels in directly smoked pork sausages. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 68(35), 9530–9536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rascón, A. J., Azzouz, A., &amp; Ballesteros, E. (2018). Assessing polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in cereal‐based foodstuffs by using a continuous solid‐phase extraction system and gas chromatography–mass spectrometry. Food Control, 92, 92–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rey‐Salgueiro, L., García‐Falcón, M. S., Martínez‐Carballo, E., &amp; Simal‐Gándara, J. (2008). Effects of toasting procedures on the levels of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in toasted bread. Food Chemistry, 108(2), 607–615.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rey‐Salgueiro, L., Martínez‐Carballo, E., García‐Falcón, M. S., &amp; Simal‐Gándara, J. (2008). Effects of a chemical company fire on the occurrence of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in plant foods. Food Chemistry, 108(1), 347–353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rostampour, R., Kamalabadi, M., Kamankesh, M., Hadian, Z., Jazaeri, S., Mohammadi, A., &amp; Zolgharnein, J. (2017). An efficient, sensitive and fast microextraction method followed by gas chromatography‐mass spectrometry for the determination of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in bread samples. Analytical Methods, 9(44), 6246–6253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rozentale, I., Zacs, D., Perkons, I., &amp; Bartkevics, V. (2017). A comparison of gas chromatography coupled to tandem quadrupole mass spectrometry and high‐resolution sector mass spectrometry for sensitive determination of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in cereal products. Food Chemistry, 221, 1291–1297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha, M., Togo, A., Mizukawa, K., Murakami, M., Takada, H., Zakaria, M. P., Chiem, N. H., Tuyen, B. C., Prudente, M., &amp; Boonyatumanond, R. (2009). Sources of sedimentary PAHs in tropical Asian waters: Differentiation between pyrogenic and petrogenic sources by alkyl homolog abundance. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 58(2), 189–200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sampaio, G. R., Guizellini, G. M., da Silva, S. A., de Almeida, A. P., Pinaffi‐Langley, A. C. C., Rogero, M. M., de Camargo, A. C., &amp; Torres, E. A. (2021). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in foods: Biological effects, legislation, occurrence, analytical methods, and strategies to reduce their formation. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 22(11), 6010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez‐Arévalo, C. M., Olmo‐García, L., Fernández‐Sánchez, J. F., &amp; Carrasco‐Pancorbo, A. (2020). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in edible oils: An overview on sample preparation, determination strategies, and relative abundance of prevalent compounds. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 19(6), 3528–3573.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwarzer, G., Carpenter, J. R., &amp; Rücker, G. (2015). Meta‐analysis with R (Vol., 4784). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekar, M., &amp; Praveenkumar, T. (2023). Critical review on the formations and exposure of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in the conventional hydrocarbon‐based fuels: Prevention and control strategies. Chemosphere, 350, 141005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Semlali, A., Khannous, S., Chafik, A., Talbi, M., &amp; Budzinsk, H. (2012). Origin and distribution of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in lagoon ecosystems of Morocco. The Open Environmental Pollution &amp; Toxicology Journal, 3(1), 37–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seyadain Ardebili, S. M., &amp; Hoseini, E. (2019). Identification and simultaneous analysis of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in Barbary bread samples using gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS). Food Science and Technology, 16(93), 11–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, L., &amp; Agarwal, T. (2022). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) exposure through cooking environment and assessment strategies for human health implications. Human and Ecological Risk Assessment: An International Journal, 28(5–6), 635–663.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, L., Varshney, J. G., &amp; Agarwal, T. (2016). Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons’ formation and occurrence in processed food. Food Chemistry, 199, 768–781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soceanu, A., Dobrinas, S., &amp; Popescu, V. (2022). Levels of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in toasted bread. Polycyclic Aromatic Compounds, 42(9), 6112–6123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soclo, H., Garrigues, P., &amp; Ewald, M. (2000). Origin of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in coastal marine sediments: Case studies in Cotonou (Benin) and Aquitaine (France) areas. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 40(5), 387–396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stogiannidis, E., &amp; Laane, R. (2014). Source characterization of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons by using their molecular indices: An overview of possibilities. Reviews of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, 234, 49–133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, L.‐P., Li, X., Zhao, M.‐Z., Shi, J.‐R., Ji, S.‐Q., Jiang, W.‐Y., Liang, Q.‐J., Lei, Y.‐H., Zhou, Y.‐Y., &amp; Cheng, R. (2021). Chrysene, a four‐ring polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon, induces hepatotoxicity in mice by activation of the aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AhR). Chemosphere, 276, 130108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tehrani, G. M., Hashim, R., Sulaiman, A. H., Sany, S. T., Salleh, A., Jazani, R. K., Savari, A., &amp; Barandoust, R. F. (2013). Distribution of total petroleum hydrocarbons and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in Musa Bay sediments (Northwest of the Persian Gulf). Environment Protection Engineering, 39(1), 115–128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Treviño‐Reséndez, J., &amp; Nacheva, P. M. (2021). Removal of naphthalene and phenanthrene in synthetic solutions by electro‐oxidation coupled with membrane bioreactor. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 28(35), 48543–48555.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udowelle, N. A., Igweze, Z. N., Asomugha, R. N., &amp; Orisakwe, O. E. (2017). Health risk assessment and dietary exposure of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs), lead and cadmium from bread consumed in Nigeria. Roczniki Państwowego Zakładu Higieny, 68(3), 269–280.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veyrand, B., Sirot, V., Durand, S., Pollono, C., Marchand, P., Dervilly‐Pinel, G., Tard, A., Leblanc, J.‐C., &amp; Le Bizec, B. (2013). Human dietary exposure to polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons: Results of the second French Total Diet Study. Environment International, 54, 11–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). (2009). Codex Alimentarius: Food hygiene, basic texts (4th ed.). WHO.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, A., Lea‐Langton, A., &amp; Bartle, K. (2022). The formation of PAH compounds from the combustion of biofuels. In Advances in energy and combustion: Safety and sustainability (pp. 105–124). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yazdanpanah, H., Kobarfard, F., Tsitsimpikou, C., Eslamizad, S., Alehashem, M., &amp; Tsatsakis, A. (2022). Health risk assessment of process‐related contaminants in bread. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 170, 113482.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yebra‐Pimentel, I., Fernández‐González, R., Martínez‐Carballo, E., &amp; Simal‐Gándara, J. (2015). A critical review about the health risk assessment of PAHs and their metabolites in foods. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 55(10), 1383–1405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, B., Xie, X., Ma, L. Q., Kan, H., &amp; Zhou, Q. (2014). Source, distribution, and health risk assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in urban street dust from Tianjin, China. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 21, 2817–2825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yunker, M. B., Macdonald, R. W., Vingarzan, R., Mitchell, R. H., Goyette, D., &amp; Sylvestre, S. (2002). PAHs in the Fraser River basin: A critical appraisal of PAH ratios as indicators of PAH source and composition. Organic Geochemistry, 33(4), 489–515.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zelinkova, Z., &amp; Wenzl, T. (2015). The occurrence of 16 EPA PAHs in food–a review. Polycyclic Aromatic Compounds, 35(2–4), 248–284.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>