<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39246535</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2636-0780</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>44</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food science of animal resources</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Sci Anim Resour</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Psychrotrophic Bacteria Threatening the Safety of Animal-Derived Foods: Characteristics, Contamination, and Control Strategies.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1011</StartPage><EndPage>1027</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1011-1027</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5851/kosfa.2024.e70</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Animal-derived foods, such as meat and dairy products, are prone to spoilage by psychrotrophic bacteria due to their high-water activity and nutritional value. These bacteria can grow at refrigerated temperatures, posing significant concerns for food safety and quality. Psychrotrophic bacteria, including <i>Pseudomonas</i>, <i>Listeria</i>, and <i>Yersinia</i>, not only spoil food but can also produce heat-resistant enzymes and toxins, posing health risks. This review examines the characteristics and species composition of psychrotrophic bacteria in animal-derived foods, their impact on food spoilage and safety, and contamination patterns in various products. It explores several nonthermal techniques to combat bacterial contamination as alternatives to conventional thermal methods, which can affect food quality. This review highlights the importance of developing nonthermal technologies to control psychrotrophic bacteria that threaten the cold storage of animal-derived foods. By adopting these technologies, the food industry can better ensure the safety and quality of animal-derived foods for consumers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Korean Society for Food Science of Animal Resources.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oh</LastName><ForeName>Hyemin</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8073-7242</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Risk Analysis Research Center, Sookmyung Women's University, Seoul 04310, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food and Nutrition, Sookmyung Women's University, Seoul 04310, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Jeeyeon</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5885-6835</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food &amp; Nutrition, Dong-eui University, Busan 47340, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Food Sci Anim Resour</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101742126</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2636-0772</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">animal-derived foods</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nonthermal techniques</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prevalence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychrotrophic bacteria</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39246535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11377203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5851/kosfa.2024.e70</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">kosfa-44-5-1011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aganovic K, Smetana S, Grauwet T, Toepfl S, Mathys A, Van Loey A, Heinz V. Pilot scale thermal and alternative pasteurization of tomato and watermelon juice: An energy comparison and life cycle assessment. J Clean Prod. 2017;141:514–525. doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2016.09.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2016.09.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed HA, Tahoun ABMB, Elez RMMA, Abd El-Hamid MI, Abd Ellatif SS. Prevalence of Yersinia enterocolitica in milk and dairy products and the effects of storage temperatures on survival and virulence gene expression. Int Dairy J. 2019;94:16–21. doi: 10.1016/j.idairyj.2019.02.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.idairyj.2019.02.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akrami-Mohajeri F, Derakhshan Z, Ferrante M, Hamidiyan N, Soleymani M, Oliveri Conti G, Dehghani Tafti R. The prevalence and antimicrobial resistance of Listeria spp in raw milk and traditional dairy products delivered in Yazd, central Iran. Food Chem Toxicol. 2018;114:141–144. doi: 10.1016/j.fct.2018.02.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2018.02.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29448094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali S, Aslam R, Arshad MI, Mahmood MS, Nawaz Z. Meat borne bacterial pathogens. In: Abbas RZ, Khan A, editors. In Section B: Bacterial diseases. Veterinary pathobiology and public health. (ed) Unique Scientific; Faisalabad, Pakistan: 2021. pp. 216–228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47278/book.vpph/2021.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Mariri A, Younes A, Ramadan L. Prevalence of Listeria spp. in raw milk in Syria. Bulg J Vet Med. 2013;16:112–122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arslan S, Eyi A, Özdemir F. Spoilage potentials and antimicrobial resistance of Pseudomonas spp. isolated from cheeses. J Dairy Sci. 2011;94:5851–5856. doi: 10.3168/jds.2011-4676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2011-4676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22118075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aziz SAAA, Mahmoud R, Mohamed MBED. Control of biofilm-producing Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated from dairy farm using virokill silver nano-based disinfectant as an alternative approach. Sci Rep. 2022;12:9452. doi: 10.1038/s41598-022-13619-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-13619-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9177611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35676412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barakat RK, Harris LJ. Growth of Listeria monocytogenes and Yersinia enterocolitica on cooked modified-atmosphere-packaged poultry in the presence and absence of a naturally occurring microbiota. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1999;65:342–345. doi: 10.1128/AEM.65.1.342-345.1999.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.65.1.342-345.1999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC91029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9872806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barash JR, Hsia JK, Arnon SS. Presence of soil-dwelling clostridia in commercial powdered infant formulas. J Pedatr. 2010;156:402–408. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2009.09.072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2009.09.072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20004414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barba FJ, Koubaa M, do Prado-Silva L, Orlien V, Sant’ana AS. Mild processing applied to the inactivation of the main foodborne bacterial pathogens: A review. Trends Food Sci Technol. 2017;66:20–35. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2017.05.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2017.05.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beltran MS, Gerba CP, Fett AP, Luchansky JB, Chaidez C. Prevalence and characterization of Listeria monocytogenes, Salmonella and Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli isolated from small Mexican retail markets of queso fresco. Int J Environ Health Res. 2015;25:140–148. doi: 10.1080/09603123.2014.915016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09603123.2014.915016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24809389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benie CKD, Nathalie G, Adjéhi D, Solange A, Fernique konan K, Desire K, Bourahima B, Marcellin DK, Mireille D. Prevalence and antibiotic resistance of Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated from bovine meat, fresh fish and smoked fish. Arch Clin Microbiol. 2017;8:40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beumer RR, Te Giffel MC, Cox LJ, Rombouts FM, Abee T. Effect of exogenous proline, betaine, and carnitine on growth of Listeria monocytogenes in a minimal medium. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1994;60:1359–1363. doi: 10.1128/aem.60.4.1359-1363.1994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.60.4.1359-1363.1994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC201482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8017923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolumar T, Orlien V, Sikes A, Aganovic K, Bak KH, Guyon C, Stubler AS, de Lamballerie M, Hertel C, Bruggemann DA. High-pressure processing of meat: Molecular impacts and industrial applications. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf. 2020;20:332–368. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12670.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33443800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brett MM, McLauchlin J, Harris A, O’Brien S, Black N, Forsyth RJ, Roberts D, Bolton FJ. A case of infant botulism with a possible link to infant formula milk powder: Evidence for the presence of more than one strain of Clostridium botulinum in clinical specimens and food. J Med Microbiol. 2005;54:769–776. doi: 10.1099/jmm.0.46000-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.46000-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16014431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruckner S, Albrecht A, Petersen B, Kreyenschmidt J. Characterization and comparison of spoilage processes in fresh pork and poultry. J Food Qual. 2012;35:372–382. doi: 10.1111/j.1745-4557.2012.00456.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4557.2012.00456.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budisa N, Schulze-Makuch D. Supercritical carbon dioxide and its potential as a life-sustaining solvent in a planetary environment. Life. 2014;4:331–340. doi: 10.3390/life4030331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/life4030331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4206850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25370376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calvo-Arrieta K, Matamoros-Montoya K, Arias-Echandi ML, Huete-Soto A, Redondo-Solano M. Presence of Listeria monocytogenes in ready-to-eat meat products sold at retail stores in Costa Rica and analysis of contributing factors. J Food Prot. 2021;84:1729–1740. doi: 10.4315/JFP-21-020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/JFP-21-020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34047780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carminati D, Bonvini B, Rossetti L, Zago M, Tidona F, Giraffa G. Investigation on the presence of blue pigment-producing Pseudomonas strains along a production line of fresh mozzarella cheese. Food Control. 2019;100:321–328. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.02.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.02.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casanueva A, Tuffin M, Cary C, Cowan DA. Molecular adaptations to psychrophily: The impact of ‘omic’ technologies. Trends Microbiol. 2010;18:374–381. doi: 10.1016/j.tim.2010.05.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2010.05.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20646925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavicchioli R. On the concept of a psychrophile. ISME J. 2016;10:793–795. doi: 10.1038/ismej.2015.160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ismej.2015.160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4796924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26371407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavicchioli R, Siddiqui KS, Andrews D, Sowers KR. Low-temperature extremophiles and their applications. Curr Opin Biotechnol. 2002;13:253–261. doi: 10.1016/S0958-1669(02)00317-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0958-1669(02)00317-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12180102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celik Y, Drori R, Pertaya-Braun N, Altan A, Barton T, Bar-Dolev M, Groisman A, Davies PL, Braslavsky I. Microfluidic experiments reveal that antifreeze proteins bound to ice crystals suffice to prevent their growth. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2013;110:1309–1314. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1213603110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1213603110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3557080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23300286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan YC, Wiedmann M. Physiology and genetics of Listeria monocytogenes survival and growth at cold temperatures. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2008;49:237–253. doi: 10.1080/10408390701856272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408390701856272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19093268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chattopadhyay MK. Mechanism of bacterial adaptation to low temperature. J Biosci. 2006;31:157–165. doi: 10.1007/BF02705244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF02705244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16595884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chattopadhyay MK, Jagannadham MV. A branched chain fatty acid promotes cold adaptation in bacteria. J Biosci. 2003;28:363–364. doi: 10.1007/BF02705110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF02705110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12799482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Kawamura S, Koseki S. Effect of d-tryptophan on the psychrotrophic growth of Listeria monocytogenes and its application in milk. Food Control. 2020;110:107048. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.107048.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.107048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper IR. A review of current methods using bacteriophages in live animals, food and animal products intended for human consumption. J Microbiol Methods. 2016;130:38–47. doi: 10.1016/j.mimet.2016.07.027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2016.07.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27485708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costanzo N, Ceniti C, Santoro A, Clausi MT, Casalinuovo F. Foodborne pathogen assessment in raw milk cheeses. Int J Food Sci. 2020;2020:3616713. doi: 10.1155/2020/3616713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2020/3616713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6996669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32064273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Amico S, Claverie P, Collins T, Georlette D, Gratia E, Hoyoux A, Meuwis MA, Feller G, Gerday C. Molecular basis of cold adaptation. Phil Trans R Soc Lond B. 2002;357:917–925. doi: 10.1098/rstb.2002.1105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rstb.2002.1105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1692995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12171655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Maayer P, Anderson D, Cary C, Cowan DA. Some like it cold: Understanding the survival strategies of psychrophiles. EMBO Rep. 2014;15:508–517. doi: 10.1002/embr.201338170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/embr.201338170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4210084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24671034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhama K, Rajagunalan S, Chakraborty S, Verma AK, Kumar A, Tiwari R, Kapoor S. Food-borne pathogens of animal origin-diagnosis, prevention, control and their zoonotic significance: A review. Pak J Biol Sci. 2013;16:1076–1085. doi: 10.3923/pjbs.2013.1076.1085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3923/pjbs.2013.1076.1085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24506006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elbehiry A, Marzouk E, Aldubaib M, Moussa I, Abalkhail A, Ibrahem M, Hamada M, Sindi W, Alzaben F, Almuzaini AM, Algammal AM, Rawway M. Pseudomonas species prevalence, protein analysis, and antibiotic resistance: An evolving public health challenge. AMB Express. 2022;12:53. doi: 10.1186/s13568-022-01390-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13568-022-01390-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9086069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35532863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ercolini D, Russo F, Nasi A, Ferranti P, Villani F. Mesophilic and psychrotrophic bacteria from meat and their spoilage potential in vitro and in beef. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2009;75:1990–2001. doi: 10.1128/AEM.02762-08.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02762-08</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2663181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19201980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esnault E, Labbé A, Houdayer C, Denis M. Proceedings of the 10th International Conference on the Epidemiology and Control of Biological. Chemical and Physical Hazards in Pigs and Pork; Edinburgh, UK: 2013. Yersinia enterocolitica prevalence, on fresh pork, poultry and beef meat at retail level, in France; pp. 72–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31274/safepork-180809-914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farber JN, Harris LJ, Parish ME, Beuchat LR, Suslow TV, Gorney JR, Garrett EH, Busta FF. Microbiological safety of controlled and modified atmosphere packaging of fresh and fresh-cut produce. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf. 2003;2:142–160. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-4337.2003.tb00032.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2003.tb00032.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feligini M, Brambati E, Panelli S, Ghitti M, Sacchi R, Capelli E, Bonacina C. One-year investigation of Clostridium spp. occurrence in raw milk and curd of Grana Padano cheese by the automated ribosomal intergenic spacer analysis. Food Control. 2014;42:71–77. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2014.02.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2014.02.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrentino G, Balzan S, Spilimbergo S. Supercritical carbon dioxide processing of dry cured ham spiked with Listeria monocytogenes: Inactivation kinetics, color, and sensory evaluations. Food Bioprocess Technol. 2013;6:1164–1174. doi: 10.1007/s11947-012-0819-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11947-012-0819-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenda T, Grabczak M, Kwiatek K, Bober A. Prevalence of C. botulinum and C. perfringens spores in food products available on Polish market. J Vet Res. 2017;61:287–291. doi: 10.1515/jvetres-2017-0038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/jvetres-2017-0038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5894417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29978085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenda T, Grabczak M, Sieradzki Z, Kwiatek K, Pohorecka K, Skubida M, Bober A. Clostridium botulinum spores in Polish honey samples. J Vet Sci. 2018;19:635–642. doi: 10.4142/jvs.2018.19.5.635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4142/jvs.2018.19.5.635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6167343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29929360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerrero SN, Ferrario M, Schenk M, Carrillo MG. Hurdle technology using ultrasound for food preservation. In: Bermudez-Aguirre D, editor. In Ultrasound: Advances for food processing and preservation. (ed) Academic Press; Cambridge, MA, USA: 2017. pp. 39–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-804581-7.00003-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagve TA. Effects of unsaturated fatty acids on cell membrane functions. Scand J Clin Lab Invest. 1988;48:381–388. doi: 10.1080/00365518809085746.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00365518809085746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3060983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan N, Anesio AM, Rafiq M, Holtvoeth J, Bull I, Haleem A, Shah AA, Hasan F. Temperature driven membrane lipid adaptation in glacial psychrophilic bacteria. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:824. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2020.00824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7240044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32477293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hordofa DL. Review on yersiniosis and its public health importance. Int J Vet Sci Anim Husb. 2021;6:37–41. doi: 10.22271/veterinary.2021.v6.i6a.449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22271/veterinary.2021.v6.i6a.449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Guo Y, Hou Q, Huang M, Zhou X. Dynamic changes of the bacterial communities in roast chicken stored under normal and modified atmosphere packaging. J Food Sci. 2020;85:1231–1239. doi: 10.1111/1750-3841.15038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.15038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32180226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson JA, Mott SJ, Penney N. Growth of Listeria monocytogenes, Aeromonas hydrophila, and Yersinia enterocolitica on vacuum and saturated carbon dioxide controlled atmosphere-packaged sliced roast beef. J Food Prot. 1994;57:204–208. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X-57.3.204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X-57.3.204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31113062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hurtado A, Dolors Guàrdia M, Picouet P, Jofré A, Bañón S, María Ros J. Shelf-life extension of multi-vegetables smoothies by high-pressure processing compared with thermal treatment. Part I: Microbial and enzyme inhibition, antioxidant status, and physical stability. J Food Process Preserv. 2019;43:e14139. doi: 10.1111/jfpp.14139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.14139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismaiel AAR, Ali AES, Enan G. Incidence of Listeria in Egyptian meat and dairy samples. Food Sci Biotechnol. 2014;23:179–185. doi: 10.1007/s10068-014-0024-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10068-014-0024-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Issimov A, Baibatyrov T, Tayeva A, Kenenbay S, Abzhanova S, Shambulova G, Kuzembayeva G, Kozhakhiyeva M, Brel-Kisseleva I, Safronova O, Bauzhanova L, Yeszhanova G, Bukarbayev K, Katasheva A, Uzal FA. Prevalence of Clostridium perfringens and detection of its toxins in meat products in selected areas of West Kazakhstan. Agriculture. 2022;12:1357. doi: 10.3390/agriculture12091357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agriculture12091357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadhav HB, Annapure US, Deshmukh RR. Non-thermal technologies for food processing. Front Nutr. 2021;8:657090. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2021.657090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2021.657090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8217760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34169087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamali H, Paydar M, Radmehr B, Ismail S. Prevalence, characterization, and antimicrobial resistance of Yersinia species and Yersinia enterocolitica isolated from raw milk in farm bulk tanks. J Dairy Sci. 2015;98:798–803. doi: 10.3168/jds.2014-8853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2014-8853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25497824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jauhar S, Ismail-Fitry MR, Chong GH, Nor-Khaizura MAR, Ibadullah WZW. Different pressures, low temperature, and short-duration supercritical carbon dioxide treatments: Microbiological, physicochemical, microstructural, and sensorial attributes of chill-stored chicken. Appl Sci. 2020;10:6629. doi: 10.3390/app10196629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app10196629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Júnior JCR, de Oliveira AM, de G Silva F, Tamanini R, de Oliveira ALM, Beloti V. The main spoilage-related psychrotrophic bacteria in refrigerated raw milk. J Dairy Sci. 2018;101:75–83. doi: 10.3168/jds.2017-13069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29102138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kader AA. Biochemical and physiological basis for effects of controlled and modified atmospheres on fruits and vegetables. Food Technol. 1986;40:99–104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kahraman T, Ozmen G, Ozinan B, Omer Goksoy E. Prevalence of Salmonella spp. and Listeria monocytogenes in different cheese types produced in Turkey. Br Food J. 2010;112:1230–1236. doi: 10.1108/00070701011088214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/00070701011088214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanekar PP, Kanekar SP. Psychrophilic, psychrotrophic, and psychrotolerant microorganisms. In Diversity and biotechnology of extremophilic microorganisms from India. In: Kanekar PP, Kanekar SP, editors. Microorganisms for sustainability. (ed) Springer; Singapore: 2022. pp. 215–249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-981-19-1573-4_7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang JH, Bai J, Min SC. Inactivation of indigenous microorganisms and Salmonella in Korean rice cakes by in-package cold plasma treatment. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:3360. doi: 10.3390/ijerph18073360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18073360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8036629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33805200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim B, Yun H, Jung S, Jung Y, Jung H, Choe W, Jo C. Effect of atmospheric pressure plasma on inactivation of pathogens inoculated onto bacon using two different gas compositions. Food Microbiol. 2011;28:9–13. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2010.07.022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2010.07.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21056769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koddy JK, Miao W, Hatab S, Tang L, Xu H, Nyaisaba BM, Chen M, Deng S. Understanding the role of atmospheric cold plasma (ACP) in maintaining the quality of hairtail (Trichiurus lepturus) Food Chem. 2021;343:128418. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.128418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.128418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33160769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramarenko T, Roasto M, Meremae K, Kuningas M, Poltsama P, Elias T. Listeria monocytogenes prevalence and serotype diversity in various foods. Food Control. 2013;30:24–29. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.06.047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.06.047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambertz ST, Nilsson C, Bradenmark A, Sylven S, Johansson A, Jansson LM, Lindblad M. Prevalence and level of Listeria monocytogenes in ready-to-eat foods in Sweden 2010. Int J Food Microbiol. 2012;160:24–31. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2012.09.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2012.09.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23141642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lante A, Tinello F, Lomolino G. Effect of UV light on microbial proteases: From enzyme inactivation to antioxidant mitigation. Innov Food Sci Emerg Technol. 2013;17:130–134. doi: 10.1016/j.ifset.2012.11.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ifset.2012.11.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SY, Sagong HG, Ryu S, Kang DH. Effect of continuous ohmic heating to inactivate Escherichia coli O157:H7, Salmonella Typhimurium and Listeria monocytogenes in orange juice and tomato juice. J Appl Microbiol. 2012;112:723–731. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2672.2012.05247.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2012.05247.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22292508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee Y, Yoon Y. Principles and applications of non-thermal technologies for meat decontamination. Food Sci Anim Resour. 2024;44:19–38. doi: 10.5851/kosfa.2023.e72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5851/kosfa.2023.e72</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10789560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38229860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H, Wang P, Lan R, Luo L, Cao X, Wang Y, Wang Y, Li H, Zhang L, Ji S, Ye C. Risk factors and level of Listeria monocytogenes contamination of raw pork in retail markets in China. Front Microbiol. 2018;9:1090. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2018.01090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5986919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29896170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao X, Liu D, Xiang Q, Ahn J, Chen S, Ye X, Ding T. Inactivation mechanisms of non-thermal plasma on microbes: A review. Food Control. 2017;75:83–91. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.12.021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.12.021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacDonald E, Heier BT, Nygård K, Stalheim T, Cudjoe KS, Skjerdal T, Wester AL, Lindstedt BA, Stavnes TL, Vold L. Yersinia enterocolitica outbreak associated with ready-to-eat salad mix, Norway, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012;18:1496–1499. doi: 10.3201/eid1809.120087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1809.120087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3437701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22932318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahato A, Mahato S, Dhakal K, Dhakal A. Investigating the diversity of spoilage and food intoxicating bacteria from chicken meat of Biratnagar, Nepal. J Bacteriol Mycol. 2020;7:1141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maikanov B, Mustafina R, Auteleyeva L, Wiśniewski J, Anusz K, Grenda T, Kwiatek K, Goldsztejn M, Grabczak M. Clostridium botulinum and Clostridium perfringens occurrence in Kazakh honey samples. Toxins. 2019;11:472. doi: 10.3390/toxins11080472.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins11080472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6723067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31412583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makroo HA, Rastogi NK, Srivastava B. Ohmic heating assisted inactivation of enzymes and microorganisms in foods: A review. Trends Food Sci Technol. 2020;97:451–465. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2020.01.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2020.01.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mancini ME, Beverelli M, Donatiello A, Didonna A, Dattoli L, Faleo S, Occhiochiuso G, Galante D, Rondinone V, Del Sambro L, Bianco A, Miccolupo A, Goffredo E. Isolation and characterization of Yersinia enterocolitica from foods in Apulia and Basilicata regions (Italy) by conventional and modern methods. PLOS ONE. 2022;17:e0268706. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0268706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0268706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9278756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35830422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manzocco L, Quarta B, Dri A. Polyphenoloxidase inactivation by light exposure in model systems and apple derivatives. Innov Food Sci Emerg Technol. 2009;10:506–511. doi: 10.1016/j.ifset.2009.02.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ifset.2009.02.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchand S, De Block J, De Jonghe V, Coorevits A, Heyndrickx M, Herman L. Biofilm formation in milk production and processing environments: Influence on milk quality and safety. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf. 2012;11:133–147. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-4337.2011.00183.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2011.00183.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matle I, Mbatha KR, Lentsoane O, Magwedere K, Morey L, Madoroba E. Occurrence, serotypes, and characteristics of Listeria monocytogenes in meat and meat products in South Africa between 2014 and 2016. J Food Saf. 2019;39:e12629. doi: 10.1111/jfs.12629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfs.12629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLeod A, Liland KH, Haugen JE, Sørheim O, Myhrer KS, Holck AL. Chicken fillets subjected to UV-C and pulsed UV light: Reduction of pathogenic and spoilage bacteria, and changes in sensory quality. J Food Saf. 2018;38:e12421. doi: 10.1111/jfs.12421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfs.12421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6084340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30122794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meza-Bone GA, Meza Bone JS, Cedeño Á, Martín I, Martín A, Maddela NR, Córdoba JJ. Prevalence of Listeria monocytogenes in RTE meat products of Quevedo (Ecuador) Foods. 2023;12:2956. doi: 10.3390/foods12152956.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12152956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10418838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37569226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitelut A, Popa M, Geicu M, Niculita P, Vatuiu D, Vatuiu I, Gilea B, Balint R, Cramariuc R. Ohmic treatment for microbial inhibition in meat and meat products. Rom Biotechnol Lett. 2011;16:149–152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadi TN, Shen C, Li Y, Zayda MG, Sato J, Masuda Y, Honjoh K, Miyamoto T. Characterization of Clostridium perfringens bacteriophages and their application in chicken meat and milk. Int J Food Microbiol. 2022;361:109446. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2021.109446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2021.109446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34742146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Momtaz H, Rahimian MD, Dehkordi FS. Identification and characterization of Yersinia enterocolitica isolated from raw chicken meat based on molecular and biological techniques. J Appl Poult Res. 2013;22:137–145. doi: 10.3382/japr.2012-00549.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/japr.2012-00549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montanari R. Cold chain tracking: A managerial perspective. Trends Food Sci Technol. 2008;19:425–431. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2008.03.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2008.03.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monteiro MLG, Mársico ET, Mutz YS, Castro VS, de Barros Pinto Moreira RV, Álvares TS, Conte-Junior CA. Combined effect of oxygen-scavenger packaging and UV-C radiation on shelf life of refrigerated tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) fillets. Sci Rep. 2020;10:4243. doi: 10.1038/s41598-020-61293-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-61293-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7060221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32144402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moye ZD, Woolston J, Sulakvelidze A. Bacteriophage applications for food production and processing. Viruses. 2018;10:205. doi: 10.3390/v10040205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v10040205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5923499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29671810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyer CL, Eric Collins R, Morita RY. Reference module in life sciences. Elsevier; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2017. Psychrophiles and psychrotrophs.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-809633-8.02282-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munsch-Alatossava P, Gursoy O, Alatossava T. Potential of nitrogen gas (N2) to control psychrotrophs and mesophiles in raw milk. Microbiol Res. 2010;165:122–132. doi: 10.1016/j.micres.2009.02.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2009.02.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19398315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myers K, Montoya D, Cannon J, Dickson J, Sebranek J. The effect of high hydrostatic pressure, sodium nitrite and salt concentration on the growth of Listeria monocytogenes on RTE ham and turkey. Meat Sci. 2013;93:263–268. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.09.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.09.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23046896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najjar MB, Chikindas M, Montville TJ. Changes in Listeria monocytogenes membrane fluidity in response to temperature stress. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2007;73:6429–6435. doi: 10.1128/AEM.00980-07.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00980-07</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2075051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17704268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha N, Hsiao HI, Vlajic J, Yang MF, Lin HTV. Time-temperature abuse in the food cold chain: Review of issues, challenges, and recommendations. Food Control. 2018;89:12–21. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.01.027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.01.027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odeyemi OA, Alegbeleye OO, Strateva M, Stratev D. Understanding spoilage microbial community and spoilage mechanisms in foods of animal origin. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf. 2020;19:311–331. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33325162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oswaldi V, Dzierzon J, Thieme S, Merle R, Meemken D. Slaughter pigs as carrier of Listeria monocytogenes in Germany. J Consum Prot Food Saf. 2021;16:109–115. doi: 10.1007/s00003-021-01322-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00003-021-01322-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palau R, Bloomfield SJ, Jenkins C, Greig DR, Jorgensen F, Mather AE. Yersinia enterocolitica biovar 1A: An underappreciated potential pathogen in the food chain. Int J Food Microbiol. 2024;412:110554. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38176093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park S, Park E, Yoon Y. Comparison of nonthermal decontamination methods to improve the safety for raw beef consumption. J Food Prot. 2022;85:664–670. doi: 10.4315/JFP-21-243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/JFP-21-243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34935939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires RPS, Guimarães JT, Barros CP, Balthazar CF, Chincha AIA, Freitas MQ, Duarte MCKH, Silva PHF, Pimentel TC, Abud YKD, Sant’Anna C, Sant’Ana AS, Silva MC, Nascimento JS, Cruz AG. Ohmic heating increases inactivation and morphological changes of Salmonella sp. and the formation of bioactive compounds in infant formula. Food Microbiol. 2021;97:103737. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2021.103737.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2021.103737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33653516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimi E, Ameri M, Momtaz H. Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance of Listeria species isolated from milk and dairy products in Iran. Food Control. 2010;21:1448–1452. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2010.03.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2010.03.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reichel J, Kehrenberg C, Krischek C. UV-C irradiation of rolled fillets of ham inoculated with Yersinia enterocolitica and Brochothrix thermosphacta. Foods. 2020;9:552. doi: 10.3390/foods9050552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods9050552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7278610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaloo M, Motalebi A, Mashak Z, Anvar A. Prevalence, antimicrobial resistance, and molecular description of Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated from meat and meat products. J Food Qual. 2022;2022:9899338. doi: 10.1155/2022/9899338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/9899338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richa R, Shahi NC, Singh A, Lohani UC, Omre PK, Kumar A, Bhattacharya TK. Ohmic heating technology and its application in meaty food: A review. Adv Res. 2017;10:1–10. doi: 10.9734/AIR/2017/33799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/AIR/2017/33799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossi LPR, Almeida RCC, Lopes LS, Figueiredo ACL, Ramos MPP, Almeida PF. Occurrence of Listeria spp. in Brazilian fresh sausage and control of Listeria monocytogenes using bacteriophage P100. Food Control. 2011;22:954–958. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2010.12.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2010.12.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouger A, Moriceau N, Prévost H, Remenant B, Zagorec M. Diversity of bacterial communities in French chicken cuts stored under modified atmosphere packaging. Food Microbiol. 2018;70:7–16. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2017.08.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2017.08.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29173642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz-Roldán L, Rojo-Bezares B, de Toro M, López M, Toledano P, Lozano C, Chichón G, Alvarez-Erviti L, Torres C, Sáenz Y. Antimicrobial resistance and virulence of Pseudomonas spp. among healthy animals: Concern about exolysin ExlA detection. Sci Rep. 2020;10:11667. doi: 10.1038/s41598-020-68575-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-68575-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7363818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32669597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha S, Majumder R, Rout P, Hossain S. Unveiling the significance of psychrotrophic bacteria in milk and milk product spoilage: A review. Microbe. 2024;2:100034. doi: 10.1016/j.microb.2024.100034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microb.2024.100034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samaržija D, Zamberlin Š, Pogačić T. Psychrotrophic bacteria and their negative effects on milk and dairy products quality. Mljekarstvo. 2012;62:77–95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saxena J, Makroo HA, Srivastava B. Optimization of time-electric field combination for PPO inactivation in sugarcane juice by ohmic heating and its shelf life assessment. LWT-Food Sci Technol. 2016;71:329–338. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2016.04.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2016.04.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaltout FA, Osman IM, Kamel EA, Abd-Alla AK. Isolation of Clostridium perfringens from meat samples obtained from the University Students’ Hostel. EC Nutr. 2017;9:142–150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheir SH, Ibrahim HM, Hassan MA, Shawky NA. Incidence of psychotropic bacteria in frozen chicken meat products with special reference to Pseudomonas species. Benha Vet Med J. 2020;39:165–168. doi: 10.21608/bvmj.2020.37744.1238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21608/bvmj.2020.37744.1238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sillankorva SM, Oliveira H, Azeredo J. Bacteriophages and their role in food safety. Int J Microbiol. 2012;2012:863945. doi: 10.1155/2012/863945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2012/863945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3536431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23316235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva FVM, Evelyn Pasteurization of food and beverages by high pressure processing (HPP) at room temperature: Inactivation of Staphylococcus aureus, Escherichia coli, Listeria monocytogenes, Salmonella, and other microbial pathogens. Appl Sci. 2023;13:1193. doi: 10.3390/app13021193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app13021193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sofy AR, Sharaf AEMA, Al Karim AG, Hmed AA, Moharam KM. Prevalence of the harmful gram-negative bacteria in ready-to-eat foods in Egypt. Food Public Health. 2017;7:59–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soltan Dallal MM, Doyle MP, Rezadehbashi M, Dabiri H, Sanaei M, Modarresi S, Bakhtiari R, Sharifiy K, Taremi M, Zali MR, Sharifi-Yazdi MK. Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance profiles of Salmonella serotypes, Campylobacter and Yersinia spp. isolated from retail chicken and beef, Tehran, Iran. Food Control. 2010;21:388–392. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2009.06.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2009.06.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stratakos AC, Inguglia ES, Linton M, Tollerton J, Murphy L, Corcionivoschi N, Koidis A, Tiwari BK. Effect of high pressure processing on the safety, shelf life and quality of raw milk. Innov Food Sci Emerg Technol. 2019;52:325–333. doi: 10.1016/j.ifset.2019.01.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ifset.2019.01.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H, Kawamura S, Himoto J, Itoh K, Wada T, Kimura T. Effects of ohmic heating on microbial counts and denaturation of proteins in milk. Food Sci Technol Res. 2008;14:117–123. doi: 10.3136/fstr.14.117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3136/fstr.14.117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapia MS, Alzamora SM, Chirife J. Effects of water activity (aw) on microbial stability as a hurdle in food preservation. In: Barbosa-Cánovas GV, Fontana AJ Jr, Schmidt SJ, Labuza TP, editors. In: Water activity in foods: Fundamentals and applications. 2nd ed. Wiley; Hoboken, NJ, USA: 2020. pp. 323–355. (ed)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/9781118765982.ch14</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tatini SR, Kauppi KL. ANALYSIS | Microbiological analyses. In: Roginski H, editor. In Encyclopedia of dairy sciences. Elsevier; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2002. pp. 74–79. (ed)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B0-12-227235-8/00021-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomat D, Casabonne C, Aquili V, Balagué C, Quiberoni A. Evaluation of a novel cocktail of six lytic bacteriophages against Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli in broth, milk and meat. Food Microbiol. 2018;76:434–442. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2018.07.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2018.07.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30166171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres-Vitela MR, Mendoza-Bernardo M, Castro-Rosas J, Gomez-Aldapa CA, Garay-Martinez LE, Navarro-Hidalgo V, Villarruel-López A. Incidence of Salmonella, Listeria monocytogenes, Escherichia coli O157:H7, and Staphylococcal Enterotoxin in two types of Mexican fresh cheeses. J Food Prot. 2012;75:79–84. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-11-258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-11-258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22221358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turchi B, Pero S, Torracca B, Fratini F, Mancini S, Galiero A, Pedonese F, Nuvoloni R, Cerri D. Occurrence of Clostridium spp. in ewe’s milk: Enumeration and identification of isolates. Dairy Sci Technol. 2016;96:693–701. doi: 10.1007/s13594-016-0298-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13594-016-0298-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulbin-Figlewicz N, Jarmoluk A. Antimicrobial activity of low-pressure plasma treatment against selected foodborne bacteria and meat microbiota. Ann Microbiol. 2014;65:1537–1546. doi: 10.1007/s13213-014-0992-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13213-014-0992-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4529465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26273240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vianna PCB, Walter EHM, Dias MEF, Faria JAF, Netto FM, Gigante ML. Effect of addition of CO2 to raw milk on quality of UHT-treated milk. J Dairy Sci. 2012;95:4256–4262. doi: 10.3168/jds.2012-5387.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2012-5387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22818439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visuthiwan S, Assatarakul K. Kinetic modeling of microbial degradation and antioxidant reduction in lychee juice subjected to UV radiation and shelf life during cold storage. Food Control. 2021;123:107770. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vitas AI, Garcia-Jalon VAI. Occurrence of Listeria monocytogenes in fresh and processed foods in Navarra (Spain) Int J Food Micobiol. 2004;90:349–356. doi: 10.1016/S0168-1605(03)00314-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(03)00314-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14751690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang GY, Li M, Ma F, Wang H, Xu X, Zhou G. Physicochemical properties of Pseudomonas fragi isolates response to modified atmosphere packaging. FEMS Microbiol Lett. 2017;364:fnx106. doi: 10.1093/femsle/fnx106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/femsle/fnx106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28531290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang LH, Wang MS, Zeng XA, Liu ZW. Temperature-mediated variations in cellular membrane fatty acid composition of Staphylococcus aureus in resistance to pulsed electric fields. Biochim Biophys Acta Biomembr. 2016;1858:1791–1800. doi: 10.1016/j.bbamem.2016.05.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2016.05.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27155566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei CI, Balaban MO, Fernando SY, Peplow AJ. Bacterial effect of high pressure CO2 treatment on foods spiked with Listeria or Salmonella. J Food Prot. 1991;54:189–193. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X-54.3.189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X-54.3.189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31051644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei Q, Wang X, Sun DW, Pu H. Rapid detection and control of psychrotrophic microorganisms in cold storage foods: A review. Trends Food Sci Technol. 2019;86:453–464. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2019.02.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2019.02.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickramasinghe NN, Ravensdale J, Coorey R, Chandry SP, Dykes GA. The predominance of psychrotrophic pseudomonads on aerobically stored chilled red meat. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf. 2019;18:1622–1635. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33336914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiśniewski P, Chajęcka-Wierzchowska W, Zadernowska A. Impact of high-pressure processing (HPP) on Listeria monocytogenes: An overview of challenges and responses. Foods. 2024;13:14. doi: 10.3390/foods13010014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13010014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10778341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38201041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X, Yang L, Wu Y, Li H, Shao B. Spread of multidrug-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa in animal-derived foods in Beijing, China. Int J Food Microbiol. 2023;403:110296. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110296.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37392610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon Y, Lee H, Lee S, Kim S, Choi KH. Membrane fluidity-related adaptive response mechanisms of foodborne bacterial pathogens under environmental stresses. Food Res Int. 2015;72:25–36. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2015.03.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2015.03.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan L, Sadiq FA, Burmølle M, Wang N, He G. Insights into psychrotrophic bacteria in raw milk: A review. J Food Prot. 2019;82:1148–1159. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-19-032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-19-032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31225978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan L, Sadiq FA, Liu T, Flint S, Chen J, Yang H, Gu J, Zhang G, He G. Psychrotrophic bacterial populations in Chinese raw dairy milk. LWT-Food Sci Technol. 2017;84:409–418. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2017.05.023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2017.05.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeisel SH, Mar MH, Howe JC, Holden JM. Concentrations of choline-containing compounds and betaine in common foods. J Nutr. 2003;133:1302–1307. doi: 10.1093/jn/133.5.1302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jn/133.5.1302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12730414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Zhang J, Zhang Y, Hu H, Luo S, Zhang L, Zhou H, Li P. Effects of in-package atmospheric cold plasma treatment on the qualitative, metabolic and microbial stability of fresh-cut pears. J Sci Food Agric. 2021;101:4473–4480. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.11085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.11085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33432579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>