<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39245914</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Photodynamic inactivation of edible photosensitizers for fresh food preservation: Comprehensive mechanism of action and enhancement strategies.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70006</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70006</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70006</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Foodborne harmful bacteria not only cause waste of fresh food, but also pose a major threat to human health. Among many new sterilization and preservation technologies, photodynamic inactivation (PDI) has the advantages of low-cost, broad-spectrum, energy-saving, nontoxic, and high efficiency. In particular, PDI based on edible photosensitizers (PSs) has a broader application prospect due to edible, accessible, and renewable features, it also can maximize the retention of the nutritional characteristics and sensory quality of the food. Therefore, it is meaningful and necessary to review edible PSs and edible PSs-mediated PDI, which can help to arouse interest and concern and promote the further development of edible PSs-mediated PDI in the future field of nonthermally sterilized food preservation. Herein, the classification and modification of edible PSs, PS-mediated in vivo and PS-mediated in vitro mechanism of PDI, strengthening strategy to improve PDI efficiency by the structure change synergistic and multitechnical means, as well as the application in fresh food preservation were reviewed systematically. Finally, the deficiency and possible future perspectives of edible PSs-mediated PDI were articulated. This review aimed to provide new perspective for the future food preservation and microbial control.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Haoran</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Hefei University of Technology, Hefei, Anhui Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ni</LastName><ForeName>Yongsheng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Hefei University of Technology, Hefei, Anhui Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Bio-Process of Ministry of Education, School of Food &amp; Biological Engineering, Hefei University of Technology, Hefei, Anhui Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Jinsong</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Hefei University of Technology, Hefei, Anhui Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yumeng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Hefei University of Technology, Hefei, Anhui Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Baocai</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0706-8863</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Hefei University of Technology, Hefei, Anhui Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Bio-Process of Ministry of Education, School of Food &amp; Biological Engineering, Hefei University of Technology, Hefei, Anhui Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>Grant/AwardNumber</GrantID><Agency>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>JZ2023HGTA0174</GrantID><Agency>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Grant/AwardNumber</GrantID><Agency>Ningxia Hui Autonomous Region Key Research and Development Program</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2023BCFO1041</GrantID><Agency>Ningxia Hui Autonomous Region Key Research and Development Program</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Grant/AwardNumber</GrantID><Agency>Hefei University of Technology Talent Introduction Initiation Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>13020-03712022048</GrantID><Agency>Hefei University of Technology Talent Introduction Initiation Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D017319">Photosensitizing Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017319" MajorTopicYN="Y">Photosensitizing Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005519" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Preservation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001419" MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000528" MajorTopicYN="N">radiation effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enhancement mechanism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food preservation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">photodynamic inactivation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39245914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Afrasiabi, S., &amp; Chiniforush, N. (2023). Antibacterial potential of riboflavin mediated blue diode laser photodynamic inactivation against Enterococcus faecalis: A laboratory investigation. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 41, 103291. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2023.103291</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alves, F., Gomes Guimarães, G., Mayumi Inada, N., Pratavieira, S., Salvador Bagnato, V., &amp; Kurachi, C. (2021). Strategies to improve the antimicrobial efficacy of photodynamic, sonodynamic, and sonophotodynamic therapies. Lasers in Surgery and Medicine, 53(8), 1113–1121. https://doi.org/10.1002/lsm.23383</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakun, P., Czarczynska‐Goslinska, B., Goslinski, T., &amp; Lijewski, S. (2021). In vitro and in vivo biological activities of azulene derivatives with potential applications in medicine. Medicinal Chemistry Research, 30(4), 834–846. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00044‐021‐02701‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhavya, M. L., Shewale, S. R., Rajoriya, D., &amp; Hebbar, H. U. (2021). Impact of blue LED illumination and natural photosensitizer on bacterial pathogens, enzyme activity and quality attributes of fresh‐cut pineapple slices. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 14(2), 362–372. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐021‐02581‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chai, Z., Zhang, F., Liu, B., Chen, X., &amp; Meng, X. (2021). Antibacterial mechanism and preservation effect of curcumin‐based photodynamic extends the shelf life of fresh‐cut pears. LWT, 142, 110941. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.110941</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, H.‐M., Zhou, Q., Huang, L.‐J., Lin, J., Liu, J.‐F., Huang, Z.‐Y., Zhang, R.‐L., Wang, J.‐J., Zhao, Y., Wu, Y.‐N., Yang, X.‐F., &amp; Wu, W.‐L. (2023). Curcumin‐mediated photodynamic treatment extends the shelf life of salmon (Salmo salar) sashimi during chilled storage: Comparisons of preservation effects with five natural preservatives. Food Research International, 113325. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2023.113325</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, L., Dong, Q., Shi, Q., Du, Y., Zeng, Q., Zhao, Y., &amp; Wang, J. J. (2021). Novel 2,3‐dialdehyde cellulose‐based films with photodynamic inactivation potency by incorporating the β‐cyclodextrin/curcumin inclusion complex. Biomacromolecules, 22(7), 2790–2801. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.biomac.1c00165</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, L., Li, X., Chen, J., Lin, R., Mai, Y., Lin, Y., Wang, G., Chen, Z., Zhang, W., Wang, J., Yuan, C., Jiang, L., Xu, P., &amp; Huang, M. (2024). Formulation with zinc acetate enhances curcumin's inherent and photodynamic antimicrobial effects for food preservation. Food Control, 157, 110200. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110200</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, L., Zhao, Y., Wu, W., Zeng, Q., &amp; Wang, J. J. (2023). New trends in the development of photodynamic inactivation against planktonic microorganisms and their biofilms in food system. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 1541–4337, 13215. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.13215</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, K., Wang, H., Sun, S., Wu, M., Shen, H., Chen, K., Zhang, Z., Li, S., &amp; Lin, H. (2023). Specific chemiluminescence imaging and enhanced photodynamic therapy of bacterial infections by hemin‐modified carbon dots. Small, 19(31), 2207868. https://doi.org/10.1002/smll.202207868</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choe, E., &amp; Min, D. B. (2006). Chemistry and reactions of reactive oxygen species in foods. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 46(1), 1–22. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408390500455474</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corrêa, T. Q., Blanco, K. C., Garcia, É. B., Perez, S. M. L., Chianfrone, D. J., Morais, V. S., &amp; Bagnato, V. S. (2020). Effects of ultraviolet light and curcumin‐mediated photodynamic inactivation on microbiological food safety: A study in meat and fruit. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 30, 101678. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2020.101678</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa, T. P. C., Rodrigues, E. M., Dias, L. P., Pupin, B., Ferreira, P. C., &amp; Rangel, D. E. N. (2021). Different wavelengths of visible light influence the conidial production and tolerance to ultra‐violet radiation of the plant pathogens Colletotrichum acutatum and Fusarium fujikuroi. European Journal of Plant Pathology, 159(1), 105–115. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10658‐020‐02146‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crocker, L. B., Lee, J. H., Mital, S., Mills, G. C., Schack, S., Bistrović‐Popov, A., Franck, C. O., Mela, I., Kaminski, C. F., Christie, G., &amp; Fruk, L. (2022). Tuning riboflavin derivatives for photodynamic inactivation of pathogens. Scientific Reports, 12(1), 6580. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐022‐10394‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crugeira, P. J. L., Almeida, H. H. S., Teixeira, L. G., &amp; Barreiro, M. F. (2023). Photodynamic inactivation of Staphylococcus aureus by ecological antibacterial solutions associating LED (ʎ 450 ± 10 nm) with curcumin and olive leaf extracts. Journal of Photochemistry and Photobiology B: Biology, 238, 112626. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2022.112626</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Moraes Pinto, L. A., Frizzo, A., Benito, C. E., Da Silva Júnior, R. C., Alvares, L. K., Pinto, A. N., Tellini, C., De Oliveira Monteschio, J., &amp; Fernandes, J. I. M. (2023). Effect of an antimicrobial photoinactivation approach based on a blend of curcumin and Origanum essential oils on the quality attributes of chilled chicken breast. LWT, 176, 114484. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114484</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Petrillo, A., Orrù, G., Fais, A., &amp; Fantini, M. C. (2022). Quercetin and its derivates as antiviral potentials: A comprehensive review. Phytotherapy Research, 36(1), 266–278. https://doi.org/10.1002/ptr.7309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dibona‐Villanueva, L., &amp; Fuentealba, D. (2022). Protoporphyrin IX–chitosan oligosaccharide conjugate with potent antifungal photodynamic activity. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70(30), 9276–9282. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.2c01644</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong, L., Qin, J., Tai, L., Mou, K., Liao, X., Chen, F., &amp; Hu, X. (2022). Inactivation of Bacillus subtilis by curcumin‐mediated photodynamic technology through inducing oxidative stress response. Microorganisms, 10(4), 802. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms10040802</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, T., Li, X., Wang, S., Su, Z., Sun, H., Wang, J., &amp; Zhang, W. (2023). Phytochemicals‐based edible coating for photodynamic preservation of fresh‐cut apples. Food Research International, 163, 112293. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2022.112293</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, Y., Sun, J., Tian, Z., Cheng, Y., &amp; Long, C. (2023). Effect of blue light treatments on Geotrichum citri‐aurantii and the corresponding physiological mechanisms of citrus. Food Control, 145, 109468. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109468</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, J., Yang, X., Wang, T., Du, T., Zhuo, J., Zhang, P., Zhang, L., Sun, H., Han, Y., Xia, Y., Wang, J., &amp; Zhang, W. (2023). Reassembled one‐dimensional VB2 submicrorods with enhanced photosensitivity and H2O2 supply for efficient antibacterial therapy. ACS Sustainable Chemistry &amp; Engineering, 11(35), 13081–13095. https://doi.org/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c03176</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, Y., Xu, H., Sun, Y., Xia, R., Hou, Z., Li, Y., Wang, Y., Pan, S., Li, L., Zhao, C., Ren, H., &amp; Xin, G. (2023). Effect of light on quality of preharvest and postharvest edible mushrooms and its action mechanism: A review. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 139, 104119. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2023.104119</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flórez, M., Guerra‐Rodríguez, E., Cazón, P., &amp; Vázquez, M. (2022). Chitosan for food packaging: Recent advances in active and intelligent films. Food Hydrocolloids, 124, 107328. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2021.107328</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foresto, E., Gilardi, P., Ibarra, L. E., &amp; Cogno, I. S. (2021). Light‐activated green drugs: How we can use them in photodynamic therapy and mass‐produce them with biotechnological tools. Phytomedicine Plus, 1(3), 100044. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phyplu.2021.100044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, J., Srichamnong, W., Chathiran, W., &amp; Matthews, K. R. (2023). Influences of photosensitizer curcumin on microbialsurvival and physicochemical properties of chicken during storage. Poultry Science, 102(2), 102417. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psj.2022.102417</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosh, T., Nakano, K., Mulchandani, N., &amp; Katiyar, V. (2021). Curcumin loaded iron functionalized biopolymeric nanofibre reinforced edible nanocoatings for improved shelf life of cut pineapples. Food Packaging and Shelf Life, 28, 100658. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fpsl.2021.100658</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greco, G., Ulfo, L., Turrini, E., Marconi, A., Costantini, P. E., Marforio, T. D., Mattioli, E. J., Di Giosia, M., Danielli, A., Fimognari, C., &amp; Calvaresi, M. (2023). Light‐enhanced cytotoxicity of doxorubicin by photoactivation. Cells, 12(3), 392. https://doi.org/10.3390/cells12030392</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu, W., Liu, D., &amp; Sun, J. (2022). Co‐crystallization of curcumin for improved photodynamic inactivation of Vibrio parahaemolyticus and its application for the preservation of cooked clams. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 378, 109816. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2022.109816</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gusmão, L. A., Machado, A. E. H., &amp; Perussi, J. R. (2022). Improved Hypericin solubility via β‐cyclodextrin complexation: Photochemical and theoretical study for PDT applications. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 40, 103073. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2022.103073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamblin, M. R., &amp; Abrahamse, H. (2019). Tetracyclines: Light‐activated antibiotics? Future Medicinal Chemistry, 11(18), 2427–2445. https://doi.org/10.4155/fmc‐2018‐0513</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He, Y., Yuan, J., Khan, I. M., Zhang, L., Ma, P., &amp; Wang, Z. (2023). Research progress of aptasensor technology in the detection of foodborne pathogens. Food Control, 153, 109891. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.109891</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herculano, L. S., Kalschne, D. L., Canan, C., Reis, T. S., Marcon, C. T., Benetti, V. P., Malacarne, L. C., Blanco, K., &amp; Bagnato, V. S. (2022). Antimicrobial curcumin‐mediated photodynamic inactivation of bacteria in natural bovine casing. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 40, 103173. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2022.103173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, J., Chen, B., Zeng, Q.‐H., Liu, Y., Liu, H., Zhao, Y., &amp; Wang, J. J. (2021). Application of the curcumin‐mediated photodynamic inactivation for preserving the storage quality of salmon contaminated with L. monocytogenes. Food Chemistry, 359, 129974. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.129974</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, L., Yong, K. W. L., Fernando, W. C., Carpinelli De Jesus, M., De Voss, J. J., Sultanbawa, Y., &amp; Fletcher, M. T. (2021). The inactivation by curcumin‐mediated photosensitization of Botrytis cinerea spores isolated from strawberry fruits. Toxins, 13(3), 196. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins13030196</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyun, J.‐E., Moon, S.‐K., &amp; Lee, S.‐Y. (2022). Application of blue light‐emitting diode in combination with antimicrobials or photosensitizers to inactivate Escherichia coli O157:H7 on fresh‐cut apples and cherry tomatoes. Food Control, 131, 108453. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108453</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam, M. T., Sain, M., Stark, C., Fefer, M., Liu, J., Hoare, T., Ckurshumova, W., &amp; Rosa, C. (2023). Overview of methods and considerations for the photodynamic inactivation of microorganisms for agricultural applications. Photochemical &amp; Photobiological Sciences, 22(11), 2675–2686. https://doi.org/10.1007/s43630‐023‐00466‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, M.‐ J., Da Jeong, M., Zheng, Q., &amp; Yuk, H.‐ G. (2021). Antimicrobial activityof 405 nm light‐emitting diode (LED) in the presence of riboflavin againstListeria monocytogenes on the surface of smoked salmon. Food Science andBiotechnology, 30(4), 609–618. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10068‐021‐00895‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, D.‐K., Shin, M., Kim, H.‐S., &amp; Kang, D.‐H. (2022). Inactivation efficacy of combination treatment of blue light‐emitting diodes (LEDs) and riboflavin to control E. coli O157:H7 and S. Typhimurium in apple juice. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 78, 103014. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2022.103014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai, D., Zhou, A., Tan, B. K., Tang, Y., Sarah Hamzah, S., Zhang, Z., Lin, S., &amp; Hu, J. (2021). Preparation and photodynamic bactericidal effects of curcumin‐β‐cyclodextrin complex. Food Chemistry, 361, 130117. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai, D., Zhou, F., Zhou, A., Hamzah, S. S., Zhang, Y., Hu, J., &amp; Lin, S. (2022). Comprehensive properties of photodynamic antibacterial film based on κ‐Carrageenan and curcumin‐β‐cyclodextrin complex. Carbohydrate Polymers, 282, 119112. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2022.119112</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lan, X., Liu, Y., Wang, L., Wang, H., Hu, Z., Dong, H., Yu, Z., &amp; Yuan, Y. (2023). A review of curcumin in food preservation: Delivery system and photosensitization. Food Chemistry, 424, 136464. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.136464</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le, T. D., Phasupan, P., &amp; Nguyen, L. T. (2020). Antimicrobial photodynamic efficacy of selected natural photosensitizers against food pathogens: Impacts and interrelationship of process parameters. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 32, 102024. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2020.102024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le, T. D., Phasupan, P., Visaruthaphong, K., Chouwatat, P., Thi Thu, V., &amp; Nguyen, L. T. (2021). Development of an antimicrobial photodynamic poly(3‐hydroxybutyrate‐co‐3‐hydroxyvalerate) packaging film for food preservation. Food Packaging and Shelf Life, 30, 100749. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fpsl.2021.100749</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, I.‐H., Kim, S.‐H., &amp; Kang, D.‐H. (2023). Quercetin mediated antimicrobial photodynamic treatment using blue light on Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Listeria monocytogenes. Current Research in Food Science, 6, 100428. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.crfs.2022.100428</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lena, A., Marino, M., Manzano, M., Comuzzi, C., &amp; Maifreni, M. (2024). An overview of the application of blue light‐emitting diodes as a non‐thermic green technology for microbial inactivation in the food sector. Food Engineering Reviews, 16(1), 59–84. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12393‐023‐09355‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Tan, L., Chen, B., Huang, J., Zeng, Q., Liu, H., Zhao, Y., &amp; Wang, J. J. (2021). Antibacterial potency of riboflavin‐mediated photodynamic inactivation against Salmonella and its influences on tuna quality. LWT, 146, 111462. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111462</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, P., Wen, F., Yan, H., Xu, Q., &amp; Su, W. (2023). Antimicrobial activity of Emodin in combination with visible light against Escherichia coli and Staphylococcus aureus: Applications for food safety technology. LWT, 181, 114750. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114750</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, R., Fang, Q., Li, P., Zhang, C., Yuan, Y., &amp; Zhuang, H. (2021). Effects of emulsifier type and post‐treatment on stability, curcumin protection, and sterilization ability of nanoemulsions. Foods, 10(1), 149. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10010149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Tan, L., Liu, F., Li, M., Zeng, S., Gui, Y., Zhao, Y., &amp; Wang, J. J. (2023). Effects of soluble Antarctic krill protein‐curcumin complex combined with photodynamic inactivation on the storage quality of shrimp. Food Chemistry, 403, 134388. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.134388</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., &amp; Wu, M. X. (2021). Reversal of polymicrobial biofilm tolerance to ciprofloxacin by blue light plus carvacrol. Microorganisms, 9(10), 2074. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms9102074</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Xu, Y., Liao, Q., Xie, M., Tao, H., &amp; Wang, H. (2021). Synergistic effect of hypocrellin B and curcumin on photodynamic inactivation of Staphylococcus aureus. Microbial Biotechnology, 14(2), 692–707. https://doi.org/10.1111/1751‐7915.13734</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao, X., Zhuang, X., Liang, C., Li, J., Flaumenhaft, R., Yuan, C., &amp; Huang, M. (2022). Flavonoids as protein disulfide isomerase inhibitors: Key molecular and structural features for the interaction. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70(14), 4475–4483. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.1c07994</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, Y., Lai, D., Wang, D., Zhou, F., Tan, B. K., Zhang, Z., Hu, J., &amp; Lin, S. (2021). Application of curcumin‐mediated antibacterial photodynamic technology for preservation of fresh Tremella Fuciformis. LWT, 147, 111657. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111657</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, D., Gu, W., Wang, L., &amp; Sun, J. (2023). Photodynamic inactivation and its application in food preservation. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 63(14), 2042–2056. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2021.1969892</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, D., Jiang, L., Chen, J., Chen, Z., Yuan, C., Lin, D., &amp; Huang, M. (2023). Monomer and oligomer transition of zinc phthalocyanine is key for photobleaching in photodynamic therapy. Molecules, 28(12), 4639. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules28124639</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, F., Li, Z., Cao, B., Wu, J., Wang, Y., Xue, Y., Xu, J., Xue, C., &amp; Tang, Q. J. (2016). The effect of a novel photodynamic activation method mediated by curcumin on oyster shelf life and quality. Food Research International, 87, 204–210. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2016.07.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Wang, S., Wu, J., Qi, G., Chen, G., Li, H., &amp; Wang, H. (2023). Photodynamic inactivation mediated by curcumin solid lipid nanoparticles on bacteria and its application for fresh carrot juice. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 17(5), 1294–1308. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐023‐03199‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Weng, L., Lin, Y., Lin, D., Xie, L., &amp; Zhong, T. (2023). Carvacrol/β‐cyclodextrin inclusion complex as a fumigant to control decay caused by Penicillium digitatum on Shatangju mandarin slices. Heliyon, 9(8), e18804. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e18804</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, H., Zheng, S., Fang, J., &amp; Zhu, J. (2023). Photodynamic inactivation of spoilers Pseudomonas lundensis and Brochothrix thermosphacta by food‐grade curcumin and its application on ground beef. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 87, 103410. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2023.103410</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, M., Wang, S., Wang, T., Hu, S., Bhayana, B., Ishii, M., Kong, Y., Cai, Y., Dai, T., Cui, W., &amp; Wu, M. X. (2021). Bacteria‐specific phototoxic reactions triggered by blue light and phytochemical carvacrol. Science translational medicine, 13(575), eaba3571. https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.aba3571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, K., Zhe, T., Li, F., Zhang, Y., Yu, M., Li, R., &amp; Wang, L. (2022). Sustainable films containing AIE‐active berberine‐based nanoparticles: A promising antibacterial food packaging. Food Hydrocolloids, 123, 107147. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2021.107147</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, T., Chen, Y., Zhi, X., &amp; Du, B. (2021). Cellulose laurate films containing curcumin as photoinduced antibacterial agent for meat preservation. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 193, 1986–1995. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.11.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meerovich, G. A., Akhlyustina, E. V., Romanishkin, I. D., Makarova, E. A., Tiganova, I. G., Zhukhovitsky, V. G., Kholina, E. G., Kovalenko, I. B., Romanova, Y. M., Loschenov, V. B., &amp; Strakhovskaya, M. G. (2023). Photodynamic inactivation of bacteria: Why it is not enough to excite a photosensitizer. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 44, 103853. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2023.103853</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montaseri, H., Kruger, C. A., &amp; Abrahamse, H. (2021). Inorganic nanoparticles applied for active targeted photodynamic therapy of breast cancer. Pharmaceutics, 13(3), 296. https://doi.org/10.3390/pharmaceutics13030296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morales‐de‐Echegaray, A. V., Maltais, T. R., Lin, L., Younis, W., Kadasala, N. R., Seleem, M. N., &amp; Wei, A. (2018). Rapid uptake and photodynamic inactivation of Staphylococci by Ga(III)‐protoporphyrin IX. ACS Infectious Diseases, 4(11), 1564–1573. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsinfecdis.8b00125</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukubesa, N., Nguenha, R., Hong, H. T., Seididamyeh, M., Netzel, M. E., &amp; Sultanbawa, Y. (2022). Curcumin‐based photosensitization, a green treatment in inactivating Aspergillus flavus spores in peanuts. Foods, 11(3), 354. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11030354</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najari, E., Zamani, S., Sheikh Arabi, M., &amp; Ardebili, A. (2024). Antimicrobial photodynamic effect of the photosensitizer riboflavin, alone and in combination with colistin, against pandrug‐resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa clinical isolates. Journal of Infection and Chemotherapy, 30(9), 892–898. S1341321×24000758. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jiac.2024.03.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni, Y., Sun, J., &amp; Wang, J. (2021). Enhanced antimicrobial activity of konjac glucomannan nanocomposite films for food packaging. Carbohydrate Polymers, 267, 118215. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2021.118215</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega‐Zambrano, D., Fuentes‐López, D., &amp; Mercado‐Uribe, H. (2022). Photoinactivation of Escherichia coli using five photosensitizers and the same number of photons. Journal of Innovative Optical Health Sciences, 15(06), 2240010. https://doi.org/10.1142/S1793545822400107</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pei, J., Zhu, S., Liu, Y., Song, Y., Xue, F., Xiong, X., &amp; Li, C. (2022). Photodynamic effect of riboflavin on chitosan coatings and the application in pork preservation. Molecules, 27(4), 1355. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27041355</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phasupan, P., Le, T. D., &amp; Nguyen, L. T. (2021). Assessing the photodynamic efficacy of different photosensitizer‐light treatments against foodborne bacteria based on the number of absorbed photons. Journal of Photochemistry and Photobiology B: Biology, 221, 112249. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2021.112249</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polat, E., &amp; Kang, K. (2021). Natural photosensitizers in antimicrobial photodynamic therapy. Biomedicines, 9(6), 584. https://doi.org/10.3390/biomedicines9060584</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafeeq, S., Shiroodi, S., Schwarz, M. H., Nitin, N., &amp; Ovissipour, R. (2020). Inactivation of Aeromonas hydrophila and Vibrio parahaemolyticus by curcumin‐mediated photosensitization and nanobubble‐ultrasonication approaches. Foods, 9(9), 1306.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramanauskaite, E., Moraschini, V., Machiulskiene, V., &amp; Sculean, A. (2021). Clinical efficacy of single and multiple applications of antimicrobial photodynamic therapy in periodontal maintenance: A systematic review and network meta‐analysis. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 36, 102435. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2021.102435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodoni, L. M., &amp; Lemoine, M. L. (2023). Shedding light about the use of photosensitizers and photodynamic treatments during postharvest of fruit and vegetables: Current and future state. Postharvest Biology and Technology, 204, 112463. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.postharvbio.2023.112463</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo, M., Rigano, F., Arigò, A., Dugo, P., &amp; Mondello, L. (2021). Coumarins, psoralens and polymethoxyflavones in cold‐pressed citrus essential oils: A review. Journal of Essential Oil Research, 33(3), 221–239. https://doi.org/10.1080/10412905.2020.1857855</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha, P., &amp; Rafe, M. R. (2023). Cyclodextrin: A prospective nanocarrier for the delivery of antibacterial agents against bacteria that are resistant to antibiotics. Heliyon, 9(9), e19287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e19287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saraiva, B. B., Campanholi, K. D. S. S., Machado, R. R. B., Nakamura, C. V., Silva, A. A., Caetano, W., &amp; Pozza, M. S. D. S. (2024). Reducing Pseudomonas fluorescens in milk through photodynamic inactivation using riboflavin and curcumin with 450 nm blue light‐emitting diode. International Dairy Journal, 148, 105787. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.idairyj.2023.105787</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saraiva, B. B., Rodrigues, B. M., Da Silva, R. C. Junior, Scapim, M. R. D. S., Lancheros, C. A. C., Nakamura, C. V., Caetano, W., Pereira, P. C. D. S., De Santana, E. H. W., &amp; Pozza, M. S. D. S. (2021). Photodynamic inactivation of Pseudomonas fluorescens in Minas Frescal cheese using curcumin as a photosensitizer. LWT, 151, 112143. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saraiva, B. B., Sestito, J. M. B., Bezerra, R. A. D., De Oliveira, G. L. M., Da Silva Júnior, R. C., Machado, R. R. B., Nakamura, C. V., Alfieri, A. A., &amp; Pozza, M. S. D. S. (2024). Reduction of Staphylococcus aureus in vitro and in milk by photodynamic inactivation using riboflavin and curcumin as photosensitizers: Cell damage and effects on product quality. Journal of Photochemistry and Photobiology A: Chemistry, 446, 115120. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jphotochem.2023.115120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarker, M. A. R., &amp; Ahn, Y.‐H. (2022). Green phytoextracts as natural photosensitizers in LED‐based photodynamic disinfection of multidrug‐resistant bacteria in wastewater effluent. Chemosphere, 297, 134157. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.134157</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarwar, S., Netzel, G., Netzel, M. E., Mereddy, R., Phan, A. D. T., Hong, H. T., Cozzolino, D., &amp; Sultanbawa, Y. (2021). Impact of curcumin‐mediated photosensitization on fungal growth, physicochemical properties and nutritional composition in australian grown strawberry. Food Analytical Methods, 14(3), 465–472. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12161‐020‐01896‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sela, A., Shkuri, N., Tish, N., Vinokur, Y., Rodov, V., &amp; Poverenov, E. (2023). Carboxymethyl chitosan‐quercetin conjugate: A sustainable one‐step synthesis and use for food preservation. Carbohydrate Polymers, 316, 121084. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2023.121084</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, G., Raturi, K., Dang, S., Gupta, S., &amp; Gabrani, R. (2014). Combinatorial antimicrobial effect of curcumin with selected phytochemicals on Staphylococcus epider. Journal of Asian Natural Products Research, 16(5), 535–541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng, L., Li, X., &amp; Wang, L. (2022). Photodynamic inactivation in food systems: A review of its application, mechanisms, and future perspective. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 124, 167–181. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2022.04.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, Y., Lin, S., Chen, W., Jiang, L., Gu, Q., &amp; Li, D. (2022). Dual‐stage blue‐light‐guided membrane and DNA‐targeted photodynamic inactivation using octyl gallate for ultraefficient eradication of planktonic bacteria and sessile biofilms. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70(24), 7547–7565. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.2c01667</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, Y., Zhu, C., Li, D., Shi, Z., Gu, Q., Chen, Y., Wang, J., Ettelaie, R., &amp; Chen, J.‐S. (2021). New horizons in microbiological food safety: Ultraefficient photodynamic inactivation based on a gallic acid derivative and UV‐A light and its application with electrospun cyclodextrin nanofibers. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 69(49), 14961–14974. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.1c04827</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva E Carvalho, I., Pratavieira, S., Salvador Bagnato, V., &amp; Alves, F. (2023). Sonophotodynamic inactivation of Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilm mediated by curcumin. Biofouling, 39(6), 606–616. https://doi.org/10.1080/08927014.2023.2241385</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su, L., Huang, J., Li, H., Pan, Y., Zhu, B., Zhao, Y., &amp; Liu, H. (2021). Chitosan‐riboflavin composite film based on photodynamic inactivation technology for antibacterial food packaging. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 172, 231–240. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.01.056</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su, Z., Guo, B., Xu, H., Yuan, Z., Liu, H., Guo, T., Deng, Z., Zhang, Y., Yin, D., Liu, C., Chen, J., &amp; Rao, Y. (2024). Synthetic biology‐based construction of unnatural perylenequinones with improved photodynamic anticancer activities. Angewandte Chemie International Edition, 63(11), e202317726. https://doi.org/10.1002/anie.202317726</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, L., Zhao, Y., Li, Y., Peng, Z., He, T., Liu, Y., Zeng, Q., &amp; Wang, J. J. (2022). Potent eradication of mixed‐species biofilms using photodynamic inactivation coupled with slightly alkaline electrolyzed water. LWT, 155, 112958. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112958</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thi Nguyen, T., Pham, B.‐T. T., Nhien Le, H., Bach, L. G., &amp; Thuc, C. N. H. (2022). Comparative characterization and release study of edible films of chitosan and natural extracts. Food Packaging and Shelf Life, 32, 100830. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fpsl.2022.100830</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vetchapitak, T., Rana, M. S., Sasaki, S., Taniguchi, T., Sugiyama, S., Soejima, J., Luangtongkum, T., Yamaguchi, Y., &amp; Misawa, N. (2021). A new disinfectant technique for Campylobacter jejuni and spoilage bacteria on chicken skin using a high‐pressure pulsed jet spray apparatus. Food Control, 125, 107989. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.107989</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker, P., Taylor, A. J., Hitchcock, A., Webb, J. P., Green, J., Weinstein, J., &amp; Kelly, D. J. (2022). Exploiting violet‐blue light to kill Campylobacter jejuni: Analysis of global responses, modeling of transcription factor activities, and identification of protein targets. mSystems, 7(4), e00454–22. https://doi.org/10.1128/msystems.00454‐22</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, D., Zhou, F., Lai, D., Zhang, Y., Hu, J., &amp; Lin, S. (2021). Curcumin‐mediated sono/photodynamic treatment preserved the quality of shrimp surimi and influenced its microbial community changes during refrigerated storage. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 78, 105715. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2021.105715</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, F., Wang, R., Pan, Y., Du, M., Zhao, Y., &amp; Liu, H. (2022). Gelatin/chitosan films incorporated with curcumin based on photodynamic inactivation technology for antibacterial food packaging. Polymers, 14(8), 1600. https://doi.org/10.3390/polym14081600</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Q., Shi, Q., Li, Y., Lu, S., &amp; Xie, X. (2022). Visible light‐regulated cationic polymer coupled with photodynamic inactivation as an effective tool for pathogen and biofilm elimination. Journal of Nanobiotechnology, 20(1), 492. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12951‐022‐01702‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Li, J., Geng, S., Wang, X., Cui, Z., Ma, W., Yuan, M., Liu, C., &amp; Ji, Y. (2021). Aloe‐emodin‐mediated antimicrobial photodynamic therapy against multidrug‐resistant Acinetobacter baumannii: An in vivo study. Photodiagnosis and Photodynamic Therapy, 34, 102311. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdpdt.2021.102311</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Liao, J., Lyu, Y., Guo, Q., Zhu, Z., Wu, X., Yu, J., Wang, Q., &amp; Zhu, W. (2023). An AIE photosensitizer with simultaneous type I and type II ROS generation: Efficient bacterial elimination and hypoxic tumor ablation. Advanced Functional Materials, 33(33), 2301692. https://doi.org/10.1002/adfm.202301692</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Zhao, Y., Wu, R., Gao, J., Chen, M., Cui, Y., Hao, J., Han, J., &amp; Matthews, K. (2023). Photodynamic inactivation of curcumin combined with ascorbic acid against Penicillium italicum in vitro and on fresh‐cut orange. LWT, 182, 114900. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114900</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z., Jia, Y., Li, W., &amp; Zhang, M. (2021). Antimicrobial photodynamic inactivation with curcumin against Staphylococcus saprophyticus, in vitro and on fresh dough sheet. LWT, 147, 111567. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111567</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen, F., Li, P., Yan, H., &amp; Su, W. (2023). Turmeric carbon quantum dots enhanced chitosan nanocomposite films based on photodynamic inactivation technology for antibacterial food packaging. Carbohydrate Polymers, 311, 120784. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2023.120784</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, C., Zhang, F., Song, L., Chen, X., &amp; Meng, X. (2021). Photosensitization effect of curcumin for controlling plant pathogen Botrytis cinerea in postharvest apple. Food Control, 123, 107683. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107683</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, J., Li, J., Xu, F., Zhou, A., Zeng, S., Zheng, B., &amp; Lin, S. (2023). Effective preservation of chilled pork using photodynamic antibacterial film based on curcumin‐β‐cyclodextrin complex. Polymers, 15(4), 1023. https://doi.org/10.3390/polym15041023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, Y., Lu, Y., Qian, S., Zhang, J., Gao, Y., Wei, Y., &amp; Heng, W. (2023). An efficient cocrystallization strategy for separation of dihydromyricetin from vine tea and enhanced its antibacterial activity for food preserving application. Food Chemistry, 426, 136525. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.136525</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, J., Yao, H., Li, Y., Liao, Q., Wan, X., Liu, L., Ma, X., Tao, H., Wang, H.‐L., &amp; Xu, Y. (2023). Antimicrobial photodynamic inactivation as an alternative approach to inhibit the growth of Cronobacter sakazakii by fine‐tuning the activity of CpxRA two‐component system. Frontiers in Microbiology, 13, 1063425. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.1063425</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, H., Lin, X., Duan, N., Khan, I. M., Wang, Z., &amp; Wu, S. (2023). Gelatin‒carboxymethyl cellulose film incorporated porphyrin metal–organic frameworks with photodynamic/photothermal synergistic antibacterial activities for pork packaging application. Journal of Food Engineering, 353, 111556. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2023.111556</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, Y., Tan, L., Li, H., Chen, B., Huang, J., Zhao, Y., Wang, J., &amp; Ou, J. (2021). Photodynamic inactivation of planktonic Staphylococcus aureus by sodium magnesium chlorophyllin and its effect on the storage quality of lettuce. Photochemical &amp; Photobiological Sciences, 20(6), 761–771. https://doi.org/10.1007/s43630‐021‐00057‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye, Z., Hua, D., Rao, Y., Bai, S., Seeberger, P. H., Yin, J., &amp; Hu, J. (2020). Targeted photodynamic therapy with a novel photosensitizer cercosporin encapsulated multifunctional copolymer. Colloids and Surfaces A: Physicochemical and Engineering Aspects, 585, 124136. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.colsurfa.2019.124136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, J., Zhang, F., Zhang, J., Han, Q., Song, L., &amp; Meng, X. (2021). Effect of photodynamic treatments on quality and antioxidant properties of fresh‐cut potatoes. Food Chemistry, 362, 130224. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130224</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan, Y., Liu, Q., Huang, Y., Qi, M., Yan, H., Li, W., &amp; Zhuang, H. (2022). Antibacterial efficacy and mechanisms of curcumin‐based photodynamic treatment against staphylococcus aureus and its application in juices. Molecules, 27(20), 7136. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27207136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, Q.‐H., Hu, D., Wang, R.‐H., Li, Y., Wen, Y., Xiao, H., Zhao, Y., &amp; Wang, J. J. (2023). Curcumin‐loaded emulsions stabilized by the succinylated Antarctic krill proteins: Establishment of photodynamic inactivation to preserve salmon. LWT, 178, 114613. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114613</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zha, Z., Tang, R., Wang, C., Li, Y., Liu, S., Wang, L., &amp; Wang, K. (2022). Riboflavin inhibits browning of fresh‐cut apples by repressing phenolic metabolism and enhancing antioxidant system. Postharvest Biology and Technology, 187, 111867. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.postharvbio.2022.111867</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, C., Zhang, Y., Fang, Q., Li, R., Yuan, Y., &amp; Zhuang, H. (2023). Nanoemulsions loaded with compound photosensitisers: Synergistic photodynamic inactivation effects of curcumin and riboflavin tetra butyrate. International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology, 58(4), 1728–1740. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.16258</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Cheng, J., Li, Z., Weng, M., Zhang, X., Tang, X., &amp; Pan, Y. (2024). Effects of ultra‐high pressure, thermal pasteurization, and ultra‐high temperature sterilization on color and nutritional components of freshly‐squeezed lettuce juice. Food Chemistry, 435, 137524. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.137524</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Zheng, P., Li, J., Yang, Y., Zeng, S., Qiu, J., &amp; Lin, S. (2022). Curcumin‐mediated sono‐photodynamic treatment inactivates Listeria monocytogenes via ROS‐induced physical disruption and oxidative damage. Foods, 11(6), 808. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11060808</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., Chen, D., Yu, D., Regenstein, J. M., Jiang, Q., Dong, J., Chen, W., &amp; Xia, W. (2022). Modulating physicochemical, antimicrobial and release properties of chitosan/zein bilayer films with curcumin/nisin‐loaded pectin nanoparticles. Food Hydrocolloids, 133, 107955. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2022.107955</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X., Zhang, M., Xu, B., Mujumdar, A. S., &amp; Guo, Z. (2022). Light‐emitting diodes (below 700 nm): Improving the preservation of fresh foods during postharvest handling, storage, and transportation. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 21(1), 106–126. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12887</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z., Chen, R., Mao, S., Zhang, Y., Yao, L., Xi, J., Luo, S., Liu, R., Liu, Y., &amp; Wang, R. (2023). A novel strategy to enhance photocatalytic killing of foodborne pathogenic bacteria by modification of non‐metallic monomeric black phosphorus with Elaeagnus mollis polysaccharides. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 242, 125015. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.125015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z., Qin, J., Wang, Z., Chen, F., Liao, X., Hu, X., &amp; Dong, L. (2022). Sodium copper chlorophyll mediated photodynamic treatment inactivates Escherichia coli via oxidative damage. Food Research International, 157, 111472. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111472</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, X., Shi, T.‐ J., Liu, Y.‐ Y., &amp; Chen, L.‐ J. (2023). Porphyrinic Metal‐Organic Framework‐Loaded Polycaprolactone Composite Films with a High Photodynamic Antibacterial Activity for the Preservation of Fresh‐Cut Apples. ACS Applied Polymer Materials, 5(1), 560–566. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsapm.2c01667</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, M., Chen, W., Zhao, Y., Fang, Q., Wang, L., Tian, S., Shi, Y., &amp; Chen, J. (2024). Ascorbic acid potentiates photodynamic inactivation mediated by octyl gallate and blue light for rapid eradication of planktonic bacteria and biofilms. Food Chemistry, 448, 139073. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.139073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, Y., Liu, R., Zhou, C., Gao, Z., Gu, Y., Chen, S., Yang, Q., &amp; Yan, B. (2023). Dynamically crosslinked chitosan/cellulose nanofiber‐based films integrated with γ‐cyclodextrin/curcumin inclusion complex as multifunctional packaging materials for perishable fruit. Food Hydrocolloids, 144, 108996. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2023.108996</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, S., Song, Y., Pei, J., Xue, F., Cui, X., Xiong, X., &amp; Li, C. (2021). The application of photodynamic inactivation to microorganisms in food. Food Chemistry: X, 12, 100150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fochx.2021.100150</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, X., Yan, H., Cui, Z., Li, H., Zhou, W., Liu, Z., Zhang, H., Manoli, T., Mo, H., &amp; Hu, L. (2023). Ultrasound‐assisted blue light killing Vibrio parahaemolyticus to improve salmon preservation. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 95, 106389. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2023.106389</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou, Y., Yu, Y., Cheng, L., Li, L., Zou, B., Wu, J., Zhou, W., Li, J., &amp; Xu, Y. (2021). Effects of curcumin‐based photodynamic treatment on quality attributes of fresh‐cut pineapple. LWT, 141, 110902. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.110902</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>