<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39248351</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2224-9435</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the South African Veterinary Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J S Afr Vet Assoc</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Retrospective case-control non-inferiority analysis of ultrasound-guided erector spinae plane block in dogs undergoing mini-hemilaminectomy for intervertebral disc disease.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.36303/JSAVA.600</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Veterinary medicine has seen significant advancements in locoregional anaesthesia and pain management, including the emergence of the erector spinae plane (ESP) block. However, limited clinical evidence exists on its efficacy and safety.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study compares ultrasound-guided ESP block (ESP group) with an intraoperative intravenous ketamine infusion analgesic protocol (CRI group) in dogs undergoing thoracolumbar mini-hemilaminectomy, focusing on intraoperative opioid consumption, cardiovascular response to surgical stimulation (CR), postoperative pain scores (PS), and postoperative opioid consumption.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Retrospective, case-control, non-inferiority study conducted in a single centre. Data collected included demographics, bupivacaine dose, ESP block operator, intraoperative recorded variables (haemodynamic variables, CR, complications, rescue analgesia), pre- and postoperative analgesia, 24-hour PS and opioid administration, first food intake post-extubation and postoperative complications. Univariate and multiple regression analyses were applied.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">One-hundred dogs were included, 75 in the ESP group and 25 in the CRI group. Univariate analysis revealed no significant differences between treatment groups in terms of CR, PS, postoperative rescue analgesia, intraoperative and postoperative opioid consumption, or time to first meal intake. However, the multivariate regression analysis indicated that dogs receiving ketamine infusion had higher CR suspected to be nociception-related (<i>p</i> = 0.036), and higher postoperative opioid consumption (<i>p</i> = 0.013).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our study suggests that ultrasound-guided ESP block is as effective as intraoperative ketamine infusion providing perioperative analgesia in dogs undergoing thoracolumbar mini-hemilaminectomy for intervertebral disc disease. ESP group showed significantly lower CR suspected to be nociception-related intraoperatively and lower postoperative opioid consumption within the initial 24 hours.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alza Salvatierra</LastName><ForeName>D N</ForeName><Initials>DN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northwest Veterinary Specialists, Linnaeus Veterinary Limited, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Motta</LastName><ForeName>L</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northwest Veterinary Specialists, Linnaeus Veterinary Limited, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Redondo</LastName><ForeName>J I</ForeName><Initials>JI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departamento de Medicina y Cirugía Animal, Facultad de Veterinaria, Universidad Cardenal Herrera-CEU, CEU Universities, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>du Toit</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northwest Veterinary Specialists, Linnaeus Veterinary Limited, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pompermaier</LastName><ForeName>E</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wear Referrals, Linnaeus Veterinary Limited, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martinez</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ChesterGates Veterinary Specialists, CVS Group public limited company, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>South Africa</Country><MedlineTA>J S Afr Vet Assoc</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7503122</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1019-9128</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39248351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36303/JSAVA.600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>