<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">39256461</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparative study of safflower yellow adjuvant to conventional treatment regimen and conventional treatment regimen on diabetic nephropathy.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>21140</StartPage><MedlinePgn>21140</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">21140</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-64216-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Diabetic nephropathy (DN) is one of the most important comorbidities of diabetic patients, which places large physiological and economic burdens on patients. Safflower yellow, a natural pigment extracted from the petals of safflower, has been put into adjuvant therapy. Databases including Chinese National Knowledge Infrastructure (CNKI), Wanfang Database, MEDLINE and etc. will be searched for relevant articles. A meta-analysis was carried out to assess the efficacy and safety of safflower yellow adjuvant to conventional treatment regimen using mean differences (MD) and rate ratios (RR). A cost-effectiveness analysis was also conducted based on the result of meta-analysis. Finally, 28 articles involving 2251 patients were included in meta-analysis. The results showed that compared with conventional treatment, the fasting blood-glucose (FBG) [MD = 0.40], urinary albumin ejection rate (UAER) within 24 h [MD = 48.16], serum creatinine (Scr) [MD = 9.63], blood urea nitrogen (BUN) [MD = 1.73] were significantly lower and the clinical efficacy [RR = 1.28] was more remarkable in safflower yellow adjuvant to conventional treatment group. Our analysis suggested that safflower yellow adjuvant to conventional treatment regimen not only had better clinical efficacy but more cost-effective than conventional treatment regimen.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Liang</LastName><ForeName>Yun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of regulatory science, China Pharmaceutical University, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China. 20239712@qq.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Research Center of National Drug Policy &amp; Ecosystem, China Pharmaceutical University, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China. 20239712@qq.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Xudong</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Pharmacy, Jinan University, Guangzhou, Guangdong Province, China. 530645703@qq.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Sainan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Food and Drug Vocational College, Guangzhou, Guangdong Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of International Pharmaceutical Business, China Pharmaceutical University, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China. liyang19860423@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>SGY21A008</GrantID><Agency>Higher Education Association of Jiangsu Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D003160">Comparative Study</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D001786">Blood Glucose</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>5S5A2Q39HX</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D002599">Chalcone</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>AYI8EX34EU</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D003404">Creatinine</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>1401-20-3</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C076422">safflower yellow</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001786" MajorTopicYN="N">Blood Glucose</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002599" MajorTopicYN="Y">Chalcone</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000031" MajorTopicYN="N">analogs &amp; derivatives</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003404" MajorTopicYN="N">Creatinine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="N">blood</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003928" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diabetic Nephropathies</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="N">blood</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016896" MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000094703" MajorTopicYN="N">Cost-Effectiveness Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39256461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11387831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-64216-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-64216-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tuttle, K. R. et al. Diabetic kidney disease: A report from an ADA consensus conference. Diabetes Care37, 2864–2883. 10.2337/dc14-1296 (2014). 10.2337/dc14-1296</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc14-1296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4170131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25249672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong, G. &amp; Zhu, D. Interpretation of clinical practice guidelines and expert consensuses for the evaluation and management of diabetic kidney disease at home and abroad. Chin. J. Pract. Internal Med.37, 211–216. 10.19538/j.nk2017030108 (2017).10.19538/j.nk2017030108</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19538/j.nk2017030108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, S. et al. Analysis of the influence of metabolic syndrome on diabetic nephropathy in type 2 diabetes. Chin. J. Prev. Control Chron. Dis.19, 509–511. 10.16386/j.cjpccd.issn.1004-6194.2011.05.036 (2011).10.16386/j.cjpccd.issn.1004-6194.2011.05.036</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16386/j.cjpccd.issn.1004-6194.2011.05.036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, L. &amp; Zheng, S. Research progress of early diagnosis and treatment of diabetic nephropathy. Guizhou Med. J.1, 183–185 (1992).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, L. &amp; Ma, K. Effect of continuous quality improvement model combined with psychological nursing in the application of low blood sugar management and negative emotion in patients with diabetic nephropathy. J. Clin. Pathol. Res.36, 1665–1669 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, L. The Economic Burden and Some Related Factors of type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM) and its Complications in Urban China (Fudang University, Fudang, 2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, L., Hu, K., Jin, S. &amp; Liu, J. Hospitalization cost analysis of patients with different type II diabetes mellitus subtypes. Acad. J. Chin. PLA Med. Sch.32, 663–666 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, J., Fan, W., Huang, Y. &amp; Chen, W. Economic burden of type 2 diabetes mellitus with nephropathy complications in China. Chin. Health Econ.32, 32–34 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, X. &amp; Ren, Y. Research progress on the pharmacologic actions of safflower yellow. J. Trop. Med.15, 421–424 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stroup, D. F. et al. Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology: A proposal for reporting. JAMA: J. Am. Med. Assoc.283, 1 (2000).10.1001/jama.283.15.2008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.283.15.2008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10789670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Husereau, D. et al. Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS)—Explanation and elaboration: A Report of the ISPOR Health Economic Evaluation Publication Guidelines Good Reporting Practices Task Force. Value Health16, 1 (2013). 10.1016/j.jval.2013.02.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2013.02.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23538175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, N. &amp; Liu, X. Criteria of diagnosis, syndrome differentiation and efficacy evaluation on diabetic kidney disease (Trial). Shanghai J. Tradit. Chin. Med.1, 7–8. 10.16305/j.1007-1334.2007.07.003 (2007).10.16305/j.1007-1334.2007.07.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16305/j.1007-1334.2007.07.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins, J. &amp; Green, S. Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions, Version 5.1.0. The Cochrane Collaboration. (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi, F. et al. Common costs and their estimation methods in pharmacoeconomics. Shanghai Med. Pharm. J.36, 7–9 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, F. &amp; Yan, S. Cost-effectiveness analyses of 3 kinds of traditional Chinese medicinal injections in the treatment of coronary heart disease-induced angina pectoris caused. Tianjin Pharm.24, 53–54 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drug price inquiry website. https://www.315jiage.cn.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z. The Study on the Burden of Diabetes in China (Fudang University Press, Fudang, 2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan, X., Li, H., Shao, R., He, Y. &amp; Ma, A. A systematic review and economic evaluation of one-week esomeprazole-based triple therapy versus omeprazole-based triple therapy for patients with peptic ulcer. Chin. J. Hosp. Pharm.39, 502–507. 10.13286/j.cnki.chinhosppharmacyj.2019.05.15 (2019).10.13286/j.cnki.chinhosppharmacyj.2019.05.15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13286/j.cnki.chinhosppharmacyj.2019.05.15</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai, X., Li, X., Song, J., Zhang, X. &amp; Li, H. Soflor yellow on hs-CRP and IL-8 in patients with early diabetic nephropathy. Chin. J. Integrat. Tradit. Western Nephrol.13, 698–700 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bao, X. et al. Effects of safflower yellow combined with metformin on NF-κB signaling pathway of patients with early diabetic nephropathy. Hebei Med. J.39, 1664–1666 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, Y. et al. Effect of soffor yellow combined with benazepril on the renal function of patients with early diabetic nephropathy. Progress Mod. Biomed.15, 4333–4336. 10.13241/j.cnki.pmb.2015.22.034 (2015).10.13241/j.cnki.pmb.2015.22.034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13241/j.cnki.pmb.2015.22.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Z. &amp; Wang, W. Efficacy of safflower yellow combined with losartan potassium in the treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. People’s Milit. Surg.55, 27–28 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, J., Lu, L., Hu, F. &amp; Yuan, H. Effects of safflower yellow on insulin resistance and hypercoagulability in patients with early type 2 diabetic nephropathy. Chin. J. Difficult Complicat. Cases18, 805–808 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, X., Li, X. &amp; Liu, X. Clinical observation of safflower yellow pigment in the treatment of elderly patients with diabetic nephropathy complicated with acute myocardial infarction. China Pharm.28, 4140–4143 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu, T., Wang, X., Yuan, J., Wang, G. &amp; Wang, M. Observation on the clinical effect of safflower yellow pigment injection in the adjuvant treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. Progress Mod. Biomed.13, 5975–5977. 10.13241/j.cnki.pmb.2013.30.027 (2013).10.13241/j.cnki.pmb.2013.30.027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13241/j.cnki.pmb.2013.30.027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Liu, Y. &amp; Ran, H. Observation on efficacy of carthamin yellow combined with metformin in treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. Eval. Anal. Drug-Use Hosp. China17, 1370–1371. 10.14009/j.issn.1672-2124.2017.10.028 (2017).10.14009/j.issn.1672-2124.2017.10.028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14009/j.issn.1672-2124.2017.10.028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan, L., Li, J. &amp; Jiang, X. Analysis of clinical efficacy of safflower yellow powder injection combined with alprostadil on diabetic nephropathy. Nei Mongol J. Tradit. Chin. Med.36, 53–54. 10.16040/j.cnki.cn15-1101.2017.16.054 (2017).10.16040/j.cnki.cn15-1101.2017.16.054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16040/j.cnki.cn15-1101.2017.16.054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, Y. Effect of safflower yellow injection combined with Shenmai Injection on expression of urinary protein in early diabetic nephropathy. Asia-Pac. Tradit. Med.12, 137–138 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, Y. &amp; Gu, Y. Influences of sofflor yellow on inflammatory reaction and proteinuria of patients with diabetic nephropathy. J. Chengde Med. Coll.33, 194–196. 10.15921/j.cnki.cyxb.2016.03.006 (2016).10.15921/j.cnki.cyxb.2016.03.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15921/j.cnki.cyxb.2016.03.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, Y., Yuan, L., Zhang, L. &amp; Liu, N. Analysis of 44 cases of safflower yellow combined with telmisartan in the treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. Guizhou Med. J.39, 986–988 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, H. et al. Soffor yellow injection therapy in patients with unstable angina and diabeticnephropathy. Chin. J. Thrombos. Hemostas.20, 258–259 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, Z. Clinical study on valsartan combined with safflower yellow in the treatment of diabetic nephropathy proteinuria. Asia-Pac. Tradit. Med.11, 134–135 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, S., Zeng, B. &amp; Lin, S. Clinical observation of safflower yellow injection in the treatment of diabetic renal failure. Chin. Commun. Doct.35, 99 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, R. et al. Effect of sulodexide combined with carthamin yellow on renal function and blood lipid in DN patients. Liaon. J. Tradit. Chin. Med.45, 2576–2578. 10.13192/j.issn.1000-1719.2018.12.036 (2018).10.13192/j.issn.1000-1719.2018.12.036</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13192/j.issn.1000-1719.2018.12.036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, T. &amp; He, C. Efficacy of safflower yellow injection combined with pancreatic kininogenase in the treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. J. North Pharm.11, 32–33 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, S. &amp; Liu, J. Clinical efficacy evaluation of safflower yellow injection combined with valsartan in the treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. Anti-infect. Pharm.12, 963–965. 10.13493/j.issn.1672-7878.2015.06-065 (2015).10.13493/j.issn.1672-7878.2015.06-065</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13493/j.issn.1672-7878.2015.06-065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, B., Yang, L., Yang, X. &amp; Chen, B. Clinical efficacy of safflower yellow injection in the treatment of diabetic nephropathy. Seek Med. Ask Med.9, 147 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, X. Clinical observation of safflower yellow sodium chloride injection in the treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. J. Shand. Univ. Tradit. Chin. Med.1, 304–305. 10.16294/j.cnki.1007-659x.2007.04.017 (2007).10.16294/j.cnki.1007-659x.2007.04.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16294/j.cnki.1007-659x.2007.04.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, X. &amp; Dai, Li. The explore of the protective effect of safflower yellow injection combined with alpha-lipoic acid in treating the patients with type 2 diabetes and early signs of nephropathy. J. Tradit. Chin. Med. Mater. Med.33, 23–24. 10.1654/j.cnki.53-1120/r.2012.04.046 (2012).10.1654/j.cnki.53-1120/r.2012.04.046</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1654/j.cnki.53-1120/r.2012.04.046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao, S. &amp; Zhang, C. Clinical observation of acupoint Injection of safflower yellow injection in the treatment of early diabetic nephropathy. China Health Industry9, 81. 10.16659/j.cnki.1672-5654.2012.32.110 (2012).10.16659/j.cnki.1672-5654.2012.32.110</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16659/j.cnki.1672-5654.2012.32.110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin, M. Influence of carthamin yellow pigment injection on oxidative stress indexes and inflammatory factors of patients with early diabetic nephropathy. J. Clin. Med. Pract.22, 51–54 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, Y. &amp; Jiao, J. Observation on efficacy of safflower yellow pigment lyophilized power in the treatment of diabetic nephropathy. Qingdao Med. J.42, 259–260 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, L. &amp; Yang, G. Clinical research on safflower yellow in treatment of early type 2 diabetic nephropathy. Proc. Clin. Med.19, 502–503 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, D., Wang, Y., Chen, Z., Bian, D. &amp; Qi, H. Efficacy of treatment in 39 patients with diabetic nephropathy by safflor yellow and benazepril in combination. Chin. J. Integr. Tradit. West. Med.1, 360–363 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18543495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X. Clinical efficacy of safflower yellow injection combined with irbesartan in the treatment of diabetic nephropathy. Pract. Clin. Med.11, 24–26 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, Z. The effect of valsartan combined with safflower yellow on UAER and hs-CRP in diabetic nephropathy. Mod. Diagnosis Treatment26, 3431–3432 (2015).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>