<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39259944</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1520-4898</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>57</Volume><Issue>19</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Accounts of chemical research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acc Chem Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Conductive Framework Materials for Chemiresistive Detection and Differentiation of Toxic Gases.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2775</StartPage><EndPage>2789</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2775-2789</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acs.accounts.4c00319</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>ConspectusSensing complex gaseous mixtures and identifying their composition and concentration have the potential to achieve unprecedented improvements in environmental monitoring, medical diagnostics, industrial safety, and the food/agriculture industry. Electronically transduced chemical sensors capable of recognizing and differentiating specific target gases and transducing these chemical stimuli in a portable electronic device offer an opportunity for impact by bridging the utility of chemical information with global wireless connectivity. Among electronically transduced chemical sensors, chemiresistors stand out as particularly promising due to combined features of low-power requirements, room temperature operation, non-line-of-sight detection, high portability, and exceptional modularity. Relying on changes in resistance of a functional material triggered by variations in the surrounding chemical environment, these devices have achieved part-per-billion sensitivities of analytes by employing conductive polymers, graphene, carbon nanotubes (CNTs), metal oxides, metal nanoparticles, metal dichalcogenides, or MXenes as sensing materials. Despite these tremendous developments, the need for stable, selective, and sensitive chemiresistors demands continued innovation in material design in order to operate in complex mixtures with interferents as well as variations in humidity and temperature.To fill existing gaps in sensing capabilities, conductive metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) and covalent organic frameworks (COFs) have recently emerged as a promising class of materials for chemiresistive sensing. In contrast to previously reported chemiresistors, these materials offer at least three unique features for gas sensing applications: (i) bottom-up synthesis from molecularly precise precursors that allows for strategic control of material-analyte interactions, (ii) intrinsic conductivity that simultaneously facilitates charge transport and signal transduction under low power requirements, and (iii) high surface area that enables the accessibility of abundant active sites and decontamination of gas streams by coordinating to and, sometimes, detoxifying harmful analytes. Through an emphasis on molecular engineering of structure-property relationships in conductive MOFs and COFs, combined with strategic innovations in device integration strategies and device form factor (i.e., the physical dimensions and design of device components), our group has paved the way to demonstrating the multifunctional utility of these materials in the chemiresistive detection of gases and vapors. Backed by spectroscopic assessment of material-analyte interactions, we illustrated how molecular-level features lead to device performance in detection, filtration, and detoxification of gaseous analytes. By merging the bottom-up synthesis of these materials with device integration, we show the versatility and scalability of using these materials in low-power electronic sensing devices. Taken together, our achievements, combined with the progress spearheaded on this class of materials by other researchers, establish conductive MOFs and COFs as promising multifunctional materials for applications in electronically transduced, portable, low-power sensing devices.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Benedetto</LastName><ForeName>Georganna</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6551-4673</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Dartmouth College, Hanover, New Hampshire 03755, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mirica</LastName><ForeName>Katherine A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1779-7568</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Dartmouth College, Hanover, New Hampshire 03755, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Acc Chem Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0157313</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0001-4842</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39259944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.accounts.4c00319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>