<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39251121</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-6424</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>362</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental pollution (Barking, Essex : 1987)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Pollut</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Fate of chlordecone in soil food webs in a banana agroecosystem in Martinique.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>124874</StartPage><MedlinePgn>124874</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.124874</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0269-7491(24)01588-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Large quantities of chlordecone-based insecticides were produced and used throughout the world. One of its most important uses was to control the damage caused by Cosmopolites sordidus in banana-growing regions. In the islands of Martinique and Guadeloupe, 18,000 ha of farmland are potentially contaminated. Despite the key role played by soil macrofauna in agroecosystems, there are currently no data on their contamination. The aim of this study was to explore the fate of chlordecone (CLD) and its transfer to different organisms of the soil food web. Seven species of invertebrates representing different taxonomic groups and trophic levels of the soil communities of Martinique were targeted and collected in six experimental banana fields, with a level of contamination within a range of values classically observed. Soil samples and macrofauna from the study sites were analysed for CLD and chlordecol (CLDOH) its main transformation product. The contamination of the soil fauna were related to δ<sup>15</sup>N (trophic level), proportion of soil ingestion (diet) and types of epidermis (mucus or exoskeleton) in order to study the different mechanisms of macrofauna contamination. Presence of CLD and CLDOH could be quantified in all the soil organisms from contaminated fields. Results showed a significant relationship between the CLD contamination of detritivorous and the ash content of their faeces, suggesting that soil ingestion was the main contamination pathway. In contrast, the exoskeleton-bearing diplopod Trigoniulus coralinus and the soft-bodied earthworm Eudrilus eugeniae, both detritivores with a comparable diet, had similar contamination levels, suggesting that the type of tegument has little influence on bioaccumulation. At the scale of the entire trophic network, a significant relationship was uncovered between δ<sup>15</sup>N values and CLD contamination of the fauna, therefore providing some in situ evidence for a bioamplification process along the soil food chain.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Coulis</LastName><ForeName>Mathieu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CIRAD, UPR GECO, F-97285 Le Lamentin, Martinique, France; GECO, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, Montpellier, France. Electronic address: mathieu.coulis@cirad.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Senecal</LastName><ForeName>Julie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CIRAD, UPR GECO, F-97285 Le Lamentin, Martinique, France; GECO, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, Montpellier, France; CIRAD, UPR HortSys, F-97285 Le Lamentin, Martinique, France; HortSys, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Devriendt-Renault</LastName><ForeName>Yoann</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Paris Est Creteil, ANSES, Laboratory for Food Safety, Pesticides and Marine Biotoxins Unit, 14 Rue Pierre et Marie Curie, F-94701 Maisons-Alfort, France; LDA26, Departmental Laboratory of Analyses of La Drôme, F-26000, Valence, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guerin</LastName><ForeName>Thierry</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ANSES, Strategy and Programmes Department, F-94701 Maisons-Alfort, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parinet</LastName><ForeName>Julien</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Paris Est Creteil, ANSES, Laboratory for Food Safety, Pesticides and Marine Biotoxins Unit, 14 Rue Pierre et Marie Curie, F-94701 Maisons-Alfort, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pak</LastName><ForeName>Lai Ting</ForeName><Initials>LT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CIRAD, UPR HortSys, F-97285 Le Lamentin, Martinique, France; HortSys, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Pollut</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8804476</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0269-7491</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioaccumulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Geophagy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Organochlorine pesticide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Soil macrofauna</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests:Mathieu coulis reports financial support was provided by the BANABIO project funding obtained under DEPHY EXPE program of the Ecophyto II plan. Julien PARINET reports financial support was provided by French National Research Agency (ANR-19-CE21-0002). Lai Ting pak reports financial support was provided by The French Ministry of the Overseas for this study that was part of the Territoires Durables project carried out in Martinique. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39251121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.124874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0269-7491(24)01588-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>