<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39254810</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1614-7499</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science and pollution research international</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Hybrid machine learning approach integrating GMDH and SVR for heavy metal concentration prediction in dust samples.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11356-024-34795-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In agricultural regions prone to dust storms, heavy metal contamination of soil and crops from airborne particulates poses significant risks to food safety and public health. This study has assessed the potential of machine learning models for predicting concentrations of toxic heavy metals like arsenic, chromium, and lead in dust from the agricultural Sistan region of southeastern Iran. This region experiences frequent dust storms mobilizing particulates from local dried lakes onto agricultural lands. The metals including nickel, copper, magnesium, cobalt, zinc, chromium, arsenic, and lead were measured in summer dust samples during 2012-2018 across 15 stations. Two hybrid models were developed combining group method of data handling (GMDH) and support vector regression (SVR) machine learning with harmony search optimization (H) so as to predict toxic metals arsenic, chromium, and lead using nickel, copper, magnesium, cobalt, and zinc inputs. Standard error maps were uncertainty higher in southern and western areas, and they are most impacted by dust storms. Results demonstrated that the hybrid GMDH + H and SVR + H models improved the accuracy of individual GMDH and SVR models in predicting heavy metals. The GMDH + H model performed the best for the lead with an agreement index (d-index) of 0.98, root mean square error (RMSE) of 2.87 ppm, normalized RMSE (NRMSE) of 0.12, and coefficient of determination (RR) of 0.96. The SVR + H model showed the highest accuracy for arsenic and chromium, obtaining d-index 0.96, RMSE 0.47 ppm, NRMSE 0.09, and RR 0.92 for arsenic, and d-index 0.96, RMSE 11.24 ppm, NRMSE 0.16, and RR 0.93 for chromium. Taylor's diagram and heatmap analysis confirmed the superiority of the hybrid techniques. This work demonstrates the utility of state-of-the-art computing for addressing complex environmental health challenges.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Piri</LastName><ForeName>Jamshid</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Water Engineering, Faculty of Soil &amp; Water, University of Zabol, P.O. Box: 98615-538, Zabol, Iran. j.piri@uoz.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kahkha</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Reza Rezaei</ForeName><Initials>MRR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, Faculty of Health, Zabol University of Medical Sciences, Zabol, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kisi</LastName><ForeName>Ozgur</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil Engineering, Lubeck University of Applied Sciences, 23562, Lübeck, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil Engineering, Ilia State University, 0162, Tbilisi, Georgia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9441769</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0944-1344</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dust</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Harmony search optimization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Heavy metal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Improved GMDH</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Improved SVR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prediction</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39254810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-34795-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11356-024-34795-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abdelaziz AY, Osama RA, Elkhodary SM (2013) Distribution systems reconfiguration using ant colony optimization and harmony search algorithms. Electric Power Components Syst 41:537–554</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi MH, Sadeghzadeh M, Raffiee AH, Chau K-w (2019) Applying GMDH neural network to estimate the thermal resistance and thermal conductivity of pulsating heat pipes. Eng Appl Comput Fluid Mech 13:327–336</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akbari M, Mirchi A, Roozbahani A, Gafurov A, Kløve B, Haghighi AT (2022) Desiccation of the transboundary Hamun Lakes between Iran and Afghanistan in response to hydro-climatic droughts and anthropogenic activities. J Great Lakes Res 48:876–889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alizadeh-Choobari O, Zawar-Reza P, Sturman A (2014) The “wind of 120 days” and dust storm activity over the Sistan Basin. Atmos Res 143:328–341</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amiri M, Soleimani S (2021) ML-based group method of data handling: an improvement on the conventional GMDH. Complex Intell Syst 7:2949–2960</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azhar B, Gunawan S, Setyadi ERF, Majidah L, Taufany F, Atmaja L, Aparamarta HW (2023) Purification and separation of glucomannan from porang tuber flour (Amorphophallus muelleri) using microwave assisted extraction as an innovative gelatine substituent. Heliyon 9:e21972</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balali-Mood M, Naseri K, Tahergorabi Z, Khazdair MR, Sadeghi M (2021) Toxic mechanisms of five heavy metals: mercury, lead, chromium, cadmium, and arsenic. Front Pharmacol 227:643972</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balzani P, Kouba A, Tricarico E, Kourantidou M, Haubrock PJ (2022) Metal accumulation in relation to size and body condition in an all-alien species community. Environ Sci Pollut Res 29:25848–25857</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang F-J, Chang Y-T (2006) Adaptive neuro-fuzzy inference system for prediction of water level in reservoir. Adv Water Resour 29:1–10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Wang L, Hu B, Xu J, Liu X (2022) Potential driving forces and probabilistic health risks of heavy metal accumulation in the soils from an e-waste area, southeast China. Chemosphere 289:133–182</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarkson TW (1987) Metal toxicity in the central nervous system. Environ Health Perspect 75:59–64</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cobos C, Andrade J, Constain W, Mendoza M, León E (2010) Web document clustering based on global-best harmony search, K-means, frequent term sets and Bayesian information criterion, IEEE congress on evolutionary computation. IEEE, pp 1–8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Csuros M, Csuros C (2016) Environmental sampling and analysis for metals. CRC Press. https://doi.org/10.1201/9781420032345</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Miguel E, Llamas JF, Chacón E, Berg T, Larssen S, Røyset O, Vadset M (1997) Origin and patterns of distribution of trace elements in street dust: unleaded petrol and urban lead. Atmos Environ 31:2733–2740</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodangeh E, Panahi M, Rezaie F, Lee S, Bui DT, Lee C-W, Pradhan B (2020) Novel hybrid intelligence models for flood-susceptibility prediction: meta optimization of the GMDH and SVR models with the genetic algorithm and harmony search. J Hydrol 590:125423</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elbana TA, Ramadan MA, Gaber HM, Bahnassy MH, Kishk FM, Selim H (2013) Heavy metals accumulation and spatial distribution in long term wastewater irrigated soils. J Environ Chem Eng 1:925–933</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elzwayie A, Afan HA, Allawi MF, El-Shafie A (2017) Heavy metal monitoring, analysis and prediction in lakes and rivers: state of the art. Environ Sci Pollut Res 24:12104–12117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engwa GA, Ferdinand PU, Nwalo FN, Unachukwu MN (2019) Mechanism and health effects of heavy metal toxicity in humans. Poisoning Modern World-New Tricks Old Dog 10:70–90</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eslami S, Hasanlou M (2019) Coral reef modeling using support vector regression and applying spectral indices</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fesanghary M, Mahdavi M, Minary-Jolandan M, Alizadeh Y (2008) Hybridizing harmony search algorithm with sequential quadratic programming for engineering optimization problems. Comput Methods Appl Mech Eng 197:3080–3091</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galán CO, Lasheras FS, de Cos Juez FJ, Sánchez AB (2017) Missing data imputation of questionnaires by means of genetic algorithms with different fitness functions. J Comput Appl Math 311:704–717</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goudie AS, Middleton NJ (2006) Desert dust in the global system. Springer Science &amp; Business Media</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heddam S, Kisi O (2017) Extreme learning machines: a new approach for modeling dissolved oxygen (DO) concentration with and without water quality variables as predictors. Environ Sci Pollut Res 24:16702–16724</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu X, Zhang Y, Luo J, Wang T, Lian H, Ding Z (2011) Bioaccessibility and health risk of arsenic, mercury and other metals in urban street dusts from a mega-city, Nanjing, China. Environ Pollut 159:1215–1221</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang G, Wang X, Chen D, Wang Y, Zhu S, Zhang T, Liao L, Tian Z, Wei N (2022) A hybrid data-driven framework for diagnosing contributing factors for soil heavy metal contaminations using machine learning and spatial clustering analysis. J Hazard Mater 437:129324</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiries A (2003) Vehicular contamination of dust in Amman, Jordan. Environmentalist 23:205–210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kahkha MRR, Somaye B, Noori R, Piri J, Javan S (2017) Examining total concentration and sequential extraction of heavy metals in agricultural soil and wheat. Pol J Environ Stud 26(5):2021–2028. https://doi.org/10.15244/pjoes/67658</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ke B, Nguyen H, Bui X-N, Bui H-B, Choi Y, Zhou J, Moayedi H, Costache R, Nguyen-Trang T (2021) Predicting the sorption efficiency of heavy metal based on the biochar characteristics, metal sources, and environmental conditions using various novel hybrid machine learning models. Chemosphere 276:130204</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Yang H, Zhang C, Zeng G, Liu Y, Xu W, Wu Y, Lan S (2017) Spatial distribution and transport characteristics of heavy metals around an antimony mine area in central China. Chemosphere 170:17–24</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Li W, Song W, Guo M (2018) Remediation techniques for heavy metal-contaminated soils: principles and applicability. Sci Total Environ 633:206–219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Wang L, Gu K (2021) A support vector regression (SVR)-based method for dynamic load identification using heterogeneous responses under interval uncertainties. Appl Soft Comput 110:107599</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu C, Xu Z, Dong B, Zhang Y, Wang M, Zeng Y, Zhang C (2022) Machine learning for the prediction of heavy metal removal by chitosan-based flocculants. Carbohyd Polym 285:119240</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv Y, Liu J, Yang T, Zeng D (2013) A novel least squares support vector machine ensemble model for NOx emission prediction of a coal-fired boiler. Energy 55:319–329</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitra S, Chakraborty AJ, Tareq AM, Emran TB, Nainu F, Khusro A, Idris AM, Khandaker MU, Osman H, Alhumaydhi FA (2022) Impact of heavy metals on the environment and human health: novel therapeutic insights to counter the toxicity. J King Saud Univ-Sci 34:101865</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadpour M, Roshan H, Arashpour M, Masoumi H (2023) Effect of spatial variability of downhole geophysical logs on machine learning exercises. Int J Coal Geol 277:104333</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulashani AK, Shen C, Nkurlu BM, Mkono CN, Kawamala M (2022) Enhanced group method of data handling (GMDH) for permeability prediction based on the modified Levenberg Marquardt technique from well log data. Energy 239:121915</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nariman-Zadeh N, Salehpour M, Jamali A, Haghgoo E (2010) Pareto optimization of a five-degree of freedom vehicle vibration model using a multi-objective uniform-diversity genetic algorithm (MUGA). Eng Appl Artif Intell 23:543–551</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojha VK, Abraham A, Snášel V (2017) Metaheuristic design of feedforward neural networks: a review of two decades of research. Eng Appl Artif Intell 60:97–116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paithankar JG, Saini S, Dwivedi S, Sharma A, Chowdhuri DK (2021) Heavy metal associated health hazards: an interplay of oxidative stress and signal transduction. Chemosphere 262:128350</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piri J, Shamshirband S, Petković D, Tong CW, ur Rehman MH (2015) Prediction of the solar radiation on the earth using support vector regression technique. Infrared Phys Technol 68:179–185</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piri J, Pirzadeh B, Keshtegar B, Givehchi M (2021a) Reliability analysis of pumping station for sewage network using hybrid neural networks-genetic algorithm and method of moment. Process Saf Environ Prot 145:39–51</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piri J, Pirzadeh B, Keshtegar B, Givehchi M (2021b) A hybrid statistical regression technical for prediction wastewater inflow. Comput Electron Agric 184:106115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piri J, Abdolahipour M, Keshtegar B (2023a) Advanced machine learning model for prediction of drought indices using hybrid SVR-RSM. Water Resour Manag 37:683–712</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piri J, Mollaeinia M, Mostafaie A (2023b) Assessment of response surface method and hybrid models to predict evaporation (case study: Chahnimeh and Pishein reservoirs in Sistan and Baluchestan Province of Iran). Arab J Geosci 16:346</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porto DC, Sande LS, Perrone ACB, Campos LFdS, Couto DL, da Silva JR, Passos RdS, Oliveira AA, Pereira R (2021) The entropy of Rr intervals is associated to gestational age in full-term newborns with adequate weight for gestational age. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med 34:3639–3644</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Priyadarshanee M, Das S (2021) Biosorption and removal of toxic heavy metals by metal tolerating bacteria for bioremediation of metal contamination: a comprehensive review. J Environ Chem Eng 9:104686</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin Y, Langari R, Gu L (2015) A new modeling algorithm based on ANFIS and GMDH. J Intell Fuzzy Syst 29:1321–1329</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin G, Niu Z, Yu J, Li Z, Ma J, Xiang P (2021) Soil heavy metal pollution and food safety in China: effects, sources and removing technology. Chemosphere 267:129205</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rai PK, Song H, Kim K-H (2023) Nanoparticles modulate heavy-metal and arsenic stress in food crops: hormesis for food security, safety, and public health. Sci Total Environ 902:166064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramezani CA, Zounemat KM (2017) Evaluation of the efficiency of support vector regression, multi-layer perceptron neural network and multivariate linear regression on groundwater level prediction (case study: Shahrekord Plain). J Watershed Manag Res 8(15):1–12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos CC, Souza AN, Chiachia G, Falcão AX, Papa JP (2011) A novel algorithm for feature selection using harmony search and its application for non-technical losses detection. Comput Electr Eng 37:886–894</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashki A, Middleton NJ, Goudie AS (2021) Dust storms in Iran–distribution, causes, frequencies and impacts. Aeol Res 48:100655</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasmussen P, Subramanian K, Jessiman B (2001) A multi-element profile of house dust in relation to exterior dust and soils in the city of Ottawa, Canada. Sci Total Environ 267:125–140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman Q, Rehman K, Akash MSH (2021) Heavy metals and neurological disorders: from exposure to preventive interventions, Environmental contaminants and neurological disorders. Springer, pp 69–87</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saeedi M, Li LY, Salmanzadeh M (2012) Heavy metals and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons: pollution and ecological risk assessment in street dust of Tehran. J Hazard Mater 227:9–17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schröder P, Beckers B, Daniels S, Gnädinger F, Maestri E, Marmiroli N, Mench M, Millán R, Obermeier MM, Oustriere N (2018) Intensify production, transform biomass to energy and novel goods and protect soils in Europe—a vision how to mobilize marginal lands. Sci Total Environ 616:1101–1123</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaghaghi S, Bonakdari H, Gholami A, Ebtehaj I, Zeinolabedini M (2017) Comparative analysis of GMDH neural network based on genetic algorithm and particle swarm optimization in stable channel design. Appl Math Comput 313:271–286</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh I (2023) Heavy metals and human health: a case study. J Healthc Life-Sci Res 2:1–15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y, Zhan D, He Z, Li W, Duan W, Yang Z, Lu M (2023) HPO-empowered machine learning with multiple environment variables enables spatial prediction of soil heavy metals in coastal delta farmland of China. Comput Electron Agric 213:108254</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srinivas R (2010) Managing large data sets using support vector machines</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srinivasan D (2008) Energy demand prediction using GMDH networks. Neurocomputing 72:625–629</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subasi A, Ercelebi E (2005) Classification of EEG signals using neural network and logistic regression. Comput Methods Programs Biomed 78:87–99</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Touat N, Benseddiq N, Ghoul A, Rechak S (2014) An accelerated pseudo-genetic algorithm for dynamic finite element model updating. Eng Optim 46:340–360</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Usman M, Idi A, Aisami A (2023) Fungal endophyte: a promising tool of heavy metal bioremediation: SAJSET-01-2023-0023. Savannah J Sci Eng Technol 1:60–65</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vithanage M, Bandara PC, Novo LA, Kumar A, Ambade B, Naveendrakumar G, Ranagalage M, Magana-Arachchi DN (2022) Deposition of trace metals associated with atmospheric particulate matter: environmental fate and health risk assessment. Chemosphere 303:135051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Yang H, Liu H (2018) GMDH-based semi-supervised feature selection for electricity load classification forecasting. Sustainability 10:217</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Zhang H, Qiu S, Sooranna SR, Deng X, Qu X, Yin W, Chen Q, Niu B (2022) Risk assessment and early warning of the presence of heavy metal pollution in strawberries. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 243:114001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai X, Li Z, Huang B, Luo N, Huang M, Zhang Q, Zeng G (2018) Remediation of multiple heavy metal-contaminated soil through the combination of soil washing and in situ immobilization. Sci Total Environ 635:92–99</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng CW, Li CY (2015) Variation of the wave energy and significant wave height in the China Sea and adjacent waters. Renew Sustain Energy Rev 43:381–387</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong S, Zhang K, Bagheri M, Burken JG, Gu A, Li B, Ma X, Marrone BL, Ren ZJ, Schrier J (2021) Machine learning: new ideas and tools in environmental science and engineering. Environ Sci Technol 55:12741–12754</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>