<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39269415</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1876-7591</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JACC. Cardiovascular imaging</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JACC Cardiovasc Imaging</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Predictors for Vulnerable Plaque in Functionally Significant Lesions.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1936-878X(24)00311-5</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jcmg.2024.07.021</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Vulnerable plaque presents prognostic implications in addition to functional significance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The aim of this study was to identify relevant features of vulnerable plaque in functionally significant lesions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this multicenter, prospective study conducted across 5 countries, including patients who had invasive fractional flow reserve (FFR) ≤0.80, a total of 95 patients with available pullback pressure gradient (PPG) and plaque analysis on coronary computed tomographic angiography and optical coherence tomography were analyzed. Vulnerable plaque was defined as the presence of plaque rupture or thin-cap fibroatheroma on optical coherence tomography. Among the 25 clinical characteristics, invasive angiographic findings, physiological indexes, and coronary computed tomographic angiographic findings, significant predictors of vulnerable plaque were identified.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Mean percentage diameter stenosis, FFR, and PPG were 77.8% ± 14.6%, 0.66 ± 0.13, and 0.65 ± 0.13, respectively. Vulnerable plaque was present in 53 lesions (55.8%). PPG and FFR were identified as significant predictors of vulnerable plaque (P &lt; 0.05 for all). PPG &gt;0.65 and FFR ≤0.70 were significantly related to a higher probability of vulnerable plaque after adjustment for each other (OR: 6.75 [95% CI: 2.39-19.1]; P &lt; 0.001] for PPG &gt;0.65; OR: 4.61 [95% CI: 1.66-12.8]; P = 0.003 for FFR ≤0.70). When categorizing lesions according to combined PPG &gt;0.65 and FFR ≤0.70, the prevalence of vulnerable plaque was 20.0%, 57.1%, 66.7%, and 88.2% in the order of PPG ≤0.65 and FFR &gt;0.70, PPG ≤0.65 and FFR ≤0.70, PPG &gt;0.65 and FFR &gt;0.70, and PPG &gt;0.65 and FFR ≤0.70 (P for trend &lt; 0.001), respectively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Among low-FFR lesions, the presence of vulnerable plaque can be predicted by PPG combined with FFR without additional anatomical or plaque characteristics. (Precise Percutaneous Coronary Intervention Plan [P3] Study; NCT03782688).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 American College of Cardiology Foundation. Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Seokhun</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine and Cardiovascular Center, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul National University of College of Medicine, Seoul, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hwang</LastName><ForeName>Doyeon</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine and Cardiovascular Center, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul National University of College of Medicine, Seoul, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sakai</LastName><ForeName>Koshiro</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Showa University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mizukami</LastName><ForeName>Takuya</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Division of Clinical Pharmacology, Department of Pharmacology, Showa University, Tokyo, Japan; Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, Gifu Heart Center, Gifu, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leipsic</LastName><ForeName>Jonathon</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine and Radiology, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Belmonte</LastName><ForeName>Marta</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Department of Cardiology, University of Milan, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sonck</LastName><ForeName>Jeroen</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Department of Advanced Biomedical Sciences, University Federico II, Naples, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nørgaard</LastName><ForeName>Bjarne L</ForeName><Initials>BL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Aarhus University Hospital, Aarhus, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Otake</LastName><ForeName>Hiromasa</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Graduate School of Medicine, Kobe University, Kobe, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ko</LastName><ForeName>Brian</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Monash Cardiovascular Research Centre, Monash University and Monash Heart, Monash Health, Clayton, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maeng</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Aarhus University Hospital, Aarhus, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Møller Jensen</LastName><ForeName>Jesper</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Aarhus University Hospital, Aarhus, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Buytaert</LastName><ForeName>Dimitri</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Munhoz</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Department of Advanced Biomedical Sciences, University Federico II, Naples, Italy; Discipline of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Campinas, Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andreini</LastName><ForeName>Daniele</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Cardiologico Monzino, IRCCS, Milan, Italy; Department of Biomedical and Clinical Sciences, University of Milan, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ohashi</LastName><ForeName>Hirofumi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Department of Cardiology, Aichi Medical University, Aichi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shinke</LastName><ForeName>Toshiro</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Showa University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taylor</LastName><ForeName>Charles A</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computational Engineering and Sciences, University of Texas, Austin, Texas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barbato</LastName><ForeName>Emanuele</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Department of Advanced Biomedical Sciences, University Federico II, Naples, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>De Bruyne</LastName><ForeName>Bernard</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium; Department of Cardiology, Lausanne University Hospital, Lausanne, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Collet</LastName><ForeName>Carlos</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Center Aalst, OLV Clinic, Aalst, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koo</LastName><ForeName>Bon-Kwon</ForeName><Initials>BK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine and Cardiovascular Center, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul National University of College of Medicine, Seoul, South Korea. Electronic address: bkkoo@snu.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT03782688</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>JACC Cardiovasc Imaging</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101467978</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1876-7591</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fractional flow reserve</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">myocardial ischemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">plaque rupture</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pullback pressure gradients</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thin-cap fibroatheroma</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Funding Support and Author Disclosures This study received funding from HeartFlow and was also supported by grants from the Patient-Centered Clinical Research Coordinating Center (HI19C0481 and HC19C0305) funded by the Ministry of Health and Welfare and from the Ministry of Food and Drug Safety (RS-2023-00215667), Republic of Korea. Dr Mizukami has received consulting fees from Zeon Medical and HeartFlow; and has received speaker fees from Abbott Vascular. Dr Leipsic is a consultant for and holds stock options in Circle CVI and HeartFlow; has received a research grant from GE; and has received modest speaker fees from GE and Philips. Drs Sonck and Munhoz have received research grants provided by the Cardiopath PhD program. Dr Nørgaard has received unrestricted institutional research grants from Siemens and HeartFlow. Dr Otake has received research grants from Abbott Vascular; and has received speaker fees from HeartFlow and Abbott Vascular. Dr Ko has received consulting fees from Canon Medical, Abbott, and Medtronic. Dr Koo has received institutional research grants from HeartFlow. Dr Maeng has received advisory board and lecture fees from AstraZeneca, Bayer, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol Myers Squibb, Boston Scientific, and Novo Nordics; and has received institutional research grants from Bayer, Philips Healthcare, and Novo Nordisk. Dr Jensen has received unrestricted institutional research grants from Siemens and HeartFlow. Dr Andreini has received research grants from GE Healthcare and Bracco. Dr Shinke has received research grants from Boston Scientific and Abbott Vascular. Dr Barbato has received speaker fees from Boston Scientific, Abbott Vascular, and GE. Dr De Bruyne has received consulting fees from Boston Scientific and Abbott Vascular; has received research grants from Coroventis Research, Pie Medical Imaging, CathWorks, Boston Scientific, Siemens, HeartFlow, and Abbott Vascular; and owns equity in Siemens, GE, Philips, HeartFlow, Edwards Lifesciences, Bayer, Sanofi, and Celyad. Dr Collet has received research grants from Biosensor, Coroventis Research, Medis Medical Imaging, Pie Medical Imaging, CathWorks, Boston Scientific, Siemens, HeartFlow, and Abbott Vascular; and has received consulting fees from HeartFlow, OpSens, Abbott Vascular, and Philips Volcano. All other authors have reported that they have no relationships relevant to the contents of this paper to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39269415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcmg.2024.07.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1936-878X(24)00311-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>