<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39261347</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1559-0305</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Molecular biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mol Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Milk Lipid Regulation in Dairy Goats: A Comprehensive Review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12033-024-01283-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The growth, development, and milk production traits of dairy goats, which are important sources of high-quality animal protein, are significantly influenced by a combination of genetic and environmental factors. It is imperative to identify key genetic loci that govern economically valuable traits in order to enhance breeding programs. Despite advancements in genomic technologies, there are still gaps in knowledge regarding the interplay between genetic factors and environmental influences, particularly in relation to the regulation of milk production and quality. Therefore, the aim of this paper was to synthesize advancements in the genetic and environmental factors affecting milk production and quality in dairy goats and identify key regulatory mechanisms. This review summarizes the recent progress on the identification of genes associated with milk production traits using whole-genome resequencing, the use of transcriptomic profiling to identify genes linked to milk production, the exploration of regulatory mechanisms of lipid metabolism in goat mammary epithelial cells, and the evaluation of the influence of nutritional factors on milk quality. A comprehensive understanding of these interactions is essential for enhancing breeding strategies and ensuring the sustainability of dairy goat farming. Future research should incorporate multi-omics approaches to unravel the intricate regulatory processes governing milk production and adapt practices to meet global demand while upholding economic and environmental sustainability.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Bingzhi</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Youth Innovation Team of Shaanxi Universities in Yangling Vocational and Technical College, Yangling, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Efficient Ruminant Breeding Technology of Higher Education Institutions in Shaanxi Province, Yangling, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Youth Innovation Team of Shaanxi Universities in Yangling Vocational and Technical College, Yangling, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Efficient Ruminant Breeding Technology of Higher Education Institutions in Shaanxi Province, Yangling, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tian</LastName><ForeName>Wanqiang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Youth Innovation Team of Shaanxi Universities in Yangling Vocational and Technical College, Yangling, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Efficient Ruminant Breeding Technology of Higher Education Institutions in Shaanxi Province, Yangling, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abebe</LastName><ForeName>Belete Kuraz</ForeName><Initials>BK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal Science and Technology, Northwest A&amp;F University, No.22 Xinong Road, Yangling, 712100, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raza</LastName><ForeName>Sayed Haidar Abbas</ForeName><Initials>SHA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Food Quality and Safety / Nation-Local Joint Engineering Research Center for Machining and Safety of Livestock and Poultry Products, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Hengwei</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3112-057X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal Science and Technology, Northwest A&amp;F University, No.22 Xinong Road, Yangling, 712100, Shaanxi, China. 18792427097@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Mol Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9423533</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1073-6085</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dairy goat</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Genetic factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Genomic investigations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Milk production quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Molecular pathways</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39261347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12033-024-01283-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12033-024-01283-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zeder, M. A., &amp; Hesse, B. (2000). The initial domestication of goats (Capra hircus) in the Zagros mountains 10,000 years ago. Science, 287(5461), 2254–2257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10731145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.287.5461.2254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zobel, G., Neave, H. W., &amp; Webster, J. (2019). Understanding natural behavior to improve dairy goat (Capra hircus) management systems. Translational Animal Science, 3(1), 212–224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32704793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/tas/txy145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, C. D. (2023). The role of goats in the world: Society, science, and sustainability. Small Ruminant Research, 227, 107056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2023.107056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller, B. A., &amp; Lu, C. D. (2019). Current status of global dairy goat production: An overview. Asian-Australasian Journal of Animal Sciences, 32(8), 1219–1232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31357263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6668863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5713/ajas.19.0253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong, J., Bao, J., Wenping, H., Shang, M., &amp; Zhang, L. (2022). Whole-genome resequencing reveals genetic diversity and selection characteristics of dairy goat. Frontiers in Genetics, 13, 1044017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36685859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fgene.2022.1044017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>German, J. B., Dillard, C. J., &amp; Ward, R. E. (2002). Bioactive components in milk. Current Opinion in Clinical Nutrition &amp; Metabolic Care, 5(6), 653–658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00075197-200211000-00007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evrigh, N. H., Nourouzi, Z., Vahedi, V., &amp; Benemar, H. A. (2018). Genetic association between the variation of dgat1 gene and milk production traits in khalkhali goats. Agriculture Food, 6(1), 188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, J., Wang, W., &amp; Sun, S. (2019). Research advances in reproduction for dairy goats. Asian-Australasian journal of animal sciences, 32(8 Suppl), 1284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31357269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6668861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5713/ajas.19.0486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devendra, C., &amp; Haenlein, G. (2016). Goat breeds.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, S., Yao, Z., Li, X., Zhang, Z., Liu, X., Yang, P., Chen, N., Xia, X., Lyu, S., Shi, Q., Wang, E., Baorui, R., Jiang, Y., Lei, C., Chen, H., &amp; Huang, Y. (2022). Assessing genomic diversity and signatures of selection in Pinan cattle using whole-genome sequencing data. BMC Genomics, 23(1), 460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35729510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9215082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12864-022-08645-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hengwei, Y., Zhang, K., Cheng, G., Mei, C., Wang, H., &amp; Zan, L. (2024). Genome-wide analysis reveals genomic diversity and signatures of selection in Qinchuan beef cattle. BMC Genomics, 25(1), 558.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12864-024-10482-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asadollahpour Nanaei, H., Esmailizadeh, A., Ayatollahi Mehrgardi, A., Han, J., Wu, D. D., Li, Y., &amp; Zhang, Y. P. (2020). Comparative population genomic analysis uncovers novel genomic footprints and genes associated with small body size in Chinese pony. BMC Genomics, 21(1), 496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32689947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7370493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12864-020-06887-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni, J., Xian, M., Ren, Y., Yang, L., Li, Y., Guo, S., Ran, B., &amp; Hu, J. (2024). Whole-genome resequencing reveals candidate genes associated with milk production trait in Guanzhong dairy goats. Animal Genetics, 55(1), 168–172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38093616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/age.13380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moneva, C. S. O., Sangel, P. P., Angeles, A. A., Mendioro, M. S., &amp; Vega, R. S. (2024). Prolactin gene (C576A) polymorphism is associated with milk production performance in crossbred Anglo-Nubian dairy goats. The Indian Journal of Animal Sciences, 94(5), 431–434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.56093/ijans.v94i5.139677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gündüz, Z., &amp; Biçer, O. (2023). Milk-y Way: The impact of single-nucleotide polymorphisms on milk production traits in Kilis dairy goats. Archives Animal Breeding, 66(4), 369–378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38111384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10726025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5194/aab-66-369-2023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selionova, M., Trukhachev, V., Aibazov, M., Sermyagin, A., Belous, A., Gladkikh, M., &amp; Zinovieva, N. (2024). Genome-wide association study of milk composition in karachai goats. Animals: An Open Access Journal From MDPI, 14(2), 327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38275787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani14020327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dettori, M. L., Pazzola, M., Noce, A., Landi, V., &amp; Vacca, G. M. (2023). Variations in casein genes are associated with milk protein and fat contents in Sarda goats (Capra hircus), with an important role of CSN1S2 for milk yield. Animals: an Open Access Journal From MDPI, 14(1), 56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38200787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani14010056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kravchenko, O., &amp; Karban, Y. (2023). Association of DGAT1 with goat milk and meat production traits. Scientific Messenger of LNU of Veterinary Medicine Biotechnologies. Series: Agricultural sciences, 25(99), 241–245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.32718/nvlvet-a9939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Barzinji, Y. M., &amp; Zainal, F. K. (2023). Genetic evaluation of milk production traits in local goat. Iraqi Journal of Agricultural Sciences, 54(6), 1548–1556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36103/ijas.v54i6.1855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghanatsaman, Z. A., Mehrgardi, A. A., Nanaei, H. A., &amp; Esmailizadeh, A. (2023). Comparative genomic analysis uncovers candidate genes related with milk production and adaptive traits in goat breeds. Scientific Reports, 13(1), 8722.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-35973-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scholtens, M., Lopez-Villalobos, N., Lehnert, K., Snell, R., Garrick, D., &amp; Blair, H. T. (2020). Advantage of including genomic information to predict breeding values for lactation yields of milk fat and protein or somatic cell score in. Animal: An Open Access Journal From, 11(1), 24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brzáková, M., Rychtářová, J., Čítek, J., &amp; Sztankóová, Z. (2021). A candidate gene association study for economically important traits in czech dairy goat breeds. Animals: An Open Access Journal From MDPI, 11(6), 1796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34208578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani11061796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji, Z., Chao, T., Zhang, C., Liu, Z., Hou, L., Wang, J., Wang, A., Wang, Y., Zhou, J., Xuan, R., Wang, G., &amp; Wang, J. (2019). Transcriptome analysis of dairy goat mammary gland tissues from different lactation stages. DNA and Cell Biology, 38(2), 129–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30726149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/dna.2018.4349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, C., Zhu, J., Shi, H., Luo, J., Zhao, W., Shi, H., Huifen, X., Wang, H., &amp; Loor, J. J. (2020). Comprehensive transcriptome profiling of dairy goat mammary gland identifies genes and networks crucial for lactation and fatty acid metabolism. Frontiers In Genetics, 11, 878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33101357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7545057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fgene.2020.00878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crisà, A., Ferrè, F., Chillemi, G., &amp; Moioli, B. (2016). RNA-Sequencing for profiling goat milk transcriptome in colostrum and mature milk. BMC Veterinary Research, 12(1), 264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27884183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5123407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12917-016-0881-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, L., Jiao, H., Gao, W., Huang, L., Shi, C., Zhang, F., Jiao, W., &amp; Luo, J. (2023). Fatty acid desaturation is suppressed in Mir-26a/b knockout goat mammary epithelial cells by upregulating INSIG1. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 24(12), 10028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37373175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10298109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms241210028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao, W., Luo, J., He, Q., Xia, Y., Huibin Tian, L., Zhu, C. L., &amp; Loor, J. J. (2023). Docosahexaenoic acid alters lipid metabolism processes via H3K9ac epigenetic modification in dairy goat. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 71(22), 8527–8539.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.3c01606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao, W., Luo, J., Xia, Y., An, X., Guo, P., He, Q., Tian, H., Qingyong, H., Li, C., &amp; Wang, H. (2023). Goat FADS2 controlling fatty acid metabolism is directly regulated by SREBP1 in mammary epithelial cells. Journal of Animal Science. https://doi.org/10.1093/jas/skad030</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skad030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37773415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Wang, Y., Yang, P., Han, H., Zhang, G., Huifen, X., &amp; Quan, K. (2023). Overexpression of ATGL impairs lipid droplet accumulation by accelerating lipolysis in goat mammary epithelial cells. Animal Biotechnology, 34(7), 3126–3134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36306180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10495398.2022.2136678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, W., Zhang, C., Luo, J., Huifen, X., Liu, J., Loor, J. J., &amp; Shi, H. (2022). The LXRB-SREBP1 network regulates lipogenic homeostasis by controlling the synthesis of polyunsaturated fatty acids in goat mammary epithelial cells. Journal of Animal Science and Biotechnology, 13(1), 120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36336695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9639257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40104-022-00774-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Z., Qinyue, L., Zhang, X., Zhang, Z., Cao, X., Wang, K., Xiaotan, L., Yang, Z., Loor, J. J., &amp; Jiao, P. (2022). Circ007071 inhibits unsaturated fatty acid synthesis by interacting with miR-103-5p to enhance PPARγ expression in the dairy goat mammary gland. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70(42), 13719–13729.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36222227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.2c06174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao, P., Zhang, M., Wang, Z., Liang, G., Xie, X., Zhang, Y., Chen, Z., Jiang, Q., &amp; Loor, J. J. (2022). Circ003429 regulates unsaturated fatty acid synthesis in the dairy goat mammary gland by interacting with miR-199a-3p, targeting the YAP1 gene. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 23(7), 4068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35409428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8999533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms23074068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Luo, J., Wang, H., Shi, H., Zhu, J., Sun, Y., Kang, Y., &amp; Yao, D. (2015). Adipose triglyceride lipase regulates lipid metabolism in dairy goat mammary epithelial cells. Gene, 554(1), 125–130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25307872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2014.10.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, T., Huang, J., Yi, Y., Zhang, X., Loor, J. J., Cao, Y., Shi, H., &amp; Luo, J. (2018). Akt serine/threonine kinase 1 regulates de novo fatty acid synthesis through the mammalian target of rapamycin/sterol regulatory element binding protein 1 axis in dairy goat mammary epithelial cells. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 66(5), 1197–1205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29323924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.7b05305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He, Q., Gao, L., Zhang, F., Yao, W., Jiao, W., Song, N., Luo, J., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2023). The FoxO1-ATGL axis alters milk lipolysis homeostasis through PI3K/AKT signaling pathway in dairy goat mammary epithelial cells. Journal of Animal Science. https://doi.org/10.1093/jas/skad286</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skad286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38038705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10760506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, J., Dai, B., Hexuan, Q., Zhong, Y., Ma, Y., Luo, J., Hadsell, D., &amp; Shi, H. (2020). Epidermal growth factor stimulates fatty acid synthesis mainly via PLC-γ1/Akt signaling pathway in dairy goat mammary epithelial cells. Animals: An Open Access Journal From MDPI., 10(6), 930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32481546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani10060930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao, D., Luo, J., He, Q., Shi, H., Li, J., Wang, H., Xu, H., Chen, Z., Yi, Y., &amp; Loor, J. J. (2017). SCD1 Alters Long-Chain Fatty Acid (LCFA) Composition and Its Expression Is Directly Regulated by SREBP-1 and PPARγ 1 in Dairy Goat Mammary Cells. Journal of Cellular Physiology, 232(3), 635–649.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27341271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcp.25469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, H. B., Zhang, C. H., Zhao, W., Luo, J., &amp; Loor, J. J. (2017). Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor delta facilitates lipid secretion and catabolism of fatty acids in dairy goat mammary epithelial cells. Journal of Dairy Science, 100(1), 797–806.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27865496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2016-11647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, H. B., Luo, J., Yao, D. W., Zhu, J. J., Xu, H. F., Shi, H. P., &amp; Loor, J. J. (2013). Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ stimulates the synthesis of monounsaturated fatty acids in dairy goat mammary epithelial cells via the control of stearoyl-coenzyme A desaturase. Journal of Dairy Science, 96(12), 7844–7853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24119817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2013-7105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji, Z., Liu, Z., Chao, T., Hou, L., Fan, R., He, R., Wang, G., &amp; Wang, J. (2017). Screening of miRNA profiles and construction of regulation networks in early and late lactation of dairy goat mammary glands. Scientific Reports, 7(1), 11933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28931951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5607250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-12297-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, X. Z., Luo, J., Zhang, L. P., Wang, W., Shi, H. B., &amp; Zhu, J. J. (2013). MiR-27a suppresses triglyceride accumulation and affects gene mRNA expression associated with fat metabolism in dairy goat mammary gland epithelial cells. Gene, 521(1), 15–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23537996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2013.03.050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oancea, A. G., Dragomir, C., Untea, A. E., Saracila, M., Cismileanu, A. E., Vlaicu, P. A., &amp; Varzaru, I. (2024). The effects of flax and mustard seed inclusion in dairy goats’ diet on milk nutritional quality. Agriculture, 14(7), 1009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agriculture14071009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd Rahman, M. R., Hassan, Z., Hassan, M. S., Hashim, R., Shing, W. L., &amp; Jaafar, S. H. S. (2022). Multi-nutrient milk quality analysis applying chemometrics: a supplementation-based approach using dairy goats. Journal of Advanced Research in Applied Sciences Engineering Technology, 28(3), 123–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.37934/araset.28.3.123143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laurent, H., Caillat, C. L., Girard, A., Ferlay, S., Laverroux, J., &amp; Jost, B. (2023). Graulet Impacts of production conditions on goat milk vitamin, carotenoid contents and colour indices. Animal: An International Journal of Animal Bioscience, 17(1), 100683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36610084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.animal.2022.100683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Si, W., Zhang, Y., Li, X., Du, Y., &amp; Xu, Q. (2021). Understanding the functional activity of polyphenols using omics-based approaches. Nutrients, 13(11), 3953.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34836207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8625961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13113953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadri, H., et al. (2017). Antioxidant effects of biochanin A in streptozotocin induced diabetic rats. Brazilian Archives of Biology Technology, 60, e17160741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1678-4324-2017160741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, Q., Li, Y., Du, W., Zheng, N., Wang, J., &amp; Zhao, S. (2023). Effect of dietary biochanin A on lactation performance, antioxidant capacity, rumen fermentation and rumen microbiome of dairy goat. Frontiers in Microbiology, 14, 1101849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36814572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9939525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1101849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas-Bello-Pérez, E., Pedersen, N. C., Khushvakov, J., Ye, Y., Dhakal, R., Hansen, H. H., Ahrné, L., &amp; Khakimov, B. (2022). Effect of supplementing dairy goat diets with rapeseed oil or sunflower oil on performance, milk composition, milk fatty acid profile, and in vitro fermentation kinetics. Frontiers in Veterinary Science, 9, 899314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35782564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9244143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.899314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapetti, L., Colombini, S., Battelli, G., Castiglioni, B., Turri, F., Galassi, G., Battelli, M., &amp; Crovetto, G. M. (2021). Effect of linseeds and hemp seeds on milk production, energy and nitrogen balance, and methane emissions in the dairy goat. Animals: An Open Access Journal From MDPI, 11(9), 2717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34573683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani11092717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa, R. G., Freire, R. M. B., de Araújo, G. G. L., Queiroga, R. D. C. R. D. E., Paiva, G. N., Ribeiro, N. L., Oliveira, R. L. D., Domínguez, R., &amp; Lorenzo, J. M. (2021). Effect of increased salt water intake on the production and composition of dairy goat milk. Animals: An Open Access Journal From MDPI, 11(9), 2642.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34573608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani11092642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>