<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39265811</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-1208</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>196</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbial pathogenesis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microb Pathog</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Immune and microbiome modulatory effects of Limosilactobacillus fermentum NCDC 400 in an immunocompromised mouse model.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>106927</StartPage><MedlinePgn>106927</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.106927</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0882-4010(24)00394-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The present study was aimed to assess and validate the safety and functional efficacy of an indigenous probiotic strain Limosilactobacillus fermentum NCDC 400 (hereafter, LFN400) in an immunocompromised murine model. The study included four groups; a normal control (NC) group without immune suppression; an experimental model control (MC) with immune suppression induced via intraperitoneal cyclophosphamide (Cy) administration; and two MC groups orally administered with either low dose (LD) or high dose (HD) of LFN400 at dose 10<sup>8</sup> and 10<sup>10</sup> CFU/mouse/day, respectively, for 15-days. Both control groups received normal saline as placebo control. LFN400 improved specific experimental characteristics including hematological and serum biochemical markers. Compared to MC group, LFN400-fed groups showed markedly (P &lt; 0.05) decreased arrays of detrimental caecal enzymes. We did not observe instances of bacterial translocation of LFN400 from gut to bloodstream or extra-intestinal organs. LFN400 intake significantly (P &lt; 0.05) enhanced spleen cell differentiation, immune and oxidative stress markers, and restored Cy-induced histopathological changes in multiple tissues, including the spleen. There was no genotoxic effect of LFN400 on bone marrow cells. Although not statistically significant, LFN400 feeding moderately increased gut microbiome diversity, supporting the growth of beneficial saccharolytic microorganisms and reducing the presence of pathobionts. The findings demonstrate that the probiotic strain LFN400 possesses in vivo safety and immunomodulatory potency and thus should be considered a potential candidate for future human clinical studies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nataraj</LastName><ForeName>Basavaprabhu Haranahalli</ForeName><Initials>BH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Techno-functional Starter Lab, National Collection of Dairy Cultures (NCDC), Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-National Dairy Research Institute, Karnal, 132001, Haryana, India; Dairy Bacteriology Section, Southern Regional Station (SRS), ICAR-National Dairy Research Institute, Adugodi, Bengaluru, 560 030, Karnataka, India. Electronic address: basavaprabhu73@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ranveer</LastName><ForeName>Soniya A</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Techno-functional Starter Lab, National Collection of Dairy Cultures (NCDC), Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-National Dairy Research Institute, Karnal, 132001, Haryana, India. Electronic address: soniyaranveer11@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>K</LastName><ForeName>Jeevan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Regional Ayurveda Research Institute, Central Council for Research in Ayurvedic Sciences, Aamkho, Gwalior, 474009, Madhya Pradesh, India. Electronic address: jeevank1116@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nagpal</LastName><ForeName>Ravinder</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Gut Biome Lab, Department of Health, Nutrition, and Food Sciences, Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL, 32306, USA. Electronic address: nagpal511@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Behare</LastName><ForeName>Pradip V</ForeName><Initials>PV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Techno-functional Starter Lab, National Collection of Dairy Cultures (NCDC), Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-National Dairy Research Institute, Karnal, 132001, Haryana, India. Electronic address: pradip.behare@icar.gov.in.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Microb Pathog</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8606191</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0882-4010</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">16S rRNA metagenomic analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cyclophosphamide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Genotoxicity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gut microbiome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immunocompromised</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Probiotics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Safety evaluation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they do not have any conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39265811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.106927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0882-4010(24)00394-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>