<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39269638</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1678-4405</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Brazilian journal of microbiology : [publication of the Brazilian Society for Microbiology]</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Braz J Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Characterization of toxigenic genes of Bacillus cereus strains isolated from different spices sold in Algeria.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s42770-024-01514-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Many cooked foods are prepared with spices and dried herbs; these can be contaminated by several types of microorganisms, including aerobic spore-forming bacteria. The Bacillus cereus group is very widespread in nature and is known among the common food contaminants. They are involved in food poisoning, causing two types of syndromes, diarrheal and emetic. The aims of the present work were to determine the prevalence of toxigenic Bacillus cereus spores in spices and herbs marketed in the Laghouat area and to identify their toxigenic genes via PCR. Among the 191 samples, 14.13% were determined to be B. cereus, with concentrations ranging from 2.52 to 5.82 log cfu/g, where the highest level of contamination was observed in allspice and ginger. Moreover, entFM (100%), nhe (88.23%) and cytK (70.58%) were the most frequently identified toxin genes, whereas hbl (23.52%) was less common, and no emetic toxin-encoding gene (cesB) was found in any of the samples. Considering the results of the present study, the B. cereus microbial load and toxin gene profiles of spices show that spices have potential for public health in Algeria. In this context, it is crucial to guarantee the microbiological safety of spices by respecting good hygiene practices, eliminating bacterial spores and toxin production via sterilization and using appropriate packaging for these products.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s) under exclusive licence to Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madouri</LastName><ForeName>Redhwane</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Biological and Agronomic Sciences, Université Amar Telidji de Laghouat, BP 37G, Route de Ghardaïa, Laghouat, 03000, Algeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ziane</LastName><ForeName>Mohammed</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1370-7104</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Département de Biologie, Facultés des sciences et Technologie, Université de Ain Témouchent, route de Sidi bel abbès, N101, Ain Temouchent, 46000, Algérie. mohamed.ziane@univ-temouchent.edu.dz.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Benaceur</LastName><ForeName>Farouk</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Biological and Agronomic Sciences, Université Amar Telidji de Laghouat, BP 37G, Route de Ghardaïa, Laghouat, 03000, Algeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cufaoglu</LastName><ForeName>Gizem</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Hygiene and Technology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Kirikkale University, Yahsihan,, 71450, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Brazil</Country><MedlineTA>Braz J Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101095924</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1517-8382</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacillus cereus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food poisoning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spices</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Toxin genes</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39269638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42770-024-01514-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s42770-024-01514-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Cufaoglu G, Ayaz ND (2022) Potential risk of Bacillus cereus in spices in Turkey. Food Control 132:1–6. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108570</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peter K (2001) Handbook of herbs and spices. Published by Woodhead Publishing Limited. pp332</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peter K (2004) Handbook of herbs and spices. woodhead pub.2. pp 374</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurtler JB, Keller SE, Kornacki JL, Bassam A, Annous BA, Jin T, Fan X (2019) Challenges in recovering Foodborne pathogens from Low-Water-Activity foods. J Food Prot 82(6):988–996. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-18-204</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-18-204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31121101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO/WHO (2014) Ranking of low moisture foods in support of microbiological risk management - preliminary Report (Part I - Main Report)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (2005) Opinion of the Scientific Panel on biological hazards on Bacillus cereus and other Bacillus spp in food stuffs. EFSA J 175:1–48. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2005.175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2005.175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (2016) Risks for public health related to the presence of Bacillus cereus and other Bacillus spp. Including Bacillus thuringiensis in food stuffs. EFSA J 14(7):4524. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2016.4524</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stenfors-Arnesen P, fagerlund A, Granum PE (2008) From soil to gut: Bacillus cereus and its food poisoning toxins. FEMS Microbiol Rev 32:579–606. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6976.2008.00112.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2008.00112.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18422617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park YB, Kim JB, Shin SW, Kim JC, Cho SH, Lee BK, Ahn J, Kim JM, Oh DH (2009) Prevalence, genetic diversity, and antibiotic susceptibility of Bacillus cereus strains isolated from rice and cereals collected in Korea. J Food Prot 72:612–617. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028x-72.3.612</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028x-72.3.612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19343952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter l, Chase HR, Gieseker CM, Hasbrouck NR, Stine CB, Khan A, Ewing-peeples lJ, Tall BD, Gopinath GR (2018) Analysis of enterotoxigenic Bacillus cereus strains from dried foods using whole-genome sequencing, multilocus sequence analysis and toxin gene prevalence and distribution using endpoint PCR analysis. Int J Food Microbiol 284:31–39. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.06.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.06.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29990637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berthold-Pluta A, Pluta A, Garbowska M, Stefanska I, Pluta B (2019) Prevalence and toxicity characterization of Bacillus cereus in food products from Poland. Foods 8:269. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods8070269</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods8070269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31331094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6678163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghelardi E, Celandroni F, Salvetti S, Barsotti C, Baggiani A, Senesi S (2002) Identification and characterization of toxigenic Bacillus cereus isolates responsible for two food-poisoning outbreaks. FEMS Microbiol Lett 28(1):129–134. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6968.2002.tb11072.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2002.tb11072.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackburn CD, McClure PJ (2009) Pathogenic Bacillus species, 2nd edn. Hazards, Risk Analysis and Control, Foodborne Pathogens, p 176</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumari S, Sarkar PK (2016) Bacillus cereus hazard and control in industrial dairy processing environment. Food Control 69:20–29. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.04.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.04.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheldeman P, Herman L, Foster S, Heyndrickx M (2006) Bacillus sporothermodurans and other highly heat-resistant sporeformers in milk. J Appl Microbiol 101:542–555. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2672.2006.02964.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2006.02964.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16907805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esteban MDJ, Huertas P, Fernandez PS, Palop A (2013) Effect of the medium characteristics and the heating and cooling rates on the nonisothermal heat resistance of Bacillus sporothermodurans IC4 spores. Food Microbiol 34:158–163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2012.11.020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2012.11.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23498193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlin F, Nguyen-The C (2013) Pathogen update: Bacillus species. In J. Sofos (Vol. Ed.), Advances in microbial food safety: Vol. 1, (pp. 70–96). Cambridge: Woodhead Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1533/9780857098740.2.70</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carroll LM, Kovac J, Miller RA, Wiedmann M (2017) Rapid, high-throughput identification of anthrax-causing and emetic Bacillus cereus Group genome assemblies via B typer, a computational tool for virulence-based classification of Bacillus cereus Group isolates by using nucleotide sequencing data. Appl Environ Microbiol 83:e01096–e01017. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.01096-17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01096-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28625989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5561296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fogele B, Granta R, Valcina O, Berzinˇs A (2017) Occurrence and diversity of Bacillus cereus and molds in spices and herbs. Food Control 83:69–74. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.05.038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.05.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frentzel H, Kraushaar B, Krause G, Bodi D, Wichmann-Schauer H, Appel B, Mader A (2018) Phylogenetic and toxinogenic characteristics of Bacillus cereus group members isolated from spices and herbs. Food Control 83:90–98. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.12.022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.12.022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hariram U, Labb´e R (2015) Spore prevalence and toxigenicity of Bacillus cereus and Bacillus thuringiensis isolates from U.S. retail spices. J Food Prot 78:590–596. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-14-380</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-14-380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25719886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fagerlund A, Brillard J, Fürst R, Guinebretière MH, Granum PE (2007) Toxin production in a rare and genetically remote cluster of strains of the Bacillus cereus group. BMC Microbiol 7:43. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2180-7-43</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-7-43</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17517121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">1888693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jovanovic J, Ornelis VFM, Madder A, Rajkovic A (2021) Bacillus cereus food intoxication and toxicoinfection. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 20(4):3719–3761. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541-4337.12785</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34160120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interministerial decree of 2 Moharram 1438 corresponding to October 4, 2016 setting the microbiological criteria for food stuffs. J.O.R.A.D.P 39: 11–32. https://www.joradp.dz/FTP/JO-FRANCAIS/2017/F2017039.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziane M, Leguerinel I, Membré JM (2019) A quantitative microbiological exposure assessment of Bacillus cereus group IV in Couscous Semolina, Algeria. Microb Risk Anal 11:11–22. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mran.2018.07.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mran.2018.07.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 7932: (2004) Microbiology of Food and Animal Feeding Stuffs—Horizontal Method for the Enumeration of Presumptive Bacillus cereus—Colony-Count Technique at 30°C. Available online: http://www.iso.org/iso/catalogue_detail.htm?csnumber=382192004 (accessed on 12janury 2021)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RinttilA T, Lyra A, Krogius-Kurikka L, Palva A (2011) Real-time PCR analysis of enteric pathogens from fecal samples of irritable bowel syndrome subjects. Gut Pat 3(1):6. https://doi.org/10.1186%2F1757-4749-3-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1757-4749-3-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei S, Chelliah R, Park BJ, Kim SH, Forghani F, Cho M (2019) Differentiation of Bacillus thuringiensis from Bacillus cereus group using a unique marker based on real-time PCR. Front Microbiol 10:883. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.00883</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31114555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6503103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baghbadorani ST, Rahimi E, Shakerian A (2023) Investigation of virulence and antibiotic-resistance of Bacillus cereus isolated from various spices. Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol 2023:1–6. https://doi.org/10.1155/2023/8390778</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2023/8390778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çetin E, Yaman G, Yıbar A (2021) Investigation of Toxin-Producing and antibiotic-resistant Bacillus cereus in spices used in the production of Sucuk. Eur J Sci Tech 31(1):331–340</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hampikyan H, Bingol EB, Colak H, Aydin A (2009) The evaluation of microbiological profile of some spices used in Turkish meat industry. J Food Agric Environ 7:111–115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heini N, Stephan R, Ehling-Schulz M, Johler S (2018) Characterization of Bacillus cereus group isolates from powdered food products. Int J Food Microbiol 283:59–64. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.06.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.06.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30099996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jessberger N, Kranzler M, Da Riol C, Schwenk V, Buchacher T, Dietrich R, Ehling-Schulz M, Martlbauer E (2019) Assessing the toxic potential of enteropathogenic Bacillus cereus. Food Microbiol 84:103276. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2019.103276</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2019.103276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31421762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lind T, Fagerlund A, Rodland MS, Granum PE (2004) Characterization of the Bacillus cereus nhe enterotoxin. Microbiol 150:3959–3967. https://doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.27359-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27359-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guinebretière MH, Broussolle V, Nguyen-The C (2002) Enterotoxigenic profiles of food-poisoning and foodborne Bacillus cereus strains. J Clin Microbiol 40(8):3053–3056. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.40.8.3053-3056.2002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.40.8.3053-3056.2002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12149378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">120679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang IC, Shih DYC, Huang TP, Huang YP, Wang JY, Guinebretiere MH (2005) Establishment of a novel multiplex PCR assay and detection of toxigenic strains of the species in the Bacillus cereus group. J Food Prot 68(10):2123–2130. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028x-68.10.2123</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028x-68.10.2123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16245717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fagerlund A, Ween O, Lund T, Hardy S (2004) Genetic and functional analysis of the cytK family of genes in Bacillus cereus. Microbiol 150:2689–2697. https://doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.26975-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/mic.0.26975-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lund T, De Buyser ML, Granum PE (2000) A new cytotoxin from Bacillus cereus that may cause necrotic enteritis. Mol Microbiol 38:254–261. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2958.2000.02147.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2000.02147.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11069652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chica JS (2020) Genomic and toxigenic heterogeneity of Bacillus cereus sensu lato isolated from ready-to-eat foods and powdered milk in day care centers in Colombia. Foodborne Pathog Dis 17(5):340–347. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2019.2709 . Correa MM, Diez AE, Rasschaert G, Heyndrickx M</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/fpd.2019.2709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samapundo S, Heyndrickx M, Xhaferi R, Devlieghere F (2011) Incidence, diversity and toxin gene characteristics of Bacillus cereus group strains isolated from food products marketed in Belgium. Int J Food Microbiol 150:34–41. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2011.07.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2011.07.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21840614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngamwongsatit P, Buasri W, Pianariyanon P, Pulsrikarn C, Ohba M, Assavanig A, Watanalai Panbangred W (2008) Broad distribution of enterotoxin genes (hblCDA, nheABC, cytK, and entFM) among Bacillus thuringiensis and Bacillus cereus as shown by novel primers. Int J Food Microbiol 121(3):352–356. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2007.11.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2007.11.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18068844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceuppens S, Rajkovic A, Heyndrickx M, Tsilia V, Wiele TVD, Boon N, Uyttendaele M (2011) Regulation of toxin production by Bacillus cereus and its food safety implications. Crit Rev Microbiol 37:188–213. https://doi.org/10.3109/1040841X.2011.558832</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/1040841X.2011.558832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21417966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granum, Lindback</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffiths MW, Schraft H (2017) Bacillus cereus food poisoning. Foodborne diseases: Dodd, 3rd edn. Elsevier Inc, pp 395–405. C., Aldsworth, T., Stein</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forghani F, Kim JB, Oh DH (2014) Enterotoxigenic profiling of emetic toxin-and enterotoxin-producing Bacillus cereus, isolated from food, environmental, and clinical samples by multiplex PCR. J Food Sci 79(11):2288–2293. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750-3841.12666</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.12666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Feng L, Xu H, Liu C, Shah NP, Wei H (2014) Detection of viable enterotoxin-producing Bacillus cereus and analysis of toxigenicity from ready-to-eat foods and infant formula milk powder by multiplex PCR. J Dairy Sci 99:1047–1055. https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.2015-10147</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2015-10147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>