<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39268189</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1664-042X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in physiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Physiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis lameness in broiler chickens and its implications for welfare, meat safety, and quality: a review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1452318</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1452318</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1452318</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fphys.2024.1452318</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The exponential increase in global population continues to present an ongoing challenge for livestock producers worldwide to consistently provide a safe, high-quality, and affordable source of protein for consumers. In the last 50 years, the poultry industry has spearheaded this effort thanks to focused genetic and genomic selection for feed-efficient, high-yielding broilers. However, such intense selection for productive traits, along with conventional industry farming practices, has also presented the industry with a myriad of serious issues that negatively impacted animal health, welfare, and productivity-such as woody breast and virulent diseases commonly associated with poultry farming. Bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis (BCO) lameness is one such issue, having rapidly become a key issue affecting the poultry industry with serious impacts on broiler welfare, meat quality, production, food safety, and economic losses since its discovery in 1972. This review focuses on hallmark clinical symptoms, diagnosis, etiology, and impact of BCO lameness on key issues facing the poultry industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Anthney, Do and Alrubaye.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Anthney</LastName><ForeName>Amanda</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence for Poultry Science, University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, AR, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Do</LastName><ForeName>Anh Dang Trieu</ForeName><Initials>ADT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence for Poultry Science, University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, AR, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cell and Molecular Biology Program, University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, AR, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alrubaye</LastName><ForeName>Adnan A K</ForeName><Initials>AAK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence for Poultry Science, University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, AR, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cell and Molecular Biology Program, University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, AR, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Physiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101549006</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1664-042X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">animal welfare</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lameness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meat quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poultry</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39268189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11390708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphys.2024.1452318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1452318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adell E., Calvet S., Pérez-Bonilla A., Jiménez-Belenguer A., García J., Herrera J., et al. (2015). Air disinfection in laying hen houses: effect on airborne microorganisms with focus on Mycoplasma gallisepticum. Biosyst. Eng. 129, 315–323. 10.1016/j.biosystemseng.2014.10.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biosystemseng.2014.10.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adnan Yousaf S. T., Kumar LOOKESH, Rahman SAIF.-U. R., Channo ABDULLAH, Panhwar MUHAMMAD IBRAHIM, Soomro A. L. I. G. U. L., et al. (2021). A review study on legs lameness and weaknesses assessment methods in commercial broiler farming in Pakistan. Biomed. J. Sci. and Tech. Res. 40. 10.26717/bjstr.2021.40.006433</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26717/bjstr.2021.40.006433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alharbi K., Asnayanti A., Do A. D. T., Perera R., AL-Mitib L., Shwani A., et al. (2024a). Identifying dietary timing of organic trace minerals to reduce the incidence of osteomyelitis lameness in broiler chickens using the aerosol transmission model. Animals 14, 1526. 10.3390/ani14111526</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani14111526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11171233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38891572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alharbi K., Ekesi N., Hasan A., Asnayanti A., Liu J., Murugesan R., et al. (2024b). Deoxynivalenol and fumonisin predispose broilers to bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis lameness. Poult. Sci. 103, 103598. 10.1016/j.psj.2024.103598</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2024.103598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10951539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38489885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AL-Rubaye A. A. K., Couger M. B., Ojha S., Pummill J. F., Koon J. A., Wideman R. F., et al. (2015). Genome analysis of Staphylococcus agnetis, an agent of lameness in broiler chickens. PLOS ONE 10, e0143336. 10.1371/journal.pone.0143336</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0143336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4659636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26606420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alrubaye A. A. K., Ekesi N. S., Hasan A., Elkins E., Ojha S., Zaki S., et al. (2020). Chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis in broilers: further defining lameness-inducing models with wire or litter flooring to evaluate protection with organic trace minerals. Poult. Sci. 99, 5422–5429. 10.1016/j.psj.2020.08.027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2020.08.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7647863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33142459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AL-Rubaye A. A. K., Ekesi N. S., Zaki S., Emami N. K., Wideman R. F., Rhoads D. D. (2017). Chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis in broilers: further defining a bacterial challenge model using the wire flooring model. Poult. Sci. 96, 332–340. 10.3382/ps/pew299</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pew299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27587724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antunes P., Mourão J., Campos J., Peixe L. (2016). Salmonellosis: the role of poultry meat. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 22, 110–121. 10.1016/j.cmi.2015.12.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2015.12.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26708671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>APHIS (2022). in HPAI response - response goals and depopulation policy. Editor AGRICULTURE U. S. D. O. (United States: USDA; ).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Applegate T. J., Lilburn M. S. (2002). Growth of the femur and tibia of a commercial broiler line. Poult. Sci. 81, 1289–1294. 10.1093/ps/81.9.1289</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/81.9.1289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12269606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asnayanti A., Alharbi K., Do A. D. T., AL-Mitib L., Bühler K., VAN Der Klis J. D., et al. (2024a). Early 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3-glycosides supplementation: an efficient feeding strategy against bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis lameness in broilers assessed by using an aerosol transmission model. J. Appl. Poult. Res. 33, 100440. 10.1016/j.japr.2024.100440</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.japr.2024.100440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asnayanti A., Do A. D. T., Alharbi K., Alrubaye A. (2024b). Inducing experimental bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis lameness in broiler chickens using aerosol transmission model. Poult. Sci. 103, 103460. 10.1016/j.psj.2024.103460</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2024.103460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10846381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38301493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asnayanti A., Hasan A., Alharbi K., Hassan I., Bottje W., Rochell S. J., et al. (2024c). Assessing the impact of Spirulina platensis and organic trace minerals on the incidence of bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis lameness in broilers using an aerosol transmission model. J. Appl. Poult. Res. 33, 100426. 10.1016/j.japr.2024.100426</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.japr.2024.100426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AVIAGEN INC (2022). Ross 708 broiler performance objectives - 2022. Management Handbook. United States.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellairs R., Osmond M. (2005). Atlas of chick development. Elsevier Science and Technology Books.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berg C. (2004). Pododermatitis and hock burn in broiler chickens. Measuring and auditing broiler welfare . Wallingford UK: CABI publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biesek J., Banaszak M., Kądziołka K., Wlaźlak S., Adamski M. (2022). Growth of broiler chickens, and physical features of the digestive system, and leg bones after aluminosilicates used. Sci. Rep. 12, 20425. 10.1038/s41598-022-25003-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-25003-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9702739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36443386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilgili S., Hess J. (2008). Green muscle disease. Reducing incidence broiler flock. Ross Tech 8, 3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BIOSECURITY NOVA SCOTIA (2020). Tips for "all in/all out" production. Canada.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boerboom G., VAN Kempen T., Navarro-Villa A., Pérez-Bonilla A. (2018). Unraveling the cause of white striping in broilers using metabolomics. Poult. Sci. 97, 3977–3986. 10.3382/ps/pey266</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pey266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6162359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29931266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borst L. B., Suyemoto M. M., Sarsour A. H., Harris M. C., Martin M. P., Strickland J. D., et al. (2017). Pathogenesis of enterococcal spondylitis caused by Enterococcus cecorum in broiler chickens. Veterinary Pathol. 54, 61–73. 10.1177/0300985816658098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0300985816658098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27511310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borst L. B., Suyemoto M. M., Scholl E. H., Fuller F. J., Barnes H. J. (2015). Comparative genomic analysis identifies divergent genomic features of pathogenic Enterococcus cecorum including a type IC CRISPR-cas system, a capsule locus, an epa-like locus, and putative host tissue binding proteins. PLOS ONE 10, e0121294. 10.1371/journal.pone.0121294</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4393107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25860249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bortolaia V., Espinosa-Gongora C., Guardabassi L. (2016). Human health risks associated with antimicrobial-resistant enterococci and Staphylococcus aureus on poultry meat. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 22, 130–140. 10.1016/j.cmi.2015.12.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2015.12.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26706616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bos J. M., VAN Den Belt H., Feindt P. H. (2018). Animal welfare, consumer welfare, and competition law: the Dutch debate on the Chicken of Tomorrow. Anim. Front. 8, 20–26. 10.1093/af/vfx001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/af/vfx001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6951831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32002211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottje W. G., Wang S., Kelly F. J., Dunster C., Williams A., Mudway I. (1998). Antioxidant defenses in lung lining fluid of broilers: impact of poor ventilation conditions. Poult. Sci. 77, 516–522. 10.1093/ps/77.4.516</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/77.4.516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9565232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradshaw R., Kirkden R., Broom D. (2002). A review of the aetiology and pathology of leg weakness in broilers in relation to welfare. Avian Poult. Biol. Rev. 13, 45–103. 10.3184/147020602783698421</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3184/147020602783698421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braga J. F. V., Silva C. C., Teixeira M. D. P. F., Martins N. R. D. S., Ecco R. (2016). Vertebral osteomyelitis associated with single and mixed bacterial infection in broilers. Avian Pathol. 45, 640–648. 10.1080/03079457.2016.1193843</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2016.1193843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27315453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Brothers D. (2022). New farmer’s Guide to the commercial broiler industry: poultry husbandry and biosecurity basics. Ala. Coop. Ext. Syst.
Available at: https://www.aces.edu/blog/topics/farm-management/new-farmers-guide-to-the-commercial-broiler-industry-poultry-husbandry-biosecurity-basics/(Accessed June 10, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buijs S., Keeling L., Rettenbacher S., VAN Poucke E., Tuyttens F. A. M. (2009). Stocking density effects on broiler welfare: identifying sensitive ranges for different indicators. Poult. Sci. 88, 1536–1543. 10.3382/ps.2009-00007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2009-00007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19590066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caldas-Cueva J. P., Owens C. M. (2020). A review on the woody breast condition, detection methods, and product utilization in the contemporary poultry industry. J. Animal Sci. 98, skaa207. 10.1093/jas/skaa207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skaa207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7419734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32783056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carnaghan R. (1966). Spinal cord compression in fowls due to spondylitis caused by Staphylococcus Pyogenes. J. Comp. Pathol. 76, 9–14. 10.1016/0021-9975(66)90042-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0021-9975(66)90042-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5907819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro F. L. S., Chai L., Arango J., Owens C. M., Smith P. A., Reichelt S., et al. (2023). Poultry industry paradigms: connecting the dots. J. Appl. Poult. Res. 32, 100310. 10.1016/j.japr.2022.100310</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.japr.2022.100310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L. R., Suyemoto M. M., Sarsour A. H., Cordova H. A., Oviedo-Rondón E. O., Barnes H. J., et al. (2018). Prevalence and severity of osteochondrosis of the free thoracic vertebra in three modern broiler strains and the Athens Canadian Random Bred control broiler. Avian Pathol. 47, 152–160. 10.1080/03079457.2017.1388499</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2017.1388499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28975826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choppa V. S. R., Kim W. K. (2023). A review on pathophysiology, and molecular mechanisms of bacterial chondronecrosis and osteomyelitis in commercial broilers. Biomolecules 13, 1032. 10.3390/biom13071032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biom13071032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10377700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37509068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COBB-VANTRESS INC (2022). Cobb500 broiler Performance and Nutrition Supplement. United States.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook M. E. (2000). Skeletal deformities and their causes: introduction. Poult. Sci. 79, 982–984. 10.1093/ps/79.7.982</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/79.7.982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10901198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox N. A., Stern N. J., Hiett K. L., Berrang M. E. (2002). Identification of a new source of Campylobacter contamination in poultry: transmission from breeder hens to broiler chickens. Avian Dis. 46, 535–541. 10.1637/0005-2086(2002)046[0535:IOANSO]2.0.CO;2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1637/0005-2086(2002)046[0535:IOANSO]2.0.CO;2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12243515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damaziak K., Charuta A., Niemiec J., Tatara M. R., Krupski W., Gozdowski D., et al. (2019). Femur and tibia development in meat-type chickens with different growth potential for 56 days of rearing period. Poult. Sci. 98, 7063–7075. 10.3382/ps/pez445</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pez445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8914001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31399733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daum R. S., Davis W. H., Farris K. B., Campeau R. J., Mulvihill D. M., Shane S. M. (1990). A model of Staphylococcus aureus bacteremia, septic arthritis, and osteomyelitis in chickens. J. Orthop. Res. 8, 804–813. 10.1002/jor.1100080605</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jor.1100080605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2213337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Meyer F., Eeckhaut V., Ducatelle R., Dhaenens M., Daled S., Dedeurwaerder A., et al. (2019). Host intestinal biomarker identification in a gut leakage model in broilers. Veterinary Res. 50, 46. 10.1186/s13567-019-0663-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13567-019-0663-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6582533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31215487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Mauro A., Neu J., Riezzo G., Raimondi F., Martinelli D., Francavilla R., et al. (2013). Gastrointestinal function development and microbiota. Italian J. Pediatr. 39, 15. 10.1186/1824-7288-39-15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1824-7288-39-15</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3615966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23433508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinev I. (2009). Clinical and morphological investigations on the prevalence of lameness associated with femoral head necrosis in broilers. Br. Poult. Sci. 50, 284–290. 10.1080/00071660902942783</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00071660902942783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19637027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinev I. (2012). Pathomorphological investigations on the incidence of clinical spondylolisthesis (kinky back) in different commercial broiler strains. Rev. médecine vétérinaire 163, 511–515. 10.2141/jpsa.0120144</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2141/jpsa.0120144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinev I. (2014). Axial skeleton pathology in broiler chickens. World's Poult. Sci. J. 70, 303–308. 10.1017/s0043933914000312</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0043933914000312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Do A. D. T., Anthney A., Alharbi K., Asnayanti A., Meuter A., Alrubaye A. A. K. (2024). Assessing the impact of spraying an Enterococcus faecium-based probiotic on day-old broiler chicks at hatch on the incidence of bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis lameness using a Staphylococcus challenge model. Animals 14, 1369. 10.3390/ani14091369</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani14091369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11083080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38731373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ducatelle R., Goossens E., Eeckhaut V., VAN Immerseel F. (2023). Poultry gut health and beyond. Anim. Nutr. 13, 240–248. 10.1016/j.aninu.2023.03.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2023.03.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10164775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37168453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duff S. R. I. (1990). Do different forms of spondylolisthesis occur in broiler fowls? Avian Pathol. 19, 279–294. 10.1080/03079459008418680</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079459008418680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18679938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunnam G., Thornton J. K., Pulido-Landinez M. (2023). Characterization of an emerging Enterococcus cecorum outbreak causing severe systemic disease with concurrent leg problems in a broiler integrator in the southern United States. Avian Dis. 67, 137–144. 10.1637/aviandiseases-D-22-00085</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1637/aviandiseases-D-22-00085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37556292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (2012). European Food Safety Authority Panel on Animal Health and Welfare (AHAW): scientific opinion on the use of animal-based measures to assess welfare of broilers. EFSA J. 10, 2774. 10.2903/j.efsa.2012.2774</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2012.2774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekesi N. S., Dolka B., Alrubaye A. A. K., Rhoads D. D. (2021). Analysis of genomes of bacterial isolates from lameness outbreaks in broilers. Poult. Sci. 100, 101148. 10.1016/j.psj.2021.101148</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8173297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34077848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elliott K. E. C., Branton S. L., Evans J. D., Peebles E. D. (2019). Occurrence of horizontal transmission in layer chickens after administration of an in ovo strain F Mycoplasma gallisepticum vaccine1,2,3. Poult. Sci. 98, 4492–4497. 10.3382/ps/pez306</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pez306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31180119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emslie K. R., Nade S. (1983). Acute hematogenous staphylococcal osteomyelitis. A description of the natural history in an avian model. Am. J. Pathol. 110, 333–345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1916166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6829712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estes S., Edgar L. D. (2013). Consumer perceptions of poultry production in Arkansas: perceptions analysis. Discov. Student J. Dale Bump. Coll. ofs Agric. Food Life Sci. 14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Favati A., Leimar O., Løvlie H. (2014a). Personality predicts social dominance in male domestic fowl. PLoS One 9, e103535. 10.1371/journal.pone.0103535</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4114777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25072296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Favati A., Leimar O., Radesäter T., Løvlie H. (2014b). Social status and personality: stability in social state can promote consistency of behavioural responses. Proc. Biol. Sci. 281, 20132531. 10.1098/rspb.2013.2531</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rspb.2013.2531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3843839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24225462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferver A., Greene E., Wideman R., Dridi S. (2021). Evidence of mitochondrial dysfunction in bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis–affected broilers. Front. Veterinary Sci. 8, 640901. 10.3389/fvets.2021.640901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.640901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7902039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33634182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giampietro-Ganeco A., Fidelis H. D. A., Cavalcanti E. N., Mello J. L. M., Borba H., De Souza R. A., et al. (2022). Research Note: quality parameters of Turkey hens breast fillets detected in processing plant with deep pectoral myopathy and white striping anomaly. Poult. Sci. 101, 101709. 10.1016/j.psj.2022.101709</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2022.101709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8819116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35124445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gifford C. A., Holland B. P., Mills R. L., Maxwell C. L., Farney J. K., Terrill S. J., et al. (2012). Growth and Development Symposium: impacts of inflammation on cattle growth and carcass merit. J. Animal Sci. 90, 1438–1451. 10.2527/jas.2011-4846</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2527/jas.2011-4846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22573836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Cerón F., Rekaya R., Aggrey S. E. (2015). Genetic analysis of bone quality traits and growth in a random mating broiler population. Poult. Sci. 94, 883–889. 10.3382/ps/pev056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pev056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25784765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granquist E. G., Vasdal G., De Jong I. C., Moe R. O. (2019). Lameness and its relationship with health and production measures in broiler chickens. Animal 13, 2365–2372. 10.1017/S1751731119000466</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1751731119000466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6749567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30894238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene E. S., Ramser A., Wideman R., Bedford M., Dridi S. (2024). Dietary inclusion of phytase and stimbiotic decreases mortality and lameness in a wire ramp challenge model in broilers. Avian Pathol. 53, 1–18. 10.1080/03079457.2024.2359592</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2024.2359592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38776101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haynes J. S. (2023). Pathology of the bones and joints. Atlas Veterinary Surg. Pathology, 59–89. 10.1002/9781119261254.ch2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/9781119261254.ch2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herdt P., Defoort P., Steelant J., Swam H., Tanghe L., Goethem S., et al. (2009). Enterococcus cecorum osteomyelitis and arthritis in broiler chickens. Vlaams Diergeneeskd. Tijdschr. 78, 44–48. 10.21825/vdt.87495</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21825/vdt.87495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heyndrickx M., Vandekerchove D., Herman L., Rollier I., Grijspeerdt K., De Zutter L. (2002). Routes for salmonella contamination of poultry meat: epidemiological study from hatchery to slaughterhouse. Epidemiol. Infect. 129, 253–265. 10.1017/s0950268802007380</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0950268802007380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2869884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12403101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hisasaga C. (2021). Assessing the accuracy of a woody breast identification technique and evaluating the association between mitochondria values to woody breast severity. Fresno: California State University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoving-Bolink A. H., Kranen R. W., Klont R. E., Gerritsen C. L. M., De Greef K. H. (2000). Fibre area and capillary supply in broiler breast muscle in relation to productivity and ascites. Meat Sci. 56, 397–402. 10.1016/s0309-1740(00)00071-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0309-1740(00)00071-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22062170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang S., Kong A., Cao Q., Tong Z., Wang X. (2019). The role of blood vessels in broiler chickens with tibial dyschondroplasia. Poult. Sci. 98, 6527–6532. 10.3382/ps/pez497</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pez497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8913930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31433842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ichimiya T., Yamakawa T., Hirano T., Yokoyama Y., Hayashi Y., Hirayama D., et al. (2020). Autophagy and autophagy-related diseases: a review. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 21, 8974. 10.3390/ijms21238974</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms21238974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7729615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33255983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacob F. G., Baracho M. S., Nääs I. A., Lima N. S. D., Salgado D. D., Souza R. (2016). Risk of incidence of hock burn and pododermatitis in broilers reared under commercial conditions. Braz. J. Poult. Sci. 18, 357–362. 10.1590/1806-9061-2015-0183</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1806-9061-2015-0183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang T., Mandal R. K., Wideman R. F., JR., Khatiwara A., Pevzner I., Min Kwon Y. (2015). Molecular survey of bacterial communities associated with bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis (BCO) in broilers. PLOS ONE 10, e0124403. 10.1371/journal.pone.0124403</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0124403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4400152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25881241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julian R. (1998). Rapid growth problems: ascites and skeletal deformities in broilers. Poult. Sci. 77, 1773–1780. 10.1093/ps/77.12.1773</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/77.12.1773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9872578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapell D. N. R. G., Hill W. G., Neeteson A. M., Mcadam J., Koerhuis A. N. M., Avendaño S. (2012). Twenty-five years of selection for improved leg health in purebred broiler lines and underlying genetic parameters. Poult. Sci. 91, 3032–3043. 10.3382/ps.2012-02578</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2012-02578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23155010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karsenty G., Wagner E. F. (2002). Reaching a genetic and molecular understanding of skeletal development. Dev. cell 2, 389–406. 10.1016/s1534-5807(02)00157-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s1534-5807(02)00157-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11970890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kierończyk B., Rawski M., Józefiak D., Świątkiewicz S. (2017). Infectious and non-infectious factors associated with leg disorders in poultry–a review. Ann. animal Sci. 17, 645–669. 10.1515/aoas-2016-0098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/aoas-2016-0098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laurentie J., Loux V., Hennequet-Antier C., Chambellon E., Deschamps J., Trotereau A., et al. (2023). Comparative genome analysis of Enterococcus cecorum reveals intercontinental spread of a lineage of clinical poultry isolates. mSphere 8, e0049522–22. 10.1128/msphere.00495-22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/msphere.00495-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10117131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36794931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leblanc S. J., Lissemore K. D., Kelton D. F., Duffield T. F., Leslie K. E. (2006). Major advances in disease prevention in dairy cattle. J. Dairy Sci. 89, 1267–1279. 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(06)72195-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(06)72195-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16537959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J., Mienaltowski M. J. (2023). Broiler white striping: a review of its etiology, effects on production, and mitigation efforts. Poultry 2, 292–304. 10.3390/poultry2020022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/poultry2020022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leinonen I., Williams A. G., Wiseman J., Guy J., Kyriazakis I. (2012). Predicting the environmental impacts of chicken systems in the United Kingdom through a life cycle assessment: broiler production systems. Poult. Sci. 91, 8–25. 10.3382/ps.2011-01634</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2011-01634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22184424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y.-J., Zhang L., Papasian C. J., Deng H.-W. (2014). Genome-wide association studies for osteoporosis: a 2013 update. jbm 21, 99–116. 10.11005/jbm.2014.21.2.99</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11005/jbm.2014.21.2.99</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4075273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25006567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marino L. (2017). Thinking chickens: a review of cognition, emotion, and behavior in the domestic chicken. Anim. Cogn. 20, 127–147. 10.1007/s10071-016-1064-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10071-016-1064-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5306232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28044197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mcculloch V. (2017). Public Perception and Poultry Production: comparing public awareness and opinion of the UK poultry industry with published data. Anim. Welf. Found.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mcnamee P. T., Mccullagh J. J., Thorp B. H., Ball H. J., Graham D., Mccullough S. J., et al. (1998). Study of leg weakness in two commercial broiler flocks. Veterinary Rec. 143, 131–135. 10.1136/vr.143.5.131</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/vr.143.5.131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9725184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mcnamee P. T., Smyth J. A., Smyth J. A. (2000). Bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis ('femoral head necrosis') of broiler chickens: a review. Avian Pathol. 29, 253–270. 10.1080/03079450050118386</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079450050118386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19184815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell R. (2014). Broiler lameness in the United States: an industry perspective. 25 th ANNUAL AUSTRALIAN. Poult. Sci. SYMPOSIUM, 175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montgomery R. K., Mulberg A. E., Grand R. J. (1999). Development of the human gastrointestinal tract: twenty years of progress. Gastroenterology 116, 702–731. 10.1016/s0016-5085(99)70193-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0016-5085(99)70193-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10029630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris G. K., Wells J. G. (1970). Salmonella contamination in a poultry-processing plant. Appl. Microbiol. 19, 795–799. 10.1128/am.19.5.795-799.1970</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/am.19.5.795-799.1970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC376791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5463577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nääs I. A., Paz I. C. L. A., Baracho M. S., Menezes A. G., Bueno L. G. F., Almeida I. C. L., et al. (2009). Impact of lameness on broiler well-being. J. Appl. Poult. Res. 18, 432–439. 10.3382/japr.2008-00061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/japr.2008-00061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nairn M., Watson A. (1972). Leg weakness of poultry-a clinical and pathological characterisation.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4576900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakhon S., Numthuam S., Charoensook R., Tartrakoon W., Incharoen P., Incharoen T. 2019. Growth performance, meat quality, and bone-breaking strength in broilers fed dietary rice hull silicon. Anim. Nutr , 5, 152–155. 10.1016/j.aninu.2018.11.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2018.11.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6544762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31193881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
NATIONAL CHICKEN COUNCIL (2021a). Broiler chicken industry key facts 2021. Available at: https://www.nationalchickencouncil.org/about-the-industry/statistics/broiler-chicken-industry-key-facts/ (Accessed June 2, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
NATIONAL CHICKEN COUNCIL (2021b). “
Per capita consumption of poultry and livestock, 1965 to forecast 2022,” in Pounds. Available at: https://www.nationalchickencouncil.org/about-the-industry/statistics/per-capita-consumption-of-poultry-and-livestock-1965-to-estimated-2012-in-pounds/ (Accessed June 2, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang B., Bowker B., Yang Y., Zhang J., Zhuang H. (2020). Relationships between instrumental texture measurements and subjective woody breast condition scores in raw broiler breast fillets. Poult. Sci. 99, 3292–3298. 10.1016/j.psj.2019.12.072</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2019.12.072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7597666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32475465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papah M. B., Brannick E. M., Schmidt C. J., Abasht B. (2018). Gene expression profiling of the early pathogenesis of wooden breast disease in commercial broiler chickens using RNA-sequencing. PLOS ONE 13, e0207346. 10.1371/journal.pone.0207346</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0207346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6281187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30517117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pattison M. (1992). Impacts of bone problems on the poultry meat industry. Poult. Sci. Symposium.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearce J., Chang Y. M., Abeyesinghe S. (2023). Individual monitoring of activity and lameness in conventional and slower-growing breeds of broiler chickens using accelerometers. Anim. (Basel) 13, 1432. 10.3390/ani13091432</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani13091432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10177109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37174469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen I. J., Tahamtani F. M., Forkman B., Young J. F., Poulsen H. D., Riber A. B. (2020). Effects of environmental enrichment on health and bone characteristics of fast growing broiler chickens. Poult. Sci. 99, 1946–1955. 10.1016/j.psj.2019.11.061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2019.11.061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7587693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32241475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petracci M., Berri C. (2017). Poultry quality evaluation: quality attributes and consumer values. Sawston, Cambridge, United Kingdom: Woodhead Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pineda B., Tarín J., Hermenegildo C., Laporta P., Cano A., García-Pérez M. (2011). Gene–gene interaction between CD40 and CD40L reduces bone mineral density and increases osteoporosis risk in women. Osteoporos. Int. 22, 1451–1458. 10.1007/s00198-010-1324-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00198-010-1324-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20577873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quarles C. L., Caveny D. D. (1979). Effect of air contaminants on performance and quality of broilers. Poult. Sci. 58, 543–548. 10.3382/ps.0580543</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.0580543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramser A., Greene E., Alrubaye A. A. K., Wideman R., Dridi S. (2022). Role of autophagy machinery dysregulation in bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis. Poult. Sci. 101, 101750. 10.1016/j.psj.2022.101750</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2022.101750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8914211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35278754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramser A., Greene E., Wideman R., Dridi S. (2021). Local and systemic cytokine, chemokine, and FGF profile in bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis (BCO)-Affected broilers. Cells 10, 3174. 10.3390/cells10113174</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cells10113174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8620240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34831397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramser A., Hawken R., Greene E., Okimoto R., Flack B., Christopher C. J., et al. (2023). Bone metabolite profile differs between normal and femur head necrosis (FHN/BCO)-Affected broilers: implications for dysregulated metabolic cascades in FHN pathophysiology. Metabolites 13, 662. 10.3390/metabo13050662</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/metabo13050662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10223080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37233703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rath N. C., Huff G. R., Huff W. E., Balog J. M. (2000). Factors regulating bone maturity and strength in poultry. Poult. Sci. 79, 1024–1032. 10.1093/ps/79.7.1024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/79.7.1024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10901206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhoads D. D., Pummill J., Alrubaye A. A. K. (2024). Molecular genomic analyses of Enterococcus cecorum from sepsis outbreaks in broilers. Microorganisms 12, 250. 10.3390/microorganisms12020250</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12020250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10892122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38399654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robbins K. M., Suyemoto M. M., Lyman R. L., Martin M. P., Barnes H. J., Borst L. B. (2012). An outbreak and source investigation of enterococcal spondylitis in broilers caused by Enterococcus cecorum. Avian Dis. 56, 768–773. 10.1637/10253-052412-Case.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1637/10253-052412-Case.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23397855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouger A., Tresse O., Zagorec M. (2017). Bacterial contaminants of poultry meat: sources, species, and dynamics. Microorganisms 5, 50. 10.3390/microorganisms5030050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms5030050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5620641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28841156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanotra G. S., Lawson L. G., Vestergaard K. S., Thomsen M. G. (2001). Influence of stocking density on tonic immobility, lameness, and tibial dyschondroplasia in broilers. J. Appl. Animal Welf. Sci. 4, 71–87. 10.1207/s15327604jaws0401_4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1207/s15327604jaws0401_4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos M. N., Widowski T. M., Kiarie E. G., Guerin M. T., Edwards A. M., Torrey S. (2022). In pursuit of a better broiler: tibial morphology, breaking strength, and ash content in conventional and slower-growing strains of broiler chickens. Poult. Sci. 101, 101755. 10.1016/j.psj.2022.101755</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2022.101755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8914365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35276495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schlievert P. M., Cahill M. P., Hostager B. S., Brosnahan A. J., Klingelhutz A. J., Gourronc F. A., et al. (2019). Staphylococcal superantigens stimulate epithelial cells through CD40 to produce chemokines. MBio 10, e00214. 10.1128/mbio.00214-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mbio.00214-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6426597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30890614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Seaman J., Fangman T. (2023). Biosecurity for today's swine operation. United States: University of Missouri Extension. Available at: https://extension.missouri.edu/publications/g2340 (Accessed July 17, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepherd E., Fairchild B. (2010). Footpad dermatitis in poultry. Poult. Sci. 89, 2043–2051. 10.3382/ps.2010-00770</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2010-00770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20852093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shwani A., Adkins P. R., Ekesi N. S., Alrubaye A., Calcutt M. J., Middleton J. R., et al. (2020). Whole-genome comparisons of Staphylococcus agnetis isolates from cattle and chickens. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 86, 004844–e520. 10.1128/AEM.00484-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00484-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7267197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32245765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siegel P. B., Barger K., Siewerdt F. (2019). Limb health in broiler breeding: history using genetics to improve welfare. J. Appl. Poult. Res. 28, 785–790. 10.3382/japr/pfz052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/japr/pfz052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sihvo H. K., Airas N., Lindén J., Puolanne E. (2018). Pectoral vessel density and early ultrastructural changes in broiler chicken wooden breast myopathy. J. Comp. Pathology 161, 1–10. 10.1016/j.jcpa.2018.04.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcpa.2018.04.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30173852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinclair M., Yan W., Phillips C. J. C. (2019). Attitudes of pig and poultry industry stakeholders in guandong province, China, to animal welfare and farming systems. Animals 9, 860. 10.3390/ani9110860</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani9110860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6912402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31652966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sonntag W. I., Spiller A., Von Meyer-Höfer M. (2019). Discussing modern poultry farming systems—insights into citizen's lay theories. Poult. Sci. 98, 209–216. 10.3382/ps/pey292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pey292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29982708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stalker M. J., Brash M. L., Weisz A., Ouckama R. M., Slavic D. (2010a). Arthritis and osteomyelitis associated with Enterococcus cecorum infection in broiler and broiler breeder chickens in Ontario, Canada. J. Vet. Diagn Invest 22, 643–645. 10.1177/104063871002200426</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/104063871002200426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20622242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stalker M. J., Brash M. L., Weisz A., Ouckama R. M., Slavic D. (2010b). Arthritis and osteomyelitis associated with Enterococcus cecorum infection in broiler and broiler breeder chickens in ontario, Canada. J. Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation 22, 643–645. 10.1177/104063871002200426</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/104063871002200426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20622242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szafraniec G. M., Szeleszczuk P., Dolka B. (2022). Review on skeletal disorders caused by Staphylococcus spp. in poultry. Veterinary Q. 42, 21–40. 10.1080/01652176.2022.2033880</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01652176.2022.2033880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8843168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35076352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tallentire C. W., Leinonen I., Kyriazakis I. (2016). Breeding for efficiency in the broiler chicken: a review. Agron. Sustain. Dev. 36, 66. 10.1007/s13593-016-0398-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13593-016-0398-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tixier-Boichard M. (2020). From the jungle fowl to highly performing chickens: are we reaching limits? World's Poult. Sci. J. 76, 2–17. 10.1080/00439339.2020.1729676</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00439339.2020.1729676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomita M., Ohkubo R., Hayashi M. (2004). Lipopolysaccharide transport system across colonic epithelial cells in normal and infective rat. Drug metabolism Pharmacokinet. 19, 33–40. 10.2133/dmpk.19.33</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2133/dmpk.19.33</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15499167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>UC DAVIS VETERINARY MEDICINE (2019). All out - all in" poultry management approach to disease control - a guide for poultry owners. Davis, CA, United States: A Guide for Poultry Owners.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
USDA (2023). Poultry sector at a glance United States department of agriculture. Available at: https://www.ers.usda.gov/topics/animal-products/poultry-eggs/sector-at-a-glance/ (Accessed June 2, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
USDA (2024). Livestock, poultry and grain. Washington, DC, United States: United States Department of Agriculture. Available at: https://www.ams.usda.gov/market-news/livestock-poultry-grain (Accessed June 2, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>VAN Oudenhove L., Levy R. L., Crowell M. D., Drossman D. A., Halpert A. D., Keefer L., et al. (2016). Biopsychosocial aspects of functional gastrointestinal disorders: how central and environmental processes contribute to the development and expression of functional gastrointestinal disorders. Gastroenterology 150, 1355–1367.e2. 10.1053/j.gastro.2016.02.027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2016.02.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8809487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27144624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vukina T. (2001). Vertical integration and contracting in the US poultry sector. J. Food Distribution Res. 32, 29–38. 10.22004/ag.econ.27819</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22004/ag.econ.27819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weeks C., Danbury T., Davies H., Hunt P., Kestin S. (2000). The behaviour of broiler chickens and its modification by lameness. Appl. animal Behav. Sci. 67, 111–125. 10.1016/s0168-1591(99)00102-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0168-1591(99)00102-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10719194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weimer S. L., Wideman R. F., Scanes C. G., Mauromoustakos A., Christensen K. D., Vizzier-Thaxton Y. (2021). Impact of experimentally induced bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis (BCO) lameness on health, stress, and leg health parameters in broilers. Poult. Sci. 100, 101457. 10.1016/j.psj.2021.101457</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8496169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34607149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welter A. A., Wu W. J., Maurer R., O'Quinn T. G., Chao M. D., Boyle D. L., et al. (2022). An investigation of the altered textural property in woody breast myopathy using an integrative omics approach. Front. Physiol. 13, 860868. 10.3389/fphys.2022.860868</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphys.2022.860868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8970568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35370787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whiley H., Ross K. (2015). Salmonella and eggs: from production to plate. Int. J. Environ. Res. public health 12, 2543–2556. 10.3390/ijerph120302543</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph120302543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4377917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25730295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wideman R. F. (2016). Bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis and lameness in broilers: a review. Poult. Sci. 95, 325–344. 10.3382/ps/pev320</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pev320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26527707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wideman R. F., Prisby R. D. (2013). Bone circulatory disturbances in the development of spontaneous bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis: a translational model for the pathogenesis of femoral head necrosis. Front. Endocrinol. 3, 183. 10.3389/fendo.2012.00183</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fendo.2012.00183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3550519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23346077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wideman R., AL-Rubaye A., Gilley A., Reynolds D., Lester H., Yoho D., et al. (2013). Susceptibility of 4 commercial broiler crosses to lameness attributable to bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis. Poult. Sci. 92, 2311–2325. 10.3382/ps.2013-03150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2013-03150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23960113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wideman R., Hamal K., Stark J., Blankenship J., Lester H., Mitchell K., et al. (2012). A wire-flooring model for inducing lameness in broilers: evaluation of probiotics as a prophylactic treatment. Poult. Sci. 91, 870–883. 10.3382/ps.2011-01907</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2011-01907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22399726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousefi A., Saki A. (2019). Iron loaded chitooligosaccharide nanoparticles reduces incidence of bacterial chondronecrosis with osteomyelitis in broiler chickens. Iran. J. Appl. Animal Sci. 9, 329–336.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Z., Shen D., Wang K., Liu J., Li M., Win-Shwe T.-T., et al. (2023). Pulmonary microbiota intervention alleviates fine particulate matter-induced lung inflammation in broilers. J. Animal Sci. 101, skad207. 10.1093/jas/skad207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skad207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10390102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37341706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuidhof M. J., Schneider B. L., Carney V. L., Korver D. R., Robinson F. E. (2014). Growth, efficiency, and yield of commercial broilers from 1957, 1978, and 2005. Poult. Sci. 93, 2970–2982. Available at:. 10.3382/ps.2014-04291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2014-04291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4988556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25260522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>