<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39276829</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0953</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>262</Volume><Issue>Pt 2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Antibiotic residues in the cirata reservoir, Indonesia and their effect on ecology and the selection for antibiotic-resistant bacteria.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>119992</StartPage><MedlinePgn>119992</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.envres.2024.119992</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0013-9351(24)01899-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Antibiotic residues, their mixture toxicity, and the potential selection for antibiotic-resistant bacteria could pose a problem for water use and the ecosystem of reservoirs. This study aims to provide a comprehensive understanding of the occurrence, concentration, distribution, and ecological risks associated with various antibiotics in the Cirata reservoir, Indonesia. In our water and sediment samples, we detected 24 out of the 65 antibiotic residues analyzed, revealing a diverse range of antibiotic classes present. Notably, sulphonamides, diaminopyrimidine, and lincosamides were frequently found in the water, while the sediment predominantly contained tetracyclines and fluoroquinolones. Most antibiotic classes reached their highest concentrations in the water during the dry season. However, fluoroquinolones and tetracyclines showed their highest concentrations in the water during the wet season. Ecotoxicological risk assessments indicated that the impact of most antibiotic residues on aquatic organisms was negligible, except for fluoroquinolones. Looking at the impact on cyanobacteria, however, varying risks were indicated, ranging from medium to critical, with antibiotics like sulfamethoxazole, ciprofloxacin, norfloxacin, and lincomycin posing substantial threats. Among these, ciprofloxacin emerged as the antibiotic with the strongest risk. Furthermore, fluoroquinolones may have the potential to contribute to the selection of antibiotic-resistant bacteria. The presence of mixtures of antibiotic residues during the wet season significantly impacted species loss, with Potentially Affected Fraction of Species (msPAF) values exceeding 0.75 in almost 90% of locations. However, the impact of mixtures of antibiotic residues in sediment remained consistently low across all locations and seasons. Based on their occurrences and associated risks, 12 priority antibiotic residues were identified for monitoring in the reservoir and its tributaries. Moreover, the study suggests that river inflow serves as the most significant source of antibiotic residues in the reservoir. Further investigations into the relative share attribution of antibiotic sources in the reservoir is recommended to help identify effective interventions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ariyani</LastName><ForeName>Miranti</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Earth Systems and Global Change Group, Wageningen University &amp; Research, Droevendaalsesteeg 4, Wageningen, 6708, PB, Netherlands; Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University &amp; Research, Akkermaalsbos 2, Wageningen, 6708, WB, Netherlands; National Research and Innovation Agency of Indonesia, Research Centre for Environment &amp; Clean Technology, KST Samaun Samadikun, Jl. Sangkuriang, Bandung, 40135, Indonesia. Electronic address: miranti.ariyani@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jansen</LastName><ForeName>Larissa J M</ForeName><Initials>LJM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University &amp; Research, Akkermaalsbos 2, Wageningen, 6708, WB, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Balzer-Rutgers</LastName><ForeName>Paula</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University &amp; Research, Akkermaalsbos 2, Wageningen, 6708, WB, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hofstra</LastName><ForeName>Nynke</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Earth Systems and Global Change Group, Wageningen University &amp; Research, Droevendaalsesteeg 4, Wageningen, 6708, PB, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Oel</LastName><ForeName>Pieter</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Water Resources Management Group, Wageningen University &amp; Research, Droevendaalsesteeg 4, Wageningen, 6708, PB, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van de Schans</LastName><ForeName>Milou G M</ForeName><Initials>MGM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University &amp; Research, Akkermaalsbos 2, Wageningen, 6708, WB, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0147621</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0013-9351</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antibiotic residues</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antibiotic-resistant bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ecotoxicological risk assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">LC-MS/MS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">msPAF</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39276829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2024.119992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0013-9351(24)01899-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>