<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39276547</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-7072</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>463</Volume><Issue>Pt 2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Integrated, high-throughput metabolomics approach for metabolite analysis of four sprout types.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>141182</StartPage><MedlinePgn>141182</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.141182</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0308-8146(24)02832-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In this study, we combined two distinct extraction and separation techniques with the aim of comprehensively collecting metabolite features in sprouts, particularly hydrophilic compounds. By synergistically analyzing the data using MS-DIAL and MetaboAnalystR, we obtained a greater number of annotated metabolites and explored differences in annotation across analytical tools. We found that this approach significantly increased the number of detected metabolite features and the final identification counts. Furthermore, we explored the functional component characteristics of four sprout types. This study provides data supporting the potential of sprouts as nutritious vegetables and functional food ingredients, emphasizing their value in the development of functional foods.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Junyan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Quality Standards and Testing Technology for Agro-Products of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Key Laboratory of Agro-food Safety and Quality, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Beijing 100081, PR China; College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100083, PR China. Electronic address: yujunyan@cau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Lei</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Quality Standards and Testing Technology for Agro-Products of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Key Laboratory of Agro-food Safety and Quality, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Beijing 100081, PR China; College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100083, PR China. Electronic address: xulei@cau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mi</LastName><ForeName>Lu</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Quality Standards and Testing Technology for Agro-Products of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Key Laboratory of Agro-food Safety and Quality, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Beijing 100081, PR China; College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100083, PR China. Electronic address: milu@cau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Nan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Quality Standards and Testing Technology for Agro-Products of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Key Laboratory of Agro-food Safety and Quality, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Beijing 100081, PR China. Electronic address: 82101225512@caas.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Fengjuan</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Quality Standards &amp; Testing Technology for Agro-Products, Xinjiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Urumqi 830091, PR China. Electronic address: liufengjuan@xaas.ac.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100083, PR China. Electronic address: zhaojing@cau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Zhenzhen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Quality Standards and Testing Technology for Agro-Products of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Key Laboratory of Agro-food Safety and Quality, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Beijing 100081, PR China; College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100083, PR China. Electronic address: xuzhenzhen@caas.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7702639</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0308-8146</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hydrophilic interaction chromatography technique</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MS-DIAL</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MetaboAnalystR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metabolomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sprouts</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39276547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.141182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0308-8146(24)02832-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>