<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39271576</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1867-1632</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Mycotoxin research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mycotoxin Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mycotoxin management: exploring natural solutions for mycotoxin prevention and detoxification in food and feed.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12550-024-00562-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Mycotoxins, secondary metabolites produced by various fungi, pose a significant threat to food and feed safety worldwide due to their toxic effects on human and animal health. Traditional methods of mycotoxin management often involve chemical treatments, which may raise concerns about residual toxicity and environmental impact. In recent years, there has been growing interest in exploring natural alternatives for preventing mycotoxin contamination and detoxification. This review provides an overview of the current research on the use of natural products for mitigating mycotoxin risks in food and feed. It encompasses a wide range of natural sources, including plant-derived compounds, microbial agents, and enzymatic control. The mechanisms underlying the efficacy of these natural products in inhibiting mycotoxin synthesis, adsorbing mycotoxins, or enhancing detoxification processes are discussed. Challenges and future directions in the development and application of natural products for mycotoxin management are also addressed. Overall, this review highlights the promising role of natural products as sustainable and eco-friendly alternatives for combating mycotoxin contamination in the food and feed supply chain.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s) under exclusive licence to Society for Mycotoxin (Research Gesellschaft für Mykotoxinforschung e.V.) and Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ntungwe</LastName><ForeName>Epole Ngolle</ForeName><Initials>EN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6596-8985</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, University of Coimbra, P-3004-535, Coimbra, Portugal. epole.ntungwe@uc.pt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agri-Food Safety and One Health Agency (AFS1HA), Yaounde, Cameroon. epole.ntungwe@uc.pt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tchana</LastName><ForeName>Angéle N</ForeName><Initials>AN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Science, University of Yaounde 1, P.O. Box 812, Yaounde, Cameroon.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abia</LastName><ForeName>Wilfred Angie</ForeName><Initials>WA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3796-8616</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Science, University of Yaounde 1, P.O. Box 812, Yaounde, Cameroon. abiawilfred@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agri-Food Safety and One Health Agency (AFS1HA), Yaounde, Cameroon. abiawilfred@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Food Security, School of Biological Sciences, The Queen's University of Belfast, Belfast, Northern Ireland, BT9 5DL, UK. abiawilfred@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Mycotoxin Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8807334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0178-7888</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Detoxification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food and feed safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Management</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mycotoxin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Natural products</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39271576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12550-024-00562-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12550-024-00562-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abdi M, Asadi A, Maleki F et al (2021) Microbiological detoxification of mycotoxins: focus on mechanisms and advances. Infect Disord Drug Targets 21:339–357. https://doi.org/10.2174/1871526520666200616145150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1871526520666200616145150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32543365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abou Dib A, Assaf JC, El Khoury A, El Khatib S, Koubaa M, Louka N (2022) Single, subsequent, or simultaneous treatments to mitigate mycotoxins in solid foods and feeds: a critical review. Foods 11:3304. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11203304</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11203304</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37431053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9601460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abraham N, Chan ETS, Zhou T, Seah SYK (2022) Microbial detoxification of mycotoxins in food. Front Microbiol 13:1–18. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.957148</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.957148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agriopoulou S, Stamatelopoulou E, Varzakas T (2020) Advances in occurrence, importance, and mycotoxin control strategies: prevention and detoxification in foods. Foods 9. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods9020137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad MM, Qamar F, Saifi M, Abdin MZ (2022) Natural inhibitors: a sustainable way to combat aflatoxins. Front Microbiol 13:1–9. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.993834</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.993834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida NA, Freire L, Carnielli-Queiroz L et al (2024) Essential oils: an eco-friendly alternative for controlling toxigenic fungi in cereal grains. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 23:e13251. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541-4337.13251</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.13251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38284600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Owaisi A, Al-Sadi AM, Al-Sabahi JN et al (2022) In vitro detoxification of aflatoxin B1 by aqueous extracts of medicinal herbs. All Life 15:314–324. https://doi.org/10.1080/26895293.2022.2049900</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/26895293.2022.2049900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Álvarez-García S, Moumni M, Romanazzi G (2023) Antifungal activity of volatile organic compounds from essential oils against the postharvest pathogens Botrytis cinerea, Monilinia fructicola, Monilinia fructigena, and Monilinia laxa. Front Plant Sci 14:1–12. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2023.1274770</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2023.1274770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avantaggiato G, Greco D, Damascelli A et al (2014) Assessment of multi-mycotoxin adsorption efficacy of grape pomace. J Agric Food Chem 62:497–507. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf404179h</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf404179h</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24364566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awuchi CG, Nwozo OS, Aja PM, Odongo GA (2023) High-pressure acidified steaming with varied citric acid dosing can successfully detoxify mycotoxins. Food Sci Nutr 11:2677–2685. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.3324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fsn3.3324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37324899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10261742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awuchi CG, Ondari EN, Ogbonna CU et al (2021) Mycotoxins affecting animals, foods, humans, and plants: types, occurrence, toxicities, action mechanisms, prevention, and detoxification strategies—a revisit. Foods 1–48. https://doi.org/10.3390/foo</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azam MS, Ahmed S, Islam MN et al (2021) Critical assessment of mycotoxins in beverages and their control measures. Toxins (Basel) 13:1–26. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins13050323</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins13050323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bangar SP, Sharma N, Bhardwaj A, Phimolsiripol Y (2022) Lactic acid bacteria. Qual Assur Saf Crop Foods 14:13–31. https://doi.org/10.15586/QAS.V14I2.1014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15586/QAS.V14I2.1014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boy FR, Casquete R, Gudiño I et al (2023) Antifungal effect of autochthonous aromatic plant extracts on two mycotoxigenic strains of Aspergillus flavus. Foods 12. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12091821</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter AC, King JB, Mattes AO et al (2019) Natural-product-inspired compounds as countermeasures against the liver carcinogen aflatoxin B1. J Nat Prod 82:1694–1703. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b00290</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b00290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31136174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castano-Duque L, Gilbert MK, Mack BM et al (2021) Flavonoids modulate the accumulation of toxins from Aspergillus flavus in maize kernels. Front Plant Sci 12:1–15. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2021.761446</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2021.761446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castano-Duque L, Lebar MD, Carter-Wientjes C et al (2022) Flavonoids modulate Aspergillus flavus proliferation and aflatoxin production. J Fungi 8. https://doi.org/10.3390/jof8111211</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Changwa R, Abia W, Msagati T et al (2018) Multi-mycotoxin occurrence in dairy cattle feeds from the gauteng province of South Africa: a pilot study using UHPLC-QTOF-MS/MS. Toxins (Basel) 10:. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins10070294</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chhonker SK, Rawat D, Naik RA, Koiri RK (2018) An overview of mycotoxins in human health with emphasis on development and progression of liver cancer. Clin Oncol 3:1408</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury NN, Islam MN, Jafrin R et al (2023) Natural plant products as effective alternatives to synthetic chemicals for postharvest fruit storage management. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 63:10332–10350. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2022.2079112</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2022.2079112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35612470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhifi W, Bellili S, Jazi S et al (2016) Essential oils’ chemical characterization and investigation of some biological activities: a critical review. Med (Basel, Switzerland) 3. https://doi.org/10.3390/medicines3040025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dias MC, Pinto DCGA, Silva AMS (2021) Plant flavonoids: chemical characteristics and biological activity. Molecules 26:1–16. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26175377</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26175377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>dos Santos VM, da Silva Oliveira G, de Lima CAR, Curvello FA (2021) Broiler chick performance using Saccharomyces cerevisiae yeast cell wall as an anti-mycotoxin additive. Czech J Anim Sci 66:65–72. https://doi.org/10.17221/237/2020-CJAS</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17221/237/2020-CJAS</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Sayed RA, Jebur AB, Kang W, El-Demerdash FM (2022) An overview on the major mycotoxins in food products: characteristics, toxicity, and analysis. J Futur Foods 2:91–102. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfutfo.2022.03.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfutfo.2022.03.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eskola M, Kos G, Elliott CT et al (2020) Worldwide contamination of food-crops with mycotoxins: validity of the widely cited ‘FAO estimate’ of 25%. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 60:2773–2789. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2019.1658570</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2019.1658570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31478403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falleh H, Ben Jemaa M, Saada M, Ksouri R (2020) Essential oils: a promising eco-friendly food preservative. Food Chem 330:127268. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.127268</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.127268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32540519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrigo D, Bharti S, Mondin M, Raiola A (2021) Effect of naturally occurring compounds on fumonisin production and fum gene expression in Fusarium verticillioides. Agronomy 11. https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy11061060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farbo MG, Urgeghe PP, Fiori S et al (2018) Effect of yeast volatile organic compounds on ochratoxin A-producing Aspergillus carbonarius and A. ochraceus. Int J Food Microbiol 284:1–10. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.06.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.06.023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29990634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freire FDCO, da Rocha MEB (2016) Impact of mycotoxins on human health. In: Mérillon J-M, Ramawat KG (eds) Fungal Metabolites. Springer International Publishing, Cham, pp 1–23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furlong EB, Buffon JG, Cerqueira MB, Kupski L (2024) Mitigation of mycotoxins in food—is it possible? Foods 13. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods13071112</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia C, Teodósio C, Oliveira C et al (2019) Naturally occurring Plectranthus-derived diterpenes with antitumoral activities. Curr Pharm Des 24:4207–4236. https://doi.org/10.2174/1381612825666190115144241</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1381612825666190115144241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gömöri C, Nacsa-Farkas E, Kerekes EB et al (2013) Evaluation of five essential oils for the control of foodspoilage and mycotoxin producing fungi. Acta Biol Szeged 57:113–116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorran A, Farzaneh M, Shivazad M et al (2013) Aflatoxin B1-reduction of Aspergillus flavus by three medicinal plants (Lamiaceae). Food Control 31:218–223. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.09.024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.09.024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y, Zhao L, Ma Q, Ji C (2021) Novel strategies for degradation of aflatoxins in food and feed: a review. Food Res Int 140:109878. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109878</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33648196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurikar C, Shivaprasad DP, Sabillón L et al (2023) Impact of mycotoxins and their metabolites associated with food grains. Grain Oil Sci Technol 6:1–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gaost.2022.10.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gaost.2022.10.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habschied K, Krstanović V, Zdunić Z et al (2021) Mycotoxins biocontrol methods for healthier crops and stored products. J Fungi 7. https://doi.org/10.3390/jof7050348</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hajare SS, Hajare SN, Sharma A (2005) Aflatoxin inactivation using aqueous extract of ajowan (Trachyspermum ammi) seeds. J Food Sci 70:. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2621.2005.tb09016.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamad GM, Mehany T, Simal-Gandara J et al (2023) A review of recent innovative strategies for controlling mycotoxins in foods. Food Control 144:109350. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan RA, Sand MI, El-Kadi SM (2012) Effect of some organic acids on fungal growth and their toxins production. J Agric Chem Biotechnol 3:391–397. https://doi.org/10.21608/jacb.2012.55011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21608/jacb.2012.55011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hathout AS, Aly SE (2014) Biological detoxification of mycotoxins: a review. Ann Microbiol 64:905–919. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13213-014-0899-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13213-014-0899-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Zhang J, Kong W et al (2017) Mechanisms of antifungal and anti-aflatoxigenic properties of essential oil derived from turmeric (Curcuma longa L.) on Aspergillus flavus. Food Chem 220:1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.09.179</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.09.179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27855875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humer E, Lucke A, Harder H et al (2016) Effects of citric and lactic acid on the reduction of deoxynivalenol and its derivatives in feeds. Toxins (Basel) 8:1–10. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins8100285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins8100285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>IARC (2012a) Mycotoxins and human health. IARC Sci Publ (158):87–104</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IARC (2012b) Economics of mycotoxins: evaluating costs to society and cost-effectiveness of interventions. IARC Sci Publ (158):119–29</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iram W, Anjum T, Iqbal M et al (2016a) Structural analysis and biological toxicity of aflatoxins B1 and B2 degradation products following detoxification by Ocimum basilicum and Cassia fistula aqueous extracts. Front Microbiol 7:1–18. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2016.01105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iram W, Anjum T, Iqbal M et al (2015) Mass spectrometric identification and toxicity assessment of degraded products of aflatoxin B1 and B2 by Corymbia citriodora aqueous extracts. Sci Rep 5. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep14672</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iram W, Anjum T, Iqbal M et al (2016b) Structural elucidation and toxicity assessment of degraded products of aflatoxin B1 and B2 by aqueous extracts of Trachyspermum ammi. Front Microbiol 7. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2016.00346</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafarzadeh S, Abdolmaleki K, Fardin Javanmardi MH, Mousavi KA (2022) Recent advances in plant-based compounds for mitigation of mycotoxin contamination in food products: current status, challenges and perspectives.pdf. Int J Food Sci Technol 57:2159–2170. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.15555</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijfs.15555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakopović Ž, Čiča KH, Mrvčić J et al (2018) Properties and fermentation activity of industrial yeasts Saccharomyces cerevisiae, S. uvarum, Candida utilis and Kluyveromyces marxianus exposed to AFB1, OTA and ZEA. Food Technol Biotechnol 56:208–217. https://doi.org/10.17113/ftb.56.02.18.5582</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17113/ftb.56.02.18.5582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30228795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6117994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jallow A, Xie H, Tang X et al (2021) Worldwide aflatoxin contamination of agricultural products and foods: from occurrence to control. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 20:2332–2381. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541-4337.12734</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33977678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janik E, Niemcewicz M, Ceremuga M et al (2020) Molecular aspects of mycotoxins—a serious problem for human health. Int J Mol Sci 21:1–21. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21218187</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms21218187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kannan K, Velazhahan R (2014) The potential of leaf extract of barleria lupulina for detoxification of aflatoxins. Indian Phytopathol 67:298–302</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karlovsky P, Suman M, Berthiller F et al (2016) Impact of food processing and detoxification treatments on mycotoxin contamination. Mycotoxin Res 32:179–205. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12550-016-0257-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12550-016-0257-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27554261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5063913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kedia A, Dwivedy AK, Jha DK, Dubey NK (2016) Efficacy of Mentha spicata essential oil in suppression of Aspergillus flavus and aflatoxin contamination in chickpea with particular emphasis to mode of antifungal action. Protoplasma 253:647–653. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00709-015-0871-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00709-015-0871-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26338202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan R, Anwar F, Ghazali FM (2024) A comprehensive review of mycotoxins: toxicology, detection, and effective mitigation approaches. Heliyon 10:e28361. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28361</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38628751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">11019184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kos J, Anic M, Radic B, Zadravec M, Hajnal EJ, JP, (2023) Climate change — a global threat resulting in increasing. Foods 12:2704</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12142704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37509796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10379110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V, Bahuguna A, Ramalingam S et al (2022) Recent technological advances in mechanism, toxicity, and food perspectives of enzyme-mediated aflatoxin degradation. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 62:5395–5412. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2021.2010647</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.2010647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34955062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kusumaningtyas E, Widiastuti R, Maryam R (2006) Reduction of aflatoxin B1 in chicken feed by using Saccharomyces cerevisiae, Rhizopus oligosporus and their combination. Mycopathologia 162:307–311. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11046-006-0047-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11046-006-0047-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17039279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ladeira C, Frazzoli C, Orisakwe OE (2017) Engaging one health for non-communicable diseases in Africa: perspective for mycotoxins. Front Public Heal 5. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2017.00266</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latham RL, Boyle JT, Barbano A et al (2023) Diverse mycotoxin threats to safe food and feed cereals. Essays Biochem 67:797–809. https://doi.org/10.1042/EBC20220221</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/EBC20220221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37313591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10500202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M, Zhang X, Luan H et al (2024) Bioenzymatic detoxification of mycotoxins. Front Microbiol 15:1–22. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2024.1434987</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2024.1434987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Chang J, Wang P et al (2019) Effects of Saccharomyces cerevisiae on alleviating cytotoxicity of porcine jejunal epithelia cells induced by deoxynivalenol. AMB Express 9. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13568-019-0863-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Xie M, Wei D (2022) Biological detoxification of mycotoxins: current status and future advances. Int J Mol Sci 23. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms23031064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loi M, Fanelli F, Liuzzi VC et al (2017) Mycotoxin biotransformation by native and commercial enzymes: present and future perspectives. Toxins (Basel) 9. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins9040111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyagin I, Efremenko E (2019) Enzymes for detoxification of various mycotoxins: origins and mechanisms of catalytic action. Molecules 24:1–39. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules24132362</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules24132362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahato DK, Lee KE, Kamle M et al (2019) Aflatoxins in food and feed: an overview on prevalence, detection and control strategies. Front Microbiol 10:1–10. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.02266</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makarewicz M, Drożdż I, Tarko T, Duda-Chodak A (2021) The interactions between polyphenols and microorganisms, especially gut microbiota. Antioxidants 10:1–70. https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox10020188</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox10020188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makhuvele R, Naidu K, Gbashi S et al (2020) The use of plant extracts and their phytochemicals for control of toxigenic fungi and mycotoxins. Heliyon 6:e05291. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33134582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7586119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mannaa M, Oh JY, Kim KD (2017) Microbe-mediated control of Aspergillus flavus in stored rice grains with a focus on aflatoxin inhibition and biodegradation. Ann Appl Biol 171:376–392</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/aab.12381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mavrommatis A, Giamouri E, Tavrizelou S et al (2021) Impact of mycotoxins on animals’ oxidative status. Antioxidants 10:1–24. https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox10020214</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox10020214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirza Alizadeh A, Hashempour-Baltork F, Mousavi Khaneghah A, Hosseini H (2021) New perspective approaches in controlling fungi and mycotoxins in food using emerging and green technologies. Curr Opin Food Sci 39:7–15. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2020.12.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2020.12.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mugao LG, Gichimu BM, Muturi PW, Mukono ST (2020) Characterization of the volatile components of essential oils of selected plants in Kenya. Biochem Res Int 2020. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/8861798</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukhtar K, Nabi BG, Ansar S et al (2023) Mycotoxins and consumers’ awareness: recent progress and future challenges. Toxicon 232:107227. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2023.107227</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxicon.2023.107227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37454753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nahle S, El Khoury A, Savvaidis I et al (2022) Detoxification approaches of mycotoxins: by microorganisms, biofilms and enzymes. Int J Food Contam 9:1–14. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40550-022-00089-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40550-022-00089-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazzaro F, Fratianni F, Coppola R, De Feo V (2017) Essential oils and antifungal activity. Pharmaceuticals 10:1–20. https://doi.org/10.3390/ph10040086</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ph10040086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndiaye S, Zhang M, Fall M et al (2022) Current review of mycotoxin biodegradation and bioadsorption: microorganisms, mechanisms, and main important applications. Toxins (Basel) 14. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins14110729</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negera M, Washe AP (2019) Use of natural dietary spices for reclamation of food quality impairment by aflatoxin. J Food Qual 2019. https://doi.org/10.1155/2019/4371206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nešić K, Habschied K, Mastanjević K (2021) Possibilities for the biological control of mycotoxins in food and feed. Toxins (Basel) 13. https://doi.org/10.3390/TOXINS13030198</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omotayo OP, Omotayo AO, Mwanza M, Babalola OO (2019) Prevalence of mycotoxins and their consequences on human health. Toxicol Res 35:1–7. https://doi.org/10.5487/TR.2019.35.1.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5487/TR.2019.35.1.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30766652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owumi S, Najophe ES, Farombi EO, Oyelere AK (2020) Gallic acid protects against aflatoxin B1-induced oxidative and inflammatory. J Food Biochem. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.13316</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfbc.13316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32496616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey AK, Samota MK, Kumar A et al (2023) Fungal mycotoxins in food commodities: present status and future concerns. Front Sustain Food Syst 7:1–21. https://doi.org/10.3389/fsufs.2023.1162595</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2023.1162595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto L, Tapia-Rodríguez MR, Baruzzi F, Ayala-Zavala JF (2023) Plant antimicrobials for food quality and safety: recent views and future challenges. Foods 12:. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12122315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piotrowska M (2021) Microbiological decontamination of mycotoxins: opportunities and limitations. Toxins (Basel) 13. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins13110819</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponzilacqua B, Rottinghaus GE, Landers BR, Oliveira CAF (2019) Effects of medicinal herb and Brazilian traditional plant extracts on in vitro mycotoxin decontamination. Food Control 100:24–27. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.01.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.01.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi X, Chen B, Rao J (2023) Natural compounds of plant origin in the control of fungi and mycotoxins in foods. Curr Opin Food Sci 52:101054. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2023.101054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2023.101054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ráduly Z, Szabó L, Madar A et al (2020) Toxicological and medical aspects of Aspergillus-derived mycotoxins entering the feed and food chain. Front Microbiol 10:1–23. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.02908</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rastegar H, Shoeibi S, Yazdanpanah H et al (2017) Removal of aflatoxin B1 by roasting with lemon juice and/or citric acid in contaminated pistachio nuts. Food Control 71:279–284. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.06.045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.06.045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rathod NB, Elabed N, Punia S et al (2023) Recent developments in polyphenol applications on human health: a review with current knowledge. Plants 12:1–30. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants12061217</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants12061217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ropejko K, Twarużek M (2021) Zearalenone and Its Metabolites—General Overview, Occurrence, and Toxicity. Toxins (Basel) 13. https://doi.org/10.3390/TOXINS13010035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakuda S (2010) Mycotoxin production ihbitors from natural products. Mycotoxins 60:79–86. https://doi.org/10.2520/myco.60.79</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2520/myco.60.79</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandosskumar R, Karthikeyan M, Mathiyazhagan S et al (2007) Inhibition of Aspergillus flavus growth and detoxification of aflatoxin B1 by the medicinal plant zimmu (Allium sativum L. x Allium cepa L.). World J Microbiol Biotechnol 23:1007–1014. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11274-006-9327-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11274-006-9327-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares AA, De Sá-Nakanishi AB, Bracht A et al (2013) Hepatoprotective effects of mushrooms. Molecules 18:7609–7630. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules18077609</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules18077609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23884116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6270077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoev SD (2024) Natural feed additives and bioactive supplements versus chemical additives as a safe and practical approach to combat foodborne mycotoxicoses. Front Nutr 11:1–26. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2024.1335779</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2024.1335779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H, He Z, Xiong D, Long M (2023) Mechanisms by which microbial enzymes degrade four mycotoxins and application in animal production: a review. Anim Nutr 15:256–274. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aninu.2023.09.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2023.09.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38033608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10685049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teshome E, Forsido SF, Rupasinghe HPV, Olika Keyata E (2022) Potentials of natural preservatives to enhance food safety and shelf life: a review. Sci World J 2022. https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/9901018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian F, Woo SY, Lee SY, Su Been Park JH, Chun HS (2022) Mycotoxins in soybean-based foods fermented with filamentous fungi occurrence. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 21:5131–5152. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541-4337.13032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.13032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36084140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian F, Woo SY, Lee SY et al (2023) Plant-based natural flavonoids show strong inhibition of aflatoxin production and related gene expressions correlated with chemical structure. Food Microbiol 109:104141. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2022.104141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2022.104141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36309443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tilocca B, Balmas V, Hassan ZU et al (2019) A proteomic investigation of Aspergillus carbonarius exposed to yeast volatilome or to its major component 2-phenylethanol reveals major shifts in fungal metabolism. Int J Food Microbiol 306:108265. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2019.108265</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2019.108265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31325815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udomkun P, Wiredu AN, Nagle M et al (2017) Mycotoxins in sub-Saharan Africa: present situation, socio-economic impact, awareness, and outlook. Food Control 72:110–122. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.07.039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.07.039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umesha S, Manukumar HMG, Chandrasekhar B et al (2017) Aflatoxins and food pathogens: impact of biologically active aflatoxins and their control strategies. J Sci Food Agric 97:1698–1707. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.814</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27859342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velazhahan R, Vijayanandraj S, Vijayasamundeeswari A et al (2010) Detoxification of aflatoxins by seed extracts of the medicinal plant, Trachyspermum ammi (L.) Sprague ex Turrill - structural analysis and biological toxicity of degradation product of aflatoxin G1. Food Control 21:719–725. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2009.10.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2009.10.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vijayanandraj S, Brinda R, Kannan K et al (2014) Detoxification of aflatoxin B1 by an aqueous extract from leaves of Adhatoda vasica Nees. Microbiol Res 169:294–300. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micres.2013.07.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2013.07.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23928380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Qin X, Hao Z et al (2019) Degradation of four major mycotoxins by eight manganese peroxidases in presence of a dicarboxylic acid. Toxins (Basel) 11:1–16. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins11100566</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins11100566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia Y, Wu Z, He R et al (2021) Simultaneous degradation of two mycotoxins enabled by a fusion enzyme in food-grade recombinant Kluyveromyces lactis. Bioresour Bioprocess 8:1–11. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40643-021-00395-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40643-021-00395-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu R, Kiarie EG, Yiannikouris A et al (2022) Nutritional impact of mycotoxins in food animal production and strategies for mitigation. J Anim Sci Biotechnol 13:1–19. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40104-022-00714-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40104-022-00714-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadavalli R, Valluru P, Raj R et al (2023) Biological detoxification of mycotoxins: emphasizing the role of algae. Algal Res 71:103039. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.algal.2023.103039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.algal.2023.103039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan L, Song W, Chen Y et al (2021) Effect of non-aflatoxigenic strains of Aspergillus flavus on aflatoxin contamination of pre-harvest peanuts in fields in China. Oil Crop Sci 6:81–86. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ocsci.2021.04.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ocsci.2021.04.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Wang J, Zhang H et al (2016) Ochratoxin A is degraded byYarrowia lipolytica and generates non-toxic degradation products. World Mycotoxin J 9:269–278. https://doi.org/10.3920/WMJ2015.1911</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/WMJ2015.1911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yehia RS (2022) Evaluation of the biological activities of β-glucan isolated from Lentinula edodes. Lett Appl Microbiol 75:317–329. https://doi.org/10.1111/lam.13727</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/lam.13727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35482469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshinari T (2022) Studies on mycotoxin detection and control by natural products. JSM Mycotoxins 72:71–73. https://doi.org/10.2520/myco.72-2-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2520/myco.72-2-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu J, Pedroso IR (2023) Health of humans, livestock animals and pets. Toxins. 15:48</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins15080480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Li M, Wu C, Peng B (2019) Physical adsorption of patulin by Saccharomyces cerevisiae during fermentation. J Food Sci Technol 56:2326–2331. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197-019-03681-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-019-03681-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30996467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6444016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng J, Zhou Y, Li Y et al (2016) Spices for prevention and treatment of cancers. Nutrients 8:495</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu8080495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27529277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4997408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>