<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39277905</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-2472</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>243</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Thrombosis research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Thromb Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Knowledge and raising awareness are the CURES for alleviating sex disparities in PE care.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>109147</StartPage><MedlinePgn>109147</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.thromres.2024.109147</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0049-3848(24)00279-2</ELocationID><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bikdeli</LastName><ForeName>Behnood</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Medicine Division, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA; Thrombosis Research Group, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA; YNHH/ Yale Center for Outcomes Research and Evaluation (CORE), New Haven, CT, USA. Electronic address: bbikdeli@bwh.harvard.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bates</LastName><ForeName>Shannon M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Hematology and Thromboembolism, Department of Medicine, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016421">Editorial</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Thromb Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0326377</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0049-3848</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">China</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gender</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pulmonary embolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sex</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest Dr. Bikdeli was supported by the Scott Schoen and Nancy Adams IGNITE Award and is supported by the Mary Ann Tynan Research Scientist award from the Mary Horrigan Connors Center for Women's Health and Gender Biology at Brigham and Women's Hospital. Outside the submitted work, Dr. Bikdeli is support by a Career Development Award from the American Heart Association and VIVA Physicians, and the Heart and Vascular Center Junior Faculty Award from Brigham and Women's Hospital. Dr. Bikdeli reports that he was a consulting expert on behalf of the plaintiff for litigation related to two specific brand models of IVC filters. Dr. Bikdeli has not been involved in the litigation in 2022–2024, nor has he received any compensation in 2022–2024. Dr. Bikdeli reports that he is a member of the Medical Advisory Board for the North American Thrombosis Forum and serves in the Data Safety and Monitory Board of the NAIL-IT trial funded by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute and Translational Sciences. Dr. Bikdeli is a collaborating consultant with the International Consulting Associates and the US Food and Drug Administration in a study to generate knowledge about the utilization, predictors, retrieval, and safety of IVC filters. Dr. Bikdeli receives compensation as an Associated Editor for the New England Journal of Medicine Journal Watch Cardiology, as an Associate Editor for Thrombosis Research, and as an Executive Associate Editor for JACC, and is a Section Editor for Thrombosis and Haemostasis (no compensation). Dr. Bates receives unencumbered salary support from McMaster University as the Eli Lilly May Cohen Chair in Women's Health. She has received honoraria from Leo Pharma Canada, Inc.; ROVI; and Sanofi. She serves on the Medical Advisory Board for the Foundation for Women and Girls with Blood Disorders (FWGBD).</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39277905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.thromres.2024.109147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0049-3848(24)00279-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>