<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39270761</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-3476</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>665</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of pharmaceutics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Pharm</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Elucidating acceptance and clinical indications to support the rational design of drug-eluting contact lenses.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>124702</StartPage><MedlinePgn>124702</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2024.124702</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0378-5173(24)00936-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The advent of drug-eluting contact lenses (DECLs) has opened up new avenues for the treatment of eye diseases. DECLs is expected to partially overcome the shortcomings of eye drops due to single-dose packaging, accurate dosing, prolonged drug elution behavior, and simplified dosing procedures. Currently, a significant proportion of the DECLs design effort has been directed towards enhancing the compatibility of contact lenses with drugs. The appropriate elution time for the drug remains unclear. Additionally, it is ambiguous for which ophthalmic diseases DECLs offers the greatest therapeutic advantage. To rationally design DECLs in practice, it is necessary to understand the acceptance of DECLs by patients and practitioners and to clarify the indications for DECLs. This review will first focus on the acceptance of DECLs by different patients and practitioners and discuss the factors that influence its acceptance. Secondly, this review presents an overview of the current effectiveness of DECLs treatments in animals and in the clinical phase, with a particular focus on the suitability of DECLs for the treatment of ophthalmic diseases. Overall, patients and practitioners expressed positive attitudes towards DECLs. However, this is related to factors such as DECLs' treatment cycle, safety, and price. In addition, DECLs has good application prospects for ocular wound healing, postoperative management, and treatment of contact lenses-related complications. Furthermore, chronic diseases such as glaucoma that necessitate long-term medication and intraocular diseases that require implants or injections represent additional potential applications for DECLs. It is hoped that this review will facilitate a deeper understanding of DECLs acceptance and indications, thereby supporting the rational design of DECLs. At the same time, this review provides a reference for the design of other drug-device combination products.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Qiang</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmacy, Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Inflammation and Molecular Drug Targets, Nantong University, Nantong 226001, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Nantong University and First People's Hospital of Nantong City, Nantong 226001, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Linlin</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering, Shandong Business Institute, Yantai 264670, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Su</LastName><ForeName>Gaoxing</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmacy, Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Inflammation and Molecular Drug Targets, Nantong University, Nantong 226001, China. Electronic address: sugaoxing@ntu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Pharm</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7804127</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0378-5173</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Acceptability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cyclosporine A (PubChem CID: 5284373)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dexamethasone (PubChem CID: 5743)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Drug-eluting contact lenses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gatifloxacin (PubChem CID: 5379)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Indications</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Latanoprost (PubChem CID: 5311221)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rational design</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Timolol maleate (PubChem CID: 5281056)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39270761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2024.124702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0378-5173(24)00936-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>