<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39276745</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-3336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>480</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of hazardous materials</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Hazard Mater</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Manganese enhances cadmium tolerance in barley through mediating chloroplast integrity, antioxidant system, and HvNRAMP expression.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>135777</StartPage><MedlinePgn>135777</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2024.135777</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0304-3894(24)02356-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Cadmium (Cd) is a toxic heavy metal that poses risks to crop production and food safety worldwide. This study evaluated whether manganese (Mn) addition could mitigate Cd toxicity and reduce Cd accumulation in barley seedlings. Hydroponically grown seedlings of Cd-tolerant (WSBZ) and Cd-sensitive (Dong17) barley cultivars were treated with 0.1 μM and 1 μM Cd as well as 0.2 mM Mn alone and in a combination with 0.1 or 1.0 μM Cd for 21 days. Cd exposure caused the dramatic alteration of growth and physiological parameters by disrupting chloroplast, and increased Cd accumulation in both genotypes. However, Mn addition markedly alleviated the negative impacts of all examined parameters caused by Cd stress. Cd addition enhanced expression of anti-oxidative enzyme related genes, including HvSOD, HvCAT, HvAPX, HvPOD in the two barley genotypes exposed to Cd stress. The expression analysis showed nearly all HvNRAMPs genes are dramatically up regulated by both Mn and Cd, with WSBZ having higher expression than Dong 17. Notably, HvNRAMP1 showed the highest expression due to Mn addition, highlighting its crucial role in Mn uptake and transportation in barley. Moreover, Cd stress and Mn addition increased and suppressed the expression of HvYSL5, HvHMA2 and HvHMA3, respectively. Conversely, the expression of HvYSL2, HvIRT1 and HvMTP8 was upregulated by both Mn and Cd treatments, with a further increase observed in the combined Cd and Mn treatments. It may be concluded that sufficient Mn supply is quite important for reducing Cd uptake and accumulation in plants.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanwal</LastName><ForeName>Farah</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agronomy, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Zijingang Campus, Hangzhou 310029, PR China. Electronic address: farahkanwal01@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Riaz</LastName><ForeName>Asad</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Queensland Alliance for Agriculture and Food Innovation, The University of Queensland, Saint Lucia, Brisbane 4072, Australia; Centre of Excellence for Plant Success in Nature and Agriculture, Saint Lucia, Brisbane 4072, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Ameer</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agronomy, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Zijingang Campus, Hangzhou 310029, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Shafaqat</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Sciences, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad 38000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Guoping</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agronomy, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Zijingang Campus, Hangzhou 310029, PR China; Zhongyuan Institute, Zhejiang University, Zhengzhou 450000, China. Electronic address: zhanggp@zju.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Hazard Mater</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9422688</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0304-3894</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antioxidative stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cadmium</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Interaction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Manganese</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NRAMP</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. Conflicts of Interest The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39276745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2024.135777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0304-3894(24)02356-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>