<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39270899</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>279</Volume><Issue>Pt 4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Recent advances in sustainable biopolymer-based nanocomposites for smart food packaging: A review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>135583</StartPage><MedlinePgn>135583</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135583</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)06391-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The main goal of emerging food-packaging technologies is to address environmental issues and minimize their impact, while also guaranteeing food quality and safety for consumers. Bio-based polymers have drawn significant interest as a means to reduce the usage and environmental impact of petroleum-derived polymeric products. Therefore, this current review highlights on the biopolymer blends, various biodegradable bio-nanocomposites materials, and their synthesis and characterization techniques recently used in the smart food packaging industry. In addition, some insights on potential challenges as well as possibilities in future smart food packaging applications are thoroughly explored. Nanocomposite packaging materials derived from biopolymers have the highest potential for use in improved smart food packaging that possesses bio-functional properties. Nanomaterials are utilized for improving the thermal, mechanical, and gas barrier attributes of bio-based polymers while maintaining their biodegradable and non-toxic qualities. The packaging films that were developed exhibited enhanced barrier qualities against carbon dioxide, oxygen, and water vapour. Additionally, they demonstrated better mechanical strength, thermal stability, and antibacterial activity. More research is needed to develop and use smart food packaging materials based on bio-nanocomposites on a worldwide scale, while removing plastic packaging.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mishra</LastName><ForeName>Bishwambhar</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Chaitanya Bharathi Institute of Technology, Hyderabad 500075, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Panda</LastName><ForeName>Jibanjyoti</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nano-biotechnology and Translational Knowledge Laboratory, Department of Applied Biology, University of Science &amp; Technology Meghalaya, Baridua, 793101, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mishra</LastName><ForeName>Awdhesh Kumar</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan 38541, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nath</LastName><ForeName>Pinku Chandra</ForeName><Initials>PC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology, Uttaranchal University, School of Applied and Life Sciences, Dehradun, Uttarakhand 248007, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nayak</LastName><ForeName>Prakash Kumar</ForeName><Initials>PK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering and Technology, Central Institute of Technology Kokrajhar, Kokrajhar 783370, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahapatra</LastName><ForeName>Uttara</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical Engineering, National Institute of Technology Agartala, Jirania 799046, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Minaxi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Centre for Life Science and Healthcare, Nottingham Ningbo China Beacons of Excellence Research and Innovation Institute (CBI), University of Nottingham Ningbo China, Ningbo 315000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chopra</LastName><ForeName>Hitesh</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biosciences, Saveetha Institute of Medical and Technical Sciences, Chennai 602105, India; Centre for Research Impact &amp; Outcome, Chitkara College of Pharmacy, Chitkara University, Rajpura, 140401, Punjab, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohanta</LastName><ForeName>Yugal Kishore</ForeName><Initials>YK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nano-biotechnology and Translational Knowledge Laboratory, Department of Applied Biology, University of Science &amp; Technology Meghalaya, Baridua, 793101, India; Centre for Herbal Pharmacology and Environmental Sustainability, Chettinad Hospital and Research Institute, Chettinad Academy of Research and Education, Kelambakkam 603103, India. Electronic address: ykmohanta@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sridhar</LastName><ForeName>Kandi</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology, Karpagam Academy of Higher Education (Deemed to be University), Coimbatore 641021, India. Electronic address: sridhar4647@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biopolymer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanocomposites</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanomaterials</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Smart food packaging</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sustainability</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39270899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)06391-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>