<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39273870</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2223-7747</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Plants (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Plants (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mitigating the Accumulation of Mercury (Hg) and Lead (Pb) through Humic Acid Application under Aquaponic Conditions Using Watercress (<i>Nasturtium officinale</i> R. Br.) as a Model Plant.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2386</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/plants13172386</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In aquaponic farming, there is a potential risk that heavy metals will contaminate the water, which can lead to heavy metal accumulation in the plants. Our research investigated the accumulation of mercury (Hg) and lead (Pb) under aquaponic conditions and the effect of their increased presence on the uptake of other macro- and micronutrients using watercress (<i>Nasturtium officinale</i>) as a model plant. The potential modifying effect of humic acid on heavy metal accumulation was also investigated. Adding Hg and Pb increased the mercury and lead levels of the watercress plants to over 300 µg kg<sup>-1</sup>, while the addition of humic acid significantly reduced the concentration of both mercury and lead in the plants compared to plants treated with heavy metals alone, from 310.647 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> to 196.320 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> for Hg and from 313.962 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> to 203.508 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> for Pb. For Fe and Mn, higher values were obtained for the Hg + humic acid treatments (188.13 mg kg<sup>-1</sup> and 6423.92 µg kg<sup>-1</sup>, respectively) and for the Pb + humic acid treatments (198.26 mg kg<sup>-1</sup> and 6454.31 µg kg<sup>-1</sup>, respectively). Conversely, the Na, K, Cu levels were lower compared to those in plants treated with heavy metals alone. Our results demonstrated that watercress can accumulate mercury, leading to high levels, even above food safety standards, highlighting the importance of water quality control in aquaponic systems. Furthermore, these results suggest that watercress could be used as a natural filter in recirculation systems. The addition of humic acid significantly reduced the accumulation of heavy metals and altered the element content in the plant.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lelesz</LastName><ForeName>Judit Éva</ForeName><Initials>JÉ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3547-9894</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Husbandry, Institute of Animal Science, Biotechnology and Nature Conservation, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences and Environmental Management, University of Debrecen, Böszörményi Str. 138, H-4032 Debrecen, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Csajbók</LastName><ForeName>József</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0281-2590</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Crop Production, Applied Ecology and Plant Breeding, Institute of Crop Sciences, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences and Environmental Management, University of Debrecen, Böszörményi Str. 138, H-4032 Debrecen, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Molnár</LastName><ForeName>Péter István</ForeName><Initials>PI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0004-6760-7365</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Husbandry, Institute of Animal Science, Biotechnology and Nature Conservation, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences and Environmental Management, University of Debrecen, Böszörményi Str. 138, H-4032 Debrecen, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Virág</LastName><ForeName>István Csaba</ForeName><Initials>IC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Crop Production, Applied Ecology and Plant Breeding, Institute of Crop Sciences, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences and Environmental Management, University of Debrecen, Böszörményi Str. 138, H-4032 Debrecen, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kutasy</LastName><ForeName>Erika Tünde</ForeName><Initials>ET</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0683-129X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Crop Production, Applied Ecology and Plant Breeding, Institute of Crop Sciences, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences and Environmental Management, University of Debrecen, Böszörményi Str. 138, H-4032 Debrecen, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Plants (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596181</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2223-7747</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">aquaponics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">element content</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">heavy metal bioaccumulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">humic acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lead (Pb)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mercury (Hg)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39273870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11396911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants13172386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">plants13172386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>FAO . The State of World Fisheries and Aquaculture 2022. FAO; Rome, Italy: 2022. Towards Blue Transformation.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4060/cc0461en</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Europe Aquaponics Market Size, Share &amp; Industry Trends Analysis Report by Facility Type, by Equipment, by Component, by Produce (Fish, Fruits &amp; Vegetables and Others), by Application, by Growing Mechanism, by Country and Growth Forecast, 2023–2030. KBV-15743 Research Report. 2023.  [(accessed on 10 June 2024)].  112p. Available online:  https://www.kbvresearch.com/europe-aquaponics-market/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Aquaponics Market Size, Share &amp; Industry Trends Analysis Report by Facility Type, by Equipment, by Component, by Produce (Fish, Fruits &amp; Vegetables and Others), by Application, By Growing Mechanism, by Regional Outlook and Forecast, 2023–2030. KBV-15741 Research Report. 2023.  [(accessed on 10 June 2024)].  341p. Available online:  https://www.kbvresearch.com/aquaponics-market/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laidlaw J., Magee L. Towards urban food sovereignty: The trials and tribulations of community-based aquaponics enterprises in Milwaukee and Melbourne. Local Environ. 2014;21:573–590. doi: 10.1080/13549839.2014.986716.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13549839.2014.986716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villarroel M., Junge R., Komives T., König B., Plaza I., Bittsánszky A., Joly A. Survey of Aquaponics in Europe. Water. 2016;8:468. doi: 10.3390/w8100468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w8100468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández-Cabanás V.M., Delgado A., Lobillo-Eguíbar J.R., Pérez-Urrestarazu L. Early production of strawberry in aquaponic systems using commercial hydroponic bands. Aquac. Eng. 2022;97:102242. doi: 10.1016/j.aquaeng.2022.102242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aquaeng.2022.102242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilles S., Ismiño R., Sánchez H., David F., Núñez J., Dugué R., Darias M.J., Römer U. An integrated closed system for fish-plankton aquaculture in Amazonian fresh water. Animal. 2014;8:1319–1328. doi: 10.1017/S1751731114001165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1751731114001165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24849417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li G., Tao L., Li X.L., Peng L., Song C.F., Dai L.L., Xie L. Design and performance of a novel rice hydroponic biofilter in a pond-scale aquaponic recirculating system. Ecol. Eng. 2018;125:1–10. doi: 10.1016/j.ecoleng.2018.10.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoleng.2018.10.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balláné Kovács A., Kremper R., Kincses I., Leviczky Á. Influences of different organic fertilizers on nutrients of humic sandy soil and on the growth of Spinach (Spinacia oleracea L.) Acta Agrar. Debreceniensis. 2016;70:23–28. doi: 10.34101/actaagrar/70/1812.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34101/actaagrar/70/1812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irhayyim T., Fehér M., Lelesz J., Bercsényi M., Bársony P. Nutrient removal efficiency and growth of watercress (Nasturtium officinale) under different harvesting regimes in integrated recirculating aquaponic systems for rearing common carp (Cyprinus carpio L.) Water. 2020;12:1419. doi: 10.3390/w12051419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w12051419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinela J., Carvalho A.M., Ferreira I.C. Watercress. In: Jaiswal A.K., editor. Nutritional Composition and Antioxidant Properties of Fruits and Vegetables. 1st ed. Academic Press; Cambridge, MA, USA: 2020. pp. 197–219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pignata G., Ertani A., Casale M., Niñirola D., Egea-Gilabert C., Fernández J.A., Nicola S. Understanding the Postharvest Phytochemical Composition Fates of Packaged Watercress (Nasturtium officinale R. Br.) Grown in a Floating System and Treated with Bacillus subtilis as PGPR. Plants. 2022;11:589. doi: 10.3390/plants11050589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants11050589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8912852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35270058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hecht S.S., Chung F.L., Richie J.P., Jr., Akerkar S.A., Borukhova A., Skowronski L., Carmella S.G. Effects of watercress consumption on metabolism of a tobacco-specific lung carcinogen in smokers. Cancer Epidemiol. Biomark. Prev. A Publ. Am. Assoc. Cancer Res. Cosponsored By Am. Soc. Prev. Oncol. 1995;4:877–884.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8634661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gill C.I., Haldar S., Boyd L.A., Bennett R., Whiteford J., Butler M., Rowland I.R. Watercress supplementation in diet reduces lymphocyte DNA damage and alters blood antioxidant status in healthy adults. Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 2007;85:504–510. doi: 10.1093/ajcn/85.2.504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ajcn/85.2.504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17284750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duman F., Ozturk F. Nickel accumulation and its effect on biomass, protein content and antioxidative enzymes in roots and leaves of watercress (Nasturtium officinale R. Br.) J. Environ. Sci. 2010;22:526–532. doi: 10.1016/S1001-0742(09)60137-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1001-0742(09)60137-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20617728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klimek-Szczykutowicz M., Szopa A., Blicharska E., Dziurka M., Komsta Ł., Ekiert H. Bioaccumulation of selected macro-and microelements and their impact on antioxidant properties and accumulation of glucosinolates and phenolic acids in in vitro cultures of Nasturtium officinale (watercress) microshoots. Food Chem. 2019;300:125184. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2019.125184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2019.125184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31351261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan A.G. Relationships between chromium biomagnification ratio, accumulation factor, and mycorrhizae in plants growing on tannery effluent-polluted soil. Environ. Int. 2001;26:417–423. doi: 10.1016/S0160-4120(01)00022-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0160-4120(01)00022-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11392761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du T., Wang J., Zhang L., Wang S., Yang C., Xie L., Sun J., Zhang W., Wang J. Missing-linker engineering of Eu (III)-doped UiO-MOF for enhanced detection of heavy metal ions. Chem. Eng. J. 2022;431:134050. doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2021.134050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2021.134050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manzoor J., Sharma M., Wani K.A. Heavy metals in vegetables and their impact on the nutrient quality of vegetables: A review. J. Plant Nutr. 2018;41:1744–1763. doi: 10.1080/01904167.2018.1462382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01904167.2018.1462382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ALSalman M.R.M., Dawood T.N. Lead, Cadmium and Mercury Concentrations in the Tap, River and Well Water with Different Treatment from Regions along Tigris River. Res Mil. 2023;13:2949–2957.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franke C., Studinger G., Berger G., Böhling S., Bruckmann U., Cohors-Fresenborg D., Jöhncke U. The assessment of bioaccumulation. Chemosphere. 1994;29:1501–1514. doi: 10.1016/0045-6535(94)90281-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0045-6535(94)90281-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Zhou Q., Ren B., Luo J., Yuan J., Ding X., Yao X. Reviews of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology. Volume 51. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2020. Trends and health risks of dissolved heavy metal pollution in global river and lake water from 1970 to 2017; pp. 1–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31011831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y., Wang D., Wei L., Zhang X., Song B. Bioaccumulation of heavy metals in plant leaves from Yan׳ an city of the Loess Plateau, China. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 2014;110:82–88. doi: 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2014.08.021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2014.08.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25199586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutleb A.C., Kranz A., Nechay G., Toman A. Heavy metal concentrations in livers and kidneys of the otter (Lutra lutra) from Central Europe. Bull. Environ. Contam. Toxicol. 1998;60:273–279. doi: 10.1007/s001289900621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s001289900621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9470989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorea J.G. Fish meal in animal feed and human exposure to persistent bioaccumulative and toxic substances. J. Food Prot. 2006;69:2777–2785. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X-69.11.2777.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X-69.11.2777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17133828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashemi M., Rajabi S., Eghbalian M., Suliburska J., Nasab H. Demographic and anthropometric characteristics and their effect on the concentration of heavy metals (arsenic, lead, chromium, zinc) in children and adolescents. Heliyon. 2023;9:e13621. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e13621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e13621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9950940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36846698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisiak-Zielińska M., Borowiak K., Budka A., Kanclerz J., Janicka E., Kaczor A., Zyromski A., Biniak-Pieróg M., Podawca K., Mleczek M., et al. How polluted are cities in central Europe?-Heavy metal contamination in Taraxacum officinale and soils collected from different land use areas of three representative cities. Chemosphere. 2021;266:129113. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.129113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.129113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33310525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerra F., Trevizam A.R., Muraoka T., Marcante N.C., Canniatti-Brazaca S.G. Heavy metals in vegetables and potential risk for human health. Sci. Agric. 2012;69:54–60. doi: 10.1590/S0103-90162012000100008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S0103-90162012000100008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen P. Distribution of mercury in the soft tissues of the blue tilapia Oreochromis aureus (Steindachner) after acute exposure to mercury (II) chloride. Bull. Environ. Contam. Toxicol. 1994;53:675–683. doi: 10.1007/BF00196939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF00196939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7833603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voegborlo R.B., El-Methnani A.M., Abedin M.Z. Mercury, cadmium and lead content of canned tuna fish. Food Chem. 1999;67:341–345. doi: 10.1016/S0308-8146(98)00008-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0308-8146(98)00008-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L., Wong M.H. Environmental mercury contamination in China: Sources and impacts. Environ. Int. 2007;33:108–121. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2006.06.022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2006.06.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16914205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Järup L. Hazards of heavy metal contamination. Br. Med. Bull. 2003;68:167–182. doi: 10.1093/bmb/ldg032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bmb/ldg032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14757716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kummer U., Pacyna J., Pacyna E., Friedrich R. Assessment of heavy metal releases from the use phase of road transport in Europe. Atmos. Environ. 2009;43:640–647. doi: 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2008.10.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2008.10.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Liu G., Gao S., Zhang Z., Huang L. Effect of humic acid on phytoremediation of heavy metal contaminated sediment. J. Hazard. Mater. Adv. 2023;9:100235. doi: 10.1016/j.hazadv.2023.100235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hazadv.2023.100235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aşik B.B., Turan M.A., Çelik H., Katkat A.V. Effects of humic substances on plant growth and mineral nutrients uptake of wheat (Triticum durum cv. Salihli) under conditions of salinity. Asian J. Crop Sci. 2009;1:87–95. doi: 10.3923/ajcs.2009.87.95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3923/ajcs.2009.87.95</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydin A., Kant C., Turan M. Humic acid application al-leviate salinity stress of bean (Phaseolus vulgaris L.) plants decreasing membrane leakage. Afr. J. Agric. Res. 2012;7:1073–1086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atiyeh R.M., Lee S., Edwards C.A., Arancon N.Q., Metzger J.D. The influence of humic acids derived from earthworm-processed organic wastes on plant growth. Bioresour. Technol. 2002;84:7–14. doi: 10.1016/S0960-8524(02)00017-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0960-8524(02)00017-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12137272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tattini M., Bertoni P., Landi A., Traversim M.L. Effect of humic acids on growth anq biomass partitioning of containergrown olive plants. Acta Hortic. 1991;294:75–80. doi: 10.17660/ActaHortic.1991.294.7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17660/ActaHortic.1991.294.7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valdrighi M.M., Pera A., Agnolucci M., Frassinetti S., Lunardi D., Vallini G. Effects of compost-derived humic acids on vegetable biomass production and microbial growth within a plant (Cichorium intybus)-soil system: A comparative study. Agric. Ecosyst. Environ. 1996;58:133–144. doi: 10.1016/0167-8809(96)01031-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0167-8809(96)01031-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birolo M., Bordignon F., Trocino A., Fasolato L., Pascual A., Godoy S., Nicoletto C., Maucieria C., Xiccato G. Effects of stocking density on the growth and flesh quality of rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) reared in a low-tech aquaponic system. Aquaculture. 2020;529:735653. doi: 10.1016/j.aquaculture.2020.735653.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2020.735653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyson R.V., Treadwell D.D., Simonne E.H. Opportunities and challenges to sustainability in aquaponic systems. HortTechnology. 2011;21:6–13. doi: 10.21273/HORTTECH.21.1.6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21273/HORTTECH.21.1.6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bordignon F., Gasco L., Birolo M., Trocino A., Caimi C., Ballarin C., Bortoletti M., Nicoletto C., Maucieri C., Xiccato G. Performance and fillet traits of rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) fed different levels of Hermetia illucens meal in a low-tech aquaponic system. Aquaculture. 2022;546:737279. doi: 10.1016/j.aquaculture.2021.737279.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2021.737279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calone R., Pennisi G., Morgenstern R., Sanyé-Mengual E., Lorleberg W., Dapprich P., Gianquinto G. Improving water management in European catfish recirculating aquaculture systems through catfish-lettuce aquaponics. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;687:759–767. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.06.167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.06.167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31412479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goddek S., Körner O. A fully integrated simulation model of multi-loop aquaponics: A case study for system sizing in different environments. Agric. Syst. 2019;171:143–154. doi: 10.1016/j.agsy.2019.01.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.agsy.2019.01.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsen R.L., Hasan M.R. A limited supply of fishmeal: Impact on future increases in global aquaculture production. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2012;27:120–128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) The State of the World Fisheries and Aquaculture 2012 FAO Fisheries and Aquaculture Department. Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO); Rome, Italy: 2012. p. 209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broadley M.R., Willey N.J., Wilkins J.C., Baker A.J.M., Mead A., White P.J. Phylogenetic variation in heavy metal accumulation in angiosperms. New Phytol. 2001;152:9–27. doi: 10.1046/j.0028-646x.2001.00238.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.0028-646x.2001.00238.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35974475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovács A.B., Kincses I., Vágó I., Loch J., Filep T. Effect of Application of Nitrogen and Different Nitrogen-Sulfur Ratios on the Quality and Quantity of Mustard Seed. Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal. 2009;40:453–461. doi: 10.1080/00103620802694399.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00103620802694399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joint Decree No. 17 of 1999 of Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development and of the Ministry of Health on Sanitary Requirements of Food Processing and Marketing (FAOLEX No: LEX-FAOC016796)  [(accessed on 9 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.fao.org/faolex/results/details/en/c/LEX-FAOC016796/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA Panel on Contaminants in the Food Chain (CONTAM); Scientific Opinion on the risk for public health related to the presence of mercury and methylmercury in food. EFSA J. 2012;10:2985. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2012.2985.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2012.2985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klimek-Szczykutowicz M., Szopa A., Ekiert H. Chemical composition, traditional and professional use in medicine, application in environmental protection, position in food and cosmetics industries, and biotechnological studies of Nasturtium officinale (watercress)—A review. Fitoterapia. 2018;129:283–292. doi: 10.1016/j.fitote.2018.05.031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2018.05.031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29852261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kara Y. Bioaccumulation of cu, Zn and Ni from the wastewater by treated Nasturtium officinale. Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2005;2:63–67. doi: 10.1007/BF03325859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF03325859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duman F., Leblebici Z., Aksoy A. Growth and bioaccumulation characteristics of watercress (Nasturtium officinale R. Br.) exposed to cadmium, cobalt and chromium. Chem. Speciat. Bioavailab. 2009;21:257–265. doi: 10.3184/095422909X12578511366924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3184/095422909X12578511366924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozturk F., Duman F., Leblebici Z., Temizgul R. Arsenic accumulation and biological responses of watercress (Nasturtium officinale R. Br.) exposed to arsenite. Environ. Exp. Bot. 2010;69:167–174. doi: 10.1016/j.envexpbot.2010.03.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envexpbot.2010.03.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydin D., Coskun O.F. Comparison of edta-enhanced phytoextraction strategies with Nasturtium officinale (Watercress) on an artificially arsenic contaminated water. Pak. J. Bot. 2013;45:1423–1429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin L., Luo L., Liao M., Zhang X., Yang D. Cadmium Accumulation Characteristic of Emerged Plant Nasturtium officinale R.Br. Resour Env. Yangtze Basin. 2015;4:50–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang K., Lin L., Chen F., Liao M., Wang J., Tang Y., Lai Y., Liang D., Xia H., Wang X., et al. Effects of live Myriophyllum aquaticum and its straw on cadmium accumulation in Nasturtium officinale. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 2017;24:22503–22509. doi: 10.1007/s11356-017-9928-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-017-9928-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28803379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordeiro C., Favas P.J.C., Pratas J., Sarkar S.K., Venkatachalam P. Uranium accumulation in aquatic macrophytes in an uraniferous region: Relevance to natural attenuation. Chemosphere. 2016;156:76–87. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.04.105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.04.105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27164268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li K., Lin L., Wang J., Xia H., Liang D., Wang X., Liao M., Wang L., Liu L., Chen C., et al. Hyperaccumulator straw improves the cadmium phytoextraction efficiency of emergent plant Nasturtium officinale. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2017;189:1–8. doi: 10.1007/s10661-017-6106-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-017-6106-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28681323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinulingga N., Nurtjahja K., Karim A. Fitoremediasi logam merkuri (Hg) pada media air oleh kangkung air (Ipomoea aquatica Forsk.) Phytoremediation of mercury (Hg) in water medium by warescress (Ipomoea aquatica Forsk.) BioLink. 2015;2:75–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission Regulation (EU) 2023/915 of 25 April 2023 on maximum levels for certain contaminants in food and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006. Off. J. Eur. Union. L. 2023;119:103–157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan N., Khan J., Ullah R., Ali K., Jones D.A., Khan M.E.H. Heavy Metals Contaminants in Watercress (Nasturtium officinale R. BR.): Toxicity and Risk Assessment for Humans along the Swat River Basin, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan. Sustainability. 2022;14:4690. doi: 10.3390/su14084690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su14084690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Jassir M.S., Shaker A., Khaliq M.A. Deposition of heavy metals on green leafy vegetables sold on roadsides of Riyadh City, Saudi Arabia. Bull. Environ. Contam. Toxicol. 2005;75:1020–1027. doi: 10.1007/s00128-005-0851-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00128-005-0851-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16400593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martín-León V., Rubio C., Rodríguez-Hernández Á., Zumbado M., Acosta-Dacal A., Henríquez-Hernández L.A., Boada L.D., Travieso-Aja M.d.M., Luzardo O.P. Evaluation of Essential, Toxic and Potentially Toxic Elements in Leafy Vegetables Grown in the Canary Islands. Toxics. 2023;11:442. doi: 10.3390/toxics11050442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxics11050442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10222910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37235256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahu G.K., Upadhyay S., Sahoo B.B. Mercury induced phytotoxicity and oxidative stress in wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) plants. Physiol. Mol. Biol. Plants. 2012;18:21–31. doi: 10.1007/s12298-011-0090-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12298-011-0090-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3550531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23573037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaughan D., Malcolm R.E. Influence of humic substances ongrowth and physiological processes. In: Vaughan D., Malcolm R.E., editors. Soil Organic Matter and Biological Activity. Martinus Nijhoff; Dordrecht, The Netherlands: 1985. pp. 37–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaughan D., Malcolm R.E., Ord B.G. Influence of humic substanceson biochemical processes in plants. In: Vaughan. D., Malcolm R.E., editors. Soil Organic Matter and Biological Activity. Martinus Nijhoff; Dordrecht, The Netherlands: 1985. pp. 78–108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaughan D. Effect of humic substances on metabolic processes. In: Burns R.G., Dell’Agnola G., Miele S., Nardi S., Savioni G., Schnitzer M., Sequi P., Vaughan D., Visser S.A., editors. Humic Substances: Effects on Soil and Plants. Ramo Editoriale degli Agricoltori; Rome, Italy: 1986. pp. 54–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visser S.A. Effects of humic substances on plant growth. In: Burns R.G., Dell’Agnola G., Miele S., Nardi S., Savioni G., Schnitzer M., Sequi P., Vaughan D., Visser S.A., editors. Humic Substances: Effects on Soil and Plants. Ramo Editoriale degli Agricoltori; Rome, Italy: 1986. pp. 89–135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berbara R.L.L., Garcia A.C. Humic substances and plant defensemetabolism. In: Ahmad P., Wani M.R., editors. Physiological Mechanisms and Adaptation Strategies in Plants under Changing Environment. Springer Science-Business Media; New York, NY, USA: 2014. pp. 297–319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calvo P., Nelson L., Kloepper J.W. Agricultural uses of plant biostimulants. Plant Soil. 2014;383:3–41. doi: 10.1007/s11104-014-2131-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11104-014-2131-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olk D.C., Dinnes D.L., Scoresby J.R., Callaway C.R., Darlington J.W. Humic products in agriculture: Potential benefits and research challenges—A review. J. Soils Sediments. 2018;18:2881–2891. doi: 10.1007/s11368-018-1916-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11368-018-1916-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldotto M.A., Baldotto L.E.B. Initial performance of corn in response to treatment of seeds with humic acids isolated from bokashi. Rev. Ceres. 2016;63:62–67. doi: 10.1590/0034-737X201663010009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0034-737X201663010009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ampong K., Thilakaranthna M.S., Gorim L.Y. Understanding the Role of Humic Acids on Crop Performance and Soil Health. Front. Agron. 2022;4:848621. doi: 10.3389/fagro.2022.848621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fagro.2022.848621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Zhi L., Zhou S., Xie F. Effects of mercury binding by humic acid and humic acid resistance on mercury stress in rice plants under high Hg/humic acid concentration ratios. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 2020;27:18650–18660. doi: 10.1007/s11356-020-08328-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-08328-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32200472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno F., Anderson C.W.N., Stewart R.B., Robinson B.H., Ghomshei M., Meech J. Induced plant uptake and transport of mercury in the presence of sulphur-containing ligands and humic acid. New Phytol. 2005;166:445–454. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01361.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01361.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15819909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Yang X., Zhang S., Tian Y., Guo W., Wang J. The influence of humic acids on the accumulation of lead (Pb) and cadmium (Cd) in tobacco leaves grown in different soils. J. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr. 2013;13:43–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasozi N., Tandlich R., Fick M., Kaiser H., Wilhelmi B. Iron supplementation and management in aquaponic systems: A review. Aquac. Rep. 2019;15:100221. doi: 10.1016/j.aqrep.2019.100221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aqrep.2019.100221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y., Clapp C.E., Magen H. Mechanisms of plant growth stimulation by humic substances: The role of organo-iron complexes. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr. 2004;50:1089–1095. doi: 10.1080/00380768.2004.10408579.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00380768.2004.10408579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bulut F., Akinci S. The effect of salinity on growth and nutrient composition in broad bean (Vicia faba L.) seedlings. Fresenius Environ. Bull. 2010;19:2901–2910.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sönmez F., Alp Ş., Yasar O. The effects of humic acid application on the nutrient contents and heavy metals in organs of marigold (Tagetes erecta L.) Fresenius Environ. Bull. 2017;26:5340–5348.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khaled H., Fawy H. Effect of Different Levels of Humic Acids on the Nutrient Content, Plant Growth, and Soil Properties under Conditions of Salinity. Soil Water Res. 2011;6:21–29. doi: 10.17221/4/2010-SWR.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17221/4/2010-SWR</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hungarian Standards Institution; Budapest, Hungary: Jan 11, 2015. Nyomelemek Meghatározása. Nyomás Alatti Feltárás. (Foodstuffs—Determination of Trace Elements—Pressure Digestion) (In Hungarian)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hungarian Standards Institution; Budapest, Hungary: Dec 1, 2002. Nyomelemek Meghatározása. Higany Meghatározása Nyomás Alatti Feltárás Utáni Hideggőz-Atomabszorpciós Spektrometriával (CVAAS) (Foodstuffs. Determination of Trace Elements. Determination of Mercury by Cold-Vapour ATOMIC absorption Spectrometry (CVAAS) after PRESSURE digestion) (In Hungarian)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hungarian Standards Institution; Budapest, Hungary: Feb 6, 2017. Mintavételi és Elemzési Módszerek. A Kalcium-, Nátrium-, FOSZFOR-, magnézium-, Kálium-, VAS-, cink-, Réz-, Mangán-, Kobalt-, Molibdén- és Ólomtartalom Meghatározása ICP-AES-sel. (Animal FEEDING stuffs: Methods of Sampling and Analysis—Determination of CALCIUM, Sodium, Phosphorus, Magnesium, potassium, Iron, Zinc, Copper, Manganese, COBALT, molybdenum and Lead by ICP-AES) (In Hungarian)</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>