<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39271473</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhancing cider quality through co-fermentation with acid protease and esterase-producing Metschnikowia species and Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13891</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">To date, cider production has primarily relied on Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Introducing novel non-Saccharomyces yeasts can enhance the diversity of cider properties. Among these, the Metschnikowia genus stands out for its ability to produce hydrolytic enzymes that may impact the sensorial and technological properties of cider. This study focused on evaluating the impact of three Metschnikowia species - Metschnikowia koreensis (Mk), M. reukaufii (Mr), and M. pulcherrima (Mp) - which exhibit acid protease and esterase activity, on the quality enhancement of cider.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The research findings indicate that the overall quality of cider produced through co-fermentation with these species surpassed that of cider fermented with mono-fermentation of S. cerevisiae (Sc). The cider fermented with the Sc + Mk combination exhibited the lowest levels of harsh-tasting malic acid and higher levels of softer lactic acid. Sensory array analysis also demonstrated that the Sc + Mk fermented cider exhibited high sensor response values for compounds contributing to a complex overall olfactory composition and richness. Furthermore, the Sc + Mk fermented cider exhibited the highest total quantity and variety of volatile organic compounds (VOCs). Specifically, the concentrations of phenethyl alcohol, 3-methyl-1-butanol, ethyl octanoate, and decanoic acid were notably elevated in comparison with other groups.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study illustrates that Metschnikowia species, particularly M. koreensis, show significant potential as starters for cider due to their various technological properties, including acidity modulation, aroma enhancement, and color improvement. The findings of this study provide a foundation for improving cider quality by co-fermenting S. cerevisiae with innovative starter cultures. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Yuzheng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yuening</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liang</LastName><ForeName>Huipeng</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Technology, China Resources Beer (Holdings) Company Limited, Beijing, P.R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Sufang</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0009-0264-0742</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Xinping</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6547-3317</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Chaofan</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2707-4619</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>This work was supported by the High-level Talents Innovation and Entrepreneurship Project of Dalian (2021RQ093), and the Basic Research Project of Education Department of Liaoning Province (LJKZ0544)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metschnikowia species</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">VOCs profiles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">apple cider</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">co‐fermentation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">organic acids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">yeast</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39271473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Jagtap UB and Bapat VA, Wines from fruits other than grapes: current status and future prospectus. Food Biosci 9:80–96 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Way ML, Jones JE, Longo R, Dambergs RG and Swarts ND, A preliminary study of yeast strain influence on chemical and sensory characteristics of apple cider. Fermentation 8:2233–2241 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Álvarez R, Garces F, Louis EJ, Dequin S and Camarasa C, Beyond S. cerevisiae for winemaking: fermentation‐related trait diversity in the genus Saccharomyces. Food Microbiol 113:104270 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarko T, Kostrz M, Duda‐Chodak A, Semik‐Szczurak D, Sroka P and Senczyszyn T, The effect of apple cultivars and yeast strains on selected quality parameters and antioxidant activity of fermented apple beverages. CyTA‐J Food 16:892–900 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gänzle MG, Monnin L, Zheng J, Zhang L, Coton M, Sicard D et al., Starter culture development and innovation for novel fermented foods. Annu Rev Food Sci Technol 15:211–239 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu W, Zhu Y, Zhu R, Bai J, Qiu J, Wu Y et al., Insight into the characteristics of cider fermented by single and co‐culture with Saccharomyces cerevisiae and Schizosaccharomyces pombe based on metabolomic and transcriptomic approaches. LWT 163:113538 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang H, Cai G, Lu J and Plaza EG, The production and application of enzymes related to the quality of fruit wine. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 61:1–11 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lilly M, Bauer FF, Lambrechts MG, Swiegers JH, Cozzolino D and Pretorius IS, The effect of increased yeast alcohol acetyltransferase and esterase activity on the flavour profiles of wine and distillates. Yeast 23:641–659 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theron LW, Bely M and Divol B, Monitoring the impact of an aspartic protease (MpAPr1) on grape proteins and wine properties. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 102:5173–5183 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sui Y, Wollan D, McRae JM, Muhlack R, Capone DL, Godden P et al., Chemical and sensory profiles of sauvignon blanc wine following protein stabilization using a combined ultrafiltration/heat/protease treatment. Front Nutr 9:799809 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theron LW, Bely M and Divol B, Monitoring the impact of an aspartic protease (MpAPr1) on grape proteins and wine properties. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 12:5173–5183 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang BQ, Shen JY, Duan CQ and Yan GL, Use of indigenous Hanseniaspora vineae and Metschnikowia pulcherrima co‐fermentation with Saccharomyces cerevisiae to improve the aroma diversity of vidal blanc icewine. Front Microbiol 9:2303 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav AN, Sachan SG, Verma P, Kaushik R and Saxena AK, Cold active hydrolytic enzymes production by psychrotrophic Bacilli isolated from three sub‐glacial lakes of NW Indian Himalayas. J Basic Microbiol 56:294–307 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ianieva O and Podgorsky V, Enological potential of non‐Saccharomyces yeast strains of enological and brewery origin from Ukrainian collection of microorganisms. Mycology 29:203–215 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandolfi R, Marinelli F, Lazzarini A and Molinari F, Cell‐bound and extracellular carboxylesterase from Streptomyces: hydrolytic and synthetic activities. J Appl Microbiol 89:870–875 (2000).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Li Z, Zou S, Dong L, Lin X, Chen Y et al., Chemical composition and flavor characteristics of cider fermented with Saccharomyces cerevisiae and non‐Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Foods 12:3565 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Zhao N, Guo L, Li P, Gu S, Yuan J et al., In‐depth exploration on the effects of organic nitrogen addition during different fermentation periods on the quality of cider. LWT‐Food Sci Technol 187:115376 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H, Ma L, Chen J, Zhao F, Huang X, Dong X et al., Effect of aliphatic aldehydes on flavor formation in glutathione–ribose maillard reactions. Foods 12:217 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincenzis S, Marangon M, Tolin S and Curioni A, Protein evolution during the early stages of white winemaking and its relations with wine stability. Aust J Grape Wine Res 17:20–27 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team, R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. https://www.r-project.org/ [19 December 2023].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Gemert LJ ed, Compilations of Odour Threshold Values in Air, Water and Other Media, 2nd edn. Oliemans Punter, the Netherlands (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Good Scents Company, The Good Scents Company Information System. http://www.thegoodscentscompany.com/index.html [20 December 2023].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bornscheuer UT, Microbial carboxyl esterase: classification, properties and application in biocatalysis. FEMS Microbiol Rev 26:73–81 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bortolini DG, Benvenutti L, Demiate IM, Nogueira A, Alberti A and Zielinski AAF, A new approach to the use of apple pomace in cider making for the recovery of phenolic compounds. LWT 126:109316 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misery B, Legendre P, Rué O, Bouchart V, Guichard H, Laplace JM et al., Diversity and dynamics of bacterial and fungal communities in cider for distillation. Int J Food Microbiol 339:108987 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nissen P, Nielsen D and Arneborg N, Viable Saccharomyces cerevisiae cells at high concentrations cause early growth arrest of non‐Saccharomyces yeasts in mixed cultures by a cell‐cell contact mediated mechanism. Yeast 20:331–341 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bedriñana RP, Lobo AP, Madrera RR and Valles BS, Characteristics of ice juices and ciders made by cryo‐extraction with different cider apple varieties and yeast strains. Food Chem 310:125831 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosa MF and Sá‐Correia I, In vivo activation by ethanol of plasma membrane ATPase of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Appl Environ Microbiol 57:830–835 (1991).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamboa JCR, da Silva AJ, de Andrade Lima LL and Ferreira TA, Wine quality rapid detection using a compact electronic nose system: application focused on spoilage thresholds by acetic acid. LWT 108:377–384 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vicente J, Baran Y, Navascués E, Santos A, Calderón F, Marquina D et al., Biological management of acidity in wine industry: a review. Int J Food Microbiol 375:109726 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim DH, Hong YA and Park HD, Cofermentation of grape must by Issatchenkia orientalis and Saccharomyces cerevisiae reduces the malic acid content in wine. Biotechnol Lett 30:1633–1638 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Y, Pu D, Zhou X and Zhang Y, Recent progress in the study of taste characteristics and the nutrition and health properties of organic acids in foods. Foods 11:3408 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valentin D, Parr WV, Peyron D, Grose C and Ballester J, Colour as a driver of pinot noir wine quality judgments: an investigation involving French and New Zealand wine professionals. Food Qual Prefer 48:251–261 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso‐Salces RM, Guyot S, Herrero C, Berrueta LA, Drilleau JF, Gallo B et al., Chemometric classification of Basque and French ciders based on their total polyphenol contents and CIELab parameters. Food Chem 91:91–98 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Yang R, Zhang H, Wang S, Chen D and Lin S, Development of a flavor fingerprint by HS‐GC‐IMS with PCA for volatile compounds of Tricholoma matsutake singer. Food Chem 290:32–39 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S, Chen H and Sun B, Recent progress in food flavor analysis using gas chromatography‐ion mobility spectrometry (GC‐IMS). Food Chem 315:126158 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kliks J, Kawa‐Rygielska J, Gasiński A, Rębas J and Szumny A, Changes in the volatile composition of apple and apple/pear ciders affected by the different dilution rates in the continuous fermentation system. LWT‐Food Sci Technol 147:111630 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bingman MT, Hinkley JL, Bradley CP and Cole CA, Aroma profiles of dry‐hopped ciders produced with citra, galaxy, and mosaic hops. Appl Sci 12:310 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei J, Zhang Y, Qiu Y, Guo H, Ju H, Wang Y et al., Chemical composition, sensorial properties, and aroma‐active compounds of ciders fermented with Hanseniaspora osmophila and Torulaspora quercuum in co‐and sequential fermentations. Food Chem 306:125623 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swiegers JH, Bartowsky EJ, Henschke PA and Pretorius IS, Yeast and bacterial modulation of wine aroma and flavour. Aust J Grape Wine Res 11:139–173 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dzialo MC, Park R, Steensels J, Lievens B and Verstrepen KJ, Physiology, ecology and industrial applications of aroma formation in yeast. FEMS Microbiol Rev 41:S95–S128 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilela‐Moura A, Schuller D, Mendes‐Faia A, Silva RD, Chaves SR, Sousa MJ et al., The impact of acetate metabolism on yeast fermentative performance and wine quality: reduction of volatile acidity of grape musts and wines. Appl Microbiol Biot 89:271–280 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Y, Huang D, Lee PR and Liu SQ, Assessment of volatile and non‐volatile compounds in durian wines fermented with four commercial non‐Saccharomycesyeasts. J Sci Food Agr 96:1511–1521 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye M, Yue T and Yuan Y, Evolution of polyphenols and organic acids during the fermentation of apple cider. J Sci Food Agric 94:2951–2957 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binati RL, Lemos‐Junior WJFL, Luzzini G, Slaghenaufi D, Ugliano M and Torriani S, Contribution of non‐Saccharomyces yeasts to wine volatile and sensory diversity: a study on Lachancea thermotolerans, Metschnikowia spp. and Starmerella bacillaris strains isolated in Italy. Int J Food Microbiol 318:108470 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hazelwood LA, Daran JM, Maris AJA, Pronk JT and Dickinson JR, The Ehrlich pathway for fusel alcohol production: a century of research on Saccharomyces cerevisiae metabolism. Appl Environ Microbiol 74:3920 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Y and Du J, A comparative study of the effect of bacteria and yeasts communities on inoculated and spontaneously fermented apple cider. Food Microbiol 111:104195 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J and Liu SQ, Ester synthesis in aqueous media by lipase: Alcoholysis, esterification and substrate hydrophobicity. J Food Biochem 39:11–18 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comitini F, Gobbi M, Domizio P, Romani C, Lencioni L, Mannazzu I et al., Selected non‐Saccharomyces wine yeasts in controlled multistarter fermentations with Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Food Microbiol 28:873–882 (2011).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>