<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39273929</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2223-7747</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Plants (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Plants (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Bioassessment of Cd and Pb at Multiple Growth Stages of Wheat Grown in Texturally Different Soils Using Diffusive Gradients in Thin Films and Traditional Extractants: A Comparative Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2445</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/plants13172445</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The bioavailability of heavy metals in soil is a crucial factor in determining their potential uptake by plants and their subsequent entry into the food chain. Various methods, including traditional chemical extractants and the diffusive gradients in thin films (DGT) technique, are employed to assess this bioavailability. The bioavailability of heavy metals, particularly cadmium (Cd) and lead (Pb), is also influenced by soil texture and their concentrations in the soil solution. The primary objectives of this experiment were to compare and correlate the assessment of the Cd and Pb bioavailability using the DGT technique and traditional extractants across two soil textural classes: sandy clay loam (SCL) and clay loam (CL) at two contamination levels: aged contaminated (NC) and artificially contaminated (AC). The specific objectives included assessing the bioavailability of Cd and Pb at different growth stages of the wheat plant and correlating the DGT-based bioassessments of Cd and Pb with their concentrations in various plant parts at different growth stages. This study also compared the effectiveness of the DGT method and traditional extraction techniques in assessing the bioavailable fractions of Cd and Pb in soil. The regression analysis demonstrated strong positive correlations between the DGT method and various extraction methods. The results showed that the wheat plants grown in the AC soils exhibited lower root, shoot, and grain weights compared to those grown in the NC soils, indicating that metal contamination negatively impacts plant performance. The concentrations of Cd and Pb in the wheat tissues varied across different growth stages, with the highest levels observed during the grain filling (S3) and maturity (S4) stages. It is concluded that the in situ assessment of Cd and Pb though DGT was strongly and positively correlated with the Cd and Pb concentration in wheat plant parts at the maturity stage. A correlation and regression analysis of the DGT assessment and traditional extractants showed that the DGT method provides a reliable tool for assessing the bioavailability of Cd and Pb in soils and helped in developing sustainable soil management strategies to ensure the safety of agricultural products for human consumption.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaghaleh</LastName><ForeName>Hiba</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9513-1729</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Key Laboratory of Integrated Regulation and Resource Development on Shallow Lakes, Ministry of Education, College of Environment, Hohai University, Nanjing 210098, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rana</LastName><ForeName>Sana</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8325-8258</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Soil and Environmental Sciences, University of Agriculture, Faisalabad 38000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zia-Ur-Rehman</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9042-9171</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Soil and Environmental Sciences, University of Agriculture, Faisalabad 38000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Usman</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8804-3790</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Soil and Environmental Sciences, University of Agriculture, Faisalabad 38000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Mujahid</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Soil and Environmental Sciences, University of Agriculture, Faisalabad 38000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alharby</LastName><ForeName>Hesham F</ForeName><Initials>HF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Science, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Plant Biology Research Group, Department of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Science, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Majrashi</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, College of Science, Taif University, P.O. Box 11099, Taif 21944, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alamri</LastName><ForeName>Amnah M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0002-6747-9995</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Science, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abu Zeid</LastName><ForeName>Isam M</ForeName><Initials>IM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Science, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alhaj Hamoud</LastName><ForeName>Yousef</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0945-9224</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The National Key Laboratory of Water Disaster Prevention, College of Hydrology and Water Resources, Hohai University, Nanjing 210098, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>(TU-DSPP-2024-144) and (7584/Punjab/NRPU/R&amp;D/HEC)</GrantID><Agency>The authors extend their appreciation to Taif University, Saudi Arabia, for supporting this work through project number. The authors are highly thankful to the R&amp;D of the Higher Education Commission of Pakistan for funding this research under the NRPU pro</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Plants (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596181</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2223-7747</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DGT</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">aged contaminated</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">agricultural productivity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bioavailable fractions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">texture class</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39273929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11397637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants13172445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">plants13172445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bharti R., Sharma R. Effect of Heavy Metals: An Overview. Mater. Today Proc. 2022;51:880–885. doi: 10.1016/j.matpr.2021.06.278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.matpr.2021.06.278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma M., Kant R., Sharma A.K., Sharma A.K. Exploring the Impact of Heavy Metals Toxicity in the Aquatic Ecosystem. Int. J. Energy Water Resour. 2024 doi: 10.1007/s42108-024-00284-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42108-024-00284-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P., Kaur J., Katnoria J.K. Assessment of Spatial Variations in Pollution Load of Agricultural Soil Samples of Ludhiana District, Punjab. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2022;195:222. doi: 10.1007/s10661-022-10816-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-022-10816-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36543983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proshad R., Islam M.S., Kormoker T. Assessment of Heavy Metals with Ecological Risk of Soils in the Industrial Vicinity of Tangail District, Bangladesh. Int. J. Adv. Geosci. 2018;6:108. doi: 10.14419/ijag.v6i1.9791.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14419/ijag.v6i1.9791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mushtaq N., Singh D.V., Bhat R.A., Dervash M.A., Hameed O. Freshwater Contamination: Sources and Hazards to Aquatic Biota. In: Qadri H., Bhat R., Mehmood M., Dar G., editors. Fresh Water Pollution Dynamics and Remediation. Springer; Singapore: 2019. pp. 27–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong W., Zhang Y., Quan X. Health Risk Assessment of Heavy Metals and Pesticides: A Case Study in the Main Drinking Water Source in Dalian, China. Chemosphere. 2020;242:125113. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31896177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang J., Zhang L., Rao S., Zhang M., Zhao K., Fu W. Spatial Variation of Heavy Metals and Their Ecological Risk and Health Risks to Local Residents in a Typical E-Waste Dismantling Area of Southeastern China. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2022;194:604. doi: 10.1007/s10661-022-10296-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-022-10296-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35867165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan D.-X., He S.-X., Li G., Teng H.H., Ma L.Q. Application of Diffusive Gradients in Thin-Films Technique for Speciation, Bioavailability, Modeling and Mapping of Nutrients and Contaminants in Soils. Crit. Rev. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;52:3035–3079. doi: 10.1080/10643389.2021.1900765.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10643389.2021.1900765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dellavia A., Marković M., Habuda-Stanić M., Kovačić Đ., Bubalo A., Popović B. Wastewater-Based Crop Irrigation: An Issue or a Solution? Poljoprivreda. 2023;29:43–52. doi: 10.18047/poljo.29.2.6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18047/poljo.29.2.6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q., Li Z., Lu X., Duan Q., Huang L., Bi J. A Review of Soil Heavy Metal Pollution from Industrial and Agricultural Regions in China: Pollution and Risk Assessment. Sci. Total Environ. 2018;642:690–700. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.06.068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.06.068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29909337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu F., Zhang J., Ji Y., Fu Y., Lang T., Shi T., Liu S. Risk Assessment of Cr, As, and Sb to Aquatic Communities at the Water-Sediment Interface in the Lower Yellow River, China, Integrated with the Diffusive Gradients in Thin-films Technique. J. Environ. Chem. Eng. 2024;12:111942. doi: 10.1016/j.jece.2024.111942.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jece.2024.111942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antoniadis V., Golia E.E., Liu Y.-T., Wang S.-L., Shaheen S.M., Rinklebe J. Soil and Maize Contamination by Trace Elements and Associated Health Risk Assessment in the Industrial Area of Volos, Greece. Environ. Int. 2019;124:79–88. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2018.12.053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.12.053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30640132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosado Rodríguez G., Otero Morales E. Assessment of Heavy Metal Contamination at Tallaboa Bay (Puerto Rico) by Marine Sponges’ Bioaccumulation and Fungal Community Composition. Mar. Pollut. Bull. 2020;161:111803. doi: 10.1016/j.marpolbul.2020.111803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2020.111803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33128981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xin J. Enhancing Soil Health to Minimize Cadmium Accumulation in Agro-Products: The Role of Microorganisms, Organic Matter, and Nutrients. Environ. Pollut. 2024;348:123890. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2024.123890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.123890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38554840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson C.M. Methods for the Determination of Heavy Metals and Metalloids in Soils. In: Alloway B., editor. Heavy Metals in Soils. Environmental Pollution. Volume 22. Springer; Dordrecht, The Netherlands: 2012. pp. 97–140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Hullebusch E.D., Guibaud G., Simon S., Lenz M., Yekta S.S., Fermoso F.G., Jain R., Duester L., Roussel J., Guillon E., et al. Methodological Approaches for Fractionation and Speciation to Estimate Trace Element Bioavailability in Engineered Anaerobic Digestion Ecosystems: An Overview. Crit. Rev. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2016;46:1324–1366. doi: 10.1080/10643389.2016.1235943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10643389.2016.1235943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelepertzis E., Paraskevopoulou V., Argyraki A., Fligos G., Chalkiadaki O. Evaluation of Single Extraction Procedures for the Assessment of Heavy Metal Extractability in Citrus Agricultural Soil of a Typical Mediterranean Environment (Argolida, Greece) J. Soils Sediments. 2015;15:2265–2275. doi: 10.1007/s11368-015-1163-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11368-015-1163-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senila M., Kovacs E. Use of Diffusive Gradients in Thin-Film Technique to Predict the Mobility and Transfer of Nutrients and Toxic Elements from Agricultural Soil to Crops-an Overview of Recent Studies. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. Int. 2024;31:34817–34838. doi: 10.1007/s11356-024-33602-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-33602-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11136807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38739340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senila M., Levei E.A., Frentiu T., Mihali C., Angyus S.B. Assessment of Mercury Bioavailability in Garden Soils around a Former Nonferrous Metal Mining Area Using DGT, Accumulation in Vegetables, and Implications for Health Risk. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2023;195:1554. doi: 10.1007/s10661-023-12144-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-023-12144-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38036722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kader M., Lamb D.T., Wang L., Megharaj M., Naidu R. Copper Interactions on Arsenic Bioavailability and Phytotoxicity in Soil. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 2018;148:738–746. doi: 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.11.025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.11.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29179146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan L., Rong Q., Zhang H., Jones K.C., Li Y., Luo J. Evaluation and Application of a Novel Diffusive Gradients in Thin-Films Technique for In Situ Monitoring of Glucocorticoids in Natural Waters. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2022;56:15499–15507. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.2c00834.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c00834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36256587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins de Barros R., Rougerie J., Guibal R., Lissalde S., Buzier R., Simon S., Guibaud G. Interest of a New Large Diffusive Gradients in Thin Films (L-DGT) for Organic Compounds Monitoring: On-Field Comparison with Conventional Passive Samplers. Environ. Pollut. 2023;323:121257. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2023.121257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2023.121257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36828359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Tu C., Wei J., Li Y., Chen C., Xu L., Mao M., Luo Y. Extended Application of Diffusive Gradients in Thin Films (DGT) in Assessing Arsenic Bioavailability and Human Health Risks in Brownfield Soils. Environ. Technol. Innov. 2023;32:103346. doi: 10.1016/j.eti.2023.103346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2023.103346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei T.-J., Guan D.-X., Li X.-Y., Hao Y.-L., Teng H.H., Yang J.-F., Xu Y.-Y., Li G. Analysis of Studies on Environmental Measurements Using Diffusive Gradients in Thin-Films (DGT) from 1994 to 2020. J. Soils Sediments. 2022;22:1069–1079. doi: 10.1007/s11368-022-03168-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11368-022-03168-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z., Luo P., Zha X., Xu C., Kang S., Zhou M., Nover D., Wang Y. Overview Assessment of Risk Evaluation and Treatment Technologies for Heavy Metal Pollution of Water and Soil. J. Clean. Prod. 2022;379:134043. doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.134043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.134043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhaj Hamoud Y., Shaghaleh H., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Rizwan M., Umair M., Usman M., Ayub M.A., Riaz U., Alnusairi G.S.H., Alghanem S.M.S. Cadmium and Lead Accumulation in Important Food Crops Due to Wastewater Irrigation: Pollution Index and Health Risks Assessment. Heliyon. 2024;10:e24712. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e24712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e24712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10838743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38317992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali M. Comparative Assessment of Phytoavailable Cadmium by Using Various Extractants in Texturally Different Contaminated Soils during the Growth of Maize Crop. Pak. J. Agric. Sci. 2023;60:389–400. doi: 10.21162/pakjas/22.98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21162/pakjas/22.98</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Usman M., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Rizwan M., Abbas T., Ayub M.A., Naeem A., Alharby H.F., Alabdallah N.M., Alharbi B.M., Qamar M.J., et al. Effect of Soil Texture and Zinc Oxide Nanoparticles on Growth and Accumulation of Cadmium by Wheat: A Life Cycle Study. Environ. Res. 2023;216:114397. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2022.114397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2022.114397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36167110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zia-ur-Rehman M., Anayatullah S., Irfan E., Hussain S.M., Rizwan M., Sohail M.I., Jafir M., Ahmad T., Usman M., Alharby H.F. Nanoparticles Assisted Regulation of Oxidative Stress and Antioxidant Enzyme System in Plants under Salt Stress: A Review. Chemosphere. 2023;314:137649. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.137649.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.137649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36587917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doležal J., Chondol T., Chlumská Z., Altman J., Čapková K., Dvorský M., Fibich P., Korznikov K.A., Ruka A.T., Kopecký M., et al. Contrasting Biomass Allocations Explain Adaptations to Cold and Drought in the World’s Highest-Growing Angiosperms. Ann. Bot. 2024;134:401–414. doi: 10.1093/aob/mcae028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aob/mcae028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11341669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38407819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu L., Luo X., Croft H., Rogers C.A., Chen J.M. Seasonal Variation in the Relationship between Leaf Chlorophyll Content and Photosynthetic Capacity. Plant Cell Environ. 2024:1–13. doi: 10.1111/pce.14997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/pce.14997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38847340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saltelli A., Ratto M., Tarantola S., Campolongo F. Sensitivity Analysis Practices: Strategies for Model-Based Inference. Reliab. Eng. Syst. Saf. 2006;91:1109–1125. doi: 10.1016/j.ress.2005.11.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ress.2005.11.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ullah S., Zia M., Meers E., Ghafoor A., Murtaza G., Sabir M., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Tack F. Chemically Enhanced Phytoextraction of Pb by Wheat in Texturally Different Soils. Chemosphere. 2010;79:652–658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20334894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizwan M., Ali S., Adrees M., Ibrahim M., Tsang D.C.W., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Zahir Z.A., Rinklebe J., Tack F.M.G., Ok Y.S. A Critical Review on Effects, Tolerance Mechanisms and Management of Cadmium in Vegetables. Chemosphere. 2017;182:90–105. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.05.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.05.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28494365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohail M.I., Zia ur Rehman M., Rizwan M., Yousaf B., Ali S., Anwar ul Haq M., Anayat A., Waris A.A. Efficiency of Various Silicon Rich Amendments on Growth and Cadmium Accumulation in Field Grown Cereals and Health Risk Assessment. Chemosphere. 2020;244:125481. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31812047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali S., Rizwan M., Hussain A., Zia ur Rehman M., Ali B., Yousaf B., Wijaya L., Alyemeni M.N., Ahmad P. Silicon Nanoparticles Enhanced the Growth and Reduced the Cadmium Accumulation in Grains of Wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) Plant Physiol. Biochem. 2019;140:1–8. doi: 10.1016/j.plaphy.2019.04.041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2019.04.041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31078051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohail M.I., Zia ur Rehman M., Aziz T., Akmal F., Azhar M., Nadeem F., Aslam M., Siddiqui A., Khalid M.A. Iron Bio-Fortification and Heavy Metal/(Loid)s Contamination in Cereals: Successes, Issues, and Challenges. Crop Pasture Sci. 2022;73:877–895. doi: 10.1071/CP21771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1071/CP21771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen F., Li Y., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Hussain S.M., Qayyum M.F., Rizwan M., Alharby H.F., Alabdallah N.M., Alharbi B.M., Ali S. Combined Effects of Zinc Oxide Nanoparticles and Melatonin on Wheat Growth, Chlorophyll Contents, Cadmium (Cd) and Zinc Uptake under Cd Stress. Sci. Total Environ. 2023;864:161061. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.161061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.161061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36565889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman M.Z., Rizwan M., Rauf A., Ayub M.A., Ali S., Qayyum M.F., Waris A.A., Naeem A., Sanaullah M. Split Application of Silicon in Cadmium (Cd) Spiked Alkaline Soil Plays a Vital Role in Decreasing Cd Accumulation in Rice (Oryza sativa L.) Grains. Chemosphere. 2019;226:454–462. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.03.182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.03.182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30951940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman M.Z., Batool Z., Ayub M.A., Hussaini K.M., Murtaza G., Usman M., Naeem A., Khalid H., Rizwan M., Ali S. Effect of Acidified Biochar on Bioaccumulation of Cadmium (Cd) and Rice Growth in Contaminated Soil. Environ. Technol. Innov. 2020;19:101015. doi: 10.1016/j.eti.2020.101015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2020.101015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayub M.A., Zia ur Rehman M., Ahmad H.R., Fox J.-P., Clubb P., Wright A.L., Anwar-ul-Haq M., Nadeem M., Rico C.M., Rossi L. Influence of Ionic Cerium and Cerium Oxide Nanoparticles on Zea mays Seedlings Grown with and without Cadmium. Environ. Pollut. 2023;322:121137. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2023.121137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2023.121137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36720342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan I., Awan S.A., Rizwan M., Akram M.A., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Wang X., Zhang X., Huang L. Physiological and Transcriptome Analyses Demonstrate the Silver Nanoparticles Mediated Alleviation of Salt Stress in Pearl Millet (Pennisetum glaucum L) Environ. Pollut. 2023;318:120863. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2022.120863.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.120863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36526056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizwan A., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Rizwan M., Usman M., Anayatullah S., Alharby H.F., Bamagoos A.A., Alharbi B.M., Ali S. Effects of Silicon Nanoparticles and Conventional Si Amendments on Growth and Nutrient Accumulation by Maize (Zea mays L.) Grown in Saline-Sodic Soil. Environ. Res. 2023;227:115740. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2023.115740.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2023.115740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36997044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin M.A., Haider G., Rizwan M., Schofield H.K., Qayyum M.F., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Ali S. Different Feedstocks of Biochar Affected the Bioavailability and Uptake of Heavy Metals by Wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) Plants Grown in Metal Contaminated Soil. Environ. Res. 2023;217:114845. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2022.114845.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2022.114845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36423665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizwan M., Ali S., Adrees M., Rizvi H., Zia-ur-Rehman M., Hannan F., Qayyum M.F., Hafeez F., Ok Y.S. Cadmium Stress in Rice: Toxic Effects, Tolerance Mechanisms, and Management: A Critical Review. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 2016;23:17859–17879. doi: 10.1007/s11356-016-6436-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-016-6436-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26996904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu G.-Z., Zhao K., Zhang S.-Q., Liang Y.-M., Yue Y.-J., Liu G.-H., Qin F.-C. Biomass Allocation and Allometric Relationship of Salix Gordejevii Branches in Sandy Habitats Heterogeneity in Northen China. Sustainability. 2024;16:5483. doi: 10.3390/su16135483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su16135483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zia-ur-Rehman M., Mubsher A., Rizwan M., Usman M., Jafir M., Umair M., Alharby H.F., Bamagoos A.A., Alshamrani R., Ali S. Effect of Farmyard Manure, Elemental Sulphur and EDTA on Growth and Phytoextraction of Cadmium by Spider Plants (Chlorophytum comosum L.) under Cd Stress. Chemosphere. 2023;313:137385. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.137385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.137385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36436583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai Y., Nasir M., Zhang Y., Gao J., Lv Y., Lv J. Comparison of DGT with Traditional Extraction Methods for Assessing Arsenic Bioavailability to Brassica Chinensis in Different Soils. Chemosphere. 2018;191:183–189. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.10.035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.10.035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29032263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang T., Li L., Xu F., Chen X., Du L., Wang X., Li Y. Assessing the Remobilization and Fraction of Cadmium and Lead in Sediment of the Jialing River by Sequential Extraction and Diffusive Gradients in Films (DGT) Technique. Chemosphere. 2020;257:127181. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32485515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Wei L., Deng H., Hu S., Xie X., Luo D., Xiao T. Hydrogeochemistry of Groundwater Surrounding a Pyrite Mine in Southern China: Assessment of the Diffusive Gradients in Thin Films Technique for in Situ Monitoring. J. Hydrol. 2023;622:129685. doi: 10.1016/j.jhydrol.2023.129685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2023.129685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang T., Zeng X., Zhang H., Lin Q., Su S., Wang Y., Bai L. Investigation of Synthetic Ferrihydrite Transformation in Soils Using Two-Step Sequential Extraction and the Diffusive Gradients in Thin Films (DGT) Technique. Geoderma. 2018;321:90–99. doi: 10.1016/j.geoderma.2018.01.034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2018.01.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo J., Cheng H., Ren J., Davison W., Zhang H. Mechanistic Insights from DGT and Soil Solution Measurements on the Uptake of Ni and Cd by Radish. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2014;48:7305–7313. doi: 10.1021/es500173e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es500173e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24853263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senila M. Real and Simulated Bioavailability of Lead in Contaminated and Uncontaminated Soils. J. Environ. Health Sci. Eng. 2014;12:108. doi: 10.1186/2052-336X-12-108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/2052-336X-12-108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4114113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25097761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sönmez O., Pierzynski G., Kaya C., Aydemir S. The Effects of Phosphorus Addition on Phytoavailability of Zinc by Diffusive Gradientsin Thin Films (DGT) Turk. J. Agric. For. 2016;40:379–385. doi: 10.3906/tar-1511-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3906/tar-1511-18</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herníková V., Dočekalová H., Diviš P. The Diffusive Gradient in Thin Films Technique (DGT) for the Mercury Determination in Aquatic Systems. Chem. Listy. 2005;99</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18969928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duquène L., Vandenhove H., Tack F., Van Hees M., Wannijn J. Diffusive Gradient in Thin FILMS (DGT) Compared with Soil Solution and Labile Uranium Fraction for Predicting Uranium Bioavailability to Ryegrass. J. Environ. Radioact. 2010;101:140–147. doi: 10.1016/j.jenvrad.2009.09.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvrad.2009.09.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19822385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowack B., Koehler S., Schulin R. Use of Diffusive Gradients in Thin Films (DGT) in Undisturbed Field Soils. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2004;38:1133–1138. doi: 10.1021/es034867j.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es034867j</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14998028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C., Ding S., Xu D., Tang Y., Wong M.H. Bioavailability Assessment of Phosphorus and Metals in Soils and Sediments: A Review of Diffusive Gradients in Thin Films (DGT) Environ. Monit. Assess. 2014;186:7367–7378. doi: 10.1007/s10661-014-3933-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-014-3933-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25015347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yobouet Y.A., Adouby K., Trokourey A., Yao B. Cadmium, Copper, Lead and Zinc Speciation in Contaminated Soils. Int. J. Eng. Sci. Technol. 2010;2:802–812.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Q., Hendershot W.H., Marshall W.D., Ge Y. Speciation of Cadmium, Copper, Lead, and Zinc in Contaminated Soils. Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal. 2000;31:1129–1144. doi: 10.1080/00103620009370502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00103620009370502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams P.N., Zhang H., Davison W., Zhao S., Lu Y., Dong F., Zhang L., Pan Q. Evaluation of in Situ DGT Measurements for Predicting the Concentration of Cd in Chinese Field-Cultivated Rice: Impact of Soil Cd:Zn Ratios. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2012;46:8009–8016. doi: 10.1021/es301195h.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es301195h</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22715943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agbenin J.O., Welp G. Bioavailability of Copper, Cadmium, Zinc, and Lead in Tropical Savanna Soils Assessed by Diffusive Gradient in Thin Films (DGT) and Ion Exchange Resin Membranes. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2012;184:2275–2284. doi: 10.1007/s10661-011-2116-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-011-2116-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21590301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H., Davison W. Performance Characteristics of Diffusion Gradients in Thin Films for the In Situ Measurement of Trace Metals in Aqueous Solution. Anal. Chem. 1995;67:3391–3400. doi: 10.1021/ac00115a005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac00115a005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soltanpour P.N. Use of Ammonium Bicarbonate DTPA Soil Test to Evaluate Elemental Availability and Toxicity. Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal. 1985;16:323–338. doi: 10.1080/00103628509367607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00103628509367607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindsay W.L., Norvell W.A. Development of a DTPA Soil Test for Zinc, Iron, Manganese, and Copper. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J. 1978;42:421–428. doi: 10.2136/sssaj1978.03615995004200030009x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2136/sssaj1978.03615995004200030009x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wear J.I., Evans C.E. Relationship of Zinc Uptake by Corn and Sorghum to Soil Zinc Measured by Three Extractants. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J. 1968;32:543–546. doi: 10.2136/sssaj1968.03615995003200040035x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2136/sssaj1968.03615995003200040035x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novozamsky I., Lexmond T.M., Houba V.J.G. A Single Extraction Procedure of Soil for Evaluation of Uptake of Some Heavy Metals by Plants. Int. J. Environ. Anal. Chem. 1993;51:47–58. doi: 10.1080/03067319308027610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03067319308027610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta S.K., Aten C. Comparison and Evaluation of Extraction Media and Their Suitability in a Simple Model to Predict the Biological Relevance of Heavy Metal Concentrations in Contaminated Soils. Int. J. Environ. Anal. Chem. 1993;51:25–46. doi: 10.1080/03067319308027609.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03067319308027609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groenenberg J.E., Römkens P.F.A.M., Van Zomeren A., Rodrigues S.M., Comans R.N.J. Evaluation of the Single Dilute (0.43 M) Nitric Acid Extraction to Determine Geochemically Reactive Elements in Soil. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2017;51:2246–2253. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.6b05151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.6b05151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5373566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28164700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symeonides C., McRae S.G. The Assessment of Plant-Available Cadmium in Soils. J. Environ. Qual. 1977;6:120–123. doi: 10.2134/jeq1977.00472425000600020003x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2134/jeq1977.00472425000600020003x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>