<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39286997</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2125</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>British journal of clinical pharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Br J Clin Pharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adverse reactions associated with nivolumab and small molecule antiangiogenic drugs: A pharmacovigilance analysis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/bcp.16242</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Immune checkpoint inhibitors, such as nivolumab, combined with small molecule antiangiogenic receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs), present a promising strategy for future immunotherapy. However, combination therapy can lead to specific adverse drug reactions (ADRs) in various clinical settings. Current research on the ADRs associated with combination therapy is limited. Our study aims to assess the safety of combination therapy.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We extracted ADR reports on combination therapy from the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Adverse Event Reporting System database, covering the period from the first quarter of 2012 to the third quarter of 2023, and conducted a large-scale retrospective study. We evaluated ADR risk signals using the reporting odds ratio (ROR) and calculated the Ro/e ratio to compare the differences in the risk of fatal ADRs among various tumour types.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We comprehensively reported the occurrence of ADRs in pan-cancer patients undergoing combination therapy. The combination therapy significantly increased the risk of sensitive skin (ROR: 231.43, 95% CI: 55.01-973.72, P &lt; .05), metastatic renal cell carcinoma (ROR: 220.71, 95% CI: 28.99-1695.41, P &lt; .05) and renal cell carcinoma (ROR: 188.22, 95% CI: 44.24-800.85, P &lt; .05). We also compared the differences in ADRs resulting from different small molecule drug combinations, as well as the differences in ADRs among patients with different types of tumours under combination therapy. Furthermore, we analysed the characteristics of patients prone to experiencing fatal ADRs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These results can help enhance understanding of the ADRs commonly associated with combination therapy and assist oncologists in formulating screening protocols.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 British Pharmacological Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Haiyang</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruan</LastName><ForeName>Zhaohui</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Changping Laboratory, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jia</LastName><ForeName>Yanan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hepatobiliary and Pancreatic Surgery, Beijing Chaoyang Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yuan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhanggongshan Communist Labour University, Shangrao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Lingwa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Yifan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Ru</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fang</LastName><ForeName>Jugao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1372-7228</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2022-1-2051</GrantID><Agency>Capital Health Research and Development of Special Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>82002880</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>XYJL-2022-0072-0005</GrantID><Agency>Beijing Medical Award Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>PX2021008</GrantID><Agency>Beijing Municipal Administration of Hospitals Incubating Program</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Br J Clin Pharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7503323</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0306-5251</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FAERS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adverse drug reactions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nivolumab</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">retrospective study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">small molecule antiangiogenic drugs</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39286997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bcp.16242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Zhu S, Zhang T, Zheng L, et al. Combination strategies to maximize the benefits of cancer immunotherapy. J Hematol Oncol. 2021;14(1):156. doi:10.1186/s13045‐021‐01164‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Q, Hong Z, Zhang C, Wang L, Han Z, Ma D. Immune checkpoint therapy for solid tumours: clinical dilemmas and future trends. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2023;8(1):320. doi:10.1038/s41392‐023‐01522‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferris RL, Blumenschein G Jr, Fayette J, et al. Nivolumab for recurrent squamous‐cell carcinoma of the head and neck. N Engl J Med. 2016;375(19):1856‐1867. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa1602252</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato K, Cho BC, Takahashi M, et al. Nivolumab versus chemotherapy in patients with advanced oesophageal squamous cell carcinoma refractory or intolerant to previous chemotherapy (ATTRACTION‐3): a multicentre, randomised, open‐label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2019;20(11):1506‐1517. doi:10.1016/S1470‐2045(19)30626‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee CK, Man J, Lord S, et al. Clinical and molecular characteristics associated with survival among patients treated with checkpoint inhibitors for advanced non‐small cell lung carcinoma: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. JAMA Oncol. 2018;4(2):210‐216. doi:10.1001/jamaoncol.2017.4427</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang D, Fang J, Wen S, et al. A comprehensive profile of TCF1+ progenitor and TCF1‐ terminally exhausted PD‐1+CD8+ T cells in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma: implications for prognosis and immunotherapy. Int J Oral Sci. 2022;14(1):8. doi:10.1038/s41368‐022‐00160‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sui Q, Zhang X, Chen C, et al. Inflammation promotes resistance to immune checkpoint inhibitors in high microsatellite instability colorectal cancer. Nat Commun. 2022;13(1):7316. doi:10.1038/s41467‐022‐35096‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagchi S, Yuan R, Engleman EG. Immune checkpoint inhibitors for the treatment of cancer: clinical impact and mechanisms of response and resistance. Annu Rev Pathol. 2021;16(1):223‐249. doi:10.1146/annurev‐pathol‐042020‐042741</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meric‐Bernstam F, Larkin J, Tabernero J, Bonini C. Enhancing anti‐tumour efficacy with immunotherapy combinations. Lancet. 2021;397(10278):1010‐1022. doi:10.1016/S0140‐6736(20)32598‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yap TA, Parkes EE, Peng W, Moyers JT, Curran MA, Tawbi HA. Development of immunotherapy combination strategies in cancer. Cancer Discov. 2021;11(6):1368‐1397. doi:10.1158/2159‐8290.CD‐20‐1209</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanahan D, Weinberg RA. Hallmarks of cancer: the next generation. Cell. 2011;144(5):646‐674. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2011.02.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Kim BYS, Chan CK, Hahn SM, Weissman IL, Jiang W. Improving immune‐vascular crosstalk for cancer immunotherapy. Nat Rev Immunol. 2018;18(3):195‐203. doi:10.1038/nri.2017.145</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu ZL, Chen HH, Zheng LL, Sun LP, Shi L. Angiogenic signaling pathways and anti‐angiogenic therapy for cancer. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2023;8(1):198. doi:10.1038/s41392‐023‐01460‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin S, Li A, Yi M, Yu S, Zhang M, Wu K. Recent advances on anti‐angiogenesis receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors in cancer therapy. J Hematol Oncol. 2019;12(1):27. doi:10.1186/s13045‐019‐0718‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel SA, Nilsson MB, Le X, Cascone T, Jain RK, Heymach JV. Molecular mechanisms and future implications of VEGF/VEGFR in cancer therapy. Clin Cancer Res. 2023;29(1):30‐39. doi:10.1158/1078‐0432.CCR‐22‐1366</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapoval SP, Lee CG, Tang C, et al. Lung vascular endothelial growth factor expression induces local myeloid dendritic cell activation. Clin Immunol. 2009;132(3):371‐384. doi:10.1016/j.clim.2009.05.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palazon A, Tyrakis PA, Macias D, et al. An HIF‐1α/VEGF‐A Axis in cytotoxic T cells regulates tumor progression. Cancer Cell. 2017;32(5):669‐683.e5. doi:10.1016/j.ccell.2017.10.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voron T, Colussi O, Marcheteau E, et al. VEGF‐A modulates expression of inhibitory checkpoints on CD8+ T cells in tumors. J Exp Med. 2015;212(2):139‐148. doi:10.1084/jem.20140559</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukumura D, Kloepper J, Amoozgar Z, Duda DG, Jain RK. Enhancing cancer immunotherapy using antiangiogenics: opportunities and challenges. Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2018;15(5):325‐340. doi:10.1038/nrclinonc.2018.29</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu T, Jiang A, Zhou C, Chen X, Li Y. Adverse reactions associated with immune checkpoint inhibitors and bevacizumab: a pharmacovigilance analysis. Int J Cancer. 2023;152(3):480‐495. doi:10.1002/ijc.34332</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motzer RJ, Penkov K, Haanen J, et al. Avelumab plus Axitinib versus sunitinib for advanced renal‐cell carcinoma. N Engl J Med. 2019;380(12):1103‐1115. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa1816047</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Shen J, Gu S, et al. Camrelizumab in combination with Apatinib in patients with advanced hepatocellular carcinoma (RESCUE): a nonrandomized, open‐label, phase II trial. Clin Cancer Res. 2021;27(4):1003‐1011. doi:10.1158/1078‐0432.CCR‐20‐2571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Li Y, Wang Y, et al. Recent progress on vascular endothelial growth factor receptor inhibitors with dual targeting capabilities for tumor therapy. J Hematol Oncol. 2022;15(1):89. doi:10.1186/s13045‐022‐01310‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Velasco G, Je Y, Bossé D, et al. Comprehensive meta‐analysis of key immune‐related adverse events from CTLA‐4 and PD‐1/PD‐L1 inhibitors in cancer patients. Cancer Immunol Res. 2017;5(4):312‐318. doi:10.1158/2326‐6066.CIR‐16‐0237</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsumoto J, Iwata N, Watari S, et al. Adverse events of Axitinib plus pembrolizumab versus Lenvatinib plus pembrolizumab: a pharmacovigilance study in Food and Drug Administration adverse event reporting system. Eur Urol Focus. 2023;9(1):141‐144. doi:10.1016/j.euf.2022.07.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Li Z, Sun Q, Xiang Y, Liu A. Severe cutaneous adverse reactions associated with immune checkpoint inhibitors therapy and anti‐VEGF combination therapy: a real‐world study of the FDA adverse event reporting system. Expert Opin Drug Saf. 2024;23(6):777‐784. doi:10.1080/14740338.2023.2251381</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou Y, Ye X, Wu G, Cheng G, Du X, He J. A comparison of disproportionality analysis methods in national adverse drug reaction databases of China. Expert Opin Drug Saf. 2014;13(7):853‐857. doi:10.1517/14740338.2014.915938</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salem JE, Manouchehri A, Moey M, et al. Cardiovascular toxicities associated with immune checkpoint inhibitors: an observational, retrospective, pharmacovigilance study. Lancet Oncol. 2018;19(12):1579‐1589. doi:10.1016/S1470‐2045(18)30608‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander SPH, Cidlowski JA, Kelly E, et al. The concise guide to PHARMACOLOGY 2023/24: introduction and other protein targets. Br J Pharmacol. 2023;180(S2):S1‐S22. doi:10.1111/bph.16179</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang X, Xiao H, Li H, Chen X, Li Y. Adverse events associated with immune checkpoint inhibitors in non‐small cell lung cancer: a safety analysis of clinical trials and FDA pharmacovigilance system. Front Immunol. 2024;15:1396752. doi:10.3389/fimmu.2024.1396752</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Do LHD, Azizi N, Maibach H. Sensitive skin syndrome: an update. Am J Clin Dermatol. 2020;21(3):401‐409. doi:10.1007/s40257‐019‐00499‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misery L, Boussetta S, Nocera T, Perez‐Cullell N, Taieb C. Sensitive skin in Europe. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2009;23(4):376‐381. doi:10.1111/j.1468‐3083.2008.03037.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding F, Liu B, Wang Y. Risk of hand‐foot skin reaction associated with vascular endothelial growth factor‐tyrosine kinase inhibitors: a meta‐analysis of 57 randomized controlled trials involving 24,956 patients. J am Acad Dermatol. 2020;83(3):788‐796. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2019.04.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacouture ME, Reilly LM, Gerami P, Guitart J. Hand foot skin reaction in cancer patients treated with the multikinase inhibitors sorafenib and sunitinib. Ann Oncol. 2008;19(11):1955‐1961. doi:10.1093/annonc/mdn389</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Golian E, Kwong BY, Swetter SM, Pugliese SB. Cutaneous complications of targeted melanoma therapy. Curr Treat Options Oncol. 2016;17(11):57. doi:10.1007/s11864‐016‐0434‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topalian SL, Hodi FS, Brahmer JR, et al. Safety, activity, and immune correlates of anti‐PD‐1 antibody in cancer. N Engl J Med. 2012;366(26):2443‐2454. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa1200690</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan Ali O, Diem S, Markert E, et al. Characterization of nivolumab‐associated skin reactions in patients with metastatic non‐small cell lung cancer. Onco Targets Ther. 2016;5(11):e1231292. doi:10.1080/2162402X.2016.1231292</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lidar M, Giat E, Garelick D, et al. Rheumatic manifestations among cancer patients treated with immune checkpoint inhibitors. Autoimmun Rev. 2018;17(3):284‐289. doi:10.1016/j.autrev.2018.01.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verspohl SH, Holderried T, Behning C, Brossart P, Schäfer VS. Prevalence, therapy and tumour response in patients with rheumatic immune‐related adverse events following immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy: a single‐Centre analysis. Ther Adv Musculoskelet Dis. 2021;13:1759720X211006963. doi:10.1177/1759720X211006963</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray‐Brown W, Wilsdon TD, Weedon H, et al. Nivolumab‐induced synovitis is characterized by florid T cell infiltration and rapid resolution with synovial biopsy‐guided therapy. J Immunother Cancer. 2020;8(1):e000281. doi:10.1136/jitc‐2019‐000281</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Q, Chen Z, Li F, et al. Discovery of highly potent and selective VEGFR2 kinase inhibitors for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Eur J Med Chem. 2023;257:115456. doi:10.1016/j.ejmech.2023.115456</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang B, Deng B, Jiao XD, et al. Low‐dose anti‐VEGFR2 therapy promotes anti‐tumor immunity in lung adenocarcinoma by down‐regulating the expression of layilin on tumor‐infiltrating CD8+T cells. Cell Oncol (Dordr). 2022;45(6):1297‐1309. doi:10.1007/s13402‐022‐00718‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin A, Plimack ER, Ernstoff MS, et al. Safety and efficacy of nivolumab in combination with sunitinib or pazopanib in advanced or metastatic renal cell carcinoma: the CheckMate 016 study. J Immunother Cancer. 2018;6(1):109. doi:10.1186/s40425‐018‐0420‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng X, Tao G, Sun S, et al. Adverse events of different PD‐1 inhibitors in lung cancer patients: a real‐world study. Ann Transl Med. 2022;10(4):183. doi:10.21037/atm‐21‐6899</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernando J, Roca‐Herrera M, García‐Álvarez A, et al. Sex differences on multikinase inhibitors toxicity in patients with advanced gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumours. Eur J Cancer. 2023;188:39‐48. doi:10.1016/j.ejca.2023.04.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ksienski D, Wai ES, Croteau NS, et al. Association of age with differences in immune related adverse events and survival of patients with advanced nonsmall cell lung cancer receiving pembrolizumab or nivolumab. J Geriatr Oncol. 2020;11(5):807‐813. doi:10.1016/j.jgo.2020.01.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyake H, Aki R, Matsushita Y, et al. Significance of age in Japanese patients receiving sunitinib as first‐line systemic therapy for metastatic renal cell carcinoma: comparative assessment of efficacy and safety between patients aged &lt;75 and ≥75 years. Anticancer Res. 2018;38(6):3593‐3599. doi:10.21873/anticanres.12633</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McQuade JL, Hammers H, Furberg H, et al. Association of Body Mass Index with the safety profile of nivolumab with or without ipilimumab. JAMA Oncol. 2023;9(1):102‐111. doi:10.1001/jamaoncol.2022.5409</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>