<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39280720</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-744X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>2024</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>TheScientificWorldJournal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ScientificWorldJournal</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Aflatoxin M1 Concentrations, Adulterants, Microbial Loads, and Physicochemical Properties of Raw Milk Collected From Nekemte City, Ethiopia.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3796985</StartPage><MedlinePgn>3796985</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">3796985</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1155/2024/3796985</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Milk is an essential part of the human diet and is a nutrient-rich food that improves nutrition and food security. The aim of this study was to determine the presence and concentration of aflatoxin M1 (AFM1), adulterants, microbial loads, and physicochemical properties of raw cow's milk (CM) in Nekemte City, Ethiopia. A total of 12 samples of fresh CM were purposefully collected from four kebeles in the city (Bake Jama, Burka Jato, Cheleleki, and Bakanisa Kese) based on the potential of each milk production and distributor site. The AFM1 concentration was determined by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) with a Sigma-Aldrich standard (St. Louis, MO, USA). The concentrations of AFM1 in Bake Jama, Burka Jato, Cheleleki, and Bakanisa Kese were found to be 0.01-0.03 g/L, 0.31-0.35 g/L, 0.19-0.21 g/L, and 0.04-0.07 g/L, respectively. The concentrations of AFM1 in the present study varied significantly (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) and ranged from 0.01 g/L to 0.35 g/L. These results show that of the 12 samples tested, all were positive for AFM1 and contaminated to varying degrees. The results of this study also revealed that the concentration of AFM1 in 7 (58%) of the 12 milk samples was above the European Union's (EU) maximum tolerance limit (0.05 g/L). The present study also revealed that of the investigated adulterants, only the addition of water had positive effects on three milk samples, while the remaining adulterants were not detected in any of the milk samples. The total bacterial count (TBC) and total coliform count (TCC) were significantly (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) different and ranged from 5.53 to 6.82 log<sub>10</sub>cfumL<sup>-1</sup> and from 4.21 to 4.74 log<sub>10</sub>cfumL<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. The physicochemical properties of the milk samples in the present study were significantly (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) different and ranged from 2.8% to 5.75% fat, 7.03% to 9.75% solid-not-fat (SNF), 2.35% to 3.61% protein, 3.33% to 5.15% lactose, 11.54% to 13.69% total solid, 0.16% to 0.18% titratable acid, 26.7 to 32.1°C, 6.35 to 6.55 pH, and 1.027 to 1.030 specific gravity. The physicochemical parameters of the raw milk in the study area met the required quality standards. Hence, further studies are required to determine the extent of the problem and the factors associated with high levels of AFM1 in raw milk in the study areas, including the detection of aflatoxin B1 (AFB1) in animal feed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Leila Nasir and Habtamu Fekadu Gemede.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nasir</LastName><ForeName>Leila</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology and Process Engineering Wollega University, P.O. Box 395, Nekemte, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gemede</LastName><ForeName>Habtamu Fekadu</ForeName><Initials>HF</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4261-1374</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology and Process Engineering Wollega University, P.O. Box 395, Nekemte, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ScientificWorldJournal</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101131163</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1537-744X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>6795-23-9</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016607">Aflatoxin M1</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005002" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Ethiopia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016607" MajorTopicYN="Y">Aflatoxin M1</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008892" MajorTopicYN="Y">Milk</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002417" MajorTopicYN="N">Cattle</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002851" MajorTopicYN="N">Chromatography, High Pressure Liquid</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058491" MajorTopicYN="N">Bacterial Load</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nekemte</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adulterants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">aflatoxin M1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cow's milk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">physicochemical</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39280720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11401672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2024/3796985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tekliye M., Gizaw M. Handling Practices, Evaluation of Adulteration and Microbial Quality of Raw Cow Milk Around Bahir Dar, Ethiopia. Food Science and Quality Management . 2017;61:1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulunda M. Determination and Quantification of Aflatoxin M1 in Fresh Milk Samples Obtained in Goats and Cattle in Selected Rural Areas of the Limpopo Province, South Africa. Journal of Human Ecology . 2016;56(1-2):183–187. doi: 10.1080/09709274.2016.11907054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09709274.2016.11907054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandiselvam R., Sruthi N. U., Kumar A., et al. Recent Applications of Vibrational Spectroscopic Techniques in the Grain Industry. Food Reviews International . 2021;39:209–239. doi: 10.1080/87559129.2021.1904253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/87559129.2021.1904253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayoubi S., Naeimipour F., Aghajani J., Kojuri S. Useful Approaches for Reducing Aflatoxin M1 Content in Milk and Dairy Products. Biomedical and Biotechnology Research Journal (BBRJ) . 2018;2(2):p. 94. doi: 10.4103/bbrj.bbrj_59_18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/bbrj.bbrj_59_18</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmani A., Jinap S., Soleimany F. Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis of Mycotoxins. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety . 2009;8(3):202–251. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-4337.2009.00079.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2009.00079.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33467794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansuri S. M., Chakraborty S. K., Mahanti N. K., Pandiselvam R. Effect of Germ Orientation During Vis-NIR Hyperspectral Imaging for the Detection of Fungal Contamination in Maize Kernel Using PLS-DA, ANN and 1D-CNN Modelling. Food Control . 2022;139:p. 109077.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fallah A. A., Jafari T., Fallah A., Rahnama M. Determination of Aflatoxin M1 Levels in Iranian White and Cream Cheese. Food and Chemical Toxicology . 2009;47(8):1872–1875. doi: 10.1016/j.fct.2009.04.042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2009.04.042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19426778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassa A., Talema A., Ketsela G. Determination of Aflatoxin M1 in Raw Cow’s Milk by Using HPLC-FLD, in Injibara Town, Awi Zone, Amhara, Ethiopia. Chemistry and Materials Science . 2020;14 doi: 10.20944/preprints202010.0181.v1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20944/preprints202010.0181.v1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barikbin B., Allahresani A., Khosravi R., Khodadadi M. Detection of Aflatoxin M1 in Dairy Products Marketed in Iran. Health Scope . 2015;4:p. e18925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sujayasree O. J., Chaitanya A. K., Bhoite R., et al. Ozone: An Advanced Oxidation Technology to Enhance Sustainable Food Consumption Through Mycotoxin Degradation. Ozone: Science and Engineering . 2022;44(1):17–37. doi: 10.1080/01919512.2021.1948388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01919512.2021.1948388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omar S. S. Aflatoxin M1 Levels in Raw Milk, Pasteurised Milk and Infant Formula. Italian Journal of Food Safety . 2016;5(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5090115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27853711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeghi N., Oveisi M., Jannat B., Hajimahmoodi M., Bonyani H., Jannat F. Incidence of Aflatoxin M1 in Human Breast Milk in Tehran, Iran. Food Control . 2009;20(1):75–78. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2008.02.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2008.02.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basharat S., Khalid S., Aslam M., et al. Qualitative Analysis of Milk Adulterants in Various Samples of Milk, Available in Local Market of Lahore, Pakistan. EAS Journal of Nutrition and Food Sciences . 2019;1(5)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gizachew D., Szonyi B., Tegegne A., Hanson J., Grace D. Aflatoxin Contamination of Milk and Dairy Feeds in the Greater Addis Ababa Milk Shed, Ethiopia. Food Control . 2016;59:773–779. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2015.06.060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2015.06.060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shigute T., Washe A. P. Reduction of Aflatoxin M1 Levels During Ethiopian Traditional Fermented Milk (Ergo) Production. Journal of Food Quality . 2018;2018:1–10. doi: 10.1155/2018/4570238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/4570238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xin H., Stone R. Chinese Probe Unmasks High-Tech Adulteration With Melamine. Science . 2008;322(5906):1310–1311. doi: 10.1126/science.322.5906.1310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.322.5906.1310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19039108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanashyam A. C., Shanker M. A., Kothakota A., Mahanti N. K., Pandiselvam R. Ozone Applications in Milk and Meat Industry. Ozone: Science and Engineering . 2022;44(1):50–65. doi: 10.1080/01919512.2021.1947776.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01919512.2021.1947776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torkar K. G., Teger S. G. The Microbiological Quality of Raw Milk After Introducing the Two Day’s Milk Collecting System. Acta Agriculture Slovenica . 2008;92:61–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serraino A., Bonilauri P., Kerekes K., et al. Occurrence of Aflatoxin M1 in Raw Milk Marketed in Italy: Exposure Assessment and Risk Characterization. Frontiers in Microbiology . 2019;10:p. 2516. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2019.02516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6856139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31787941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zebib H., Zewdu A. Nutritional Quality, Level of Chemical Contaminants and Adulterants in Milk and Dairy Products in Ethiopia: A Review. Modern Chemistry . 2020;8(4):64–72. doi: 10.11648/j.mc.20200804.13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11648/j.mc.20200804.13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoudi R., Golchin A., Hoosseinzadeh N., Ghajarbeygi P. Aflatoxin M1 and B1 Contaminations in Products of Animal Origin in Iran. Journal of Inflammatory Diseases . 2014;18(4):49–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giovati L., Magliani W., Ciociola T., Santinoli C., Conti S., Polonelli L. AFM1 in Milk: Physical, Biological, and Prophylactic Methods to Mitigate Contamination. Toxins . 2015;7(10):4330–4349. doi: 10.3390/toxins7104330.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins7104330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4626737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26512694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patyal A., Gill J. P. S., Bedi J. S., Aulakh R. S. Potential Risk Factors Associated With the Occurrence of Aflatoxin M1 in Raw Milk Produced Under Different Farm Conditions. Journal of Environmental Science and Health, Part B . 2020;55(9):827–834. doi: 10.1080/03601234.2020.1787019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03601234.2020.1787019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32602778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gemechu T., Amene T. Physicochemical Properties and Microbial Quality of Raw Cow Milk Produced by Smallholders in Bench Maji-Zone, Southwestern Ethiopia. Food Science and Quality Management . 2016;54:47–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubokaa M. M., Imungia J. K., Njuea L., Mutuab F., Grace D., Johanna F. Occurrence of Aflatoxin M1 in Raw Milk Traded in Peri-Urban. Infection Ecology &amp; Epidemiology . 2019;9(1):p. 1625703. doi: 10.1080/20008686.2019.1625703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/20008686.2019.1625703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6586110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31258853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rokhi M. L., Darsanaki R. K., Mohammadi M., Kolavani M. H., Issazadeh K., Aliabadi M. A. Determination of Aflatoxin M1 Levels in Raw Milk Samples in Gilan, Iran. Advanced Studies in Biology . 2013;5(4):151–156. doi: 10.12988/asb.2013.13013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12988/asb.2013.13013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal S. Z., Asi M. R., Ariño A. Aflatoxin M1 Contamination in Cow and Buffalo Milk Samples From the North West Frontier Province (NWFP) and Punjab Provinces of Pakistan. Food Additives and Contaminants: Part B . 2011;4(4):282–288. doi: 10.1080/19393210.2011.637237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19393210.2011.637237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24786252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang’ethe E. K., Lang’a K. Aflatoxin B1 and M1 Contamination of Animal Feeds and Milk From Urban Centers in Kenya. African Health Sciences . 2009;9(4):218–226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3074399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21503172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fink-Gremmels J. Mycotoxins in Cattle Feeds and Carryover to Dairy Milk: A Review. Food Additives and Contaminants: Part A . 2008;25(2):172–180. doi: 10.1080/02652030701823142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/02652030701823142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18286407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yohannes B., Wondossen A., Anteneh G. Analysis to Ascertain the Determination for Aflatoxin Contamination of Milk and Feeds From Gurage Zone, Ethiopia. International Journal of Agricultural Research . 2018;13(1):1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toma A. Knowledge, Attitude and Practice of Farmers’ Toward Aflatoxin in Cereal Crops in Wolaita Zone, Southern Ethiopia. EC Nutrition . 2019;14:247–254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suliman S. E., Abdalla M. A. Presence of Aflatoxin M1 in Dairy Cattle Milk in Khartoum State-Sudan. Poljoprivreda i Sumarstvo . 2013;59(2):p. 199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amer A. A., Ibrahim M. E. Determination of Aflatoxin M1 in Raw Milk and Traditional Cheeses Retailed in Egyptian Markets. Journal of Toxicology and Environmental Health Sciences . 2010;2(4):50–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makau C. M., Matofari J. W., Muliro P. S., Bebe B. O. Aflatoxin B1 and Deoxynivalenol Contamination of Dairy Feeds and Presence of Aflatoxin M1 Contamination in Milk From Smallholder Dairy Systems in Nakuru, Kenya. International Journal of Flow Control . 2016;3(1):6–15. doi: 10.1186/s40550-016-0033-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40550-016-0033-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Egmond H. P., Schothorst R. C., Jonker M. A. Regulations Relating to Mycotoxins in Food: Perspectives in a Global and European Context. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry . 2007;389(1):147–157. doi: 10.1007/s00216-007-1317-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-007-1317-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17508207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battacone G., Nudda A., Palomba M., Pascale M., Nicolussi P., Pulina G. Transfer of Aflatoxin B1 From Feed to Milk and From Milk to Curd and Whey in Dairy Sheep Fed Artificially Contaminated Concentrates. Journal of Dairy Science . 2005;88(9):3063–3069. doi: 10.3168/jds.s0022-0302(05)72987-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.s0022-0302(05)72987-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16107394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anyango G., Mutua F., Kagera I., Andang’O P., Grace D., Lindahl J. F. A Survey of Aflatoxin M1 Contamination in Raw Milk Produced in Urban and Peri-Urban Areas of Kisumu County, Kenya. Infection Ecology and Epidemiology . 2018;8(1):p. 1547094. doi: 10.1080/20008686.2018.1547094.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/20008686.2018.1547094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6263096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30598736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandra H., Bahuguna J., Singh A. Detection of Aflatoxin in Zea mays L. From Indian Markets by Competitive ELISA. Octa Journal of Biosciences . 2013;1(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbas H. K., Weaver M. A., Zablotowicz R. M., Horn B. W., Shier W. T. Relationships Between Aflatoxin Production and Sclerotia Formation Among Isolates of Aspergillus Section Flavi From the Mississippi Delta. European Journal of Plant Pathology . 2005;112(3):283–287. doi: 10.1007/s10658-004-4888-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10658-004-4888-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee C., Wang W., Wilson B. K., Connett M., Keller M. D. Detecting Adulterants in Milk With Lower Cost Mid-Infrared and Raman Spectroscopy. Optics and Biophotonics in Low-Resource Settings IV; February 13, 2018; San Francisco, CA. p. p. 104850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1117/12.2291979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aparnathi K. D., Agnihotri A., Chauhan M. P., Shaikh A. I., Patel A. M., Patel S. I. Application of Qualitative Tests for Detection of Adulterants in Sterilized Milk and During Its Subsequent Storage. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation . 2019;43(7):p. e13963. doi: 10.1111/jfpp.13963.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.13963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy D. M., Venkatesh K., Reddy C. V. S. Adulteration of Milk and Its Detection: A Review. International Journal of Chemical Studies . 2017;5(4):613–617.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conceicao D. G., Gonçalves B. H. R., Hora F. F. D., Faleiro A. S., Santos L. S., Ferrão S. P. Use of FTIR-ATR Spectroscopy Combined With Multivariate Analysis as a Screening Tool to Identify Adulterants in Raw Milk. Journal of the Brazilian Chemical Society . 2019;30(4):780–785.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty M., Biswas K. Limit of Detection for Five Common Adulterants in Milk: A Study With Different Fat Percent. IEEE Sensors Journal . 2018;18(6):2395–2403. doi: 10.1109/jsen.2018.2794764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/jsen.2018.2794764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azad T., Ahmed S. Common Milk Adulteration and Their Detection Techniques. International Journal of Flow Control . 2016;3(1):22–29. doi: 10.1186/s40550-016-0045-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40550-016-0045-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negash F., Tadesse E., Woldu T. Microbial Quality and Chemical Composition of Raw Milk in the Mid-Rift Valley of Ethiopia. African Journal of Agricultural Research . 2012;7(29):4167–4170. doi: 10.5897/ajar12.830.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5897/ajar12.830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tola A., Ofodile L. N., Beyene F. Microbial Quality and Chemical Composition of Raw Whole Milk From Horro Cattle in East Wollega, Ethiopia. Ethiopian Journal of Education and Sciences . 2008;3(1):1–10. doi: 10.4314/ejesc.v3i1.41995.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4314/ejesc.v3i1.41995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biruk H., Samson W., Zelalem Y. Microbial Properties of Milk and Traditionally Produced Ethiopian Fermented Milk Products: a Review. Proceedings of the 17th Annual Conference of the Ethiopian Society of Animal Production (ESAP); September 2009; Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. pp. 137–148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tesfay T., Kebede A., Seifu E. Quality and Safety of Cow Milk Produced and Marketed in Dire Dawa Town, Eastern Ethiopia. International Journal of Integrated Science and Technology . 2013;2:1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EAC. East African Standard: Raw Cow Milk‐Specification . Arusha: EAC; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desalegn A. Assessing the Microbiological Quality of Milk. World Journal of Agronomy, Food Science and Technology . 2014;1(1):1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bereda A., Yilma Z., Nurfeta A. Hygienic and Microbial Quality of Raw Whole Cow Milk Produced in Ezha District of the Gurage Zone, Southern Ethiopia. Wudpecker Journal of Agricultural Research . 2012;1(11):459–465.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dehinenet G., Mekonnen H., Ashenafi M., Emmanuelle G. Determinants of Raw Milk Quality Under a Smallholder Production System in Selected Areas of Amhara and Oromia National Regional States, Ethiopia. Agriculture and Biology Journal of North America . 2013;4:84–90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temamogullari F., Kanici A. Short Communication: Aflatoxin M1 in Dairy Products Sold in Şanlıurfa, Turkey. Journal of Dairy Science . 2014;97(1):162–165. doi: 10.3168/jds.2012-6184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2012-6184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24239070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Standard E. Unprocessed Whole/Raw Cow Milk Specification. ES General . 2009;3460:p. 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tesfay T., Kebede A., Seifu E. Physicochemical Properties of Cow Milk Produced and Marketed in Dire Dawa Town, Eastern Ethiopia. Food Science and Quality Management . 2015;42:56–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Derese T. Present Situation of Urban and Peri-Urban Milk Production and Quality of Raw Milk Produced in West Shoa Zone, Oromia Region, Ethiopia. Journal of Marketing and Consumer Research . 2008;23:46–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekele A., Fekadu B., Mitiku E. Chemical Composition and Microbial Quality of Cow Milk in Urban and Peri Urban Area of Dangila Town, Western Amhara Region, Ethiopia. Global Journal of Dairy Farming and Milk Production . 2015;3(1):81–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Öztürk Yilmaz S., Altinci A. Incidence of Aflatoxin M1 Contamination in Milk, White Cheese, Kashar and Butter From Sakarya, Turkey. Food Science and Technology . 2019;39(suppl 1):190–194. doi: 10.1590/fst.40817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/fst.40817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebho H. K., Meskel D. H. Determination of Adulteration and Chemical Composition of Raw Milk Sold in Hossana Town, South Ethiopia. Journal of Dairy and Veterinary Sciences . 2018;6(5):1–7. doi: 10.19080/jdvs.2018.06.555699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19080/jdvs.2018.06.555699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitiku E., Mekdes S., Yesihak Y. M. Milk Production, Marketing Practices and Qualities Along Milk Supply Chains of Haramaya District, Ethiopia. African Journal of Agricultural Research . 2019;14(35):1990–2005. doi: 10.5897/ajar2019.14087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5897/ajar2019.14087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azhari Ali A., Irshad N. B., Razaz S. A., Manahil A. A. Microbiological Safety of Raw Milk in Khartoum State, Sudan: 1-Khartoum and Omdurman Cities. Pakistan Journal of Nutrition . 2010;9(5):426–429. doi: 10.3923/pjn.2010.426.429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3923/pjn.2010.426.429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain I., Anwar J. A Study on Contamination of Aflatoxin M1 in Raw Milk in the Punjab Province of Pakistan. Food Control . 2008;19(4):393–395. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2007.04.019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2007.04.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>