<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39283627</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2168-6157</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JAMA neurology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JAMA Neurol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficacy and Safety of Erenumab for Nonopioid Medication Overuse Headache in Chronic Migraine: A Phase 4, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e243043</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1001/jamaneurol.2024.3043</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="IMPORTANCE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Patients with chronic migraine and medication overuse headaches (CM-MOH) represent a particularly burdened subpopulation. This trial provides first, to our knowledge, American Academy of Neurology class I evidence for a preventive therapy in CM-MOH.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To assess erenumab efficacy and safety in patients with nonopioid CM-MOH.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN, SETTINGS, AND PARTICIPANTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, placebo-controlled trial took place at 67 centers in North America, Europe, and Australia from October 7, 2019, to November 2, 2022. This report reflects the primary analysis conducted in January 2023, using a database snapshot from December 1, 2022, which contains the complete dataset of the double-blind treatment period (DBTP). Participants included adults with CM-MOH who had 1 or more preventive treatment failure(s). There were 992 participants screened and 620 participants enrolled (584 in nonopioid cohort and 36 in opioid cohort).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERVENTIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Erenumab, 70 mg, 140 mg, or placebo, once monthly for 24 weeks.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The primary end point was MOH remission at month 6. Secondary end points included change from baseline in mean monthly acute headache medication days (AHMD) at month 6 and sustained MOH remission throughout the DBTP. Safety end points were adverse events and changes in vital signs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The primary analysis population included 584 participants in the nonopioid-treated cohort with a mean age of 44 years and 482 participants were female (82.5%). Baseline demographics and disease characteristics were balanced across groups. At month 6, 134 participants in the erenumab, 140 mg group (69.1%) (odds ratio [OR], 2.01; 95% CI, 1.33-3.05; P &lt; .001 vs placebo) and 117 in the erenumab, 70 mg group (60.3%) (OR, 1.37; 95% CI, 0.92-2.05; P = .13 vs placebo) achieved MOH remission vs 102 participants in the placebo group (52.6%). AHMD use was also reduced in the erenumab groups vs placebo. Least squares mean (standard error) change from baseline in average monthly AHMD was -9.4 (0.4) days in the erenumab, 140 mg group (difference from placebo, -2.7; 95% CI, -3.9 to -1.6; P &lt; .001) and -7.8 (0.4) days in the erenumab, 70 mg group (difference from placebo, -1.2; 95% CI, -2.4 to -0.1; P = .03), vs -6.6 (0.4) days in the placebo group. MOH remission throughout the DBTP was sustained in 119 participants (61.3%,) 96 participants (49.5%), and 73 participants (37.6%) in the erenumab, 140 mg, 70 mg, and placebo groups, respectively. Adverse events were consistent with the known safety profile of erenumab. Treatment-emergent adverse events incidence in the combined erenumab group was 66.8% (259 participants; constipation 15.2% (59 participants) and COVID-19 13.9% (54 participants) were most common.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In this study, monthly, 140 mg, erenumab injections safely and effectively achieved MOH remission in patients with nonopioid CM-MOH within 6 months.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="TRIAL REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT03971071.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tepper</LastName><ForeName>Stewart J</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The New England Institute for Neurology and Headache, Stamford, Connecticut.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dodick</LastName><ForeName>David W</ForeName><Initials>DW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Mayo Clinic, Scottsdale, Arizona.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Atria Academy of Science and Medicine, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lanteri-Minet</LastName><ForeName>Michel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pain Department and FHU InovPain, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice-Côte Azur and University, Nice, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Inserm U1107, Neuro-Dol, Université Clermont Auvergne, Clermont-Ferrand, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dolezil</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Prague Headache Center, DADO MEDICAL sro, Prague, Czech Republic.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gil-Gouveia</LastName><ForeName>Raquel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurology Department, Hospital da Luz, Luz Saude, Lisboa, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Interdisciplinary Research in Health, Universidade Católica Portuguesa, Lisboa, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lucas</LastName><ForeName>Christian</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pain, CHU Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Piasecka-Stryczynska</LastName><ForeName>Karolina</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Poznan University of Medical Sciences, Poznan, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Szabó</LastName><ForeName>Gyöngyi</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Óbudai Egészségügyi Centrum, Budapest, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mikol</LastName><ForeName>Daniel D</ForeName><Initials>DD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amgen Inc, Thousand Oaks, California.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chehrenama</LastName><ForeName>Mahan</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amgen Inc, Thousand Oaks, California.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chou</LastName><ForeName>Denise E</ForeName><Initials>DE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amgen Inc, Thousand Oaks, California.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Yiping</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amgen Inc, Thousand Oaks, California.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paiva da Silva Lima</LastName><ForeName>Gabriel</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amgen Inc, Thousand Oaks, California.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT03971071</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>JAMA Neurol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101589536</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-6149</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement><b>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</b> Dr Tepper reported personal fees from Amgen during the conduct of the study; and research funding from Abbvie, Aeon, Amgen, Annovis, Axsome, Cassava, Cognition, Eli Lilly, Inhibikase, Ipsen, Lundbeck, Merz, Neurolief, Pfizer, PrecisionMed, Revance, Scilex, Suven, and UCB; consultant and/or advisory board honoraria from Abbvie, Aeon, Alphasights, Amgen, Aruene/eNeura, Atheneum, Axsome Therapeutics, Becker Pharmaceutical , ClearView Healthcare Partners, ClickTherapeutics, CoolTech, CRG Medical Services, Decision Resources, Defined Health, Decision Resources Group, Eli Lilly, ExpertConnect, FCB Health, Fenix, Gilmartin Capital, Gerson Lehrman Group, Guidepoint Global, Health Advances, Health Science Communications, HMP Communications, Impel, Initiator Pharma, InteractiveForums, IQVIA, Keyquest, Ki Health Partners, Krog and Partners, Lundbeck, M3 Global Research, Magellan Health, Magnolia Innovation, Miravo Healthcare, MJH Holdings, Neurofront Therapeutics, Neurolief, Nocira, Novartis, P Value Communications, Pain Insights, Palion Medical, Perfood, Pfizer, Pulmatrix, Putnam Associates, Rehaler, SAI MedPartners, Satsuma, Scilex, Slingshot Insights, Spherix Global Insights, Strategy, Synapse Medical Communication, System Analytic, Taylor and Francis, Tegus, Teva, Theranica, Third Bridge, Tonix, Trinity Partners, Unity HA, Vial, and XOC Technologies; salary from Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center, Thomas Jefferson University, and Ki Health Partners; speakers fees from AbbVie, Eli Lilly, Pfizer, Scilex, and Teva; and Continuing Medical Education honoraria from the American Academy of Neurology, the American Headache Society, Annenberg Center for Health Sciences, Catamount Medical Education, Diamond Headache Clinic, Forefront Collaborative, Haymarket Medical Education, HMP Global, Medical Education Speakers Network, Medical Learning Institute Peerview, Migraine Association of Ireland, Miller Medical Education, the National Association for Continuing Education, North American Center for CME, The Ohio State University, Physicians’ Education Resource, PlatformQ Education, Primed, Vindico Medical Education, and WebMD/Medscape. Dr Dodick reported personal fees from Amgen during the conduct of the study; personal fees from the American Academy of Neurology, Headache Cooperative of the Pacific, Headache Cooperative of New England, Canadian Headache Society, MF Med Ed Research, Biopharm Communications, CEA Group Holding Company, Teva, Amgen Japan, Eli Lilly Canada, Lundbeck, Amgen, Atria, CapiThera, Cerecin, Ceruvia Lifesciences, CoolTech, Ctrl M, Allergan, AbbVie, Biohaven, Escient, GlaxoSmithKline, Halion, Lundbeck, Eli Lilly, Novartis, Impel, Satsuma, Theranica, WL Gore, Genentech, Nocira, Perfood, Praxis, AYYA Biosciences, Revance, and Pfizer outside the submitted work; in addition, Dr Dodick had a patent for Onabotulinum Toxin Dosage Regimen for Chronic Migraine Prophylaxis (17189376.1-1466) (nonroyalty bearing) issued and has a patent application submitted for Synaquell (Precon Health) pending; and reported a full disclosure statement (5 years) and consulting fees from Amgen, Atria, CapiThera, Cerecin, Ceruvia Lifesciences, CoolTech, Ctrl M, Allergan, AbbVie, Biohaven, Escient, GlaxoSmithKline, Halion, Lundbeck, Eli Lilly, Novartis, Impel, Satsuma, Theranica, WL Gore, Genentech, Nocira, Perfood, Praxis, AYYA Biosciences, Revance, and Pfizer; honoraria from the American Academy of Neurology, Headache Cooperative of the Pacific, Headache Cooperative of New England, Canadian Headache Society, MF Med Ed Research, Biopharm Communications, CEA Group Holding Company, Teva, Amgen Japan, Eli Lilly Canada, Lundbeck, Pfizer, Vector Psychometric Group, Clinical Care Solutions, CME Outfitters, Curry Rockefeller Group, DeepBench, Global Access Meetings, KLJ Associates, Academy for Continued Healthcare Learning, Majallin, Medlogix Communications, Medica Communications, MJH Lifesciences, Miller Medical Communications, WebMD Health/Medscape, Wolters Kluwer, Oxford University Press, and Cambridge University Press; nonprofit board membership from the American Brain Foundation, the American Migraine Foundation, ONE Neurology, Precon Health Foundation, Global Patient Advocacy Coalition, Atria Health Collaborative, Atria Academy of Science and Medicine, Arizona Brain Injury Alliance, Domestic Violence HOPE Foundation/Panfila, and CSF Leak Foundation; research support from the US Department of Defense, the National Institutes of Health, Henry Jackson Foundation, Sperling Foundation, the American Migraine Foundation, Henry Jackson Foundation, and Patient Centered Outcomes Research Institute; stock options/shareholder/patents/board of directors from Ctrl M, Aural analytics, Axon Therapeutics, ExSano, Palion, Keimon Medical, Man and Science, Healint, Theranica, Second Opinion/Mobile Health, Epien, Nocira, Matterhorn, Ontologics, King-Devick Technologies, Precon Health, ScotiaLyfe, EigenLyfe, AYYA Biosciences, Axon Therapeutics, Cephalgia Group, and Atria Health; a patent for Onabotulinum Toxin Dosage Regimen for Chronic Migraine Prophylaxis (nonroyalty bearing) (17189376.1-1466) and a patent application submitted for Synaquell (Precon Health). Dr Lanteri-Minet reported taking part in a study with Amgen during the conduct of the study and personal fees from Abbvie, Eli Lilly, Grunenthal, Lundbeck, Medtronic, Orion Pharma, Per Food, Orion Pharma, Pfizer, Reckitt Benckiser, Salvia Bio Electronics, Sanofi Aventis, Teva, and University of Professional Studies outside the submitted work. Dr Dolezil reported participating in clinical trials with Allergan/AbbVie, Amgen, and Novartis and personal fees from Lundbeck, Teva, Eli Lilly, and Organon outside the submitted work. Dr Gouveia reported being a principal investigator for an Amgen clinical trial during the conduct of the study, personal fees from AbbVie Pfizer, Teva, Organon, Lilly, Novartis, and grants from Novartis outside the submitted work. Dr Lucas reported personal fees from Abbvie, Amgen, Lilly, Lundbeck, Pfizer, Orion, Teva, and Reckitt during the conduct of the study. Dr Mikol reported personal fees and employment from Amgen during the conduct of the study and employment from NervGen outside the submitted work. Dr Chou reported prior employment and stock ownership from Amgen during the conduct of the study and current employment and stock ownership with Pfizer outside the submitted work. Dr Yang reported current employment and stock ownership with Amgen. Dr Paiva da Silva Lima reported being a fulltime employee and holding stocks/stock options of Amgen. No other disclosures were reported.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39283627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11406451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2024.3043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2823594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Raggi A, Schiavolin S, Leonardi M, et al. . Chronic migraine with medication overuse: association between disability and quality of life measures, and impact of disease on patients’ lives. J Neurol Sci. 2015;348(1-2):60-66. doi:10.1016/j.jns.2014.11.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2014.11.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25434715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diener HC, Holle D, Solbach K, Gaul C. Medication-overuse headache: risk factors, pathophysiology and management. Nat Rev Neurol. 2016;12(10):575-583. doi:10.1038/nrneurol.2016.124</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2016.124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27615418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kristoffersen ES, Lundqvist C. Medication-overuse headache: epidemiology, diagnosis and treatment. Ther Adv Drug Saf. 2014;5(2):87-99. doi:10.1177/2042098614522683</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/2042098614522683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4110872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25083264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwedt TJ, Buse DC, Argoff CE, et al. . Medication overuse and headache burden: results from the CaMEO study. Neurol Clin Pract. 2021;11(3):216-226. doi:10.1212/CPJ.0000000000001037</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1212/CPJ.0000000000001037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8382341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34476122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Headache Classification Committee of the International Headache Society . Headache Classification Committee of the International Headache Society (IHS) The International Classification of Headache Disorders; 3rd edition. Cephalalgia. 2018;38(1):1-211. doi:10.1177/0333102417738202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0333102417738202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29368949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwedt TJ, Sahai-Srivastava S, Murinova N, et al. ; MOTS Investigators . Determinants of pain interference and headache impact in patients who have chronic migraine with medication overuse: results from the MOTS trial. Cephalalgia. 2021;41(10):1053-1064. doi:10.1177/03331024211006903</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/03331024211006903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33938249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suh GI, Park JW, Shin HE. Differences in clinical features and disability according to the frequency of medication use in patients with chronic migraine. J Clin Neurol. 2012;8(3):198-203. doi:10.3988/jcn.2012.8.3.198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3988/jcn.2012.8.3.198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3469800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23091529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell MB, Lundqvist C. Prevention and management of medication overuse headache. Curr Opin Neurol. 2012;25(3):290-295. doi:10.1097/WCO.0b013e328352c431</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/WCO.0b013e328352c431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22547100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linde M, Gustavsson A, Stovner LJ, et al. . The cost of headache disorders in Europe: the Eurolight project. Eur J Neurol. 2012;19(5):703-711. doi:10.1111/j.1468-1331.2011.03612.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2011.03612.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22136117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandenbussche N, Laterza D, Lisicki M, et al. . Medication-overuse headache: a widely recognized entity amidst ongoing debate. J Headache Pain. 2018;19(1):50. doi:10.1186/s10194-018-0875-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s10194-018-0875-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6043466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30003412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlsen LN, Munksgaard SB, Nielsen M, et al. . Comparison of 3 treatment strategies for medication overuse headache: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Neurol. 2020;77(9):1069-1078. doi:10.1001/jamaneurol.2020.1179</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2020.1179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7251504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32453406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goadsby PJ, Reuter U, Hallström Y, et al. . A controlled trial of erenumab for episodic migraine. N Engl J Med. 2017;377(22):2123-2132. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa1705848</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1705848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29171821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodick DW, Ashina M, Brandes JL, et al. . ARISE: a Phase 3 randomized trial of erenumab for episodic migraine. Cephalalgia. 2018;38(6):1026-1037. doi:10.1177/0333102418759786</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0333102418759786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tepper SJ, Diener HC, Ashina M, et al. . Erenumab in chronic migraine with medication overuse: subgroup analysis of a randomized trial. Neurology. 2019;92(20):e2309-e2320. doi:10.1212/WNL.0000000000007497</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000007497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6598821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30996056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silberstein SD, Cohen JM, Seminerio MJ, Yang R, Ashina S, Katsarava Z. The impact of fremanezumab on medication overuse in patients with chronic migraine: subgroup analysis of the HALO CM study. J Headache Pain. 2020;21(1):114. doi:10.1186/s10194-020-01173-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s10194-020-01173-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7507645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32958075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tepper SJ, Lipton RB, Silberstein SD, et al. . Long-term efficacy and safety of erenumab in patients with chronic migraine and acute medication overuse: a subgroup analysis. Headache. 2023;63(6):730-742. doi:10.1111/head.14536</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.14536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37313616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodick DW, Doty EG, Aurora SK, et al. . Medication overuse in a subgroup analysis of phase 3 placebo-controlled studies of galcanezumab in the prevention of episodic and chronic migraine. Cephalalgia. 2021;41(3):340-352. doi:10.1177/0333102420966658</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0333102420966658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33143451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diener HC, Marmura MJ, Tepper SJ, et al. . Efficacy, tolerability, and safety of eptinezumab in patients with a dual diagnosis of chronic migraine and medication-overuse headache: subgroup analysis of PROMISE-2. Headache. 2021;61(1):125-136. doi:10.1111/head.14036</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.14036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33314079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu S, Zhou J, Luo G, et al. . Efficacy and safety of eptinezumab in patients with chronic migraine and medication-overuse headache: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. BMC Neurol. 2023;23(1):441. doi:10.1186/s12883-023-03477-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12883-023-03477-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10722704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38102535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tepper SJ, Dodick DW, Lucas S, et al. . 62(nd) Annual Scientific Meeting American Headache Society((R)). Efficacy of erenumab in chronic migraine patients with acute headache medication overuse: a post hoc analysis assessing outcomes using different definitions of remission. Headache. 2020;60(suppl 1):1-156. doi:10.1111/head.13854</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.13854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32533851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwedt TJ, Hentz JG, Sahai-Srivastava S, et al. ; MOTS Investigators . Headache characteristics and burden from chronic migraine with medication overuse headache: Cross-sectional observations from the Medication Overuse Treatment Strategy trial. Headache. 2021;61(2):351-362. doi:10.1111/head.14056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.14056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33432635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Goffau MJ, Klaver ARE, Willemsen MG, Bindels PJE, Verhagen AP. The effectiveness of treatments for patients with medication overuse headache: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Pain. 2017;18(6):615-627. doi:10.1016/j.jpain.2016.12.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2016.12.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28007591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossi P, Faroni JV, Tassorelli C, Nappi G. Advice alone versus structured detoxification programmes for complicated medication overuse headache (MOH): a prospective, randomized, open-label trial. J Headache Pain. 2013;14(1):10. doi:10.1186/1129-2377-14-10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1129-2377-14-10</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3620000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23565591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pageler L, Katsarava Z, Diener HC, Limmroth V. Prednisone vs. placebo in withdrawal therapy following medication overuse headache. Cephalalgia. 2008;28(2):152-156. doi:10.1111/j.1468-2982.2007.01488.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1468-2982.2007.01488.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18039339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bøe MG, Mygland A, Salvesen R. Prednisolone does not reduce withdrawal headache: a randomized, double-blind study. Neurology. 2007;69(1):26-31. doi:10.1212/01.wnl.0000263652.46222.e8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000263652.46222.e8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17475943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghdiri F, Togha M, Razeghi Jahromi S, Paknejad SM. Celecoxib vs prednisone for the treatment of withdrawal headache in patients with medication overuse headache: a randomized, double-blind clinical trial. Headache. 2015;55(1):128-135. doi:10.1111/head.12487</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.12487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25600720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arab A, Khoshbin M, Karimi E, Saberian G, Saadatnia M, Khorvash F. Effects of greater occipital nerve block with local anesthetic and triamcinolone for treatment of medication overuse headache: an open-label, parallel, randomized, controlled clinical trial. Neurol Sci. 2022;43(1):549-557. doi:10.1007/s10072-021-05295-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10072-021-05295-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33945036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scher AI, Rizzoli PB, Loder EW. Medication overuse headache: an entrenched idea in need of scrutiny. Neurology. 2017;89(12):1296-1304. doi:10.1212/WNL.0000000000004371</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000004371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28821684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reuter U, Ehrlich M, Gendolla A, et al. . Erenumab versus topiramate for the prevention of migraine—a randomised, double-blind, active-controlled phase 4 trial. Cephalalgia. 2022;42(2):108-118. doi:10.1177/03331024211053571</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/03331024211053571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8793299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34743579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robblee J, Hakim SM, Reynolds JM, Monteith TS, Zhang N, Barad M. Nonspecific oral medications versus anti-calcitonin gene-related peptide monoclonal antibodies for migraine: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Headache. 2024;64(5):547-572. doi:10.1111/head.14693</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.14693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38634515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pozo-Rosich P, Dolezil D, Paemeleire K, et al. . Early use of erenumab vs nonspecific oral migraine preventives: the APPRAISE randomized clinical trial. JAMA Neurol. 2024;81(5):461-470. doi:10.1001/jamaneurol.2024.0368</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2024.0368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10964163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38526461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gil-Gouveia R, Dolezil D, Paemeleire K, et al. . Abstracts of the 8(th) Congress of the European Academy of Neurology, Vienna, Austria. Sustained benefit of monthly erenumab versus daily oral preventives in episodic migraine patients from the APPRAISE study. Eur J Neurol. 2022;29(suppl 1):6-918. doi:10.1111/ene.15461</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ene.15461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35749279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kopruszinski CM, Xie JY, Eyde NM, et al. . Prevention of stress- or nitric oxide donor-induced medication overuse headache by a calcitonin gene-related peptide antibody in rodents. Cephalalgia. 2017;37(6):560-570. doi:10.1177/0333102416650702</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0333102416650702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27206958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caronna E, José Gallardo V, Alpuente A, et al. ; Spanish CGRP-COVID Study Group . Safety of anti-CGRP monoclonal antibodies in patients with migraine during the COVID-19 pandemic: present and future implications. Neurologia (Engl Ed). 2021;36(8):611-617. doi:10.1016/j.nrl.2021.03.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nrl.2021.03.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7973059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33832802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tepper SJ, Sheikh HU, Dougherty CO, et al. . Erenumab dosage for migraine prevention: an evidence-based narrative review with recommendations. Headache. 2022;62(4):420-435. doi:10.1111/head.14266</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.14266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35137404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tepper SJ, Cirillo J, Kim E, et al. . The temporal trend of placebo response in migraine prevention from 1990 to 2021: a systematic literature review and meta-analysis with regression. J Headache Pain. 2023;24(1):54. doi:10.1186/s10194-023-01587-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s10194-023-01587-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10189936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37193973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forbes RB, McCarron M, Cardwell CR. Efficacy and contextual (placebo) effects of CGRP antibodies for migraine: systematic review and meta-analysis. Headache. 2020;60(8):1542-1557. doi:10.1111/head.13907</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.13907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32668023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeeberg P, Olesen J, Jensen R. Probable medication-overuse headache: the effect of a 2-month drug-free period. Neurology. 2006;66(12):1894-1898. doi:10.1212/01.wnl.0000217914.30994.bd</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000217914.30994.bd</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16707727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlsen LN, Munksgaard SB, Jensen RH, Bendtsen L. Complete detoxification is the most effective treatment of medication-overuse headache: a randomized controlled open-label trial. Cephalalgia. 2018;38(2):225-236. doi:10.1177/0333102417737779</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0333102417737779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29050498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashina S, Terwindt GM, Steiner TJ, et al. . Medication overuse headache. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2023;9(1):5. doi:10.1038/s41572-022-00415-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41572-022-00415-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36732518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, Fenton BT, Deng Y, et al. . Calcitonin gene-related peptide monoclonal antibodies and risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection and severe COVID-19 outcomes among veterans with migraine disorder. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(7):e2326371. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.26371</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.26371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10391301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37523183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pascual J, Núñez M, Panni T, Díaz-Cerezo S, Novick D, Ciudad A. Burden and unmet needs in migraine patients: results from the OVERCOME (Spain) study. Pain Ther. 2023;12(5):1209-1220. doi:10.1007/s40122-023-00538-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40122-023-00538-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10444706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37458965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lipton RB, Nicholson RA, Reed ML, et al. . Diagnosis, consultation, treatment, and impact of migraine in the US: results of the OVERCOME (US) study. Headache. 2022;62(2):122-140. doi:10.1111/head.14259</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/head.14259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9305407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35076091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>