<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39281612</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of kesse, koseret, and tosign extract treatments on the oxidative stability of oil during the repeated frying of potato chips.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e36868</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e36868</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e36868</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36868</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Fried food safety and quality are crucial concerns for consumers and the food industry due to the deterioration of oil quality and the loss of sensory properties during repeated frying. The current study investigated the use of leaf extracts from endemic dietary herbs: kesse (<i>Lippia adoensis</i> var. adoensis), koseret (<i>Lippia adoensis</i> var. koseret), and tosign (<i>Thymus schimperi</i> Ronninger) to enhance oil quality during the repeated frying of potato chips. The analysis of various parameters, including free fatty acids (FFA), iodine value (IV), peroxide value (PV), thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS), viscosity, and color (L*, a*, and b*), was conducted after every 5th frying cycle to assess oil quality. The results revealed significant (p &lt; 0.05) decreases in deterioration markers for oils treated with herb extracts compared to the control oils. Specifically, after 20 frying cycles, oils treated with the dietary herb extracts exhibited lower percentage of FFA (0.63-1.05), IV (51.7-46.7), PV (6.69-7.68), and TBARS (50.27-56.08) compared to the control. The herb-treated oils also maintained lower FFA, PV, and TBARS values throughout the frying cycles and reduced viscosity, while IV gradually decreased. Furthermore, the L* value decreased gradually, and a* and b* values increased as the number of frying cycles increased. The herb extracts provided better protection against degradation compounds compared to BHT-treated and control oils, which was attributed to their lower FFA and PV. Sensory analysis indicated that potato chips fried in kesse extract-treated oil were the most preferred, followed by those treated with tosign extract. These findings highlight the potential application of herb extracts to increasing oil stability during repeated frying cycles, which add value at the interface between culinary excellence and health perspectives. Natural antioxidants from endemic herbs can maintain oil quality, reduce harmful compounds, and enhance the sensory properties of fried foods, making them a promising alternative to synthetic antioxidants.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Assefa</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, College of Natural and Computational Sciences, Dilla University, Dilla, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dessalegn</LastName><ForeName>Engida</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Hawassa College of Teacher Education, Hawassa, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abegaz</LastName><ForeName>Kebede</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nutrition, Food Science, and Technology, Hawassa University, Hawassa, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Frying cycles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Herb extracts</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Natural antioxidants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Oil stability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sensory properties</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39281612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11401040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)12899-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Khattab R. Physicochemical quality and thermal stability of vegetable oils during deep-fat frying of potato chips. Curr. Nutr. Food Sci. 2024;20:523–528. doi: 10.2174/1573401318666220903105129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1573401318666220903105129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q., Saleh A.S.M., Chen J., Shen Q. Chemical alterations taken place during deep-fat frying based on certain reaction products: a review. Chem. Phys. Lipids. 2012;165:662–681. doi: 10.1016/j.chemphyslip.2012.07.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemphyslip.2012.07.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22800882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaghi A.N., Barbalho S.M., Guiguer E.L., Nalon A., Barbalho S.M. Frying process : from conventional to air frying technology frying process : from conventional to air frying technology. Food Rev. Int. 2019:1–15. doi: 10.1080/87559129.2019.1600541. 0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/87559129.2019.1600541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak P.K., Dash U.M.A., Rayaguru K., Krishnan K.R. Physio-chemical changes during repeated frying of cooked oil: a review. J. Food Biochem. 2016;40:371–390. doi: 10.1111/jfbc.12215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maskan M. Vol. 65. 2014. (Effect of Carvacrol on the Oxidative Stability of Palm Oil during Frying).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soleimanifar M., Niazmand R., Jafari S.M. Evaluation of oxidative stability, fatty acid profile, and antioxidant properties of black cumin seed oil and extract. J. Food Meas. Charact. 2019;13:383–389. doi: 10.1007/s11694-018-9953-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11694-018-9953-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habarakada A., Perumpuli P.A.B.N., Thathsaranee W.T.V., Wanninaika I.P. Physical, chemical, and nutritional quality parameters of three different types of oil: determination of their reusability in deep frying. Food Res. 2021;5:226–235. doi: 10.26656/FR.2017.5(5).079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26656/FR.2017.5(5).079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X.R., Liu Q., Singh S. Engineering nutritionally improved edible plant oils. Annu. Rev. Food Sci. Technol. 2023;14:247–269. doi: 10.1146/annurev-food-052720-104852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-food-052720-104852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36972153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarick K., Aladedunye F., Przybylski R. Effect of breading and battering ingredients on performance of frying oils. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol. 2014;116:763–770. doi: 10.1002/ejlt.201300342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ejlt.201300342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanka S. Vol. 2. 2015. pp. 3521–3525. (Determination of Changes Occurring in Chemical Properties of Fat Repeatedly Used for Food Frying).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mogol B.A., Gökmen V. Thermal process contaminants: acrylamide, chloropropanols and furan. Curr. Opin. Food Sci. 2016;7:86–92. doi: 10.1016/j.cofs.2016.01.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2016.01.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teng J., Hu X., Tao N., Wang M. Impact and inhibitory mechanism of phenolic compounds on the formation of toxic Maillard reaction products in food. Front. Agric. Sci. Eng. 2018;5:321–329. doi: 10.15302/J-FASE-2017182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15302/J-FASE-2017182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghobadi S., Akhlaghi M., Shams S., Mazloomi S.M. Acid and peroxide values and total polar compounds of frying oils in fast food restaurants of shiraz, southern Iran. Int. J. Nutr. Sci. 2018;3:25–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dourado C., Pinto C., Barba F.J., Lorenzo J.M., D, et al. Innovative non-thermal technologies affecting potato tuber and fried potato quality. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2019;88:274–289. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2019.03.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2019.03.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacoste F., Lechat H., Pages X., Arnaud J.N., Brenne E., Soulet B., Camisuli B., Birot C., Fazeuilh S., Escabasse J. Contrôle des composés indésirables dans les huiles végétales et mise en place d’observatoires, Oléagineux, Corps Gras. Lipides. 2005;12:372–377. doi: 10.1051/ocl.2005.0372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1051/ocl.2005.0372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ravi Kiran C., Sasidharan I., Soban Kumar D.R., Sundaresan A. Influence of natural and synthetic antioxidants on the degradation of Soybean oil at frying temperature. J. Food Sci. Technol. 2015;52:5370–5375. doi: 10.1007/s13197-015-1774-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-015-1774-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4519514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26243968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydeniz B., Yilmaz E. Performance of different natural antioxidant compounds in frying oil. Food Technol. Biotechnol. 2016;54:21–30. doi: 10.17113/ftb.54.01.16.4109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17113/ftb.54.01.16.4109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5105636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27904389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aladedunye F.A. Curbing thermo-oxidative degradation of frying oils: current knowledge and challenges. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol. 2015;117:1867–1881. doi: 10.1002/ejlt.201500047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ejlt.201500047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J.V.T. Tsakni D.H.A., Chatzilazarou E., Tsakali A.G. Identification of bioactive compounds in plant extracts of Greek flora and their antimicrobial and antioxidant activity. Separations. 2023;10:331–339. doi: 10.3390/separations10070373.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/separations10070373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orozco M.I., Priego-Capote F., Luque De Castro M.D. Influence of deep frying on the unsaponifiable fraction of vegetable edible oils enriched with natural antioxidants. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2011;59:7194–7202. doi: 10.1021/jf2015792.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf2015792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21644588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saoudi S., Chammem N., Sifaoui I., Bouassida-Beji M., Jiménez I.A., Bazzocchi I.L., Silva S.D., Hamdi M., Bronze M.R. Influence of Tunisian aromatic plants on the prevention of oxidation in soybean oil under heating and frying conditions. Food Chem. 2016;212:503–511. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.05.186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.05.186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27374561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Nigist S.D., Nigist A., Sebsebe D. Aromatic plants of Ethiopia. Addis ababa, Ethiopia: Shama books., Lwt. 2009;37(2009):137–138. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2004.03.001. p. 137 - 138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2004.03.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z.Y, Shiferaw M.D.M. Physicochemical properties and biological activities of koseret (lippia adoensis hochst. Var. Koseret) seed and leaf oil extracts. Recent Patents Biotechnol. 2022;17 doi: 10.2174/1872208316666220617104318. 01–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1872208316666220617104318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35718955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engeda D.G., Haki G.D., Rupasinghe H.P.V. Evaluation of in vitro antidiabetic potential of thymus schimperi R. And thymus vulgaris L. J. Heal. Med. Nurs. 2019:9–16. doi: 10.7176/jhmn/69-02.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7176/jhmn/69-02</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yordanos G., Tegenu M. Identification of bioactive compound, phytochemical analysis and antimicrobial activity of lippia adoensis var. koseret from Ethiopia. Sch. Int. J. Tradit. Complement. Med. 2021;4:139–153. doi: 10.36348/sijtcm.2021.v04i08.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36348/sijtcm.2021.v04i08.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abegaz B., Asfaw N., Lwande W. Constituents of the essential oils from wild and cultivated Lippia adoensis Hochst. ex Walp. J. Essent. Oil Res. 1993;5:487–491. doi: 10.1080/10412905.1993.9698268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10412905.1993.9698268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asres K., Bucar F. Analysis of the essential oil and antioxidant activity of lippia adoensis var . adoensis. Ethiop. Pharm. J. 2002;20:31–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hailemariam G. Antioxidant activity and preservative effect of thyme (thymus schimperi R.) Br. J. Appl. Sci. Technol. 2013;3:1311–1326. doi: 10.9734/bjast/2014/4563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/bjast/2014/4563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assefa D., Dessalegn E., Abegaz K. Antioxidant activity and reduction potential of dietary herbs on acrylamide formation in asparagine-glucose reaction model. Int. J. Food Prop. 2023;26:2273–2284. doi: 10.1080/10942912.2023.2244701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10942912.2023.2244701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Q., Gao S., Sun Y., Gao Y., Wang X., Zhang Z. Antioxidant efficacy of rosemary ethanol extract in palm oil during frying and accelerated storage. Ind. Crops Prod. 2016;94:82–88. doi: 10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.08.032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.08.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moufakkir C., Kharbach Y., Tanghort M., Dassouli A., Remmal A. Preserving soybean oil for the frying of breaded butterfly shrimp using natural rosemary antioxidant. Int. J. Food Sci. 2023;2023 doi: 10.1155/2023/5984636.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2023/5984636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10065861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37007843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniali G., Jinap S., Hajeb P., Sanny M., Tan C.P. Acrylamide formation in vegetable oils and animal fats during heat treatment. Food Chem. 2016;212:244–249. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.05.174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.05.174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27374529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urbančič S., Kolar M.H., Dimitrijević D., Demšar L., Vidrih R. Stabilisation of sunflower oil and reduction of acrylamide formation of potato with rosemary extract during deep-fat frying. LWT - Food Sci. Technol. 2014;57:671–678. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2013.11.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2013.11.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kruatian T., Jitmanee K. Greener analytical method for determination of iodine number of edible oils. J. Food Res. 2020;9:36. doi: 10.5539/jfr.v9n6p36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5539/jfr.v9n6p36</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ju J., Zheng Z., Xu Y.J., Cao P., Li J., Li Q., Liu Y. Influence of total polar compounds on lipid metabolism, oxidative stress and cytotoxicity in HepG2 cells. Lipids Health Dis. 2019;18:1–13. doi: 10.1186/s12944-019-0980-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12944-019-0980-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6359786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30709407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jurid L.S., Zubairi S.I., Kasim Z.M., Kadir I.A.A. The effect of repetitive frying on physicochemical properties of refined, bleached and deodorized Malaysian tenera palm olein during deep-fat frying. Arab. J. Chem. 2020;13:6149–6160. doi: 10.1016/j.arabjc.2020.05.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arabjc.2020.05.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman M.H., Hossain M.M., Rahman S.M.E., Amin M.R., Oh D.H. Evaluation of physicochemical deterioration and lipid oxidation of beef muscle affected by freeze-thaw cycles. Korean J. Food Sci. Anim. Resour. 2015;35:772–782. doi: 10.5851/kosfa.2015.35.6.772.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5851/kosfa.2015.35.6.772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4726957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26877637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serjouie A., Tan C.P., Mirhosseini H., Man Y.B.C. Effect of vegetable-based oil blends on physicochemical properties of oils during deep-fat frying. Am. J. Food Technol. 2010;5:310–323. doi: 10.3923/ajft.2010.310.323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3923/ajft.2010.310.323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garg M., Wason S., Meena P.L., Chopra R., Sadhu S.D., Dhyani A. Effect of frying on physicochemical properties of sesame and soybean oil blend. J. Appl. Nat. Sci. 2021;13:820–829. doi: 10.31018/jans.v13i3.2744.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31018/jans.v13i3.2744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>li Liu X., hua Mu T., nan Sun H., Zhang M., wang Chen J. Influence of potato flour on dough rheological properties and quality of steamed bread. J. Integr. Agric. 2016;15:2666–2676. doi: 10.1016/S2095-3119(16)61388-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2095-3119(16)61388-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyedeji A.B., Sobukola O.P., Henshaw F., Adegunwa M.O., Ijabadeniyi O.A., Sanni L.O., Tomlins K.I. Effect of frying treatments on texture and colour parameters of deep fat fried yellow fleshed cassava chips. J. Food Qual. 2017;2017 doi: 10.1155/2017/8373801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2017/8373801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devi K., Haripriya S. Pasting behaviors of starch and protein in soy flour-enriched composite flours on quality of biscuits. J. Food Process. Preserv. 2014;38:116–124. doi: 10.1111/j.1745-4549.2012.00752.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4549.2012.00752.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serka S., Getahun D., Abegaz K. Formulation and sensory acceptability of flat bread from kocho with broad bean (Vicia faba L.) and quality protein maize (Zea mays) flours, J. Food process. Technol. 2019;10:1–6. doi: 10.35248/2157-7110.19.10.812.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.35248/2157-7110.19.10.812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turan M., Ekinci M., Yildirim E., Güneş A., Karagöz K., Kotan R., Dursun A. Plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria improved growth, nutrient, and hormone content of cabbage (Brassica oleracea) seedlings. Turkish J. Agric. For. 2014;38:327–333. doi: 10.3906/tar-1308-62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3906/tar-1308-62</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Carmen Flores-Álvarez M., Molina-Hernández E.F., Hernández-Raya J.C., Sosa-Morales M.E. The effect of food type (fish nuggets or French fries) on oil blend degradation during repeated frying. J. Food Sci. 2012;77 doi: 10.1111/j.1750-3841.2012.02930.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2012.02930.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23107039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baydir A.T., Soltanbeigi A., Maral H. The antioxidant effect of rosemary on the oxidation stability of refıned sunflower oil rafine ayçiçek yağının oksidasyon kararlılığı üzerine biberiye ’ nin. Antioksidan Etkisi. 2023:60–65. doi: 10.31590/ejosat.1233032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31590/ejosat.1233032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra S., Firdaus M.A., Patel M., Pandey G. A study on the effect of repeated heating on the physicochemical and antioxidant properties of cooking oils used by fried food vendors of Lucknow city. Discov. Food. 2023;3 doi: 10.1007/s44187-023-00046-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44187-023-00046-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L., Zhu X., Yu X., Huyan Z., Wang X. Rapid and simultaneous determination of the iodine value and saponification number of edible oils by FTIR spectroscopy. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol. 2018;120 doi: 10.1002/ejlt.201700396.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ejlt.201700396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Meulenaer B., Medeiros R., Mestdagh F. second ed. Elsevier Inc.; 2016. Acrylamide in Potato Products.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-800002-1.00018-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohd F., Mohamed S., Aini N., Ismail R. Vol. 110. 2008. pp. 319–327. (Antioxidative Properties of Pandanus Amaryllifolius Leaf Extracts in Accelerated Oxidation and Deep Frying Studies).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.02.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26049222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abenoza M., De Las Heras P., Benito M., Oria R., Sánchez-Gimeno A.C. Changes in the physicochemical and nutritional parameters of picual and arbequina olive oils during frying. J. Food Process. Preserv. 2016;40:353–361. doi: 10.1111/jfpp.12612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.12612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chebe J., Kinyanjui T., Cheplogoi Chairman P.K., Cheplogoi Chairman P.K., Chebet J., Cheplogoi P.K. Impact of frying on iodine value of vegetable oils before and after deep frying in different types of food in Kenya. J. Sci. Innov. Res. 2016;5:193–196. www.jsirjournal.com</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Hecke T., Le Ho P., Goethals S., De Smet S. The potential of herbs and spices to reduce lipid oxidation during heating and gastrointestinal digestion of a beef product Thomas. Food Res. Int. 2017 doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2017.09.090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2017.09.090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29196013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perestrelo R., Silva C., Silva P., Câmara J.S. Global volatile profile of virgin olive oils flavoured by aromatic/medicinal plants. Food Chem. 2017;227:111–121. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.01.090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.01.090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28274410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veronezi C.M., Costa T., Jorge N. Basil (ocimum BasilicumL.) as a natural antioxidant. J. Food Process. Preserv. 2014;38:255–261. doi: 10.1111/j.1745-4549.2012.00771.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4549.2012.00771.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo J., Zhao R., Li J., Wu D., Yang Q., Zhang Y., Wang S. Furan formation from ingredient interactions and furan mitigation by sugar alcohols and antioxidants of bamboo leaves in milk beverage model systems. 2019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.9739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30977142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taha E., Abouelhawa S., El-Geddawy M., Sorour M., Aladedunye F., Matthäus B. Stabilization of refined rapeseed oil during deep-fat frying by selected herbs. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol. 2014;116:771–779. doi: 10.1002/ejlt.201300279.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ejlt.201300279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Yang L., Zu Y., Chen X., Wang F., Liu F. Oxidative stability of sunflower oil supplemented with carnosic acid compared with synthetic antioxidants during accelerated storage. Food Chem. 2010;118:656–662. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.05.038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.05.038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25214334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitrea D.M., Mittasch M., Gomes B.F., Klein I.A., Murcko M.A. Modulating biomolecular condensates: a novel approach to drug discovery. Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 2022;21:841–862. doi: 10.1038/s41573-022-00505-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41573-022-00505-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9380678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35974095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassanien M.F.R., Sharoba A.M. Rheological characteristics of vegetable oils as affected by deep frying of French fries. J. Food Meas. Charact. 2014;8:171–179. doi: 10.1007/s11694-014-9178-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11694-014-9178-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jane M.N., Grace C. Vol. 8. 2020. pp. 117–120. (Investigation of the Effects of Repeated Frying on the Quality of Vegetable Oil).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11648/j.ajac.20200804.13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandran J., Nayana N., Roshini N., Nisha P. Oxidative stability, thermal stability and acceptability of coconut oil flavored with essential oils from black pepper and ginger. J. Food Sci. Technol. 2017;54:144–152. doi: 10.1007/s13197-016-2446-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-016-2446-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5305711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28242912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma R., Gao T., Song L., Zhang L., Jiang Y., Li J., Zhang X., Gao F., Zhou G. Effects of oil-water mixed frying and pure-oil frying on the quality characteristics of soybean oil and chicken chop. Food Sci. Technol. 2016;36:329–336. doi: 10.1590/1678-457X.0092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1678-457X.0092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava Y., Semwal A.D. A study on monitoring of frying performance and oxidative stability of virgin coconut oil (VCO) during continuous/prolonged deep fat frying process using chemical and FTIR spectroscopy. J. Food Sci. Technol. 2015;52:984–991. doi: 10.1007/s13197-013-1078-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-013-1078-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4325013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25694709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodoo D., Adjei F., Tulashie S.K., Adukpoh K.E., Agbolegbe R.K., Gawou K., Manu G.P. Quality evaluation of different repeatedly heated vegetable oils for deep-frying of yam fries. Meas. Food. 2022;7 doi: 10.1016/j.meafoo.2022.100035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meafoo.2022.100035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jing Y., Li X., Hu X., Ma Z., Liu L., Ma X. Effect of buckwheat extracts on acrylamide formation and the quality of bread. J. Sci. Food Agric. 2019;99:6482–6489. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.9927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.9927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31294827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chammem N., Saoudi S., Sifaoui I., Sifi S., de Person M., Abderraba M., Moussa F., Hamdi M. Improvement of vegetable oils quality in frying conditions by adding rosemary extract. Ind. Crops Prod. 2015;74:592–599. doi: 10.1016/j.indcrop.2015.05.054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2015.05.054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>