<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39288531</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1877-9603</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Ticks and tick-borne diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ticks Tick Borne Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Knowledge, attitudes and behaviour towards ticks and tick-borne diseases-A survey among Lyme borreliosis cases in Bavaria in 2019.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>102396</StartPage><MedlinePgn>102396</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2024.102396</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1877-959X(24)00089-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Lyme borreliosis (LB) is the most common tick-borne disease (TBD) in Germany. In Bavaria, the average annual incidence of reported cases was 34.3 cases per 100,000 inhabitants between 2013 and 2020, although case numbers were presumed to be substantially higher. Since no vaccine against LB is currently available, prevention focuses on individual protection measures. This study aims to address knowledge, attitudes, and behaviours among LB cases, a population group at increased exposure to ticks, tick bites and repeated infections. We invited Bavarian LB cases reported between weeks 23 and 35 in 2019 to participate in a questionnaire study. Questions included socio-demographic characteristics, experiences with TBDs, potential tick exposures, details of the recent episode of LB, and knowledge, attitudes, and behaviours regarding TBDs and protection measures. Among the 377 participants, 300 were adults/adolescents, 77 were children (&lt;14 years). Two third resided in rural areas. Although mostly well informed, a significant proportion of participants did not know or were misinformed about availability of repellents (48.5 %), risk of LB in their district (24.9 %), ticks not falling from trees (22.1 %) and non-availability of vaccination against LB (20.9 %). Even though a majority perceived checking for ticks after spending time outdoors, wearing long clothes, wearing closed shoes and tucking pants in socks as effective protection measures against tick bites, a much lower proportion applied those measures frequently (proportions perceived vs. applied: 99.2 % vs. 72.1%; 93.8 % vs. 40.2 %, 88.8 % vs. 51.1 % and 85.4 % vs. 16.8 %, respectively). Identified lack of knowledge or misconception regarding risk factors, availability of protection measures and tick behaviour may hamper application of recommended protection measures. There appeared to be a discrepancy between perceived effectiveness and frequency of application of protection measures. Addressing identified gaps in education campaigns, specifically targeting people living in rural areas, and utilising physician-patient interactions for education are promising entry points to increase awareness and prevent TBDs. Moreover, motivators and barriers for the application of preventive behaviour should be subject of future studies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Böhm</LastName><ForeName>Stefanie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit, Bavarian Health and Food Safety Authority (LGL), 80636 Munich, Germany; Faculty of Medicine, Ludwig-Maximilians-University of Munich, 80336 Munich, Germany. Electronic address: stefanie.boehm@lgl.bayern.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fingerle</LastName><ForeName>Volker</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Reference Centre for Borrelia, Bavarian Health and Food Safety Authority (LGL), 85764 Oberschleissheim, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beyerlein</LastName><ForeName>Andreas</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit, Bavarian Health and Food Safety Authority (LGL), 80636 Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wildner</LastName><ForeName>Manfred</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pettenkofer School of Public Health (PSPH), Ludwig Maximilians University, 81377 Munich, Germany; State Institute for Health, Bavarian Health and Food Safety Authority (LGL), 85764 Oberschleissheim, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Böhmer</LastName><ForeName>Merle M</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit, Bavarian Health and Food Safety Authority (LGL), 80636 Munich, Germany; Institute of Social Medicine and Health Systems Research, Otto-von-Guericke-University, 39120 Magdeburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Ticks Tick Borne Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101522599</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1877-959X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">KAB survey</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lyme borreliosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prevention</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Protection measure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tick-borne disease</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39288531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2024.102396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1877-959X(24)00089-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>