<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39283274</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2165-0497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbiology spectrum</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microbiol Spectr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Water chlorination increases the relative abundance of an antibiotic resistance marker in developing sourdough starters.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0112123</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0112123</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/spectrum.01121-23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">Multiple factors explain the proper development of sourdough starters. Although the role of raw ingredients and geography, among other things, have been widely studied recently, the possible effect of air quality and water chlorination on the overall bacterial communities associated with sourdough remains to be explored. Here, using <i>16S rRNA</i> amplicon sequencing, we show that clean, filtered-air severely limited the presence of lactic acid bacteria in sourdough starters, suggesting that surrounding air is an important source of microorganisms necessary for the development of sourdough starters. We also show that water chlorination at levels commonly found in drinking water systems has a limited impact on the overall bacterial communities developing in sourdough starters. However, using targeted sequencing, which offers a higher resolution, we found that the abundance of integron 1, a genetic mechanism responsible for the horizontal exchange of antibiotic-resistance genes in spoilage and pathogenic bacteria, increased significantly with the level of water chlorination. Although our results suggest that water chlorination might not impact sourdough starters at a deep phylogenetic level, they indicate that it can favor the spread of genetic elements associated with spoilage bacteria.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPORTANCE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Proper development of sourdough starters is critical for making tasty and healthy bread. Although many factors contributing to sourdough development have been studied, the effect of water chlorination on the bacterial communities in sourdough has been largely ignored. Researchers used sequencing techniques to investigate this effect and found that water chlorination at levels commonly found in drinking water systems has a limited impact on the overall bacterial communities developing in sourdough starters. However, they discovered that water chlorination could increase the abundance of integron 1, a genetic mechanism responsible for the horizontal exchange of antibiotic resistance genes in spoilage and pathogenic bacteria. This suggests that water chlorination could favor the growth of key spoilage bacteria and compromise the quality and safety of the bread. These findings emphasize the importance of considering water quality when developing sourdough starters for the best possible bread.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lau</LastName><ForeName>Pearson</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-7016-3008</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jain</LastName><ForeName>Swapan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7475-6754</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Perron</LastName><ForeName>Gabriel G</ForeName><Initials>GG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3526-5239</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Environmental Sciences &amp; Humanities, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Genomics and Systems Biology, New York University, New York, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Microbiol Spectr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101634614</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2165-0497</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">16S rRNA Amplicon</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fermentation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food microbioloy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">integron 1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbiomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sourdough</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">starters</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39283274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.01121-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>