<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39289805</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Managing the microbiological safety of tilapia from farm to consumer.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70023</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70023</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70023</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Tilapia stands out as one of the most extensively farmed and consumed fish species globally, valued for its ease of preparation and relative affordability. Although tilapia is a valuable protein source, it can also function as a vector for foodborne pathogens. This literature review reveals that tilapia could carry a variety of contamination with various foodborne pathogens, including Plesiomonas shigelloides, diarrheagenic Escherichia coli, Vibrio parahaemolyticus, Salmonella Weltevreden, Salmonella enterica, Shigella, Staphylococcus aureus, Campylobacter jejuni, Clostridium botulinum, and Listeria monocytogenes. Although guidelines from entities, such as the Global Seafood Alliance, Aquaculture Stewardship Council, and International Organization for Standardization, have been established to ensure the microbiological safety of tilapia, the unique challenges posed by pathogens in tilapia farming call for a more nuanced and targeted approach. Recognizing that contaminants could emerge at various stages of the tilapia supply chain, there is a crucial need for enhanced detection and monitoring of pathogens associated with this fish and its culturing environment. Additionally, it is essential to acknowledge the potential impact of climate change on the safety of tilapia, which may elevate the prevalence and contamination levels of pathogens in this fish. Proactive measures are essential to understand and mitigate the effects of climate change on tilapia production, ensuring the sustainability and safety of this seafood product for both present and future generations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ndraha</LastName><ForeName>Nodali</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8970-0342</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Food Technology and Processing, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Gunungkidul, Yogyakarta, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Hung-Yun</ForeName><Initials>HY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence for the Oceans, National Taiwan Ocean University, Keelung City, Taiwan (R.O.C.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hsiao</LastName><ForeName>Hsin-I</ForeName><Initials>HI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1920-0291</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, National Taiwan Ocean University, Keelung City, Taiwan (R.O.C.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Han-Jia</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4929-6573</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bioscience and Biotechnology, National Taiwan Ocean University, Keelung City, Taiwan (R.O.C.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NSTC110-2313-B-019-003-MY3</GrantID><Agency>National Science and Technology Council of Taiwan (R.O.C.)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>NSTC111-2311-B-019-003-MY3</GrantID><Agency>National Science and Technology Council of Taiwan (R.O.C.)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017210" MajorTopicYN="Y">Tilapia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017756" MajorTopicYN="Y">Aquaculture</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017747" MajorTopicYN="N">Seafood</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059022" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Safety</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005517" MajorTopicYN="N">Foodborne Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001419" MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">climate change</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">detection method</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">foodborne pathogen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">seafood safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">supply chain</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39289805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdel‐Latif, H. M. R., Dawood, M. A. O., Menanteau‐Ledouble, S., &amp; El‐Matbouli, M. (2020). The nature and consequences of co‐infections in tilapia: A review. Journal of Fish Diseases, 43, 651–664. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfd.13164</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel‐Latif, H. M. R., &amp; Khafaga, A. F. (2020). Natural co‐infection of cultured Nile tilapia Oreochromis niloticus with Aeromonas hydrophila and Gyrodactylus cichlidarum experiencing high mortality during summer. Aquaculture Research, 51, 1880–1892. https://doi.org/10.1111/are.14538</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Admasu, F., Mikru, A., Balkew, K., &amp; Adane, M. (2023). Microbial profile of fresh and semicooked Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) and hygienic practice of fish handlers in Hawassa, Ethiopia. International Journal of Microbiology, 2023, 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1155/2023/5866719</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akian, D. D., Quenum, C. L., Koua, D. N. Z., Houra, J. A. K., Clota, F., Bégout, M., &amp; Yao, K. (2022). Comparative study of larvae production by the Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus, Linné, 1758) Bouaké strain between earthen ponds and hapas. Aquaculture Research, 53, 6049–6055. https://doi.org/10.1111/are.16075</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam, M. M., &amp; Haque, M. M. (2021). Presence of antibacterial substances, nitrofuran metabolites and other chemicals in farmed pangasius and tilapia in Bangladesh: Probabilistic health risk assessment. Toxicology Reports, 8, 248–257. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxrep.2021.01.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alday‐Sanz, V., Brock, J., Flegel, T. W., McIntosh, R., Bondad‐Reantaso, M. G., Salazar, M., &amp; Subasinghe, R. (2020). Facts, truths and myths about SPF shrimp in aquaculture. Reviews in Aquaculture, 12, 76–84. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12305</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alejandro, D. J. C.‐S., Luis, D. E.‐C., Raquel, G.‐B., &amp; Alejandra, L. S. M.‐A. (2021). Fish, tilapia, and shigellosis: A review. African Journal of Agricultural Research, 17, 498–512. https://doi.org/10.5897/AJAR2021.15436</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arumugam, M., Jayaraman, S., Sridhar, A., Venkatasamy, V., Brown, P. B., Abdul Kari, Z., Tellez‐Isaias, G., &amp; Ramasamy, T. (2023). Recent advances in tilapia production for sustainable developments in Indian aquaculture and its economic benefits. Fishes, 8, 176. https://doi.org/10.3390/fishes8040176</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aquaculture Stewardship Council (ASC). (2019). ASC tilapia standard version 1.2. Aquaculture Stewardship Council. https://asc‐aqua.org/wp‐content/uploads/2019/03/ASC‐Tilapia‐Standard_v1.2_Final.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aung, M. M., &amp; Chang, Y. S. (2014). Temperature management for the quality assurance of a perishable food supply chain. Food Control, 40, 198–207. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2013.11.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bedane, T. D., Agga, G. E., &amp; Gutema, F. D. (2022). Hygienic assessment of fish handling practices along production and supply chain and its public health implications in Central Oromia, Ethiopia. Scientific Reports, 12, 13910. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐022‐17671‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell, R. L., Kase, J. A., Harrison, L. M., Balan, K. V., Babu, U., Chen, Y., Macarisin, D., Kwon, H. J., Zheng, J., Stevens, E. L., Meng, J., &amp; Brown, E. W. (2021). The persistence of bacterial pathogens in surface water and its impact on global food safety. Pathogens, 10, 1391. https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens10111391</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Billah, M. M., &amp; Rahman, M. S. (2024). Salmonella in the environment: A review on ecology, antimicrobial resistance, seafood contaminations, and human health implications. Journal of Hazardous Materials Advances, 13, 100407. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.hazadv.2024.100407</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolívar, A., Costa, J. C. C. P., Posada‐Izquierdo, G. D., Valero, A., Zurera, G., &amp; Pérez‐Rodríguez, F. (2018). Modelling the growth of Listeria monocytogenes in Mediterranean fish species from aquaculture production. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 270, 14–21. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.02.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosu, A., Haidar, M. I., Rahman, F., Rahman, A. M, Khan, M. H., &amp; Mahmud, Y. (2016). Risk factors associated with disease of tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) in cage culture systems. International Journal of Natural and Social Sciences, 3, 68–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brumfield, K. D., Usmani, M., Chen, K. M., Gangwar, M., Jutla, A. S., Huq, A., &amp; Colwell, R. R. (2021). Environmental parameters associated with incidence and transmission of pathogenic Vibrio spp. Environmental Microbiology, 23, 7314–7340. https://doi.org/10.1111/1462‐2920.15716</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budiati, T., Rusul, G., Wan‐Abdullah, W. N., Arip, Y. M., Ahmad, R., &amp; Thong, K. L. (2013). Prevalence, antibiotic resistance and plasmid profiling of Salmonella in catfish (Clarias gariepinus) and tilapia (Tilapia mossambica) obtained from wet markets and ponds in Malaysia. Aquaculture, 372–375, 127–132. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2012.11.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buzby, J. C., &amp; Roberts, D. (2011). Food trade and food safety violations: What can we learn from import refusal data? American Journal of Agricultural Economics, 93, 560–565. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajae/aaq148</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai, W., &amp; Arias, C. R. (2017). Biofilm formation on aquaculture substrates by selected bacterial fish pathogens. Journal of Aquatic Animal Health, 29, 95–104. https://doi.org/10.1080/08997659.2017.1290711</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavalcante, R. B., Telli, G. S., Tachibana, L., Dias, D. C., Oshiro, E., Natori, M. M., da Silva, W. F., &amp; Ranzani‐Paiva, M. J. (2020). Probiotics, prebiotics and synbiotics for Nile tilapia: Growth performance and protection against Aeromonas hydrophila infection. Aquaculture Reports, 17, 100343. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aqrep.2020.100343</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CFIA. (2019). Bacteriological guidelines for fish and fish products (end product). https://inspection.canada.ca/en/food-safety-industry/food-safety-standards-guidelines/bacteriological-guidelines (accessed on 24 March 2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Sun, R., Pan, C., Sun, Y., Mai, B., &amp; Li, Q. X. (2020). Antibiotics and food safety in aquaculture. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 68, 11908–11919. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.0c03996</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho, S., Jackson, C. R., &amp; Frye, J. G. (2020). The prevalence and antimicrobial resistance phenotypes of Salmonella, Escherichia coli and Enterococcus sp. in surface water. Letters in Applied Microbiology, 71, 3–25. https://doi.org/10.1111/lam.13301</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhury, N. R. (2024). Tilapia market outlook (2024 to 2034). Future Market Insights Inc. https://www.futuremarketinsights.com/reports/tilapia‐market</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung, C.‐Y., Chen, Y.‐J., Kang, C.‐H., Lin, H.‐Y., Huang, C.‐C., Hsu, P.‐H., &amp; Lin, H.‐J. (2021). Toxic or not toxic, that is the carbon quantum dot's question: A comprehensive evaluation with zebrafish embryo, eleutheroembryo, and adult models. Polymers, 13, 1598. https://doi.org/10.3390/polym13101598</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cortés‐Sánchez, A. D. J., Espinosa‐Chaurand, L. D., Díaz‐Ramirez, M., &amp; Torres‐Ochoa, E. (2021). Plesiomonas: A review on food safety, fish‐borne diseases, and tilapia. The Scientific World Journal, 2021, 1–10. https://doi.org/10.1155/2021/3119958</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delphino, M. K. V. C., Leal, C. A. G., Gardner, I. A., Assis, G. B. N., Roriz, G. D., Ferreira, F., Figueiredo, H. C. P., &amp; Gonçalves, V. S. P. (2019). Seasonal dynamics of bacterial pathogens of Nile tilapia farmed in a Brazilian reservoir. Aquaculture, 498, 100–108. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2018.08.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewi, R. R., Hassan, L., Daud, H. M., Matori, M. F., Nordin, F., Ahmad, N. I., &amp; Zakaria, Z. (2022). Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance of Escherichia coli, Salmonella and Vibrio derived from farm‐raised red hybrid tilapia (Oreochromis spp.) and Asian sea bass (Lates calcarifer, Bloch 1970) on the West Coast of Pen. Antibiotics, 11, 136. https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics11020136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong, H. T., Chaijarasphong, T., Barnes, A. C., Delamare‐Deboutteville, J., Lee, P. A., Senapin, S., Mohan, C. V., Tang, K. F. J., McGladdery, S. E., &amp; Bondad‐Reantaso, M. G. (2023). From the basics to emerging diagnostic technologies: What is on the horizon for tilapia disease diagnostics? Reviews in Aquaculture, 15, 186–212. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12734</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duchenne‐Moutien, R. A., &amp; Neetoo, H. (2021). Climate change and emerging food safety issues: A review. Journal of Food Protection, 84, 1884–1897. https://doi.org/10.4315/JFP‐21‐141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EC. (2020). Commission regulation (EC) No. 2073/2005 of 15 November 2005 on microbiological criteria for foodstuffs. https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/ALL/?uri=CELEX%3A32005R2073 (accessed on 20 March 2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edris, A. M., Amany, M. S., &amp; Fouad, M. A. (2014). Incidence of Listeria monocytogenes in fresh tilapia nilotica fish. Benha Veterinary Medical Journal, 26, 120–126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elbashir, S., Jahncke, M., DePaola, A., Bowers, J., Schwarz, J., Punchihewage‐Don, A. J., Min, B., Rippen, T., &amp; Parveen, S. (2023). Prevalence and abundance of bacterial pathogens of concern in shrimp, catfish and tilapia obtained at retail stores in Maryland, USA. Pathogens, 12, 187. https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens12020187</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El‐Sayed, A.‐F. M., &amp; Fitzsimmons, K. (2023). From Africa to the world—The journey of Nile tilapia. Reviews in Aquaculture, 15, 6–21. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12738</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eltholth, M., Fornace, K., Grace, D., Rushton, J., &amp; Häsler, B. (2018). Assessing the chemical and microbiological quality of farmed tilapia in Egyptian fresh fish markets. Global Food Security, 17, 14–20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2018.03.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO. (2022). The State of World Fisheries and Aquaculture. Towards Blue Transformation. Rome, FAO. https://doi.org/10.4060/cc0461en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO. (2024). FishStat: Global production by production source 1950‐2022. In: FishStatJ. Available at www.fao.org/fishery/en/statistics/software/fishstatj (accessed on 29 March 2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FSSAI. (2011). Compendium on food safety and standards (food products standards and food additives) regulation. https://www.fssai.gov.in/cms/Compendium-FSS-FPS-FA.php (accessed on 20 March 2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). (2021). Invasive disease linked to raw freshwater fish. Food and Agriculture Organization. https://www.fao.org/documents/card/en/c/CB4901EN</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima, S., Komal, W., Manzoor, F., Latif, A. A., Liaqat, R., Ameen, S., &amp; Janjua, R. S. (2021). Analysis of the growth performance, stress, profile of fatty acids and amino acids and cortisol in Tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus), cultured at high stocking density using in‐pond raceway system. Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences, 28, 7422–7431. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sjbs.2021.08.048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez‐Saiz, P., Soler, C., Lagaron, J. M., &amp; Ocio, M. J. (2010). Effects of chitosan films on the growth of Listeria monocytogenes, Staphylococcus aureus and Salmonella spp. in laboratory media and in fish soup. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 137, 287–294. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2009.11.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira, A. C. A. D. O., Pavelquesi, S. L. S., da Silva Monteiro, E., Rodrigues, L. F. S., de Souza Silva, C. M., da Silva, I. C. R., &amp; Orsi, D. C. (2021). Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance of Salmonella spp. in aquacultured Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) commercialized in Federal district, Brazil. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease, 18, 778–783. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2021.0010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foddai, A. C. G., &amp; Grant, I. R. (2020). Methods for detection of viable foodborne pathogens: Current state‐of‐art and future prospects. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 104, 4281–4288. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253‐020‐10542‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freitas, J., Vaz‐Pires, P., &amp; Câmara, J. S. (2020). From aquaculture production to consumption: Freshness, safety, traceability and authentication, the four pillars of quality. Aquaculture, 518, 734857. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2019.734857</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Froelich, B. A., &amp; Daines, D. A. (2020). In hot water: Effects of climate change on Vibrio–human interactions. Environmental Microbiology, 22, 4101–4111. https://doi.org/10.1111/1462‐2920.14967</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food Standards Australia New Zealand (FSANZ). (2022). Compendium of microbiological criteria for food. Food Standards Australia New Zealand. https://www.foodstandards.gov.au/publications/Compendium‐of‐Microbiological‐Criteria‐for‐Food</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, R., Liao, X., Zhao, X., Liu, D., &amp; Ding, T. (2021). The diagnostic tools for viable but nonculturable pathogens in the food industry: Current status and future prospects. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 20, 2146–2175. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12695</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghenem, L., Elhadi, N., Alzahrani, F., &amp; Nishibuchi, M. (2017). Vibrio parahaemolyticus: A review on distribution, pathogenesis, virulence determinants and epidemiology. Saudi Journal of Medicine &amp; Medical Sciences, 5, 93–103. https://doi.org/10.4103/sjmms.sjmms_30_17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibtan, A., Getahun, A., &amp; Mengistou, S. (2008). Effect of stocking density on the growth performance and yield of Nile tilapia [Oreochromis niloticus (L., 1758)] in a cage culture system in Lake Kuriftu, Ethiopia. Aquaculture Research, 39, 1450–1460. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2109.2008.02021.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Seafood Alliance. (2023). Best aquaculture practices certification. Global Seafood Alliance. https://www.bapcertification.org/Downloadables/pdf/GSA‐FarmStandard‐Issue3.1‐07‐February‐2023.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu, D., Hu, Y., Wei, H., Zhu, Y., Mu, X., Luo, D., Xu, M., &amp; Yang, Y. (2017). Nile tilapia Oreochromis niloticus (L.). In Biological invasions and its management in China (pp. 77–89). Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐981‐10‐3427‐5_5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haenen, O. L. M., Dong, H. T., Hoai, T. D., Crumlish, M., Karunasagar, I., Barkham, T., Chen, S. L., Zadoks, R., Kiermeier, A., Wang, B., Gamarro, E. G., Takeuchi, M., Azmai, M. N. A., Fouz, B., Pakingking, R., Wei, Z. W., &amp; Bondad‐Reantaso, M. G. (2023). Bacterial diseases of tilapia, their zoonotic potential and risk of antimicrobial resistance. Reviews in Aquaculture, 15, 154–185. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12743</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havelaar, A. H., Brul, S., de Jong, A., de Jonge, R., Zwietering, M. H., &amp; ter Kuile, B. H. (2010). Future challenges to microbial food safety. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 139, S79–S94. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2009.10.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henry‐Silva, G. G., Melo‐Junior, H. d. N., &amp; Attayde, J. L. (2019). Extreme drought events and the sustainability of fish farming in net cages in reservoirs of the semi‐arid northeastern region in Brazil. Acta Limnologica Brasiliensia, 31, e112. https://doi.org/10.1590/s2179‐975x7519</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heuer, O. E., Kruse, H., Grave, K., Collignon, P., Karunasagar, I., &amp; Angulo, F. J. (2009). Human health consequences of use of antimicrobial agents in aquaculture. Clinical Infectious Diseases, 49, 1248–1253. https://doi.org/10.1086/605667</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HPA [Health Protection Agency]. (2009). Guidelines for assessing the microbiological safety of ready‐to‐eat foods placed on the market. Health Protection Agency. https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/ready‐to‐eat‐foods‐microbiological‐safety‐assessment‐guidelines</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, H.‐T., Lin, H.‐J., Huang, H.‐J., Huang, C.‐C., Lin, J. H.‐Y., &amp; Chen, L.‐L. (2020). Synthesis and evaluation of polyamine carbon quantum dots (CQDs) in Litopenaeus vannamei as a therapeutic agent against WSSV. Scientific Reports, 10, 7343. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐020‐64325‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Commission on Microbiological Specifications for Foods (ICMSF). (1986). Microorganism in foods 2. Sampling for microbiological analysis: Principles and specific (2nd ed.). Blackwell Scientific Publications.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Organization for Standardization (ISO). (2007). ISO/TC 234 – Fisheries and aquaculture. International Organization for Standardization. https://www.iso.org/committee/541071.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jian, H.‐J., Wu, R.‐S., Lin, T.‐Y., Li, Y.‐J., Lin, H.‐J., Harroun, S. G., Lai, J.‐Y., &amp; Huang, C.‐C. (2017). Super‐cationic carbon quantum dots synthesized from spermidine as an eye drop formulation for topical treatment of bacterial keratitis. ACS Nano, 11, 6703–6716. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsnano.7b01023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Junior, P. G., Assunção, A. W. A., Baldin, J. C., &amp; Amaral, L. A. (2014). Microbiological quality of whole and filleted shelf‐tilapia. Aquaculture, 433, 196–200. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2014.06.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kabiraz, M. P., Majumdar, P. R., Mahmud, M. M. C., Bhowmik, S., &amp; Ali, A. (2023). Conventional and advanced detection techniques of foodborne pathogens: A comprehensive review. Heliyon, 9, e15482. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e15482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaktcham, P. M., Temgoua, J. B., Ngoufack Zambou, F., Diaz‐Ruiz, G., Wacher, C., &amp; Pérez‐Chabela, M. (2017). Quantitative analyses of the bacterial microbiota of rearing environment, tilapia and common carp cultured in earthen ponds and inhibitory activity of its lactic acid bacteria on fish spoilage and pathogenic bacteria. World Journal of Microbiology and Biotechnology, 33, 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11274‐016‐2197‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamaruddin, R., &amp; Baharuddin, A. H. (2015). The importance of good aquaculture practices in improving fish farmer's income. International Journal of Social Economics, 42, 1090–1105. https://doi.org/10.1108/IJSE‐02‐2014‐0028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalefa, H. S., Ahmed, Z. S., Abdel‐Kader, F., Ismail, E. M., &amp; Elshafiee, E. A. (2021). Sequencing and phylogenetic analysis of the stn gene of Salmonella species isolated from different environmental sources at Lake Qarun protectorate: The role of migratory birds and public health importance. Veterinary World, 14, 2764–2772. https://doi.org/10.14202/vetworld.2021.2764‐2772</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyule‐Muendo, D., Otachi, E., Awour, F., Ogello, E., Obiero, K., Abwao, J., Muthoni, C., &amp; Munguti, J. (2022). Status of fish health management and biosecurity measures in fish farms, cages and hatcheries in Western Kenya. CABI Agriculture and Bioscience, 3, 18. https://doi.org/10.1186/s43170‐022‐00086‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lall, S. P., &amp; Tibbetts, S. M. (2009). Nutrition, feeding, and behavior of fish. Veterinary Clinics of North America: Exotic Animal Practice, 12, 361–372. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cvex.2009.01.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leal, M. C., Pimentel, T., Ricardo, F., Rosa, R., &amp; Calado, R. (2015). Seafood traceability: Current needs, available tools, and biotechnological challenges for origin certification. Trends in Biotechnology, 33, 331–336. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tibtech.2015.03.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lebel, P., Whangchai, N., Chitmanat, C., &amp; Lebel, L. (2015). Risk of impacts from extreme weather and climate in river‐based tilapia cage culture in Northern Thailand. International Journal of Global Warming, 8, 534. https://doi.org/10.1504/IJGW.2015.073054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehel, J., Yaucat‐Guendi, R., Darnay, L., Palotás, P., &amp; Laczay, P. (2021). Possible food safety hazards of ready‐to‐eat raw fish containing product (sushi, sashimi). Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 61, 867–888. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2020.1749024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lerma‐Fierro, A. G., Flores‐López, M. K., Guzmán‐Robles, M. L., &amp; de Jesús Cortés‐Sánchez, A. (2020). Microbiological evaluation of minimally processed and marketed fish in popular market of the city of Tepic Nayarit, Mexico: Sanitary quality of tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus). Tropicultura, 38, 1–19. https://doi.org/10.25518/2295‐8010.1556</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, K., Liu, L., Zhan, J., Scippo, M.‐L., Hvidtfeldt, K., Liu, Y., &amp; Dalsgaard, A. (2017). Sources and fate of antimicrobials in integrated fish‐pig and non‐integrated tilapia farms. Science of the Total Environment, 595, 393–399. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.01.124</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, K., Petersen, G., Barco, L., Hvidtfeldt, K., Liu, L., &amp; Dalsgaard, A. (2017). Salmonella Weltevreden in integrated and non‐integrated tilapia aquaculture systems in Guangdong, China. Food Microbiology, 65, 19–24. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2017.01.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, L., Meng, H., Gu, D., Li, Y., &amp; Jia, M. (2019). Molecular mechanisms of Vibrio parahaemolyticus pathogenesis. Microbiological Research, 222, 43–51. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micres.2019.03.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y. J., Harroun, S. G., Su, Y.‐C., Huang, C.‐F., Unnikrishnan, B., Lin, H.‐J., Lin, C.‐H., &amp; Huang, C.‐C. (2016). Synthesis of self‐assembled spermidine‐carbon quantum dots effective against multidrug‐resistant bacteria. Advanced Healthcare Materials, 5, 2545–2554. https://doi.org/10.1002/adhm.201600297</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, H.‐Y., Yen, S.‐C., Kang, C.‐H., Chung, C.‐Y., Hsu, M.‐C., Wang, C.‐Y., Lin, J. H.‐Y., Huang, C.‐C., &amp; Lin, H.‐J. (2022). How to evaluate the potential toxicity of therapeutic carbon nanomaterials? A comprehensive study of carbonized nanogels with multiple animal toxicity test models. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 429, 128337. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.128337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, H.‐Y., Yen, S.‐C., Tsai, S.‐K., Shen, F., Lin, J. H.‐Y., &amp; Lin, H.‐J. (2022). Combining direct PCR technology and capillary electrophoresis for an easy‐to‐operate and highly sensitive infectious disease detection system for shrimp. Life, 12, 276. https://doi.org/10.3390/life12020276</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, Y.‐T., Pan, Y.‐F., &amp; Han, Y.‐S. (2023). Effects of adding spermidine carbon quantum dots in feed on growth, intestinal morphology, immunity and disease resistance of Anguilla japonica and Anguilla marmorata. Aquaculture Reports, 33, 101847. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aqrep.2023.101847</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, H., Whitehouse, C. A., &amp; Li, B. (2018). Presence and persistence of Salmonella in water: The impact on microbial quality of water and food safety. Frontiers in Public Health, 6, 159. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2018.00159</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, W., Lyu, J., Wu, D., Cao, Y., Ma, Q., Lu, Y., &amp; Zhang, X. (2022). Cutting techniques in the fish industry: A critical review. Foods, 11, 3206. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11203206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Gilchrist, A., Zhang, J., &amp; Li, X.‐F. (2008). Detection of viable but nonculturable Escherichia coli O157:H7 bacteria in drinking water and river water. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 74, 1502–1507. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.02125‐07</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lulijwa, R., Rupia, E. J., &amp; Alfaro, A. C. (2020). Antibiotic use in aquaculture, policies and regulation, health and environmental risks: A review of the top 15 major producers. Reviews in Aquaculture, 12, 640–663. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12344</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, G., Gao, Q., Wang, C., Liu, W., Sun, D., Li, L., &amp; Tan, H. (2014). Growth, digestive activity, welfare, and partial cost‐effectiveness of genetically improved farmed tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) cultured in a recirculating aquaculture system and an indoor biofloc system. Aquaculture, 422–423, 1–7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2013.11.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacFadden, D. R., McGough, S. F., Fisman, D., Santillana, M., &amp; Brownstein, J. S. (2018). Antibiotic resistance increases with local temperature. Nature Climate Change, 8, 510–514. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558‐018‐0161‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacKinnon, B., Debnath, P. P., Bondad‐Reantaso, M. G., Fridman, S., Bin, H., &amp; Nekouei, O. (2023). Improving tilapia biosecurity through a value chain approach. Reviews in Aquaculture, 15, 57–91. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12776</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makori, A. J., Abuom, P. O., Kapiyo, R., Anyona, D. N., &amp; Dida, G. O. (2017). Effects of water physico‐chemical parameters on tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) growth in earthen ponds in Teso North Sub‐County, Busia County. Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences, 20, 30. https://doi.org/10.1186/s41240‐017‐0075‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd El Maksod, H. E., Saad, S. M., &amp; Samir, M. M. (2023). Microbiological evaluation of some farmed fish species marketed in Sharkia Governorate, Egypt. Journal of Advanced Veterinary Research, 13, 1117–1123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez‐Cordero, F. J., Delgadillo, T. S., Sanchez‐Zazueta, E., &amp; Cai, J. (2021). Tilapia aquaculture in Mexico: Assessment with a focus on social and economic performance. FAO. https://doi.org/10.4060/cb3290en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercier, S., Villeneuve, S., Mondor, M., &amp; Uysal, I. (2017). Time‐temperature management along the food cold chain: A review of recent developments. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 16, 647–667. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12269</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morey, A., &amp; Singh, M. (2012). Low‐temperature survival of Salmonella spp. in a model food system with natural microflora. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease, 9, 218–223. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2011.1016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morshdy, A. E. M. A., Hussein, M. A., Elessawy, E. A. M., &amp; Darwish, W. (2023). Microbial quality of tilapia nilotica in Egypt: A review. Journal of Advanced Veterinary Research, 13, 1234–1236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moura, R. S. T., Valenti, W. C., &amp; Henry‐Silva, G. G. (2016). Sustainability of Nile tilapia net‐cage culture in a reservoir in a semi‐arid region. Ecological Indicators, 66, 574–582. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolind.2016.01.052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mugwanya, M., Dawood, M. A. O. O., Kimera, F., &amp; Sewilam, H. (2022). Updating the role of probiotics, prebiotics, and synbiotics for tilapia aquaculture as leading candidates for food sustainability: A review. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins, 14, 130–157. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12602‐021‐09852‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhling, B. A., Jacobs, J., Stock, C. A., Gaitan, C. F., &amp; Saba, V. S. (2017). Projections of the future occurrence, distribution, and seasonality of three Vibrio species in the Chesapeake Bay under a high‐emission climate change scenario. GeoHealth, 1, 278–296. https://doi.org/10.1002/2017GH000089</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mumbo, M. T., Nyaboga, E. N., Kinyua, J., Muge, E. K., Mathenge, S. G. K., Muriira, G., Rotich, H., Njiraini, B., &amp; Njiru, J. M. (2023b). Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance profile of bacterial foodborne pathogens in Nile tilapia fish (Oreochromis niloticus) at points of retail sale in Nairobi, Kenya. Frontiers in Antibiotics, 2, 1156258. https://doi.org/10.3389/frabi.2023.1156258</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mumbo, M. T., Nyaboga, E. N., Kinyua, J. K., Muge, E. K., Mathenge, S. G. K., Rotich, H., Muriira, G., Njiraini, B., &amp; Njiru, J. M. (2023a). Antimicrobial resistance profiles of Salmonella spp. and Escherichia coli isolated from fresh Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) fish marketed for human consumption. BMC Microbiology, 23, 306. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866‐023‐03049‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mungkung, R., Aubin, J., Prihadi, T. H., Slembrouck, J., van der Werf, H. M. G., &amp; Legendre, M. (2013). Life cycle assessment for environmentally sustainable aquaculture management: A case study of combined aquaculture systems for carp and tilapia. Journal of Cleaner Production, 57, 249–256. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2013.05.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray, K. N., Clark, T. S., Kebus, M. J., &amp; Kent, M. L. (2022). Specific pathogen free—A review of strategies in agriculture, aquaculture, and laboratory mammals and how they inform new recommendations for laboratory zebrafish. Research in Veterinary Science, 142, 78–93. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rvsc.2021.11.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha, N., &amp; Hsiao, H.‐I. (2021). Influence of climatic factors on the temporal occurrence and distribution of total and pathogenic Vibrio parahaemolyticus in oyster culture environments in Taiwan. Food Microbiology, 98, 103765. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2021.103765</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha, N., &amp; Hsiao, H.‐I. (2022). A climate‐driven model for predicting the level of Vibrio parahaemolyticus in oysters harvested from Taiwanese farms using elastic net regularized regression. Microbial Risk Analysis, 21, 100201. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mran.2022.100201</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha, N., Hsiao, H.‐I. I., Vlajic, J., Yang, M.‐F. F., &amp; Lin, H.‐T. V. T. V. (2018). Time‐temperature abuse in the food cold chain: Review of issues, challenges, and recommendations. Food Control, 89, 12–21. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.01.027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha, N., Huang, L., Wu, V. C., &amp; Hsiao, H.‐I. (2022). Vibrio parahaemolyticus in seafood: Recent progress in understanding influential factors at harvest and food‐safety intervention approaches. Current Opinion in Food Science, 48, 100927. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2022.100927</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha, N., Lin, H.‐Y., Tsai, S.‐K., Hsiao, H.‐I., &amp; Lin, H.‐J. (2023). The rapid detection of Salmonella enterica, Listeria monocytogenes, and Staphylococcus aureus via polymerase chain reaction combined with magnetic beads and capillary electrophoresis. Foods, 12, 3895. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12213895</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha, N., Lin, H.‐Y., Wang, C.‐Y., Hsiao, H.‐I., &amp; Lin, H.‐J. (2023). Rapid detection methods for foodborne pathogens based on nucleic acid amplification: Recent advances, remaining challenges, and possible opportunities. Food Chemistry: Molecular Sciences, 7, 100183. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fochms.2023.100183</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndraha, N., Wong, H.‐C. C., &amp; Hsiao, H.‐I. (2020). Managing the risk of Vibrio parahaemolyticus infections associated with oyster consumption: A review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 19, 1187–1217. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12557</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NHCC [National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China]. (2021). National standards for food safety pathogenic microorganism limits in prepacked foodstuffs. State Administration for Market Regulation. https://www.codeofchina.com/standard/GB29921‐2021.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noorlis, A., Ghazali, F. M., Cheah, Y. K., Tuan Zainazor, T. C., Ponniah, J., Tunung, R., Tang, J. Y. H., Nishibuchi, M., Nakaguchi, Y., &amp; Son, R. (2011). Prevalence and quantification of Vibrio species and Vibrio parahaemolyticus in freshwater fish at hypermarket level. International Food Research Journal, 18, 689–695. https://doi.org/10.13224/j.cnki.jasp.2014.02.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novoslavskij, A., Terentjeva, M., Eizenberga, I., Valciņa, O., Bartkevičs, V., &amp; Bērziņš, A. (2016). Major foodborne pathogens in fish and fish products: A review. Annals of Microbiology, 66, 1–15. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13213‐015‐1102‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NSAI [National Standardization Agency of Indonesia]. (2021). SNI 2729:2021 Fresh fish (in Indonesian). National Standardization Agency of Indonesia. http://sispk.bsn.go.id/SNI/DetailSNI/13810</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odeyemi, O. A. (2016). Incidence and prevalence of Vibrio parahaemolyticus in seafood: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. SpringerPlus, 5, 464. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40064‐016‐2115‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onjong, H. A., Ngayo, M. O., Mwaniki, M., Wambui, J., &amp; Njage, P. M. K. (2018). Microbiological safety of fresh tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) from Kenyan fresh water fish value chains. Journal of Food Protection, 81, 1973–1981. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐18‐078</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onjong, H. A., Ntuli, V., Mwaniki, M., &amp; Njage, P. M. K. (2021). Exposure assessment to staphylococcus enterotoxins in Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) supplied through semi‐regulated and unregulated value chains. Food Control, 119, 107487. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107487</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onjong, H. A., Ntuli, V., Wambui, J., Mwaniki, M., &amp; Njage, P. M. K. (2021). Potential influence of regulation of the food value chain on prevalence and patterns of antimicrobial resistance: The case of tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus). Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 87(23), e0094521. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.00945‐21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otomo, Y., Abe, K., Odagiri, K., Shiroto, A., Takatori, K., &amp; Hara‐Kudo, Y. (2007). Detection of Salmonella in spent hens and eggs associated with foodborne infections. Avian Diseases, 51, 578–583. https://doi.org/10.1637/0005‐2086(2007)51[578:DOSISH]2.0.CO;2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palonen, E., Lindström, M., &amp; Korkeala, H. (2010). Adaptation of enteropathogenic Yersinia to low growth temperature. Critical Reviews in Microbiology, 36, 54–67. https://doi.org/10.3109/10408410903382581</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey, P. K., &amp; Kumar, V. S. (2021). Biofilm in aquaculture production. In Advances in fisheries biotechnology (pp. 401–422). Springer Nature. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐981‐16‐3215‐0_23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paredes‐Trujillo, A., &amp; Mendoza‐Carranza, M. (2022). A systematic review and meta‐analysis of the relationship between farm management, water quality and pathogen outbreaks in tilapia culture. Journal of Fish Diseases, 45, 1529–1548. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfd.13679</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil, P. K., Mishra, S. S., Pradhan, P. K., Manna, S. K., Abraham, J. T., Solanki, H. G., Shahi, N., Swain, P., Sahoo, S. N., Avunje, S., Sharma, K. S. R., Geetha, R., Priyadharshini, R., Nagaraju, V. T., Paniprasad, K., Kumar, A., Debnath, D., Panikkar, P., Raja, R. A., … Jena, J. (2022). Usage pattern of chemicals, biologicals and veterinary medicinal products in Indian aquaculture. Reviews in Aquaculture, 14, 2038–2063. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12688</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires, N. M. M., Dong, T., Yang, Z., &amp; da Silva, L. F. B. A. (2021). Recent methods and biosensors for foodborne pathogen detection in fish: Progress and future prospects to sustainable aquaculture systems. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 61, 1852–1876. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2020.1767032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prabu, E., Rajagopalsamy, C. B. T., Ahilan, B., Jeevagan, I. J. M. A., &amp; Renuhadevi, M. (2019). Tilapia—An excellent candidate species for world aquaculture: A review. Annual Research &amp; Review in Biology, 3, 1–14. https://doi.org/10.9734/arrb/2019/v31i330052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preena, P. G., Dharmaratnam, A., &amp; Swaminathan, T. R. (2020). Antimicrobial resistance analysis of pathogenic bacteria isolated from freshwater Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) cultured in Kerala, India. Current Microbiology, 77, 3278–3287. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00284‐020‐02158‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramamurthy, T., Ghosh, A., Pazhani, G. P., &amp; Shinoda, S. (2014). Current perspectives on viable but non‐culturable (VBNC) pathogenic bacteria. Frontiers in Public Health, 2, 103. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2014.00103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjbar, R., &amp; Halaji, M. (2018). Epidemiology of Listeria monocytogenes prevalence in foods, animals and human origin from Iran: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. BMC Public Health [Electronic Resource], 18, 1057. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889‐018‐5966‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reilly, P. (2023, September 16). California mom had all her limbs amputated after consuming bad tilapia: ‘She almost lost her life’. New York Post. https://nypost.com/2023/09/16/california‐woman‐has‐all‐four‐limbs‐amputated‐after‐fighting‐bacterial‐infection‐from‐eating‐talapia/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reverter, M., Sarter, S., Caruso, D., Avarre, J.‐C., Combe, M., Pepey, E., Pouyaud, L., Vega‐Heredía, S., de Verdal, H., &amp; Gozlan, R. E. (2020). Aquaculture at the crossroads of global warming and antimicrobial resistance. Nature Communications, 11, 1870. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐020‐15735‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross, T., Dalgaard, P., &amp; Tienungoon, S. (2000). Predictive modelling of the growth and survival of Listeria in fishery products. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 62, 231–245. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0168‐1605(00)00340‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw, K. S., Jacobs, J. M., &amp; Crump, B. C. (2014). Impact of Hurricane Irene on Vibrio vulnificus and Vibrio parahaemolyticus concentrations in surface water, sediment, and cultured oysters in the Chesapeake Bay, MD, USA. Frontiers in Microbiology, 5, 1–10. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2014.00204</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Sheikha, A. F., &amp; Montet, D. (2016). How to determine the geographical origin of seafood? Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 56, 306–317. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2012.745478</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Sheikha, A. F., &amp; Xu, J., (JP). (2017). Traceability as a key of seafood safety: Reassessment and possible applications. Reviews in Fisheries Science &amp; Aquaculture, 25, 158–170. https://doi.org/10.1080/23308249.2016.1254158</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng, L., &amp; Wang, L. (2021). The microbial safety of fish and fish products: Recent advances in understanding its significance, contamination sources, and control strategies. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 20, 738–786. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12671</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherif, A. H., &amp; AbuLeila, R. H. (2022). Prevalence of some pathogenic bacteria in caged‐Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) and their possible treatment. Jordan Journal of Biological Sciences, 15, 239–247. https://doi.org/10.54319/jjbs/150211</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shinn, A. P., Avenant‐Oldewage, A., Bondad‐Reantaso, M. G., Cruz‐Laufer, A. J., García‐Vásquez, A., Hernández‐Orts, J. S., Kuchta, R., Longshaw, M., Metselaar, M., Pariselle, A., Pérez‐Ponce de León, G., Pradhan, P. K., Rubio‐Godoy, M., Sood, N., Vanhove, M. P. M., &amp; Deveney, M. R. (2023). A global review of problematic and pathogenic parasites of farmed tilapia. Reviews in Aquaculture, 15, 92–153. https://doi.org/10.1111/raq.12742</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, S. S. M., Yadav, A. S., Singh, S. S. M., &amp; Bharti, P. (2010). Prevalence of Salmonella in chicken eggs collected from poultry farms and marketing channels and their antimicrobial resistance. Food Research International, 43, 2027–2030. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2010.06.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, M., &amp; Lutz, G. C. (2022). Introduction to aquaculture in the North Central region. North Central Regional Aquaculture Center. https://doi.org/10.25923/wvv8‐mh08</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sripradite, J., Thaotumpitak, V., Atwill, E. R., Hinthong, W., &amp; Jeamsripong, S. (2024). Distribution of bacteria and antimicrobial resistance in retail Nile tilapia (Oreochromis spp.) as potential sources of foodborne illness. PLoS ONE, 19, e0299987. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299987</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thaotumpitak, V., Sripradite, J., Atwill, E. R., Tepaamorndech, S., &amp; Jeamsripong, S. (2022). Bacterial pathogens and factors associated with Salmonella contamination in hybrid red tilapia (Oreochromis spp.) cultivated in a cage culture system. Food Quality and Safety, 6, fyac036. https://doi.org/10.1093/fqsafe/fyac036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thaotumpitak, V., Tepaamorndech, S., Sripradite, J., Atwill, E. R., Anuntawirun, S., Chantarasakha, K., &amp; Jeamsripong, S. (2024). Insights into antimicrobial and multidrug resistance of Escherichia coli in hybrid red tilapia cultivation. Aquaculture, 588, 740927. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2024.740927</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuševljak, N., Rajić, A., Waddell, L., Dutil, L., Cernicchiaro, N., Greig, J., Wilhelm, B. J., Wilkins, W., Totton, S., Uhland, F. C., Avery, B., &amp; McEwen, S. A. (2012). Prevalence of zoonotic bacteria in wild and farmed aquatic species and seafood: A scoping study, systematic review, and meta‐analysis of published research. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease, 9, 487–497. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2011.1063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US FDA. (2005). Quantitative risk assessment on the public health impact of pathogenic Vibrio parahaemolyticus in raw oysters. U.S. Food and Drug Administration. https://www.fda.gov/Food/FoodScienceResearch/RiskSafetyAssessment/ucm050421.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US FDA. (2022). Fish and fishery products hazards and controls guidance. https://www.fda.gov/media/80637/download (accessed on 20 March 2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaiyapuri, M., Joseph, T. C., Rao, B. M., Lalitha, K. V., &amp; Prasad, M. M. (2019). Methicillin‐resistant Staphylococcus aureus in seafood: Prevalence, laboratory detection, clonal nature, and control in seafood chain. Journal of Food Science, 84, 3341–3351. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.14915</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valero, A., Pérez‐Rodríguez, F., Carrasco, E., Fuentes‐Alventosa, J. M., García‐Gimeno, R. M., &amp; Zurera, G. (2009). Modelling the growth boundaries of Staphylococcus aureus: Effect of temperature, pH and water activity. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 133, 186–194. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2009.05.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vergis, J., Rawool, D., Singh Malik, S., &amp; Barbuddhe, S. (2021). Food safety in fisheries: Application of one health approach. Indian Journal of Medical Research, 153, 348. https://doi.org/10.4103/ijmr.IJMR_573_21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker, L., Sun, S., Lau, S. K., Phebus, R. K., Subbiah, J., &amp; Thippareddi, H. (2024). Modeling the growth/no growth response of non‐O157 Shiga toxin‐producing Escherichia coli to temperature, pH and water activity. Lebensmittel‐Wissenschaft &amp; Technologie, 202, 116292. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2024.116292</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, C.‐Y., Ndraha, N., Wu, R.‐S., Liu, H.‐Y., Lin, S.‐W., Yang, K.‐M., &amp; Lin, H.‐Y. (2023). An overview of the potential of food‐based carbon dots for biomedical applications. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 24, 16579. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms242316579</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, F., Jiang, L., Yang, Q., Han, F., Chen, S., Pu, S., Vance, A., &amp; Ge, B. (2011). Prevalence and antimicrobial susceptibility of major foodborne pathogens in imported seafood. Journal of Food Protection, 74, 1451–1461. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐11‐146</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Zhong, Y., Gu, X., Yuan, J., Saeed, A. F., &amp; Wang, S. (2015). The pathogenesis, detection, and prevention of Vibrio parahaemolyticus. Frontiers in Microbiology, 6, 144. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2015.00144</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watterson, A., Little, D., Young, J. A., Murray, F., Doi, L., Boyd, K. A., &amp; Azim, E. (2012). Scoping a public health impact assessment of aquaculture with particular reference to tilapia in the UK. ISRN Public Health, 2012, 1–18. https://doi.org/10.5402/2012/203796</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wendwesen, T., Dagmar, N., Yitbarek, G., &amp; Matusala, M. (2017). Microbiological quality of frozen raw and undercooked Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) fillets and food safety practices of fish handlers in Arba Minch town, SNNPR, Ethiopia. Journal of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Health, 9, 55–62. https://doi.org/10.5897/JVMAH2015.0424</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, M., Hernandez‐Jover, M., &amp; Shamsi, S. (2020). Fish substitutions which may increase human health risks from zoonotic seafood borne parasites: A review. Food Control, 118, 107429. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107429</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, M. G., &amp; Busta, F. F. (1999). Most probable number (MPN). In R. K. Robinson (Ed.), Encyclopedia of food microbiology (pp. 2166–2168). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1006/rwfm.1999.4000</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wodajo, W. (2020). Review on zoonotic bacterial diseases of fish. ARC Journal of Animal and Veterinary Sciences, 6, 1–9. https://doi.org/10.20431/2455‐2518.0601004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yajima, A., &amp; Kurokura, H. (2008). Microbial risk assessment of livestock‐integrated aquaculture and fish handling in Vietnam. Fisheries Science, 74, 1062–1068. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1444‐2906.2008.01625.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi, Y. (1999). Modeling growth of Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) in a cage‐cum‐pond integrated culture system. Aquacultural Engineering, 21, 113–133. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0144‐8609(99)00027‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaher, H. A., Nofal, M. I., Hendam, B. M., Elshaer, M. M., Alothaim, A. S., &amp; Eraqi, M. M. (2021). Prevalence and antibiogram of Vibrio parahaemolyticus and Aeromonas hydrophila in the flesh of Nile tilapia, with special reference to their virulence genes detected using multiplex PCR technique. Antibiotics, 10, 654. https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics10060654</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, X., Zhong, J., Wei, C., Lin, C.‐W., &amp; Ding, T. (2017). Current perspectives on viable but non‐culturable state in foodborne pathogens. Frontiers in Microbiology, 8, 580. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.00580</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, M., Yu, S., Hong, B., Li, J., Han, H., &amp; Qie, G. (2021). Antibiotics control in aquaculture requires more than antibiotic‐free feeds: A tilapia farming case. Environmental Pollution, 268, 115854. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115854</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>