<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39285984</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0022-1155</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>61</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science and technology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci Technol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the preservation efficiency of cured betel leaf essential oil in augmenting the quality of fruit juice: a comprehensive evaluation of physicochemical, microbial, and sensory parameters.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1862</StartPage><EndPage>1873</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1862-1873</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s13197-024-05963-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">Betel leaves have deep roots in India's cultural heritage and have long been known for their use in traditional diets as a masticatory agent. These leaves contain beneficial compounds like antimicrobials, antioxidants, and anticancer properties. This study aims to investigate how betel leaf essential oil (BLEO) can act as a preservative for orange, grape, watermelon, and sugarcane juices. To make sure BLEO doesn't affect the taste, a sensory study was done using fuzzy logic analysis to determine the right concentration. Physicochemical and microbial properties in control and BLEO-treated juices were evaluated at weeks 0 and 2. Results showed that the addition of BLEO in fruit juices yielded a significant reduction in microbial populations, in total plate count and yeast and mold count. The decrease in free radical scavenging activity observed in BLEO-treated juices was comparatively less pronounced than in the control. GC-MS analysis has identified the bioactive compounds present in BLEO, revealing high concentrations of bioactive compounds. The observation of the study demonstrates the remarkable potential of BLEO to serve as a natural preservative in a diverse range of fruit juices.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s13197-024-05963-9.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Association of Food Scientists &amp; Technologists (India) 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdul Kareem</LastName><ForeName>Fathima Beevi</ForeName><Initials>FB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Food Technology, Anna University, Chennai, Tamil Nadu India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/01qhf1r47</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.252262.3</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0613 6919</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elumalai</LastName><ForeName>Arunkumar</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Planning and Monitoring Cell, Entrepreneurship and Management, National Institute of Food Technology, Tamil Nadu, Thanjavur, 613005 India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anandharaj</LastName><ForeName>Arunkumar</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Safety and Quality Testing, Entrepreneurship and Management, National Institute of Food Technology, Tamil Nadu, Thanjavur, 613005 India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sivanandham</LastName><ForeName>Vignesh</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Academics and Human Resource Development, National Institute of Food Technology, Entrepreneurship and Management-Thanjavur, Ministry of Food Processing Industries (MoFPI), Government of India, Pudukkottai Road, Thanjavur, 613005 India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nagarethinam</LastName><ForeName>Baskaran</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0168-3590</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Academics and Human Resource Development, National Institute of Food Technology, Entrepreneurship and Management-Thanjavur, Ministry of Food Processing Industries (MoFPI), Government of India, Pudukkottai Road, Thanjavur, 613005 India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci Technol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0056471</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1155</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antimicrobial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antioxidant</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Betel leaf essential oil</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fruit juices</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Preservative potential</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Competing interestsNo competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39285984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11401803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-024-05963-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">5963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Anaya-Esparza LM, Méndez-Robles MD, Sayago-Ayerdi SG, García Magaña ML, Ramírez-Mares MV, Sánchez-Burgos JA, Montalvo González E (2017) Effect of thermosonication on pathogenic bacteria, quality attributes and stability of soursop nectar during cold storage. J Food 15(4):1–9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aparna V, Dileep KV, Mandal PK, Karthe P, Sadasivan C, Haridas M (2012) Anti-inflammatory property of n-hexadecanoic acid: structural evidence and kinetic assessment. Chem Biol Drug Des 80(3):434–439 10.1111/j.1747-0285.2012.01418.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1747-0285.2012.01418.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22642495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arambewela L, Arawwawala M, Rajapaksa D (2006) Piper betle: a potential natural antioxidant. Int J Food Sci Technol 41(SUPPL. 1):10–14. 10.1111/j.1365-2621.2006.01227.x10.1111/j.1365-2621.2006.01227.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2621.2006.01227.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basak S (2018a) a) The use of fuzzy logic to determine the concentration of betel leaf essential oil and its potency as a juice preservative. Food Chem 240:1113–1120. 10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.08.047 10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.08.047</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.08.047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28946231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basak S (2018b) Shelf life extension of tomato paste through organoleptically acceptable concentration of betel leaf essential oil under accelerated storage. Environment J Food Sci 83(5):1396–1403. 10.1111/1750-3841.14133 10.1111/1750-3841.14133</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.14133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29660853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhardwaj RJ, Pandey S (2011) Juice blends-a way of utilization of under-utilized fruits, vegetables, and spices: a review. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 51:563–570 10.1080/10408391003710654</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408391003710654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21929332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas P, Anand U, Saha SC, Kant N, Mishra T, Masih H, Bar A, Pandey DK, Jha NK, Majumder M, Das N, Gadekar VS, Shekhawat MS, Kumar M, Radha Proćków J, de la Lastra JMP, Dey A (2022) Betelvine (Piper betle L.): A comprehensive insight into its ethnopharmacology, phytochemistry, and pharmacological, biomedical and therapeutic attributes. J Cell Mol Med 26(11):3083–3119. 10.1111/jcmm.17323 10.1111/jcmm.17323</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcmm.17323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9170825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35502487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao X, Bi X, Huang W, Wu J, Hu X, Liao X (2012) Changes of quality of high hydrostatic pressure processed cloudy and clear strawberry juices during storage. IFSET 16:181–190. 10.1016/j.ifset.2012.05.00810.1016/j.ifset.2012.05.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ifset.2012.05.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro-López C, Sánchez-Alejo EJ, Saucedo-Pompa S, Rojas R, Aranda-Ruiz J, Martínez-Avila GCG (2016) Fluctuations in phenolic content, ascorbic acid and total carotenoids and antioxidant activity of fruit beverages during storage. Heliyon 2(9):e00152. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00152 10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5021777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27656685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Santos CC, M P, Salvadori M S, Mota V G, Costa L M, de Almeida A A C, de Oliveira G A L, Costa J P, de Sousa D P, de Freitas R M, de Almeida R N, (2013) Antinociceptive and antioxidant activities of phytol in vivo and in vitro models. J Neurosci 2013:1–9. 10.1155/2013/94945210.1155/2013/949452</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2013/949452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4437258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26317107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faizi ZA, Mahen MY (2020) Effect of storage conditions, preservative levels and packing materials on ascorbic acid juice of mandarin cv. Nagpur Santra Turkish JAF Sci Tech 2(2):38–41</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu H, Zeng J, Liu C, Gu Y, Zou Y, Chang H (2021) Folate intake and risk of pancreatic cancer: a systematic review and updated meta-analysis of epidemiological studies. Dig Dis Sci 66:2368–2379. 10.1007/s10620-020-06525-7 10.1007/s10620-020-06525-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10620-020-06525-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32770489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadhav NL, Garule PA, Pinjari DV (2020) Comparative study of ultrasound pretreatment method with conventional hydrodistillation method for extraction of essential oil from Piper betle L (Paan). Indian Chem. Eng. 64(2):132–140. 10.1080/00194506.2020.182819310.1080/00194506.2020.1828193</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00194506.2020.1828193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaya S, Das H (2003) Sensory evaluation of mango drinks using fuzzy logic. J Sens Stud 18(2):163–17610.1111/j.1745-459X.2003.tb00382.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-459X.2003.tb00382.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jerry AA, Bright Q (2019) Effect of storage temperature on the physicochemical, nutritional and microbiological quality of pasteurised soursop (Annona muricata L.) Juice. Afr. J. Food Sci. 13(2):38–47. 10.5897/AJFS2018.176710.5897/AJFS2018.1767</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5897/AJFS2018.1767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaddumukasa PP, Imathiu SM, Mathara JM, Nakavuma JL (2017) Influence of physicochemical parameters on storage stability: Microbiological quality of fresh unpasteurized fruit juices. Food Sci Nutr 5(6):1098–1105. 10.1002/fsn3.500 10.1002/fsn3.500</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fsn3.500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5694882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29188037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konwar, Kardong (2019) Assessment of antioxidant activity in the fresh fruit juice and the brew fermented from Syzygium cumini (L) fruit. Curr Trends Pharmaceut Res 7(1). www.dibru.ac.in/ctpr</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latika Y, Archana C (2013) Effect of keeping time period on acidity of fruit juices and determination of fungal growth in fruit juices. Asian J Home Sci 8:166–169</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madhumita M, Guha P, Nag A, Prabhakar PK (2021) Natural preservative efficacy of cured betel leaf essential oil for sapota juice: Effect on physicochemical, microbial, and sensory properties. J Food Process Preserv. 10.1111/jfpp.1592710.1111/jfpp.15927</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.15927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayaka NM, Sasadara MM, Sanjaya DA, Yuda PE, Dewi NL, Cahyaningsih E, Hartati, (2020) Piper betle (L.) recent review of antibacterial and antifungal properties, safety profiles, and commercial applications. Molecules 26(8):232110.3390/molecules26082321</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26082321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8073370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33923576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pongsavee M (2015) Effect of sodium benzoate preservative on micronucleus induction, chromosome break, and Ala40Thr superoxide dismutase gene mutation in lymphocytes. Biomed Res Int 2015:103512. 10.1155/2015/103512 10.1155/2015/103512</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2015/103512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4346689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25785261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh SK, Sharma M (2017) Review on biochemical changes associated with storage of fruit juice. Int J Curr Microbiol Appl Sci 6(8):236–24510.20546/ijcmas.2017.608.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20546/ijcmas.2017.608.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singleton VL, Orthofer R, Lamuela-Raventós RM (1999) Analysis of total phenols and other oxidation substrates and antioxidants by means of folin-ciocalteu reagent. Meth Enzymol Academic Press 299:152–178. 10.1016/S0076-6879(99)99017-110.1016/S0076-6879(99)99017-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0076-6879(99)99017-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swamy MK, Akhtar MS, Sinniah UR (2016) Antimicrobial properties of plant essential oils against human pathogens and their mode of action: an updated review. Evid Based Complem Alternat Med 2016:3012462. 10.1155/2016/301246210.1155/2016/3012462</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2016/3012462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5206475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28090211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tayse E, da Cruz Almeida, Geany Targino de Souza, Jossana Pereira de Sousa Guedes, Isabella Medeiros Barbosa, Cristina Paiva de Sousa, Lúcio Roberto Cançado Castellano, Marciane Magnani, Evandro Leite de Souza, (2019) Mentha piperita L. essential oil inactivates spoilage yeasts in fruit juices through the perturbation of different physiological functions in yeast cells. Food Microbiol 82:20–29. 10.1016/j.fm.2019.01.023 10.1016/j.fm.2019.01.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2019.01.023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31027774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toprani R, Patel D (2013) Betel leaf: revisiting the benefits of an ancient Indian herb. South Asian J Cancer 2(3):140–141. 10.4103/2278-330X.114120 10.4103/2278-330X.114120</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/2278-330X.114120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3892533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24455591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viuda-Martos M, Fernandez-Lopez J, Sayas-Barbera E, Sendra E, Perez-Alvarez JA (2011) Physicochemical characterization of the orange juice waste water of a citrus by-product. J Food Process Preserv 35(2):264–27110.1111/j.1745-4549.2009.00450.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4549.2009.00450.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yashwant CP, Rajendran V, Krishnamoorthy S, Nagarathinam B, Rawson A, Anandharaj A, Sivanandham V (2022) Antibiotic resistance profiling and valorization of food waste streams to starter culture biomass and exopolysaccharides through fed-batch fermentations. Food Sci Biotechnol 32:863–874. 10.1007/s10068-022-01222-9 10.1007/s10068-022-01222-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10068-022-01222-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10082887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37041804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin X, Chen K, Cheng H, Chen X, Feng S, Song Y, Liang L (2022) Chemical stability of ascorbic acid integrated into commercial products: a review on bioactivity and delivery technology. Antioxidants. 10.3390/antiox11010153 10.3390/antiox11010153</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox11010153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8773188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35052657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zielinski A, Haminiuki C, Alberti A, Nogueira A, Demiate I, Granato D (2014) Comparative study of the phenolic compounds and the in vitro antioxidant activity of different Brazilian teas using multivariate statistical techniques. Food Res Int 60:246–254. 10.1016/j.foodres.2013.09.01010.1016/j.foodres.2013.09.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2013.09.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>