<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39289814</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>89</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>North American considerations, strategies, and practices in reducing the sodium content in processed foods.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>6086</StartPage><EndPage>6097</EndPage><MedlinePgn>6086-6097</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17361</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Most Americans exceed the recommended limit for sodium in their diet, a risk factor for hypertension and cardiovascular disease. Efforts have been made by the food industry and government agencies to reduce the sodium content in foods and encourage the consumption of lower sodium diets. Such efforts, however, are not successful in improving public health when consumers do not accept and consume lower sodium foods. This review article provides an overview of the strategies that have been used by the US food industry to reduce and replace sodium in consumer packaged goods, as well as future sodium reduction strategies and approaches for replacing sodium with potassium salts. Challenges in consumer acceptance regarding the reduction of sodium in foods are also discussed. Because of the widespread consumption of numerous sodium-containing consumer packaged goods, implementing future strategies in various aspects of salt reduction and potassium replacement in foods should have a profound impact on the health of Americans. PRACTICAL APPLICATION: New information is provided herein as it discusses the most current and collective perspectives of major food industry successes and challenges, as well as government strategies to decrease sodium intake. The information provided also addresses future strategies for reducing sodium content in foods, increasing potassium intake, and consumer acceptance of lower sodium foods.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Food Science published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Trumbo</LastName><ForeName>Paula R</ForeName><Initials>PR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4539-320X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health Sciences, Paula R. Trumbo Consulting and Liberty University, Mount Pleasant, South Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Glass</LastName><ForeName>Kathleen A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Research Institute, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Soo-Yeun</ForeName><Initials>SY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science, Washington State University, Pullman, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moshfegh</LastName><ForeName>Alanna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Surveys Research Group, Beltsville Human Nutrition Research Center, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Center, Beltsville, Maryland, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Welling</LastName><ForeName>Paul A</ForeName><Initials>PA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zecca</LastName><ForeName>Patricia</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Institute for the Advancement of Food and Nutrition Sciences, Washington, DC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Institute for the Advancement of Food and Nutrition Sciences (IAFNS)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>This work was supported by the Institute for the Advancement of Food and Nutrition Sciences (IAFNS). IAFNS is a nonprofit science organization that pools funding from industry and advances science through in-kind and financial contributions from private and public sector members. This perspective article, in part, includes information from a series of webinars held in January 2024, followed by presentations during a dialogue meeting among academia, industry, and government employees from the United States and Canada. P.R.T. received funding to participate in the March 2024 IAFNS meeting and to prepare the manuscript. P.W. and K.G. received travel funding to participate in the March 2024 meeting. P.Z. is an employee of the IAFNS that funded this work.</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012982">Sodium, Dietary</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012982" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sodium, Dietary</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003258" MajorTopicYN="N">Consumer Behavior</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005511" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Handling</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019649" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Industry</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014481" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United States</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057140" MajorTopicYN="N">Fast Foods</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018673" MajorTopicYN="N">Nutrition Policy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009656" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">North America</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000092965" MajorTopicYN="N">Food, Processed</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">consumer acceptance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food technology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">reformulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sodium</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39289814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. (2018). Sodium and potassium intake: Effects on chronic disease outcomes and risks. https://effectivehealthcare.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/pdf/cer‐206‐report‐sodium‐potassium‐update.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Diabetes Association. (2015). Cutting back on salt. http://main.diabetes.org/dorg/PDFs/awareness‐programs/hhm/what_can_i_eat‐cutting_salt‐American_Diabetes_Association.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Heart Association. (2024). Heart‐Check Certification. https://www.heart.org/en/healthy‐living/company‐collaboration/heart‐check‐certification</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appel, L. J., Moore, T. J., Obarzanek, E., Vollmer, W. M., Svetkey, L. P., Sacks, F. M., Bray, G. A., Vogt, T. M., Cutler, J. A., Windhauser, M. M., Lin, P.‐H., Karanja, N., Simons‐Morton, D., McCullough, M., Swain, J., Steele, P., Evans, M. A., Miller, E. R., Harsha, D. W., &amp; DASH Collaborative Research Group. (1997). A clinical trial of the effects of dietary patterns on blood pressure. New England Journal of Medicine, 336(16), 1117–1124. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJM199704173361601</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beauchamp, G., &amp; Engelman, K. (1982). Long‐term reduction in dietary sodium alters the taste of salt. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 36(6), 1134–1144. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajcn/36.6.1134</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beck, P. H. B., De Camargo Lima Beluci, N., Monteiro, A. R. G., Dos Santos Scholz, M. B., &amp; Neto, A. Á. M. (2022). Carnauba wax utilization in salt encapsulation: Application in bread. Journal of Food Science Technology, 59(8), 3307–3311. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐022‐05504‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berry, D. (2024). Stealthy reduction: Addressing sodium in dairy products. Dairy Processing. https://www.dairyprocessing.com/articles/2562‐stealthy‐reduction‐addressing‐sodium‐in‐dairy‐products</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breslin, P. A. S., &amp; Beauchamp, G. K. (1997). Salt enhances flavour by bitterness. Nature, 387(6633), Article 563. https://doi.org/10.1038/42388</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cargill, Inc. (2023) Cargill Ethnogrpahic Research. [Unpublished manuscript]. Cargill, Inc., Minneapolis, MN.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chavhan, G. B., Kanawjia, S. K., Khetra, Y., &amp; Puri, R. (2015). Effect of potassium‐based emulsifying salts on sensory, textural, and functional attributes of low‐sodium processed Mozzarella cheese. Dairy Science and Technology, 95, 265–278. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13594‐014‐0207‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, D., Bedale, W., Chetty, S., &amp; Yu, J.‐H. (2024). Comprehensive review of clean‐label antimicrobials used in dairy products. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 23, Article e13263. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.13263</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clase, C. M., Carerro, J. J., Ellison, D. H., Grams, M. E., Hemmelgarn, B. R., Jardine, M. J., Kovesdy, C. P., Kline, G. A., Lindner, G., Obrador, G. T., Palmer, B. F., Cheung, M., Wheeler, D. C., Winkelmayer, W. C., Pecoits‐Filho, R., &amp; Conference Participants. (2020). Potassium homeostasis and management of dyskalemia in kidney diseases: Conclusions from a kidney disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) Controversies Conference. Kidney International, 97, 42–61. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.kint.2019.09.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Code of Federal Regulations. (2024a). 21 CFR 101.9: Nutrition labeling of food. https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title‐21/chapter‐I/subchapter‐B/part‐101/subpart‐A/section‐101.9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Code of Federal Regulations. (2024b). 21 CFR 101.11: Nutrition labeling of standard menu items in covered establishments. https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title‐21/chapter‐I/subchapter‐B/part‐101/subpart‐A/section‐101.11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combase. (2024). A web resource for quantitative and predictive food microbiology. https://www.Combase.cc</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crowe‐White, K. M., Baumler, M., Gradwell, E., Juturu, V., White, D. A., &amp; Handu, D. (2023). Application of umami tastants for sodium reduction in food: An evidence analysis center scoping review. Journal of Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics, 123, 1606.e8–1620.e8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2022.08.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Silva, S. L., Lorenzo, J. M., Machado, J. M., Manfio, M., Cichoski, A. J., Fries, L. L. M., Morgano, M. A., &amp; Campagnol, P. C. B. (2020). Application of arginine and histidine to improve the technological and sensory properties of low‐fat and low‐sodium bologna‐type sausages produced with high levels of KCl. Meat Science, 159, Article 107939. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2019.107939</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyle, M. E., &amp; Glass, K. A. (2010). Sodium reduction and its effect on food safety, food quality, and human health. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 9, 44–56. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1541‐4337.2009.00096.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunteman, A. N., Lee, Y., &amp; Lee, S.‐Y. (2023). A qualitative look at perception and experience of sodium reduction strategies in the food industry through focus groups and individual interviews. Journal of Food Science, 88, 2203–2216. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.16564</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunteman, A. N., Mckenzie, E. N., Yang, Y., Lee, Y., &amp; Lee, S.‐Y. (2022). Compendium of sodium reduction strategies in foods: A scoping review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 21, 1300–1335. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12915</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felicio, T. L., Esmerino, E. A., Vidal, V. A. S., Cappato, L. P., Garcia, R. K. A., Cavalcanti, R. N., Freitas, M. Q., Conte Junior, C. A., Padilha, M. C., Silva, M. C., Raices, R. S. L., Arellano, D. B., Bollini, H. M. A., Pollonio, M. A. R., &amp; Cruz, A. G. (2016). Physico‐chemical changes during storage and sensory acceptance of low sodium probiotic Minas cheese added with arginine. Food Chemistry, 196, 628–637. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.09.102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>General Mills. (2023). G stands for good. https://globalresponsibility.generalmills.com/images/General_Mills‐Global_Responsibility_2023.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glass, K. A., Mu, M., Levine, B., &amp; Rossi, F. (2017). Inhibition of Clostridium botulinum in model reduced‐sodium pasteurized prepared cheese products. Journal of Food Protection, 80, 1478–1488. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐17‐027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, X., Tao, S., Pan, J., Lin, X., Ji, C., Liang, H., Dong, X., &amp; Li, S. (2020). Effects of l‐lysine on the physiochemical properties and sensory characteristics of salt‐reduced reconstructed ham. Meat Science, 166, Article 108133. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2020.108133</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harnack, L. J., Cogswell, M. E., Shikany, J. M., Gardner, C. D., Gillespie, C., Loria, C. M., Zhou, X., Yuan, K., &amp; Steffen, L. M. (2017). Sources of sodium in US adults from 3 geographic regions. Circulation, 135, 1775–1783. https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.116.024446</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hathcock, J. N., Shao, A., Vieth, R., &amp; Heaney, R. (2017). Risk assessment for potassium chloride used as a food additive. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 57, 2942–2953. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2015.1126213</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada. (2020). Voluntary sodium reduction targets for processed foods 2020‐2025. https://www.canada.ca/en/health‐canada/services/publications/food‐nutrition/sodium‐reduced‐targets‐2020‐2025.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute for the Advancement of Food Science and Nutrition. (2024). Effects of sodium reduction on food safety and quality. https://iafns.org/effects‐of‐sodium‐reduction‐on‐food‐safety‐and‐quality/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Food Research. (2005). Microbial risks associated with salt reduction in certain foods and alternative options for preservation. IFR Enterprises.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaenke, R., Barzi, F., Mcmahon, E., Webster, J., &amp; Brimblecombe, J. (2017). Consumer acceptance of reformulated food products: A systematic review and meta‐analysis of salt‐reduced foods. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 57(16), 3357–3372. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2015.1118009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraft Heinz Company. (2023). Kraft Heinz brands take action to support communities. https://kraftheinzcompany.com</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lichtenstein, A. H., Appel, L. J., Vadiveloo, M., Hu, F. B., Kris‐Etherton, P. M., Rebholz, C. M., Sacks, F. M., Thorndike, A. N., Van Horn, L., &amp; Wylie‐Rosett, J. (2021). Dietary guidance to improve cardiovascular health: A scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Circulation, 144, e472–e487. https://doi.org/10.1161/CIR.0000000000001031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, X., Tang, Y., Hu, Y., Lu, Y., Sun, Q., Lv, Y., Zhang, Q., Wu, C., Zhu, M., He, Q., &amp; Chi, Y. (2021). Sodium reduction in traditional fermented foods: Challenges, strategies, and perspectives. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 69(29), 8065–8080. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.1c01687</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mennella, J. A., Finkbeiner, S., Lipchock, S. V., Hwang, L.‐D., &amp; Reed, D. R. (2014). Preferences for salty and sweet tastes are elevated and related to each other during childhood. PLoS ONE, 9(3), Article e92201. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0092201</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercado, C. I., Cogswell, M. E., Valderrama, A. L., Wang, C.‐Y., Loria, C. M., Moshfegh, A. J., Rhodes, D. G., &amp; Carriquiry, A. L. (2015). Difference between 24‐h diet recall and urine excretion for assessing population sodium and potassium intake in adults aged 18‐39 y. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 101(2), 376–386. https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.113.081604</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monteiro, A. R. G., Nakagawa, A., Pimentel, T. C., &amp; Sousa, I. (2021). Increasing saltiness perception and keeping quality properties of low salt bread using inhomogeneous salt distribution achieved with salt agglomerated by waxy starch. LWT ‐ Food Science Technology, 146, Article 111451. (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111451)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy, M. M., Scrafford, C. G., Barraj, L. M., Bi, X., Higgins, K. A., Jaykus, L.‐A., &amp; Tran, N. L. (2021). Potassium chloride‐based replacers: Modeling effects on sodium and potassium intakes of the US population with cross‐sectional data from NHANES 2015–2016 and 2009–2010. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 114(1), 220–230. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajcn/nqab020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakamura, H., Kawashima, T., Yamasaki, L., Lwin, K. S., Eguchi, A., Hayabuchi, H., Tanoe, Y., Tanaka, S., Yoneoka, D., Ghaznavi, C., Uneyama, H., Shibuya, K., &amp; Nomura, S. (2022). Reducing salt intake with umami: A secondary analysis of data in the UK National Diet and Nutrition Survey. Food Science Nutrition, 11, 872–882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine. (2019). Dietary reference intakes for sodium and potassium. National Academies Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Advisory Committee on Microbiological Criteria for Foods. (2010). Parameters for determining inoculated pack/challenge study protocols. Journal of Food Protection, 73(1), 140–202. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028x‐73.1.140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nilesen. (2021). NielsenIQ acquires label insight, product attribute powerhouse. Deal supercharges data intelligence in the health and wellness space. NIQ.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nurmilah, S., Cahyana, Y., Utama, G. L., &amp; Aït‐Kaddour, A. (2022). Strategies to reduce salt content and its effect on food characteristics and acceptance: A review. Foods, 11(19), Article 3120. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11193120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oparil, S., Acelajado, M. C., Bakris, G. L., Berlowitz, D. R., Cífková, R., Dominiczak, A. F., Grassi, G., Jordan, J., Poulter, N. R., Rodgers, A., &amp; Whelton, P. K. (2017). Hypertension. Nutrition Reviews Primers, 4, Article 18014. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrdp.2018.14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pateiro, M., Munekata, P. E., Cittadini, A., Domínguez, R., &amp; Lorenzo, J. M. (2021). Metallic‐based salt substitutes to reduce sodium content in meat products. Current Opinion in Food Science, 38, 21–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raiten, D. J., Namasté, S., Brabin, B., Combs, G., L'abbe, M. R., Wasantwisut, E., &amp; Darnton‐Hill, I. (2011). The timing and duration of a sensitive period in human flavor learning: A randomized trial. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 94(5), 633S–650S. https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.110.008227</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riis, N. L., Bjoernsbo, K. S., Toft, U., Trolle, E., Hyldig, G., Hartley, I. E., Keast, R., &amp; Lassen, A. D. (2021). Impact of salt reduction interventions on salt taste sensitivity and liking, a cluster randomized controlled trial. Food Quality and Preference, 87, Article 104059.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santiesteban‐López, N. A., Gómez‐Salazar, J. A., Santos, E. M., Campagnol, P. C. B., Teixeira, A., Lorenzo, J. M., Sosa‐Morales, M. E., &amp; Domínguez, R. (2022). Natural Antimicrobials: A clean label strategy to improve the shelf life and safety of reformulated meat products. Foods, 11(17), Article 2613. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11172613</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, F. F. D., Dantas, N. M., Simoni, N. K., Pontes, L. S., &amp; PINTO‐E‐SILVA, M. E. M. (2020). Are foods naturally rich in glutamic acid an alternative to sodium reduction? Food Science and Technology, 40, 190–196. https://doi.org/10.1590/fst.08819</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sato, H., Wada, H., Matsumoto, H., Takagiwa, M., &amp; Goto, T. K. (2022). Differences in dynamic perception of salty taste intensity between young and older adults. Science Reports, 1, Article 7558. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐022‐11442</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, X., Zhong, K., Zhang, D., Shi, B., Wang, H., Shi, J., Battino, M., Wang, G., Zou, X., &amp; Zhao, L. (2022). The enhancement of the perception of saltiness by umami sensation elicited by flavor enhancers in salt solutions. Food Research International, 157, Article 111287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka, N., Traisman, E., Plantinga, P., Finn, L., Flom, W., Meske, L., &amp; Guggisberg, J. (1986). Evaluation of factors involved in antibotulinal properties of pasteurized process cheese spreads. Journal of Food Protection, 49(7), 526–531. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐49.7.526</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA). (2024a). FoodData Central. https://fdc.nal.usda.gov/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA). (2024b). FoodData Central Help. https://fdc.nal.usda.gov/help.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), &amp; U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS). (2020). Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2020‐2025: 9th edition. https://www.dietaryguidelines.gov/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service (USDA ARS). (2012). Nutrient intakes from food and beverages: Mean amounts consumed per individual, by gender and age, What We Eat in AMERICA, NHANES 2009‐2010. https://www.ars.usda.gov/northeast‐area/beltsville‐md‐bhnrc/beltsville‐human‐nutrition‐research‐center/food‐surveys‐research‐group/docs/wweia‐data‐tables/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service (USDA ARS). (2016). Nutrient intakes from food and beverages: Mean amounts consumed per individual, by gender and age, What We Eat in America, NHANES 2013‐2014. https://www.ars.usda.gov/northeast‐area/beltsville‐md‐bhnrc/beltsville‐human‐nutrition‐research‐center/food‐surveys‐research‐group/docs/wweia‐data‐tables/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service (USDA ARS). (2022a). Nutrient intakes from food and beverages: Mean amounts consumed per individual, by gender and age, What We Eat in America, NHANES 2017‐March 2020. https://www.ars.usda.gov/northeast‐area/beltsville‐md‐bhnrc/beltsville‐human‐nutrition‐research‐center/food‐surveys‐research‐group/docs/wweia‐data‐tables/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service (USDA ARS). (2022b). USDA Food and Nutrient Database for Dietary Studies 2019‐2020. http://www.ars.usda.gov/nea/bhnrc/fsrg</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA). (2020). The use of an alternate name for potassium chloride in food labeling: Guidance for industry. https://www.fda.gov/media/125081/download</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA). (2021). Guidance for industry: Voluntary sodium reduction goals. https://www.fda.gov/regulatory‐information/search‐fda‐guidance‐documents/guidance‐industry‐voluntary‐sodium‐reduction‐goals</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA). (2023). Use of salt substitutes to reduce the sodium content in standardized foods. https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/FR‐2023‐04‐10/pdf/2023‐06456.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidal, V. A. S., Lorenzo, J. M., Munekata, P. E. S., &amp; Pollonio, M. A. R. (2021). Challenges to reduce or replace NaCl by chloride salts in meat products made from whole pieces—A review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 61(13), 2194–2206. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2020.1774495</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidal, V. A. S., Santana, J. B., Paglarini, C. S., Da Silva, M. A. A. P., Freitas, M. Q., Esmerino, E. A., Cruz, A. G., &amp; Pollonio, M. A. R. (2020). Adding lysine and yeast extract improves sensory properties of low sodium salted meat. Meat Science, 159, Article 107911. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2019.107911</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vinceti, M., Filippini, T., Crippa, A., De Sesmaisons, A., Wise, L. A., &amp; Orsini, N. (2016). Meta‐analysis of potassium intake and the risk of stroke. Journal of the American Heart Association, 5(10), Article e004210. https://doi.org/10.1161/JAHA.116.004210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker, J. C., &amp; Dando, R. (2023). Sodium replacement with KCl and MSG: Attitudes, perception, and acceptance in reduced salt soups. Foods, 12(10), Article 2063. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12102063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, K.‐Y., Gritter, M., Vogt, L., De Borst, M. H., Rotmans, J. I., &amp; Hoorn, E. J. (2020). Dietary potassium and the kidney: Lifesaving physiology. Clinical Kidney Journal, 13(6), 952–968. https://doi.org/10.1093/ckj/sfaa157</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weippert, M., Schermel, A., &amp; L'Abbé, M. (2021). Assessing the turnover rate of Canadian food and beverage labels—Implications for the proposed front‐of‐package labelling transition period. Canadian Nutrition Society. https://cdnsciencepub.com/doi/pdf/10.1139/apnm‐2021‐0172</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilailux, C., Sriwattana, S., Chokumnoyporn, N., &amp; Prinyawiwatkul, W. (2020). Texture and colour characteristics, and optimisation of sodium chloride, potassium chloride and glycine of reduced‐sodium frankfurter. International Journal of Food Science and Technology, 55, 2232–2241. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.14476</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaika, L. L. (2002). Influence of NaCl content and cooling rate on outgrowth of Clostridium perfringens spores in cooked ham and beef. Journal of Food Protection, 66(9), 1599–1603. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028x‐66.9.1599</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zehren, V. L., &amp; Nusbaum, D. D. (1992). Process cheese. Schreiber Foods.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., Qiao, Z., Liu, S., Wang, J., &amp; Ma, C. (2024). Particle size reduction technique for NaCl crystals as effective and applicable strategy for saltiness enhancement in solid foods. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology, 191, Article 115655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, Y., Yan, Y., Yu, Z., Wu, T., &amp; Bennett, L. E. (2022). Effects of high pressure processing on microbial, textural and sensory properties of low‐salt emulsified beef sausage. Food Control, 133, Article 108596.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>