<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39286220</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Emerging lactic acid bacteria bacteriocins as anti-cancer and anti-tumor agents for human health.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e37054</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e37054</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e37054</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37054</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Modern cancer diagnostics and treatment options have greatly improved survival rates; the illness remains a major cause of mortality worldwide. Current treatments for cancer, such as chemotherapy, are not cancer-specific and may cause harm to healthy cells; therefore, it is imperative that new drugs for cancer be developed that are both safe and effective. It has been found that lactic acid bacteria (LAB) have the potential to produce bacteriocins, which could potentially offer a promising alternative for cancer treatment. They have been shown in several studies to be effective against cancer cells while having no effect on healthy cells. More research is needed to fully understand the potential of LAB bacteriocins as anti-cancer medicines, to find the appropriate dose and delivery route, and to conduct clinical trials to evaluate the effectiveness and safety of the products in human patients, as is suggested by this work. Furthermore, LAB bacteriocins may evolve into a significant new class of anti-cancer drugs and food products. Patients with cancer may have a safe and effective alternative treatment option in the form of anti-cancer foods and drugs. Therefore, the aim of this study is to provide an in-depth analysis of the recent breakthroughs and potential future technical advancements of significant bacteriocins that are produced by LAB, how these bacteriocins function, and how these bacteriocins may be utilized as an anti-cancer agent. In addition, the current analysis emphasizes the significant constraints and boundaries that bacteriocins face when they are used as an anti-cancer factor.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Niamah</LastName><ForeName>Alaa Kareem</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, College of Agriculture, University of Basrah, Basra City, Iraq.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Sahlany</LastName><ForeName>Shayma Thyab Gddoa</ForeName><Initials>STG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, College of Agriculture, University of Basrah, Basra City, Iraq.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verma</LastName><ForeName>Deepak Kumar</ForeName><Initials>DK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural and Food Engineering Department, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, Kharagpur 721302, West Bengal, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shukla</LastName><ForeName>Rakesh Mohan</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Processing and Food Engineering Division, College of Agricultural Engineering and Technology (CoAE&amp;T), Sher-e-Kashmir University of Agricultural Sciences and Technology of Kashmir, Srinagar, 190 025, Jammu and Kashmir, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Ami R</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Dairy Microbiology, Mansinhbhai Institute of Dairy and Food Technology-MIDFT, Dudhsagar Dairy Campus, Mehsana-384 002, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tripathy</LastName><ForeName>Soubhagya</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural and Food Engineering Department, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, Kharagpur 721302, West Bengal, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Smita</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Allied Health Sciences, Chitkara School of Health Sciences, Chitkara University, Punjab 140401, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baranwal</LastName><ForeName>Deepika</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Home Science, Arya Mahila PG College, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh, 221005, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Amit Kumar</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Post Harvest Technology, College of Horticulture, Banda University of Agriculture and Technology, Banda 210 001, Uttar Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Utama</LastName><ForeName>Gemilang Lara</ForeName><Initials>GL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Agro-Industrial Technology, Universitas Padjadjaran, Sumedang 45363, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Environment and Sustainability Science, Universitas Padjadjaran, Bandung 40132, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chávez González</LastName><ForeName>Mónica L</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bioprocesses and Bioproducts Group, Food Research Department, School of Chemistry, Universidad Autónoma de Coahuila, Saltillo Campus., 25280, Coahuila, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alhilfi</LastName><ForeName>Wissal Audah Hassan</ForeName><Initials>WAH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Marine Science Center, University of Basrah, Basra City, Iraq.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srivastav</LastName><ForeName>Prem Prakash</ForeName><Initials>PP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural and Food Engineering Department, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, Kharagpur 721302, West Bengal, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aguilar</LastName><ForeName>Cristobal Noe</ForeName><Initials>CN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bioprocesses and Bioproducts Group, Food Research Department, School of Chemistry, Universidad Autónoma de Coahuila, Saltillo Campus., 25280, Coahuila, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteriocin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cancer cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lactic acid bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mode of action</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39286220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11402949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)13085-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hegde P.S., Chen D.S. Top 10 challenges in cancer immunotherapy. Immunity. 2020;52(1):17–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31940268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (World Health Organization)  Cancer. 2022 https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cancer URL:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bray F., Ferlay J., Soerjomataram I., Siegel R.L., Torre L.A., Jemal A. Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA: a cancer journal for clinicians. 2018;68(6):394–424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30207593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu J.J., Mehrzad R. The Link between Obesity and Cancer. Academic Press; 2023. The biology of cancer; pp. 35–45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pecorino L. Oxford University Press; 2021. Molecular Biology of Cancer: Mechanisms, Targets, and Therapeutics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R.A., Li Q.L., Li Z.S., Zheng P.J., Zhang H.Z., Huang X.F.…Cui R. Apoptosis drives cancer cells proliferate and metastasize. J. Cell Mol. Med. 2013;17(1):205–211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3823150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23305095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Rossi J., Arefeayne Y., Robinson A., Segatori L. Emerging technologies for genetic control systems in cellular therapies. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2022;78</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10091305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36334445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sonnenschein C., Soto A.M. The aging of the 2000 and 2011 Hallmarks of Cancer reviews: a critique. J. Biosci. 2013;38:651–663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3882065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23938395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Payne S., Miles D. Mechanisms of anticancer drugs. Scott-Brown's Otorhinolaryngology: Head Neck Surg. 2008;3:134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Herrero E., Fernández-Medarde A. Advanced targeted therapies in cancer: drug nanocarriers, the future of chemotherapy. Eur. J. Pharm. Biopharm. 2015;93:52–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25813885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan S., Wei J., Huang L., Wu L. Chemotherapy and chemo-resistance in nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2020;207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32858472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barocas D.A., Alvarez J., Resnick M.J., Koyama T., Hoffman K.E., Tyson M.D.…Penson D.F. Association between radiation therapy, surgery, or observation for localized prostate cancer and patient-reported outcomes after 3 years. JAMA. 2017;317(11):1126–1140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5782813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28324093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur J., Elms J., Munn A.L., Good D., Wei M.Q. Immunotherapy for non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), as a stand-alone and in combination therapy. Crit. Rev. Oncol. Hematol. 2021;164</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34242772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma D.K., Thakur M., Singh S., Tripathy S., Gupta A.K., Baranwal D.…Srivastav P.P. Bacteriocins as antimicrobial and preservative agents in food: biosynthesis, separation and application. Food Biosci. 2022;46</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel A., Shah N., Verma D.K. Microorganisms in Sustainable Agriculture, Food, and the Environment. Apple Academic Press; 2017. Lactic acid bacteria (lab) bacteriocins: an ecologicaland sustainable biopreservative approach to improve the safety and shelf life of foods; pp. 197–257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Ramos A., Madi-Moussa D., Coucheney F., Drider D. Current knowledge of the mode of action and immunity mechanisms of LAB-bacteriocins. Microorganisms. 2021;9(10):2107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8538875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34683428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi Y., Li P., Zhao F., Zhang T., Shan Y., Wang X.…Lü X. Current status and potentiality of class II bacteriocins from lactic acid bacteria: structure, mode of action and applications in the food industry. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2022;120:387–401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandenbergh P.A. Lactic acid bacteria, their metabolic products and interference with microbial growth. FEMS (Fed. Eur. Microbiol. Soc.) Microbiol. Rev. 1993;12(1–3):221–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalid K. An overview of lactic acid bacteria. Int. J. Biosci. 2011;1(3):1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng J., Wittouck S., Salvetti E., Franz C.M., Harris H.M., Mattarelli P.…Lebeer S. A taxonomic note on the genus Lactobacillus: description of 23 novel genera, emended description of the genus Lactobacillus Beijerinck 1901, and union of Lactobacillaceae and Leuconostocaceae. Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol. 2020;70(4):2782–2858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32293557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reis J.A., Paula A.T., Casarotti S.N., Penna A.L.B. Lactic acid bacteria antimicrobial compounds: characteristics and applications. Food Eng. Rev. 2012;4:124–140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee H.J., Kim H.Y. Lantibiotics, class I bacteriocins from the genus Bacillus. J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2011;21(3):229–235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21464591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niamah A.K. University of Basrah; Iraq: 2010. Production Of Pediocin like Bacteriocin from a Local Isolate of Pediococcus Acidilactici and Using it as Foods Preservative (Doctoral Dissertation, Ph. D. Thesis, College of Agriculture.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-González J.C., Martínez-Tapia A., Lazcano-Hernández G., García-Pérez B.E., Castrejón-Jiménez N.S. Bacteriocins from lactic acid bacteria. A powerful alternative as antimicrobials, probiotics, and immunomodulators in veterinary medicine. Animals. 2021;11(4):979.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8067144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33915717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahdy E.N.D., Al-Zahrani S.H.M., Al-Mahmoudi Z.A.H.M. Partial purification, characterization and antibacterial activity of bacteriocin from Leuconostoc mesenteroides. Int. J. Life Sci. Pharma Res. 2020;10(3):L6–L13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xin B., Liu H., Zheng J., Xie C., Gao Y., Dai D.…Sun M. In silico analysis highlights the diversity and novelty of circular bacteriocins in sequenced microbial genomes. mSystems. 2020;5(3) 20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8534725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32487738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauková A., Czikková S., Dobránsky T., Burdová O. Inhibition ofListeria monocytogenesandStaphylococcus aureusby enterocin CCM 4231 in milk products. Food Microbiol. 1999;16(1):93–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farizano J.V., Díaz Vergara L.I., Masias E., Baillo A.A., Torino M.I., Fadda S.…Minahk C. Biotechnological use of dairy by-products for the production and microencapsulation of the food preservative enterocin CRL35. FEMS (Fed. Eur. Microbiol. Soc.) Microbiol. Lett. 2022;369(1):fnac033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35325116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumariya R., Garsa A.K., Rajput Y.S., Sood S.K., Akhtar N., Patel S. Bacteriocins: classification, synthesis, mechanism of action and resistance development in food spoilage causing bacteria. Microb. Pathog. 2019;128:171–177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30610901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cesa-Luna C., Alatorre-Cruz J.M., Carreno-Lopez R., Quintero-Hernandez V., Baez A. Emerging applications of bacteriocins as antimicrobials, anticancer drugs, and modulators of the gastrointestinal microbiota. Pol. J. Microbiol. 2021;70(2):143–159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8326989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34349808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goh K.S., Ng Z.J., Halim M., Oslan S.N., Oslan S.N.H., Tan J.S. A comprehensive review on the anticancer potential of bacteriocin: preclinical and clinical studies. Int. J. Pept. Res. Therapeut. 2022;28(2):75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teixeira V., Feio M.J., Bastos M. Role of lipids in the interaction of antimicrobial peptides with membranes. Prog. Lipid Res. 2012;51(2):149–177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22245454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smits S.H., Schmitt L., Beis K. Self‐immunity to antibacterial peptides by ABC transporters. FEBS Lett. 2020;594(23):3920–3942.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33040342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meade E., Slattery M.A., Garvey M. Bacteriocins, potent antimicrobial peptides and the fight against multi drug resistant species: resistance is futile? Antibiotics. 2020;9(1):32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7168330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31963311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur S., Kaur S. Bacteriocins as potential anticancer agents. Front. Pharmacol. 2015;6:272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4639596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26617524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molujin A.M., Abbasiliasi S., Nurdin A., Lee P.C., Gansau J.A., Jawan R. Bacteriocins as potential therapeutic approaches in the treatment of various cancers: a review of in vitro studies. Cancers. 2022;14(19):4758.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9563265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36230679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baindara P., Korpole S., Grover V. Bacteriocins: perspective for the development of novel anticancer drugs. Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2018;102:10393–10408.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30338356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira F.D., Castanho M.A., Gaspar D. Microbial Infections and Cancer Therapy. Jenny Stanford Publishing; 2019. Bacteriocins as anticancer peptides: a biophysical approach; pp. 367–409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ríos Colombo N.S., Chalón M.C., Navarro S.A., Bellomio A. Pediocin-like bacteriocins: new perspectives on mechanism of action and immunity. Curr. Genet. 2018;64:345–351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28983718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes A., Jobby R. Bacteriocins from lactic acid bacteria and their potential clinical applications. Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol. 2022;194(10):4377–4399.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35290605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y., Pang X., Wu Y., Liu X., Zhang X. Enterocins: classification, synthesis, antibacterial mechanisms and food applications. Molecules. 2022;27(7):2258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9000605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35408657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang F., Teng K., Liu Y., Cao Y., Wang T., Ma C.…Zhong J. Bacteriocins: potential for human health. Oxid. Med. Cell. Longev. 2021;2021:1–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8055394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33936381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai T.L., Li A.C., Chen Y.C., Liao Y.S., Lin T.H. Antimicrobial peptide m2163 or m2386 identified from Lactobacillus casei ATCC 334 can trigger apoptosis in the human colorectal cancer cell line SW480. Tumor Biol. 2015;36:3775–3789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25557887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ankaiah D., Palanichamy E., Antonyraj C.B., Ayyanna R., Perumal V., Ahamed S.I.B., Arul V. Cloning, overexpression, purification of bacteriocin enterocin-B and structural analysis, interaction determination of enterocin-A, B against pathogenic bacteria and human cancer cells. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2018;116:502–512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29729340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi S., Ghollasi M., Hosseini H.M. The apoptotic impact of nisin as a potent bacteriocin on the colon cancer cells. Microb. Pathog. 2017;111:193–197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28867631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Madboly L.A., El-Deeb N.M., Kabbash A., Nael M.A., Kenawy A.M., Ragab A.E. Purification, characterization, identification, and anticancer activity of a circular bacteriocin from Enterococcus thailandicus. Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol. 2020;8:450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7324803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32656185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duy Nguyen V., Nguyen H.H.C. Advanced Computational Methods for Knowledge Engineering: Proceedings of 3rd International Conference on Computer Science, Applied Mathematics and Applications-ICCSAMA 2015. Springer International Publishing; 2015. Molecular screening of azurin-like anticancer bacteriocins from human gut microflora using bioinformatics; pp. 219–229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buss G.P., Wilson C.M. Exploring the cytotoxic mechanisms of Pediocin PA-1 towards HeLa and HT29 cells by comparison to known bacteriocins: microcin E492, enterocin heterodimer and Divercin V41. PLoS One. 2021;16(9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8412286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34473709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niamah A.K. Structure, mode of action and application of pediocin natural antimicrobial food preservative: a review. Basrah Journal of Agricultural Sciences. 2018;31(1):59–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil S.M., Kunda N.K. Nisin ZP, an antimicrobial peptide, induces cell death and inhibits non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) progression in vitro in 2D and 3D cell culture. Pharmaceut. Res. 2022;39(11):2859–2870.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35246758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sand S.L., Nissen-Meyer J., Sand O., Haug T.M. Plantaricin A, a cationic peptide produced by Lactobacillus plantarum, permeabilizes eukaryotic cell membranes by a mechanism dependent on negative surface charge linked to glycosylated membrane proteins. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Biomembranes. 2013;1828(2):249–259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23142566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martín R., Escobedo S., Martín C., Crespo A., Quiros L.M., Suarez J.E. Surface glycosaminoglycans protect eukaryotic cells against membrane-driven peptide bacteriocins. Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 2015;59(1):677–681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4291419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25331698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamarajan P., Hayami T., Matte B., Liu Y., Danciu T., Ramamoorthy A.…Kapila Y. Nisin ZP, a bacteriocin and food preservative, inhibits head and neck cancer tumorigenesis and prolongs survival. PLoS One. 2015;10(7)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4489501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26132406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharsallaoui A., Oulahal N., Joly C., Degraeve P. Nisin as a food preservative: part 1: physicochemical properties, antimicrobial activity, and main uses. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2016;56(8):1262–1274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25675115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azmi M.F., Al Khateeb A., Froemming G.A., Ab Rahim S., Omar E. Nisin as a potential anticancer agent. Science, Engineering and Health Studies. 2021 21010007-21010007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Gutierrez E., O'Connor P.M., Saalbach G., Walsh C.J., Hegarty J.W., Guinane C.M.…Cotter P.D. First evidence of production of the lantibiotic nisin P. Sci. Rep. 2020;10(1):3738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7048740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32111904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paiva A.D., de Oliveira M.D., de Paula S.O., Baracat-Pereira M.C., Breukink E., Mantovani H.C. Toxicity of bovicin HC5 against mammalian cell lines and the role of cholesterol in bacteriocin activity. Microbiology. 2012;158(11):2851–2858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22956757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balcik-Ercin P., Sever B. An investigation of bacteriocin nisin anti-cancer effects and FZD7 protein interactions in liver cancer cells. Chem. Biol. Interact. 2022;366</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36084725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monfared Y.K., Mahmoudian M., Caldera F., Pedrazzo A.R., Zakeri-Milani P., Matencio A., Trotta F. Nisin delivery by nanosponges increases its anticancer activity against in-vivo melanoma model. J. Drug Deliv. Sci. Technol. 2023;79</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaye K., Li C.G., Chang D., Bhuyan D.J. The role of key gut microbial metabolites in the development and treatment of cancer. Gut Microb. 2022;14(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8890435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35220885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdoullahi S., Jahangiri A., Shahali M., Rashmezad M.A., Halabian R. Combination of nisin and glabridin enhanced apoptosis in colorectal cancer cells. Int. J. Pept. Res. Therapeut. 2023;29(3):44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed S.S.T.S., Abdulrahman Z.F.A., Othman R.T. Anticancer activity of cloned Nisin as an alternative therapy for MCF-7 brest cancer cell line. Cellular and Molecular Biology. 2023;69(9):149–155.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37807320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil S.M., Barji D.S., Aziz S., McChesney D.A., Bagde S., Muttil P., Kunda N.K. Pulmonary delivery of spray-dried Nisin ZP antimicrobial peptide for non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) treatment. Int. J. Pharm. 2023;634</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36709012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goudarzi F., Esmaeilzadeh M., Yaghoubi H. The mechanisms of anticancer activity of Nisin peptide on myelogenous leukemia cell line (K562) as a new treatment: inducing apoptosis by changing in the expression of Bax and Bcl-2 Genes. Int. J. Pept. Res. Therapeut. 2021;27:2661–2670.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosseini S.S., Hajikhani B., Faghihloo E., Goudarzi H. Increased expression of caspase genes in colorectal cancer cell line by nisin. Archives of Clinical Infectious Diseases. 2020;15(2)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousefy Z., Esmaeili D., Goudarzi H. Cloning and the expression of the protein fusion enterocin-nisin-epidermicin as a candidate for the treatment of gastric cancer. Gene Reports. 2020;20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim N.E.S., Morsy H., Abdelgwad M. The comparative effect of nisin and thioridazine as potential anticancer agents on hepatocellular carcinoma. Reports of Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology. 2021;9(4):452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8068446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33969139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu W., Kapila Y.L. Nisin, a probiotic bacteriocin, combined with limited chemoradiation therapy in head and neck cancer. Archives of Clinical and Medical Case Reports. 2021;5(4):531–536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rana K., Pandey S.K., Chauhan S., Preet S. Anticancer therapeutic potential of 5-fluorouracil and nisin co-loaded chitosan coated silver nanoparticles against murine skin cancer. Int. J. Pharm. 2022;620</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35427747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radaic A., Malone E., Kamarajan P., Kapila Y.L. Solid lipid nanoparticles loaded with nisin (SLN-Nisin) are more effective than free nisin as antimicrobial, antibiofilm, and anticancer agents. J. Biomed. Nanotechnol. 2022;18(4):1227–1235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9741812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35854440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preet S., Bharati S., Panjeta A., Tewari R., Rishi P. Effect of nisin and doxorubicin on DMBA-induced skin carcinogenesis—a possible adjunct therapy. Tumor Biol. 2015;36:8301–8308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26002579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar B., Balgir P.P., Kaur B., Mittu B., Chauhan A. In vitro cytotoxicity of native and rec-pediocin CP2 against cancer cell lines: a comparative study. Pharmaceutical Analytical Acta. 2012;1(6)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swacita I.B.N., Suardana I.W., Sudisma I.G.N., Wihadmadyatami H. Molecular identification of lactic acid bacteria SR6 strain and evaluation of its activity as an anticancer in T47D cell line. Vet. World. 2022;15(6):1583.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9375210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35993063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villarante K.I., Elegado F.B., Iwatani S., Zendo T., Sonomoto K., de Guzman E.E. Purification, characterization and in vitro cytotoxicity of the bacteriocin from Pediococcus acidilactici K2a2-3 against human colon adenocarcinoma (HT29) and human cervical carcinoma (HeLa) cells. World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2011;27:975–980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chikindas M.L., García-Garcerá M.J., Driessen A.J., Ledeboer A.M., Nissen-Meyer J., Nes I.F.…Venema G. Pediocin PA-1, a bacteriocin from Pediococcus acidilactici PAC1. 0, forms hydrophilic pores in the cytoplasmic membrane of target cells. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1993;59(11):3577–3584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC182501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8285666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P., Kaur S., Chadha B.S., Kaur R., Kaur M., Kaur S. Anticancer and antimicrobial potential of enterocin 12a from Enterococcus faecium. BMC Microbiol. 2021;21(1):1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7860584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33541292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viedma P.M., Abriouel H., Ben Omar N., López R.L., Valdivia E., Gálvez A. Assay of enterocin AS-48 for inhibition of foodborne pathogens in desserts. J. Food Protect. 2009;72(8):1654–1659.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19722396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yusuf M. Food Packaging and Preservation. Academic Press; 2018. Natural antimicrobial agents for food biopreservation; pp. 409–438.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Giani A., Bovio F., Forcella M., Fusi P., Sello G., Di Gennaro P. Identification of a bacteriocin-like compound from Lactobacillus plantarum with antimicrobial activity and effects on normal and cancerogenic human intestinal cells. Amb. Express. 2019;9(1):1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6579796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31209580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das D., Goyal A. Characterization of a noncytotoxic bacteriocin from probiotic Lactobacillus plantarum DM5 with potential as a food preservative. Food Funct. 2014;5(10):2453–2462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25103206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>López-Cuellar M.D.R., Rodríguez-Hernández A.I., Chavarría-Hernández N. LAB bacteriocin applications in the last decade. Biotechnol. Biotechnol. Equip. 2016;30(6):1039–1050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-S'adoon R.N.H., Al-Rawi A.M. A novel in vitro evidence on anticancer effect of local isolate Enterococcus faecalis bacteriocin. Journal of Global Scientific Research. 2023;8(2):2976–2986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerdkumthong K., Chanket W., Runsaeng P., Nanarong S., Songsurin K., Tantimetta P.…Obchoei S. Two recombinant bacteriocins, rhamnosin and lysostaphin, show synergistic anticancer activity against gemcitabine-resistant cholangiocarcinoma Cell Lines. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins. 2023:1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37294416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siddiqui A.J., Patel M., Adnan M., Jahan S., Saxena J., Alshahrani M.M.…Ouhtit A. Bacteriocin-nanoconjugates (Bac 10307-AgNPs) biosynthesized from Lactobacillus acidophilus-derived bacteriocins exhibit enhanced and promising biological activities. Pharmaceutics. 2023;15(2):403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9967518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36839725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnamoorthi R., Srinivash M., Mahalingam P.U., Malaikozhundan B., Suganya P., Gurushankar K. Antimicrobial, anti-biofilm, antioxidant and cytotoxic effects of bacteriocin by Lactococcus lactis strain CH3 isolated from fermented dairy products—an in vitro and in silico approach. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2022;220:291–306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35981676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Dein A.N., El-Deen A.M.N., El-Shatoury E.H., Awad G.A., Ibrahim M.K., Awad H.M., Farid M.A. Assessment of exopolysaccharides, bacteriocins and in vitro and in vivo hypocholesterolemic potential of some Egyptian Lactobacillus spp. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2021;173:66–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33482208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fathizadeh H., Saffari M., Esmaeili D., et al. Anticancer effect of enterocin A-colicin E1 fusion peptide on the gastric cancer cell. Probiotics &amp; Antimicro. Prot. 2021;13:1443–1451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34131854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbdul-Kaliq M.T., Rasool K.H., Essa R.H. Effect of crude bacteriocin isolated from locally Lactococcus lactis on cancer cell lines. Indian Journal of Forensic Medicine &amp; Toxicology. 2020;14(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y.C., Tsai T.L., Ye X.H., Lin T.H. Anti-proliferative effect on a colon adenocarcinoma cell line exerted by a membrane disrupting antimicrobial peptide KL15. Cancer Biol. Ther. 2015;16(8):1172–1183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4622422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26147829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rayapu V., Revathi K., Arunagirinathan A. Isolation, characterization of Lactobacillus delbrueckiiderived bacteriocin and assessment of its bioactive potential. Annals of the Romanian Society for Cell Biology. 2021:7520–7530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar B., Kaur B., Balgir P.P., Garg N. Cloning and expression of bacteriocins of Pediococcus spp. Arch. Clin. Microbiol. 2011;2:1–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaulieu L. Universite Laval; Quebec: 2004. Production, Purification et Caracterisation de la Pediocine PA-1 Naturelle et de ses Formes Recombiantes: Contribution a la Mise en Evidence d’une Nouvelle Activite Biologique.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dicks L.M., Dreyer L., Smith C., Van Staden A.D. A review: the fate of bacteriocins in the human gastro-intestinal tract: do they cross the gut–blood barrier? Front. Microbiol. 2018;9:2297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6173059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30323796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govari M., Kafentzi M.C., Pavlidis D.Ε., Tsouggou N., Pemaj V., Slavko A.…Papadimitriou K. In: Encyclopedia of Food Safety. second ed. Smithers G.W., editor. Elsevier B.V.; 2023. Antimicrobial proteins and peptides as a promising weapon to promote food safety under the one health approach; pp. 510–530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaghoubi A., Khazaei M., Avan A., Hasanian S.M., Soleimanpour S. The bacterial instrument as a promising therapy for colon cancer. Int. J. Colorectal Dis. 2020;35:595–606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32130489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H., Hu Y., Qi B., Yan C., Wang L., Zhang Y., Chen L. Network pharmacology and molecular docking to elucidate the mechanism of pulsatilla decoction in the treatment of colon cancer. Front. Pharmacol. 2022;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9393233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36003525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>