<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39299044</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1751-732X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>18</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Animal : an international journal of animal bioscience</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Animal</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>How does a superior quality sign guarantee the quality of lamb meat? The Label Rouge case.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>101312</StartPage><MedlinePgn>101312</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.animal.2024.101312</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1751-7311(24)00249-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Owing to the social, environmental and health changes in Europe, meat quality is becoming a critical issue for the long-term future of livestock farming. Label Rouge (LR) is a quality label owned by the French government that identifies food products produced inside or outside the European Union. This label guarantees the superior quality of a product compared with a standard product. This superior quality is guaranteed throughout the production process by specifications negotiated between the Institut National de l'Origine et de la Qualité (INAO) and operators in the sector. These specifications comprise two documents: first, common production conditions that apply to all specifications in a sector, and second, a book of specifications (BoSs). These two documents, which form the qualification mechanism, are divided into several parts: product name, product description, traceability, production method, labelling and the main control points. This study aims to understand how the LR defines lamb meat quality in the 11 existing BoSs using the seven dimensions of quality of animal-source foods (nutritional, sensory, commercial, technological, safety, convenience and image). We performed a computerised qualitative transversal analysis of the commitments associated with the production method and description of the product. This analysis was enriched by five semi-structured interviews with INAO members. We show that although LR is committed to all aspects of lamb meat quality, the sensory, image and carcass commercial quality attributes are predominant. However, the image attribute of quality is so ubiquitous that it required refinement to provide a better understanding of the construction of quality in terms of its environmental, ethical and cultural components.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Drevon</LastName><ForeName>D</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Inrae, Cirad, Institut Agro Montpellier, UMR Selmet Campus de la Gaillarde, 2 Place Pierre Viala, 34060 Montpellier, France. Electronic address: david.drevon@inrae.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prache</LastName><ForeName>S</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Clermont Auvergne, Inrae, Vetagro Sup, UMR1213 Herbivores, 63122 Saint-Genès-Champanelle, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nozières-Petit</LastName><ForeName>M-O</ForeName><Initials>MO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Inrae, Cirad, Institut Agro Montpellier, UMR Selmet Campus de la Gaillarde, 2 Place Pierre Viala, 34060 Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Animal</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101303270</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1751-7311</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Book of specifications</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Image</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meat quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quality attributes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sensory</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39299044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.animal.2024.101312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1751-7311(24)00249-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>