<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39290803</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2042-0986</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Therapeutic advances in drug safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ther Adv Drug Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Fetal exposure to isotretinoin in Saudi Arabia: a multicenter real-world data analysis from 2015 to 2020.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>20420986241272822</StartPage><MedlinePgn>20420986241272822</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">20420986241272822</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/20420986241272822</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Despite its high efficacy in treating severe acne, isotretinoin is associated with serious side effects, including teratogenicity. However, the extent of isotretinoin exposure during pregnancy in Saudi Arabia remains unknown.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study aims to quantify the extent of fetal exposure to isotretinoin in Saudi Arabia and to evaluate adherence to risk minimization measures approved by the Saudi Food and Drug Authority.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Retrospective cohort study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This multicenter retrospective study included a cohort of 6233 women of childbearing ages (WCBAs) who had received isotretinoin therapy between 2015 and 2020. Exposure to isotretinoin use was ascertained from patients' electronic health records and was defined as any positive pregnancy test (urine or serum) or any diagnosis or procedure related to pregnancy occurring during the risk period. We defined the risk period starting from isotretinoin initiation until up to 30 days after the last prescription. We quantified the overall incidence proportion of fetal exposure to isotretinoin by dividing the number of pregnancy cases during the risk period by the total study sample of WCBAs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The cohort predominantly included young females (20-29 years), with a mean age of 24 years. Only 5% of the WCBAs used contraceptives, and 10% have a record of pregnancy testing. During the risk period, 34 pregnancies were identified, yielding a cumulative pregnancy incidence of 5.6 per 1000 WCBAs. Pregnancy outcomes for exposed women were about 5% of births had defects, while abortions accounted for 14.3% of pregnancies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Our investigation shows an alarming incidence of fetal exposure to isotretinoin in Saudi Arabia, substantially surpassing global estimates. These results underscore a critical need for enhanced interventions and robust risk minimization strategies tailored to the distinct challenges faced by the Saudi Arabian population.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Albogami</LastName><ForeName>Yasser</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2816-6526</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, King Saud University, King Khalid Road, PO Box 145111, Riyadh 12372, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almadani</LastName><ForeName>Ohoud</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almohareb</LastName><ForeName>Sumaya N</ForeName><Initials>SN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy Practice, College of Pharmacy, King Saud bin Abdulaziz University for Health Sciences, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>King Abdullah International Medical Research Center, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ministry of the National Guard-Health Affairs, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alshehri</LastName><ForeName>Sultan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alkhaibari</LastName><ForeName>Abdullah</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anzan</LastName><ForeName>Mona</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacy Services, King Saud University Medical City, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alsharif</LastName><ForeName>Alaa</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy Practice, College of Pharmacy, Princess Nourah bint Abdulrahman University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alhossan</LastName><ForeName>Abdulaziz</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alrwisan</LastName><ForeName>Adel</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Ther Adv Drug Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101549074</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2042-0986</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText>Evaluating isotretinoin use during pregnancy in Saudi Arabia Why was the study done? Isotretinoin is highly effective for treating severe acne but is known to cause serious birth defects if used during pregnancy. The extent to which pregnant women in Saudi Arabia are exposed to isotretinoin was not known. Understanding this exposure is crucial to improve patient safety and adherence to preventive measures. What did the researchers do? The researchers conducted a retrospective study involving 6,233 women of childbearing age who received isotretinoin between 2015 and 2020. They used electronic health records from multiple healthcare institutions to identify cases of isotretinoin exposure during pregnancy. The study assessed the frequency of fetal exposure and evaluated adherence to risk minimization measures approved by the Saudi Food and Drug Authority (SFDA). What did the researchers find? The study found a significant incidence of fetal exposure to isotretinoin, with 5.6 cases per 1,000 women of childbearing age, which is much higher than global estimates. During the study period, 34 pregnancies were identified among isotretinoin users, with a notable percentage resulting in birth defects (5%) and abortions (14.3%). The adherence to contraceptive use (5%) and pregnancy testing (10%) among isotretinoin users was low, indicating a gap in following SFDA guidelines. What do the findings mean? These findings highlight a critical need for improved regulatory strategies and interventions to prevent fetal exposure to isotretinoin in Saudi Arabia. Enhanced measures might include better education on contraceptive use, stricter enforcement of pregnancy testing, and the integration of digital healthcare solutions to ensure adherence to safety protocols. This study sets a foundation for future efforts to improve the safe use of isotretinoin and protect unborn children from its harmful effects.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">REMS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Saudi Arabia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acne</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">contraceptive</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">drug safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fetal exposure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">isotretinoin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pregnancy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk minimization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">teratogenicity</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39290803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11406652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20420986241272822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_20420986241272822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Blasiak RC, Stamey CR, Burkhart CN, et al.. High-dose isotretinoin treatment and the rate of retrial, relapse, and adverse effects in patients with acne vulgaris. JAMA Dermatol 2013; 149: 1392–1398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24173086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lammer EJ, Chen DT, Hoar RM, et al.. Retinoic acid embryopathy. N Engl J Med 1985; 313: 837–841.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3162101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
U. S. Food &amp; Drug Administration. Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS): the iPLEDGE program, https://www.fda.gov/media/80023/download (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Alisa S.
Stop selling Roaccutane in private pharmacies. Alwatan Newspaper, https://www.alwatan.com.sa/a/360221 (2017, accessed 5 May 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abo El-Fetoh NM, Alenezi NG, Alshamari NG, et al.. Epidemiology of acne vulgaris in adolescent male students in Arar, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. J Egypt Public Health Assoc 2016; 91: 144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27749646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alshammrie FF, Alshammari R, Alharbi RM, et al.. Epidemiology of acne vulgaris and its association with lifestyle among adolescents and young adults in Hail, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia: a community-based study. Cureus 2020; 12: e9277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7431307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32821620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Mashat S, Al Sharif N, Zimmo S. Acne awareness and perception among population in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. J Saudi Soc Dermatol Dermatol Surg 2013; 17: 47–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Robaee AA. Prevalence, knowledge, beliefs and psychosocial impact of acne in University students in Central Saudi Arabia. Saudi Med J 2005; 26: 1958–1961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16380781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albogami Y. World Health Organization. Women of reproductive age (15–49 years) population (thousands), https://www.who.int/data/gho/indicator-metadata-registry/imr-details/women-of-reproductive-age-(15-49-years)-population-(thousands) (2023, accessed 9 August 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, et al.. The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. Ann Intern Med 2007; 147: 573–577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17938396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin J, Cheetham TC, Wong L, et al.. The impact of the iPLEDGE program on isotretinoin fetal exposure in an integrated health care system. J Am Acad Dermatol 2011; 65: 1117–1125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21565419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albogami Y, Sarayani A, Hincapie-Castillo JM, et al.. Real-world fetal exposure to acne treatments in the United States: a retrospective analysis from 2006 to 2015. Drug Saf 2021; 44: 447–454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7994218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33683646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uusküla A, Pisarev H, Kurvits K, et al.. Compliance with pregnancy prevention recommendations for isotretinoin in Estonia in 2012–2016. Drugs Real World Outcomes 2018; 5: 129–136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5984611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29790022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henry D, Dormuth C, Winquist B, et al.. Occurrence of pregnancy and pregnancy outcomes during isotretinoin therapy. CMAJ 2016; 188: 723–730.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4938682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27114489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crijns HJMJ, Straus SM, Gispen-de Wied C, et al.. Compliance with pregnancy prevention programmes of isotretinoin in Europe: a systematic review. Br J Dermatol 2011; 164: 238–244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20716214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouzès A, Jonville-Béra A-P. [Exposure to isotretinoin during pregnancy in France: 25 years of follow-up]. Therapie 2014; 69: 53–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24698189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alomair N, Alageel S, Davies N, et al.. Sexual and reproductive health knowledge, perceptions and experiences of women in Saudi Arabia: a qualitative study. Ethn Health 2022; 27: 1310–1328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33554633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi JS, Koren G, Nulman I. Pregnancy and isotretinoin therapy. CMAJ 2013; 185: 411–413.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3602257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23296582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
World Health Organization. Family planning/contraception methods, https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/family-planning-contraception (2023, accessed 11 October 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Vankar P. Contraceptive prevalence by region globally
2019. Statista, https://www.statista.com/statistics/978911/global-contraceptive-prevalence-by-region/ (2023, accessed 11 October 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haakenstad A, Angelino O, Irvine CMS, et al.. Measuring contraceptive method mix, prevalence, and demand satisfied by age and marital status in 204 countries and territories, 1970–2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet 2022; 400: 295–327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9304984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35871816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
World Bank Group. World Bank Open Data, https://data.worldbank.org (2019, accessed 11 October 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elamin HAM, Gadir IKA, Alhazmi MHA, et al.. The prevalence and factors affecting the use of contraceptive methods among Saudi women in Sabya, Jazan, Saudi Arabia. Saudi J Health Sci 2022; 11: 48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Saudi Health Council. Basic Health Insurance Policy, https://chi.gov.sa/en/Rules/Documents/Updated%20Essential%20Benefit%20Package%20%20%28%20effective%201%20October%202022%29.pdf (2022, accessed 29 October 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim AAM, Alshatri AA, Alsuwaidan S, et al.. Awareness of isotretinoin use and Saudi FDA pregnancy prevention program in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia: a cross-sectional study among female patients. Saudi Pharm J 2021; 29: 527–532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8233528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34194259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alrwisan AA, Alshammari TM, Tahir KW, et al.. Community pharmacists’ knowledge of isotretinoin safety. Saudi Med J 2014; 35: 81–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24445895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Algoblan S, Bakhsh S, Alharithy R. Women’s experiences regarding isotretinoin risk reduction counseling in Riyadh. J Dermatol Dermatol Surg 2019; 23: 13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>REMS lack data, according to US Inspector General. Reactions Weekly 1441, 2013, p. 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prokes M, Root A. A retrospective analysis of adherence to risk evaluation and mitigation strategies requirements for pulmonary arterial hypertension drugs. Hosp Pharm 2019; 54: 309–313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6751974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31555006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>