<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39296179</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Preliminary study on the geographical origin of Chinese 'Cuiguan' pears using integrated stable isotope and multi-element analyses.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e37450</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e37450</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e37450</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37450</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Distinguish the geographical origin of the pear is important due to the increasingly valued brand protection and reducing the potential food safety risks. In this study, the profiles of stable isotopes (δ<sup>13</sup>C, δ<sup>15</sup>N, δ<sup>2</sup>H, δ<sup>18</sup>O) and the contents of 16 elements in pear peer from four production areas were analyzed. The δ<sup>13</sup>C, δ<sup>15</sup>N, δ<sup>2</sup>H, δ<sup>18</sup>O and 12 elements were significantly different (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) in the four production areas. Chemometrics analysis including principal component analysis (PCA), orthogonal partial least squares discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA) and linear discriminant analysis (LDA) were exploited for geographical origin classification of samples. OPLS-DA analysis showed that crucial variables (δ<sup>13</sup>C, δ<sup>18</sup>O, δ<sup>2</sup>H, Ni, Cd, Ca, δ<sup>15</sup>N, Sr and Ga) are more relevant for the discrimination of the samples. OPLS-DA achieved pear origin accuracy rates of 87.76 % by combining stable isotope ratios and elemental contents. LDA had a higher accuracy rate than OPLS-DA, and the LDA analysis showed that the original discrimination rate reached to 100 %, while the cross-validated rate reached to 95.7 %. These studies indicated that this method could be used to assess the geographical discrimination of pear from different producing areas and could potentially control the fair trade of pear in fruit markets.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Tingting</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fu</LastName><ForeName>Tingting</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Yongchuan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gong</LastName><ForeName>Jiuping</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Bingjing</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoxia</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Mingfeng</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agricultural Quality Standard and Testing Technology, Chongqing Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chongqing 401329, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Product Quality and Safety Supervision, Inspection and Testing Center, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Chongqing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Geographical origin traceability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mineral elements</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pear</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Stable isotope</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39296179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)13481-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>United States Department of Agriculture (USDA)   Pears, Fresh: Production, Supply and Distribution. 2023. https://apps.fas.usda.gov/psdonline Available from.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu W., Sun T., Wu W., Hu T., Liu M. Determination of soluble solids content in cuiguan pear by Vis/NIR diffuse transmission spectroscopy and variable selection methods. Adv. Intell. Syst. Comput. 2014;278:269–276.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C., Kang X., Nie J., Li A., Farag M., Liu C., Rogers K.M., Xiao J., Yuan Y. Recent advances in Chinese food authentication and origin verification using isotope ratio mass spectrometry. Food Chem. 2022;398:1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35986998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X., Wu H., Pan J., Chen H., Rogers K.M. Geographical traceability of south-east Asian durian: a chemometric study using stable isotopes and elemental compositions. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2021;101:1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X., Rogers K.M., Li Y., Yang S., Zhou J. Untargeted and targeted discrimination of honey collected by apis cerana and apis mellifera based on volatiles using HS-GC-IMS and HS-SPME-GC-MS. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2019;67:12144–12152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31587558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing R., Wang N., Hu R., Zhang J., Han J., Chen Y. Application of next generation sequencing for species identification in meat and poultry products: a DNA metabarcoding approach. Food Control. 2019;101:173–179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C., Zhao W., Liu D., Fan Z., Tian Y., Wu W., Liang W., Rogers K.M. Modeling of stable isotope and multi-element compositions of jujube (Ziziphus jujuba Mill.) for origin traceability of protected geographical indication (PGI) products in Xinjiang, China. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2020;92</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li A., Zhao J., Xi Y., Yao J., Jin X., Chen X., Pan Q., Li G. Geographical authentication of peach in China based on stable isotope combined with multielement analysis of peach juice. Food Control. 2021;127</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J., Zhang A. Determination of geographical origin of concentrated apple juice through analysis of stable isotopic and mineral elemental fingerprints: preliminary results. J. Sci. Food Agr. 2021;101:3795–3803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33306834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung I., Kim J., Jin Y., Oh Y., Prabakaran M., Youn K., Kim S. Discriminative study of a potato (Solanum tuberosum L.) cultivation region by measuring the stable isotope ratios of bio-elements. Food Chem. 2016;212:48–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27374505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Opatic A.M., Necemer M., Lojen S., Masten J., Zlatic E., Sircelj H., Stopar D., Vidrih R. Determination of geographical origin of commercial tomato through analysis of stable isotopes, elemental composition and chemical markers. Food Control. 2017;89:133–141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magdas D.A., Feher I., Dehelean A., Cristea G., Magdas T.M., Puscas R., Marincas O. Isotopic and elemental markers for geographical origin and organically grown carrots discrimination. Food Chem. 2018:231–239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29934162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pianezze S., Perini M., Bontempo L., Ziller L., D'Archivio A.A. Geographical discrimination of garlic (Allium Sativum L.) based on Stable isotope ratio analysis coupled with statistical methods: the Italian case study. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2019;134</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31568853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X., Liu Z., Qian Q., Song W., Yuan Y. Isotope chemometrics determines farming methods and geographical origin of vegetables from Yangtze River Delta Region, China. Food Chem. 2020;342</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33097333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wadood S.A., Nie J., Li C., Rogers K.M., Zhang Y., Yuan Y. Geographical origin classification of peanuts and processed fractions using stable isotopes. Food Chem.:X. 2022;16:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9529559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36203953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong F., Liu C., Kang C., Wan X., Sun J., Wang T., Wang S., Li H., Yang J., Guo L. Authenticating the geographical origin of the Chinese yam (Tiegun) with stable isotopes and multiple elements. Food Chem.:X. 2023;18:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10149263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37131848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Zhang X., Li Y., Zhao X., Wang H. Preliminary research on the stable isotope composition characteristics of Apostichopus japonicus in the Bohai and Yellow Seas. Mar. Environ. Sci. 2017;36:37–42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S., Wang H., Jin L., White J.F., Kingsley K.L., Gou W., Cui L., Wang F., Wang Z., Wu G. Validation and analysis of the geographical origin of Angelica sinensis (Oliv.) Diels using multi-element and stable isotopes. PeerJ. 2021;9:1–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8351574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34434658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hai C., Yang X., Fu H., Chen H., He S., Kang L., Hao Q., Zhou L., Zhan Z., Liu Z., Yang J., Guo L. Determination of geographical origin for Atractylodes macrocephala Koidz by stable isotope and multielement analyses combined with chemometrics. J. Food Sci. 2023;88:1939–1953.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36994555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nie J., Shao S., Xia W., Liu Z., Rogers K.M. Stable isotopes verify geographical origin of yak meat from Qinghai-Tibet plateau. Meat Sci. 2020;165</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32203812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhaxi C., Zhao S., Zhang T., Dong H., Liu H., Zhao Y. Stable isotopes verify geographical origin of Tibetan chicken. Food Chem. 2021;358</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33940300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo R., Jiang T., Chen X., Zheng C., Liu H., Yang J. Determination of geographic origin of Chinese mitten crab (Eriocheir sinensis) using integrated stable isotope and multi-element analyses. Food Chem. 2019;274:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30372912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia Y., Jia L., Zhang K., Xie J., Yu E., Tian J., Gong W., Li Z., Li H., Wang G., Liu Y. Geographical origin traceability of procambarus clarkii based on mineral elements and stable isotopes. Foods. 2022;11:1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9564081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36230136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anna-Akrivi Thomatou E.P., Mazarakioti Eleni C., Katerinopoulou Katerina, Tsirogiannis Georgios, Zotos Anastasios, Kontogeorgos Achilleas, Patakas Angelos, Ladavos Athanasios. Stable isotope analysis for the discrimination of the geographical origin of Greek Bottarga ‘avgotaracho messolongiou’: a preliminary research. Foods. 2022;11:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9564321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36230036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu H., Tian L., Chen B., Jin B., Lin G. Verication of imported red wine origin into China using multi isotope and elemental analyses. Food Chem. 2019;301</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31362191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung I.M., Kim J.K., Lee J.H., An M.J., Lee K.J., Park S.K., Kim J.U., Kim M.J., Kim S.H. C/N/O/S stable isotopic and chemometric analyses for determining the geographical origin of Panax ginseng cultivated in Korea. J. Ginseng Res. 2017;42:485–495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6187101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30337809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou P., Li Z., Ouyang L., Gong X., Meng P., Dai M., Wang Z., Wang Y. A multi-element stable isotope approach coupled with chemometrics for the determination of Tieguanyin tea geographical origin and harvest season. Anal. Methods. 2019;11:346–352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng C., Zhang Y., Song W., Ya N., Zheng Q., Zhang P., Zheng Z., Xiao C., Cai R., Hui M. Using stable isotope signatures to delineate the geographic point-of-origin of Keemun black tea. J. Sci. Food Agr. 2019;99:2596–2601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30411367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang K., Zhu H., Zhao S., Liu H., Zhao Y. Determining the geographical origin of flaxseed based on stable isotopes, fatty acids and antioxidant capacity. J. Sci. Food Agr. 2021;102:673–679.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34213038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z., Wei Y., Hao Y., Liu W., Li B., Meng G. Multi-stable isotope and multi-element origin traceability of rice from the main producing regions in Asia: a long-term investigation during 2017–2020. Food Chem. 2023;412:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36753940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coelho I., Matos A.S., Teixeira R., Nascimento A., Bordado J., Donard O., Castanheira I. Combining multielement analysis and chemometrics to trace the geographical origin of Rocha pear. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2019;77:1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farquhar G.D., Ehleringer J.R., Hubick K.T. Carbon isotope discrimination and photosynthesis. Annu. Rev. Plant Biol. 1989;40:503–537.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diefendorf A.F., Mueller K.E., Wing S.L., Koch P.L., Freeman K.H. Global patterns in leaf C-13 discrimination and implications for studies of past and future climate. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2010;107:5738–5743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2851872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20231481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bat K.B., Vidrih R., Nečmer M., Vodopivec B.M., Mulič I., Kump P., Ogrinc N. Characterization of slovenian apples with respect to their botanical and geographical origin and agricultural production practice. J. Food Sci. 2012;50:107–116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z., Erasmus S.W., Dekker P., Guo B., Ruth S.M.V. Linking growing conditions to stable isotope ratios and elemental compositions of Costa Rican bananas (Musa spp.) Food Res. Int. 2019;129</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32036917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui L., Huan C., Yuan Y., Zhu F., Nie J., Han S., Fu Y.n., Hou H., Hu Q., Chen Z. Tracing the geographical origin of tobacco at two spatial scales by stable isotope and element analyses with chemometrics. Food Chem. 2023;18:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10314160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37397212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbour, Margaret M. Stable oxygen isotope composition of plant tissue: a review. Funct. Plant Biol. 2007;34:83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32689335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galimov E.M. The Biological Fractionation ofIsotopes. 1985. Fractionation of isotopes in biological systems; pp. 174–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teng Y., Wu J., Lu S., Wang Y., Jiao X., Song L. Soil and soil environmental quality monitoring in China: a review. Environ. Int. 2014;69:177–199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24875802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rohloff J., Uleberg E., Nes A., Krogstad T., Martinussen I. Nutritional composition of bilberries (Vaccinium myrtillus L.) from forest fields in Norway-Effects of geographic origin, climate, fertilization and soil properties. J. Appl. Bot. Food Qual. 2015;88:274–287.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdi H., Williams L.J. Principal component analysis. Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Comput. Stat. 2010;2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boccard J., Rutledge D.N. A consensus orthogonal partial least squares discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA) strategy for multiblock Omics data fusion. Anal. Chim. Acta. 2013;769:30–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23498118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tharwat A., Gaber T., Ibrahim A., Hassanien E. 2017. Linear Discriminant Analysis: a Detailed Tutorial.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belmonte-Sánchez J.R., Romero-González R., Arrebola F.J., Vidal J.L.M., Frenich A.G. An innovative metabolomic approach for golden rum classification combining ultrahigh-performance liquid chromatography-orbitrap mass spectrometry and chemometric strategies. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2019;67:1302–1311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30618256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao R., Su M., Zhao Y., Chen G., Yang S. Chemical analysis combined with multivariate statistical methods to determine the geographical origin of milk from four regions in China. Foods. 2021;10:1119–1132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8158098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34070041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>