<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39296155</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Monitoring pesticide residues in pepper (<i>Capsicum annuum</i> L.) from Al-Qassim region, Saudi Arabia: Occurrence, quality, and risk evaluations.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e36805</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e36805</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e36805</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36805</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The Al-Qassim region, a prominent agricultural hub in Saudi Arabia, significantly contributes to the national production of vegetables and fruits. This study validated the standard EN-QuEChERS (Quick, Easy, Cheap, Effective, Rugged and Safe) method in conjunction with liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) to determine 90 multiple pesticide residues in three categories of peppers: green bell, green hot and red chilli peppers. Validation criteria, including linearity range, accuracy, precision, limit of detection (LOD), and limit of quantification (LOQ), were within the acceptance range of the SANTE/11312/2021 guideline. The validated method was then used to analyse 536 pepper samples collected in 2023 from the Al-Qassim region of Saudi Arabia. The analysis of 536 pepper samples revealed that 394 samples (73.51 %) contained pesticide residues, with 126 (23.51 %) exceeding the established maximum residue limits (MRLs). The most frequently identified pesticide was imidacloprid (171 samples, 31.9 %) and acetamiprid (94 samples, 17.54 %), followed by bifenazate and difenoconazole, which were each detected in 66 samples (12.31 %). Among the remaining 32 pesticides, 24 were detected in 1%-10 % of the samples, whereas 8 were detected in &lt;1 %. The 36 pesticides detected were classified into 14 insecticides (38.9 %), 14 fungicides (38.9 %) and 8 acaricides (22.2 %). Notably, the overall detection rate of the pesticides was relatively higher in red chilli peppers (232 %) compared with bell peppers (165 %), followed by green hot peppers (132 %). Red chilli peppers also showed the highest residue concentrations of various pesticides. Neonicotinoids and triazoles exhibited the highest detection rates in this study. The residue quality index (IqR) of the samples analysed fell into the categories excellent (26.49 %), good (31.72 %), and adequate (14.06 %), with 28.73 % of the samples deemed inadequate. Long-term dietary exposure was examined for adults and children. This study highlights the crucial role of continual observation in defending public health and securing the trade standardisation and safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alminderej</LastName><ForeName>Fahad M</ForeName><Initials>FM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, College of Science, Qassim University, Buraidah 51452, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saleh</LastName><ForeName>Sayed M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, College of Science, Qassim University, Buraidah 51452, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdallah</LastName><ForeName>Osama I</ForeName><Initials>OI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide Residues and Environmental Pollution Department, Central Agricultural Pesticide Laboratory, Agriculture Research Center, Dokki, Giza, 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety Laboratory, Al-Qassim Municipality, Buraidah, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Method validation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Peppers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pesticide residues</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quality index</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Risk assessment</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39296155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)12836-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>KumAr O.A., Tata S.S. Ascorbic acid contents in chili peppers (Capsicum L.) Not. Sci. Biol. 2009;1:50–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard L.R., Talcott S.T., Brenes C.H., Villalon B. Changes in phytochemical and antioxidant activity of selected pepper cultivars (Capsicum species) as influenced by maturity. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2000;48:1713–1720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10820084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramchiary N., Kehie M., Brahma V., Kumaria S., Tandon P. Application of genetics and genomics towards Capsicum translational research. Plant Biotechnology Reports. 2014;8:101–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spiller F., Alves M.K., Vieira S.M., Carvalho T.A., Leite C.E., Lunardelli A., Poloni J.A., Cunha F.Q., de Oliveira J.R. Anti‐inflammatory effects of red pepper (Capsicum baccatum) on carrageenan‐and antigen‐induced inflammation. J. Pharm. Pharmacol. 2008;60:473–478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18380920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Careaga M., Fernández E., Dorantes L., Mota L., Jaramillo M.E., Hernandez-Sanchez H. Antibacterial activity of Capsicum extract against Salmonella typhimurium and Pseudomonas aeruginosa inoculated in raw beef meat. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 2003;83:331–335.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12745238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvarez-Parrilla E., de la Rosa L.A., Amarowicz R., Shahidi F. Antioxidant activity of fresh and processed Jalapeno and Serrano peppers. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2011;59:163–173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21126003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam M.N., BintENaser S.F., Khan M.S. Pesticide food laws and regulations, pesticide residue in foods: sources. Manag. Control. 2017:37–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazić S., Šunjka D., Stojanović I. 2014. Determination of Acetamiprid Residues in Paprika.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EU MRL Database. Available Online: EU Pesticides Database - MRLs (europa.Eu) 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CODEX Alimentarius Commission (CODEX) 2024. Available Online: Pesticides | CODEXALIMENTARIUS FAO-WHO.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SFDA . Available Online: PESTICIDE-RESIDUES-AGRICULTURAL-FOOD-PRODUCTS.Pdf (sfda.gov.Sa) 2021. Maximum limits of pesticide residues in agricultural and food products.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan Y., Guan N., Li P., Li J., Luo J. Monitoring and dietary exposure assessment of pesticide residues in cowpea (Vigna unguiculata L. Walp) in Hainan, China. Food Control. 2016;59:250–255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z., Nie J., Yan Z., Cheng Y., Lan F., Huang Y., Chen Q., Zhao X., Li A. A monitoring survey and dietary risk assessment for pesticide residues on peaches in China. Regul. Toxicol. Pharmacol. 2018;97:152–162.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29909271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akoto O., Andoh H., Darko G., Eshun K., Osei-Fosu P. Health risk assessment of pesticides residue in maize and cowpea from Ejura, Ghana. Chemosphere. 2013;92:67–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23557726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong C., Huang Y., Hu J. Occurrence and safety assessment of 18 frequently registered pesticides and their metabolites on cucumbers in open field and greenhouse in China. Microchem. J. 2023;189</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shim J.-H., Eun J.-B., Zaky A.A., Hussein A.S., Hacimüftüoğlu A., Abd El-Aty A.M. A comprehensive review of pesticide residues in peppers. Foods. 2023;12:970.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10000673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36900487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yıldırım İ., Çiftçi U. Monitoring of pesticide residues in peppers from Çanakkale (Turkey) public market using QuEChERS method and LC–MS/MS and GC–MS/MS detection. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2022;194:570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35796789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Authority E.F.S., Medina‐Pastor P., Triacchini G. The 2018 European Union report on pesticide residues in food. EFSA J. 2020;18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7447915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32874271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ersoy N., Tatli O., Ozcan S., Evcil E., Coskun L.S., Erdogan E. Some pesticide residues of stone and nuts fruit species. Selcuk Journal of Agriculture and Food Sciences. 2011;25:75–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramadan M.F.A., Abdel-Hamid M.M.A., Altorgoman M.M.F., AlGaramah H.A., Alawi M.A., Shati A.A., Shweeta H.A., Awwad N.S. Evaluation of pesticide residues in vegetables from the Asir region, Saudi Arabia. Molecules. 2020;25:205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6982748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31947847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu Z., Zhuang M., Li S., Xiao P., Li M., Liu D., Zhou J., Chen J., Zhao J. Residue levels and health risk of pesticide residues in bell pepper in Shandong. Food Addit. Contam. 2019;36:1385–1392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31294676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman K.A., Al-Humaid A.M., Al-Rehiayani S.M., Al-Redhaiman K.N. Monitoring of pesticide residues in vegetables marketed in Al-Qassim region, Saudi Arabia. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 2010;73:1433–1439.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20627311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdallah O.I., Alamer S.S., Alrasheed A.M. Monitoring pesticide residues in dates marketed in Al‐Qassim, Saudi Arabia using a QuEChERS methodology and liquid chromatography–tandem mass spectrometry. Biomed. Chromatogr. 2018;32</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29377192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen T.D., Lee M.H., Lee G.H. Multiresidue determination of 156 pesticides in watermelon by dispersive solid phase extraction and gas chromatography/mass spectrometry. Bull. Korean Chem. Soc. 2008;29:57–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kataoka H., Lord H.L., Pawliszyn J. Applications of solid-phase microextraction in food analysis. J. Chromatogr. A. 2000;880:35–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10890509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mills G.A., Walker V. Headspace solid-phase microextraction procedures for gas chromatographic analysis of biological fluids and materials. J. Chromatogr. A. 2000;902:267–287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11192159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehotay S.J., Son K.A., Kwon H., Koesukwiwat U., Fu W., Mastovska K., Hoh E., Leepipatpiboon N. Comparison of QuEChERS sample preparation methods for the analysis of pesticide residues in fruits and vegetables. J. Chromatogr. A. 2010;1217:2548–2560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20144460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng K., Wu X., Chen J., Chen J., Lian W., Su J., Shi L. Establishment of an LC-MS/MS method for the determination of 45 pesticide residues in fruits and vegetables from Fujian, China. Molecules. 2022;27:8674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9788273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36557806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Costa Morais E.H., Collins C.H., Jardim I.C.S.F. Pesticide determination in sweet peppers using QuEChERS and LC–MS/MS. Food Chem. 2018;249:77–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29407934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission E. Directive (2002/63/EC). Establishing Community methods of sampling for the official control of pesticide residues in and on products of plant and animal origin. Official Journal of the European Communities. 2002;187:30–45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pihlström T., Fernández-Alba A.R., Amate C.F., Poulsen M.E., Hardebusch B., Anastassiades M., Lippold R., Cabrera L.C., de Kok A., Oregan F. 2021. Analytical Quality Control and Method Validation Procedures for Pesticide Residues Analysis in Food and Feed SANTE 11312/2021; p. v2. Sante 11312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhamami M.A.M., Algethami J.S., Ramadan M.F., Abdallah O.I. A vortex-assisted liquid-liquid extraction followed by dispersive-solid phase extraction (VA-LLE/d-SPE) for the determination of eight benzoylphenylureas insecticides in tomatoes and cucumbers. Acta Chromatogr. 2024 doi: 10.1556/1326.2024.01200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1556/1326.2024.01200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdallah O.I., Abd El-Hamid R.M., Ahmed N.S., Saleh S.M., Alminderej F.M. Terminal residues and risk assessment of Spiromesifen and Spirodiclofen in tomato fruits. Plants. 2023;12:1493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10097050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37050119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibi A., Rafique N., Khalid S., Samad A., Ahad K., Mehboob F. Method optimization and validation for the routine analysis of multi-class pesticide residues in Kinnow Mandarin and fruit quality evaluation. Food Chem. 2022;369</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34461515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhamami M.A.M., Algethami J.S., Seliem A.F., Alnaam Y.A., Ramadan M.F., Abdallah O.I. Dissipation profile and risk assessment of diflubenzuron and novaluron in tomato fruits under greenhouse conditions. Cogent Food Agric. 2023;9 doi: 10.1080/23311932.2023.2275393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/23311932.2023.2275393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malhat F., Abdallah O., Anagnostopoulos C., Hussien M., Purnama I., Helmy R., Soliman H., El-Hefny D. Residue, dissipation, and dietary intake evaluation of fenpyroximate acaricide in/on guava, orange, and eggplant under open field condition. Front. Nutr. 2022;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9470998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36118744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z., Zhang Y., Zhao Q., Wang C., Cui Y., Li J., Chen A., Liang G., Jiao B. Occurrence, temporal variation, quality and safety assessment of pesticide residues on citrus fruits in China. Chemosphere. 2020;258</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32569958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumari D., John S. Health risk assessment of pesticide residues in fruits and vegetables from farms and markets of Western Indian Himalayan region. Chemosphere. 2019;224:162–167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30822723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrer C., Lozano A., Agüera A., Girón A.J., Fernández-Alba A.R. Overcoming matrix effects using the dilution approach in multiresidue methods for fruits and vegetables. J. Chromatogr. A. 2011;1218:7634–7639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21820661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matuszewski B.K., Constanzer M.L., Chavez-Eng C.M. Strategies for the assessment of matrix effect in quantitative bioanalytical methods based on HPLC− MS/MS. Anal. Chem. 2003;75:3019–3030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12964746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor P.J. Matrix effects: the Achilles heel of quantitative high-performance liquid chromatography–electrospray–tandem mass spectrometry. Clin. Biochem. 2005;38:328–334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15766734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui K., Wu X., Wei D., Zhang Y., Cao J., Xu J., Dong F., Liu X., Zheng Y. Health risks to dietary neonicotinoids are low for Chinese residents based on an analysis of 13 daily-consumed foods. Environ. Int. 2021;149</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33503555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma N., Banerjee H., Pal S., Sharma K.K. Persistence of thiacloprid and deltamethrin residues in tea grown at different locations of North-East India. Food Chem. 2018;253:88–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29502848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S., Liu Y., Jiao S., Zhao Y., Guo Y., Wang M., Zhu G. Quantum-dot-based lateral flow immunoassay for detection of neonicotinoid residues in tea leaves. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2017;65:10107–10114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29077402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oerke E.-C., Dehne H.-W. Safeguarding production—losses in major crops and the role of crop protection. Crop Protect. 2004;23:275–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malhat F., Abdallah O., Ahmed F., Salam S.A., Anagnostopoulos C., Ahmed M.T. Dissipation behavior of thiophanate-methyl in strawberry under open field condition in Egypt and consumer risk assessment. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Control Ser. 2021;28:1029–1039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32827299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasreddine L., Parent-Massin D. Food contamination by metals and pesticides in the European Union. Should we worry? Toxicol. Lett. 2002;127:29–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12052638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaya T., Tuna A.L. 2019. Investigation of Pesticide Residue Levels in Fruit and Vegetables Collected from Three Farmers Market in İzmir Province.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sungur Ş., Tunur C. Investigation of pesticide residues in vegetables and fruits grown in various regions of Hatay, Turkey. Food Addit. Contam. B. 2012;5:265–267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24786407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golge O., Hepsag F., Kabak B. Health risk assessment of selected pesticide residues in green pepper and cucumber. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2018;121:51–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30121352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozowicka B. Health risk for children and adults consuming apples with pesticide residue. Sci. Total Environ. 2015;502:184–198.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25260164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Chow W., Chang J., Wong J.W. Development and validation of a qualitative method for target screening of 448 pesticide residues in fruits and vegetables using UHPLC/ESI Q-Orbitrap based on data-independent acquisition and compound database. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2017;65:473–493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28002940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szpyrka E., Kurdziel A., Matyaszek A., Podbielska M., Rupar J., Słowik-Borowiec M. Evaluation of pesticide residues in fruits and vegetables from the region of south-eastern Poland. Food Control. 2015;48:137–142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sapbamrer R., Hongsibsong S. Organophosphorus pesticide residues in vegetables from farms, markets, and a supermarket around Kwan Phayao Lake of Northern Thailand. Arch. Environ. Contam. Toxicol. 2014;67:60–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24609615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakırcı G.T., Acay D.B.Y., Bakırcı F., Ötleş S. Pesticide residues in fruits and vegetables from the Aegean region, Turkey. Food Chem. 2014;160:379–392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24799252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osei-Fosu P., Donkor A.K., Nyarko S., Nazzah N.K., Asante I.K., Kingsford-Adabo R., Arkorful N.A. Monitoring of pesticide residues of five notable vegetables at Agbogbloshie market in Accra, Ghana. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2014;186:7157–7163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25007773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mac Loughlin T.M., Peluso M.L., Etchegoyen M.A., Alonso L.L., de Castro M.C., Percudani M.C., Marino D.J.G. Pesticide residues in fruits and vegetables of the argentine domestic market: occurrence and quality. Food Control. 2018;93:129–138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehmann E., Turrero N., Kolia M., Konaté Y., De Alencastro L.F. Dietary risk assessment of pesticides from vegetables and drinking water in gardening areas in Burkina Faso. Sci. Total Environ. 2017;601:1208–1216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28605838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z., Nie J., Lu Z., Xie H., Kang L., Chen Q., Li A., Zhao X., Xu G., Yan Z. Cumulative risk assessment of the exposure to pyrethroids through fruits consumption in China–Based on a 3-year investigation. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2016;96:234–243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27515867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung S.W.C. How effective are common household preparations on removing pesticide residues from fruit and vegetables? A review. J. Sci. Food Agric. 2018;98:2857–2870.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29222908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jankowska M., Łozowicka B., Kaczyński P. Comprehensive toxicological study over 160 processing factors of pesticides in selected fruit and vegetables after water, mechanical and thermal processing treatments and their application to human health risk assessment. Sci. Total Environ. 2019;652:1156–1167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30586803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>