<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39297558</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Limosilactobacillus reuteri RE225 alleviates gout by modulating the TLR4/MyD88/NF-κB inflammatory pathway and the Nrf2/HO-1 oxidative stress pathway, and by regulating gut microbiota.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13908</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Gout poses a significant health threat. The use of Lactobacillus from the gut microbiota is one potential remedy. However, the intricate molecular mechanisms governing the impact of Lactobacillus on gout remain largely uncharted. In this study, a strain of Limosilactobacillus reuteri RE225 was separated from the gut of mice and colitis was treated with polypeptide intervention.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Limosilactobacillus reuteri RE225 reduced foot tumefaction markedly in mice with gout and extended the pain threshold time in their feet. It also improved the health of gut microbiota. Intervention with L. reuteri RE225 also suppressed the TLR4/MyD88/NF-κB and nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2)/heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1) pathways in the mice, reduced the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines - interleukin 1β (IL-1β), interleukin 6 (IL-6), and tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) - and increased the level of the anti-inflammatory cytokine interleukin 10 (IL-10), thereby mitigating inflammation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study provides a theoretical basis for the comprehensive development of Limosilactobacillus reuteri and new ideas for the non-pharmacological treatment of gout. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Qin</LastName><ForeName>Yang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, School of Marine Science, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Yucong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biological and Environmental Science, Zhejiang Wanli University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiong</LastName><ForeName>Jiayi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, School of Marine Science, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Chenyang</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, School of Marine Science, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, School of Marine Science, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Su</LastName><ForeName>Xiurong</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, School of Marine Science, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Han</LastName><ForeName>Jiaojiao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2821-8522</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, School of Marine Science, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>General Project of Zhejiang Provincial Department of Education (Y202146257)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province (LTGC23C190001)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province (LQ22D060002)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Limosilactobacillus reuteri</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gout</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gut microbiota</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inflammatory pathways</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oxidative stress</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39297558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Sun ZR, Liu HR, Hu D, Fan MS, Wang MY, An MF et al., Ellagic acid exerts beneficial effects on hyperuricemia by inhibiting xanthine oxidase and NLRP3 inflammasome activation. J Agric Food Chem 69:12741–12752 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu B, Wang Y, Zhou W, Jin S, Shen Z, Zhang H et al., Trend dynamics of gout prevalence among the Chinese population, 1990‐2019: a joinpoint and age‐period‐cohort analysis. Front Public Health 10:1008598 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schlesinger N, Pillinger MH, Simon LS and Lipsky PE, Interleukin‐1β inhibitors for the management of acute gout flares: a systematic literature review. Arthritis Res Ther 25:128 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cipolletta E, Tata LJ, Nakafero G, Avery AJ, Mamas MA and Abhishek A, Association between gout flare and subsequent cardiovascular events among patients with gout. JAMA 328:440–450 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sivera F, Andres M and Dalbeth N, A glance into the future of gout. Ther Adv Musculoskeletal Dis 14:1759720x221114098 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamanaka H, Taniguchi A, Tsuboi H, Kano H and Asami Y, Hypouricaemic effects of yoghurt containing Lactobacillus gasseri PA‐3 in patients with hyperuricaemia and/or gout: a randomised, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled study. Mod Rheumatol 29:146–150 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao J, Liu Q, Hao H, Bu Y, Tian X, Wang T et al., Lactobacillus paracasei X11 ameliorates hyperuricemia and modulates gut microbiota in mice. Front Immunol 13:940228 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chien CY, Chien YJ, Lin YH, Lin YH, Chan ST, Hu WC et al., Supplementation of Lactobacillus plantarum (TCI227) prevented potassium‐oxonate‐induced hyperuricemia in rats. Nutrients 14 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu Y, Sun S, Huang Y, Gao Q, Xie X, Wang P et al., Metagenomic analysis revealed the potential role of gut microbiome in gout. NPJ Biofilms Microbiomes 7:66 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Li Y, Liao W, Huang J, Liu Y, Li Z et al., Gut microbiota remodeling: a promising therapeutic strategy to confront hyperuricemia and gout. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 12:935723 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim HW, Yoon EJ, Jeong SH and Park MC, Distinct gut microbiota in patients with asymptomatic hyperuricemia: a potential protector against gout development. Yonsei Med J 63:241–251 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Z, Zhang J, Wang Z, Ang KY, Huang S, Hou Q et al., Intestinal microbiota distinguish gout patients from healthy humans. Sci Rep 6:20602 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Ye Z, Feng P, Li R, Chen X, Tian X et al., Limosilactobacillus fermentum JL‐3 isolated from “Jiangshui” ameliorates hyperuricemia by degrading uric acid. Gut Microbes 13:1–18 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Shi Q, Feng Y, Han J, Lu C, Zhou J et al., Targeted screening of an anti‐inflammatory polypeptide from Rhopilema esculentum Kishinouye cnidoblasts and elucidation of its mechanism in alleviating ulcerative colitis based on an analysis of the gut microbiota and metabolites. Food Sci Human Wellness 13:1336 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Feng Y, Han J, Lu C, Zhou J, Wang Z et al., Characteristics and functions of Limosilactobacillus reuteri (Lactobacillus reuteri) from the intestine of mice supplemented with three dietary components based on genome resequencing and metabolite analysis. Food Biosci 53:102694 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng Y, Ma Y, Luo Z, Jiang Y, Xu Z and Yu R, Lactobacillus reuteri in digestive system diseases: focus on clinical trials and mechanisms. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 13:1254198 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Z, Chen A, Xie A, Liu X, Jiang S and Yu R, Limosilactobacillus reuteri in immunomodulation: molecular mechanisms and potential applications. Front Immunol 14:1228754 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones SE and Versalovic J, Probiotic Lactobacillus reuteri biofilms produce antimicrobial and anti‐inflammatory factors. BMC Microbiol 9:35 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karimi K, Inman MD, Bienenstock J and Forsythe P, Lactobacillus reuteri‐induced regulatory T cells protect against an allergic airway response in mice. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 179:186–193 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng F, Wang Z, Stanton C, Ross RP, Zhao J, Zhang H et al., Lactobacillus rhamnosus FJSYC4‐1 and Lactobacillus reuteri FGSZY33L6 alleviate metabolic syndrome via gut microbiota regulation. Food Funct 12:3919–3930 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt AP, Böhmer AE, Antunes C, Schallenberger C, Porciúncula LO, Elisabetsky E et al., Anti‐nociceptive properties of the xanthine oxidase inhibitor allopurinol in mice: role of A1 adenosine receptors. Br J Pharmacol. 156:163–172 (2009). doi:10.1111/j.1476‐5381.2008.00025.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han J, Wang Z, Lu C, Zhou J, Li Y, Ming T et al., The gut microbiota mediates the protective effects of anserine supplementation on hyperuricaemia and associated renal inflammation. Food Funct 12:9030–9042 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han J, Wang X, Tang S, Lu C, Wan H, Zhou J et al., Protective effects of tuna meat oligopeptides (TMOP) supplementation on hyperuricemia and associated renal inflammation mediated by gut microbiota. FASEB J 34:5061–5076 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashiq K, Bajwa MA, Tanveer S, Qayyum M, Ashiq S, Khokhar R et al., A comprehensive review on gout: the epidemiological trends, pathophysiology, clinical presentation, diagnosis and treatment. J Pak Med Assoc 71:1234–1238 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards SW, Hughes V, Barlow J and Bucknall R, Immunological detection of myeloperoxidase in synovial fluid from patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Biochem J 250:81–85 (1988).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin DE, Liang W, Yu Y, Whelan EC, Yuan X, Wang ZL et al., Modified Simiaowan prevents and treats gouty arthritis via the Nrf2/NLRP3 inflammasome signaling pathway. J Ethnopharmacol 318:116906 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>So AK and Martinon F, Inflammation in gout: mechanisms and therapeutic targets. Nat Rev Rheumatol 13:639–647 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kienhorst LB, van Lochem E, Kievit W, Dalbeth N, Merriman ME, Phipps‐Green A et al., Gout is a chronic inflammatory disease in which high levels of Interleukin‐8 (CXCL8), myeloid‐related protein 8/myeloid‐related protein 14 complex, and an altered proteome are associated with diabetes mellitus and cardiovascular disease. Arthritis Rheumatol (Hoboken, NJ) 67:3303–3313 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng JJ, Ma XD, Ai GX, Yu QX, Chen XY, Yan F et al., Palmatine protects against MSU‐induced gouty arthritis via regulating the NF‐κB/NLRP3 and Nrf2 pathways. Drug Des Devel Ther 16:2119–2132 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SJ, Nam KI, Jin HM, Cho YN, Lee SE, Kim TJ et al., Bone destruction by receptor activator of nuclear factor κB ligand‐expressing T cells in chronic gouty arthritis. Arthritis Res Ther 13:R164 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choe JY, Jung HY, Park KY and Kim SK, Enhanced p62 expression through impaired proteasomal degradation is involved in caspase‐1 activation in monosodium urate crystal‐induced interleukin‐1b expression. Rheumatology (Oxford) 53:1043–1053 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Li L, Yan H, Jiang X, Hu W, Han N et al., Anti‐gouty arthritis and anti‐hyperuricemia properties of celery seed extracts in rodent models. Mol Med Rep 20:4623–4633 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun X, Li P, Qu X and Liu W, Isovitexin alleviates acute gouty arthritis in rats by inhibiting inflammation via the TLR4/MyD88/NF‐κB pathway. Pharm Biol 59:1326–1333 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poligone B and Baldwin AS, Positive and negative regulation of NF‐kappaB by COX‐2: roles of different prostaglandins. J Biol Chem 276:38658–38664 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jhang JJ, Cheng YT, Ho CY and Yen GC, Monosodium urate crystals trigger Nrf2‐ and heme oxygenase‐1‐dependent inflammation in THP‐1 cells. Cell Mol Immunol 12:424–434 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirvani‐Rad S, Khatibzade‐Nasari N, Ejtahed HS and Larijani B, Exploring the role of gut microbiota dysbiosis in gout pathogenesis: a systematic review. Front Med 10:1163778 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu CL, Hou YH, Wang CS, Lin SW, Jhou BY, Chen CC et al., Antiobesity and uric acid‐lowering effect of Lactobacillus plantarum GKM3 in high‐fat‐diet‐induced obese rats. J Am Coll Nutr 38:623–632 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng J, Li Y, Zou Y, Yang Y, Yang T and Zhou Y, Intestinal toxicity alleviation and efficacy potentiation through therapeutic administration of Lactobacillus paracasei GY‐1 in the treatment of gout flares with colchicine. Food Funct (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Zhao Z, Zhao L, Zhao Y, Yang G, Wang C et al., Lactobacillus plantarum DP189 reduces α‐SYN aggravation in MPTP‐induced parkinson's disease mice via regulating oxidative damage, inflammation, and gut microbiota disorder. J Agric Food Chem 70:1163–1173 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian M, Wang J, Wang Y, Nie A, Zhu C, Sun Z et al., Chicory ameliorates hyperuricemia via modulating gut microbiota and alleviating LPS/TLR4 axis in quail. Biomed Pharmacother 131:110719 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv Q, Xu D, Ma J, Wang Y, Yang X, Zhao P et al., Uric acid drives intestinal barrier dysfunction through TSPO‐mediated NLRP3 inflammasome activation. Inflammation Res 70:127–137 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Jia Y, Wen L, Mu W, Wu X, Liu T et al., Porphyromonas gingivalis promotes colorectal carcinoma by activating the hematopoietic NLRP3 inflammasome. Cancer Res 81:2745–2759 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Yu C, Zhang X, Chen H, Dong J, Lu W et al., Porphyromonas gingivalis lipopolysaccharide induces cognitive dysfunction, mediated by neuronal inflammation via activation of the TLR4 signaling pathway in C57BL/6 mice. J Neuroinflammation 15:37 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prochazkova P, Roubalova R, Dvorak J, Kreisinger J, Hill M, Tlaskalova‐Hogenova H et al., The intestinal microbiota and metabolites in patients with anorexia nervosa. Gut Microbes 13:1–25 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dziarski R, Park SY, Kashyap DR, Dowd SE and Gupta D, Pglyrp‐regulated gut microflora prevotella falsenii, parabacteroides distasonis and bacteroides eggerthii enhance and alistipes finegoldii attenuates colitis in mice. PLoS One 11:e0146162 (2016).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>