<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39290370</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1178-6302</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>18</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental health insights</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Health Insights</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exposure to Dietary Glycidyl and 3-MCPD Fatty Acid Esters and Associated Burden of Cancer in Selected Asian and European Countries: A Review and Data Synthesis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>11786302241277628</StartPage><MedlinePgn>11786302241277628</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">11786302241277628</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/11786302241277628</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study evaluated the health implications and oncological impact of consuming glycidyl esters (GE) and 3-monochloro-1,2-propanediol esters (3-MCPDE) in selected Asian and European populations. Data on dietary GE and 3-MCPDE were compiled from 10 studies conducted in China, Taiwan, Poland, and Spain, identified through a systematic search in PubMed and ScienceDirect databases from 2012 to 2022. Studies on food supplements and analytical methods were excluded from the analysis. Health metrics for these nations, spanning 2015 to 2019, were sourced from the Institute of Health Metrics and Evaluation, among others. A Monte Carlo Simulation was employed for data analysis. The results showed that "grains and grain products" was the most consumed food category (260.45-395.35 g/day), whereas "food for infants and children" was the least consumed (0.01-0.09 g/day). Additionally, "fats from animal or plant origin" had the highest contamination levels. While 3-MCPDE exposures remained within safe limits, median GE exposure correlated with an incidence of colon cancer ranging from 3.66 × 10<sup>-8</sup> to 0.744%, lung cancer from 0.00256 to 0.287%, and breast cancer from 0.0262 to 2.42% within the study areas. This translated to a total cancer burden of 6.69 to 1020 Disability-Adjusted Life Years (DALYs) per 100 000 individuals. The population in China recorded the highest DALY rate (1,020), followed by Spain (30.2), Poland (19.7), and Taiwan (6.69). Projections suggest an uptick in GE-related cancer cases and associated burdens in the coming decades attributed to demographic shifts, ageing populations, and dietary changes. The study underscores the urgency of mitigating GE and 3-MCPDE food contamination, bolstering public health awareness, and establishing safety guidelines.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yabani</LastName><ForeName>Daniel Sitsofe</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New Products Development Unit, Cocoa Research Institute of Ghana, New Tafo-Akim, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Systems Chemistry, Toxicology, and Risks Studies, Department of Food Science and Technology, College of Science, Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology, Kumasi, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ofosu</LastName><ForeName>Isaac Williams</ForeName><Initials>IW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Systems Chemistry, Toxicology, and Risks Studies, Department of Food Science and Technology, College of Science, Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology, Kumasi, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ankar-Brewoo</LastName><ForeName>Gloria Mathanda</ForeName><Initials>GM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Systems Chemistry, Toxicology, and Risks Studies, Department of Food Science and Technology, College of Science, Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology, Kumasi, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lutterodt</LastName><ForeName>Herman Erick</ForeName><Initials>HE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Systems Chemistry, Toxicology, and Risks Studies, Department of Food Science and Technology, College of Science, Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology, Kumasi, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Health Insights</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101488505</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1178-6302</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">3-MCPD ester</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">burden of disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dietary exposure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">glycidyl ester</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">human cancer risk</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39290370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11406649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/11786302241277628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_11786302241277628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO. Global Health Estimates: Leading Causes of Death, Cause-Specific Mortality, 2000–2019. The Global Health Observatory, WHO; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
WHO. Cancer. Accessed December 8, 2023. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cancer</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bray F, Laversanne M, Weiderpass E, Soerjomataram I. The ever-increasing importance of cancer as a leading cause of premature death worldwide. Cancer. 2021;127:3029-3030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34086348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. Risks for human health related to the presence of 3- and 2-monochloropropanediol (MCPD), and their fatty acid esters, and glycidyl fatty acid esters in food. EFSA J. 2016;14:1-159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beekmann K, Sloot SJ, Oey SB, van Leeuwen SPJ. MCPD esters and glycidyl esters in food supplements of fish oils, algae oils, and krill oils. Food Control. 2022;136:108865.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yabani DS, Ofosu IW, Ankar-Brewoo GM, Lutterodt HE. 3-monochloropropandiol and glycidyl esters in heat-processed oil-based food products: exposure and risk. Appl Food Res. 2024;4:100393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui X, Zhang L, Yang D, et al.. Occurrence of 3- and 2-monochloropropanediol esters in infant formulas in China and exposure assessment. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2021;38:1470-1480.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34229561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang L, Jing Z, Yibaina W, et al.. Dietary exposure to fatty acid esters of monochloropropanediols and glycidol of 2- to 3-year-old children attending nursery schools from two areas in China using the duplicate-diet collection method. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2021;38:70-80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33332977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González N, Marquès M, Calderón J, et al.. Occurrence and dietary intake of food processing contaminants (FPCs) in Catalonia, Spain. J Food Compost Anal. 2022;106:104272.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abraham K, Hielscher J, Kuhlmann J, Monien BH. Urinary excretion of 2/3-monochloropropanediol (2/3-MCPD) and 2,3-dihydroxypropylmercapturic acid (DHPMA) after a single high dose of fatty acid esters of 2/3-MCPD and glycidol: a controlled exposure study in humans. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2021;65:e2000735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33079463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Custodio-Mendoza JA, Carro AM, Lage-Yusty MA, et al.. Occurrence and exposure of 3-monochloropropanediol diesters in edible oils and oil-based foodstuffs from the Spanish market. Food Chem. 2019;270:214-222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30174037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M, Huang G, Wang TTY, Sun X, Yu L. 3-MCPD 1-palmitate induced tubular cell apoptosis in vivo via JNK/p53 pathways. Toxicol Sci. 2016;151:181-192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4914803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27008853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing H, Chen S, Wang X, Li J, Ren F. 3-Monochloropropane-1,2-diol causes spermatogenesis failure in male rats via Sertoli cell dysfunction but not testosterone reduction. Toxicol Lett. 2022;360:1-10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35063618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. Scientific opinion on the update of the risk assessment on 3-monochloropropane diol and its fatty acid esters. EFSA J. 2018;16:1-48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7009698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32625654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>JECFA. Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives: Eighty-Third Meeting - Evaluations of Contaminants. WHO; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IARC. Some Chemicals Present in Industrial and Consumer Products. Vol 101. WHO Press; 2012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4939416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24772663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beekman JK, Grassi K, Macmahon S, Beekman JK, Grassi K, Macmahon S. A updated occurrence of 3-monochloropropane-1, 2- diol esters (3-MCPD ) and glycidyl esters in infant formulas purchased in the United States between 2017 and 2019 and 2019. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2020;37:374-390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31917641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai HC, Yang YF, Pan PJ, Chen SC. Disease burden due to COVID-19 in Taiwan: disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) with implication of Monte Carlo simulations. J Infect Public Health. 2023;16:884-892.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10060021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37058869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quartey NKA, Haagsma JA, Jakobsen LS, Ofosu IW. Dietary acrylamide-linked burden of cancers in four sub-Sahara African countries: a review and data synthesis. Heliyon. 2024;10:e23075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10758739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38169883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakobsen LS, Granby K, Knudsen VK, Nauta M, Pires SM, Poulsen M. Burden of disease of dietary exposure to acrylamide in Denmark. Food Chem Toxicol. 2016;90:151-159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26845613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>IARC. Estimated number of new cases in 2020, all cancers, both sexes, all ages. Cancer Today. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shamseer L, Moher D, Ghersi D, et al.. Preferred reporting items for systematic review and explanation meta-analysis protocols (PRISMA-P) 2015: elaboration and explanation. BMJ. 2015:349:g7647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25555855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas J, Chandler J, Cumpston M, Li T, Page MJ, Welch VA. Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions. John Wiley &amp; Sons; 2019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10284251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31643080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Nie S-P, Zhou Y-Q, Xie M-Y, Carlo M. Exposure assessment of 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol esters from edible oils and fats in China. Food Chem Toxicol. 2015;75:8-13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25447762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan JC, He H, Ren R, Wang S. Monochloropropanediol in edible vegetable oils from Hangzhou market in China: occurrence and exposure risk assessment. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2021;38:1867-1874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34279183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung HY, Chung SWC, Chan BTP, Ho YY, Xiao Y. Dietary exposure of Hong Kong adults to fatty acid esters of 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2013;30:1508-1512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23862736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Chen J, Huang L, et al.. Occurrence and risk assessment of 3- and 2-monochloropropanediol (MCPD) esters in vegetable oils and related products from Zhejiang market. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2020;37:931-937.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32240043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Tsao CH, Chang YH, Lee WJ. Occurrence of thermally induced glycidyl esters and 3-monochloropropane-1,2-diol esters in refined oils and pressed oils manufactured by different processes and associated with human health risks in Taiwan. Food Chem. 2021;360:130053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34022517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadowska-Rociek A, Surma M, Cieślik E. Analysis of acrylamide, 3-monochloropropane-1,2-diol, its esters and glycidyl esters in carbohydrate-rixh products available on the Polish market. Rocz Panstw Zakl Hig. 2018;69:127-137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29766691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadowska-Rociek A. Monitoring of monochloropropanediol esters and glycidyl esters in different types of chocolates using the modified sample preparation approach. LWT. 2022;165:113692.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GEMS/Food. GEMS/Food Cluster Diets - 2013. WHO; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nemeth N, Rudnak I, Ymeri P, Fogarassy C. The role of cultural factors in sustainable food consumption-An investigation of the consumption habits among international students in Hungary. Sustainability (Switzerland). 2019;11:3052.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Principles and Methods for the Risk Assessment of Chemicals in Food. Environmental Health Criteria 240. WHO; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
IHME. GBD Compare. University of Washington. Accessed December 11, 2023. https://vizhub.healthdata.org/gbd-compare/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabih Q, Young J, Takabe K. Management of male breast cancer: the journey so far and future directions. World J Oncol. 2021;12:206-213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8734504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35059080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA. Guidelines for Exposure Assessment. EPA/600/Z-92/001. EPA; 1992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
OEHHA. No Significant Risk Level (NSRL) for the Proposition 65 Carcinogen Glycidol. 2010. Accessed December 11, 2023. https://oehha.ca.gov/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Liu J, Wang Y, Wei S. Cancer risk and disease burden of dietary acrylamide exposure in China, 2016. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf. 2022;238:113551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35489291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank. The World Bank Annual Report-2022. The World Bank Group, NW Washington; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GlobalData. Data and Insights: Taiwan. GlobalData Plc; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vardell E. Global health observatory data repository. Med Ref Serv Q. 2020;39:67-74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32069199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maertens A, Golden E, Luechtefeld TH, Hoffmann S, Tsaioun K, Hartung T. Probabilistic risk assessment – the keystone for the future of toxicology. ALTEX. 2022;39:3-29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8906258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35034131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osborne JW, Overbay A. The power of outliers (and why researchers should always check for them), practical assessment. Res Eval. 2004;9:1-12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Y. Per Capita Consumption of Major Foods in Urban Households in China in 2022, by Product. Statista Inc; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macmahon S, Begley TH, Diachenko GW. Occurrence of 3-MCPD and glycidyl esters in edible oils in the United States. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2013;30:2081-2092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24138540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makarenko MA, Malinkin AD, Bessonov VV, Bokov DO. Alkaline transesterification CG-MS/MS method of monochlorpropanediol and glycidyl esters’ determination in some edible fats, oils and fat blends on Russian market. Vopr Pitan. 2020;89:113-122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33476504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arisseto AP, Marcolino PFC, Vicente E. Determination of 3-monochloropropane-1,2-diol fatty acid esters in Brazilian vegetable oils and fats by an in-house validated method. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2014;31:1385-1392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24919798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng W, Liu G, Wang L, Liu Z. Glycidyl fatty acid esters in refined edible oils: a review on formation, occurrence, analysis, and elimination methods. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf. 2017;16:263-281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33371535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becalski A, Zhao T, Feng S, Lau BPY. A pilot survey of 2- and 3-monochloropropanediol and glycidol fatty acid esters in baby formula on the Canadian market 2012-2013. J Food Compost Anal. 2015;44:111-114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng WW, Liu G, Liu X. Formation of glycidyl fatty acid esters both in real edible oil during laboratory-scale refining and in chemical model during high temperature exposure. J Agric Food Chem. 2016;64:5919–5927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27319409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamikata K, Vicente E, Arisseto-Bragotto AP, de Oliveira Miguel AMR, Milani RF, Tfouni SAV. Occurrence of 3-MCPD, 2-MCPD and glycidyl esters in extra virgin olive oils, olive oils and oil blends and correlation with identity and quality parameters. Food Control. 2019;95:135-141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Q, Zhou P, Yang D. Chloropropanol and glycidyl esters content in edible vegetable oils in China in 2015-2017. Wei Sheng Yan Jiu. 2021;50:75-78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33517965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagy K, Sandoz L, Craft BD, Destaillats F. Mass-defect filtering of isotope signatures to reveal the source of chlorinated palm oil contaminants. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2011;28:1492-1500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21995762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Destaillats F, Craft BD, Sandoz L, Nagy K. Formation mechanisms of Monochloropropanediol (MCPD) fatty acid diesters in refined palm (Elaeis guineensis) oil and related fractions. Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess. 2011;29:29-37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22129209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lupo PJ, Spector LG. Cancer progress and priorities: childhood cancer. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2020;29:1081-1094.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9400945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32482635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White MC, Holman DM, Boehm JE, Peipins LA, Grossman M, Jane Henley S. Age and cancer risk. Am J Prev Med. 2014;46:S7-S15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4544764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24512933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bo L, Wang Y, Li Y, Wurpel JND, Huang Z, Chen ZS. The battlefield of chemotherapy in pediatric cancers. Cancers (Basel). 2023;15:1963.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10093214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37046624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzmaurice C, Allen C, Barber RM, et al.. Global, regional, and national cancer incidence, mortality, years of life lost, years lived with disability, and disability-adjusted life-years for 32 cancer groups, 1990 to 2015. JAMA Oncol. 2017;3:524.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6103527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27918777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siegel RL, Miller KD, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2016. CA Cancer J Clin. 2016;66:7-30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26742998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim HI, Lim H, Moon A. Sex differences in cancer: epidemiology, genetics and therapy. Biomol Ther (Seoul). 2018;26:335-342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6029678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29949843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farhana L, Nangia-Makker P, Arbit E, et al.. Bile acid: a potential inducer of colon cancer stem cells. Stem Cell Res Ther. 2016;7:181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5134122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27908290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao T, Tao Y, Li H, et al.. Cancer burden and risk in the Chinese population aged 55 years and above: a systematic analysis and comparison with the USA and Western Europe. J Glob Health. 2024;14:04014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10810324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38271210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson SS, Marks MA, Katki HA, et al.. Sex disparities in the incidence of 21 cancer types: quantification of the contribution of risk factors. Cancer. 2022;128:3531-3540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35934938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gańczak M, Miazgowski T, Kożybska M, et al.. Changes in disease burden in Poland between 1990–2017 in comparison with other Central European countries: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. PLoS One. 2020;15:e0226766.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7051048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32119685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aasa J, Vryonidis E, Abramsson-Zetterberg L, Törnqvist M. Internal doses of glycidol in children and estimation of associated cancer risk. Toxics. 2019;7:1-13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6468878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30717263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mihalache OA, Dall’Asta C. Food processing contaminants: dietary exposure to 3-MCPD and glycidol and associated burden of disease for Italian consumers. Environ Res. 2023;234:116559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37419202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zavala VA, Bracci PM, Carethers JM, Carvajal-Carmona L, Coggins NB, Cruz-Correa MR. Cancer health disparities in racial/ethnic minorities in the United States. Br J Cancer. 2021;124:315-332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7852513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32901135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>JECFA. Evaluation of Certain Contaminants in Food: Eighty-Third Report of the Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives. WHO Technical Report Series 1002. WHO; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Zheng R, Zhang S, et al.. Colorectal cancer burden and trends: comparison between China and major burden countries in the world. Chin J Cancer Res. 2021;33:1-10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7941684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33707923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostermeyer U, Merkle S, Karl H, Fritsche J. Free and bound MCPD and glycidyl esters in smoked and thermally treated fishery products of the German market. Eur Food Res Technol. 2021;247:1757-1769.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GBD 2019 Cancer Risk Factors Collaborators. The global burden of cancer attributable to risk factors, 2010–19: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2022;400:563-591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9395583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35988567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>