<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39296209</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Application of nano-urea in conventional flood-irrigated Boro rice in Bangladesh and nitrogen losses investigation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e37150</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e37150</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e37150</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37150</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Bangladesh stands third in global rice production while complete modernization of rice production is not fully enforced. The boon of nano agriculture might circumvent the challenge of increasing the yield with minimal ecological damage. Nanofertilizer might be one of the solutions to address the problem of modern agriculture confronting environmental hazards owing to the excessive use of synthetic fertilizers by farmers in Bangladesh. We synthesized nanourea by chemical co-precipitation (CP) and hydrothermal (HT) methods in an attempt to develop environmentally friendly nanofertilizers. We characterized the nanourea and confirmed the functionalization of nanohydroxyapatite (nHAP) with urea by scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM)/EDS mapping. The CP method produced particle dimensions of 45.62 nm for length and 14.16 nm for width. In comparison, the readings obtained through the HT method were around 74.69 nm and 20.44 nm for length and width, respectively. The field application of nanourea demonstrated impressive results, indicating a significant relationship between the particle size of nanourea and its impact on several agricultural factors. The grain yield using traditional synthetic fertilizer (urea) ranged from 6.47 to 6.52 t ha<sup>-1</sup> with a very low NUE of 35.8-36.34 %. Contrarily, the grain yield was found from 6.52 to 6.84 t ha<sup>-1</sup> and the obtained NUE ranged from 57.58 to 71.0 % using nanourea of the same concentration calibrated with traditional urea by two methods. Additionally, nanourea treatments having 25 % less nitrogen (N) provided higher total N (TN) in grain suggesting possible nutritional enrichment while checking the yield penalty and substantial increase in N use efficiency (NUE). However, further upscaling of this research on a field scale is necessary to confirm the findings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asif</LastName><ForeName>Md Abdullah Al</ForeName><Initials>MAA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soil Science, Bangladesh Agricultural University, Mymensingh, 2202, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahjabin</LastName><ForeName>Farah</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soil Science, Bangladesh Agricultural University, Mymensingh, 2202, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science, Western Sydney University, Richmond, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singha</LastName><ForeName>Sourav Kumar</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bangladesh Food Safety Authority, Dhaka, 1000, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahman Jahangir</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Mofizur</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soil Science, Bangladesh Agricultural University, Mymensingh, 2202, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoque</LastName><ForeName>Sheikh Manjura</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Materials Science Division, Atomic Energy Centre Dhaka, Dhaka, 1000, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EDS mapping</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hydroxyapatite (HAP)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">N use efficiency (NUE)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanourea</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39296209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)13181-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>FAO UN Report Global Hunger Numbers Rose to as Many as 828 Million in 2021. Newsroom. 2022 (who.int)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed A., Bakhtiar M.M. Boro rice procurement in Bangladesh: Implications for policy. International Food Policy Research Institute (IFPRI; Washington, DC: 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2499/p15738coll2.133724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chhipa H. Nanofertilizers and nanopesticides for agriculture. Environ. Chem. Lett. 2017;15:15–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo J.H., Liu X.J., Zhang Y., Shen J.L., Han W.X., Zhang W.F., Christie P., Goulding K.W.T., Vitousek P.M., Zhang F.S. Significant acidification in major Chinese croplands. Science. 2010;327(5968):1008–1010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20150447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tilman D., Cassman K.G., Matson P.A., Naylor R., Polasky S. Agricultural sustainability and intensive production practices. Nature. 2002;418(6898):671–677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12167873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W., Dou Z., He P., Ju X.-T., Powlson D., Chadwick D., Norse D., Lu Y.-L., Zhang Y., Wu L. New technologies reduce greenhouse gas emissions from nitrogenous fertilizer in China. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2013;110(21):8375–8380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3666697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23671096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai G.X., Chen D.L., Ding H., Pacholski A., Fan X.H., Zhu Z.L. Nitrogen losses from fertilizers applied to maize, wheat and rice in the North China Plain. Nutrient Cycl. Agroecosyst. 2002;63:187–195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X., Ma C., Zhou H., Liu Y., Huang X., Wang M., Cai Y., Su D., Muneer M.A., Guo M. Identifying the main crops and key factors determining the carbon footprint of crop production in China, 2001–2018. Resour. Conserv. Recycl. 2021;172</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li P., Lu J., Hou W., Pan Y., Wang Y., Khan M.R., Ren T., Cong R., Li X. Reducing nitrogen losses through ammonia volatilization and surface runoff to improve apparent nitrogen recovery of double cropping of late rice using controlled release urea. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Control Ser. 2017;24:11722–11733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28332086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang X.Q., Chen Y.X., Li H., Tian G.M., Ni W.Z., He M.M., Zhang Z.J. Modeling transport and fate of nitrogen from urea applied to a near-trench paddy field. Environ. Pollut. 2007;150(3):313–320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17374427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lakshman K., Chandrakala M., Prasad P.S., Babu G.P., Srinivas T., Naik N.R., Korah A. Liquid nano-urea: an emerging nano fertilizer substitute for conventional urea. Chronicle of Bioresource Management. 2022;6(Jun, 2):54–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeRosa M.C., Monreal C., Schnitzer M., Walsh R., Sultan Y. Nanotechnology in fertilizers. Nat. Nanotechnol. 2010;5(2) 91–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20130583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karunaratne V., Kottegoda N., De Alwis A. Nanotechnology in a world out of balance. J. Natl. Sci. Found. Sri Lanka. 2012;40(1):3–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kottegoda N., Munaweera I., Madusanka N., Karunaratne V. A green slow-release fertilizer composition based on urea-modified hydroxyapatite nanoparticles encapsulated wood. Curr. Sci. 2011:73–78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Morales J., Iafisco M., Delgado-López J.M., Sarda S., Drouet C. Progress on the preparation of nanocrystalline apatites and surface characterization: overview of fundamental and applied aspects. Prog. Cryst. Growth Char. Mater. 2013;59(1):1–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sprio S., Sandri M., Ruffini A., Adamiano A., Iafisco M., Dapporto M., Panseri S., Montesi M., Tampieri A. Advances in Ceramic Biomaterials. Elsevier; 2017. Tissue engineering and biomimetics with bioceramics; pp. 407–432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tampieri A., Iafisco M., Sprio S., Ruffini A., Panseri S., Montesi M., Adamiano A., Sandri M. Hydroxyapatite: from nanocrystals to hybrid nanocomposites for regenerative medicine. Handbook of Bioceramics and Biocomposites. 2016:119–144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kottegoda N., Sandaruwan C., Priyadarshana G., Siriwardhana A., Rathnayake U.A., Berugoda Arachchige D.M., Kumarasinghe A.R., Dahanayake D., Karunaratne V., Amaratunga G.A. Urea-hydroxyapatite nanohybrids for slow release of nitrogen. ACS Nano. 2017;11(2):1214–1221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28121129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brammer H., Antoine J., Kassam A.H., van Velthuizen H.T., Land resources appraisal of Bangladesh for agricultural development, Agroecological regions of Bangladesh (1988). Report 5: Land resources, v. 2-5: Land resources map and legend, Sherour - Jamalpur - Tangail (fao.org).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeney D.R., Nelson D.W. In: Agronomy Monographs. Page A.L., editor. American Society of Agronomy, Soil Science Society of America; 2015. Nitrogen-inorganic forms; pp. 643–698.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2134/agronmonogr9.2.2ed.c33</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poinern G.J.E., Brundavanam R., Le X.T., Djordjevic S., Prokic M., Fawcett D. Thermal and ultrasonic influence in the formation of nanometer scale hydroxyapatite bio-ceramic. Int. J. Nanomed. 2011:2083–2095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3215150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22114473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sagle L.B., Zhang Y., Litosh V.A., Chen X., Cho Y., Cremer P.S. Investigating the hydrogen-bonding model of urea denaturation. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2009;131(26):9304–9310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19527028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma B., Afonso L.O., Singh M.P., Soni U., Cahill D.M. Zinc-and magnesium-doped hydroxyapatite-urea nanohybrids enhance wheat growth and nitrogen uptake. Sci. Rep. 2022;12(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9663570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36376430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gyergyek S., Drofenik M., Makovec D. Oleic-acid-coated CoFe2O4 nanoparticles synthesized by co-precipitation and hydrothermal synthesis. Mater. Chem. Phys. 2012;133(1):515–522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang G., Lu C.-H., Yang H.-H. Novel Nanomaterials for Biomedical, Environmental and Energy Applications. 2019. Magnetic nanomaterials for magnetic bioanalysis; pp. 89–109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zabardasti A. Theoretical calculation of equilibrium constant for keto-enol tautomerism in cyanuric acid. Chem. Heterocycl. Compd. 2007;43:1344–1346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinne-Saffran E., Kinne R.K.H. Vitalism and synthesis of urea: from friedrich wöhler to hans A. Krebs. Am. J. Nephrol. 1999;19(2):290–294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10213830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar P., Gupta R.K., Pandey D.S. Half-sandwich arene ruthenium complexes: synthetic strategies and relevance in catalysis. Chem. Soc. Rev. 2014;43(2):707–733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24193103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jug K. On the development of semiempirical methods in the MO formalism. Theor. Chim. Acta. 1969;14(2):91–135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu X., Zhou X., Jing Y., Li Y. Electrochemical synthesis of urea on MBenes. Nat. Commun. 2021;12(1):4080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8253759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34215749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stradella L., Argentero M. A study of the thermal decomposition of urea, of related compounds and thiourea using DSC and TG-EGA. Thermochim. Acta. 1993;219:315–323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schaber P.M., Colson J., Higgins S., Thielen D., Anspach B., Brauer J. Thermal decomposition (pyrolysis) of urea in an open reaction vessel. Thermochim. Acta. 2004;424(1–2):131–142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FRG . vol. 1215. Bangladesh Agricultural Research Council (BARC); Farmgate, Dhaka: 2018. (Fertilizer Recommendation Guide-2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Khuzai A.H.G., Al-Juthery H.W.A. Effect of DAP fertilizer source and nano fertilizers (silicon and complete) spray on some growth and yield indicators of rice (Oryza sativa L. cv. Anber 33) IOP Conf. Ser. Earth Environ. Sci. 2020;553(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S.-L., Pu C., Ren Y.-X., Zhao X.-L., Zhao X., Chen F., Xiao X.-P., Zhang H.-L. Yield variation of double-rice in response to climate change in Southern China. Eur. J. Agron. 2016;81:161–168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong Y., Xie Y., Song Q., Zeng W. The relationship between meteorological factors and rice yield in Liuzhi special zone. Guizhou Agricultural Sciences. 2009;10:79–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye T., Li Y., Zhang J., Hou W., Zhou W., Lu J., Xing Y., Li X. Nitrogen, phosphorus, and potassium fertilization affects the flowering time of rice (Oryza sativa L.) Global Ecology and Conservation. 2019;20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qureshi A., Singh D.K., Dwivedi S. Nano-fertilizers: a novel way for enhancing nutrient use efficiency and crop productivity. Int. J. Curr. Microbiol. App. Sci. 2018;7(2):3325–3335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liscano J.F., Wilson C.E., Norman-Jr R.J., Slaton N.A. Arkansas Agricultural Experiment Station; Fayetteville, CA, USA: 2000. Zinc Availability to Rice from Seven Granular Fertilizers. vol. 963.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siddiqi K.S., Husen A. Plant response to engineered metal oxide nanoparticles. Nanoscale Res. Lett. 2017;12(1):1–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5293712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28168616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amanullah, Ullah H., Soliman Elshikh M., Alwahibi M.S., Alkahtani J., Muhammad A., Khalid S., Imran Nitrogen contents in soil, grains, and straw of hybrid rice differ when applied with different organic nitrogen sources. Agriculture. 2020;10(9):386.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deo H.R., Chandrakar T., Srivastava L.K., Nag N.K., Singh D.P., Thakur A. 2022. Effect of Nano-DAP on Yield, Nutrient Uptake and Nutrient Use Efficiency by Rice under Bastar Plateau.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behboudi F., Tahmasebi Sarvestani Z., Kassaee M.Z., Modares Sanavi S.A.M., Sorooshzadeh A. Improving growth and yield of wheat under drought stress via application of SiO2 nanoparticles. J. Agric. Sci. Technol. 2018;20(7):1479–1492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cakmak I. Tansley Review No. 111 Possible roles of zinc in protecting plant cells from damage by reactive oxygen species. New Phytol. 2000;146(2):185–205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33862977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dobermann A., Fairhurst T.H. Rice straw management. Better Crops International. 2002;16(1):7–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharmila R.C. Tamil Nadu Agricultural University; Coimbatore: 2010. Nutrient Release Pattern of Nano-Fertilizer Formulations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta C., Prakash D. Effect of nano-fertilizers on soil microflora. Ann. Plant Sci. 2020;9:3846–3859.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujita T., Takahashi C., Yoshida S., Shimizu H. Coated granular fertilizer capable of controlling the effect of temperature upon dissolution-out rate. Google Patents. 1983 https://patents.google.com/patent/US4369055A/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lunt O.R., Oertli J.J. Controlled release of fertilizer minerals by incapsulating membranes: II. Efficiency of recovery, influence of soil moisture, mode of application, and other considerations related to use. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J. 1962;26(6):584–587. doi: 10.2136/sssaj1962.03615995002600060020x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2136/sssaj1962.03615995002600060020x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solanki P., Bhargava A., Chhipa H., Jain N., Panwar J. Nano-fertilizers and their smart delivery system. Nanotechnologies in Food and Agriculture. 2015:81–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chhipa H., Joshi P. Nanofertilisers, nanopesticides and nanosensors in agriculture. Nanoscience in Food and Agriculture. 2016;1:247–282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uzzaman S.A. Bangladesh opens southeast asia's largest fertilizer factory. Confluence. 2023, November 12 https://theconfluence.blog/bangladesh-opens-southeast-asias-largest-fertilizer-factory/</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>