<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39298809</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-3573</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>281</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Talanta</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Talanta</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Ratiometric fluorescence sensing and discrimination of tetracycline analogs by using coumarin-embedded Eu-MOF nanosensor.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>126914</StartPage><MedlinePgn>126914</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.talanta.2024.126914</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0039-9140(24)01293-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>As widely used antibiotics, tetracycline residues exist in food and environmental media, which pose certain hidden dangers and negative effects on public health. Therefore, the sensing and discrimination of tetracycline analogs (TCs) have great significance for improving food safety and preventing environmental pollution. Herein, a 7-hydroxycoumarin-3-carboxylic acid-embedded Eu-MOF (HC@Eu-MOF) material was constructed and then developed for the detection of TCs. Upon addition of TCs, the synthesized sensor displays opposite fluorescence changes at two different wavelengths due to the simultaneous presence of the inner filter effect (IFE) and the antenna effect (AE), and achieves a stable ratio signal response within 90 s. In addition, six important tetracycline analogs, including chlortetracycline (CTC), oxytetracycline (OTC), tetracycline (TC), metacycline (MC), doxycycline (DC) and demeclocycline (DMC) can be discriminated with 100 % accuracy through the principal component analysis even in extremely complicated mixtures. Further, a smartphone-assisted portable device was applied for visual sensing of TCs. The as-developed platform possessed the characteristics of simple synthesis, fast response, high sensitivity, and high stability, which further lays a further foundation for the on-site visual detection and discrimination of TCs in real samples.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Peng-Xiang</ForeName><Initials>PX</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmaceutical Science, Hengyang Medical School, University of South China, Hengyang 421001, Hunan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yu-Ping</ForeName><Initials>YP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmaceutical Science, Hengyang Medical School, University of South China, Hengyang 421001, Hunan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Fangfang</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmaceutical Science, Hengyang Medical School, University of South China, Hengyang 421001, Hunan, China; Key Laboratory of Haikou Trauma, Key Laboratory of Hainan Trauma and Disaster Rescue, Key Laboratory of Emergency and Trauma, Ministry of Education, The First Affiliated Hospital of Hainan Medical University, Hainan Medical University, Haikou 571199, Hainan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Liu-Pan</ForeName><Initials>LP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmaceutical Science, Hengyang Medical School, University of South China, Hengyang 421001, Hunan, China. Electronic address: yanglp@usc.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Li-Li</ForeName><Initials>LL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmaceutical Science, Hengyang Medical School, University of South China, Hengyang 421001, Hunan, China; Department of Pharmacy, The First Affiliated Hospital, Hengyang Medical School, University of South China, Hengyang 421001, Hunan, China. Electronic address: wangll@usc.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Talanta</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2984816R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0039-9140</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39298809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2024.126914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0039-9140(24)01293-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>