<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39292296</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-2959</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>196</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental monitoring and assessment</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Monit Assess</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The human health risks assessment posed by the presence of heavy metals in the rice varieties available in the Neyshabur market.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>949</StartPage><MedlinePgn>949</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10661-024-12976-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The present study was designed to determine the levels of heavy metals (Cu, Pb, Ni, Cr, Zn, Mn, Cd, and Co), Mn, and As in Iranian-grown rice and imported rice consumed in Neyshabur City. For this research, 90 samples from 30 different brands widely consumed in this city were collected. The content of heavy metals and the health risks associated with their use were then studied. The study found that Zn (14.21 mg kg<sup>-1</sup>) had the highest content in Iranian and imported rice varieties, whereas Cd (0.02 mg kg<sup>-1</sup>) had the lowest value. The health risk assessment was also done in three scenarios and separately for two types of rice. The results showed that the total hazard quotient (i.e., THQ) was measured for all metals and all three scenarios, and for both types of rice, it is THQ &gt; 1, which indicates the risk of non-carcinogenic in rice. The cancer risk for three scenarios and two types of imported and Iranian rice is in the unsafe range for As (8.80 × 10<sup>-4</sup> to 7.00 × 10<sup>-3</sup>), Ni (4.60 × 10<sup>-4</sup> to 3.60 × 10<sup>-3</sup>) and Cr (2.20 × 10<sup>-4</sup> to 1.90 × 10<sup>-3</sup>) and negligible for Pb (1.09 × 10<sup>-6</sup> to 1.49 × 10<sup>-5</sup>) and Cd (7.83 × 10<sup>-6</sup> to 8.20 × 10<sup>-5</sup>).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature Switzerland AG.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramezani</LastName><ForeName>Amir M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Healthy Ageing Research Centre, Neyshabur University of Medical Sciences, Neyshabur, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Basic Medical Sciences, Neyshabur University of Medical Sciences, Neyshabur, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hassanabadi</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Naimabadi</LastName><ForeName>Abolfazl</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Neyshabur University of Medical Sciences, Neyshabur, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Javan</LastName><ForeName>Safoura</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Neyshabur University of Medical Sciences, Neyshabur, Iran. safoora_javan@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Monit Assess</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8508350</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0167-6369</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D019216">Metals, Heavy</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012989">Soil Pollutants</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019216" MajorTopicYN="Y">Metals, Heavy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012275" MajorTopicYN="Y">Oryza</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007492" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Iran</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018570" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Contamination</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012989" MajorTopicYN="Y">Soil Pollutants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="Y">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hazard quotient</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health risk assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Heavy metals</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neyshabur City</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rice</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39292296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-024-12976-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10661-024-12976-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adila Omar, N., Mangala Praveena, S., Zaharin Aris, A., &amp; Hashim, Z. (2015). Bioavailability of heavy metal in cooked rice and health risk assessment using in vitro digestion model. International Journal of Sciences: Basic and Applied Research, 4531, 358–367. https://gssrr.org/index.php/JournalOfBasicAndApplied/article/view/3296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Yousuf, M. H., El-Shahawi, M. S., &amp; Al-Ghais, S. M. (2000). Trace metals in liver, skin and muscle of Lethrinus lentjan fish species in relation to body length and sex. Science of the Total Environment,256(2–3), 87–94. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0048-9697(99)00363-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0048-9697(99)00363-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baruah, S. G., Ahmed, I., Das, B., Ingtipi, B., Boruah, H., Gupta, S. K., et al. (2021). Heavy metal(loid)s contamination and health risk assessment of soil-rice system in rural and peri-urban areas of lower brahmaputra valley, northeast India. Chemosphere,266, 129150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.129150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.129150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell, R. (2016). Micronutrients. In P. J. W. Zed Rengel, &amp; I. Cakmak (Eds.), Marschner’s mineral nutrition of plants (4th ed., pp. 1–23). Academic Press</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellassoued, K., Hamza, A., Van Pelt, J., &amp; Elfeki, A. (2013). Seasonal variation of Sarpa salpa fish toxicity, as related to phytoplankton consumption, accumulation of heavy metals, lipids peroxidation level in fish tissues and toxicity upon mice. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 185(2), 1137–1150. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10661-012-2621-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-012-2621-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brus, D. J., Li, Z., Song, J., Koopmans, G. F., Temminghoff, E. J. M., Yin, X., et al. (2009). Predictions of spatially averaged cadmium contents in rice grains in the Fuyang valley, P.R. China. Journal of Environmental Quality,38(3), 1126–1136. https://doi.org/10.2134/jeq2008.0228</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2134/jeq2008.0228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, Z., Mou, R., Cao, Z., Lin, X., Xu, P., Chen, Z., et al. (2017). Nickel in milled rice (Oryza sativa L.) from the three main rice-producing regions in China. Food Additives and Contaminants: Part B Surveillance, 10(1), 69–77. https://doi.org/10.1080/19393210.2016.1250822</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19393210.2016.1250822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandorkar, S., &amp; Deota, P. (2013). Heavy metal content of foods and health risk assessment in the study population of Vadodara. Current World Environment Journal, 8(2), 291–297. https://doi.org/10.12944/cwe.8.2.15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheraghi, M., Mosaed, H. P., Lorestani, B., &amp; Yousefi, N. (2012). Heavy metal contamination in some rice samples. Electronic Journal of Environmental, Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 11, 424–432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codex Alimentarius International Food Standard. (2023). General standard for contaminants and toxins in food and feed. CXS 193-1995. https://www.fao.org/fao-who-codexalimentarius/thematic-areas/contaminants/en/ . Accessed 4 July 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhankhar, R., &amp; Hooda, A. (2011). Fungal biosorption-an alternative to meet the challenges of heavy metal pollution in aqueous solutions. Environmental Technology,32(5), 467–491. https://doi.org/10.1080/09593330.2011.572922</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09593330.2011.572922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhevagi, P., Ramya, A., Priyatharshini, S., Sindhuja, M., &amp; Avudainayagam, S. (2021). Bioavailable forms of heavy metals from rice samples and its potential health risk assessment. Journal of Experimental Biology and Agricultural Sciences,9(1), 25–35. https://doi.org/10.18006/2021.9(1).25.35</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djahed, B., Kermani, M., Farzadkia, M., Taghavi, M., &amp; Norzaee, S. (2020). Exposure to heavy metal contamination and probabilistic health risk assessment using Monte Carlo simulation: A study in the Southeast Iran. Journal of Environmental Health Science and Engineering,18(2), 1217–1226. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40201-020-00539-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40201-020-00539-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djahed, B., Taghavi, M., Farzadkia, M., Norzaee, S., &amp; Miri, M. (2018). Stochastic exposure and health risk assessment of rice contamination to the heavy metals in the market of Iranshahr, Iran. Food and Chemical Toxicology,115(December 2017), 405–412. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2018.03.040</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2018.03.040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fangmin, C., Ningchun, Z., Haiming, X., Yi, L., Wenfang, Z., Zhiwei, Z., &amp; Mingxue, C. (2006). Cadmium and lead contamination in japonica rice grains and its variation among the different locations in southeast China. Science of the Total Environment,359(1–3), 156–166. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2005.05.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2005.05.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filazi, A., Baskaya, R., Kum, C., &amp; Hismiogullari, S. E. (2003). Metal concentrations in tissues of the Black Sea fish Mugil auratus from Sinop-Icliman, Turkey. Human and Experimental Toxicology,22(2), 85–87. https://doi.org/10.1191/0960327103ht323oa</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1191/0960327103ht323oa</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, J., Zhou, Q., Liu, J., Liu, W., Wang, T., Zhang, Q., &amp; Jiang, G. (2008). High levels of heavy metals in rice (Oryza sativa L.) from a typical E-waste recycling area in southeast China and its potential risk to human health. Chemosphere,71(7), 1269–1275. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2007.11.065</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2007.11.065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, Q. L., Li, L., Achal, V., Jiao, A. Y., &amp; Liu, Y. (2015). Concentrations of heavy metals and arsenic in market rice grain and their potential health risks to the population of Fuzhou. China. Human and Ecological Risk Assessment, 21(1), 117–128. https://doi.org/10.1080/10807039.2014.884398</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, Z., Fu, W., Zhang, M., Zhao, K., Tunney, H., &amp; Guan, Y. (2016). Potentially hazardous metals contamination in soil-rice system and it’s spatial variation in Shengzhou City, China. Journal of Geochemical Exploration, 167, 62–69. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gexplo.2016.05.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gexplo.2016.05.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghazanfarirad, N., Dehghan, K., Fakhernia, M., Rahmanpour, F., Bolouki M., Zeynali, F. et al. (2014). Determination of lead, cadmium and arsenic metals in imported rice into the West Azerbaijan Province, Northwest of Iran. Agricultural and Food Sciences (pp. 452–456). Environmental Science. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Determination-of-Cadmium-%2C-Lead-%2C-Copper-and-in-Raw-K./a88f7692b3cdf76fa6afc0069c1dc4cb7779add8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griboff, J., Wunderlin, D. A., &amp; Monferran, M. V. (2017). Metals, As and Se determination by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry (ICP-MS) in edible fish collected from three eutrophic reservoirs. Their consumption represents a risk for human health? Microchemical Journal,130, 236–244. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.microc.2016.09.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2016.09.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, Y., Huang, M., You, W., Cai, L., Hong, Y., Xiao, Q., et al. (2022). Spatial analysis and risk assessment of heavy metal pollution in rice in Fujian Province, China. Frontiers in Environmental Science,10, 1–14. https://doi.org/10.3389/fenvs.2022.1082340</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fenvs.2022.1082340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamid, A., Wasim, A., Azfar, A., Amjad, R., &amp; Nazir, R. (2020). Monitoring and health risk assessment of selected trace metals in wheat rice and soil samples. Food Science and Technology (Brazil), 40(4), 917–923. https://doi.org/10.1590/fst.23319</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/fst.23319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hang, X., Wang, H., Zhou, J., Ma, C., Du, C., &amp; Chen, X. (2009). Risk assessment of potentially toxic element pollution in soils and rice (Oryza sativa) in a typical area of the Yangtze River Delta. Environmental Pollution,157(8–9), 2542–2549. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2009.03.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2009.03.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harindintwali, J. D., Zhou, J., Yang, W., Gu, Q., &amp; Yu, X. (2020). Biochar-bacteria-plant partnerships: Eco-solutions for tackling heavy metal pollution. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety,204(July), 111020. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.111020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.111020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, B., Shao, S., Fu, T., Fu, Z., Zhou, Y., Li, Y., et al. (2020). Composite assessment of human health risk from potentially toxic elements through multiple exposure routes: A case study in farmland in an important industrial city in East China. Journal of Geochemical Exploration,210(July 2019), 106443. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gexplo.2019.106443</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gexplo.2019.106443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Y., Chen, Q., Deng, M., Japenga, J., Li, T., Yang, X., &amp; He, Z. (2018). Heavy metal pollution and health risk assessment of agricultural soils in a typical peri-urban area in southeast China. Journal of Environmental Management,207, 159–168. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2017.10.072</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2017.10.072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Z., Pan, X. D., Wu, P. G., Han, J. L., &amp; Chen, Q. (2013). Health risk assessment of heavy metals in rice to the population in Zhejiang, China. Plos ONE, 8(9), 1–6. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0075007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ihedioha, J. N., Ujam, O. T., Nwuche, C. O., Ekere, N. R., &amp; Chime, C. C. (2016). Assessment of heavy metal contamination of rice grains (Oryza sativa) and soil from Ada field, Enugu, Nigeria: Estimating the human healtrisk. Human and Ecological Risk Assessment: An International Journal, 22(8), 1665–1677. https://doi.org/10.1080/10807039.2016.1217390</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10807039.2016.1217390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Javan, S., Eskandari, M., Babaei, Z., Aminisani, N., Ahmadi, R., &amp; Ramezani, A. M. (2023). Separation and identification of snuff constituents by using GC–MS and ICP-OES as well as health risk assessment of some existing heavy metals. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment,195(12), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10661-023-12121-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-023-12121-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karadede, H., Oymak, S. A., &amp; Ünlü, E. (2004). Heavy metals in mullet, Liza abu, and catfish, Silurus triostegus, from the Atatürk Dam Lake (Euphrates), Turkey. Environment International,30(2), 183–188. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0160-4120(03)00169-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0160-4120(03)00169-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanam, R., Kumar, A., Nayak, A. K., Shahid, M., Tripathi, R., Vijayakumar, S., et al. (2020). Metal(loid)s (As, Hg, Se, Pb and Cd) in paddy soil: Bioavailability and potential risk to human health. Science of the Total Environment,699, 134330. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134330</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kukusamude, C., Sricharoen, P., Limchoowong, N., and Kongsri, S. (2021). Heavy metals and probabilistic risk assessment via rice consumption in Thailand. Food Chemistry, 334(May 2020), 127402. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.127402</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwon, J. C., Nejad, Z. D., &amp; Jung, M. C. (2017). Arsenic and heavy metals in paddy soil and polished rice contaminated by mining activities in Korea. CATENA,148, 92–100. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2016.01.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.catena.2016.01.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Fang, F., Wu, M., Kuang, Y., &amp; Wu, H. (2018). Heavy metal contamination and health risk assessment in soil-rice system near Xinqiao mine in Tongling city, Anhui province, China. Human and Ecological Risk Assessment, 24(3), 743–753. https://doi.org/10.1080/10807039.2017.1398631</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10807039.2017.1398631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lien, K. W., Pan, M. H., and Ling, M. P. (2021). Levels of heavy metal cadmium in rice (Oryza sativa L.) produced in Taiwan and probabilistic risk assessment for the Taiwanese population. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 28(22), 28381–28390.  https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-020-11902-w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, A., Hamel, C., Hamilton, R. I., Ma, B. L., and Smith, D. L. (2000). Acquisition of Cu, Zn, Mn and Fe by mycorrhizal maize (Zea mays L.) grown in soil at different P and micronutrient levels. Mycorrhiza, 9(6), 331–336.  https://doi.org/10.1007/s005720050277</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, X., Song, Q., Tang, Y., Li, W., Xu, J., Wu, J., et al. (2013). Human health risk assessment of heavy metals in soil–vegetable system: A multi-medium analysis. Science of the Total Environment,463–464, 530–540. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.06.064</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.06.064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozowicka, B., Abzeitova, E., Sagitov, A., Kaczynski, P., Toleubayev, K., &amp; Li, A. (2015). Studies of pesticide residues in tomatoes and cucumbers from Kazakhstan and the associated health risks. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment,187(10), 609. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10661-015-4818-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-015-4818-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lü, Q., Xiao, Q., Wang, Y., Wen, H., Han, B., Zheng, X., &amp; Lin, R. (2021). Risk assessment and hotspots identification of heavy metals in rice: A case study in Longyan of Fujian province, China. Chemosphere,270, 128626. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128626</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, L., Wang, L., Tang, J., &amp; Yang, Z. (2017). Arsenic speciation and heavy metal distribution in polished rice grown in Guangdong Province, Southern China. Food Chemistry,233, 110–116. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.04.097</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.04.097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manzurul Hassan, M. (2018). Arsenic in groundwater : Poisoning and risk assessment (1st ed.). CRC Press.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1201/9781315117034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massa, N., Andreucci, F., Poli, M., Aceto, M., Barbato, R., &amp; Berta, G. (2010). Screening for heavy metal accumulators amongst autochtonous plants in a polluted site in Italy. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety,73(8), 1988–1997. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2010.08.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2010.08.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrabi, A., Zareiyan, M., Maryamabadi, A., Ghajarbeygi, P., Zarei, H., Ramezani, H., et al. (2023). Assessment of heavy metals in rice brands and their potential risk on public health. Journal of Chemical Health Risks, 14(2), 309–318. https://sanad.iau.ir/journal/jchr/Article/1087835</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirlohi, M., Morekian, R., Azadbakht, L., &amp; Maracy, M. (2013). Heavy metal distribution frequency in Iranian and imported rice varieties marketed in central Iran, Yazd, 2012. International Journal of Environmental Health Engineering,2(1), 36. https://doi.org/10.4103/2277-9183.122419</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/2277-9183.122419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naimabadi, A., Gholami, A., &amp; Ramezani, A. M. (2021). Determination of heavy metals and health risk assessment in indoor dust from different functional areas in Neyshabur. Iran. Indoor and Built Environment, 30(10), 1781–1795. https://doi.org/10.1177/1420326X20963378</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1420326X20963378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naseri, M., Vazirzadeh, A., Kazemi, R., &amp; Zaheri, F. (2015). Concentration of some heavy metals in rice types available in Shiraz market and human health risk assessment. Food Chemistry,175, 243–248. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.11.109</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.11.109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parmar, M., &amp; Singh Thakur, L. (2013). Heavy metal Cu, Ni and Zn: Toxicity, health hazards and their removal techniques by low cost adsorbents: A short overview. International Journal of Plant, Animal and Environmetal Sciences, 3(3), 143–157. https://www.researchgate.net/publication/271281628_Heavy_metal_Cu_Ni_and_Zn_Toxicity_health_hazards_and_their_removal_techniques_by_low_cost_adsorbents_A_short_overview</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, F., Li, J., Gong, Z., Yue, B., Wang, X., Manyande, A., &amp; Du, H. (2022). Investigation of bioaccumulation and human health risk assessment of heavy metals in Crayfish (Procambarus clarkii) farming with a rice-crayfish-based coculture breeding modes. Foods, 11(3), 1–15. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11030261</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11030261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pirsaheb, M., Hadei, M., &amp; Sharafi, K. (2021). Human health risk assessment by Monte Carlo simulation method for heavy metals of commonly consumed cereals in Iran- Uncertainty and sensitivity analysis. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis,96, 103697. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfca.2020.103697</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2020.103697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Praveena, S. M., &amp; Omar, N. A. (2017). Heavy metal exposure from cooked rice grain ingestion and its potential health risks to humans from total and bioavailable forms analysis. Food Chemistry,235, 203–211. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.05.049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.05.049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian, Y., Chen, C., Zhang, Q., Li, Y., Chen, Z., &amp; Li, M. (2010). Concentrations of cadmium, lead, mercury and arsenic in Chinese market milled rice and associated population health risk. Food Control, 21(12 SUPPL.), 1757–1763. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2010.08.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2010.08.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanaei, F., Amin, M. M., Alavijeh, Z. P., Esfahani, R. A., Sadeghi, M., Bandarrig, N. S., et al. (2021). Health risk assessment of potentially toxic elements intake via food crops consumption: Monte Carlo simulation-based probabilistic and heavy metal pollution index. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 28(2), 1479–1490. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-020-10450-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-10450-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satarug, S., Garrett, S. H., Sens, M. A., &amp; Sens, D. A. (2010). Cadmium, environmental exposure, and health outcomes. Environmental Health Perspectives,118(2), 182–190. https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.0901234</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.0901234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sen Gupta, S., Baksi, A., Subramanian, V., &amp; Pradeep, T. (2016). Cooking-induced corrosion of metals. ACS Sustainable Chemistry and Engineering,4(9), 4781–4787. https://doi.org/10.1021/acssuschemeng.6b00980</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.6b00980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharafi, K., Nodehi, R. N., Yunesian, M., Hossein Mahvi, A., Pirsaheb, M., &amp; Nazmara, S. (2019). Human health risk assessment for some toxic metals in widely consumed rice brands (domestic and imported) in Tehran, Iran: Uncertainty and sensitivity analysis. Food Chemistry,277, 145–155. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.10.090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.10.090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, M., Garg, V. K., Gautam, Y. P., &amp; Kumar, A. (2014). Soil to grain transfer factors of heavy metals in rice and health risk analysis in the vicinity of Narora Atomic Power Station (NAPS), Narora, India. Journal of Scientific and Industrial Research, 73(3), 181–186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Z., Hu, Y., &amp; Cheng, H. (2020). Public health risk of toxic metal(loid) pollution to the population living near an abandoned small-scale polymetallic mine. Science of the Total Environment,718, 137434. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.137434</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.137434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, L., Deng, S., Tan, D., Long, J., &amp; Lei, M. (2019). Heavy metal distribution, translocation, and human health risk assessment in the soil-rice system around Dongting Lake area, China. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 26, 17655–17665</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theobald, H. (2003). Metal contamination of food: Its significance for food quality and human health. In C. Reilly (Ed.), Nutrition Bulletin (3rd ed., Vol. 28). Oxford University Press. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1467-3010.2003.00356.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uddin, M. M., Cassim, M., Zakeel, M., &amp; Zavahir, J. S. (2021). Heavy metal accumulation in rice and aquatic plants used as human food: A general review. Toxics, 9(360), 1–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA. (2000). Risk-based concentration table. United States Environmental Protection Agency.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA. (2001). Risk assessment guidance for superfund: Volume III Part A, Process for conducting probabilistic risk assessment. Washington, DC: United States Environmental Protection Agency</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA. (2005). Human health risk assessment protocol for hazardous waste combustion facilities. Office of Solid Waste. United States Environmental Protection Agency, 530-R-05–006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA. (2017). Integrated risk information system (IRIS). https://www.epa.gov/iris . Accessed 4 July 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Ma, L., &amp; Yang, Z. (2018). Spatial variation and risk assessment of heavy metals in paddy rice from Hunan Province, Southern China. International Journal of Environmental Science and Technology,15(7), 1561–1572. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13762-017-1504-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13762-017-1504-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z., Qin, H., &amp; Liu, X. (2019). Health risk assessment of heavy metals in the soil-water-rice system around the Xiazhuang uranium mine, China. Environmental Science and Pollution Research,26(6), 5904–5912. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-018-3955-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-3955-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe, T., Shimbo, S., Moon, C. S., Zhang, Z. W., &amp; Ikeda, M. (1996). Cadmium contents in rice samples from various areas in the world. Science of the Total Environment,184(3), 191–196. https://doi.org/10.1016/0048-9697(96)05100-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0048-9697(96)05100-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfgang, M. (2013). Zinc biochemistry: From a single zinc enzyme to a key element of life. Advances in Nutrition, 4(1), 82–91. https://doi.org/10.3945/an.112.003038.82</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3945/an.112.003038.82</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, X., Luo, P., Li, S., Zhang, Q., &amp; Sun, D. (2022). Distributions of heavy metals in rice and corn and their health risk assessment in Guizhou Province. Bulletin of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology,108(5), 926–935. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00128-021-03407-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00128-021-03407-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zakaria, Z., Zulkafflee, N. S., Mohd Redzuan, N. A., Selamat, J., Ismail, M. R., Praveena, S. M., et al. (2021). Understanding potential heavy metal contamination, absorption, translocation and accumulation in rice and human health risks. Plants, 10(6).  https://doi.org/10.3390/plants10061070</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zazouli, M., Bandpei, A., Ebrahimi, M., &amp; Izanloo, H. (2010). Investigation of cadmium and lead contents in Iranian rice cultivated in Babol region. Asian Journal of Chemistry, 22, 1369–1376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zazouli, M. A., Shorkzadeh, M., &amp; Ebrahimi, M. (2008). Cadmium and lead contents in raw and boiled rice (Oryza sativa) in the North of Iran. Toxicology Letters,180, S207. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxlet.2008.06.251</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2008.06.251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, F., Wei, W., Li, M., Huang, R., Yang, F., &amp; Duan, Y. (2015). Heavy metal contamination in rice-producing soils of Hunan province, China and potential health risks. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health,12(12), 15584–15593. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph121215005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph121215005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z., Zhang, N., Li, H., Lu, Y., &amp; Yang, Z. (2020). Potential health risk assessment for inhabitants posed by heavy metals in rice in Zijiang River basin, Hunan Province, China. Environmental Science and Pollution Research,27(19), 24013–24024. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-020-08568-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-08568-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, F. J. (2020). Strategies to manage the risk of heavy metal(loid) contamination in agricultural soils. Frontiers of Agricultural Science and Engineering, 7(3), 333–338. https://doi.org/10.15302/J-FASE-2020335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, K., Liu, X., Xu, J., &amp; Selim, H. M. (2010). Heavy metal contaminations in a soil-rice system: Identification of spatial dependence in relation to soil properties of paddy fields. Journal of Hazardous Materials,181(1–3), 778–787. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2010.05.081</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2010.05.081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>