<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39319130</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of commercial DNA kits for allergen detection of celery in food matrices.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e36824</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e36824</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e36824</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36824</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>For correct allergen risk management by industry, retail and food safety authorities, sensitive and reliable fast allergen detection methods are required, even more when precautionary allergen labelling based on reference doses will be implemented in legislation. This study aimed to perform a comparative assessment of three commercially available quantitative or qualitative test kits, for DNA analysis of celery in food products. Five product groups, representing different sectors of the AOAC food-matrix triangle, being (plant-based) meat products, snacks, sauces, dried herbs and spices, and smoothies, were identified to potentially contain celery. From each group, blank and incurred (labelled to contain celery) food products were selected, of which the blank food products were additionally spiked with low protein levels of celery prior to qPCR assessment. Results show that the assessed test kits perform according to their specifications, however, a clear influence of the matrix on the detection ability of celery was observed. In addition, quantification of the amount of celery in the different food products showed to be challenging in all food product groups using the two quantification kits.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Voorhuijzen-Harink</LastName><ForeName>Marleen M</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University and Research, P.O. Box 230, 6700 AE, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fronen</LastName><ForeName>Bas J</ForeName><Initials>BJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University and Research, P.O. Box 230, 6700 AE, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Willemsen</LastName><ForeName>Linda</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University and Research, P.O. Box 230, 6700 AE, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koops</LastName><ForeName>Andries</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University and Research, P.O. Box 230, 6700 AE, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoek-van den Hil</LastName><ForeName>Elise F</ForeName><Initials>EF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University and Research, P.O. Box 230, 6700 AE, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smits</LastName><ForeName>Nathalie G E</ForeName><Initials>NGE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen University and Research, P.O. Box 230, 6700 AE, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39319130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)12855-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Sicherer S.H., Sampson H.A. Food allergy: a review and update on epidemiology, pathogenesis, diagnosis, prevention, and management. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 2018;141(1):41–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29157945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue D., Ciccolini A., Avilla E., Waserman S. Food allergy and anaphylaxis. J. Asthma Allergy. 2018:111–120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6016602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29950871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO and WHO for the United Nations . 2018. Codex Alimentarius – General Standard for the Labelling of Prepackaged Foods. CXS 1-1985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission . 2011. Commission Regulation (EU) No 1169/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 25 October 2011 on the Provision of Food Information to Consumers.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Remington B.C., Baumert J., Blom W.M., Bucchini L., Buck N., Crevel R., Walker M. 2022. Practical Guidance on the Application of Food Allergen Quantitative Risk Assessment.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senyuva H.Z., Jones I.B., Sykes M., Baumgartner S. A critical review of the specifications and performance of antibody and DNA-based methods for detection and quantification of allergens in foods. Food Addit. Contam. 2019;36(4):507–547.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30856064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linacero R., Sanchiz A., Ballesteros I., Cuadrado C. Application of real-time PCR for tree nut allergen detection in processed foods. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2020;60(7):1077–1093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30638046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prado M., Ortea I., Vial S., Rivas J., Calo-Mata P., Barros-Velázquez J. Advanced DNA-and protein-based methods for the detection and investigation of food allergens. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2016;56(15):2511–2542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25848852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frigerio J., Pellesi R., Mezzasalma V., De Mattia F., Galimberti A., Lambertini F., Labra M. Development of a DNA barcoding-like approach to detect mustard allergens in wheat flours. Genes. 2019;10(3):234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6470546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30893940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cau S., Tilocca M.G., Spanu C., Soro B., Tedde T., Salza S.…Mudadu A.G. Detection of celery (Apium graveolens) allergen in foods of animal and plant origin by droplet digital PCR assay. Food Control. 2021;130</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dölle-Bierke S., Höfer V., Francuzik W., Näher A.F., Bilo M.B., Cichocka-Jarosz E.…Worm M. Food-induced anaphylaxis: data from the European anaphylaxis registry. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. Pract. 2023;11(7):2069–2079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36990430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission . 2009. Commission Regulation (EC) No 152/2009 of 27 January 2009 Laying Down the Methods of Sampling and Analysis for the Official Control of Feed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krul E.S. Calculation of nitrogen‐to‐protein conversion factors: a review with a focus on soy protein. J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc. 2019;96(4):339–364.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hupfer C., Waiblinger H.-U., Busch U. Development and validation of a real-time PCR detection method for celery in food. Eur. Food Res. Technol. 2007;225:329–335. 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staats M., Arulandhu A.J., Gravendeel B., Holst-Jensen A., Scholtens I., Peelen T.…Kok E. Advances in DNA metabarcoding for food and wildlife forensic species identification. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2016;408:4615–4630.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4909793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27178552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kress J.W., Erickson D.L. A two-locus global DNA barcode for land plants: the coding rbcL gene complements the non-coding trnH-psbA spacer region. PLoS One. 2007;2(6) doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0000508.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1876818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17551588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fazekas A.J., Kuzmina M.L., Newmaster S.G., Hollingsworth P.M. DNA barcoding methods for land plants. DNA barcodes: Methods and protocols. 2012:223–252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22684959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen S., Yao H., Han J., Liu C., Song J., Shi L., Zhu Y., Ma X., Gao T., Pang X., Luo K., Li Y., Li X., Jia X., Lin Y., Leon C. Validation of the ITS2 region as a novel DNA barcode for identifying medicinal plant species. PLoS One. 2010;5(1) doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0008613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2799520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20062805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y., Skinner D., Liang G., Hulbert S. Phylogenetic analysis of Sorghum and related taxa using internal transcribed spacers of nuclear ribosomal DNA. Theoretical and Applied Genetics. 1994;89(1):26–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24177765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White T.J., Bruns T., Lee S.J.W.T., Taylor J. Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal RNA genes for phylogenetics. PCR protocols: a guide to methods and applications. 1990;18(1):315–322.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taberlet P., Gielly L., Pautou G., Bouvet J. Universal primers for amplification of three non-coding regions of chloroplast DNA. Plant Mol. Biol. 1991;17(5):1105–1109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1932684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arulandhu A.J., Staats M., Hagelaar R., Voorhuijzen M.M., Prins T.W., Scholtens I.…Kok E. Development and validation of a multi-locus DNA metabarcoding method to identify endangered species in complex samples. GigaScience. 2017;6(10):gix080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5632295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29020743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson M., Ellison S.L., Wood R. The International Harmonized Protocol for the proficiency testing of analytical chemistry laboratories (IUPAC Technical Report) Pure Appl. Chem. 2006;78(1):145–196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 13528 . 2015. Statistical Methods for Use in Proficiency Testing by Interlaboratory Comparison.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustin S.A., Benes V., Garson J.A., Hellemans J., Huggett J., Kubista M.…Wittwer C.T. 2009. The MIQE Guidelines: Minimum Information for Publication of Quantitative Real-Time PCR Experiments.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19246619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broeders S., Huber I., Grohmann L., Berben G., Taverniers I., Mazzara M.…Morisset D. Guidelines for validation of qualitative real-time PCR methods. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2014;37(2):115–126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbau-Piednoir E., Botteldoorn N., Yde M., Mahillon J., Roosens N.H. Development and validation of qualitative SYBR® Green real-time PCR for detection and discrimination of Listeria spp. and Listeria monocytogenes. Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2013;97:4021–4037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3627020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23086339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchesi U., Mazzara M., Broll H., Giacomo M., Grohmann L., Herau V.…Woll K. European network of GMO laboratories (ENGL) 2015 definition of minimum performance requirements for analytical methods of GMO testing. 2015. http://gmõcrl.jrc.ec.europa.eu/doc/Min_Perf_Requirements_Analytical_methods.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulikkottil Rajan D. Extraction, isolation, and characterization techniques of structural proteins. Fish Structural Proteins and its Derivatives: Functionality and Applications. 2024:37–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Pinto A., Forte V., Guastadisegni M.C., Martino C., Schena F.P., Tantillo G. A comparison of DNA extraction methods for food analysis. Food Control. 2007;18(1):76–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pafundo S., Gullì M., Marmiroli N. Comparison of DNA extraction methods and development of duplex PCR and real-time PCR to detect tomato, carrot, and celery in food. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2011;59(19):10414–10424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21894887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz-Villalba A., Ruijter J.M., van den Hoff M.J. Use and misuse of Cq in qPCR data analysis and reporting. Life. 2021;11(6):496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8229287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34072308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platteau C., De Loose M., De Meulenaer B., Taverniers I. Detection of allergenic ingredients using real-time PCR: a case study on hazelnut (Corylus avellena) and soy (Glycine max) J. Agric. Food Chem. 2011;59(20):10803–10814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21888436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayer W., Schuller M., Viehauser M.C., Hochegger R. Quantification of the allergen soy (Glycine max) in food using digital droplet PCR (ddPCR) European Food Research and Technology. 2019;245:499–509. Owen, L. and J. Gilbert, Proficiency testing for quality assurance of allergens methods. Analytical and bioanalytical chemistry, 2009. 395(1): pp. 147–153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO and WHO Risk assessment of food allergens - Part 2: review and establish threshold levels in foods for the priority allergens. Meeting report. Food Safety and Quality Series. 2022;15 doi: 10.4060/cc2946en. Rome.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4060/cc2946en</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holzhauser T. Protein or no protein? Opportunities for DNA-based detection of allergenic foods. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2018;66(38):9889–9894.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30180550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smits N., Voorhuijzen-Harink M., Cochrane S., Robouch P., Cubero Leon E., Catapan F., Ravenhorst M.…Hoek-van den Hil E. Report Wageningen Food Safety Research. 2024. Guidance on how to analyse unintended food allergen presence.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kefelegn N., Haile G., Palanivel H. Effect of plant tissues on DNA quantity and quality of barley (Hordeum vulgare) validating through PCR technique. bioRxiv. 2021 2021-10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varma A., Padh H., Shrivastava N. Plant genomic DNA isolation: an art or a science. Biotechnol. J.: Healthcare Nutrition Technology. 2007;2(3):386–392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17285676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewinsohn E., Steele C.L., Croteau R. Simple isolation of functional RNA from woody stems of gymnosperms. Plant Mol. Biol. Rep. 1994;12:20–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birot S., Madsen C.B., Kruizinga A.G., Crépet A., Christensen T., Brockhoff P.B. Food groups for allergen risk assessment: combining food consumption data from different countries in Europe. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2018;118:371–381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29778497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>