<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39317609</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1618-131X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of hygiene and environmental health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Hyg Environ Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The SAM-Krom biomonitoring study shows occupational exposure to hexavalent chromium and increased genotoxicity in Denmark.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>114444</StartPage><MedlinePgn>114444</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijheh.2024.114444</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1438-4639(24)00125-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Hexavalent chromium (Cr(VI)) is a carcinogen. Exposure to Cr(VI) may occur in different industrial processes such as chrome plating and stainless steel welding. The aim of this study was to assess occupational exposure to Cr(VI) in Denmark.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This cross-sectional study included 28 workers and 8 apprentices with potential Cr(VI) exposure and 24 within company controls, all recruited from six companies and one vocational school. Use of occupational safety and health (OSH) risk prevention measures were assessed through triangulation of interviews, a questionnaire and systematic observations. Inhalable Cr(VI) and Cr-total were assessed by personal air exposure measurements on Cr(VI) exposed participants and stationary measurements. Cr concentrations were measured in urine and in red blood cells (RBC) (the latter reflecting Cr(VI)). Genotoxicity was assessed by measurement of micronuclei in peripheral blood reticulocytes (MNRET).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">At announced visits, a consistent high degree of compliance to OSH risk prevention measures were seen in 'chromium bath plating' for both technical devices (e.g. ventilation, plastic balls, sheet coverings) and in the use of personal protective equipment (e.g. gloves, respirators), yet a lesser degree of compliance was observed in 'stainless steel welding'. The geometric mean of the air concentration of Cr(VI) was 0.26 μg/m<sup>3</sup> (95% confidence interval (CI): 0.12-0.57) for the Cr(VI)-exposed workers and 3.69 μg/m<sup>3</sup> (95% CI: 1.47-9.25) for the Cr(VI)-exposed apprentices. Subdivided by company type, the exposure levels were 0.13 μg/m<sup>3</sup> (95% CI: 0.04-0.41) for companies manufacturing and processing metal products, and 0.81 μg/m<sup>3</sup> (95% CI: 0.46-1.40) for bath plating companies. Workers with occupational exposure to Cr(VI) had significantly higher median levels of urinary Cr (2.42 μg/L, 5th-95th percentile 0.28-58.39), Cr in RBC (0.89 μg/L, 0.54-4.92) and MNRET (1.59 ‰, 0.78-10.92) compared to the within company controls (urinary: 0.40 μg/L, 0.16-21.3, RBC: 0.60 μg/L, 0.50-0.93,MNRET: 1.06 ‰, 0.71-2.06). When sub-dividing by company type, urinary Cr (4.61 μg/L, 1.72-69.5), Cr in RBC (1.33 μg/L, 0.95-4.98) and MNRET (1.89 μg/L, 0.78-12.92) levels were increased for workers with potential Cr(VI) exposure in bath-plating companies, and when subdividing by work task, workers engaged in process operation had increased levels of urinary Cr (8.51 μg/L, 1.71-69.5), Cr in RBC (1.33 μg/L, 0.95-4.98) and MNRET (1.89 μg/L, 0.82-12.92) levels.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This biomonitoring study shows that bath platers were highly exposed to Cr(VI), as suggested by relatively high levels of urinary Cr, Cr in RBC and increased levels of micronuclei. The urinary Cr concentrations were high when compared to the French biological limit value of 2.5 μg Cr/L, corresponding to the Danish occupational exposure limit of 1 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. This, in turn, indirectly suggests that additional exposure routes than via air may contribute to the exposure. For welders, no statistically significant increases compared to within company controls were observed, however, the observed urinary Cr levels were similar to the levels observed in a European study (HBM4EU), and were higher than the levels observed for welders in Sweden (SafeChrom). In spite of a high degree of self-reported and observed compliance to OSH risk prevention measures during announced visits, the biomarkers of exposure reflecting recent exposure (urinary Cr) or exposure during the last four months (Cr in RBC) may point to variation in compliance to OSH risk prevention measures in general. Reduced occupational exposure to Cr(VI) may be achieved by applying the hierarchy of controls in eliminating or substituting Cr(VI), and the use of more effective technical solutions (e.g. automation).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saber</LastName><ForeName>Anne Thoustrup</ForeName><Initials>AT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Research Centre for the Working Environment, 105 Lersø Parkallé, DK-2100, Copenhagen Ø, Denmark. Electronic address: ats@nfa.dk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Levin</LastName><ForeName>Marcus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>FORCE Technology, 345 Park Allé, DK-2605, Brøndby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kines</LastName><ForeName>Pete</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Research Centre for the Working Environment, 105 Lersø Parkallé, DK-2100, Copenhagen Ø, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aimonen</LastName><ForeName>Kukka</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health, 00250, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Givelet</LastName><ForeName>Lucas</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, DK-2800, Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andersen</LastName><ForeName>Christina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>FORCE Technology, 345 Park Allé, DK-2605, Brøndby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huusom</LastName><ForeName>Anja Julie</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Copenhagen University Hospital, Bispebjerg and Frederiksberg, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carøe</LastName><ForeName>Tanja</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Occupational and Social Medicine, Holbæk University Hospital, DK-3400, Holbæk, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ebbehøj</LastName><ForeName>Niels Erik</ForeName><Initials>NE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Occupational and Social Medicine, Holbæk University Hospital, DK-3400, Holbæk, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Christensen</LastName><ForeName>Frans Møller</ForeName><Initials>FM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>COWI A/S, Parallelvej 2, DK-2800, Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Zheshun</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lundh</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tinnerberg</LastName><ForeName>Håkan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Occupational and Environmental Medicine, School of Public Health and Community Medicine, Institute of Medicine, University of Gothenburg, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Albin</LastName><ForeName>Maria</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden; Unit of Occupational Medicine, Institute of Environmental Medicine, Karolinska Institutet, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Engfeldt</LastName><ForeName>Malin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden; Department of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Region Skåne, SE-22381, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Broberg</LastName><ForeName>Karin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Research Centre for the Working Environment, 105 Lersø Parkallé, DK-2100, Copenhagen Ø, Denmark; Division of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Catalan</LastName><ForeName>Julia</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health, 00250, Helsinki, Finland; Department of Anatomy, Embryology and Genetics, University of Zaragoza, 50013, Zaragoza, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Loeschner</LastName><ForeName>Katrin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, DK-2800, Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fuglsang</LastName><ForeName>Karsten</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>FORCE Technology, 345 Park Allé, DK-2605, Brøndby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vogel</LastName><ForeName>Ulla</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Research Centre for the Working Environment, 105 Lersø Parkallé, DK-2100, Copenhagen Ø, Denmark; National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, DK-2800, Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Hyg Environ Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100898843</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1438-4639</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bath platers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biomarkers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hexavalent chromium</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Occupational exposure limits</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vocational schools</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Welding</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39317609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijheh.2024.114444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1438-4639(24)00125-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>