<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39316302</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-2983</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>46</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental geochemistry and health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Geochem Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Advances in perfluoro-alkylated compounds (PFAS) detection in seafood and marine environments: A comprehensive review on analytical techniques and global regulations.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>424</StartPage><MedlinePgn>424</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10653-024-02194-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Per- and poly-fluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) are persistent organic pollutants that severely threaten the environment and human health due to their distinct chemical composition, extensive production, widespread distribution, bioaccumulation in nature, and long-term persistence. This review focuses on the occurrence and sources of PFAS in seafood, with a particular emphasis on advanced detection methods viz. nanoparticle-based, biosensor-based, and metal-organic frameworks-based, and mass spectrometric techniques. The challenges associated with these advanced detection technologies are also discussed. Recent research and regulatory updates about PFAS, including hazardous and potential health effects, epidemiological studies, and various risk assessment models, have been reviewed. In addition, the need for global monitoring programs and regulations on PFAS are critically reviewed by underscoring their crucial role in protecting human health and the environment. Further, approaches for reducing PFAS in seafood are highlighted with future innovative remediation directions. Although advanced PFAS analytical methods are available, selectivity, sample preparation, and sensitivity are still significant challenges associated with detection of PFAS in seafood matrices.  Moreover, crucial research gaps and solutions to essential concerns are critically explored in this review.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramasamy Chandrasekaran</LastName><ForeName>Prasath</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Marine Environmental Engineering, National Kaohsiung University of Science and Technology (NKUST), Kaohsiung, 811, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chinnadurai</LastName><ForeName>Jeganathan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PhD Program in Life Science, College of Life Science, Kaohsiung Medical University (KMU), Kaohsiung, 807, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lim</LastName><ForeName>Yee Cheng</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Marine Environmental Engineering, National Kaohsiung University of Science and Technology (NKUST), Kaohsiung, 811, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Chiu-Wen</ForeName><Initials>CW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Marine Environmental Engineering, National Kaohsiung University of Science and Technology (NKUST), Kaohsiung, 811, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsai</LastName><ForeName>Pei-Chien</ForeName><Initials>PC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal and Applied Chemistry, Kaohsiung Medical University (KMU), Kaohsiung, 807, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computational Biology, Institute of Bioinformatics, Saveetha School of Engineering, Saveetha Institute of Medical and Technical Sciences, Chennai, Tamil Nadu, 602105, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Po-Chin</ForeName><Initials>PC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences, National Health Research Institutes (NHRI), Miaoli, 350, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Precision Environmental Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University (KMU), Kaohsiung City, 807, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Research, China Medical University Hospital (CMUH), China Medical University (CMU), Taichung City, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gavahian</LastName><ForeName>Mohsen</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, Agriculture College, National Pingtung University of Science and Technology (NPUST), Pingtung, 91201, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andaluri</LastName><ForeName>Gangadhar</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Civil and Environmental Engineering Department, College of Engineering, Temple University, Philadelphia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dong</LastName><ForeName>Cheng-Di</ForeName><Initials>CD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Marine Environmental Engineering, National Kaohsiung University of Science and Technology (NKUST), Kaohsiung, 811, Taiwan. cddong@nkust.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology, College of Hydrosphere Science, National Kaohsiung University of Science and Technology (NKUST), Kaohsiung City, 811, Taiwan. cddong@nkust.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Yuan-Chung</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Environmental Engineering, National Sun Yat-Sen University (NSYSU), Kaohsiung, Taiwan. yclin@faculty.nsysu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Emerging Contaminants Research, National Sun Yat-Sen University, Kaohsiung City, Taiwan. yclin@faculty.nsysu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ponnusamy</LastName><ForeName>Vinoth Kumar</ForeName><Initials>VK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal and Applied Chemistry, Kaohsiung Medical University (KMU), Kaohsiung, 807, Taiwan. kumar@kmu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Precision Environmental Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University (KMU), Kaohsiung City, 807, Taiwan. kumar@kmu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, Agriculture College, National Pingtung University of Science and Technology (NPUST), Pingtung, 91201, Taiwan. kumar@kmu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology, College of Hydrosphere Science, National Kaohsiung University of Science and Technology (NKUST), Kaohsiung City, 811, Taiwan. kumar@kmu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Research, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital (KMUH), Kaohsiung City, 807, Taiwan. kumar@kmu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NSTC110-2113-M-037-009</GrantID><Agency>National Science and Technology Council</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>NSTC110-2113-M-037-009</GrantID><Agency>National Science and Technology Council</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>NSTC110-2113-M-037-009</GrantID><Agency>National Science and Technology Council</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>NSTC110-2113-M-037-009</GrantID><Agency>National Science and Technology Council</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Geochem Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8903118</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0269-4042</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D005466">Fluorocarbons</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014874">Water Pollutants, Chemical</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017747" MajorTopicYN="Y">Seafood</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005466" MajorTopicYN="Y">Fluorocarbons</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014874" MajorTopicYN="Y">Water Pollutants, Chemical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="Y">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018570" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013058" MajorTopicYN="N">Mass Spectrometry</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Analytical techniques</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aquatic environment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Global regulations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PFAS remediation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Perfluoro-alkylated compounds</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Seafood contamination</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39316302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-024-02194-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10653-024-02194-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abraham, K., Mielke, H., Fromme, H., Völkel, W., Menzel, J., Peiser, M., Zepp, F., Willich, S. N., &amp; Weikert, C. (2020). Internal exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) and biological markers in 101 healthy 1-year-old children: Associations between levels of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and vaccine response. Archives of Toxicology, 94, 2131–2147. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00204-020-02715-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00204-020-02715-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahrens, L. (2011). Polyfluoroalkyl compounds in the aquatic environment: A review of their occurrence and fate. Journal of Environmental Monitoring, 13, 20–31. https://doi.org/10.1039/C0EM00373E</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C0EM00373E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ait Bamai, Y., Goudarzi, H., Araki, A., Okada, E., Kashino, I., Miyashita, C., &amp; Kishi, R. (2020). Effect of prenatal exposure to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances on childhood allergies and common infectious diseases in children up to age 7 years: The Hokkaido study on environment and children’s health. Environment International, 143, 105979. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2020.105979</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Amin, M., Sobhani, Z., Liu, Y., Dharmaraja, R., Chadalavada, S., Naidu, R., Chalker, J. M., &amp; Fang, C. (2020). Recent advances in the analysis of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS)—A review. Environmental Technology &amp; Innovation, 19, 100879. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eti.2020.100879</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2020.100879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali, A. M., Sanden, M., Higgins, C. P., Hale, S. E., Alarif, W. M., Al-Lihaibi, S. S., Ræder, E. M., Langberg, H. A., &amp; Kallenborn, R. (2021). Legacy and emerging per- and polyfluorinated alkyl substances (PFASs) in sediment and edible fish from the Eastern Red Sea. Environmental Pollution, 280, 116935. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2021.116935</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.116935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alderete, T. L., Jin, R., Walker, D. I., Valvi, D., Chen, Z., Jones, D. P., Peng, C., Gilliland, F. D., Berhane, K., Conti, D. V., Goran, M. I., &amp; Chatzi, L. (2019). Perfluoroalkyl substances, metabolomic profiling, and alterations in glucose homeostasis among overweight and obese Hispanic children: A proof-of-concept analysis. Environment International, 126, 445–453. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2019.02.047</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allred, B. M., Lang, J. R., Barlaz, M. A., &amp; Field, J. A. (2015). Physical and biological release of poly- and perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) from municipal solid waste in anaerobic model landfill reactors. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 49, 7648–7656. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.5b01040</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.5b01040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderko, L., &amp; Pennea, E. (2020). Exposures to per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS): Potential risks to reproductive and children’s health. Current Problems in Pediatric and Adolescent Health Care, 50, 100760. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cppeds.2020.100760</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cppeds.2020.100760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen, M. E., Hagenbuch, B., Apte, U., Corton, J. C., Fletcher, T., Lau, C., Roth, W. L., Staels, B., Vega, G. L., Clewell, H. J., 3rd., &amp; Longnecker, M. P. (2021). Why is elevation of serum cholesterol associated with exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in humans? A workshop report on potential mechanisms. Toxicology, 459, 152845. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tox.2021.152845</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2021.152845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attanasio, R. (2019). Sex differences in the association between perfluoroalkyl acids and liver function in US adolescents: Analyses of NHANES 2013–2016. Environmental Pollution, 254, 113061. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayala-Cabrera, J. F., Contreras-Llin, A., Moyano, E., &amp; Santos, F. J. (2020). A novel methodology for the determination of neutral perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances in water by gas chromatography-atmospheric pressure photoionisation-high resolution mass spectrometry. Analytica Chimica Acta, 1100, 97–106. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aca.2019.12.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2019.12.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bach, C., Boiteux, V., Hemard, J., Colin, A., Rosin, C., Munoz, J.-F., &amp; Dauchy, X. (2016). Simultaneous determination of perfluoroalkyl iodides, perfluoroalkane sulfonamides, fluorotelomer alcohols, fluorotelomer iodides and fluorotelomer acrylates and methacrylates in water and sediments using solid-phase microextraction-gas chromatography/mas. Journal of Chromatography A, 1448, 98–106. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2016.04.025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2016.04.025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Backe, W. J., Day, T. C., &amp; Field, J. A. (2013). Zwitterionic, cationic, and anionic fluorinated chemicals in aqueous film forming foam formulations and groundwater from U.S. military bases by nonaqueous large-volume injection HPLC-MS/MS. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 47, 5226–5234. https://doi.org/10.1021/es3034999</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es3034999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballesteros, V., Costa, O., Iñiguez, C., Fletcher, T., Ballester, F., &amp; Lopez-Espinosa, M.-J. (2017). Exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances and thyroid function in pregnant women and children: A systematic review of epidemiologic studies. Environment International, 99, 15–28. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2016.10.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2016.10.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baluyot, J. C., Reyes, E. M., &amp; Velarde, M. C. (2021). Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) as contaminants of emerging concern in Asia’s freshwater resources. Environmental Research, 197, 111122. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2021.111122</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2021.111122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banjabi, A. A., Li, A. J., Kumosani, T. A., Yousef, J. M., &amp; Kannan, K. (2020). Serum concentrations of perfluoroalkyl substances and their association with osteoporosis in a population in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. Environmental Research, 187, 109676. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2020.109676</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banzhaf, S., Filipovic, M., Lewis, J., Sparrenbom, C. J., &amp; Barthel, R. (2017). A review of contamination of surface-, ground-, and drinking water in Sweden by perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs). Ambio, 46, 335–346. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-016-0848-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13280-016-0848-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barhoumi, B., Sander, S. G., Driss, M. R., &amp; Tolosa, I. (2022). Survey of legacy and emerging per- and polyfluorinated alkyl substances in Mediterranean seafood from a North African ecosystem. Environmental Pollution, 292, 118398. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118398</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baronas, R. (2017). Nonlinear effects of diffusion limitations on the response and sensitivity of amperometric biosensors. Electrochimica Acta, 240, 399–407. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2017.04.075</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2017.04.075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartell, S. M., &amp; Vieira, V. M. (2021). Critical review on PFOA, kidney cancer, and testicular cancer. Journal of the Air and Waste Management Association, 71, 663–679. https://doi.org/10.1080/10962247.2021.1909668</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10962247.2021.1909668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bedi, M., Sapozhnikova, Y., Taylor, R. B., &amp; Ng, C. (2023). Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) measured in seafood from a cross-section of retail stores in the United States. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 459, 132062. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2023.132062</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2023.132062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhavsar, S. P., Zhang, X., Guo, R., Braekevelt, E., Petro, S., Gandhi, N., Reiner, E. J., Lee, H., Bronson, R., &amp; Tittlemier, S. A. (2014). Cooking fish is not effective in reducing exposure to perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances. Environment International, 66, 107–114. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2014.01.024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2014.01.024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bil, W., Ehrlich, V., Chen, G., Vandebriel, R., Zeilmaker, M., Luijten, M., Uhl, M., Marx-Stoelting, P., Halldorsson, T. I., &amp; Bokkers, B. (2023). Internal relative potency factors based on immunotoxicity for the risk assessment of mixtures of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in human biomonitoring. Environment International, 171, 107727. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2022.107727</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2022.107727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bjorke-Monsen, A. -L., Varsi, K., Averina, M., Brox, J., &amp; Huber, S. (2020). Perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) and mercury in never-pregnant women of fertile age: association with fish consumption and unfavorable lipid profile. BMJ Nutrition, Prevention &amp; Health, 3(2), 277–284. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjnph-2020-000131</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blake, B. E., &amp; Fenton, S. E. (2020). Early life exposure to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) and latent health outcomes: A review including the placenta as a target tissue and possible driver of peri- and postnatal effects. Toxicology, 443, 152565. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tox.2020.152565</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2020.152565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blomberg, A. J., Shih, Y.-H., Messerlian, C., Jørgensen, L. H., Weihe, P., &amp; Grandjean, P. (2021). Early-life associations between per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances and serum lipids in a longitudinal birth cohort. Environmental Research, 200, 111400. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2021.111400</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonefeld-Jorgensen, E. C., Long, M., Bossi, R., Ayotte, P., Asmund, G., Krüger, T., Ghisari, M., Mulvad, G., Kern, P., Nzulumiki, P., &amp; Dewailly, E. (2011). Perfluorinated compounds are related to breast cancer risk in greenlandic inuit: A case control study. Environmental Health, 10, 88. https://doi.org/10.1186/1476-069X-10-88</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1476-069X-10-88</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boone, J. S., Vigo, C., Boone, T., Byrne, C., Ferrario, J., Benson, R., Donohue, J., Simmons, J. E., Kolpin, D. W., Furlong, E. T., &amp; Glassmeyer, S. T. (2019). Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in source and treated drinking waters of the United States. Science of the Total Environment, 653, 359–369. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.10.245</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.10.245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown, A. S., Yun, X., McKenzie, E. R., Heron, C. G., Field, J. A., &amp; Salice, C. J. (2023). Spatial and temporal variability of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in environmental media of a small pond: Toward an improved understanding of PFAS bioaccumulation in fish. Science of the Total Environment, 880, 163149. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163149</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buck, R. C., Franklin, J., Berger, U., Conder, J. M., Cousins, I. T., de Voogt, P., Jensen, A. A., Kannan, K., Mabury, S. A., &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. J. (2011). Perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances in the environment: Terminology, classification, and origins. Integrated Environmental Assessment and Management, 7, 513–541. https://doi.org/10.1002/ieam.258</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ieam.258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai, D., Li, Q.-Q., Mohammed, Z., Chou, W.-C., Huang, J., Kong, M., Xie, Y., Yu, Y., Hu, G., Qi, J., Zhou, Y., Tan, W., Lin, L., Qiu, R., Dong, G., &amp; Zeng, X.-W. (2023). Fetal glucocorticoid mediates the association between prenatal per- and polyfluoroalkyl substance exposure and neonatal growth index: Evidence from a birth cohort study. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 57, 11420–11429. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.2c08831</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c08831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capozzi, S. L., Xia, C., Shuwal, M., Zaharias Miller, G., Gearhart, J., Bloom, E., Gehrenkemper, L., &amp; Venier, M. (2023). From watersheds to dinner plates: Evaluating PFAS exposure through fish consumption in Southeast Michigan. Chemosphere, 345, 140454. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.140454</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.140454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cara, B., Lies, T., Thimo, G., Robin, L., &amp; Lieven, B. (2022). Bioaccumulation and trophic transfer of perfluorinated alkyl substances (PFAS) in marine biota from the Belgian North Sea: Distribution and human health risk implications. Environmental Pollution, 311, 119907. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119907</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlsson, P., Crosse, J. D., Halsall, C., Evenset, A., Heimstad, E. S., &amp; Harju, M. (2016). Perfluoroalkylated substances (PFASs) and legacy persistent organic pollutants (POPs) in halibut and shrimp from coastal areas in the far north of Norway: Small survey of important dietary foodstuffs for coastal communities. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 105, 81–87. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.02.053</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.02.053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casey, J. S., Jackson, S. R., Ryan, J., &amp; Newton, S. R. (2023). The use of gas chromatography—high resolution mass spectrometry for suspect screening and non-targeted analysis of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances. Journal of Chromatography A, 1693, 463884. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2023.463884</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2023.463884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cennamo, N., Zeni, L., Tortora, P., Regonesi, M. E., Giusti, A., Staiano, M., D’Auria, S., &amp; Varriale, A. (2018a). A high sensitivity biosensor to detect the presence of perfluorinated compounds in environment. Talanta, 178, 955–961. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2017.10.034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2017.10.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang, C. -J., Barr, D. B., Zhang, Q., Dunlop, A. L., Smarr, M. M., Kannan, K., Panuwet, P., Tangpricha, V., Shi, L., Liang, D., Corwin, E. J., &amp; Ryan, P. B. (2021). Associations of single and multiple per- and polyfluoroalkyl substance (PFAS) exposure with vitamin D biomarkers in African American women during pregnancy. Environmental Research, 202, 111713. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2021.111713</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, C., Lu, Y., Zhang, X., Geng, J., Wang, T., Shi, Y., Hu, W., &amp; Li, J. (2009). A review of spatial and temporal assessment of PFOS and PFOA contamination in China. Chemical Ecology, 25, 163–177. https://doi.org/10.1080/02757540902918321</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/02757540902918321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Jayachandran, M., Bai, W., &amp; Xu, B. (2022). A critical review on the health benefits of fish consumption and its bioactive constituents. Food Chemistry, 369, 130874. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130874</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, M., Zhu, L., Wang, Q., &amp; Shan, G. (2021). Tissue distribution and bioaccumulation of legacy and emerging per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in edible fishes from Taihu Lake, China. Environmental Pollution, 268, 115887. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115887</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Q., Zhu, P., Xiong, J., Gao, L., &amp; Tan, K. (2020). A new dual-recognition strategy for hybrid ratiometric and ratiometric sensing perfluorooctane sulfonic acid based on high fluorescent carbon dots with ethidium bromide. Spectrochimica Acta Part a: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy, 224, 117362. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.saa.2019.117362</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.saa.2019.117362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Z., Zhan, X., Zhang, J., Diao, J., Su, C., Sun, Q., Zhou, Y., Zhang, L., Bi, R., Ye, M., &amp; Wang, T. (2023). Bioaccumulation and risk mitigation of legacy and novel perfluoroalkyl substances in seafood: Insights from trophic transfer and cooking method. Environment International, 177, 108023. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2023.108023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2023.108023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, H., Lv, C., Li, J., Wu, D., Zhan, X., Song, Y., Zhao, N., &amp; Jin, H. (2022). Bioaccumulation and biomagnification of emerging poly- and perfluoroalkyl substances in marine organisms. Science of the Total Environment, 851, 158117. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158117</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, Z., Dong, H., Liang, J., Zhang, F., Chen, X., Du, L., &amp; Tan, K. (2019). Highly selective fluorescent visual detection of perfluorooctane sulfonate via blue fluorescent carbon dots and berberine chloride hydrate. Spectrochimica Acta Part a: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy, 207, 262–269. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.saa.2018.09.028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.saa.2018.09.028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, S., Kim, J.-J., Kim, M.-H., Joo, Y.-S., Chung, M.-S., Kho, Y., &amp; Lee, K.-W. (2020). Origin and organ-specific bioaccumulation pattern of perfluorinated alkyl substances in crabs. Environmental Pollution, 261, 114185. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chou, W.-C., &amp; Lin, Z. (2020). Probabilistic human health risk assessment of perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) by integrating in vitro, in vivo toxicity, and human epidemiological studies using a Bayesian-based dose-response assessment coupled with physiologically based pharmacokinetic. Environment International, 137, 105581. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2020.105581</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christensen, K. Y., Raymond, M., Blackowicz, M., Liu, Y., Thompson, B. A., Anderson, H. A., &amp; Turyk, M. (2017). Perfluoroalkyl substances and fish consumption. Environmental Research, 154, 145–151. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2016.12.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2016.12.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu, S., Letcher, R. J., McGoldrick, D. J., &amp; Backus, S. M. (2016). A new fluorinated surfactant contaminant in Biota: Perfluorobutane sulfonamide in several fish species. Environmental Science and Technology, 50, 669–675. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.5b05058</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.5b05058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colosi, L. M., Pinto, R. A., Huang, Q., &amp; Weber, W. J., Jr. (2009). Peroxidase-mediated degradation of perfluorooctanoic acid. Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, 28, 264–271. https://doi.org/10.1897/08-282.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1897/08-282.1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission, E. (2020). Commission delegated regulation (EU) 2020/784 of 8 April 2020 amending annex I to regulation (EU) 2019/1021 of the European parliament and of the council as regards the listing of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA), its salts and PFOA-related compounds. Official Journal of the European Union.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conley, J. M., Lambright, C. S., Evans, N., Medlock-Kakaley, E., Dixon, A., Hill, D., McCord, J., Strynar, M. J., Ford, J., &amp; Gray, L. E. (2022). Cumulative maternal and neonatal effects of combined exposure to a mixture of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and perfluorooctane sulfonic acid (PFOS) during pregnancy in the Sprague-Dawley rat. Environment International, 170, 107631. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2022.107631</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2022.107631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cousins, I. T., DeWitt, J. C., Glüge, J., Goldenman, G., Herzke, D., Lohmann, R., Miller, M., Ng, C. A., Scheringer, M., Vierke, L., &amp; Wang, Z. (2020). Strategies for grouping per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) to protect human and environmental health. Environmental Science. Processes &amp; Impacts, 22, 1444–1460. https://doi.org/10.1039/d0em00147c</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/d0em00147c</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, D., Li, X., &amp; Quinete, N. (2020). Occurrence, fate, sources and toxicity of PFAS: What we know so far in Florida and major gaps. Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 130, 115976. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2020.115976</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trac.2020.115976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darrow, L. A., Groth, A. C., Winquist, A., Shin, H.-M., Bartell, S. M., &amp; Steenland, K. (2016). Modeled perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) exposure and liver function in a mid-ohio valley community. Environmental Health Perspectives, 124, 1227–1233. https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.1510391</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.1510391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das, K. P., Wood, C. R., Lin, M. T., Starkov, A. A., Lau, C., Wallace, K. B., Corton, J. C., &amp; Abbott, B. D. (2017). Perfluoroalkyl acids-induced liver steatosis: Effects on genes controlling lipid homeostasis. Toxicology, 378, 37–52. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tox.2016.12.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2016.12.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dauchy, X., Boiteux, V., Colin, A., Bach, C., Rosin, C., &amp; Munoz, J.-F. (2019). Poly- and perfluoroalkyl substances in runoff water and wastewater sampled at a firefighter training area. Archives of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, 76, 206–215. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00244-018-0585-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00244-018-0585-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dawson, D. E., Lau, C., Pradeep, P., Sayre, R. R., Judson, R. S., Tornero-Velez, R., &amp; Wambaugh, J. F. (2023). A machine learning model to estimate toxicokinetic half-lives of per- and polyfluoro-alkyl substances (PFAS) in multiple species. Toxics. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxics11020098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxics11020098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Gobbo, L., Tittlemier, S., Diamond, M., Pepper, K., Tague, B., Yeudall, F., &amp; Vanderlinden, L. (2008). Cooking decreases observed perfluorinated compound concentrations in fish. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 56, 7551–7559. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf800827r</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf800827r</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhiman, S., &amp; Ansari, N. G. (2024). A review on extraction, analytical and rapid detection techniques of Per/Poly fluoro alkyl substances in different matrices. Microchemical Journal, 196, 109667. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.microc.2023.109667</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2023.109667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diao, J., Chen, Z., Wang, T., Su, C., Sun, Q., Guo, Y., Zheng, Z., Wang, L., Li, P., Liu, W., Hong, S., &amp; Khim, J. S. (2022). Perfluoroalkyl substances in marine food webs from South China Sea: Trophic transfer and human exposure implication. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 431, 128602. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.128602</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.128602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domingo, J. L., Ericson-Jogsten, I., Perelló, G., Nadal, M., Van Bavel, B., &amp; Kärrman, A. (2012). Human exposure to perfluorinated compounds in catalonia, spain: Contribution of drinking water and fish and shellfish. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 60, 4408–4415. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf300355c</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf300355c</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong, Z., Wang, H., Yu, Y. Y., Li, Y. B., Naidu, R., &amp; Liu, Y. (2019). Using 2003–2014 U.S. NHANES data to determine the associations between per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances and cholesterol: Trend and implications. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 173, 461–468. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.02.061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.02.061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, D., Lu, Y., Zhou, Y., Li, Q., Zhang, M., Han, G., Cui, H., &amp; Jeppesen, E. (2021). Bioaccumulation, trophic transfer and biomagnification of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in the marine food web of the South China Sea. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 405, 124681. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124681</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekperusi, A. O., Bely, N., Pollono, C., Mahé, K., Munschy, C., &amp; Aminot, Y. (2023). Prevalence of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in marine seafood from the Gulf of Guinea. Chemosphere, 335, 139110. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.139110</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.139110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA. (2024). Retrieved 2 August, 2024 from https://www.epa.gov/system/files/documents/2024-04/drinking-water-utilities-and-professionals-technical-overview-of-pfas-npdwr.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA. (2024.2). Retrieved August 8, 2024, from https://www.epa.gov/system/files/documents/2024-07/other-test-method-45-rev1-final-_1.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eriksson, U., Kärrman, A., Rotander, A., Mikkelsen, B., &amp; Dam, M. (2013). Perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in food and water from Faroe Islands. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 20, 7940–7948. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-013-1700-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-013-1700-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fair, P. A., Wolf, B., White, N. D., Arnott, S. A., Kannan, K., Karthikraj, R., &amp; Vena, J. E. (2019). Perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in edible fish species from Charleston Harbor and tributaries, South Carolina, United States: Exposure and risk assessment. Environmental Research, 171, 266–277. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2019.01.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2019.01.021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, Y., Li, X., Xu, Q., Zhang, Y., Yang, X., Han, X., Du, G., Xia, Y., Wang, X., &amp; Lu, C. (2020). Serum albumin mediates the effect of multiple per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances on serum lipid levels. Environmental Pollution, 266, 115138. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, C., Chen, Z., Megharaj, M., &amp; Naidu, R. (2016). Potentiometric detection of AFFFs based on MIP. Environmental Technology &amp; Innovation, 5, 52–59. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eti.2015.12.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2015.12.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, C., Zhang, X., Dong, Z., Wang, L., Megharaj, M., &amp; Naidu, R. (2018). Smartphone app-based/portable sensor for the detection of fluoro-surfactant PFOA. Chemosphere, 191, 381–388. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.10.057</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.10.057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiedler, H., Kallenborn, R., de Boer, J., &amp; Sydnes, L. K. (2019). The Stockholm convention: A tool for the global regulation of persistent organic pollutants. Chemistry International, 41, 4–11. https://doi.org/10.1515/ci-2019-0202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/ci-2019-0202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiorenza, S., Denly, E., Vitale, R. J., Nigro, N., Leahy, M. C., Neslund, C., Blye, D. R., &amp; Farmer, N. (2022). PFAS experts symposium 2: An update on advances in chemical analysis of PFAS. Remediation (n. y.), 32, 9–17. https://doi.org/10.1002/rem.21707</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rem.21707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaherty, J. M., Connolly, P. D., Decker, E. R., Kennedy, S. M., Ellefson, M. E., Reagen, W. K., &amp; Szostek, B. (2005). Quantitative determination of perfluorooctanoic acid in serum and plasma by liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry. Journal of Chromatography b, Analytical Technologies in the Biomedical and Life Sciences, 819, 329–338. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jchromb.2005.03.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jchromb.2005.03.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fletcher, T., Galloway, T. S., Melzer, D., Holcroft, P., Cipelli, R., Pilling, L. C., Mondal, D., Luster, M., &amp; Harries, L. W. (2013). Associations between PFOA, PFOS and changes in the expression of genes involved in cholesterol metabolism in humans. Environment International, 57–58, 2–10. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2013.03.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2013.03.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujii, Y., Kato, Y., Miyatake, M., Akeda, S., Nagata, S., Ando, J., Kido, K., Ohta, C., Koga, N., Harada, K. H., &amp; Haraguchi, K. (2024). Levels and spatial profile of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in edible shrimp products from Japan and neighboring countries; a potential source of dietary exposure to humans. Environment International, 189, 108685. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2024.108685</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2024.108685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujii, Y., Tuda, H., Kato, Y., Kimura, O., Endo, T., Harada, K. H., Koizumi, A., &amp; Haraguchi, K. (2019). Levels and profiles of long-chain perfluoroalkyl carboxylic acids in Pacific cod from 14 sites in the North Pacific Ocean. Environmental Pollution, 247, 312–318. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2019.01.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.01.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaines, L. G. T. (2023). Historical and current usage of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS): A literature review. American Journal of Industrial Medicine, 66(2023), 353–378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ajim.23362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallo, V., Leonardi, G., Genser, B., Lopez-Espinosa, M.-J., Frisbee, S. J., Karlsson, L., Ducatman, A. M., &amp; Fletcher, T. (2012). Serum perfluorooctanoate (PFOA) and perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) concentrations and liver function biomarkers in a population with elevated PFOA exposure. Environmental Health Perspectives, 120, 655–660. https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.1104436</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.1104436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardener, H., Sun, Q., &amp; Grandjean, P. (2021). PFAS concentration during pregnancy in relation to cardiometabolic health and birth outcomes. Environmental Research, 192, 110287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2020.110287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genualdi, S., Young, W., Peprah, E., Srigley, C., Fisher, C. M., Ng, B., &amp; deJager, L. (2024). Analyte and matrix method extension of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in food and feed. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 416, 627–633. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216-023-04833-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-023-04833-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giari, L., Guerranti, C., Perra, G., Cincinelli, A., Gavioli, A., Lanzoni, M., &amp; Castaldelli, G. (2023). PFAS levels in fish species in the Po River (Italy): New generation PFAS, fish ecological traits and parasitism in the foreground. Science of the Total Environment, 876, 162828. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162828</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Göckener, B., Weber, T., Rüdel, H., Bücking, M., &amp; Kolossa-Gehring, M. (2020). Human biomonitoring of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in German blood plasma samples from 1982 to 2019. Environment International, 145, 106123. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2020.106123</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.106123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodrow, S. M., Ruppel, B., Lippincott, R. L., Post, G. B., &amp; Procopio, N. A. (2020). Investigation of levels of perfluoroalkyl substances in surface water, sediment and fish tissue in New Jersey, USA. Science of the Total Environment, 729, 138839. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138839</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gosetti, F., Chiuminatto, U., Zampieri, D., Mazzucco, E., Robotti, E., Calabrese, G., Gennaro, M. C., &amp; Marengo, E. (2010). Determination of perfluorochemicals in biological, environmental and food samples by an automated on-line solid phase extraction ultra high performance liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry method. Journal of Chromatography A, 1217, 7864–7872. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2010.10.049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2010.10.049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grandjean, P., Timmermann, C. A. G., Kruse, M., Nielsen, F., Vinholt, P. J., Boding, L., Heilmann, C., &amp; Mølbak, K. (2020). Severity of COVID-19 at elevated exposure to perfluorinated alkylates. medRxiv.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groffen, T., Keirsebelik, H., Dendievel, H., Falcou-Préfol, M., Bervoets, L., &amp; Schoelynck, J. (2024). Are Chinese mitten crabs (Eriocheir sinensis) suitable as biomonitor or bioindicator of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) pollution? Journal of Hazardous Materials, 464, 133024. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2023.133024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2023.133024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groffen, T., Wepener, V., Malherbe, W., &amp; Bervoets, L. (2018). Distribution of perfluorinated compounds (PFASs) in the aquatic environment of the industrially polluted Vaal River, South Africa. Science of the Total Environment, 627, 1334–1344. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.02.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.02.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habibullah-Al-Mamun, M., Ahmed, M. K., Raknuzzaman, M., Islam, M. S., Ali, M. M., Tokumura, M., &amp; Masunaga, S. (2017). Occurrence and assessment of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in commonly consumed seafood from the coastal area of Bangladesh. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 124, 775–785. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2017.02.053</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2017.02.053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, X., Nabb, D. L., Russell, M. H., Kennedy, G. L., &amp; Rickard, R. W. (2012). Renal elimination of perfluorocarboxylates (PFCAs). Chemical Research in Toxicology, 25, 35–46. https://doi.org/10.1021/tx200363w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/tx200363w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harding-Marjanovic, K. C., Houtz, E. F., Yi, S., Field, J. A., Sedlak, D. L., &amp; Alvarez-Cohen, L. (2015). Aerobic biotransformation of fluorotelomer thioether amido sulfonate (Lodyne) in AFFF-amended microcosms. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 49, 7666–7674. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.5b01219</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.5b01219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haug, L. S., Salihovic, S., Jogsten, I. E., Thomsen, C., van Bavel, B., Lindström, G., &amp; Becher, G. (2010). Levels in food and beverages and daily intake of perfluorinated compounds in Norway. Chemosphere, 80, 1137–1143. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.06.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.06.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hauser-Davis, R. A., Bordon, I. C., Kannan, K., Moreira, I., &amp; Quinete, N. (2021). Perfluoroalkyl substances associations with morphometric health indices in three fish species from differentially contaminated water bodies in Southeastern Brazil. Environmental Technology and Innovation, 21, 101198. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eti.2020.101198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2020.101198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedgespeth, M. L., Taylor, D. L., Balint, S., Schwartz, M., &amp; Cantwell, M. G. (2023). Ecological characteristics impact PFAS concentrations in a U.S. North Atlantic food web. Science of the Total Environment, 880, 163302. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163302</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hepburn, E., Northway, A., Bekele, D., &amp; Currell, M. (2019). Incorporating perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAA) into a geochemical index for improved delineation of legacy landfill impacts on groundwater. Science of the Total Environment, 666, 1198–1208. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong, S., Khim, J. S., Wang, T., Naile, J. E., Park, J., Kwon, B.-O., Song, S. J., Ryu, J., Codling, G., Jones, P. D., Lu, Y., &amp; Giesy, J. P. (2015). Bioaccumulation characteristics of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in coastal organisms from the west coast of South Korea. Chemosphere, 129, 157–163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.06.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.06.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Y., Wei, C., Wang, L., Zhou, Z., Wang, T., Liu, G., Feng, Y., &amp; Liang, Y. (2020). Cooking methods affect the intake of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) from grass carp. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 203, 111003. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.111003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.111003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabeen, M., Fayyaz, M., &amp; Irudayaraj, J. (2020). Epigenetic modifications, and alterations in cell cycle and apoptosis pathway in A549 lung carcinoma cell line upon exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances. Toxics, 8(4), 112. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxics8040112</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janousek, R. M., Mayer, J., &amp; Knepper, T. P. (2019). Is the phase-out of long-chain PFASs measurable as fingerprint in a defined area? Comparison of global PFAS concentrations and a monitoring study performed in Hesse, Germany from 2014 to 2018. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 120, 115393. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2019.01.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trac.2019.01.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, H., Liu, H., Liu, G., Yu, J., Liu, N., Jin, Y., Bi, Y., &amp; Wang, H. (2022). Associations between polyfluoroalkyl substances exposure and breast cancer: A meta-analysis. Toxics, 10, 318. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxics10060318</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxics10060318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, J.-J., Okvitasari, A. R., Huang, F.-Y., &amp; Tsai, C.-S. (2021). Characteristics, pollution patterns and risks of Perfluoroalkyl substances in drinking water sources of Taiwan. Chemosphere, 264, 128579. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128579</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin, H., Mao, L., Xie, J., Zhao, M., Bai, X., Wen, J., Shen, T., &amp; Wu, P. (2020a). Poly- and perfluoroalkyl substance concentrations in human breast milk and their associations with postnatal infant growth. Science of the Total Environment, 713, 136417. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.136417</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.136417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin, Q., Shi, Y., &amp; Cai, Y. (2020b). Occurrence and risk of chlorinated polyfluoroalkyl ether sulfonic acids (Cl-PFESAs) in seafood from markets in Beijing, China. Science of the Total Environment, 726, 138538. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138538</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaboré, H. A., Goeury, K., Desrosiers, M., Vo Duy, S., Liu, J., Cabana, G., Munoz, G., &amp; Sauvé, S. (2022). Novel and legacy per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in freshwater sporting fish from background and firefighting foam impacted ecosystems in Eastern Canada. Science of the Total Environment, 816, 151563. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151563</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaboré, H. A., Vo Duy, S., Munoz, G., Méité, L., Desrosiers, M., Liu, J., Sory, T. K., &amp; Sauvé, S. (2018). Worldwide drinking water occurrence and levels of newly-identified perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances. Science of the Total Environment, 616–617, 1089–1100. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.10.210</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.10.210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang, H., Choi, K., Lee, H.-S., Kim, D.-H., Park, N.-Y., Kim, S., &amp; Kho, Y. (2016). Elevated levels of short carbon-chain PFCAs in breast milk among Korean women: Current status and potential challenges. Environmental Research, 148, 351–359. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2016.04.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2016.04.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, M., Park, J., Luo, L., Min, J., Kim, J. H., Yang, H., Kho, Y., Kang, G. J., Chung, M., Shin, S., &amp; Moon, B. (2020). Effect of washing, soaking, and cooking methods on perfluorinated compounds in mackerel (Scomber japonicus ). Food Science &amp; Nutrition, 8, 4399–4408. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.1737</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubwabo, C., Kosarac, I., &amp; Lalonde, K. (2013). Determination of selected perfluorinated compounds and polyfluoroalkyl phosphate surfactants in human milk. Chemosphere, 91, 771–777. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2013.02.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2013.02.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kucharzyk, K. H., Darlington, R., Benotti, M., Deeb, R., &amp; Hawley, E. (2017). Novel treatment technologies for PFAS compounds: A critical review. Journal of Environmental Management, 204, 757–764. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2017.08.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2017.08.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kudo, N., Katakura, M., Sato, Y., &amp; Kawashima, Y. (2002). Sex hormone-regulated renal transport of perfluorooctanoic acid. Chemico-Biological Interactions, 139, 301–316. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0009-2797(02)00006-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0009-2797(02)00006-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumari, K. (2021). Persistent organic pollutants: gaps in management and associated challenges. CRC Press.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1201/9781003046806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Land, M., de Wit, C. A., Bignert, A., Cousins, I. T., Herzke, D., Johansson, J. H., &amp; Martin, J. W. (2018). What is the effect of phasing out long-chain per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances on the concentrations of perfluoroalkyl acids and their precursors in the environment? A systematic review. Environmental Evidence, 7, 1. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13750-017-0114-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13750-017-0114-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lebigre, C., Aminot, Y., Munschy, C., Drogou, M., Le Goff, R., Briant, N., &amp; Chouvelon, T. (2022). Trace metal elements and organic contaminants are differently related to the growth and body condition of wild European sea bass juveniles. Aquatic Toxicology, 248, 106207. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquatox.2022.106207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aquatox.2022.106207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, A. Y.-C., Panchangam, S. C., &amp; Ciou, P. -S. (2010). High levels of perfluorochemicals in Taiwan’s wastewater treatment plants and downstream rivers pose great risk to local aquatic ecosystems. Chemosphere, 80(10), 1167–1174. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.06.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, J., Du, J., Su, Y., &amp; Zhao, H. (2019). A facile solvothermal synthesis of 3D magnetic MoS<sub>2</sub>/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites with enhanced peroxidase-mimicking activity and colorimetric detection of perfluorooctane sulfonate. Microchemical Journal, 149, 104019. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.microc.2019.104019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2019.104019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Q., Huang, A., Wang, N., Zheng, G., &amp; Zhu, L. (2015). Rapid fluorometric determination of perfluorooctanoic acid by its quenching effect on the fluorescence of quantum dots. Journal of Luminescence, 161, 374–381. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jlumin.2015.01.045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jlumin.2015.01.045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, S., Junaid, M., Zhong, W., Zhu, Y., &amp; Xu, N. (2020). A sensitive method for simultaneous determination of 12 classes of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in groundwater by ultrahigh performance liquid chromatography coupled with quadrupole orbitrap high resolution mass spectrometry. Chemosphere, 251, 126327. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.126327</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.126327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loi, E. I. H., Yeung, L. W. Y., Taniyasu, S., Lam, P. K. S., Kannan, K., &amp; Yamashita, N. (2011). Trophic magnification of poly- and perfluorinated compounds in a subtropical food web. Environmental Science and Technology, 45, 5506–5513. https://doi.org/10.1021/es200432n</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es200432n</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukić Bilela, L., Matijošytė, I., Krutkevičius, J., Alexandrino, D. A. M., Safarik, I., Burlakovs, J., Gaudêncio, S. P., &amp; Carvalho, M. F. (2023). Impact of per- and polyfluorinated alkyl substances (PFAS) on the marine environment: Raising awareness, challenges, legislation, and mitigation approaches under the One Health concept. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 194, 115309. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2023.115309</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2023.115309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, L., Kim, M.-J., Park, J., Yang, H.-D., Kho, Y., Chung, M.-S., &amp; Moon, B. (2019). Reduction of perfluorinated compound content in fish cake and swimming crab by different cooking methods. Applied Biological Chemistry, 6, 2. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13765-019-0449-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13765-019-0449-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv, L., Liu, B., Zhang, B., Yu, Y., Gao, L., &amp; Ding, L. (2023). A systematic review on distribution, sources and sorption of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in soil and their plant uptake. Environmental Research, 231, 116156. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2023.116156</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2023.116156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macorps, N., Le Menach, K., Pardon, P., Guérin-Rechdaoui, S., Rocher, V., Budzinski, H., &amp; Labadie, P. (2022). Bioaccumulation of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substance in fish from an urban river: Occurrence, patterns and investigation of potential ecological drivers. Environmental Pollution, 303, 119165. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119165</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manu, M. K., Li, D., Liwen, L., Jun, Z., Varjani, S., &amp; Wong, J. W. C. (2021). A review on nitrogen dynamics and mitigation strategies of food waste digestate composting. Bioresource Technology, 334, 125032. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2021.125032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2021.125032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marín-García, M., Fàbregas, C., Argenté, C., Díaz-Ferrero, J., &amp; Gómez-Canela, C. (2023). Accumulation and dietary risks of perfluoroalkyl substances in fish and shellfish: A market-based study in Barcelona. Environmental Research, 237, 117009. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2023.117009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2023.117009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCord, J., &amp; Strynar, M. (2019). Identification of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in the cape fear river by high resolution mass spectrometry and nontargeted screening. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 53, 4717–4727. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.8b06017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b06017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonough, J., Hurst, J., Miles, J. A. L., &amp; Pancras, T. (2019). Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances. In Ross, I., &amp; Kalve, E. (Eds.), Emerging Contaminants Handbook. CRC Press, Boca Raton: Taylor &amp; Francis, a CRC title, part of the Taylor &amp; Francis imprint, a member of the Taylor &amp; Francis Group, the academic division of T&amp;F Informa, plc, 2018., pp. 85–262. https://doi.org/10.1201/b22226-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonough, J. T., Kirby, J., Bellona, C., Quinnan, J. A., Welty, N., Follin, J., &amp; Liberty, K. (2022). Validation of supercritical water oxidation to destroy perfluoroalkyl acids. Remediation (n. y.), 32, 75–90. https://doi.org/10.1002/rem.21711</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rem.21711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng, J., Liu, S., Zhou, Y., &amp; Wang, T. (2019). Are perfluoroalkyl substances in water and fish from drinking water source the major pathways towards human health risk? Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 181, 194–201. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.06.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.06.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menger, R. F., Funk, E., Henry, C. S., &amp; Borch, T. (2021). Sensors for detecting per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS): A critical review of development challenges, current sensors, and commercialization obstacles. Chemical Engineering Journal, 417, 129133. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cej.2021.129133</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2021.129133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miranda, D. A., Benskin, J. P., Awad, R., Lepoint, G., Leonel, J., &amp; Hatje, V. (2021). Bioaccumulation of Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in a tropical estuarine food web. Science of the Total Environment, 754, 142146. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142146</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra, B., Varjani, S., Iragavarapu, G. P., Ngo, H. H., Guo, W., &amp; Vishal, B. (2019). Microbial fingerprinting of potential biodegrading organisms. Current Pollution Reports, 5, 181–197. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40726-019-00116-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40726-019-00116-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moro, G., Bottari, F., Liberi, S., Covaceuszach, S., Cassetta, A., Angelini, A., De Wael, K., &amp; Moretto, L. M. (2020). Covalent immobilization of delipidated human serum albumin on poly(pyrrole-2-carboxylic) acid film for the impedimetric detection of perfluorooctanoic acid. Bioelectrochemistry, 134, 107540. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioelechem.2020.107540</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bioelechem.2020.107540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munoz, G., Budzinski, H., Babut, M., Drouineau, H., Lauzent, M., Le Menach, K., Lobry, J., Selleslagh, J., Simonnet-Laprade, C., &amp; Labadie, P. (2017). Evidence for the trophic transfer of perfluoroalkylated substances in a temperate macrotidal estuary. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 51, 8450–8459. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b02399</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.7b02399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munschy, C., Vigneau, E., Bely, N., Héas-Moisan, K., Olivier, N., Pollono, C., Hollanda, S., &amp; Bodin, N. (2020). Legacy and emerging organic contaminants: Levels and profiles in top predator fish from the western Indian Ocean in relation to their trophic ecology. Environmental Research, 188, 109761. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2020.109761</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.109761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakayama, S. F., Yoshikane, M., Onoda, Y., Nishihama, Y., Iwai-Shimada, M., Takagi, M., Kobayashi, Y., &amp; Isobe, T. (2019). Worldwide trends in tracing poly- and perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in the environment. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 121, 115410. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2019.02.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trac.2019.02.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neagu, M. (2020). The bumpy road to achieve herd immunity in COVID-19. Journal of Immunoassay and Immunochemistry, 41, 928–945. https://doi.org/10.1080/15321819.2020.1833919</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15321819.2020.1833919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nilsen, E., Muensterman, D., Carini, L., Waite, I., Payne, S., Field, J. A., Peterson, J., Hafley, D., Farrer, D., &amp; Jones, G. D. (2024). Target and suspect per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in fish from an AFFF-impacted waterway. Science of the Total Environment, 906, 167798. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.167798</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.167798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu, H., Wang, S., Zhou, Z., Ma, Y., Ma, X., &amp; Cai, Y. (2014). Sensitive colorimetric visualization of perfluorinated compounds using poly (ethylene glycol) and perfluorinated thiols modified gold nanoparticles. Analytical Chemistry, 86, 4170–4177. https://doi.org/10.1021/ac403406d</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac403406d</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolen, R. M., Faulkner, P., Ross, A. D., Kaiser, K., Quigg, A., &amp; Hala, D. (2022). PFASs pollution in Galveston Bay surface waters and biota (shellfish and fish) following AFFFs use during the ITC fire at deer park (March 17th–20th 2019), Houston, TX. Science of the Total Environment, 805, 150361. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150361</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojemaye, C. Y., &amp; Petrik, L. (2019). Occurrences, levels and risk assessment studies of emerging pollutants (pharmaceuticals, perfluoroalkyl and endocrine disrupting compounds) in fish samples from Kalk Bay harbour, South Africa. Environmental Pollution, 252, 562–572. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2019.05.091</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.05.091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojo, A. F., Peng, C., &amp; Ng, J. C. (2021). Assessing the human health risks of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances: A need for greater focus on their interactions as mixtures. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 407, 124863. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124863</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otake, T. (2024). Japan’s food safety panel drafts intake limit for “forever chemicals” [WWW Document]. The Japan Times. Retrieved 2 August, 2024, from https://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2024/03/04/japan/explainer/pfas-explainer/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan, C.-G., Liu, Y.-S., &amp; Ying, G.-G. (2016). Perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in wastewater treatment plants and drinking water treatment plants: Removal efficiency and exposure risk. Water Research, 106, 562–570. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2016.10.045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2016.10.045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan, C.-G., Xiao, S.-K., Yu, K.-F., Wu, Q., &amp; Wang, Y.-H. (2021). Legacy and alternative per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in a subtropical marine food web from the Beibu Gulf, South China: Fate, trophic transfer and health risk assessment. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 403, 123618. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.123618</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.123618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey, A. K., Gaur, V. K., Udayan, A., Varjani, S., Kim, S.-H., &amp; Wong, J. W. C. (2021). Biocatalytic remediation of industrial pollutants for environmental sustainability: Research needs and opportunities. Chemosphere, 272, 129936. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129936</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey, K., Singh, B., Pandey, A. K., Badruddin, I. J., Pandey, S., Mishra, V. K., &amp; Jain, P. A. (2017). Application of microbial enzymes in industrial waste water treatment. International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences, 6, 1243–1254. https://doi.org/10.20546/ijcmas.2017.608.151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20546/ijcmas.2017.608.151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadopoulou, E., Stratakis, N., Basagaña, X., Brantsæter, A. L., Casas, M., Fossati, S., Gražulevičienė, R., Småstuen Haug, L., Heude, B., Maitre, L., McEachan, R. R. C., Robinson, O. Roumeliotaki, T., Sabidó, E., Borràs, E., Urquiza, J., Vafeiadi, M., Zhao, Y., Slama, R., &amp; Chatzi, L (2021). Prenatal and postnatal exposure to PFAS and cardiometabolic factors and inflammation status in children from six European cohorts. Environment International, 157, 106853. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2021.106853</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, H., Choo, G., Kim, H., &amp; Oh, J.-E. (2018). Evaluation of the current contamination status of PFASs and OPFRs in South Korean tap water associated with its origin. Science of the Total Environment, 634, 1505–1512. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.04.068</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.04.068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, K., Nikapitiya, C., Kwak, T.-S., &amp; Kwak, I.-S. (2015). Antioxidative-related genes expression following perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) exposure in the intertidal mud crab, Macrophthalmus japonicus. Ocean Science Journal, 50, 547–556. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12601-015-0050-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12601-015-0050-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilli, S., Pandey, A. K., Pandey, V., Pandey, K., Muddam, T., Thirunagari, B. K., Thota, S. T., Varjani, S., &amp; Tyagi, R. D. (2021). Detection and removal of poly and perfluoroalkyl polluting substances for sustainable environment. Journal of Environmental Management, 297, 113336. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.113336</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.113336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinsino, A., Bastús, N. G., Busquets-Fité, M., Canesi, L., Cesaroni, P., Drobne, D., Duschl, A., Ewart, M.-A., Gispert, I., Horejs-Hoeck, J., Italiani, P., Kemmerling, B., Kille, P., Procházková, P., Puntes, V. F., Spurgeon, D. J., Svendsen, C., Wilde, C. J., &amp; Boraschi, D. (2020). Probing the immune responses to nanoparticles across environmental species. A perspective of the EU Horizon 2020 project PANDORA. Environmental Science: Nano, 7, 3216–3232. https://doi.org/10.1039/D0EN00732C</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0EN00732C</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Place, B. J., &amp; Field, J. A. (2012). Identification of novel fluorochemicals in aqueous film-forming foams usedby the US military. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 46, 7120–7127. https://doi.org/10.1021/es301465n</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es301465n</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevedouros, K., Cousins, I. T., Buck, R. C., &amp; Korzeniowski, S. H. (2006). Sources, fate and transport of perfluorocarboxylates. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 40, 32–44. https://doi.org/10.1021/es0512475</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es0512475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulster, E. L., Rullo, K., Gilbert, S., Ash, T. M., Goetting, B., Campbell, K., Markham, S., &amp; Murawski, S. A. (2022). Assessing per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in sediments and fishes in a large, urbanized estuary and the potential human health implications. Frontiers in Marine Science. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2022.1046667</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmars.2022.1046667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quinete, N., &amp; Hauser-Davis, R. A. (2021). Drinking water pollutants may affect the immune system: Concerns regarding COVID-19 health effects. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 28, 1235–1246. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-020-11487-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-11487-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quinete, N., Wu, Q., Zhang, T., Yun, S. H., Moreira, I., &amp; Kannan, K. (2009). Specific profiles of perfluorinated compounds in surface and drinking waters and accumulation in mussels, fish, and dolphins from southeastern Brazil. Chemosphere, 77, 863–869. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2009.07.079</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2009.07.079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramírez Carnero, A., Lestido-Cardama, A., Vazquez Loureiro, P., Barbosa-Pereira, L., Bernaldo, R., de Quirós, A., &amp; Sendón, R. (2021). Presence of perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in food contact materials (FCM) and its migration to food. Foods, 10, 1443. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10071443</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10071443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao, D. N. (2016). Title TBD. In 13th International Conference on Fiber Optics and Photonics. Presented at the International Conference on Fibre Optics and Photonics, OSA, Washington, D.C. https://doi.org/10.1364/photonics.2016.tu3f.2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rayne, S., &amp; Forest, K. (2009). Perfluoroalkyl sulfonic and carboxylic acids: A critical review of physicochemical properties, levels and patterns in waters and wastewaters, and treatment methods. Journal of Environmental Science and Health, Part A, 44, 1145–1199. https://doi.org/10.1080/10934520903139811</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10934520903139811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riedel, T. P., Lang, J. R., Strynar, M. J., Lindstrom, A. B., &amp; Offenberg, J. H. (2019). Gas-Phase detection of fluorotelomer alcohols and other oxygenated per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances by chemical ionization mass spectrometry. Environmental Science &amp; Technology Letters, 6, 289–293. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.estlett.9b00196</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.estlett.9b00196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rochling, F. A. (2021). Intravenous lipid emulsions in the prevention and treatment of liver disease in intestinal failure. Nutrients, 13, 895. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13030895</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13030895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez, K. L., Hwang, J.-H., Esfahani, A. R., Sadmani, A. H. M. A., &amp; Lee, W. H. (2020). Recent developments of PFAS-detecting sensors and future direction: A review. Micromachines (Basel), 11, 667. https://doi.org/10.3390/mi11070667</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/mi11070667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruffle, B., Vedagiri, U., Bogdan, D., Maier, M., Schwach, C., &amp; Murphy-Hagan, C. (2020). Perfluoroalkyl Substances in U.S. market basket fish and shellfish. Environmental Research, 190, 109932. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2020.109932</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.109932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salihovic, S., Lind, L., Larsson, A., &amp; Lind, P. M. (2020). Plasma perfluoroalkyls are associated with decreased levels of proteomic inflammatory markers in a cross-sectional study of an elderly population. Environment International, 145, 106099. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2020.106099</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.106099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sammut, G., Sinagra, E., Helmus, R., &amp; de Voogt, P. (2017). Perfluoroalkyl substances in the Maltese environment—(I) surface water and rain water. Science of the Total Environment, 589, 182–190. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.02.128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.02.128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schecter, A., Colacino, J., Haffner, D., Patel, K., Opel, M., Päpke, O., &amp; Birnbaum, L. (2010). Perfluorinated compounds, polychlorinated biphenyls, and organochlorine pesticide contamination in composite food samples from Dallas, Texas, USA. Environmental Health Perspectives, 118, 796–802. https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.0901347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.0901347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schiavone, C., &amp; Portesi, C. (2023). PFAS: A review of the state of the art, from legislation to analytical approaches and toxicological aspects for assessing contamination in food and environment and related risks. Applied Sciences (Basel), 13, 6696. https://doi.org/10.3390/app13116696</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app13116696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultes, L., van Noordenburg, C., Spaan, K. M., Plassmann, M. M., Simon, M., Roos, A., &amp; Benskin, J. P. (2020). High concentrations of unidentified extractable organofluorine observed in blubber from a greenland killer whale (Orcinus orca). Environmental Science &amp; Technology Letters, 7, 909–915. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.estlett.0c00661</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.estlett.0c00661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Semerád, J., Horká, P., Filipová, A., Kukla, J., Holubová, K., Musilová, Z., Jandová, K., Frouz, J., &amp; Cajthaml, T. (2022). The driving factors of per- and polyfluorinated alkyl substance (PFAS) accumulation in selected fish species: The influence of position in river continuum, fish feed composition, and pollutant properties. Science of the Total Environment, 816, 151662. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151662</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, R., Shelke, S., Bagheri Kashani, M., Morose, G., Christuk, C., &amp; Nagarajan, R. (2023). Safer and effective alternatives to perfluoroalkyl-based surfactants in etching solutions for the semiconductor industry. Journal of Cleaner Production, 415, 137879. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2023.137879</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2023.137879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheriff, I., Debela, S. A., Kabia, O. A., Ntoutoume, C. E., &amp; Turay, M. J. (2020). The phase out of and restrictions on per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances: Time for a rethink. Chemosphere, 251, 126313. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.126313</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.126313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shojaei, M., Joyce, A. S., Ferguson, P. L., &amp; Guelfo, J. L. (2022). Novel per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in an active-use C<sub>6</sub>-based aqueous film forming foam. Journal of Hazardous Materials Letters, 3, 100061. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.hazl.2022.100061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hazl.2022.100061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Q., Zong, G., Valvi, D., Nielsen, F., Coull, B., &amp; Grandjean, P. (2018). Plasma concentrations of perfluoroalkyl substances and risk of type 2 diabetes: A prospective investigation among U.S. women. Environmental Health Perspectives. https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP2619</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/EHP2619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, X., Wang, R., Li, L., Wang, X., &amp; Ji, W. (2021). Online extraction based on ionic covalent organic framework for sensitive determination of trace per- and polyfluorinated alkyl substances in seafoods by UHPLC-MS/MS. Food Chemistry, 362, 130214. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130214</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunantha, G., &amp; Vasudevan, N. (2021). A method for detecting perfluorooctanoic acid and perfluorooctane sulfonate in water samples using genetically engineered bacterial biosensor. Science of the Total Environment, 759, 143544. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143544</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sungur, Ş, Köroğlu, M., &amp; Turgut, F. (2018). Determination of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and perfluorooctane sulfonic acid (PFOS) in food and beverages. International Journal of Environmental Analytical Chemistry, 98, 360–368. https://doi.org/10.1080/03067319.2018.1468440</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03067319.2018.1468440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takayose, M., Akamatsu, K., Nawafune, H., Murashima, T., &amp; Matsui, J. (2012). Colorimetric detection of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) utilizing polystyrene-modified gold nanoparticles. Analytical Letters, 45, 2856–2864. https://doi.org/10.1080/00032719.2012.696225</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00032719.2012.696225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, M. D., &amp; Johnson, D. D. (2016). Preliminary investigation of perfluoroalkyl substances in exploited fishes of two contaminated estuaries. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 111, 509–513. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.06.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.06.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, M. D., Johnson, D. D., Nilsson, S., Lin, C.-Y., Braeunig, J., Mueller, J., &amp; Bowles, K. C. (2021). Trial of a novel experimental design to test depuration of PFASs from the edible tissues of Giant Mud Crab following exposure under natural conditions in the wild. Science of the Total Environment, 758, 143650. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143650</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, M. D., Nilsson, S., Bräunig, J., Bowles, K. C., Cole, V., Moltschaniwskyj, N. A., &amp; Mueller, J. F. (2019). Do conventional cooking methods alter concentrations of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in seafood? Food and Chemical Toxicology, 127, 280–287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2019.03.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2019.03.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thapa, B. S., Pandit, S., Mishra, R. K., Joshi, S., Idris, A. M., &amp; Tusher, T. R. (2024). Emergence of per- and poly-fluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) and advances in the remediation strategies. Science of the Total Environment, 916, 170142. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.170142</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.170142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tittlemier, S. A., Pepper, K., Seymour, C., Moisey, J., Bronson, R., Cao, X.-L., &amp; Dabeka, R. W. (2007). Dietary exposure of canadians to perfluorinated carboxylates and perfluorooctane sulfonate via consumption of meat, fish, fast foods, and food items prepared in their packaging. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 55, 3203–3210. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf0634045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf0634045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tran, T. T., Li, J., Feng, H., Cai, J., Yuan, L., Wang, N., &amp; Cai, Q. (2014). Molecularly imprinted polymer modified TiO<sub>2</sub> nanotube arrays for photoelectrochemical determination of perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS). Sensors and Actuators b: Chemical, 190, 745–751. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.snb.2013.09.048</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2013.09.048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNEP. (2011). Draft revised guidance on the global monitoring plan for persistent organic pollutants—conference of the Parties to the Stockholm Convention on Persistent Organic Pollutants 137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccher, V., Ingenbleek, L., Adegboye, A., Hossou, S. E., Koné, A. Z., Oyedele, A. D., Kisito, C. S. K. J., Dembélé, Y. K., Hu, R., Adbel Malak, I., Cariou, R., Vénisseau, A., Veyrand, B., Marchand, P., Eyangoh, S., Verger, P., Dervilly-Pinel, G., Leblanc, J.-C., &amp; Le Bizec, B. (2020). Levels of persistent organic pollutants (POPs) in foods from the first regional Sub-Saharan Africa Total Diet Study. Environment International, 135, 105413. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2019.105413</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2019.105413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Gerwen, M., Colicino, E., Guan, H., Dolios, G., Nadkarni, G. N., Vermeulen, R. C. H., Wolff, M. S., Arora, M., Genden, E. M., &amp; Petrick, L. M. (2023). Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) exposure and thyroid cancer risk. eBioMedicine, 97, e104831. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2023.104831</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2023.104831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vassiliadou, I., Costopoulou, D., Kalogeropoulos, N., Karavoltsos, S., Sakellari, A., Zafeiraki, E., Dassenakis, M., &amp; Leondiadis, L. (2015). Levels of perfluorinated compounds in raw and cooked Mediterranean finfish and shellfish. Chemosphere, 127, 117–126. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.12.081</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.12.081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieira, V. M., Hoffman, K., Shin, H.-M., Weinberg, J. M., Webster, T. F., &amp; Fletcher, T. (2013). Perfluorooctanoic acid exposure and cancer outcomes in a contaminated community: A geographic analysis. Environmental Health Perspectives, 121, 318–323. https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.1205829</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.1205829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vorst, K. L., Saab, N., Silva, P., Curtzwiler, G., &amp; Steketee, A. (2021). Risk assessment of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in food: Symposium proceedings. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 116, 1203–1211. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2021.05.038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.05.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walekar, L. S., Zheng, M., Zheng, L., &amp; Long, M. (2019). Selenium and nitrogen co-doped carbon quantum dots as a fluorescent probe for perfluorooctanoic acid. Microchimica Acta, 186, 278. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00604-019-3400-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00604-019-3400-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, C., Lu, Y., Sun, B., Zhang, M., Mao, R., Li, X., Song, S., Zhao, J., Yu, M., Shi, Y., &amp; Wang, P. (2022). Biomanipulation impacts on per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances accumulation and trophic transfer in an eutrophic lake. Environment International, 160, 107057. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2021.107057</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2021.107057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, P., Lu, Y., Su, H., Su, C., Johnson, A. C., Yu, L., &amp; Jenkins, A. (2020). Managing health risks of perfluoroalkyl acids in aquatic food from a river-estuary-sea environment affected by fluorochemical industry. Environment International, 138, 105621. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2020.105621</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, S., Niu, H., Cai, Y., &amp; Cao, D. (2018). Multifunctional Au NPs-polydopamine-polyvinylidene fluoride membrane chips as probe for enrichment and rapid detection of organic contaminants. Talanta, 181, 340–345. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2018.01.038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2018.01.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, T., Wang, P., Meng, J., Liu, S., Lu, Y., Khim, J. S., &amp; Giesy, J. P. (2015). A review of sources, multimedia distribution and health risks of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in China. Chemosphere, 129, 87–99. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.09.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.09.021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z., DeWitt, J. C., Higgins, C. P., &amp; Cousins, I. T. (2017). A never-ending story of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs)? Environmental Science and Technology, 51, 2508–2518. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.6b04806</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.6b04806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wanninayake, D. M. (2021). Comparison of currently available PFAS remediation technologies in water: A review. Journal of Environmental Management, 283, 111977. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.111977</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.111977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, C., Wang, Q., Song, X., Chen, X., Fan, R., Ding, D., &amp; Liu, Y. (2018). Distribution, source identification and health risk assessment of PFASs and two PFOS alternatives in groundwater from non-industrial areas. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 152, 141–150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.01.039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.01.039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, T., Leung, J. Y. S., &amp; Wang, T. (2024). Can PFAS threaten the health of fish consumers? A comprehensive analysis linking fish consumption behaviour and health risk. Science of the Total Environment, 920, 170960. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.170960</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.170960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wendelken, S. C., Rosenblum, L., &amp; Epa, U. S. (2019). Method 533: Determination of per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances in drinking water by isotope dilution anion exchange solid phase extraction and liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry. Retrieved from Epa. Gov Website: Https://Www.Epa.Gov/Sites/Default/Files/2019-12/Documents/Method-533-815b19020.Pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiener, R. C., &amp; Waters, C. (2019). Perfluoroalkyls/polyfluoroalkyl substances and dental caries experience in children, ages 3–11 years, National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey, 2013–2014. Journal of Public Health Dentistry, 79(4), 307–319. https://doi.org/10.1111/jphd.12329</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winchell, L. J., Wells, M. J. M., Ross, J. J., Fonoll, X., Norton, J. W., Jr., Kuplicki, S., Khan, M., &amp; Bell, K. Y. (2021). Analyses of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) through the urban water cycle: Toward achieving an integrated analytical workflow across aqueous, solid, and gaseous matrices in water and wastewater treatment. Science of the Total Environment, 774, 145257. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.145257</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.145257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, Y., Wang, Y., Li, J., Zhao, Y., Guo, F., Liu, J., &amp; Cai, Z. (2012). Perfluorinated compounds in seafood from coastal areas in China. Environment International, 42, 67–71. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2011.04.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2011.04.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, W., Wan, Y.-J., Wang, X., Li, Y.-Y., Yang, W.-J., Wang, C.-X., &amp; Xu, S.-Q. (2011). Sensitive bioassay for detection of PPARα potentially hazardous ligands with gold nanoparticle probe. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 192, 1148–1154. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2011.06.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2011.06.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Z., Men, K., Guo, J., Liu, R., Liu, H., Wei, J., Zhang, J., Liu, L., Lin, X., Zhang, M., Liu, Y., Chen, Y., &amp; Tang, N.-J. (2023). Association between exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances and uric acid in Chinese adults. Chemosphere, 312, 137164. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.137164</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.137164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young, W. M., South, P., Begley, T. H., &amp; Noonan, G. O. (2013). Determination of perfluorochemicals in fish and shellfish using liquid chromatography–tandem mass spectrometry. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 61, 11166–11172. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf403935g</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf403935g</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young, W., Wiggins, S., Limm, W., Fisher, C. M., DeJager, L., &amp; Genualdi, S. (2022). Analysis of per- and poly(fluoroalkyl) substances (PFASs) in highly consumed seafood products from U.S. markets. Journal of Agriculture and Food Chemistry, 70, 13545–13553. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.2c04673</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.2c04673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zabaleta, I., Bizkarguenaga, E., Prieto, A., Ortiz-Zarragoitia, M., Fernández, L. A., &amp; Zuloaga, O. (2015). Simultaneous determination of perfluorinated compounds and their potential precursors in mussel tissue and fish muscle tissue and liver samples by liquid chromatography–electrospray-tandem mass spectrometry. Journal of Chromatography A, 1387, 13–23. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2015.01.089</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2015.01.089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zafeiraki, E., Gebbink, W. A., Hoogenboom, R. L. A. P., Kotterman, M., Kwadijk, C., Dassenakis, E., &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. J. (2019). Occurrence of perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in a large number of wild and farmed aquatic animals collected in the Netherlands. Chemosphere, 232, 415–423. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.05.200</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.05.200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, A., Wang, P., Lu, Y., Zhang, M., Zhou, Y., Wang, Y., &amp; Zhang, S. (2019). Occurrence and health risk of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in seafood from Yellow Sea, China. Science of the Total Environment, 665, 1026–1034. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.165</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Wan, Y., Li, Y., Zhang, Q., Xu, S., Zhu, H., &amp; Shu, B. (2011). A rapid and high-throughput quantum dots bioassay for monitoring of perfluorooctane sulfonate in environmental water samples. Environmental Pollution, 159, 1348–1353. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2011.01.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2011.01.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, T., Zhao, H., Lei, A., &amp; Quan, X. (2014). Electrochemical biosensor for detection of perfluorooctane sulfonate based on inhibition biocatalysis of enzymatic fuel cell. Electrochemistry, 82, 94–99. https://doi.org/10.5796/electrochemistry.82.94</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5796/electrochemistry.82.94</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X., Niu, H., Pan, Y., Shi, Y., &amp; Cai, Y. (2010). Chitosan-coated octadecyl-functionalized magnetite nanoparticles: Preparation and application in extraction of trace pollutants from environmental water samples. Analytical Chemistry, 82, 2363–2371. https://doi.org/10.1021/ac902589t</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac902589t</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y.-T., Zeeshan, M., Su, F., Qian, Z.-M., Dee Geiger, S., Edward McMillin, S., Wang, Z.-B., Dong, P.-X., Ou, Y.-Q., Xiong, S.-M., Shen, X.-B., Zhou, P.-E., Yang, B.-Y., Chu, C., Li, Q.-Q., Zeng, X.-W., Feng, W.-R., Zhou, Y.-Z., &amp; Dong, G.-H. (2022). Associations between both legacy and alternative per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances and glucose-homeostasis: The Isomers of C8 health project in China. Environment International, 158, 106913. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2021.106913</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>