<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323873</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2297-1769</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in veterinary science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Vet Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Influence of medium chain fatty acids on selected microbes and on <i>in vitro</i> ruminal fermentation of air-exposed corn silage.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1416695</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1416695</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1416695</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fvets.2024.1416695</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Several medium chain fatty acids and different chemical forms of these acids were evaluated <i>in vitro</i> as treatments of aerobically-exposed corn silage against spoilage and pathogenic microbes and for effects on rumen fermentation. Treatments were control (no additive), myristate (MY), laurate (LA), monolaurin (MLA), methyl ester laurate (MELA), a blend of mono-, di- and triglycerides of laurate (BLA), and monocaprylate (MC). After 24 h of aerobic incubation (37°C), yeast and mold growth were not influenced (<i>P</i> &gt; 0.05) by treatments, while the net growth of lactic acid bacteria was decreased, albeit slightly, compared to that by untreated controls (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) by all treatments of the air-exposed corn silage. Compared with controls, wild-type enterococci were decreased (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) in MLA, MELA, and BLA. <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> was reduced (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) with MLA, MELA, BLA, and MC. Total aerobes showed reductions (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) with MLA, BLA, and MC. <i>Listeria monocytogenes</i> numbers were reduced (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) with MELA. Anaerobic incubation (24 h; 39°C) of ruminal fluid (10 mL) with 0.2 g air-exposed and MCFA-treated corn silage revealed higher hydrogen accumulations (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) with MLA and MC over the control treatment. Methane was decreased (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) solely by MLA. There was an increase (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) of acetate with MELA and MC; of propionate with MELA or by BLA; and of butyrate with MLA, MELA, BLA, and MC. Total VFA, hexose fermented, and ammonia were increased (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) with MELA, BLA, and MC. The acetate:propionate ratio was increased (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.01) with MC. The results showed that treatment of air-exposed corn silage with esterified MCFA had no effect on yeasts and molds but prevented propagation or reduced populations of some unwanted and potentially desirable bacteria. Modest methane reduction was seen during <i>in vitro</i> incubation of rumen fluid suspensions with MLA-treated silage and ammonia accumulations were increased in esterified MCFA-treated silage. Little, if any, other detrimental effects on beneficial ruminal fermentation characteristics were observed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Salinas-Chavira, Arzola-Alvarez, Hume, Fonseca, Ruiz-Barrera, Castillo-Castillo, Ontiveros-Magadan, Jones, Crippen, Poole, Zuñiga-Serrano and Anderson.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salinas-Chavira</LastName><ForeName>Jaime</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Science, Autonomous University of Tamaulipas, Ciudad Victoria, Tamaulipas, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arzola-Alvarez</LastName><ForeName>Claudio</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal Science and Ecology, Autonomous University of Chihuahua, Chihuahua, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hume</LastName><ForeName>Michael E</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service, Food and Feed Safety Research Unit, College Station, TX, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fonseca</LastName><ForeName>Mozart</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agriculture, Nutrition and Veterinary Sciences, University of Nevada, Reno, NV, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruiz-Barrera</LastName><ForeName>Oscar</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal Science and Ecology, Autonomous University of Chihuahua, Chihuahua, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Castillo-Castillo</LastName><ForeName>Yamicela</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Animal Science and Ecology, Autonomous University of Chihuahua, Chihuahua, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ontiveros-Magadan</LastName><ForeName>Marina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departamento de Ciencias Veterinarias, Autonomous University of Ciudad Juarez, Ciudad Juarez, Chihuahua, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jones</LastName><ForeName>Barbara</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Science and Veterinary Technology, Tarleton State University, Stephenville, TX, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Crippen</LastName><ForeName>Tawni L</ForeName><Initials>TL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service, Food and Feed Safety Research Unit, College Station, TX, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Poole</LastName><ForeName>Toni L</ForeName><Initials>TL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service, Food and Feed Safety Research Unit, College Station, TX, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zuñiga-Serrano</LastName><ForeName>Aracely</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Science, Autonomous University of Tamaulipas, Ciudad Victoria, Tamaulipas, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anderson</LastName><ForeName>Robin C</ForeName><Initials>RC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service, Food and Feed Safety Research Unit, College Station, TX, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Vet Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101666658</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2297-1769</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">aerobic phase</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">corn silage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fatty acids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rumen</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11422213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1416695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Pahlow G, Muck RE, Driehuis F, Oude Elferink SJWH, Spoelstra SF. Microbiology of ensiling. In:Buxton DR, Muck RE, Harrison HJ, editors. Silage Science and Technology (Agronomy Series No. 42). Madison, WI: American Society of Agronomy; (2003). p. 31–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Driehuis F, Oude Elferink SJWH, Van Wikleaar PG. Lactobacillus buchneri improves the aerobic stability of laboratory and farm scale whole crop maize but does not affect feed intake and milk production of dairy cows. In: Proc. 12th Intl. Silage Conf., Uppsala, Sweden. Swedish Univ. Agric. Sci. Uppsala (1999). p. 106–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borreani, G, Fernandes Bernardes T, Tabacco E. Aerobic deterioration influences the fermentative, microbiological and nutritional quality of maize and sorghum silages on farm in high quality milk and cheese production chains. R Bras Zootec. (2008) 37:68–77. 10.1590/S1516-35982008001300009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S1516-35982008001300009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galbraith H, Miller TB, Paton AM, Thompson JK. Antibacterial activity of long chain fatty acids and the reversal with calcium, magnesium, ergocalciferol and cholesterol. J Appl Bacteriol. (1971) 34:803–13. 10.1111/j.1365-2672.1971.tb01019.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.1971.tb01019.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5004248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bunkova L, Bunka F, Janis R, Krejci J, Dolezalkova I, Pospisil Z, et al. . Comparison of antibacterial effect of seven 1-monoglycerides on food-borne pathogens or spoilage bacteria. Acta Vet Brno. (2011) 80:29–39. 10.2754/avb201180010029</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2754/avb201180010029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair MKM, Vasudevan P, Hoagland T, Venkitanarayanan K. Inactivation of Escherichia coli O157: H7 and Listeria monocytogenes in milk by caprylic acid and monocaprylin. Food Microbiol. (2004) 21:611–6. 10.1016/j.fm.2004.01.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2004.01.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skrivanová E, Savka OG, Marounek M. In vitro effect of C2-C18 fatty acids on Salmonellas. Folia Microbiol. (2004) 49:199–202. 10.1007/BF02931402</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF02931402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15227798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de los Santos FS, Donoghue AM, Venkitanarayanan K, Dirain ML, Reyes-Herrera I, Blore PJ, et al. . Caprylic acid supplemented in feed reduces enteric Campylobacter jejuni colonization in ten-day-old broiler chickens. Poult Sci. (2008) 87:800–4. 10.3382/ps.2007-00280</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2007-00280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18340004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skrivanová E, Molatová Z, Skrivanová V, Marounek M. Inhibitory activity of rabbit milk and medium-chain fatty acids against enteropathogenic Escherichia coli O128. Vet Microbiol. (2009) 135:358–62. 10.1016/j.vetmic.2008.09.083</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2008.09.083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19019572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cenesiz AA, Çiftci I. Modulatory effects of medium chain fatty acids in poultry nutrition and health. Worlds Poult Sci J. (2020) 76:234–48. 10.1080/00439339.2020.1739595</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00439339.2020.1739595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonald P, Henderson AR. The use of fatty acids as grass silage additives. J Sci Food Agric. (1974) 25:791–5. 10.1002/jsfa.2740250708</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.2740250708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4408386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abel H, Immig I, Harman E. Effect of adding caprylic and capric acid to grass on fermentation characteristics during ensiling and in the artificial rumen system RUSITEC. Anim Feed Sci Tech. (2002) 99:65–72. 10.1016/S0377-8401(02)00084-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0377-8401(02)00084-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Queiroz OCM, Ogunade IM, Weinberg Z, Adesogan AT. Silage review: foodborne pathogens in silage and their mitigation by silage additives. J Dairy Sci. (2018) 101:4132–42. 10.3168/jds.2017-13901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29685282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dohme F, Machmüller A, Wasserfallen A, Kreuzer M. Ruminal methanogenesis as influenced by individual fatty acids supplemented to complete ruminant diets. Lett Appl Microbiol. (2001) 32:47–51. 10.1046/j.1472-765x.2001.00863.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1472-765x.2001.00863.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11169041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soliva CR, Hindrichsen IK, Meile L, Kreuzer M, Machmuller A. Effects of mixtures of lauric and myristic acid on rumen methanogens and methanogenesis in vitro. Lett Appl Microbiol. (2003) 37:35–9. 10.1046/j.1472-765X.2003.01343.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1472-765X.2003.01343.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12803553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joch M, Vadronová M, Cešpiva M, Zabloudilová P, Výborná A, Tyrolová Y, et al. . Capric and lauric acid mixture decreased rumen methane production, while combination with nitrate had no further benefit in methane reduction. Ann Anim Sci. (2023) 23:799–808. 10.2478/aoas-2023-0010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2478/aoas-2023-0010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ontiveros-Magadan M, Anderson RC, Ruiz-Barrera O, Arzola-Alvarez C, Salinas-Chavira J, Hume ME, et al. . Evaluation of antimicrobial compounds to inhibit growth of select Gram-positive pathogenic or antimicrobial resistant bacteria in air-exposed silage. Can J Anim Sci. (2022) 102:75–84. 10.1139/cjas-2021-0061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/cjas-2021-0061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arzola-Alvarez C, Ruiz-Barrera O, Castillo-Castillo Y, Ontiveros M, Fonseca M, Jones BW, et al. . Effects in air-exposed corn silage of medium chain fatty acids on select spoilage microbes, zoonotic pathogens, and in vitro rumen fermentation. J Environ Sci Health B. (2023) 58:45–50. 10.1080/03601234.2023.2168449</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03601234.2023.2168449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36661390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Božic A, Anderson RC, Arzola-Alvarez C, Ruiz-Barrera O, Corral-Luna A, Castillo-Castillo Y, et al. . Inhibition of multidrug-resistant staphylococci by sodium chlorate and select nitro- and medium chain fatty acid compounds. J Appl Microbiol. (2019) 128:1508–16. 10.1111/jam.14232</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.14232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30803130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leyendecker SA, Callaway TR, Anderson RC, Nisbet DJ. Technical note on a much simplified method for collecting ruminal fluid using a nylon paint strainer. J Sci Food Agric. (2004) 84:387–9. 10.1002/jsfa.1673</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.1673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cagle CM, Batista LFD, Anderson RC, Fonseca MA, Cravey MD, Julien C, et al. . Evaluation of different inclusion levels of dry live yeast impacts on various rumen parameters and in situ digestibilities of dry matter and neutral detergent fiber in growing and finishing beef cattle. J Anim Sci. (2019) 97:4987–98. 10.1093/jas/skz342</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skz342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6915237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31679025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allison MJ, Mayberry WR, McSweeney CS, Stahl DA. Synergistes jonesii, gen. nov, sp nov: a rumen bacterium that degrades toxic pyridinediols. Syst Appl Microbiol. (1992) 15:522–9. 10.1016/S0723-2020(11)80111-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0723-2020(11)80111-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaney AL, Marbach EP. Modified reagents for determination of urea and ammonia. Clin Chem. (1962) 8:130–2. 10.1093/clinchem/8.2.130</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/clinchem/8.2.130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13878063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalupa W. Manipulating rumen fermentation. J Anim Sci. (1977) 46:585–99. 10.2527/jas1977.453585x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2527/jas1977.453585x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelsey JA, Bayles KW, Shafii B, McGuire MA. Fatty acids and monoacylglycerols inhibit growth of Staphylococcus aureus. Lipids. (2006) 41:951–61. 10.1007/s11745-006-5048-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11745-006-5048-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17180883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barker LA, Bakkum BW, Chapman C. The clinical use of monolaurin as a dietary supplement: a review of the literature. J Chiropract Med. (2019) 18:305–10. 10.1016/j.jcm.2019.02.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcm.2019.02.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7486475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32952476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackman JA, Boyd RD, Elrod CC. Medium-chain fatty acids and monoglycerides as feed additives for pig production: towards gut health improvement and feed pathogen mitigation. J Anim Sci Biotechnol. (2020) 11:44. 10.1186/s40104-020-00446-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40104-020-00446-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7178611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32337029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellis JK, Hindrichsen IK, Klop G, Kinley RD, Milora N, Bannink A, et al. . Effects of lactic acid bacteria silage inoculation on methane emission and productivity of Holstein Friesian dairy cattle. J Dairy Sci. (2016) 99:7159–74. 10.3168/jds.2015-10754</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2015-10754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27372595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woolford MK. Microbiological screening of the straight chain fatty acids (Cl-C12) as potential silage additives. J Sci Food Agric. (1975) 26:219–28. 10.1002/jsfa.2740260213</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.2740260213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">237145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Razavi-Rohani SM, Griffiths MW. The effect of mono and polyglycerol laurate on spoilage and pathogenic bacteria associated with foods. J Food Saf. (1994) 14:131–51. 10.1111/j.1745-4565.1994.tb00590.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4565.1994.tb00590.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang LL, Johnson EA. Inhibition of Listeria monocytogenes by fatty-acids and monoglycerides. Appl Environ Microbiol. (1992) 58:624–9. 10.1128/aem.58.2.624-629.1992</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.58.2.624-629.1992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC195293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1610184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goel G, Arvidsson K, Vlaeminck B, Bruggeman G, Deschepper K, Fievez, V. Effects of capric acid on rumen methanogenesis and biohydrogenation of linoleic and α-linolenic acid. Animal. (2009) 3:810–6. 10.1017/S1751731109004352</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1751731109004352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22444767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan E, Lovett DK, Monahan FJ, Callan J, Flynn B, O'mara FP. Effect of refined coconut oil or copra meal on methane output and on intake and performance of beef heifers. J Animal Sci. (2006) 84:162–70. 10.2527/2006.841162x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2527/2006.841162x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16361503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hristov AN, Pol MV, Agle M, Zaman S, Schneider C, Ndegwa P, et al. . Effect of lauric acid and coconut oil on ruminal fermentation, digestion, ammonia losses from manure, and milk fatty acid composition in lactating cows. J Dairy Sci. (2009) 92:5561–82. 10.3168/jds.2009-2383</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2009-2383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19841218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hristov AN, Lee C, Cassidy T, Long M, Heyler K, Corl B, et al. . Effects of lauric and myristic acids on ruminal fermentation, production, and milk fatty acid composition in lactating dairy cows. J Dairy Sci. (2011) 94:382–95. 10.3168/jds.2010-3508</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2010-3508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21183049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>