<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323200</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1552-8618</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental toxicology and chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Toxicol Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Do Crops Grown at Urban Dumpsites Contain Metals at Levels that Pose Unacceptable Health Risks to Consumers?</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/etc.5995</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Excessive dietary metal intake from crops grown on contaminated urban dumpsites poses a global health risk to consumers. We evaluated the health risk to adult and child consumers from dietary exposure to metals and metalloids in crops cultivated at the Mbale (Uganda) dumpsite centre. Thirteen crop types grown on the dumpsite soil were sampled and analyzed for concentrations of 11 metals: Fe, Al, Zn, Mn, Cu, Pb, Cr, Hg, Co, Ni, Cd, and two metalloids: Se and As. Different proportions of the crops were combined into 12 meal classes to simulate the diets of residents and estimate noncancer and cancer risks. The findings indicated that most individual crop types and simulated diets lacked sufficient selenium for bodily functions. Furthermore, their metal accumulations exceeded the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) and the World Health Organization (WHO) permissible limits (mg/kg) for Al (20), Fe (100), Ni (10), Cu (20), Mn (10), Pb (0.3), Se (0.05), and Zn (99.4). The four most abundant metals in the various crop types and diets were Al, Fe, Mn, and Zn. A positive correlation between the metals in the crops indicated a common origin, which could possibly be the dumpsite soil. The chronic dietary intake (CDI) of metals was higher in children, and thus children faced higher noncancer and cancer risks compared with adults. The overall CDI values for each metal ranged from 0.000718 to 2.171 in adults, and 0.00125 to 3.781662 in children, which is approximately 1.74 times higher in children than in adult consumers. The noncancer and cancer risks ranged from moderate to high with Co, Cr, Fe, Mn, and Zn being mostly responsible for the high noncancer risks, and Al being the predominant contributor to cancer risks. The total noncancer risk levels equally ranged from moderate (1.4-3.3) for adults, and moderate to high (2.4-5.7) for children; the cancer risks were moderate to high in adults, with Al contributing to between 68% and 92% of the total risks across the 12 meal classes. Overall, CDI values and noncancer and cancer risks were all higher in children than in adults. The vegetables Amaranthus hybridus, Vigna unguiculate, Amaranthus dubius, and Cucurbita maxima significantly contributed to the high noncancer risk to both adults and children, particularly when they constituted 40% or more of the meal. Four additional vegetables (Cocorhrous olitorous, Brassica oleracea, Amaranthus cruentus, and Gynandropsis gynandra) also posed a high risk to children when consumed in large quantities. Our results highlight the urgent need to develop regulatory frameworks and/or rigorously enforce existing land and food governance policies to protect consumers' health from unsafe metal concentrations in crops grown on dumpsites. Environ Toxicol Chem 2024;00:1-17. © 2024 The Author(s). Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of SETAC.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of SETAC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Awino</LastName><ForeName>Florence Barbara</ForeName><Initials>FB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8103-9673</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Health, University of Canberra, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maher</LastName><ForeName>William A</ForeName><Initials>WA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7564-3383</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research School of Earth Sciences, Australian National University, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fai</LastName><ForeName>Patricia Bi Asanga</ForeName><Initials>PBA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3666-3362</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Technology, University of Bamenda, Bambili, Cameroon.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Biology, Dschang School of Science and Technology, University of Dschang, Dschang, Cameroon.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Schlumberger Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Toxicol Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8308958</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0730-7268</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cancer exposure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dietary risk assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dumpsite crops</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meal class</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Total risk</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/etc.5995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adefemi, O. S., &amp; Awokunmi, E. E. (2013). Uptake of heavy metals by tomato (Lycopersicum esculentus) grown on soil collected from dumpsites in Ekiti State, Southwest, Nigeria. International Journal of Chemistry, 5(3), 70. https://doi.org/10.5539/ijc.v5n3p70</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Affourtit, F., Bakker, M. I., &amp; Pronk, M. E. J. (2020). Human health risk assessment of aluminium (RIVM report 2020‐0001). National Institute for Public Health and the Environment (RIVM). https://www.rivm.nl/bibliotheek/rapporten/2020-0001.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agbeshie, A. A., Adjei, R., Anokye, J., &amp; Banunle, A. (2020). Municipal waste dumpsite: Impact on soil properties and heavy metal concentrations, Sunyani, Ghana. Scientific African, 8(2020), e00390. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sciaf.2020.e00390</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry. (2023). Toxicological profile for cobalt. Draft for public comment January 2023. US Department of Health and Human Services. https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp33.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akintan, O. B., Olusola, J. A., &amp; Azeez, A. M. (2019). Heavy metals load in soil, farmlands, and plant crop at open dumpsite. Global Journal of Environmental Science and Management, 5(4), 449–460. https://doi.org/10.22034/GJESM.2019.04.05</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alghobar, M. A., &amp; Suresha, S. (2017). Evaluation of metal accumulation in soil and S. lycopersicum irrigated with sewage water from Mysore city, Karnataka, India. Journal of the Saudi Society of Agricultural Sciences, 16, 49–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali, M. H. H., &amp; Al‐Qahtani, K. M. (2012). Assessment of some heavy metals in vegetables, cereals, and fruits in Saudi Arabian markets. Egypt Journal of Aquatic Research, 38, 31–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejar.2012.08.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antoniadis, V., Golia, E. E., Liu, Y.‐T., Wang, S.‐L., Shaheen, S. M., &amp; Rinklebe, J. (2019). Soil and maize contamination by trace elements and associated health risk assessment in the industrial area of Volos, Greece. Environment International, 124, 79–88. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2018.12.053</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armaroli, E., Bechaux, C., Delagrave, R., Ingenbleek, L., Leblanc, J. C., &amp; Verger, P. (2020). A method to prioritize the surveillance of chemicals in food commodities to access the international market and its application to four countries in Sub‐Saharan Africa. Environment International, 135, 105386. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2019.105386</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ason, B., Armah, F. A., &amp; Essumang, D. K. (2023). Risks of toxic elements and endocrine disruptors in some soils in Ghana. International Journal of Environmental Studies, 80(4), 902–916. https://doi.org/10.1080/00207233.2023.2192617</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Augustsson, A., Lundgren, M., Qvarforth, A., Hough, R., Engström, E., Paulukat, C., &amp; Rodushkin, I. (2023). Managing health risks in urban agriculture: The effect of vegetable washing for reducing exposure to metal contaminants. Science of The Total Environment, 863, 160996. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.160996</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awino, F., Maher, W., Krikowa, F., &amp; Lynch, A. J. J. (2020). Occurrence of trace metals in food crops grown on the Mbale dumpsite, Uganda, and human health risks. Integrated Environmental Assessment and Management, 16(3), 362–377. https://doi.org/10.1002/ieam.4237</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awino, F. B., Maher, W., Lynch, A. J. J., Asanga Fai, P. B., &amp; Otim, O. (2021). Comparison of metal bioaccumulation in crop types and consumable parts between two growth periods. Integrated Environmental Assessment and Management, 18(4), 1056–1071. https://doi.org/10.1002/ieam.4513</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bair, E. C. (2022). A narrative review of toxic heavy metal content of infant and toddler foods and evaluation of United States policy. Frontiers in Nutrition, 27(9), 919913. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.919913</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bamuwamye, M., Ogwok, P., &amp; Tumuhairwe, V. (2015). Cancer and non‐cancer risks associated with heavy metal exposures from street foods: Evaluation of roasted meats in an urban setting. Journal of Environment Pollution and Human Health, 3(2), 24–30. https://doi.org/10.12691/jephh-3-2-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bamuwamye, M., Ogwok, P., Tumuhairwe, V., Eragu, R., Nakisozi, H., &amp; Ogwang, P. (2017). Human health risk assessment of heavy metals in Kampala (Uganda) drinking water. Journal of Food Research, 6(4), 6–16. http://ir.must.ac.ug/xmlui/handle/123456789/2359</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barlow, S. M., Boobis, A. R., Bridges, J., Cockburn, A., Dekant, W., Hepburn, P., Houben, G. F., König, J., Nauta, M. J., Schuermans, J., &amp; Bánáti, D. (2015). The role of hazard‐ and risk‐based approaches in ensuring food safety. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 46(2), 176–188. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2015.10.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhatti, S. S., Kumar, V., Kumar, A., Kirby, J. K., Gouzos, J., Correll, R., Singh, J., Sambyal, V., &amp; Nagpal, A. K. (2020). Potential carcinogenic and non‐carcinogenic health hazards of metal(loid)s in food grains. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 27(14), 17032–17042. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-020-08238-w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bocio, A., Nadal, M., &amp; Domingo, J. L. (2005). Human exposure to metals through the diet in Tarragona, Spain: Temporal trend. Biological Trace Element Research, 104, 193–201. https://doi.org/10.1385/BTER:104:3:193</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonfiglio, R., Scimeca, M., &amp; Mauriello, A. (2023). The impact of aluminum exposure on human health. Archives of Toxicology, 97(11), 2997–2998. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00204-023-03581-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borjac, J., El Joumaa, M., Youssef, L., Kawach, R., &amp; Blake, D. A. (2020). Quantitative analysis of heavy metals and organic compounds in soil from Deir Kanoun Ras El Ain dump, Lebanon. The Scientific World Journal, 2020, 8151676. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/8151676</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, W., Lei, S., Bian, Z., Zhao, Y., Li, Y., &amp; Gan, Y. (2020). Geographic distribution of heavy metals and identification of their sources in soils near large, open‐pit coal mines using positive matrix factorization. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 387, 121666. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.121666</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherfi, A., Abdoun, S., &amp; Gaci, O. (2014). Food survey: Levels and potential health risks of chromium, lead, zinc and copper content in fruits and vegetables consumed in Algeria. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 70, 48–53. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2014.04.044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chary, N. S., Kamala, C. T., &amp; Raj, D. S. (2008). Assessing risk of heavy metals from consuming food grown on sewage irrigated soils and food chain transfer. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 69(3), 513–524. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2007.04.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, Y. (2011). International/national standards for heavy metals in food. Government Laboratory.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cortez, L. A. S., &amp; Ching, J. A. (2014). Heavy metal concentration of dumpsite soil and accumulation in Zea mays (corn) growing in a closed dumpsite in Manila, Philippines. International Journal of Environmental Science and Development, 5, 77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz, N., Rodrigues, S. M., Coelho, C., Carvalho, L., Duarte, A. C., Pereira, E., &amp; Römkens, P. F. A. M. (2014). Urban agriculture in Portugal: Availability of potentially toxic elements for plant uptake. Applied Geochemistry, 44, 27–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeochem.2013.07.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dharni, K., &amp; Sharma, S. (2008). Food safety standards, trade &amp; WTO. Foreign Trade Review, XLIII(3), 3–20. https://doi.org/10.1177/00157325150803</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, F., He, Z., Liu, S., Zhang, S., Zhao, F., Li, Q., &amp; Stoffella, P. J. (2017). Heavy metals in composts of China: Historical changes, regional variation, and potential impact on soil quality. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 24(3), 3194–3209. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-016-8057-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dragović, S., Mihailović, N., &amp; Gajić, B. (2008). Heavy metals in soils: Distribution, relationship with soil characteristics and radionuclides and multivariate assessment of contamination sources. Chemosphere, 72(3), 491–495. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2008.02.063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, Y., Zhu, T., Li, M., He, J., &amp; Huang, R. (2017). Heavy metal contamination in soil and brown rice and human health risk assessment near three mining areas in Central China. Journal of Healthcare Engineering, 2017, 4124302. https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/4124302</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fung, F., Wang, H.‐S., &amp; Menon, S. (2018). Food safety in the 21st century. Biomedical Journal, 41(2), 88–95. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bj.2018.03.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galal, T. M., Hassan, L. M., Ahmed, D. A., Alamri, S. A. M., Alrumman, S. A., &amp; Eid, E. M. (2021). Heavy metals uptake by the global economic crop (Pisum sativum L.) grown in contaminated soils and its associated health risks. PloS One, 16(6), e0252229. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0252229</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gang, L., Wenwen, G., Bingru, L., Jimin, Z., Ligang, P., &amp; Xinhui, L. (2019). Analysis of heavy metals in foodstuffs and an assessment of the health risks to the public via Consumption in Beijing, China. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 16(6), 909. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph16060909</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebeyehu, H. R., &amp; Bayissa, L. D. (2020). Levels of heavy metals in soil and vegetables and associated health risks in Mojo area, Ethiopia. PloS One, 15(1), e0227883. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0227883</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong, C., Wang, S., Wang, D., Lu, H., Dong, H., Liu, J., Yan, B., &amp; Wang, L. (2022). Ecological and human health risk assessment of heavy metal(loid)s in agricultural soil in hotbed chives hometown of Tangchang, Southwest China. Scientific Reports, 12, 8563. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-11397-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadayat, N., De Oliveira, L. M., Da Silva, E., Han, L., Hussain, M., Liu, X., &amp; Ma, L. Q. (2018). Assessment of trace metals in five most‐consumed vegetables in the US: Conventional vs. organic. Environmental Pollution, 243, 292–300. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2018.08.065</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haque, M. M., Niloy, N. M., Khirul, M. A., Alam, M. F., &amp; Tareq, S. M. (2021). Appraisal of probabilistic human health risks of heavy metals in vegetables from industrial, non‐industrial and arsenic contaminated areas of Bangladesh. Heliyon, 7(2), e06309. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou, S., Zheng, N., Tang, L., Ji, X., &amp; Li, Y. (2019). Effect of soil pH and organic matter content on heavy metals availability in maize (Zea mays L.) rhizospheric soil of non‐ferrous metals smelting area. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 191(10), 634. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10661-019-7793-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Integrated Risk Information System. (1993). Reference dose (RfD): Description and use in health risk assessments. Background document 1A. March 15, 1993. US Environmental Protection Agency. https://www.epa.gov/iris/reference-dose-rfd-description-and-use-health-risk-assessments#1.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Integrated Risk Information System. (2019). United States Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA) human health carcinogenic and non‐carcinogenic risk assessment: Oral reference doses and screening levels. US Environmental Protection Agency. https://www.epa.gov/iris</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivey, M. L. L., LeJeune, J. T., &amp; Miller, S. A. (2012). Vegetable producers' perceptions of food safety hazards in the Midwestern USA. Food Control, 26(2), 453–465. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.01.065</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeddi, M. Z., Boon, P. E., Cubadda, F., Hoogenboom, R., Mol, H., Verhagen, H., &amp; Sijm, D. T. (2022). A vision on the ‘foodture’ role of dietary exposure sciences in the interplay between food safety and nutrition. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 120(6), 288–300. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2022.01.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasbekar, A. (2018). Top food safety challenges of 2018 in Europe, the US and beyond [Unpublished work], Regulatory Affairs, Freyr Company.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasozi, K. I., Otim, E. E., Ninsiima, H. I., Ziritunda, G., Tamale, A., Ekou, J., Musoke, G. H., Muyinda, R., Mujinya, R., Matove, H., &amp; Otim, O. (2021). An analysis of heavy metals contamination and estimating the daily intakes of vegetables from Uganda. Toxicology Research and Application, 5, 1–5. https://doi.org/10.1177/2397847320985255</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, S., Farooq, R., Shahbaz, S., Khan, M. A., &amp; Sadique, M. (2009). Health risk assessment of heavy metals for population via consumption of vegetables. World Applied Science Journal, 6(12), 1602–1606.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King, T., Cole, M., Farber, J. M., Eisenbrand, G., Zabaras, D., Fox, E. M., &amp; Hill, J. P. (2017). Food safety for food security: Relationship between global megatrends and developments in food safety. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 68, 160–175. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2017.08.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, V., Singh, J., &amp; Kumar, P. (2019). Heavy metals accumulation in crop plants: Sources, response mechanisms, stress tolerance and their effects. In R. Kumar, V. Kumar, J. Singh, &amp; P. Kumar (Eds.), Contaminants in agriculture and environment: Health risks and remediation (pp. 38–57). Agriculture and Environmental Science Academy. https://www.aesacademy.org/books/cae-vol-1/04.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam, H.‐M., Remais, J., Fung, M.‐C., Xu, L., &amp; Sun, S. S.‐M. (2013). Food supply and food safety issues in China. The Lancet, 381(9882), 2044–2053. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60776-X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Likuku, A. S., &amp; Obuseng, G. (2015). Health risk assessment of heavy metals via dietary intake of vegetables irrigated with treated wastewater around Gaborone, Botswana. International Conference on Plant, Marine and Environmental Sciences (PMES‐2015), pp. 81–126. http://moodle.buan.ac.bw/handle/123456789/160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lion, G. N., &amp; Olowoyo, J. O. (2013). Population health risk due to dietary intake of toxic heavy metals from Spinacia oleracea harvested from soils collected in and around Tshwane, South Africa. South African Journal of Botany, 88, 178–182. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sajb.2013.07.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, L., Hu, L., Tang, J., Li, Y., Zhang, Q., &amp; Chen, X. (2012). Food safety assessment of planting patterns of four vegetable‐type crops grown in soil contaminated by electronic waste activities. Journal of Environmental Management, 93(1), 22–30. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2011.08.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopes, C., Herva, M., Franco‐Uría, A., &amp; Roca, E. (2011). Inventory of heavy metal content in organic waste applied as fertilizer in agriculture: Evaluating the risk of transfer into the food chain. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 18(6), 918–939. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-011-0444-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacLaurin, T. L., MacLaurin, D. J., &amp; Loi, L. S. (2000). Impact of food‐borne illness on food safety concerns of international air travellers. Tourism Economics, 6(2), 169–185. https://doi.org/10.5367/000000000101297569</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manwani, S., Vanisree, C. R., Jaiman, V., Awasthi, K. K., Yadav, C. S., Sankhla, M. S., &amp; Awasthi, G. (2022). Heavy metal contamination in vegetables and their toxic effects on human health. In V. S. Meena, S. K. Meena, R. P. Yadav, &amp; M. Choudary (Eds.), Sustainable crop production: Recent advances (pp. 1–7). IntechOpen. https://doi.org/10.5772/intechopen.102651</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Margenat, A., Matamoros, V., Díez, S., Cañameras, N., Comas, J., &amp; Bayona, J. M. (2019). Occurrence and human health implications of chemical contaminants in vegetables grown in peri‐urban agriculture. Environment International, 124, 49–57. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2018.12.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mawari, G., Kumar, N., Sarkar, S., Daga, M. K., Singh, M. M., Joshi, T. K., &amp; Khan, N. A. (2022). Heavy metal accumulation in fruits and vegetables and human health risk assessment: Findings from Maharashtra. India. Environmental Health Insights, 16(1), 10. https://doi.org/10.1177/11786302221119151</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBride, M. B., Shayler, H. A., Spliethoff, H. M., Mitchell, R. G., Marquez‐Bravo, L. G., Ferenz, G. S., &amp; Bachman, S. (2014). Concentrations of lead, cadmium and barium in urban garden‐grown vegetables: The impact of soil variables. Environmental Pollution, 194, 254–261. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2014.07.036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehmood, A., Mirza, M. A., Choudhary, M. A., Kim, K. H., Raza, W., Raza, N., Lee, S. S., Zhang, M., Lee, J. H., &amp; Sarfraz, M. (2018). Spatial distribution of heavy metals in crops in a wastewater irrigated zone and health risk assessment. Environmental Research, 168, 382–388. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2018.09.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Agriculture &amp; Ministry of Health. (2005). The national food and nutrition strategy. Kampala, Uganda. https://extranet.who.int/nutrition/gina/sites/default/files/UGA%202005%20The%20National%20Food%20and%20Nutrition%20Strategy.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health. (2004). Building a food safety system in Uganda. (Conference room document 61). Bangkok, Thailand: Food and Agriculture Organization and the World Health Organization (FAO/WHO). https://www.fao.org/3/ae1911e.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moya, J., Bearer, C. F., &amp; Etzel, R. A. (2004). Children's behaviour and physiology and how it affects exposure to environmental contaminants. Pediatrics, 113(Suppl 3), 996–1006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munishi, L. K., Ndakidemi, P. A., Blake, W., Comber, S., &amp; Hutchinson, T. H. (2021). Accumulation and bioconcentration of heavy metals in two phases from agricultural soil to plants in Usangu agroecosystem‐Tanzania. Heliyon, 7, 7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musoke, D., Ndejjo, R., Atusingwize, E., &amp; Halage, A. A. (2016). The role of environmental health in one health: A Uganda perspective. One Health, 2, 157–160. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.onehlt.2016.10.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwesigye, A. R., Young, S. D., Bailey, E. H., &amp; Tumwebaze, S. B. (2016). Population exposure to trace elements in the Kilembe copper mine area, Western Uganda: A pilot study. Science of The Total Environment, 573, 366–375. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.08.125</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwesigye, A. R., Young, S. D., Bailey, E. H., &amp; Tumwebaze, S. B. (2019). Uptake of trace elements by food crops grown within the Kilembe copper mine catchment, Western Uganda. Journal of Geochemical Exploration, 207, 106377. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gexplo.2019.106377</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nabulo, G., Black, C. R., Craigon, J., &amp; Young, S. D. (2012). Does consumption of leafy vegetables grown in peri‐urban agriculture pose a risk to human health? Environmental Pollution, 162, 389–398. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2011.11.040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nabulo, G., Young, S. D., &amp; Black, C. R. (2010). Assessing risk to human health from tropical leafy vegetables grown on contaminated urban soils. Science of the Total Environment, 408(22), 5338–5351. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2010.06.034</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nambafu, G. N. (2020). Extent of heavy metals contamination in leafy vegetables among peri‐urban farmers. Asian Journal of Research in Botany, 3(4), 38–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawab, J., Farooqi, S., Xiaoping, W., Khan, S., &amp; Khan, A. (2018). Levels, dietary intake, and health risk of potentially toxic metals in vegetables, fruits, and cereal crops in Pakistan. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 25, 5558–5571. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-017-0764-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak, R., &amp; Waterson, P. (2019). Global food safety as a complex adaptive system: Key concepts and prospects. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 91, 409–425. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2019.07.040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngweme, G. N., Konde, J. N. N., Laffite, A., Kiyombo, G. M., Mulaji, C. K., &amp; Poté, J. W. (2021). Contamination levels of toxic metals in marketed vegetable (Amaranthus viridis) at Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo. Food Science and Nutrition, 7(087), 2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Njagi, J. M., Akunga, D. N., Njagi, M. M., Ngugi, M. P., &amp; Njagi, E. M. (2016). Heavy metal pollution of the environment by dumpsites: A case of Kadhodeki dumpsite. International Journal of Life Sciences Scientific Research, 2(2), 191–197. https://iijls.com/currentissue/Heavy_Metal_Pollution_Environment_Dumpsites_Dumpsite.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuapia, Y., Chimuka, L., &amp; Cukrowska, E. (2018). Assessment of heavy metals in raw food samples from open markets in two African cities. Chemosphere, 196, 339–346. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.12.13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyambura, C., Hashim, N. O., Chege, M. W., Tokonami, S., &amp; Omonya, F. W. (2020). Cancer and non‐cancer health risks from carcinogenic heavy metal exposures in underground water from Kilimambogo. Kenya. Groundwater for Sustainable Development, 10, 100315. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gsd.2019.100315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohiagu, F. O., Chikezie, P. C., Ahaneku, C. C., &amp; Chikezie, C. M. (2022). Human exposure to heavy metals: Toxicity mechanisms and health implications. Material Science &amp; Engineering, 6(2), 78–87. https://doi.org/10.15406/mseij.2022.06.00183</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olowoyo, J. O., Okedeyi, O., Mkolo, N. M., Lion, G. N., &amp; Mdakane, S. (2012). Uptake and translocation of heavy metals by medicinal plants growing around a waste dump site in Pretoria, South Africa. South African Journal of Botany, 78, 116–121. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sajb.2011.05.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otim, O., Juma, T., &amp; Otunnu, O. (2019). Assessing the health risks of consuming ‘sachet’ alcohol in Acoli, Uganda. PloS One, 14(2), e0212938. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0212938</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panqing, Y., Abliz, A., Xiaoli, S., &amp; Aisaiduli, H. (2023). Human health‐risk assessment of heavy metal–contaminated soil based on Monte Carlo simulation. Scientific Reports, 13, 7033. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33986-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raber, M., Baranowski, T., Crawford, K., Sharma, S. V., Schick, V., Markham, C., Jia, W., Sun, M., Steinman, E., &amp; Chandra, J. (2020). The healthy cooking index: Nutrition optimizing home food preparation practices across multiple data collection methods. Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics, 120(7), 1119–1132. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jand.2020.01.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rai, P. K., Sang Soo, L., Ming, Z., Yiu Fai, T., &amp; Ki‐Hyun, K. (2019). Heavy metals in food crops: Health risks, fate, mechanisms, and management. Environment International, 125, 365–385. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2019.01.067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman, Z. U., Khan, S., Brusseau, M. L., &amp; Shah, M. T. (2017). Lead and cadmium contamination and exposure risk assessment via consumption of vegetables grown in agricultural soils of five‐selected regions of Pakistan. Chemosphere, 168, 1589–1596. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.11.152</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman, Z. U., Khan, S., Shah, M. T., Brusseau, M. L., Khan, S. A., &amp; Mainhagu, J. (2018). Transfer of heavy metals from soils to vegetables and associated human health risks at selected sites in Pakistan. Pedosphere, 28(4), 666–679. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1002-0160(17)60440-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roba, C., Rosu, C., Pistea, I., Ozunu, A., &amp; Baciu, C. (2016). Heavy metal content in vegetables and fruits cultivated in Baia mare mining area (Romania) and health risk assessment. Environmental Science &amp; Pollution Research, 23(7), 6062–6073. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-015-4799-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabir, M., Baltrėnaitė‐Gedienė, E., Ditta, A., Ullah, H., Kanwal, A., Ullah, S., &amp; Faraj, T. K. (2022). Bioaccumulation of heavy metals in a soil–plant system from an open dumpsite and the associated health risks through multiple routes. Sustainability, 14(20), 13223. https://doi.org/10.3390/su142013223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadee, B. A., &amp; Ali, R. J. (2023). Determination of heavy metals in edible vegetables and a human health risk assessment. Environmental Nanotechnology, Monitoring &amp; Management, 19, 100761. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enmm.2022.100761</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saumel, I., Kotsyuk, I., Holscher, M., Lenkereit, C., Weber, F., &amp; Kowarik, I. (2012). How healthy is urban horticulture in high‐traffic areas? Trace metal concentrations in vegetable crops from plantings within inner‐city neighbourhoods in Berlin, Germany. Environmental Pollution, 165, 124–132. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2012.02.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scutarașu, E. C., &amp; Trincă, L. C. (2023). Heavy metals in foods and beverages: Global situation, health risks and reduction methods. Foods, 12(18), 3340. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12183340</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaheen, N., Irfan, N. M., Khan, I. N., Islam, S., Islam, M. S., &amp; Ahmed, M. K. (2016). Presence of heavy metals in fruits and vegetables: Health risk implications in Bangladesh. Chemosphere, 152, 431–438. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.02.060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahid, M., Dumat, C., Khalid, S., Schreck, E., Xiong, T., &amp; Niazi, N. K. (2017). Foliar heavy metal uptake, toxicity, and detoxification in plants: A comparison of foliar and root metal uptake. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 325, 36–58. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2016.11.063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slekovec, M., &amp; Goessler, W. (2005). Accumulation of selenium in natural plants and selenium supplemented vegetable and selenium speciation by HPLC‐ICPMS. Chemical Speciation &amp; Bioavailability, 17(2), 63–73. https://doi.org/10.3184/095422905782774919</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stahl, T., Falk, T., Rohrbeck, A., Georgii, S., Herzog, C., Wiegand, A., Hotz, S., Boschek, B., Zorn, H., &amp; Brunn, H. (2017). Migration of aluminum from food contact materials to food—a health risk for consumers? Part I of III: Exposure to aluminum, release of aluminum, tolerable weekly intake (TWI), toxicological effects of aluminum, study design, and methods. Environmental Science Europe, 29, 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12302-017-0116-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tietz, T., Lenzner, A., Kolbaum, A. E., Zellmer, S., Riebeling, C., Gurtler, R., &amp; Hensel, A. (2019). Aggregated aluminium exposure: Risk assessment for the general population. Archives of Toxicology, 93, 3503–3521. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00204-019-02599-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiimub, B. M., &amp; Afua, M. A. D. (2013). Determination of selected heavy metals and iron concentration in two common fish species in Densu River at Weija district in Grater Accra region of Ghana. American International Journal of Biology, 1(1), 45–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Environmental Protection Agency. (2008). Provisional peer reviewed toxicity values for cobalt (CASRN 7440‐48‐4). EPA/690/R‐08/008F. Superfund Health Risk Technical Support Center, National Center for Environmental Assessment, Office of Research and Development.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warming, M., Hansen, M. G., Holm, P. E., Magid, J., Hansen, T. H., &amp; Trapp, S. (2015). Does intake of trace elements through urban gardening in Copenhagen pose a risk to human health? Environmental Pollution, 202, 17–23. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2015.03.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>William, N. G., Godfrey, M., &amp; Savino, B. (2011). Assessment of heavy metals in milk from selected dairy farms and shops in Wakiso District. Uganda. Journal of Natural and Social Science, 1(1), 36–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woldetsadik, D., Drechsel, P., Keraita, B., Itanna, F., &amp; Gebrekidan, H. (2017). Heavy metal accumulation and health risk assessment in wastewater‐irrigated urban vegetable farming sites of Addis Ababa. Ethiopia. International Journal of Food Contamination, 4(1), 1–13. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40550-017-0053-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2010). World health statistics 2010. Global status report on noncommunicable diseases 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization/Food and Agricultural Organization. (2021). The public health impact of chemicals: Knowns and unknowns—data addendum for 2019. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-HEP-ECH-EHD-21.01</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>