<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323241</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Lipase-catalyzed synthesis of erythorbyl oleate and its characterization as a multifunctional emulsifier.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17413</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Erythorbyl oleate (EO), a novel emulsifier with multifunctional properties, was synthesized via lipase-catalyzed solvent-free esterification between erythorbic acid and oleic acid. The reaction produced EO of 30.75 ± 1.65 mM at 60 h, monitored by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) analysis. Purified EO was chemically identified as 6-O-oleoyl-erythorbic acid by HPLC-electrospray ionization/mass spectrometry (ESI-MS), <sup>1</sup>H nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), and <sup>13</sup>C NMR analyses, and further investigations on its multifunctionalities were conducted. EO displayed antioxidant activity equivalent to erythorbic acid in 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl and 2,2'-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) radical scavenging activities. Investigation of the antibacterial activity of EO against foodborne pathogens showed MICs of 0.27 ± 0.09 and 0.40 mM for Bacillus cereus ATCC 10876 and Staphylococcus aureus ATCC 12692, respectively. EO also displayed interfacial properties, lowering interfacial tension between medium-chain triglyceride oil and water to 3.40 ± 0.04 mN/m with a critical micelle concentration of 2.54 ± 0.03 mM. Dynamic light scattering analyses of the emulsion stabilized by EO demonstrated a similar polydispersity index (0.15 ± 0.00) to Tween 80-stabilized emulsion (0.28 ± 0.01), with an average droplet size of 173.2 ± 1.8 nm. In addition, the EO-stabilized emulsion exhibited a negative surface charge (-56.83 ± 4.30 mV) in zeta potential measurements, indicating sufficient electrostatic repulsion between droplets. These results suggest that EO is a multifunctional emulsifier to simultaneously control oxidative rancidification and bacterial spoilage in emulsion-based foods. Practical Application: EO was synthesized via an enzymatic esterification reaction between erythorbic acid and oleic acid. The synthetic process excluded any use of organic solvent, diminishing potential health hazards or environmental pollution associated with chemical reactions. The interfacial properties of the resultant EO, along with excellent antioxidant and antibacterial activities, propose its potential application in emulsion-based foods. Simultaneous control of bacterial spoilage and oxidative rancidification by EO would fulfill the industrial needs for extending shelf life and enhancing consumer safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Jihoon</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agricultural Biotechnology, Seoul National University, Gwanak-gu, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choi</LastName><ForeName>Yoonseok</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Food and Bioconvergence, Seoul National University, Gwanak-gu, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nbiocell Inc., Siheung, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Hyunjong</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Major of Food Science and Biotechnology, Division of Bio-Convergence, Kyonggi University, Suwon, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chang</LastName><ForeName>Pahn-Shick</ForeName><Initials>PS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9645-7010</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agricultural Biotechnology, Seoul National University, Gwanak-gu, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Food and Bioconvergence, Seoul National University, Gwanak-gu, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Agricultural Microorganism and Enzyme, Seoul National University, Gwanak-gu, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Seoul National University, Gwanak-gu, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibacterial activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antioxidant activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cis‐unsaturated fatty acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">erythorbyl oleate</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">interfacial property</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323241</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Arcens, D., Grau, E., Grelier, S., Cramail, H., &amp; Peruch, F. (2020). Impact of fatty acid structure on CALB‐catalyzed esterification of glucose. European Journal of Lipid Science and Technology, 122(4), 1900294. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejlt.201900294</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berton‐Carabin, C. C., Ropers, M.‐H., &amp; Genot, C. (2014). Lipid oxidation in oil‐in‐water emulsions: Involvement of the interfacial layer. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 13(5), 945–977. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12097</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boudjemaa, R., Cabriel, C., Dubois‐Brissonnet, F., Bourg, N., Dupuis, G., Gruss, A., Lévêque‐Fort, S., Briandet, R., Fontaine‐Aupart, M. P., &amp; Steenkeste, K. (2018). Impact of bacterial membrane fatty acid composition on the failure of daptomycin to kill Staphylococcus aureus. Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy, 62(7). https://doi.org/10.1128/aac.00023‐18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cea, M., González, M. E., Abarzúa, M., &amp; Navia, R. (2019). Enzymatic esterification of oleic acid by Candida rugosa lipase immobilized onto biochar. Journal of Environmental Management, 242, 171–177. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2019.04.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalgleish, D. G. (2006). Food emulsions—Their structures and structure‐forming properties. Food Hydrocolloids, 20(4), 415–422. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2005.10.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danaei, M., Dehghankhold, M., Ataei, S., Hasanzadeh Davarani, F., Javanmard, R., Dokhani, A., Khorasani, S., &amp; Mozafari, M. R. (2018). Impact of particle size and polydispersity index on the clinical applications of lipidic nanocarrier systems. Pharmaceutics, 10(2). https://doi.org/10.3390/pharmaceutics10020057</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Olmo, A., Calzada, J., &amp; Nuñez, M. (2017). Benzoic acid and its derivatives as naturally occurring compounds in foods and as additives: Uses, exposure, and controversy. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 57(14), 3084–3103. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2015.1087964</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaudin, T., Lu, H., Fayet, G., Berthauld‐Drelich, A., Rotureau, P., Pourceau, G., Wadouachi, A., Van Hecke, E., Nesterenko, A., &amp; Pezron, I. (2019). Impact of the chemical structure on amphiphilic properties of sugar‐based surfactants: A literature overview. Advances in Colloid and Interface Science, 270, 87–100. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cis.2019.06.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González, M. J., Medina, I., Maldonado, O. S., Lucas, R., &amp; Morales, J. C. (2015). Antioxidant activity of alkyl gallates and glycosyl alkyl gallates in fish oil in water emulsions: Relevance of their surface active properties and of the type of emulsifier. Food Chemistry, 183, 190–196. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.03.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, X., &amp; Ahn, D. U. (2019). Lipid oxidation and its implications to meat quality and human health. Food Science and Biotechnology, 28(5), 1275–1285. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10068‐019‐00631‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huis in't Veld, J. H. J. (1996). Microbial and biochemical spoilage of foods: An overview. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 33(1), 1–18. https://doi.org/10.1016/0168‐1605(96)01139‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iliopoulos, F., Sil, B., Moore, D., Lucas, R., &amp; Lane, M. (2019). 3‐O‐ethyl‐L‐ascorbic acid: Characterisation and investigation of single solvent systems for delivery to the skin. International Journal of Pharmaceutics: X, 1, 100025. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijpx.2019.100025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J., Yu, H., Yang, E., Choi, Y., &amp; Chang, P.‐S. (2023). Effects of alkyl chain length on the interfacial, antibacterial, and antioxidative properties of erythorbyl fatty acid esters. LWT, 174, 114421. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2022.114421</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J.‐W., Yu, H., Park, K.‐M., &amp; Chang, P.‐S. (2020). Antimicrobial characterization of erythorbyl laurate for practical applications in food and cosmetics. Journal of Chemistry, 2020(1), 5073508. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/5073508</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Chikindas, M. L., Ludescher, R. D., &amp; Montville, T. J. (2002). Temperature‐ and surfactant‐induced membrane modifications that alter Listeria monocytogenes nisin sensitivity by different mechanisms. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 68(12), 5904–5910. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.68.12.5904‐5910.2002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, R., Peng, S., Zhang, R., Dai, T., Fu, G., Wan, Y., Liu, C., &amp; McClements, D. J. (2019). Formation and characterization of oil‐in‐water emulsions stabilized by polyphenol‐polysaccharide complexes: Tannic acid and β‐glucan. Food Research International, 123, 266–275. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2019.05.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez‐Huertas, E. (2010). Health effects of oleic acid and long chain omega‐3 fatty acids (EPA and DHA) enriched milks. A review of intervention studies. Pharmacological Research, 61(3), 200–207. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2009.10.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez‐Seara, H., Rog, T., Pasenkiewicz‐Gierula, M., Vattulainen, I., Karttunen, M., &amp; Reigada, R. (2007). Effect of double bond position on lipid bilayer properties: Insight through atomistic simulations. Journal of Physical Chemistry B, 111(38), 11162–11168. https://doi.org/10.1021/jp071894d</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McClements, D. J., &amp; Decker, E. (2018). Interfacial antioxidants: A review of natural and synthetic emulsifiers and coemulsifiers that can inhibit lipid oxidation. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 66(1), 20–35. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.7b05066</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meylan, W. M., &amp; Howard, P. H. (2000). Estimating log P with atom/fragments and water solubility with log P. Perspectives in Drug Discovery and Design, 19(1), 67–84. https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1008715521862</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mezaki, R., Mochizuki, M., &amp; Ogawa, K. (1999). Engineering data on mixing. (1st ed.). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pantazaki, A. A., Dimopoulou, M. I., Simou, O. M., &amp; Pritsa, A. A. (2010). Sunflower seed oil and oleic acid utilization for the production of rhamnolipids by Thermus thermophilus HB8. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 88(4), 939–951. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253‐010‐2802‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, J.‐Y., Myeong, J., Choi, Y., Yu, H., Kwon, C. W., Park, K.‐M., &amp; Chang, P.‐S. (2021). Erythorbyl fatty acid ester as a multi‐functional food emulsifier: Enzymatic synthesis, chemical identification, and functional characterization of erythorbyl myristate. Food Chemistry, 353, 129459. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.129459</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, K.‐M., Jo, S.‐K., Yu, H., Park, J.‐Y., Choi, S. J., Lee, C. J., &amp; Chang, P.‐S. (2018). Erythorbyl laurate as a potential food additive with multi‐functionalities: Antibacterial activity and mode of action. Food Control, 86, 138–145. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.11.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, K.‐M., Lee, M. J., Jo, S.‐K., Choi, S. J., Lee, J., &amp; Chang, P.‐S. (2017). Erythorbyl laurate as a potential food additive with multi‐functionalities: Interfacial characteristics and antioxidant activity. Food Chemistry, 215, 101–107. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.07.174</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peltonen, L. J., &amp; Yliruusi, J. (2000). Surface pressure, hysteresis, interfacial tension, and CMC of four sorbitan monoesters at water–air, water–hexane, and hexane–air interfaces. Journal of Colloid and Interface Science, 227(1), 1–6. https://doi.org/10.1006/jcis.2000.6810</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramana, K. V., Srivastava, S., &amp; Singhal, S. S. (2013). Lipid peroxidation products in human health and disease. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity, 2013, 583438. https://doi.org/10.1155/2013/583438</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rekvig, L., Kranenburg, M., Vreede, J., Hafskjold, B., &amp; Smit, B. (2003). Investigation of surfactant efficiency using dissipative particle dynamics. Langmuir, 19(20), 8195–8205. https://doi.org/10.1021/la0346346</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saavedra Isusi, G. I., Weilandt, M., Majollari, I., Karbstein, H. P., &amp; van der Schaaf, U. S. (2021). Emulsions stabilised with pectin‐based microgels: Investigations into the effect of pH and ionic strength on emulsion stability. Food &amp; Function, 12(16), 7227–7238. https://doi.org/10.1039/D1FO00891A</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sagdeev, D., Gabitov, I. g., Isyanov, C., Khairutdinov, V., Farakhov, M., Zaripov, Z., &amp; Abdulagatov, I. (2019). Densities and viscosities of oleic acid at atmospheric pressure. Journal of the American Oil Chemists' Society, 96(6), 647–662. https://doi.org/10.1002/aocs.12217</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakai, K., Umemoto, N., Matsuda, W., Takamatsu, Y., Matsumoto, M., Sakai, H., &amp; Abe, M. (2011). Oleic acid‐based gemini surfactants with carboxylic acid headgroups. Journal of Oleo Science, 60(8), 411–417. https://doi.org/10.5650/jos.60.411</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sales‐Campos, H., Souza, P. R., Peghini, B. C., da Silva, J. S., &amp; Cardoso, C. R. (2013). An overview of the modulatory effects of oleic acid in health and disease. Mini Reviews in Medicinal Chemistry, 13(2), 201–210. https://doi.org/10.2174/138955713804805193</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, J., Trujillo‐Cayado, L. A., Carrillo, F., López‐Castejón, M. L., &amp; Alfaro‐Rodríguez, M. C. (2022). Relation between droplet size distributions and physical stability for zein microfluidized emulsions. Polymers, 14(11). https://doi.org/10.3390/polym14112195</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Secci, G., Capperucci, A., de Medeiros, A. C., Pellicciari, L., Tanini, D., &amp; Parisi, G. (2023). Effects of two amphiphilic diesters of L‐ascorbic acid on the oxidative stability of rabbit meatballs. Chemistry (Weinheim An Der Bergstrasse, Germany), 5(2), 778–788. https://doi.org/10.3390/chemistry5020055</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sneha, K., &amp; Kumar, A. (2022). Nanoemulsions: Techniques for the preparation and the recent advances in their food applications. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 76, 102914. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2021.102914</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugumar, S., Singh, S., Mukherjee, A., &amp; Chandrasekaran, N. (2016). Nanoemulsion of orange oil with non ionic surfactant produced emulsion using ultrasonication technique: Evaluating against food spoilage yeast. Applied Nanoscience, 6(1), 113–120. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13204‐015‐0412‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, W.‐J., Zhao, H.‐X., Cui, F.‐J., Li, Y.‐H., Yu, S.‐L., Zhou, Q., Qian, J.‐Y., &amp; Dong, Y. (2013). D‐isoascorbyl palmitate: Lipase‐catalyzed synthesis, structural characterization and process optimization using response surface methodology. Chemistry Central Journal, 7(1), 114. https://doi.org/10.1186/1752‐153X‐7‐114</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verboni, M., Lucarini, S., &amp; Duranti, A. (2021). 6'‐O‐lactose ester surfactants as an innovative opportunity in the pharmaceutical field: From synthetic methods to biological applications. Pharmaceuticals, 14(12), 1306. https://doi.org/10.3390/ph14121306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiącek, A. E., &amp; Chibowski, E. (2002). Zeta potential and droplet size of n‐tetradecane/ethanol (protein) emulsions. Colloids and Surfaces B: Biointerfaces, 25(1), 55–67. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0927‐7765(01)00304‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiegand, I., Hilpert, K., &amp; Hancock, R. E. W. (2008). Agar and broth dilution methods to determine the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) of antimicrobial substances. Nature Protocols, 3(2), 163–175. https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2007.521</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, X.‐Y., Li, X.‐C., Mi, J., You, J., &amp; Hai, L. (2013). Design, synthesis and preliminary biological evaluation of brain targeting L‐ascorbic acid prodrugs of ibuprofen. Chinese Chemical Letters, 24(2), 117–119. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cclet.2013.01.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, Z., Singh, R. K., Bao, J., &amp; Wang, C. (2019). Direct effect of solvent viscosity on the physical mass transfer for wavy film flow in a packed column. Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research, 58(37), 17524–17539. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.iecr.9b01226</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yesiloglu, Y., &amp; Kilic, I. (2004). Lipase‐catalyzed esterification of glycerol and oleic acid. Journal of the American Oil Chemists' Society, 81(3), 281–284. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11746‐004‐0896‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, H., Byun, Y., &amp; Chang, P.‐S. (2022). Lipase‐catalyzed two‐step esterification for solvent‐free production of mixed lauric acid esters with antibacterial and antioxidative activities. Food Chemistry, 366, 130650. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130650</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, H., Lee, M. W., Shin, H., Park, K. M., &amp; Chang, P. S. (2019). Lipase‐catalyzed solvent‐free synthesis of erythorbyl laurate in a gas‐solid‐liquid multiphase system. Food Chemistry, 271, 445–449. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.07.134</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamaniahari, S., Jamshidi, A., Moosavy, M.‐H., &amp; Khatibi, S. A. (2022). Preparation and evaluation of Mentha spicata L. essential oil nanoemulsion: Physicochemical properties, antibacterial activity against foodborne pathogens and antioxidant properties. Journal of Food Measurement and Characterization, 16(4), 3289–3300. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11694‐022‐01436‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Q.‐Q., Cai, B.‐X., Gang, H.‐Z., Yang, S.‐Z., &amp; Mu, B.‐Z. (2014). A family of novel bio‐based zwitterionic surfactants derived from oleic acid. RSC Advances, 4(72), 38393–38396. https://doi.org/10.1039/C4RA06851C</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y.‐M., &amp; Rock, C. O. (2008). Membrane lipid homeostasis in bacteria. Nature Reviews Microbiology, 6(3), 222–233. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1839</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>