<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323552</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2054-5703</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Royal Society open science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>R Soc Open Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhanced phytoremediation of cadmium-contaminated soil using chelating agents and plant growth regulators: effect and mechanism.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>240672</StartPage><MedlinePgn>240672</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">240672</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1098/rsos.240672</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The heavy metal cadmium (Cd) is a major threat to food safety and human health. Phytoremediation is the most widely used remediation technology, and how to improve the remediation efficiency of phytoremediation has become a key issue. In this study, we constructed an intensive phytoremediation technology for remediation of Cd-contaminated soil with biodegradable chelating agent and plant growth regulator combined with maize and investigated the mechanism of this technology. The results showed that the best remediation effect was achieved in the treatment with 10<sup>-6</sup> mol l<sup>-1</sup> gibberellic acid (GA<sub>3</sub>) and 6 mmol kg<sup>-1</sup> aspartate diethoxysuccinic acid (AES) combined with maize. In this treatment, the total biomass and extraction efficiency of maize were 3.6 and 8.67 times higher than those of the control, respectively, and the antioxidant enzyme activities of maize were also increased. The soil was enriched with dominant bacterial genera that promote plant growth and metabolism and tolerance to heavy metal stress, which in turn promoted maize growth and Cd accumulation. Structural equation modelling results indicated a large effect of plant Cd concentration and plant antioxidant enzyme activity on plant Cd extraction. The enhanced phytoremediation technology showed good potential for safe use of Cd-contaminated soil.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Qiao</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9227-7757</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Land Consolidation and Rehabilitation Center, Ministry of Natural Resources, Beijing 100035, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Land Science and Technology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing 100083, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Technology Innovation Center of Land Engineering, Ministry of Natural Resources, Beijing 100035, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Hao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Land Science and Technology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing 100083, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Chen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Resource and Environment, Shanxi Agricultural University, Taigu 030801, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Zhongqiu</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Land Science and Technology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing 100083, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ju</LastName><ForeName>Zhengshan</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Land Consolidation and Rehabilitation Center, Ministry of Natural Resources, Beijing 100035, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Technology Innovation Center of Land Engineering, Ministry of Natural Resources, Beijing 100035, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jinman</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Land Science and Technology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing 100083, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bai</LastName><ForeName>Zhongke</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Land Science and Technology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing 100083, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>R Soc Open Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101647528</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2054-5703</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chelating agents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbial communities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">plant extraction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">plant growth regulator</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>We declare we have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11421895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsos.240672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">rsos240672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Xiao M, Qian L, Yang B, Zeng G, Ren S. 2024. Risk assessment of heavy metals in agricultural soil based on the coupling model of Monte Carlo simulation-triangular fuzzy number. Environ. Geochem. Health 46 , 62. (10.1007/s10653-024-01866-y)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-024-01866-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38294573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angon PB, Islam MS, Kc S, Das A, Anjum N, Poudel A, Suchi SA. 2024. Sources, effects and present perspectives of heavy metals contamination: soil, plants and human food chain. Heliyon 10 , e28357. (10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28357)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10999863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38590838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masri S, LeBrón AMW, Logue MD, Valencia E, Ruiz A, Reyes A, Wu J. 2021. Risk assessment of soil heavy metal contamination at the census tract level in the city of Santa Ana, CA: implications for health and environmental justice. Environ. Sci. 23 , 812–830. (10.1039/D1EM00007A)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1EM00007A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8224146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33954329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Okkiah SAF, El-Tahan AM, Ibrahim OM, Taha MA, Korany SM, Alsherif EA, AbdElgawad H, Abo Sen EZF, Sharaf-Eldin MA. 2022. Under cadmium stress, silicon has a defensive effect on the morphology, physiology, and anatomy of pea (Pisum sativum L.) plants. Front. Plant Sci. 13 , 997475. (10.3389/fpls.2022.997475)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.997475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9621089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36325574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarro-León E, Oviedo-Silva J, Ruiz JM, Blasco B. 2019. Possible role of HMA4a TILLING mutants of Brassica rapa in cadmium phytoremediation programs. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 180 , 88–94. (10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.04.081)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.04.081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31078020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sena L, Mica E, Valè G, Vaccino P, Pecchioni N. 2024. Exploring the potential of endophyte-plant interactions for improving crop sustainable yields in a changing climate. Front. Plant Sci. 15 , 1349401. (10.3389/fpls.2024.1349401)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2024.1349401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10988515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38571718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei C, Lei M, Chen T, Zhou C, Gu R. 2022. Method on site-specific source apportionment of domestic soil pollution across China through public data mining: a case study on cadmium from non-ferrous industries. Environ. Pollut. 295 , 118605. (10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118605)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34896223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Hou D, O’Connor D, Shen Z, Shi P, Ok YS, Tsang DCW, Wen Y, Luo M. 2019. Lead contamination in Chinese surface soils: source identification, spatial-temporal distribution and associated health risks. Crit. Rev. Environ. Sci. Technol. 49 , 1386–1423. (10.1080/10643389.2019.1571354)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10643389.2019.1571354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheraghi-Aliakbari S, Beheshti-Alagha A, Ranjbar F, Nosratti I. 2020. Comparison of Myagrum perfoliatum and Sophora alopecuroides in phytoremediation of Cd- and Pb-contaminated soils: a chemical and biological investigation. Chemosphere 259 , 127450. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127450)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32593006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashraf S, Ali Q, Zahir ZA, Ashraf S, Asghar HN. 2019. Phytoremediation: environmentally sustainable way for reclamation of heavy metal polluted soils. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 174 , 714–727. (10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.02.068)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.02.068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30878808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu P, Song Y, Wei J, Mao W, Ju J, Zheng S, Zhao H. 2023. Synergistic effects of earthworms and plants on chromium removal from acidic and alkaline soils: biological responses and implications. Biology 12 , 831. (10.3390/biology12060831)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biology12060831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10295528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37372116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunningham SD, Berti WR. 2020. Phytoextraction and phytostabilization: technical, economic, and regulatory considerations of the soil-lead issue. In Phytoremediation of contaminated soil and water, pp. 359–376. Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press. (10.1201/9780367803148-19)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1201/9780367803148-19</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng X, Zhao R, Yang Y, Zhou Y, Zhu Y, Qin P, Wang M, Huang H. 2023. Effect of the combination of phosphate-solubilizing bacteria with orange residue-based activator on the phytoremediation of cadmium by ryegrass. Plants 12 , 2727. (10.3390/plants12142727)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants12142727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10384834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37514342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villacís J, Casanoves F, Hang S, Keesstra S, Armas C. 2016. Selection of forest species for the rehabilitation of disturbed soils in oil fields in the Ecuadorian Amazon. Sci. Total Environ. 566–567 , 761–770. (10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.05.102)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.05.102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27239719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Z, Xi M, Jiang G, Liu X, Bai Z, Huang Y. 2010. Effects of IDSA, EDDS and EDTA on heavy metals accumulation in hydroponically grown maize (Zea mays, L.). J. Hazard. Mater. 181 , 455–459. (10.1016/j.jhazmat.2010.05.032)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2010.05.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20627568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang H, Fan L, Zhao Y, Jin Q, Yang G, Zhao D, Xu Z. 2022. Integrating Broussonetia papyrifera and two bacillus species to repair soil antimony pollutions. Front. Microbiol. 13 , 871581. (10.3389/fmicb.2022.871581)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.871581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9111523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35592006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karam EA, Maresca V, Sorbo S, Keramat B, Basile A. 2017. Effects of triacontanol on ascorbate-glutathione cycle in Brassica napus L. exposed to cadmium-induced oxidative stress. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 144 , 268–274. (10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.06.035)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.06.035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28633105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun S, Zhou X, Cui X, Liu C, Fan Y, McBride MB, Li Y, Li Z, Zhuang P. 2020. Exogenous plant growth regulators improved phytoextraction efficiency by Amaranths hypochondriacus L. in cadmium contaminated soil. Plant Growth Regul. 90 , 29–40. (10.1007/s10725-019-00548-5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10725-019-00548-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren XM, Guo SJ, Tian W, Chen Y, Han H, Chen E, Li BL, Li YY, Chen ZJ. 2019. Effects of plant growth-promoting bacteria (PGPB) inoculation on the growth, antioxidant activity, Cu uptake, and bacterial community structure of rape (Brassica napus L.) grown in Cu-contaminated agricultural soil. Front. Microbiol. 10 , 1455. (10.3389/fmicb.2019.01455)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6610483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31316489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Wang H, Wang H. 2020. Mechanisms of plant tolerance to heavy metals mediated by gibberellic acid. J. Ecol. Rural Environ. 36 , 137–144. (10.19741/j.issn.1673-4831.2019.0689)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19741/j.issn.1673-4831.2019.0689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L, Long C, Wang D, Yang J. 2020. Phytoremediation of cadmium (Cd) and uranium (U) contaminated soils by Brassica juncea L. enhanced with exogenous application of plant growth regulators. Chemosphere 242 , 125112. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125112)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31669993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du M, Zhang J, Wang G, Liu C, Wang Z. 2022. Response of bacterial community composition and co-occurrence network to straw and straw biochar incorporation. Front. Microbiol. 13 , 999399. (10.3389/fmicb.2022.999399)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.999399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9563622</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36246223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M, Li S, Chen S, Meng N, Li X, Zheng H, Zhao C, Wang D. 2019. Manipulation of the rhizosphere bacterial community by biofertilizers is associated with mitigation of cadmium phytotoxicity. Sci. Total Environ. 649 , 413–421. (10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.08.174)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.08.174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30176454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarwar N, Imran M, Shaheen MR, Ishaque W, Kamran MA, Matloob A, Rehim A, Hussain S. 2017. Phytoremediation strategies for soils contaminated with heavy metals: modifications and future perspectives. Chemosphere 171 , 710–721. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.12.116)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.12.116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28061428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mojiri A. 2011. The potential of corn (Zea mays) for phytoremediation of soil contaminated with cadmium and lead. J. Biol. Environ. Sci. 5 , 17–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Košnář Z, Mercl F, Tlustoš P. 2018. Ability of natural attenuation and phytoremediation using maize (Zea mays L.) to decrease soil contents of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) derived from biomass fly ash in comparison with PAHs-spiked soil. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 153 , 16–22. (10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.01.049)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.01.049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29407733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu W. 2014. Study on the mechanism of cadmium tolerance and enhanced enrichment in super sweet 38 maize. Guangzhou, China: South China University of Technology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Yang C, Yu H, Zhao Z, Bai Z. 2021. The addition of degradable chelating agents enhances maize phytoremediation efficiency in Cd-contaminated soils. Chemosphere 269 , 129373. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.129373)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.129373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33387792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Zong L, Huang Y. 2002. Application of chelators to phytoremediation of heavy metal polluted soils. Soil Env. 11 , 303–306. (10.16258/j.cnki.1674-5906.2002.03.020)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16258/j.cnki.1674-5906.2002.03.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou W, Leul M. 1999. Uniconazole-induced tolerance of rape plants to heat stress in relation to changes in hormonal levels, enzyme activities and lipid peroxidation. Plant Growth Regul. 27 , 99–104. (10.1023/A:1006165603300)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1006165603300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Zhao Z, Bai Z, Hou H, Yuan Y, Guo A, Li Y. 2019. Effects of mycorrhizae and water conditions on perennial ryegrass growth in rare earth tailings. RSC Adv. 9 , 10881–10888. (10.1039/C8RA10442E)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C8RA10442E</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9062534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35515284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu R. 2000. Soil agrochemical analysis method. Beijing, China: China Agricultural Science Technology Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bao S. 2001. Soil agrochemical analysis. Beijing, China: China Agricultural Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahedipour-Sheshglani P, Asghari M. 2020. Impact of foliar spray with 24-epibrassinolide on yield, quality, ripening physiology and productivity of the strawberry. Sci. Hortic. 268 , 109376. (10.1016/j.scienta.2020.109376)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2020.109376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fässler E, Evangelou MW, Robinson BH, Schulin R. 2010. Effects of indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) on sunflower growth and heavy metal uptake in combination with ethylene diamine disuccinic acid (EDDS). Chemosphere 80 , 901–907. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.04.077)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.04.077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20537682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu S, et al. . 2019. Inoculation of Pseudomonas sp. GHD-4 and mushroom residue carrier increased the soil enzyme activities and microbial community diversity in Pb-contaminated soils. J. Soils Sediments 19 , 1064–1076. (10.1007/s11368-018-2111-3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11368-018-2111-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geisseler D, Scow KM. 2014. Long-term effects of mineral fertilizers on soil microorganisms—a review. Soil Biol. Biochem. 75 , 54–63. (10.1016/j.soilbio.2014.03.023)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2014.03.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Wang Y, Bai J, Liu Z, Song X, Yan D, Abiyu A, Zhao Z, Yan D. 2017. High efficiency of inorganic nitrogen removal by integrating biofilm-electrode with constructed wetland: autotrophic denitrifying bacteria analysis. Bioresour. Technol. 227 , 7–14. (10.1016/j.biortech.2016.12.046)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2016.12.046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28012375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logan BE, Regan JM. 2006. Microbial fuel cells—challenges and applications. Environ. Sci. Technol. 40 , 5172–5180. (10.1021/es0627592)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es0627592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16999086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barns SM, Cain EC, Sommerville L, Kuske CR. 2007. Acidobacteria phylum sequences in uranium-contaminated subsurface sediments greatly expand the known diversity within the phylum. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 73 , 3113–3116. (10.1128/AEM.02012-06)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02012-06</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1892891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17337544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang R, Cui X, Luo X, Mao P, Zhuang P, Li Y, Li Y, Li Z. 2021. Effects of plant growth regulator and chelating agent on the phytoextraction of heavy metals by Pfaffia glomerata and on the soil microbial community. Environ. Pollut. 283 , 117159. (10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117159)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33878683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Wang X, Huang H, Wang L, Wei F, Zhang C, Rong Q. 2021. Effect of multiple heavy metals pollution to bacterial diversity and community structure in farmland soils. Hum. Ecol. Risk Assess. 27 , 724–741. (10.1080/10807039.2020.1752143)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10807039.2020.1752143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vujčić Bok V, Gerić M, Gajski G, Gagić S, Domijan AM. 2023. Phytotoxicity of bisphenol A to Allium cepa root cells is mediated through growth hormone gibberellic acid and reactive oxygen species. Molecules 28 , 2046. (10.3390/molecules28052046)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28052046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10004651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36903292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tassi E, Pouget J, Petruzzelli G, Barbafieri M. 2008. The effects of exogenous plant growth regulators in the phytoextraction of heavy metals. Chemosphere 71 , 66–73. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2007.10.027)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2007.10.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18037469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rady MM, Boriek SHK, Abd El-Mageed TA, Seif El-Yazal MA, Ali EF, Hassan FAS, Abdelkhalik A. 2021. Exogenous gibberellic acid or dilute bee honey boosts drought stress tolerance in Vicia faba by rebalancing osmoprotectants, antioxidants, nutrients, and phytohormones. Plants 10 , 748. (10.3390/plants10040748)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants10040748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8068922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33920494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Wang Y, Li J, Cai Y, Hu M, Lin W, Wu Z. 2024. Effects of continuous monoculture on rhizosphere soil nutrients, growth, physiological characteristics, hormone metabolome of Casuarina equisetifolia and their interaction analysis. Heliyon 10 , e26078. (10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e26078)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e26078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10878944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38384578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abu-Ria ME, Elghareeb EM, Shukry WM, Abo-Hamed SA, Ibraheem F. 2024. Mitigation of drought stress in maize and sorghum by humic acid: differential growth and physiological responses. BMC Plant Biol. 24 , 514. (10.1186/s12870-024-05184-4)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12870-024-05184-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11157776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38849739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang C, Han H, Dai J, Wang Z, Chai Y, Lu C, Chen H. 2020. A dissipation pattern of gibberellic acid and its metabolite, isogibberellic acid, during tea planting, manufacturing, and brewing. J. Agric. Food Chem. 68 , 14417–14425. (10.1021/acs.jafc.0c06025)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.0c06025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33191742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng J, Li T, Wei S, Jiang W, Li J, Wang Y, Li Y. 2023. Physiological and proteomic changes in Camellia semiserrata in response to aluminum stress. Genes 15 , 55. (10.3390/genes15010055)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/genes15010055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10815133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38254944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali N, Hadi F. 2015. Phytoremediation of cadmium improved with the high production of endogenous phenolics and free proline contents in Parthenium hysterophorus plant treated exogenously with plant growth regulator and chelating agent. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 22 , 13305–13318. (10.1007/s11356-015-4595-3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-015-4595-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25940488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadi F, Bano A, Fuller MP. 2010. The improved phytoextraction of lead (Pb) and the growth of maize (Zea mays L.): the role of plant growth regulators (GA3 and IAA) and EDTA alone and in combinations. Chemosphere 80 , 457–462. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.04.020)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.04.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20435330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji P, Tang X, Jiang Y, Tong Y, Gao P, Han W. 2015. Potential of gibberellic acid 3 (GA3) for enhancing the phytoremediation efficiency of Solanum nigrum L. Bull. Environ. Contam. Toxicol. 95 , 810–814. (10.1007/s00128-015-1670-x)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00128-015-1670-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26471997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camara MC, Vandenberghe L, Rodrigues C, de Oliveira J, Faulds C, Bertrand E, Soccol CR. 2018. Current advances in gibberellic acid (GA3) production, patented technologies and potential applications. Planta 248 , 1049–1062. (10.1007/s00425-018-2959-x)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00425-018-2959-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30069731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin H, Wang Z, Sha W, Song S, Qin F, Zhang W. 2024. Role of plant-growth-promoting rhizobacteria in plant machinery for soil heavy metal detoxification. Microorganisms 12 , 700. (10.3390/microorganisms12040700)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12040700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11052264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38674644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carloalberto P, Ko H, Jozsef S, Seth D. 2015. Mapping of a cellulose-deficient mutant named dwarf1-1 in sorghum bicolor to the green revolution gene gibberellin20-oxidase reveals a positive regulatory association between gibberellin and cellulose biosynthesis. Plant Physiol. 169 , 705–716. (10.1104/pp.15.00928)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1104/pp.15.00928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4577427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26198258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Que F, Khadr A, Wang GL, Li T, Wang YH, Xu ZS, Xiong AS. 2018. Exogenous brassinosteroids altered cell length, gibberellin content, and cellulose deposition in promoting carrot petiole elongation. Plant Sci. 277 , 110–120. (10.1016/j.plantsci.2018.10.010)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2018.10.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30466576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehsan S, Ali S, Noureen S, Mahmood K, Farid M, Ishaque W, Shakoor MB, Rizwan M. 2014. Citric acid assisted phytoremediation of cadmium by Brassica napus L. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 106 , 164–172. (10.1016/j.ecoenv.2014.03.007)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2014.03.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24840879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng W, He Y, He S, Luo J, Zeng Y, Zhang X, Huo Y, Jie Y, Xing H. 2023. Exogenous plant growth regulator and foliar fertilizers for phytoextraction of cadmium with Boehmeria nivea [L.] Gaudich from contaminated field soil. Sci. Rep. 13 , 11019. (10.1038/s41598-023-37971-8)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-37971-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10329045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37419889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Tang Y, Zhang H, Zhang X, Sun X, Zang X, Xu N. 2024. Physiological, transcriptome, and metabolome analyses reveal the tolerance to Cu toxicity in red macroalgae Gracilariopsis lemaneiformis. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 25 , 4770. (10.3390/ijms25094770)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms25094770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11083833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38731988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He S, Wu Q, He Z. 2014. Synergetic effects of DA-6/GA₃ with EDTA on plant growth, extraction and detoxification of Cd by Lolium perenne. Chemosphere 117 , 132–138. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.06.015)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.06.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24999226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Gao P, Li D, Liu J, Yang N, Gu W, He X, Tang W. 2019. Risk assessment for and microbial community changes in farmland soil contaminated with heavy metals and metalloids. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 185 , 109685. (10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.109685)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.109685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31541947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burkhardt EM, Bischoff S, Akob DM, Büchel G, Küsel K. 2011. Heavy metal tolerance of Fe(III)-reducing microbial communities in contaminated creek bank soils. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 77 , 3132–3136. (10.1128/AEM.02085-10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02085-10</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3126387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21378042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang JZ, Li XZ, Yin YB, Luo SC, Wang DX, Zheng H, Liu YX. 2024. High-throughput sequencing-based analysis of the composition and diversity of the endophyte community in roots of Stellera chamaejasme. Sci. Rep. 14 , 8607. (10.1038/s41598-024-59055-x)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-59055-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11016073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38615120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo H, Nasir M, Lv J, Dai Y, Gao J. 2017. Understanding the variation of microbial community in heavy metals contaminated soil using high throughput sequencing. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 144 , 300–306. (10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.06.048)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.06.048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28645031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai X, Li Y, Jing X, Zhao X, Zhao P. 2023. Response mechanisms of bacterial communities and nitrogen cycle functional genes in millet rhizosphere soil to chromium stress. Front. Microbiol. 14 , 1116535. (10.3389/fmicb.2023.1116535)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1116535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9992798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36910173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maynaud G, Willems A, Soussou S, Vidal C, Mauré L, Moulin L, Cleyet-Marel JC, Brunel B. 2012. Molecular and phenotypic characterization of strains nodulating Anthyllis vulneraria in mine tailings, and proposal of Aminobacter anthyllidis sp. nov., the first definition of Aminobacter as legume-nodulating bacteria. Syst. Appl. Microbiol. 35 , 65–72. (10.1016/j.syapm.2011.11.002)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2011.11.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22221859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asaf S, Numan M, Khan AL, Al-Harrasi A. 2020. Sphingomonas: from diversity and genomics to functional role in environmental remediation and plant growth. Crit. Rev. Biotechnol. 40 , 138–152. (10.1080/07388551.2019.1709793)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07388551.2019.1709793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31906737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M, Chen S, Chen L, Wang D. 2019. Responses of soil microbial communities and their network interactions to saline-alkaline stress in Cd-contaminated soils. Environ. Pollut. 252 , 1609–1621. (10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.082)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31284203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L, Hao Z, Li K, Sha Y, Wang E, Sui X, Mi G, Tian C, Chen W. 2021. Effects of growth-promoting rhizobacteria on maize growth and rhizosphere microbial community under conservation tillage in northeast China. Microb. Biotechnol. 14 , 535–550. (10.1111/1751-7915.13693)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7936301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33166080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Z, Te SH, He Y, Gin KYH. 2018. The characteristics and dynamics of cyanobacteria–heterotrophic bacteria between two estuarine reservoirs: tropical versus sub-tropical regions. Front. Microbiol. 9 , 2531. (10.3389/fmicb.2018.02531)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.02531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6232297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30459732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahid M, Dumat C, Khalid S, Niazi NK, Antunes P. 2016. Cadmium bioavailability, uptake, toxicity and detoxification in soil-plant system. Rev. Environ. Contam. Toxicol. 241 , 73–137. (10.1007/398_2016_8)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/398_2016_8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27300014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizwan M, Usman K, Alsafran M, Jabri HA, Samreen T, Saleem MH, Tu S. 2022. Nickel toxicity interferes with NO3 −/NH4 + uptake and nitrogen metabolic enzyme activity in rice (Oryza sativa L.). Plants 11 , 1401. (10.3390/plants11111401)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants11111401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9182924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35684174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Han D, Yang H, Liu Z, Gao C, Liu Y. 2023. Effects of peach branch organic fertilizer on the soil microbial community in peach orchards. Front. Microbiol. 14 , 1223420. (10.3389/fmicb.2023.1223420)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1223420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10361838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37485500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S, Ning Y, Li H, Zhu Y. 2024. Effects of Priestia aryabhattai on phosphorus fraction and implications for ecoremediating Cd-contaminated farmland with plant-microbe technology. Plants 13 , 268. (10.3390/plants13020268)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants13020268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10818761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38256821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin H, Liu J, Dong Y, Ren K, Zhang Y. 2018. Absorption characteristics of compound heavy metals vanadium, chromium, and cadmium in water by emergent macrophytes and its combinations. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 25 , 17820–17829. (10.1007/s11356-018-1785-9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-1785-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29679268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo J, Li Y, Su S, Huang X, Zhuo C. 2016. Response of antioxidant enzymes and PCs in root of Neyraudia reynaudiana to Cd, Pb stress. Ecol. Environ. Sci. 25 , 1047–1053. (10.16258/j.cnki.1674-5906.2016.06.019)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16258/j.cnki.1674-5906.2016.06.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang R, et al. . 2022. An amino acid fertilizer improves the emergent accumulator plant Nasturtium officinale R. Br. phytoremediation capability for cadmium-contaminated paddy soils. Front. Plant Sci. 13 , 1003743. (10.3389/fpls.2022.1003743)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.1003743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9592069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36299780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y, Wang L, You Y, Cheng Y, Ma J, Chen F. 2022. Enhancing network complexity and function of soil bacteria by thiourea-modified biochar under cadmium stress in post-mining area. Chemosphere 302 , 134811. (10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.134811)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.134811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35504469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, et al. . 2019. Microbial functional diversity and carbon use feedback in soils as affected by heavy metals. Environ. Int. 125 , 478–488. (10.1016/j.envint.2019.01.071)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2019.01.071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30771648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang G, Ren Y, Bai X, Su Y, Han J. 2022. Contributions of beneficial microorganisms in soil remediation and quality improvement of medicinal plants. Plants 11 , 3200. (10.3390/plants11233200)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants11233200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9740990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36501240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao L, Zhang C, Wang G, Guan D, Zhang R, Chen Y, Dai J. 2020. Influencing pathways of soil microbial attributes on accumulation of heavy metals in brassica (Brassica campestris L. ssp. chinensis var. utilis Tsen et Lee) leaves. Environ. Pollut. 262 , 114215. (10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114215)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu M, Liang J, Tang J, Li G, Shan S, Guo Z, Deng L. 2017. Decontamination of multiple heavy metals-containing effluents through microbial biotechnology. J. Hazard. Mater. 337 , 189–197. (10.1016/j.jhazmat.2017.05.006)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2017.05.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28521206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Yu H, Yang C, Zhao ZQ, Ju ZS, Wang JM, Bai ZK. 2024. Data from: Enhanced phytoremediation of cadmium contaminated soil using chelating agents and plant growth regulators. Dryad Digital Repository. (10.5061/dryad.44j0zpcnv)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5061/dryad.44j0zpcnv</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>