<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39332574</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>280</Volume><Issue>Pt 4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multifunctional honeysuckle extract/attapulgite/chitosan composite films containing natural carbon dots for intelligent food packaging.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136042</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136042</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136042</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)06851-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In order to fulfill people's requirements for food quality and safety, it is a promising strategy to develop intelligent biodegradable food packaging materials. Herein, honeysuckle extracts/attapulgite/chitosan composite films containing natural carbon dots were fabricated for intelligent food packaging. Different characterization techniques were employed to study the obtained composite films, while the physicochemical properties, optical properties, antibacterial and antioxidant activities of composite films were determined. The obtained composite films presented good mechanical, antibacterial and antioxidant properties, and the antibacterial ratios of composite films against Escherichia coli and Staphylococcus aureus were 99.27 ± 0.18 % and 98.85 ± 0.65 %, respectively. When the added amount of honeysuckle extracts/attapulgite nanocomposites was 4.76 %, the tensile strength and elongation at break of composite films reached 24.9 ± 2.35 MPa and 64.8 ± 2.11 %, respectively, which were obviously higher than that of pure chitosan film. Furthermore, the composite films exhibited excellent UV shielding and blue fluorescence properties, as well as pH-sensitivity due to the presence of caffeoquinic acid-based natural carbon dots derived from honeysuckle extract. Therefore, the composite films indicated a potential application for intelligent food packaging.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Wenting</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Clay Minerals of Gansu Province, Research Center of Resource Chemistry and Energy Materials, Lanzhou Institute of Chemical Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lanzhou 730000, PR China; Center of Materials Science and Optoelectronics Engineering, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mu</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Clay Minerals of Gansu Province, Research Center of Resource Chemistry and Energy Materials, Lanzhou Institute of Chemical Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lanzhou 730000, PR China; Center of Materials Science and Optoelectronics Engineering, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, PR China. Electronic address: mubin@licp.cas.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Fangfang</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Clay Minerals of Gansu Province, Research Center of Resource Chemistry and Energy Materials, Lanzhou Institute of Chemical Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lanzhou 730000, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yalong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory Medicine Center, Lanzhou University Second Hospital, Lanzhou 730030, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaomei</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Clay Minerals of Gansu Province, Research Center of Resource Chemistry and Energy Materials, Lanzhou Institute of Chemical Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lanzhou 730000, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Aiqin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Clay Minerals of Gansu Province, Research Center of Resource Chemistry and Energy Materials, Lanzhou Institute of Chemical Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lanzhou 730000, PR China; Center of Materials Science and Optoelectronics Engineering, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, PR China. Electronic address: aqwang@licp.cas.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chitosan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Honeysuckle extract</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intelligent food preservation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39332574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)06851-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>