<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39339268</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1999-4923</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pharmaceutics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pharmaceutics</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Unlocking the Potential of Silver Nanoparticles: From Synthesis to Versatile Bio-Applications.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1232</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/pharmaceutics16091232</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Silver nanoparticles (AgNPs) are leading the way in nanotechnological innovation, combining the captivating properties of silver with the accuracy of nanoscale engineering, thus revolutionizing material science. Three main techniques arise within the alchemical domains of AgNP genesis: chemical, physical, and biological synthesis. Each possesses its distinct form of magic for controlling size, shape, and scalability-key factors necessary for achieving expertise in the practical application of nanoparticles. The story unravels, describing the careful coordination of chemical reduction, the environmentally sensitive charm of green synthesis utilizing plant extracts, and the precise accuracy of physical techniques. AgNPs are highly praised in the field of healthcare for their powerful antibacterial characteristics. These little warriors display a wide-ranging attack against bacteria, fungi, parasites, and viruses. Their critical significance in combating hospital-acquired and surgical site infections is highly praised, serving as a beacon of hope in the fight against the challenging problem of antibiotic resistance. In addition to their ability to kill bacteria, AgNPs are also known to promote tissue regeneration and facilitate wound healing. The field of cancer has also observed the adaptability of AgNPs. The review documents their role as innovative carriers of drugs, specifically designed to target cancer cells with accuracy, minimizing harm to healthy tissues. Additionally, it explores their potential as cancer therapy or anticancer agents capable of disrupting the growth of tumors. In the food business, AgNPs are utilized to enhance the durability of packing materials and coatings by infusing them with their bactericidal properties. This results in improved food safety measures and a significant increase in the duration that products can be stored, thereby tackling the crucial issue of food preservation. This academic analysis recognizes the many difficulties that come with the creation and incorporation of AgNPs. This statement pertains to the evaluation of environmental factors and the effort to enhance synthetic processes. The review predicts future academic pursuits, envisioning progress that will enhance the usefulness of AgNPs and increase their importance from being new to becoming essential within the realms of science and industry. Besides, AgNPs are not only a subject of scholarly interest but also a crucial component in the continuous effort to tackle some of the most urgent health and conservation concerns of contemporary society. This review aims to explore the complex process of AgNP synthesis and highlight their numerous uses, with a special focus on their growing importance in the healthcare and food business sectors. This review invites the scientific community to explore the extensive possibilities of AgNPs in order to fully understand and utilize their potential.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almatroudi</LastName><ForeName>Ahmad</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1491-6402</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratories, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Qassim University, Buraydah 51452, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>(QU-APC-2024-9/1)</GrantID><Agency>The Researchers would like to thank the Deanship of Graduate Studies and Scientific Research at Qassim University for financial support</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Pharmaceutics</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101534003</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1999-4923</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cancer therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">other applications</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">silver nanoparticles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">synthesis methods</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39339268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11435049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics16091232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">pharmaceutics16091232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zhang X.F., Liu Z.G., Shen W., Gurunathan S. Silver Nanoparticles: Synthesis, Characterization, Properties, Applications, and Therapeutic Approaches. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2016;17:1534. doi: 10.3390/ijms17091534.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms17091534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5037809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27649147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almatroudi A. Silver Nanoparticles: Synthesis, Characterisation and Biomedical Applications. Open Life Sci. 2020;15:819–839. doi: 10.1515/biol-2020-0094.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/biol-2020-0094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7747521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33817269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L., Wang Y.Y., Huang J., Chen C.Y., Wang Z., Xie H. Silver Nanoparticles: Synthesis, Medical Applications and Biosafety. Theranostics. 2020;10:8996–9031. doi: 10.7150/thno.45413.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7150/thno.45413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7415816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32802176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galdiero S., Falanga A., Vitiello M., Cantisani M., Marra V.L.N., Galdiero M. Silver Nanoparticles as Potential Antiviral Agents. Molecules. 2011;16:8894–8918. doi: 10.3390/molecules16108894.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules16108894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6264685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22024958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burdușel A.-C., Gherasim O., Grumezescu A.M., Mogoantă L., Ficai A., Andronescu E. Biomedical Applications of Silver Nanoparticles: An Up-to-Date Overview. Nanomaterials. 2018;8:681. doi: 10.3390/nano8090681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano8090681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6163202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30200373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shinde R.P., Borle A., Dahane T., Kambala S.S. Comparative Evaluation of Antimicrobial Activity of Irreversible Hydrocolloid Impression Material Incorporated with Various Disinfectants—An in-Vitro Study. J. Pharm. Res. Int. 2021;33:3274–3280. doi: 10.9734/jpri/2021/v33i60B35004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/jpri/2021/v33i60B35004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moaddabi A., Soltani P., Rengo C., Molaei S., Mousavi S.J., Mehdizadeh M., Spagnuolo G. Comparison of Antimicrobial and Wound-Healing Effects of Silver Nanoparticle and Chlorhexidine Mouthwashes: An in Vivo Study in Rabbits. Odontology. 2022;110:577–583. doi: 10.1007/s10266-022-00690-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10266-022-00690-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9170635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35218448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunasekaran T., Nigusse T., Dhanaraju M.D. Silver Nanoparticles as Real Topical Bullets for Wound Healing. J. Am. Coll. Clin. Wound Spec. 2011;3:82–96. doi: 10.1016/j.jcws.2012.05.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcws.2012.05.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3921230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24527370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rai M., Kon K., Ingle A.P., Durán N., Galdiero S., Galdiero M. Broad-Spectrum Bioactivities of Silver Nanoparticles: The Emerging Trends and Future Prospects. Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2014;98:1951–1961. doi: 10.1007/s00253-013-5473-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-013-5473-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7080016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24407450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piri H., Mohammadi Z., Aali E., Hosseini S.A.H., Naderi Y., Gheibi N. The Effects of Oral Silver Nanoparticles and Propolis on the Level of Lipid Peroxidation in Male Wistar Rats. J. Qazvin Univ. Med. Sci. 2021;25:93–98. doi: 10.32598/JQUMS.25.2.1249.4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.32598/JQUMS.25.2.1249.4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nambiar S.S., Mohanty A., Patra A., Saini G.K. Deciphering Therapeutic Efficacy of Mycosynthesized Silver Nanoparticles Using Entomopathogenic Fungi Metarhizium anisopliae Against McF-7 Breast Cancer Cells in Vitro. bioRxiv. 2022 doi: 10.1101/2022.08.25.505221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2022.08.25.505221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad K., Noor R., Younus M., Chohan A., Habiba U., Asif H.M., Chishti A.W., Saifullah. S. Green Synthesis and Characterization of Silver Nanoparticles Using Crude Extract of Crotalaria Burhia. RADS J. Pharm. Pharm. Sci. 2020;8:209–215. doi: 10.37962/jpps.v8i4.464.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.37962/jpps.v8i4.464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christania F.S., Dwiastuti R., Yuliani S.H. Lipid and Silver Nanoparticles Gels Formulation of Tempeh Extract. J. Pharm. Sci. Community. 2020;16:56–62. doi: 10.24071/jpsc.002032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.24071/jpsc.002032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John T., Parmar K.A., Tak P. Biosynthesis and Characterization of Silver Nanoparticles from Tinospora Cordifolia Root Extract. J. Nanosci. Technol. 2019;5:622–626. doi: 10.30799/jnst.211.19050112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30799/jnst.211.19050112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zande M.v.d., Vandebriel R.J., Doren E.V., Kramer E., Rivera Z.H., Serrano-Rojero C.S., Gremmer E.R., Mast J., Peters R., Hollman P.C.H., et al. Distribution, Elimination, and Toxicity of Silver Nanoparticles and Silver Ions in Rats After 28-Day Oral Exposure. ACS Nano. 2012;6:7427–7442. doi: 10.1021/nn302649p.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/nn302649p</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22857815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antsiferova A.A., Kopaeva M.Y., Kochkin V., Kashkarov P.K. Kinetics of Silver Accumulation in Tissues of Laboratory Mice After Long-Term Oral Administration of Silver Nanoparticles. Nanomaterials. 2021;11:3204. doi: 10.3390/nano11123204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11123204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8708219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34947553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekar P., Panneerselvam C., Murugan K., Aarthi N., Kalimuthu K., Thangamani S. Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Leaves of Catharanthus Roseus Linn. G. Don and Their Antiplasmodial Activities. Asian Pac. J. Trop. Biomed. 2012;2:574–580. doi: 10.1016/s2221-1691(12)60100-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s2221-1691(12)60100-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3609350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23569974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heydari R., Rashidipour M. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Extract of Oak Fruit Hull (Jaft): Synthesis and in Vitro Cytotoxic Effect on McF-7 Cells. Int. J. Breast Cancer. 2015;2015:846743. doi: 10.1155/2015/846743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2015/846743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4313055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25685560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das V.L., Thomas R., Varghese R., Soniya E.V., Mathew J., Radhakrishnan E.K. Extracellular Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles by the Bacillus Strain CS 11 Isolated from Industrialized Area. 3Biotech. 2013;4:121–126. doi: 10.1007/s13205-013-0130-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13205-013-0130-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3964251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28324441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parveen R., Maiti P.K., Murmu N., Datta A. Preparation of Serum Capped Silver Nanoparticles for Selective Killing of Microbial Cells Sparing Host Cells. Sci. Rep. 2021;11:11610. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-91031-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-91031-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8172638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34078983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsharif S.M., Salem S.S., Abdel-Rahman M.A., Fouda A., Eid A.M., Hassan S.E.-D., Awad M.A., Mohamed A.A. Multifunctional Properties of Spherical Silver Nanoparticles Fabricated by Different Microbial Taxa. Heliyon. 2020;6:e03943. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e03943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e03943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7268287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32518846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D., Kwon S.-J., Wu X., Sauve J., Lee I., Nam J., Kim J., Dordick J.S. Selective Killing of Pathogenic Bacteria by Antimicrobial Silver Nanoparticle—Cell Wall Binding Domain Conjugates. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2018;10:13317–13324. doi: 10.1021/acsami.8b00181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.8b00181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29619821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terzioğlu E., Arslan M., Balaban B.G., Çakar Z.P. Microbial Silver Resistance Mechanisms: Recent Developments. World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2022;38:158. doi: 10.1007/s11274-022-03341-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11274-022-03341-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35821348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaiser K.G., Delattre V., Frost V.J., Buck G.W., Phu J.V., Fernandez T.G., Pavel I.E. Nanosilver: An Old Antibacterial Agent with Great Promise in the Fight against Antibiotic Resistance. Antibiotics. 2023;12:1264. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics12081264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12081264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10451389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37627684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>More P.R., Pandit S., Filippis A.D., Franci G., Mijakovic I., Galdiero M. Silver Nanoparticles: Bactericidal and Mechanistic Approach against Drug Resistant Pathogens. Microorganisms. 2023;11:369. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms11020369.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms11020369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9961011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36838334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi A.S., Singh P., Mijakovic I. Interactions of Gold and Silver Nanoparticles with Bacterial Biofilms: Molecular Interactions behind Inhibition and Resistance. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2020;21:7658. doi: 10.3390/ijms21207658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms21207658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7589962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33081366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosier-Boss P.A., Sorensen K.C., George R.D., Sims P.C., Obraztsova A. Surface Enhanced Raman Scattering of Bacteria Using Capped and Uncapped Silver Nanoparticles. Spectrochim. Acta Part A Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc. 2020;242:118742. doi: 10.1016/j.saa.2020.118742.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.saa.2020.118742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32717522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar P., Selvi S.S., Prabha A.L., Kumar K., Ganeshkumar R., Govindaraju M. Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles from Sargassum Tenerrimum and Screening Phytochemicals for Its Antibacterial Activity. Nano Biomed Eng. 2012;4:12–16. doi: 10.5101/nbe.v4i1.p12-16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5101/nbe.v4i1.p12-16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esmail R., Alihosseini A., Milani M., Akbarzadeh A., Akhondi E. Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles with High Efficiency and Stability by Culture Supernatant of Bacillus ROM6 Isolated from Zarshouran Gold Mine and Evaluating Its Antibacterial Effects. BMC Microbiol. 2022;22:97. doi: 10.1186/s12866-022-02490-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12866-022-02490-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8996393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35410116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sani N.J., Aminu B.M., Mukhtar M. Eco-Friendly Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Lactobacillus delbrueckii Subsp. Bulgaricus Isolated from Kindrimo (Locally Fermented Milk) in Kano State, Nigeria. Bayero J. Pure Appl. Sci. 2018;10:481. doi: 10.4314/bajopas.v10i1.92s.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4314/bajopas.v10i1.92s</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson J.J., Harimuralikrishnaa T., Ponmanickam P., Lakshmi M.P. Mosquito Research—Recent Advances in Pathogen Interactions, Immunity, and Vector Control Strategies. IntechOpen; London, UK: 2023. Bacterial Silver Nanoparticles: Method, Mechanism of Synthesis and Application in Mosquito Control.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5772/intechopen.104144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Shanshoury A.E.R., Elsilk S.E., Ebeid M.E. Extracellular Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Escherichia coli ATCC 8739, Bacillus subtilis ATCC 6633, and Streptococcus thermophilus ESh1 and Their Antimicrobial Activities. ISRN Nanotechnol. 2011;2011:385480. doi: 10.5402/2011/385480.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5402/2011/385480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashraf S., Chatha M.A., Ejaz W., Janjua H.A., Hussain I. Lysozyme-Coated Silver Nanoparticles for Differentiating Bacterial Strains on the Basis of Antibacterial Activity. Nanoscale Res. Lett. 2014;9:565. doi: 10.1186/1556-276X-9-565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1556-276X-9-565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4242785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25435831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mumtaz S., Wang L., Hussain S.Z., Abdullah M.I., Huma Z., Iqbal Z., Creran B., Rotello V.M., Hussain I. Dopamine Coated Fe3O4 Nanoparticles as Enzyme Mimics for the Sensitive Detection of Bacteria. Chem. Commun. 2017;53:12306–12308. doi: 10.1039/C7CC07149C.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C7CC07149C</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5690545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29094116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chavan S., Vigneshwaran N. Effects of Nanoparticles on Plant Growth-Promoting Bacteria in Indian Agricultural Soil. Agronomy. 2019;9:140. doi: 10.3390/agronomy9030140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agronomy9030140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okeniyi J.O., Popoola A.P.I., Ojewumi M.E., Okeniyi E.T., Ikotun J.O. Tectona grandis Capped Silver-Nanoparticle Material Effects on Microbial Strains Inducing Microbiologically Influenced Corrosion. Int. J. Chem. Eng. 2018;2018:7161537. doi: 10.1155/2018/7161537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/7161537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayele A., Mujmdar R.S., Addisu T., Woinue Y. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles for Various Biomedical and Agro Industrial Application. J. Nanosci. Technol. 2019;5:694–698. doi: 10.30799/jnst.233.19050211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30799/jnst.233.19050211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos T.S., Passos E.M.d., Seabra M.G.d.J., Souto E.B., Severino P., Mendonça M.d.C. Entomopathogenic Fungi Biomass Production and Extracellular Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles for Bioinsecticide Action. Appl. Sci. 2021;11:2465. doi: 10.3390/app11062465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app11062465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C., Hu Z., Li P., Gajaraj S. Governing Factors Affecting the Impacts of Silver Nanoparticles on Wastewater Treatment. Sci. Total Environ. 2016;572:852–873. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.07.145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.07.145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27542630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos T.S., Silva T.M., Cardoso J.C., Albuquerque-Júnior R.L.C.d., Zielińska A., Souto E.B., Severino P., Mendonça M.d.C. Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Mediated by Entomopathogenic Fungi: Antimicrobial Resistance, Nanopesticides, and Toxicity. Antibiotics. 2021;10:852. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics10070852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics10070852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8300670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34356773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan T., Yasmin A., Townley H.E. An Evaluation of the Activity of Biologically Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles Against Bacteria, Fungi and Mammalian Cell Lines. Colloids Surfaces B Biointerfaces. 2020;194:111156. doi: 10.1016/j.colsurfb.2020.111156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.colsurfb.2020.111156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32512312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fonseca M.S., Rodrigues D.M., Sokolonski A.R., Stanisic D., Tomé L.M.R., Góes-Neto A., Azevedo V., Meyer R., Araújo D.B.d., Tasic L., et al. Activity of Fusarium Oxysporum-Based Silver Nanoparticles on Candida Spp. Oral Isolates. Nanomaterials. 2022;12:501. doi: 10.3390/nano12030501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano12030501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8840154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35159845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zomorodian K., Pourshahid S., Sadatsharifi A., Mehryar P., Pakshir K., Rahimi M.J., Monfared A.A. Biosynthesis and Characterization of Silver Nanoparticles by Aspergillus Species. BioMed Res. Int. 2016;2016:5435397. doi: 10.1155/2016/5435397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2016/5435397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5019879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27652264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mussin J.E., Giusiano G. Biogenic Silver Nanoparticles as Antifungal Agents. Front. Chem. 2022;10:1023542. doi: 10.3389/fchem.2022.1023542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fchem.2022.1023542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9583421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36277355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christensen L., Vivekanandhan S., Misra M., Mohanty A.K. Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Murraya Koenigii (Curry Leaf): An Investigation on the Effect of Broth Concentration in Reduction Mechanism and Particle Size. Adv. Mater. Lett. 2011;2:429–434. doi: 10.5185/amlett.2011.4256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5185/amlett.2011.4256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eugênio M., Müller N., Frasés S., Almeida-Paes R., Lima L.M.T.R., Lemgruber L., Farina M., Souza W.d., Sant’Anna C. Yeast-Derived Biosynthesis of Silver/Silver Chloride Nanoparticles and Their Antiproliferative Activity Against Bacteria. RSC Adv. 2016;6:9893–9904. doi: 10.1039/C5RA22727E.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C5RA22727E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy K., Sarkar C.K., Ghosh C. Photocatalytic Activity of Biogenic Silver Nanoparticles Synthesized Using Yeast (Saccharomyces Cerevisiae) Extract. Appl. Nanosci. 2014;5:953–959. doi: 10.1007/s13204-014-0392-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13204-014-0392-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alamri S., Hashem M., Nafady N.A., Sayed M.A., Alshehri A.M., Alshaboury G.A. Controllable Biogenic Synthesis of Intracellular Silver/Silver Chloride Nanoparticles by Meyerozyma Guilliermondii KX008616. J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2018;28:917–930. doi: 10.4014/jmb.1802.02010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4014/jmb.1802.02010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29847861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aswathy R., Gabylis B., Anwesha S., Bhaskara Rao K. Green Synthesis and Characterization of Marine Yeast-Mediated Silver and Zinc Oxide Nanoparticles and Assessment of Their Antioxidant Activity. Asian J. Pharm. Clin. Res. 2017;10:235. doi: 10.22159/ajpcr.2017.v10i10.19979.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22159/ajpcr.2017.v10i10.19979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abu-Saied M.A., Elnouby M., Taha T.H., El-Shafeey M., Alshehri A., Alamri S., Alghamdi H.A., Shati A.A., Alrumman S.A., Alkahtani M.A., et al. Potential Decontamination of Drinking Water Pathogens Through K-Carrageenan Integrated Green Bottle Fly Bio-Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles. Molecules. 2020;25:1936. doi: 10.3390/molecules25081936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules25081936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7221915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32331239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Q., Xie X., Song Y., Sun L. A Review on Silver-Mediated DNA Base Pairs: Methodology and Application. Biomater. Res. 2022;26:9. doi: 10.1186/s40824-022-00254-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40824-022-00254-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8900454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35256004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu S., Yi T., Huang Z., Liu B., Wang J., Yi X., Liu J. Etching Silver Nanoparticles Using DNA. Mater. Horizons. 2018;6:155–159. doi: 10.1039/C8MH01126E.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C8MH01126E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chupradit S., Kavitha M., Suksatan W., Ansari M.J., Al Mashhadani Z.I., Kadhim M.M., Mustafa Y.F., Shafik S.S., Kianfar E. Morphological Control: Properties and Applications of Metal Nanostructures. Adv. Mater. Sci. Eng. 2022;2022:1971891. doi: 10.1155/2022/1971891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/1971891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J., Zhu Z., Liu F., Zhu B., Ma Y., Yan J., Lin B., Ke G., Liu R., Zhou L. DNA-mediated Morphological Control of Silver Nanoparticles. Small. 2016;12:5449–5487. doi: 10.1002/smll.201601338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/smll.201601338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27551864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasyanenko N., Varshavskii M., Ikonnikov E., Tolstyko E., Belykh R., Sokolov P., Bakulev V., Rolich V., Lopatko K. DNA Modified with Metal Nanoparticles: Preparation and Characterization of Ordered Metal-DNA Nanostructures in a Solution and on a Substrate. J. Nanomater. 2016;2016:3237250. doi: 10.1155/2016/3237250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2016/3237250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kukreti S., Kaushik M. Exploring the Potential of Environment Friendly Silver Nanoparticles for DNA Interaction: Physicochemical Approach. J. Photochem. Photobiol. B Biol. 2019;194:158–165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30954875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>New S.Y., Lee S.T., Su X.D. DNA-Templated Silver Nanoclusters: Structural Correlation and Fluorescence Modulation. Nanoscale. 2016;8:17729–17746. doi: 10.1039/C6NR05872H.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C6NR05872H</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27722695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farkhari N., Abbasian S., Moshaii A., Nikkhah M. Mechanism of Adsorption of Single and Double Stranded DNA on Gold and Silver Nanoparticles: Investigating Some Important Parameters in Bio-Sensing Applications. Colloids Surf. B Biointerfaces. 2016;148:657–664. doi: 10.1016/j.colsurfb.2016.09.022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.colsurfb.2016.09.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27697740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahiminezhad A., Zare-Hoseinabadi A., Sarmah A.K., Taghizadeh S., Ghasemi Y., Berenjian A. Plant-Mediated Synthesis and Applications of Iron Nanoparticles. Mol. Biotechnol. 2017;60:154–168. doi: 10.1007/s12033-017-0053-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12033-017-0053-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29256163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suman T.Y., Rajasree S.R.R., Ramkumar R., Rajthilak C., Perumal P. The Green Synthesis of Gold Nanoparticles Using an Aqueous Root Extract of Morinda citrifolia L. Spectrochim Spectrochim. Acta Part A Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc. 2013;118:11–16. doi: 10.1016/j.saa.2013.08.066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.saa.2013.08.066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24036301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dada A.O., Inyinbor A.A., Idu E.I., Bello O.M., Oluyori A.P., Adelani-Akande T.A., Okunola A.A., Dada O. Effect of Operational Parameters, Characterization and Antibacterial Studies of Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Tithonia diversifolia. PeerJ. 2018;6:e5865. doi: 10.7717/peerj.5865.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.5865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6214226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30397553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak S., Ghugare P., Vaidhun B. Green-Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles by Hygrophila Auriculata Extract: Innovative Technique and Comprehensive Evaluation. Indian J. Pharm. Educ. Res. 2021;55:s510–s517. doi: 10.5530/ijper.55.2s.122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5530/ijper.55.2s.122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dada A.O., Adekola F.A., Dada F.E., Adelani-Akande A.T., Bello M.O., Okonkwo C.R., Inyinbor A.A., Oluyori A.P., Olayanju A., Ajanaku K.O., et al. Silver Nanoparticle Synthesis by Acalypha Wilkesiana Extract: Phytochemical Screening, Characterization, Influence of Operational Parameters, and Preliminary Antibacterial Testing. Heliyon. 2019;5:e02517. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e02517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e02517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6812196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31667378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasmin S., Nouren S., Bhatti H.N., Iqbal D.N., Iftikhar S., Majeed J., Mustafa R., Nisar N., Nisar J., Nazir A., et al. Green Synthesis, Characterization and Photocatalytic Applications of Silver Nanoparticles Using Diospyros Lotus. Green Process. Synth. 2020;9:87–96. doi: 10.1515/gps-2020-0010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/gps-2020-0010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawat V., Sharma A., Bhatt V.P., Singh R.P., Maurya I.K. Sunlight Mediated Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Polygonatum Graminifolium Leaf Extract and Their Antibacterial Activity. Mater. Today Proc. 2020;29:911–916. doi: 10.1016/j.matpr.2020.05.274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.matpr.2020.05.274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chopade V., Kamble D.B. Application of Green Silver Nanoparticles Synthesized Using Leaf Extract of Tridax Procumbens for Preparation of Clinical Antimicrobial Bandages. Int. J. Pharm. Investig. 2021;11:10–13. doi: 10.5530/ijpi.2021.1.3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5530/ijpi.2021.1.3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oda A.M., Abdulkadhim H., Jabuk S.I., Hashim R., Fadhil I., Alaa D., Kareem A. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticle by Cauliflower Extract: Characterisation and Antibacterial Activity Against Storage. IET Nanobiotechnol. 2019;13:530–535. doi: 10.1049/iet-nbt.2018.5095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1049/iet-nbt.2018.5095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S.A., Priyadarshini H.S., Paramita A.P., Samal P., Sakshi G., Kar B.R., Kiran B.K. Green Synthesis and Biochemical Characterization of Silver Nanoparticles by Using Euphorbia Umbellata Leaf Extract and Analysis of Antimicrobial Activity Against Plant Pathogens. GSC Biol. Pharm. Sci. 2019;8:059–069. doi: 10.30574/gscbps.2019.8.2.0137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30574/gscbps.2019.8.2.0137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marzuk A.F.T., Adnan H., Hussein N.N., Oda A.M., Kamil S.A., Salah M. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticle by Ficus Cordata Leaf Extract and Study Its Antibacterial Activity. Orient. J. Chem. 2019;35:1195–1200. doi: 10.13005/ojc/350340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13005/ojc/350340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy P., Das B., Mohanty A., Mohapatra S. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Azadirachta Indica Leaf Extract and Its Antimicrobial Study. Appl. Nanosci. 2017;7:843–850. doi: 10.1007/s13204-017-0621-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13204-017-0621-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy A. Silver Nanoparticles Synthesis from a Pharmaceutically Important Medicinal Plant Plumbago Zeylanica. MOJ Bioequivalence Bioavailab. 2017;3:118–121. doi: 10.15406/mojbb.2017.03.00046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15406/mojbb.2017.03.00046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur A., Singh D. Phytochemical Analysis of Crude Plant Extracts and Laboratory Synthesized Green Nanoparticles from Acacia auriculiformis A. Cunn. Ex Benth. Int. J. Zool. Investig. 2022;8:47–58. doi: 10.33745/ijzi.2022.v08i02.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.33745/ijzi.2022.v08i02.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiny K.S., Sundararaj R., Mamatha N.C., Lingappa B. A New Approach to Wood Protection: Preliminary Study of Biologically Synthesized Copper Oxide Nanoparticle Formulation as an Environmental Friendly Wood Protectant Against Decay Fungi and Termites. Maderas-Cienc Tecnol. 2019;21:347–356. doi: 10.4067/S0718-221X2019005000307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4067/S0718-221X2019005000307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antony E., Sathiavelu M., Arunachalam S. Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles from the Medicinal Plant Bauhinia Acuminata and Biophytum Sensitivum—A Comparative Study of Its Biological Activities with Plant Extract. Int. J. Appl. Pharm. 2016;9:22. doi: 10.22159/ijap.2017v9i1.16277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22159/ijap.2017v9i1.16277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J., Weng X., Jin X., Megharaj M., Naidu R., Chen Z. Reactivity of Iron-Based Nanoparticles by Green Synthesis Under Various Atmospheres and Their Removal Mechanism of Methylene Blue. RSC Adv. 2015;5:70874–70882. doi: 10.1039/C5RA10629J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C5RA10629J</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H., Cao L., Lu L. Bacteria Promoted Hierarchical Carbon Materials for High-Performance Supercapacitor. Energy Environ. Sci. 2012;5:6206–6213. doi: 10.1039/c2ee03407g.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c2ee03407g</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naz M., Qureshi M.Z., Shahbaz A., Haider A., Ikram M., Nafees M., Shahzadi A., Bashir T., Ali S., Blackburn A.C., et al. Bio-Inspired Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles: Anticancer Drug Carrier, Catalytic and Bactericidal Potential. Nanosci. Nanotechnol. Lett. 2018;10:889–899. doi: 10.1166/nnl.2018.2711.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1166/nnl.2018.2711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey N., Santhiya D., Das A. Bio-Inspired Synthesis of Hollow Mesoporous Bioactive Glass Nanoparticles Using Calcium Carbonate as Solid Template. ChemistrySelect. 2022;7:e202200392. doi: 10.1002/slct.202200392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/slct.202200392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey N., Santhiya D., Das A. One-Pot Synthesis of Doxorubicin-Bioactive Glass-Ceramic Hybrid Nanoparticles Through a Bio-Inspired Route for Anti-Cancer Therapy. ChemistrySelect. 2023;8:e202203664. doi: 10.1002/slct.202203664.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/slct.202203664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinger A., Sushnitha M., Naoi T., Baudo G., Rosa E.D., Chang J.C., Tasciotti E., Taraballi F. Enhancing Inflammation Targeting Using Tunable Leukocyte-Based Biomimetic Nanoparticles. ACS Nano. 2021;15:6326–6339. doi: 10.1021/acsnano.0c05792.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsnano.0c05792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8155322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33724785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anh M.N.T., Sinh D.T., Thanh N.V.K., Trang N.T.T., Phong N.T.P., Hai N.D. Synthesis and Characterization of Silver Nanoplates by a Seed-Mediated Method. Commun. Phys. 2019;29:285. doi: 10.15625/0868-3166/29/3/13763.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15625/0868-3166/29/3/13763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraeyenhoven P.V., Glorie N., Chiaverini N., Mortier T. An Exploration of the “Sweet Nanochemistry” Synthesis for Silver and Gold Colloids. J. Chem. Educ. 2016;93:787–789. doi: 10.1021/acs.jchemed.5b00943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jchemed.5b00943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranoszek-Soliwoda K., Tomaszewska E., Socha E., Krzyczmonik P., Ignaczak A., Orłowski P., Krzyżowska M., Celichowski G., Grobelny J. The Role of Tannic Acid and Sodium Citrate in the Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles. J. Nanopart. Res. 2017;19:273. doi: 10.1007/s11051-017-3973-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11051-017-3973-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5543188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28824288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuzharov A.A., Milov A.A., Gerasina J.S., Soldatov M.A., Butova V.V., Soldatov A.V. Effect of a Stabilizer on the Structure, Synthesis, and Tribological Properties of Silver Nanoparticles. Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng. Part J J. Eng. Tribol. 2023;237:601–610. doi: 10.1177/13506501221121923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/13506501221121923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barani H., Mahltig B. Using Microwave Irradiation to Catalyze the In-Situ Manufacturing of Silver Nanoparticles on Cotton Fabric for Antibacterial and UV-Protective Application. Cellulose. 2020;27:9105–9121. doi: 10.1007/s10570-020-03400-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10570-020-03400-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinhal K.V., Sinha S., Ravisankar A., Bhatt N., Pushpavanam S. Simultaneous Synthesis and Separation of Nanoparticles Using Aqueous Two-Phase Systems. ACS Sustain. Chem. Eng. 2020;8:3013–3025. doi: 10.1021/acssuschemeng.0c00032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.0c00032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capek I., Capek I. Noble Metal Nanoparticles. Noble Metal Nanoparticles: Preparation, Composite Nanostructures, Biodecoration and Collective Properties. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2017. pp. 125–210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurian S., Gande V.V., Subramaniam P., Bauri R. Synthesis and Separation of Silver Nanoparticles Using an Aqueous Two-Phase System with Citrate as Reducing Agent. J. Nanopart. Res. 2024;26:51. doi: 10.1007/s11051-024-05958-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11051-024-05958-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aragaw B.A., Alula M.T., Majoni S., King’ondu C.K. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanomaterials. Elsevier; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Chemical Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles; pp. 21–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhargava A., Dev A., Mohanbhai S.J., Pareek V., Jain N., Choudhury S.R., Panwar J., Karmakar S. Pre-Coating of Protein Modulate Patterns of Corona Formation, Physiological Stability and Cytotoxicity of Silver Nanoparticles. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;772:144797. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.144797.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.144797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33578167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu N., Tang M., Ding J. The Interaction between Nanoparticles-Protein Corona Complex and Cells and Its Toxic Effect on Cells. Chemosphere. 2020;245:125624. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31864050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashid M., Sabir S. Biosynthesis of Self-Dispersed Silver Colloidal Particles Using the Aqueous Extract of P. peruviana for Sensing Dl-Alanine. ISRN Nanotechnol. 2014;2014:670780. doi: 10.1155/2014/670780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2014/670780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaseen B., Gangwar C., Kumar I., Sarkar J., Naik R.M. Detailed Kinetic and Mechanistic Study for the Preparation of Silver Nanoparticles by a Chemical Reduction Method in the Presence of a Neuroleptic Agent (Gabapentin) at an Alkaline PH and Its Characterization. ACS Omega. 2022;7:5739–5750. doi: 10.1021/acsomega.1c05499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsomega.1c05499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8867805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35224334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pramesti E.S., Febriani N.A., ‘Aisy R.N., Salsabila S., Rachmawati V.P.N., Susilowati E. Synthesis of Silver/K-Caragenan Nanocomposites Assisted with Microwave Iradiation as a Potential Antibacterial Material. J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2022;2190:012004. doi: 10.1088/1742-6596/2190/1/012004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1742-6596/2190/1/012004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeeq H.A., Awad M.I., Kassem M.A. Insight into Amino Acids-Stabilized Silver Nanoparticles as a Probe for Quantification of Methionine. J. Mol. Liq. 2024;398:124272. doi: 10.1016/j.molliq.2024.124272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.molliq.2024.124272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidhu A.K., Verma N., Kaushal P. Role of Biogenic Capping Agents in the Synthesis of Metallic Nanoparticles and Evaluation of Their Therapeutic Potential. Front. Nanotechnol. 2022;3:801620. doi: 10.3389/fnano.2021.801620.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnano.2021.801620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubiński K., Górka K., Janeczko M., Martyna A., Kwaśnik M., Masłyk M., Zięba E., Kowalczuk J., Kuśtrowski P., Borkowski M. Silver Is Not Equal to Silver: Synthesis and Evaluation of Silver Nanoparticles with Low Biological Activity, and Their Incorporation into C12Alanine-Based Hydrogel. Molecules. 2023;28:1194. doi: 10.3390/molecules28031194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28031194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9922004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36770861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L., Hu F., Xu D., Shen S., Wang Q. Metal Ion Redox Potential Plays an Important Role in High-Yield Synthesis of Monodisperse Silver Nanoparticles. Chem. Commun. 2012;48:4728–4730. doi: 10.1039/c2cc18152e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c2cc18152e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22493776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D., Hong B., Fang W., Guo Y., Lin R. Preparation of Well-Dispersed Silver Nanoparticles for Oil-Based Nanofluids. Ind. Eng. Chem. Res. 2010;49:1697–1702. doi: 10.1021/ie901173h.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ie901173h</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarkar A., Kapoor S., Mukherjee T. Oleic Acid-Assisted Phase Transfer of Nanosized Silver Colloids. Res. Chem. Intermed. 2010;36:403–410. doi: 10.1007/s11164-010-0150-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11164-010-0150-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Streich C., Stein F., Jakobi J., Ingendoh-Tsakmakidis A., Heine N., Rehbock C., Winkel A., Grade S., Kühnel M., Migunov V. The Origin of the Intracellular Silver in Bacteria: A Comprehensive Study Using Targeting Gold–Silver Alloy Nanoparticles. Adv. Health Mater. 2023;12:e2302084. doi: 10.1002/adhm.202302084.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adhm.202302084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37661312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shrestha S., Wang B., Dutta P. Nanoparticle Processing: Understanding and Controlling Aggregation. Adv. Colloid Interface Sci. 2020;279:102162. doi: 10.1016/j.cis.2020.102162.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cis.2020.102162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32334131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mourdikoudis S., Menelaou M., Fiuza-Maneiro N., Zheng G., Wei S., Pérez-Juste J., Polavarapu L., Sofer Z. Oleic Acid/Oleylamine Ligand Pair: A Versatile Combination in the Synthesis of Colloidal Nanoparticles. Nanoscale Horizons. 2022;7:941–1015. doi: 10.1039/D2NH00111J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D2NH00111J</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35770698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abarca-Cabrera L., Xu L., Berensmeier S., Fraga-García P. Competition at the Bio-Nano Interface: A Protein, a Polysaccharide, and a Fatty Acid Adsorb onto Magnetic Nanoparticles. ACS Appl. Bio Mater. 2022;6:146–156. doi: 10.1021/acsabm.2c00812.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsabm.2c00812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36503228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabira O., Drisya N., Ajaykumar A.P., Mathew A., Narayanan Jayaraj K., Binitha V.S., Zeena K.V., Roy K.B., Janish P.A., Sheena P. From Ficus Recemosa Leaf Galls to Therapeutic Silver Nanoparticles: Antibacterial and Anticancer Applications. Pharmaceutics. 2024;16:1025. doi: 10.3390/pharmaceutics16081025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics16081025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11359757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39204370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madani M., Hosny S., Alshangiti D.M., Nady N., Alkhursani S.A., Alkhaldi H., Al-Gahtany S.A., Ghobashy M.M., Gaber G.A. Green Synthesis of Nanoparticles for Varied Applications: Green Renewable Resources and Energy-Efficient Synthetic Routes. Nanotechnol. Rev. 2022;11:731–759. doi: 10.1515/ntrev-2022-0034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/ntrev-2022-0034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosman N.S.R., Harun N.A., Idris I., Wan Ismail W.I. Nanobiotechnology: Nature-Inspired Silver Nanoparticles towards Green Synthesis. Energy Environ. 2021;32:1183–1206. doi: 10.1177/0958305X21989883.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0958305X21989883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav S., Chamoli S., Kumar P., Maurya P.K. Structural and Functional Insights in Polysaccharides Coated Cerium Oxide Nanoparticles and Their Potential Biomedical Applications: A Review. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2023;246:125673. doi: 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.125673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.125673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37406905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caschera D., Toro R.G., Federici F., Montanari R., de Caro T., Al-Shemy M.T., Adel A.M. Green Approach for the Fabrication of Silver-Oxidized Cellulose Nanocomposite with Antibacterial Properties. Cellulose. 2020;27:8059–8073. doi: 10.1007/s10570-020-03364-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10570-020-03364-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shukla A. Facile Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticle and Their Potential Application. Am. J. Nanosci. Nanotechnol. 2014;2:84. doi: 10.11648/j.nano.20140204.14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11648/j.nano.20140204.14</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abid J.-P., Wark A.W., Brevet P.-F., Girault H.H. Preparation of Silver Nanoparticles in Solution from a Silver Salt by Laser Irradiation. Chem. Commun. 2002;7:792–793. doi: 10.1039/b200272h.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/b200272h</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12119726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torras M., Roig A. From Silver Plates to Spherical Nanoparticles: Snapshots of Microwave-Assisted Polyol Synthesis. ACS Omega. 2020;5:5731–5738. doi: 10.1021/acsomega.9b03748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsomega.9b03748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7097931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32226851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjan P., Nguyen D.H., Tanaka K., Suematsu H., Jayaganthan R., Sarathi R. Synthesis, Characterisation and Formation Mechanism of Sn-0.75 Cu Solder Nanoparticles by Pulsed Wire Discharge. Appl. Nanosci. 2019;9:341–352. doi: 10.1007/s13204-018-0910-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13204-018-0910-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfeiffer T.V., Feng J., Schmidt-Ott A. New Developments in Spark Production of Nanoparticles. Adv. Powder Technol. 2014;25:56–70. doi: 10.1016/j.apt.2013.12.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apt.2013.12.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L., Zhang Q., Zhao J., Yan W., Zhang L., Wang Z., Tie W. Study on Characteristics of Nanopowders Synthesized by Nanosecond Electrical Explosion of Thin Aluminum Wire in the Argon Gas. IEEE Trans. Plasma Sci. 2013;41:2221–2226. doi: 10.1109/TPS.2013.2240318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TPS.2013.2240318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnia L., Thakur P., Thakur A. Synthesis and Applications of Nanoparticles. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2022. Synthesis of Nanoparticles by Physical Route; pp. 45–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra D., Manohar A., Pal M., Chaudhary K., Nath N., Kumar N., Bhati G., Khan I.A., Husain S.Q. International Conference on Production and Industrial Engineering. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2023. An Innovative Review on the Oscillating Drum Ball Milling Process; pp. 19–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorrasi G., Sorrentino A. Mechanical Milling as a Technology to Produce Structural and Functional Bio-Nanocomposites. Green Chemistry. 2015;17:2610–2625. doi: 10.1039/C5GC00029G.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C5GC00029G</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charitidis C.A., Georgiou P., Koklioti M.A., Trompeta A.-F., Markakis V. Manufacturing Nanomaterials: From Research to Industry. Manuf. Rev. 2014;1:11. doi: 10.1051/mfreview/2014009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1051/mfreview/2014009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salama A., Abouzeid R.E., Owda M.E., Cruz-Maya I., Guarino V. Cellulose–Silver Composites Materials: Preparation and Applications. Biomolecules. 2021;11:1684. doi: 10.3390/biom11111684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biom11111684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8615592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34827681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naganthran A., Verasoundarapandian G., Khalid F.E., Masarudin M.J., Zulkharnain A., Nawawi N.M., Karim M., Che Abdullah C.A., Ahmad S.A. Synthesis, Characterization and Biomedical Application of Silver Nanoparticles. Materials. 2022;15:427. doi: 10.3390/ma15020427.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma15020427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8779869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35057145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vishwanath R., Negi B. Conventional and Green Methods of Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles and Their Antimicrobial Properties. Curr. Res. Green Sustain. Chem. 2021;4:100205. doi: 10.1016/j.crgsc.2021.100205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.crgsc.2021.100205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park D.H., Joe Y.H., Hwang J., Byeon J.H. Evaporation-Condensation in the Presence of Unipolar Ionic Flow for Solvent-Free Production of Ultrasmall Antibacterial Particles. Chem. Eng. J. 2020;381:122639. doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2019.122639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2019.122639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan W., Zhou T., Hui G., Wang Y., Chong X., Wang X., Song W., Han X., Zhao B. Particle Lithography-Based Patterning of Polyelectrolyte Template Films and Their Application in Fabrication of Gold/Silver Nanoparticle Assembly. J. Colloid Interface Sci. 2014;432:65–69. doi: 10.1016/j.jcis.2014.06.058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcis.2014.06.058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25080385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokes K., Clark K., Odetade D., Hardy M., Goldberg Oppenheimer P. Advances in Lithographic Techniques for Precision Nanostructure Fabrication in Biomedical Applications. Discover Nano. 2023;18:153. doi: 10.1186/s11671-023-03938-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s11671-023-03938-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10713959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38082047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capitaine A., Bochet-Modaresialam M., Poungsripong P., Badie C., Heresanu V., Margeat O., Santinacci L., Grosso D., Garnett E., Sciacca B. Nanoparticle Imprint Lithography: From Nanoscale Metrology to Printable Metallic Grids. ACS Nano. 2023;17:9361–9373. doi: 10.1021/acsnano.3c01156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsnano.3c01156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10211370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37171993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Zhang M., Lai Y., Chi L. Advanced Colloidal Lithography: From Patterning to Applications. Nano Today. 2018;22:36–61. doi: 10.1016/j.nantod.2018.08.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nantod.2018.08.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tien C.-L. Special Issue “Advanced Coating Technology by Physical Vapor Deposition and Applications”. Coatings. 2023;13:467. doi: 10.3390/coatings13020467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/coatings13020467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popok V.N., Kylián O. Gas-Phase Synthesis of Functional Nanomaterials. Appl. Nano. 2020;1:4. doi: 10.3390/applnano1010004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/applnano1010004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav H.K.S., Usman S., Ghanem K.A.F., Beevi R. Functionalized Nanomaterials II. CRC Press; Boca Raton, FL, USA: 2021. Synthesis of Nanomaterials for Drug Delivery; pp. 23–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Escorcia-Díaz D., García-Mora S., Rendón-Castrillón L., Ramírez-Carmona M., Ocampo-López C. Advancements in Nanoparticle Deposition Techniques for Diverse Substrates: A Review. Nanomaterials. 2023;13:2586. doi: 10.3390/nano13182586.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano13182586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10537803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37764615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majerič P., Rudolf R. Advances in Ultrasonic Spray Pyrolysis Processing of Noble Metal Nanoparticles. Materials. 2020;13:3485. doi: 10.3390/ma13163485.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma13163485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7476056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32784637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meierhofer F., Fritsching U. Synthesis of Metal Oxide Nanoparticles in Flame Sprays: Review on Process Technology, Modeling, and Diagnostics. Energy Fuels. 2021;35:5495–5537. doi: 10.1021/acs.energyfuels.0c04054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.energyfuels.0c04054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naser H., Alghoul M.A., Hossain M.K., Asim N., Abdullah M.F., Ali M.S., Alzubi F.G., Amin N. The Role of Laser Ablation Technique Parameters in Synthesis of Nanoparticles from Different Target Types. J. Nanopart. Res. 2019;21:249. doi: 10.1007/s11051-019-4690-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11051-019-4690-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subhan A., Mourad A.-H.I., Al-Douri Y. Influence of Laser Process Parameters, Liquid Medium, and External Field on the Synthesis of Colloidal Metal Nanoparticles Using Pulsed Laser Ablation in Liquid: A Review. Nanomaterials. 2022;12:2144. doi: 10.3390/nano12132144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano12132144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9268572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35807980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nominé A.V., Gries T., Noel C., Nominé A., Milichko V., Belmonte T. Synthesis of Nanomaterials by Electrode Erosion Using Discharges in Liquids. J. Appl. Phys. 2021;130:151101. doi: 10.1063/5.0040587.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1063/5.0040587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta T., Mishra R., Pansara C., Dhal C., Dhas N., Hariharan K., Patel J.K. Emerging Technologies for Nanoparticle Manufacturing. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2021. Manufacturing Techniques for Carbon Nanotubes, Gold Nanoparticles, and Silver Nanoparticles; pp. 397–420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nene A., Galluzzi M., Hongrong L., Somani P., Ramakrishna S., Yu X.-F. Synthetic Preparations and Atomic Scale Engineering of Silver Nanoparticles for Biomedical Applications. Nanoscale. 2021;13:13923–13942. doi: 10.1039/D1NR01851E.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1NR01851E</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34477675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghazali S.Z., Mohamed Noor N.R., Mustaffa K.M.F. Anti-Plasmodial Activity of Aqueous Neem Leaf Extract Mediated Green Synthesis-Based Silver Nitrate Nanoparticles. Prep. Biochem. Biotechnol. 2022;52:99–107. doi: 10.1080/10826068.2021.1913602.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10826068.2021.1913602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33890844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed S.F., Mofijur M., Rafa N., Chowdhury A.T., Chowdhury S., Nahrin M., Islam A.B.M.S., Ong H.C. Green Approaches in Synthesising Nanomaterials for Environmental Nanobioremediation: Technological Advancements, Applications, Benefits and Challenges. Environ. Res. 2022;204:111967. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2021.111967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2021.111967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34450159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z., Yu Z., Zhang L., Tayebee R., Pourmojahed S., Shahri E.E., Chen X. Studying Loading of 5-Fluorouracil onto the Surface of Gold–Silver Nanocomposite Utilizing DLS and UV–Vis Spectroscopy. Chem. Pap. 2023;77:6135–6145. doi: 10.1007/s11696-023-02927-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11696-023-02927-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velidandi A., Dahariya S., Pabbathi N.P.P., Kalivarathan D., Baadhe R.R. A Review on Synthesis, Applications, Toxicity, Risk Assessment and Limitations of Plant Extracts Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles. NanoWorld J. 2020;6:35–60. doi: 10.17756/nwj.2020-079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17756/nwj.2020-079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zulfiqar Z., Khan R.R.M., Summer M., Saeed Z., Pervaiz M., Rasheed S., Shehzad B., Kabir F., Ishaq S. Plant-Mediated Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles: Synthesis, Characterization, Biological Applications, and Toxicological Considerations: A Review. Biocatal. Agric. Biotechnol. 2024;57:103121. doi: 10.1016/j.bcab.2024.103121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bcab.2024.103121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salayová A., Bedlovičová Z., Daneu N., Baláž M., Lukáčová Bujňáková Z., Balážová Ľ., Tkáčiková Ľ. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles with Antibacterial Activity Using Various Medicinal Plant Extracts: Morphology and Antibacterial Efficacy. Nanomaterials. 2021;11:1005. doi: 10.3390/nano11041005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11041005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8070782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33919801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rónavári A., Igaz N., Adamecz D.I., Szerencsés B., Molnar C., Kónya Z., Pfeiffer I., Kiricsi M. Green Silver and Gold Nanoparticles: Biological Synthesis Approaches and Potentials for Biomedical Applications. Molecules. 2021;26:844. doi: 10.3390/molecules26040844.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26040844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7915205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33562781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai M.-Y., Chang M.-C., Chien H.-W. Effect of Codeposition of Polydopamine with Polyethylenimine or Poly (Ethylene Glycol) Coatings on Silver Nanoparticle Synthesis. Langmuir. 2023;39:6895–6904. doi: 10.1021/acs.langmuir.3c00526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.langmuir.3c00526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37140482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad I., Khan M.N., Hayat K., Ahmad T., Shams D.F., Khan W., Tirth V., Rehman G., Muhammad W., Elhadi M. Investigating the Antibacterial and Anti-Inflammatory Potential of Polyol-Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles. ACS Omega. 2024;9:13208–13216. doi: 10.1021/acsomega.3c09851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsomega.3c09851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10956083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38524435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albulym O., Hussien M.S.A., Kilany M., Zahran H.Y., Eid R.A., Yahia I.S., Abutalib M.M. 5-Minute Synthesis of Gelatinous Silver Nanoparticles Using Microwave Radiation: Plasmonic Optical Spectroscopy and Antimicrobial Activity. Optik (Stuttg) 2021;228:166139. doi: 10.1016/j.ijleo.2020.166139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijleo.2020.166139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Larionov K.S., Zhang S., Sobolev N.A., Konstantinov A.I., Volkov D.S., Suslova E.V., Chernov V.E., Poloskov A.I., Glushakov R.I. Humic Polyelectrolytes Facilitate Rapid Microwave Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Suitable for Wound-Healing Applications. Polymers. 2024;16:587. doi: 10.3390/polym16050587.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym16050587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10933856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38475271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maharjan S., Liao K.-S., Wang A.J., Zhu Z., McElhenny B.P., Bao J., Curran S.A. Sol-Gel Synthesis of Stabilized Silver Nanoparticles in an Organosiloxane Matrix and Its Optical Nonlinearity. Chem. Phys. 2020;532:110610. doi: 10.1016/j.chemphys.2019.110610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemphys.2019.110610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srinivasan L.V., Rana S.S. A Critical Review of Various Synthesis Methods of Nanoparticles and Their Applications in Biomedical, Regenerative Medicine, Food Packaging, and Environment. Discov. Appl. Sci. 2024;6:371. doi: 10.1007/s42452-024-06040-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42452-024-06040-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thathapudi J.J., Shobini J. A Plausible Antibacterial Green Synthesized AgNPs from Tridax Procumbens Leaf-Flower Extract. J. Pure Appl. Microbiol. 2018;12:2135–2142. doi: 10.22207/jpam.12.4.51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22207/jpam.12.4.51</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin M., Anwar F., Janjua M.R.S.A., Iqbal M., Rashid U. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Through Reduction with Solanum xanthocarpum L. Berry Extract: Characterization, Antimicrobial and Urease Inhibitory Activities Against Helicobacter Pylori. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2012;13:9923–9941. doi: 10.3390/ijms13089923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms13089923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3431837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22949839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalil M., Mohamed S.R., El-Naggar K. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Egyptian Propolis Extract and Its Antimicrobial Activity. Egypt. J. Chem. 2021;65:453–464. doi: 10.21608/ejchem.2021.104296.4838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21608/ejchem.2021.104296.4838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lade B.D., Shanware A. Smart Nanosystems for Biomedicine, Optoelectronics and Catalysis. IntechOpen; London, UK: 2020. Phytonanofabrication: Methodology and Factors Affecting Biosynthesis of Nanoparticles.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5772/intechopen.90918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le H.T., Nguyen L.A. Biosynthesis, Characterization and Photocatalytic Activity of Silver Nanoparticles Produced from AgNO3 Solution Using Aqueous Extract of Ocimum bacilicum L. Leaf as the Reducing Agent. GSC Adv. Res. Rev. 2023;14:151–158. doi: 10.30574/gscarr.2023.14.1.0033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30574/gscarr.2023.14.1.0033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suci A., Sabarudin A., Masruri M., Sumitro S.B. Characterization and Antibacterial Application of Biosynthesized Silver Nanoparticles Using Piper Retrofractum Vahl Fruit Extract as Bioreductor. J. Appl. Pharm. Sci. 2022;12:103–114. doi: 10.7324/JAPS.2022.120311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7324/JAPS.2022.120311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ameh T., Gibb M., Stevens D., Pradhan S.H., Braswell W.E., Sayes C.M. Silver and Copper Nanoparticles Induce Oxidative Stress in Bacteria and Mammalian Cells. Nanomaterials. 2022;12:2402. doi: 10.3390/nano12142402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano12142402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9319685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35889626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tailor G., Yadav B., Chaudhary J., Joshi M., Suvalka C. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Ocimum Canum and Their Anti-Bacterial Activity. Biochem. Biophys. Rep. 2020;24:100848. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrep.2020.100848.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbrep.2020.100848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7718455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33305022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balashanmugam P., Prabhu D., Devasena T., Song H.J., Jung Y., Kim H.J., Rangarajulu S.K. Facile Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Asian Spider Flower and Its in Vitro Cytotoxic Activity Against Human Breast Carcinoma Cells. Processes. 2020;8:430. doi: 10.3390/pr8040430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pr8040430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdoğan Ö., Paşa S., Çevik Ö. Green Synthesis and Characterization of Anticancer Effected Silver Nanoparticles with Silverberry (Elaeagnus angustifolia) Fruit Aqueous Extract. Int. J. Pure Appl. Sci. 2021;7:391–400. doi: 10.29132/ijpas.915005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.29132/ijpas.915005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinsipo O.B., Mustapha T.O., Adams A.N. Biosynthesis and Characterization of Silver Nanoparticles Using the Aqueous Extract of Acanthus Montanus Leaves Extract. J. Chem. Soc. Niger. 2022;47:203–213. doi: 10.46602/jcsn.v47i2.717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.46602/jcsn.v47i2.717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vijayakumar, Manjunath B.R., Hiregoudar S., Dinesha B.L., Vidya M., Pramod G. Characterization and Antibacterial Efficacy of Silver Nanoparticles Extracted from Neem (Azadirachta indica) Leaf Extract. Int. J. Chem. Stud. 2021;9:1033–1038. doi: 10.22271/chemi.2021.v9.i2o.11956.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22271/chemi.2021.v9.i2o.11956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Widdatallah M.O., Mohamed A.A., Alrasheid A.A., Widatallah H.A., Yassin L.F., Eltilib S.H., Ahmed S. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Nigella sativa Seeds and Evaluation of Their Antibacterial Activity. Adv. Nanopart. 2020;9:41–48. doi: 10.4236/anp.2020.92003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4236/anp.2020.92003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi S.C., Kaushik U., Upadhyaya A., Sharma P. Green Technology Mediated Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles from Momordica Charantia Fruit Extract and Its Bactericidal Activity. Asian J. Pharm. Clin. Res. 2017;10:196. doi: 10.22159/ajpcr.2017.v10i3.16009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22159/ajpcr.2017.v10i3.16009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qayyum A., Malik T., Mushtaq M., Ali S.R. Rosemarinus Officinalis Mediated Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles and Its Activity Against Pathogenic Fungal Strains. TJNPR. 2020;4:249–254. doi: 10.26538/tjnpr/v4i6.7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26538/tjnpr/v4i6.7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagyalakshmi J., Haritha H. Green Synthesis and Characterization of Silver Nanoparticles Using Pterocarpus Marsupium and Assessment of Its in Vitro Antidiabetic Activity. Am. J. Adv. Drug Deliv. 2017;5:118–130. doi: 10.21767/2321-547X.1000019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21767/2321-547X.1000019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatadri B., Shanparvish E., Rameshkumar M.R., Arasu M.V., Al-Dhabi N.A., Ponnusamy V.K., Agastian P. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Aqueous Rhizome Extract of Zingiber Officinale and Curcuma Longa: In-Vitro Anti-Cancer Potential on Human Colon Carcinoma HT-29 Cells. Saudi J. Biol. Sci. 2020;27:2980–2986. doi: 10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.09.021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.09.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7569115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33100856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vetrivel C., Balasubramanian B., Durairaj K., Park S., Maluventhan V., Kaul T., Liu W.C., Maruthupandian A. Biological Mediated Ag Nanoparticles from Barleria longiflora for Antimicrobial Activity and Photocatalytic Degradation Using Methylene Blue. Artif. Cells Nanomed. Biotechnol. 2019;47:2424–2430. doi: 10.1080/21691401.2019.1626407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21691401.2019.1626407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31187650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohail, Amara U., Shad S., Ilyas N., Manaf A., Raja N.I., Mashwani Z.-R. In Vitro Germination and Biochemical Profiling of Brassica napus in Response to Biosynthesised Zinc Nanoparticles. IET Nanobiotechnol. 2018;13:46–51. doi: 10.1049/iet-nbt.2018.5012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1049/iet-nbt.2018.5012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8676516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30964037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moond M., Singh S., Sangwan S., Devi P., Beniwal A., Rani J., Kumari A., Rani S. Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Utilizing Leaf Extract of Trigonella foenum-graecum L. for Catalytic Dyes Degradation and Colorimetric Sensing of Fe3+/Hg2+ Molecules. 2023;28:951. doi: 10.3390/molecules28030951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28030951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9919385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36770623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamčík J., Jung J.-M., Flakowski J., Rios P.D.L., Dietler G., Mezzenga R. Understanding Amyloid Aggregation by Statistical Analysis of Atomic Force Microscopy Images. Nat. Nanotechnol. 2010;5:423–428. doi: 10.1038/nnano.2010.59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nnano.2010.59</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20383125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed G.M., Hawar S.N. Green Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles from Moringa Oleifera Leaves and Its Antimicrobial and Cytotoxicity Activities. Int. J. Biomater. 2022;2022:4136641. doi: 10.1155/2022/4136641.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/4136641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9526645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36193175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shobana N., Prakash P., Samrot A.V., Saigeetha S., Sathiyasree M., Ramanathan T., Visvanathan S., Mohanty B.K., Sabesan G.S., Dhiva S., et al. Evaluation of the Toxic Effect of Bauhinia Purpurea Mediated Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles Against In-Vitro and in-Vivo Models. Toxics. 2022;11:9. doi: 10.3390/toxics11010009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxics11010009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9862017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36668735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnaraj C., Muthukumaran P., Ramachandran R., Balakumaran M.D., Kalaichelvan P.T. Acalypha Indica Linn: Biogenic Synthesis of Silver and Gold Nanoparticles and Their Cytotoxic Effects Against MDA-MB-231, Human Breast Cancer Cells. Biotechnol. Rep. 2014;4:42–49. doi: 10.1016/j.btre.2014.08.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.btre.2014.08.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5466127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28626661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed D.S., El-Baky R.M.A., Sandle T., Mandour S., Ahmed E.F. Antimicrobial Activity of Silver-Treated Bacteria Against Other Multi-Drug Resistant Pathogens in Their Environment. Antibiotics. 2020;9:181. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics9040181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9040181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7235873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32326384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh P., Kim Y.J., Wang C., Mathiyalagan R., Yang D.C. The Development of a Green Approach for the Biosynthesis of Silver and Gold Nanoparticles by Using Panax ginseng root Extract, and Their Biological Applications. Artif. Cells Nanomed. Biotechnol. 2015;44:1–8. doi: 10.3109/21691401.2015.1011809.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/21691401.2015.1011809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25771716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chavva S.R., Deshmukh S.K., Kanchanapally R., Tyagi N., Coym J.W., Singh A.P., Singh S. Epigallocatechin Gallate-Gold Nanoparticles Exhibit Superior Antitumor Activity Compared to Conventional Gold Nanoparticles: Potential Synergistic Interactions. Nanomaterials. 2019;9:396. doi: 10.3390/nano9030396.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano9030396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6474148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30857226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segura R., Vasquez G., Colson E., Gerbaux P., Frischmon C., Nesic A., García D.E., Cabrera-Barjas G. Phytostimulant Properties of Highly Stable Silver Nanoparticles Obtained with Saponin Extract from Chenopodium quinoa. J. Sci. Food Agric. 2020;100:4987–4994. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.10529.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.10529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32597512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo J., Qin S., Wei Y., Liu S., Peng H., Li Q., Luo L., Lv M. Silver Nanoparticles Exert Concentration-dependent Influences on Biofilm Development and Architecture. Cell Prolif. 2019;52:e12616. doi: 10.1111/cpr.12616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cpr.12616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6668980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31050052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahangir H.S., Kumar T., Concelia M.M., Alamelu R. Green Synthesis, Characterization &amp; Antibacterial Studies of Silver (Ag) and Zinc Oxide (Zno) Nanoparticles. J. Pure Appl. Microbiol. 2020;14:1999–2008. doi: 10.22207/jpam.14.3.39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22207/jpam.14.3.39</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Alfy W., Ismaiel O.A., El-Mammli M.Y., Shalaby A. Application of Silver Nanoparticles for the Spectrophotometric Determination of Cefdinir and Cefepime HCl in Pharmaceutical Preparations and Human Urine Samples. Nano Biomed. Eng. 2019;11:381–390. doi: 10.5101/nbe.v11i4.p381-390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5101/nbe.v11i4.p381-390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim E.A., Fouad H., Zhang M., Zhang Y., Qiao W., Yan C., Li B., Mo J., Chen J. Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Endophytic Bacteria and Their Role in Inhibition of Rice Pathogenic Bacteria and Plant Growth Promotion. RSC Adv. 2019;9:29293–29299. doi: 10.1039/C9RA04246F.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C9RA04246F</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9071947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35528426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjan R., Dandapat S., Kumar M., Sinha M. Synthesis and Characterization of Cuscuta Reflexa (Roxb.) Aqueous Extract Mediated Silver Nanoparticles. J. Anal. Pharm. Res. 2019;8:80–83. doi: 10.15406/japlr.2019.08.00317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15406/japlr.2019.08.00317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pipriya S., Kundu N., Tiwari U. Green Synthesis, Characterization and Antioxidant Activity of Silver Nanoparticles in Extracts of Acorus Calamus and Agaricus Bisporus. Int. J. Biochem. Res. Rev. 2018;21:1–15. doi: 10.9734/IJBCRR/2018/41615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/IJBCRR/2018/41615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han J.S., Gurunathan S., Choi Y.-J., Kim J.-H. Dual Functions of Silver Nanoparticles in F9 Teratocarcinoma Stem Cells, a Suitable Model for Evaluating Cytotoxicity- and Differentiation-Mediated Cancer Therapy. Int. J. Nanomed. 2017;12:7529–7549. doi: 10.2147/IJN.S145147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJN.S145147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5644540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29066898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari M.S., Gupta N.P., Hemal A.K., Dogra P.N., Seth A., Aron M., Singh T.P. Spectrum of Stone Composition: Structural Analysis of 1050 Upper Urinary Tract Calculi from Northern India. Int. J. Urol. 2005;12:12–16. doi: 10.1111/j.1442-2042.2004.00990.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1442-2042.2004.00990.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15661049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azizi M., Sedaghat S., Tahvildari K., Derakhshi P., Ghaemi A. Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Peganum harmala Extract as a Green Route. Green Chem. Lett. Rev. 2017;10:420–427. doi: 10.1080/17518253.2017.1395081.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/17518253.2017.1395081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorniani D., Hussein M.Z., Kura A.U., Fakurazi S., Shaari A.H., Ahmad Z. Preparation of Fe3O4 Magnetic Nanoparticles Coated with Gallic Acid for Drug Delivery. Int. J. Nanomed. 2012;7:5745–5756. doi: 10.2147/IJN.S35746.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJN.S35746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3500033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23166439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saka A., Shifera Y., Jule L.T., Badassa B., Nagaprasad N., Shanmugam R., Dwarampudi L.P., Seenivasan V., Ramaswamy K. Biosynthesis of TiO2 Nanoparticles by Caricaceae (Papaya) Shell Extracts for Antifungal Application. Sci. Rep. 2022;12:15960. doi: 10.1038/s41598-022-19440-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-19440-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9509329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36153393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lian W., Gan M. Fabrication of Folic Acid-Cysteamine Modified AgNPs as Promising Contrast Agent for CT Imaging. Preprint. 2023;1:1–21. doi: 10.21203/rs.3.rs-3160406/v1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-3160406/v1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kousar S., Iqbal A., Rasool S., Iqbal H.M. Role of Nanoparticles in Elimination of Biofilm Produced by Pathogenic Bacteria. J. Contemp. Pharm. 2022;6:23–31. doi: 10.56770/jcp2022614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.56770/jcp2022614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sudhakar C., Selvam K., Govarthanan M., Balakrishnan S., Sudalai A., Stalin M., Selvankumar T. Acorus Calamus Rhizome Extract Mediated Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles and Their Bactericidal Activity Against Human Pathogens. J. Genet. Eng. Biotechnol. 2015;13:93–99. doi: 10.1016/j.jgeb.2015.10.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jgeb.2015.10.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6299866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30647572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salmen S.H. Characterization and Antibacterial Activity of Silver Nanoparticles Biosynthesized Using (Indigofera Oblongifolia) Leaves Extract. Appl. Ecol. Environ. Res. 2019;17:12869–12876. doi: 10.15666/aeer/1706_1286912876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15666/aeer/1706_1286912876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajarathinam M., Girilal M., Peter M.K., Kalaichelvan P.T. Augmenting Potential Antifungal Activity of Gandhaka Rasayana (A Siddha Compound) Using Green Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles from Couroupita Guianensis Leaf Extract Against Selected Pathogenic Strains. Int. Res. J. Pharm. 2013;4:234–239. doi: 10.7897/2230-8407.04653.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7897/2230-8407.04653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murdock R.C., Braydich-Stolle L.K., Schrand A.M., Schlager J.J., Hussain S.M. Characterization of Nanomaterial Dispersion in Solution Prior to in Vitro Exposure Using Dynamic Light Scattering Technique. Toxicol. Sci. 2007;101:239–253. doi: 10.1093/toxsci/kfm240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kfm240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen N.H., Nhi T.T.Y., Nhi N.T.V., Cuc T.T.T., Tuan P.M., Nguyen D.H. Comparative Study of the Silver Nanoparticle Synthesis Ability and Antibacterial Activity of the Piper betle L. and Piper Sarmentosum Roxb. Extracts. J. Nanomater. 2021;2021:5518389. doi: 10.1155/2021/5518389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2021/5518389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chavan A.B., Goyal S., Patel A.M. Formulation of Silver Nanoparticles Using Gymnema Sylvestre Leaf Extract and In-Vitro Anti-Diabetic Activity. J. Pharm. Res. Int. 2022;34:39–49. doi: 10.9734/jpri/2022/v34i7A35450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/jpri/2022/v34i7A35450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugunakar Y.J., Shankar C.P. Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles from Fractionated Annona Reticulata Leaf Extract in Different Solvents and Analysis of Its Antioxidant and Antibacterial Activity. Curr. Trends Biotechnol. Pharm. 2020;14:289–301. doi: 10.5530/ctbp.2020.3.30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5530/ctbp.2020.3.30</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohanta Y.K., Biswas K., Jena S.K., Hashem A., Abd_Allah E.F., Mohanta T.K. Anti-biofilm and antibacterial activities of silver nanoparticles synthesized by the reducing activity of phytoconstituents present in the Indian medicinal plants. Front. Microbiol. 2020;11:1143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7324531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32655511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar D.G. Antioxidant, Antibacterial, Antidiabetic Potential and Genotoxicity of Silver Nanoparticles Using Leaf Extract of Curcuma Longa: A Novel Green Approach. Int. Res. J. Pharm. 2019;10:127–135. doi: 10.7897/2230-8407.100391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7897/2230-8407.100391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samoilova N.A., Krayukhina M.A., Vyshivannaya O.V., Blagodatskikh I.V. Investigation of the Binding of Lectins with Polymer Glycoconjugates and the Glycoconjugates Containing Silver Nanoparticles by Means of Optical Spectroscopy and Light Scattering. Polym. Sci. Ser. A. 2022;64:277–289. doi: 10.1134/S0965545X22700092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1134/S0965545X22700092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9149672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35669311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haase K., Pelling A.E. Investigating Cell Mechanics with Atomic Force Microscopy. J. R. Soc. Interface. 2015;12:20140970. doi: 10.1098/rsif.2014.0970.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsif.2014.0970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4345470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25589563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paulkumar K., Radhamani J., Parvathiraja C., Muthusamy N., Thangapandi E.J.J.S.B., Thangapandi J.R., Balakrishnan S., Rajeshkumar S. Green Synthesis of Multifaceted Silver Nanoparticles Using the Flower Extract of Aerva lanata and Evaluation of Its Biological and Environmental Applications. ChemistrySelect. 2020;5:2322–2331. doi: 10.1002/slct.201903228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/slct.201903228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satyavani K., Selvaraj G., Ramanathan T., Balasubramanian T. Biomedical Potential of Silver Nanoparticles Synthesized from Calli Cells of Citrullus colocynthis (L.) Schrad. J. Nanobiotechnol. 2011;9:43. doi: 10.1186/1477-3155-9-43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1477-3155-9-43</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3203035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21943321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>George S., Lin S., Ji Z., Thomas C.R., Li L., Mecklenburg M., Meng H., Wang X., Zhang H., Xia T., et al. Surface Defects on Plate-Shaped Silver Nanoparticles Contribute to Its Hazard Potential in a Fish Gill Cell Line and Zebrafish Embryos. ACS Nano. 2012;6:3745–3759. doi: 10.1021/nn204671v.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/nn204671v</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4139037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22482460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagtap R.R., Garud A., Puranik S.S., Rudrapal M., Ansari M.A., Alomary M.N., Alshamrani M., Salawi A., Almoshari Y., Khan J., et al. Biofabrication of Silver Nanoparticles (AgNPs) Using Embelin for Effective Therapeutic Management of Lung Cancer. Front. Nutr. 2022;9:960674. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2022.960674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.960674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9386231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35990347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charghadchi M., Gharari Z., Sadighian S., Yazdinezhad A., Sharafi A. Green Synthesized Silver Nanostructure Using Rhus Coriaria Fruit Extract Inhibits the Growth of Malignant McF-7 Cell Line. Braz. Arch. Biol. Technol. 2021;64:e21210069. doi: 10.1590/1678-4324-2021210069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1678-4324-2021210069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lade B.D., Shanware A., Barapatre R.M. Silver Micro-Nanoparticles—Properties, Synthesis, Characterization, and Applications. IntechOpen; London, UK: 2021. Synthesis, Characterization of Dichlorofluorescein Silver Nanoparticles (DCF-SNPs) and Their Effect on Seed Germination of Vigna radiata.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5772/intechopen.96756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebayo I.A., Usman A.I., Shittu F.B., Ismail N.Z., Arsad H., Muftaudeen T.K., Samian M.R. Boswellia dalzielii-Mediated Silver Nanoparticles Inhibited Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) Kasumi-1 Cells by Inducing Cell Cycle Arrest. Bioinorg. Chem. Appl. 2020;2020:8898360. doi: 10.1155/2020/8898360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2020/8898360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7528135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33029114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesan S., Mehalingam P., Selvam G.S. Biosynthesis and Characterization of Silver Nanoparticles Using Ginger Spent and Their Antibacterial Activity. Curr. Bot. 2021;12:174–179. doi: 10.25081/cb.2021.v12.6590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.25081/cb.2021.v12.6590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juling S., Niedzwiecka A., Böhmert L., Lichtenstein D., Selve S., Braeuning A., Thünemann A.F., Krause E., Lampen A. Protein Corona Analysis of Silver Nanoparticles Links to Their Cellular Effects. J. Proteome Res. 2017;16:4020–4034. doi: 10.1021/acs.jproteome.7b00412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.7b00412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28929768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandhoff R., Gröne H.J. Rat Kidney Lipid Composition Addressed by Mass Spectrometry Imaging. Kidney Int. 2016;90:1129–1130. doi: 10.1016/j.kint.2016.07.033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.kint.2016.07.033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27742183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haris P.I., Chapman D. The Conformational Analysis of Peptides Using Fourier Transform IR Spectroscopy. Biopolymers. 1995;37:251–263. doi: 10.1002/bip.360370404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bip.360370404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7540054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Lin Z., Zhao M., Xu T., Wang C., Hua L., Wang H., Xia H., Zhu B. Silver Nanoparticle Based Codelivery of Oseltamivir to Inhibit the Activity of the H1N1 Influenza Virus Through ROS-Mediated Signaling Pathways. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2016;8:24385–24393. doi: 10.1021/acsami.6b06613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.6b06613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27588566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Downes A., Mouras R., Elfick A. Optical Spectroscopy for Noninvasive Monitoring of Stem Cell Differentiation. J. Biomed. Biotechnol. 2010;2010:101864. doi: 10.1155/2010/101864.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2010/101864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2825551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20182537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakovitsky N., Frenk S., Kon H., Schwartz D., Temkin E., Solter E., Paikin S., Cohen R., Schwaber M.J., Carmeli Y., et al. Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy Is a New Option for Outbreak Investigation: A Retrospective Analysis of an Extended-Spectrum-Beta-Lactamase-Producing Klebsiella Pneumoniae Outbreak in a Neonatal Intensive Care Unit. J. Clin. Microbiol. 2020;58:e00098-20. doi: 10.1128/JCM.00098-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00098-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7180251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32161093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gajjar K., Trevisan J., Owens G., Keating P., Wood N., Stringfellow H.F., Martin-Hirsch P.L., Martin F. Fourier-Transform Infrared Spectroscopy Coupled with a Classification Machine for the Analysis of Blood Plasma or Serum: A Novel Diagnostic Approach for Ovarian Cancer. Analyst. 2013;138:3917–3926. doi: 10.1039/c3an36654e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c3an36654e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23325355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkhuder K. Attenuated Total Reflection-Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy: A Universal Analytical Technique with Promising Applications in Forensic Analyses. Int. J. Leg. Med. 2022;136:1717–1736. doi: 10.1007/s00414-022-02882-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00414-022-02882-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9436726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36050421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viana M.R.P., Melo I.M.A., Batista N.J.C., Raniero L., Canevari R.d.A. Micronucleus and FTIR Spectroscopy Analysis as Screening Tests for HPV Vírus Detection. Res. Soc. Dev. 2022;11:e20111636823. doi: 10.33448/rsd-v11i16.36823.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.33448/rsd-v11i16.36823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keren-Paz A., Najjar-Debbiny R. Analysis of Four Carbapenem-Resistant Acinetobacter baumannii Outbreaks Using Fourier-Transform Infrared Spectroscopy. Infect. Control. Hosp. Epidemiol. 2022;44:991–993. doi: 10.1017/ice.2022.109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/ice.2022.109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35535742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin S.-Y. Current and Potential Applications of Simultaneous DSC-FTIR Microspectroscopy for Pharmaceutical Analysis. J. Food Drug Anal. 2021;29:182. doi: 10.38212/2224-6614.3345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.38212/2224-6614.3345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9261823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35696204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arble C., Guo H., Matruglio A., Gianoncelli A., Vaccari L., Birarda G., Kolmakov A. Addressable Graphene Encapsulation of Wet Specimens on a Chip for Optical, Electron, Infrared and X-Ray Based Spectromicroscopy Studies. Lab Chip. 2021;21:4618–4628. doi: 10.1039/D1LC00440A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1LC00440A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34679149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eskandari V., Sahbafar H., Zeinalizad L., Mahmoudi R., Karimpour F., Hadi A., Bardania H. Coating of Silver Nanoparticles (AgNPs) on Glass Fibers by a Chemical Method as Plasmonic Surface-Enhanced Raman Spectroscopy (SERS) Sensors to Detect Molecular Vibrations of Doxorubicin (DOX) Drug in Blood Plasma. Arab. J. Chem. 2022;15:104005. doi: 10.1016/j.arabjc.2022.104005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arabjc.2022.104005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian L., Song X., Liu T., Li A., Ning Y., Hua X., Liang D. A Review of Spectroscopic Probes Constructed from Aptamer-Binding Gold/Silver Nanoparticles or Their Dimers in Environmental Pollutants’ Detection. Anal. Sci. 2022;38:1247–1259. doi: 10.1007/s44211-022-00168-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44211-022-00168-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35930232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasil’kov A., Batsalova T., Dzhambazov B., Naumkin A. XPS Study of Silver and Copper Nanoparticles Demonstrated Selective Anticancer, Proapoptotic, and Antibacterial Properties. Surf. Interface Anal. 2021;54:189–202. doi: 10.1002/sia.7038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/sia.7038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gudz K.Y., Matveev A.T., Permyakova E.S., Bondarev A.V., Slukin P.V., Ignatov S.G., Shtansky D.V. Nanostructured Hexagonal BN Coating-Supported Silver and Iron Oxide Nanoparticles and Related Bactericidal and Fungicidal Activities. Appl. Surf. Sci. 2022;603:154418. doi: 10.1016/j.apsusc.2022.154418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apsusc.2022.154418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talabani R.F., Hamad S.M., Barzinjy A.A., Demir U. Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles and Their Applications in Harvesting Sunlight for Solar Thermal Generation. Nanomaterials. 2021;11:2421. doi: 10.3390/nano11092421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11092421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8471701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34578737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasquez E.S., Prehn E.M., Walters K.B. Assessing Magnetic Iron Oxide Nanoparticle Properties under Different Thermal Treatments. J. Therm. Anal. Calorim. 2019;143:35–46. doi: 10.1007/s10973-019-09195-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10973-019-09195-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayawardena H.S.N., Liyanage S.H., Rathnayake K., Patel U., Yan M. Analytical Methods for Characterization of Nanomaterial Surfaces. Anal. Chem. 2021;93:1889–1911. doi: 10.1021/acs.analchem.0c05208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.0c05208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7941215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33434434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansfield E., Banash M. Modeling, Characterization, and Production of Nanomaterials. Woodhead Publishing; Sawston, UK: 2023. Thermal Analysis of Nanoparticles: Methods, Kinetics, and Recent Advances; pp. 535–547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Estupiñán P., Miranda-Carvajal I., Campos P.C., Guerrero-Fajardo C.A., Giraldo L., Moreno-Piraján J.C. Graphene-Based Materials: Analysis through Calorimetric Techniques. J. Therm. Anal. Calorim. 2022;147:9301–9351. doi: 10.1007/s10973-022-11206-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10973-022-11206-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seifi H., Gholami T., Seifi S., Ghoreishi S.M., Salavati-Niasari M. A Review on Current Trends in Thermal Analysis and Hyphenated Techniques in the Investigation of Physical, Mechanical and Chemical Properties of Nanomaterials. J. Anal. Appl. Pyrolysis. 2020;149:104840. doi: 10.1016/j.jaap.2020.104840.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaap.2020.104840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jatoi A.W., Kim I.S., Ni Q.Q. A Comparative Study on Synthesis of AgNPs on Cellulose Nanofibers by Thermal Treatment and DMF for Antibacterial Activities. Mater. Sci. Eng. C. 2019;98:1179–1195. doi: 10.1016/j.msec.2019.01.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.msec.2019.01.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30813001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qais F.A., Shafiq A., Khan H.M., Husain F.M., Khan R.A., Alenazi B., Alsalme A., Ahmad I. Antibacterial Effect of Silver Nanoparticles Synthesized Using Murraya koenigii (L.) Against Multidrug-Resistant Pathogens. Bioinorg. Chem. Appl. 2019;2019:4649506. doi: 10.1155/2019/4649506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2019/4649506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6636582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31354799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendi S.S., Shiri M., Poormoradi B., Alikhani M.Y., Afshar S., Farmani A. Antibacterial Effects of a 940 Nm Diode Laser with/ without Silver Nanoparticles Against Enterococcus faecalis. J. Lasers Med. Sci. 2021;12:e73. doi: 10.34172/jlms.2021.73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34172/jlms.2021.73</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8837865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35155158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayyar P., Sethi A., Thakur D., Khullar S., Gayati S., Adarsh K. Antibacterial Effect of Silver Nanoparticle Gel as an Intracanal Medicament in Combination with Other Medicaments Against Enterococcus Faecalis: An in Vitro Study. J. Pharm. Bioallied Sci. 2021;13:S408–S411. doi: 10.4103/jpbs.JPBS_600_20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jpbs.JPBS_600_20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8375782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34447121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandian S.R.K., Deepak V., Kalishwaralal K., Viswanathan P.C., Gurunathan S. Mechanism of Bactericidal Activity of Silver Nitrate—A Concentration Dependent Bi-Functional Molecule. Braz. J. Microbiol. 2010;41:805–809. doi: 10.1590/S1517-83822010000300033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S1517-83822010000300033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3768641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24031558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pramod G., Sharma K., Malviya R. Toxicity and Application of Nano-Silver in Multi-Drug Resistant Therapy. Lett. Appl. NanoBioSci. 2020;9:824–829. doi: 10.33263/lianbs91.824829.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.33263/lianbs91.824829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allemailem K.S., Khadri H., Azam M., Khan M.A., Rahmani A.H., Alrumaihi F., Khateef R., Ansari M.A., Alatawi E.A., Alsugoor M.H. Ajwa-Dates (Phoenix Dactylifera)-Mediated Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles and Their Anti-Bacterial, Anti-Biofilm, and Cytotoxic Potential. Appl. Sci. 2022;12:4537. doi: 10.3390/app12094537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app12094537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X., Li C.M., Huang C. Curcumin Modified Silver Nanoparticles for Highly Efficient Inhibition of Respiratory Syncytial Virus Infection. Nanoscale. 2016;8:3040–3048. doi: 10.1039/C5NR07918G.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C5NR07918G</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26781043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lara H.H., Ayala-Núñez N.V., Ixtepan-Turrent L., Rodríguez-Padilla C. Mode of Antiviral Action of Silver Nanoparticles Against HIV-1. J. Nanobiotechnol. 2010;8:1. doi: 10.1186/1477-3155-8-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1477-3155-8-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2818642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20145735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeevanandam J., Krishnan S., Hii Y.S., Pan S., Chan Y.S., Acquah C., Danquah M.K., Rodrigues J. Synthesis Approach-Dependent Antiviral Properties of Silver Nanoparticles and Nanocomposites. J. Nanostruct. Chem. 2022;12:809–831. doi: 10.1007/s40097-021-00465-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40097-021-00465-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8760111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35070207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin I.X., Zhang J., Zhao I.S., Mei M.L., Li Q., Chu C.H. The Antibacterial Mechanism of Silver Nanoparticles and Its Application in Dentistry. Int. J. Nanomed. 2020;15:2555–2562. doi: 10.2147/IJN.S246764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJN.S246764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7174845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32368040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lara H.H., Romero-Urbina D., Pierce C.G., Lopez-Ribot J.L., Arellano-Jiménez M.J., José–Yacamán M. Effect of Silver Nanoparticles on Candida Albicans Biofilms: An Ultrastructural Study. J. Nanobiotechnol. 2015;13:91. doi: 10.1186/s12951-015-0147-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12951-015-0147-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4678641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26666378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann R., Holmes A., McNeilly O., Cavaliere R., Sotiriou G.A., Rice S.A., Gunawan C. Evolution of Biofilm-Forming Pathogenic Bacteria in the Presence of Nanoparticles and Antibiotic: Adaptation Phenomena and Cross-Resistance. J. Nanobiotechnol. 2021;19:291. doi: 10.1186/s12951-021-01027-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12951-021-01027-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8474960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34579731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dudek-Wicher R., Junka A., Migdał P., Korzeniowska-Kowal A., Wzorek A., Bartoszewicz M. The Antibiofilm Activity of Selected Substances Used in Oral Health Prophylaxis. BMC Oral Health. 2022;22:509. doi: 10.1186/s12903-022-02532-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12903-022-02532-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9672622</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36397044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almatroudi A., Khadri H., Azam M., Rahmani A.H., Khaleefah A., Khaleefah F., Khateef R., Ansari M.A., Allemailem K.S. Antibacterial, Antibiofilm and Anticancer Activity of Biologically Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles Using Seed Extract of Nigella Sativa. Processes. 2020;8:388. doi: 10.3390/pr8040388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pr8040388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousef M.K., Al-Ramahi S.K. Use of Silver Biosynthesized Nanoparticles from Bacteria Pseudomonas Aeruginosa in the Treatment of Induced Bacterial Injury Infection. Int. J. Health Sci. 2022;6:12087–12095. doi: 10.53730/ijhs.v6nS1.8033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.53730/ijhs.v6nS1.8033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhoolappa M., Prasad R., Lakshmishree K.T., Sundareshan S., Choudari M., Nayak U.Y. NanoBioscaffolds as Wound Healing Biomaterials in Animals. Indian J. Anim. Res. 2021;56:1149–1153. doi: 10.18805/IJAR.B-4236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18805/IJAR.B-4236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konop M., Damps T., Misicka A., Rudnicka L. Certain Aspects of Silver and Silver Nanoparticles in Wound Care: A Minireview. J. Nanomater. 2016;2016:7614753. doi: 10.1155/2016/7614753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2016/7614753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasetyo B.C., Sugiharti R.J., Mahendra I.N.B., Halimah I., Widyasar E.M., Rusminah N., Mustika N.I.K. Evaluation of Silver Nanoparticles Addition in Periodontal Dressing for Wound Tissue Healing by 99mTc-Ciprofloxacin. J. Young-Pharm. 2018;11:17–20. doi: 10.5530/jyp.2019.11.4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5530/jyp.2019.11.4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurunathan S., Qasim M., Choi Y., Tae J., Park C., Hong K., Kim J., Song H. Antiviral Potential of Nanoparticles—Can Nanoparticles Fight Against Coronaviruses? Nanomaterials. 2020;10:1645. doi: 10.3390/nano10091645.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano10091645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7557932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32825737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marimuthu S., Rahuman A.A., Rajakumar G., Santhoshkumar T., Kirthi A.V., Jayaseelan C., Bagavan A., Zahir A.A., Elango G., Kamaraj C. Evaluation of Green Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles Against Parasites. Parasitol. Res. 2010;108:1541–1549. doi: 10.1007/s00436-010-2212-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00436-010-2212-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21181192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souza A.O., Oliveira J.W.d.F., Moreno C.J.G., Medeiros M.J.C.d., Fernandes-Negreiros M.M., Souza F.R.M., Pontes D.L., Silva M.S., Rocha H.A.O. Silver Nanoparticles Containing Fucoidan Synthesized by Green Method Have Anti-Trypanosoma Cruzi Activity. Nanomaterials. 2022;12:2059. doi: 10.3390/nano12122059.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano12122059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9231105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35745396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad A., Syed F., Shah A.A., Khan Z., Tahir K., Khan A.U., Yuan Q. Silver and Gold Nanoparticles from Sargentodoxa Cuneata: Synthesis, Characterization and Antileishmanial Activity. RSC Adv. 2015;5:73793–73806. doi: 10.1039/C5RA13206A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C5RA13206A</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adeyemi O.S., Murata Y., Sugi T., Kato K. Inorganic Nanoparticles Kill Toxoplasma gondii Via Changes in Redox Status and Mitochondrial Membrane Potential. Int. J. Nanomed. 2017;12:1647–1661. doi: 10.2147/IJN.S122178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJN.S122178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5339004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28280332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soni N., Prakash S. Green Nanoparticles for Mosquito Control. Sci. World J. 2014;2014:496362. doi: 10.1155/2014/496362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2014/496362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4163329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25243210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soni N., Prakash S. Efficacy of Fungus Mediated Silver and Gold Nanoparticles Against Aedes Aegypti Larvae. Parasitol. Res. 2011;110:175–184. doi: 10.1007/s00436-011-2467-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00436-011-2467-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21647674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padzik M., Hendiger E.B., Chomicz L., Grodzik M., Szmidt M., Grobelny J., Lorenzo-Morales J. Tannic Acid-Modified Silver Nanoparticles as a Novel Therapeutic Agent Against Acanthamoeba. Parasitol. Res. 2018;117:3519–3525. doi: 10.1007/s00436-018-6049-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00436-018-6049-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30112674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>KarimiPourSaryazdi A., Ghaffarifar F., Tavakoli P., KarimiPourSaryazdi Y., Zaki L., Bahadory S. Anti-Parasitic Effects of Herbal Extract-Based Silver Nanoparticles on the Trophozoite and Cystic Forms of Acanthamoeba Protozoa. Int. J. Enteric Pathog. 2020;8:84–88. doi: 10.34172/ijep.2020.19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34172/ijep.2020.19</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>KarimiPourSaryazdi A., Tavakoli P., Barati M., Ghaffarifar F., Ghaffari A., KarimiPourSaryazdi Y. Anti-Toxoplasma Effects of Silver Nanoparticles Based on Ginger Extract: An in Vitro Study. J. Arch. Mil. Med. 2020;7:e104248. doi: 10.5812/jamm.104248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5812/jamm.104248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alavijeh A.A., Barati M., Barati M., Dehkordi H.A. The Potential of Magnetic Nanoparticles for Diagnosis and Treatment of Cancer Based on Body Magnetic Field and Organ-on-the-Chip. Adv. Pharm. Bull. 2019;9:360–373. doi: 10.15171/apb.2019.043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15171/apb.2019.043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6773933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31592054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurunathan S., Qasim M., Park C., Yoo H., Kim J.-H., Hong K. Cytotoxic Potential and Molecular Pathway Analysis of Silver Nanoparticles in Human Colon Cancer Cells HCT116. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2018;19:2269. doi: 10.3390/ijms19082269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms19082269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6121495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30072642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed T., Shahid M., Noman M., Niazi M.B.K., Zubair M., Almatroudi A., Khurshid M., Tariq F., Mumtaz R., Li B. Bioprospecting a Native Silver-Resistant Bacillus Safensis Strain for Green Synthesis and Subsequent Antibacterial and Anticancer Activities of Silver Nanoparticles. J. Adv. Res. 2020;24:475–483. doi: 10.1016/j.jare.2020.05.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jare.2020.05.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7296185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32566283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari M.A., Asiri S.M.M., Alzohairy M.A., Alomary M.N., Almatroudi A., Khan F.A. Biofabricated Fatty Acids-Capped Silver Nanoparticles as Potential Antibacterial, Antifungal, Antibiofilm and Anticancer Agents. Pharmaceuticals. 2021;14:139. doi: 10.3390/ph14020139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ph14020139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7915658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33572296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Félix F., López-Cota A.G., Moreno-Vásquez M.J., Graciano-Verdugo A.Z., Quintero-Reyes I.E., Del-Toro-Sánchez C.L., Tapia-Hernández J.A. Sustainable-Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Safflower (Carthamus tinctorius L.) Waste Extract and Its Antibacterial Activity. Heliyon. 2021;7:e06923. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8111583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34007921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olmos D., Pontes-Quero G.M., Corral A., González-Gaitano G., González-Benito J. Preparation and Characterization of Antimicrobial Films Based on LDPE/Ag Nanoparticles with Potential Uses in Food and Health Industries. Nanomaterials. 2018;8:60. doi: 10.3390/nano8020060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano8020060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5853693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29364193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahari H., Karim G., Anvar A.A., Pooyamanesh M., Sajadis A., Mostaghim A., Heydari S. Synthesis of the Silver Nanoparticle by Chemical Reduction Method and Preparation of Nanocomposite Based on AgNPS; Proceedings of the 4th World Congress on Mechanical, Chemical, and Material Engineering, MCM’18; Madrid, Spain. 16–18 August 2018;</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11159/iccpe18.125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambré C., Baviera J.M.B., Bolognesi C., Chesson A., Cocconcelli P.S., Crebelli R., Gott D.M., Grob K., Lampi E., Mengelers M., et al. Safety Assessment of the Substance Silver Nanoparticles for Use in Food Contact Materials. EFSA J. 2021;19:e06790. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2021.6790.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2021.6790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8350891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34400977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rus A., Leordean V.D., Berce P. Silver Nanoparticles (AgNP) Impregnated Filters in Drinking Water Disinfection. MATEC Web Conf. 2017;137:07007. doi: 10.1051/matecconf/201713707007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1051/matecconf/201713707007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tankhiwale R., Bajpai S. Silver-nanoparticle-loaded Chitosan Lactate Films with Fair Antibacterial Properties. J. Appl. Polym. Sci. 2009;115:1894–1900. doi: 10.1002/app.31168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/app.31168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osanloo M., Assadpour S., Mehravaran A., Abastabar M., Akhtari J. Niosome-Loaded Antifungal Drugs as an Effective Nanocarrier System: A Mini Review. Curr. Med. Mycol. 2019;4:31–36. doi: 10.18502/cmm.4.4.384.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18502/cmm.4.4.384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6386503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30815615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y., Liu M., Yang Z., Lin W.-S., Chen L., Tan J. Enhanced Antibacterial Effect on Zirconia Implant Abutment by Silver Linear-Beam Ion Implantation. J. Funct. Biomater. 2023;14:46. doi: 10.3390/jfb14010046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jfb14010046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9865340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36662093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haugen H.J., Makhtari S., Ahmadi S., Hussain B. The Antibacterial and Cytotoxic Effects of Silver Nanoparticles Coated Titanium Implants: A Narrative Review. Materials. 2022;15:5025. doi: 10.3390/ma15145025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma15145025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9320431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35888492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian T., Dang B., Li F., Yang K., Wei D., Zhang P. Microstructure, Mechanical and Antibacterial Properties of TiNb-Based Alloy Implanted by Silver Ions. Coatings. 2021;11:1213. doi: 10.3390/coatings11101213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/coatings11101213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geng H., Poologasundarampillai G., Todd N.M., Devlin-Mullin A., Moore K.L., Golrokhi Z., Gilchrist J.B., Jones E.S., Potter R.J., Sutcliffe C., et al. Biotransformation of Silver Released from Nanoparticle Coated Titanium Implants Revealed in Regenerating Bone. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2017;9:21169–21180. doi: 10.1021/acsami.7b05150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.7b05150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28581710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorzelanny C., Kmeth R., Obermeier A., Bauer A., Halter N., Kümpel K., Schneider M., Wixforth A., Gollwitzer H., Burgkart R., et al. Silver Nanoparticle-Enriched Diamond-Like Carbon Implant Modification as a Mammalian Cell Compatible Surface with Antimicrobial Properties. Sci. Rep. 2016;6:22849. doi: 10.1038/srep22849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep22849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4783782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26955791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motas J.G., Gorji N.E., Nedelcu D., Brabazon D., Quadrini F. XPS, SEM, DSC and Nanoindentation Characterization of Silver Nanoparticle-Coated Biopolymer Pellets. Appl. Sci. 2021;11:7706. doi: 10.3390/app11167706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app11167706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Li Y., Luo X., Ding Y.H. Enhancing Antibacterial Property of Porous Titanium Surfaces with Silver Nanoparticles Coatings via Electron-Beam Evaporation. J. Mater. Sci. Mater. Med. 2022;33:57. doi: 10.1007/s10856-022-06679-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10856-022-06679-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9226093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35737197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanthasamy R., Algarni M., Leo C.P., Zakaria N.A.C., Zwawi M. The Effects of Solvent on Superhydrophobic Polyurethane Coating Incorporated with Hydrophilic SiO2 Nanoparticles as Antifouling Paint. Polymers. 2023;15:1328. doi: 10.3390/polym15061328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym15061328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10058479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36987109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jo Y.-W., Seo J.H., Choi B.-H., Kim B.J., Shin H.H., Hwang B.H., Joon H. Surface-Independent Antibacterial Coating Using Silver Nanoparticle-Generating Engineered Mussel Glue. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2014;6:20242–20253. doi: 10.1021/am505784k.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/am505784k</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25311392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpenyana-Monyatsi L., Mthombeni N.H., Momba M.N.B. Cost-Effective Filter Materials Coated with Silver Nanoparticles for the Removal of Pathogenic Bacteria in Groundwater. nt. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2012;9:244–271. doi: 10.3390/ijerph9010244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph9010244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3315070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22470290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunell M., Haapanen J., Brobbey K.J., Saarinen J.J., Toivakka M., Mäkelä J.M., Huovinen P., Eerola E. Antimicrobial Characterization of Silver Nanoparticle-Coated Surfaces by Touch Test Method. Nanotechnol. Sci. Appl. 2017;10:137–145. doi: 10.2147/NSA.S139505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/NSA.S139505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5694196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29180854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y.-C., Mi C. Improved Hydrothermal Aging Performance of Glass Fiber-reinforced Polymer Composites via Silica Nanoparticle Coating. J. Appl. Polym. Sci. 2019;137:48652. doi: 10.1002/app.48652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/app.48652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin I.X., Zhao I.S., Mei M.L., Li Q., Yu O.Y., Chu C.H. Use of Silver Nanomaterials for Caries Prevention: A Concise Review. Int. J. Nanomed. 2020;15:3181–3191. doi: 10.2147/IJN.S253833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJN.S253833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7212989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32440117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corrêa J.M., Mori M., Sanches H.L., Cruz A.D.d., Poiate E., Poiate I.A.V.P. Silver Nanoparticles in Dental Biomaterials. Int. J. Biomater. 2015;2015:485275. doi: 10.1155/2015/485275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2015/485275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4312639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25667594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandéz C.C., Sokolonski A.R., Fonseca M.S., Stanisić D., Araújo D.B.d., Azevedo V., Portela R.W., Tasić L. Applications of Silver Nanoparticles in Dentistry: Advances and Technological Innovation. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2021;22:2485. doi: 10.3390/ijms22052485.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms22052485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7957900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33801230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lubojanski A., Nowak N., Rewak-Soroczynska J., Sztyler K., Zakrzewski W., Dobrzyński W., Szymonowicz M., Rybak Z., Wiglusz K., Wiglusz R.J. Application of Selected Nanomaterials and Ozone in Modern Clinical Dentistry. Nanomaterials. 2021;11:259. doi: 10.3390/nano11020259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11020259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7909445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33498453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandhimathi C., Chandrasekharan S., Koh T.-W., Bhatnagar S.P. Synthesis, Characterization, Antibacterial and Wound Healing Efficacy of Silver Nanoparticles from Azadirachta Indica. Front. Microbiol. 2021;12:611560. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2021.611560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.611560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7932996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33679635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng L., Zhang S., Zhang Q., Gao W., Mu S., Wang B. Wound Healing Potential of Silver Nanoparticles from Hybanthus Enneaspermus on Rats. Heliyon. 2024;10:e36118. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11403429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39286104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su H., Chen Y., Jing X., Zhao X., Sun H., Liu Z., Qiu Y., Zhang Z., Guan H., Meng L. Antimicrobial, Antioxidant, and Anti-Inflammatory Nanoplatform for Effective Management of Infected Wounds. Adv. Healthc. Mater. 2024;13:2302868. doi: 10.1002/adhm.202302868.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adhm.202302868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37925607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naseer F., Ahmed M., Majid A., Kamal W., Phull A.R. Green Nanoparticles as Multifunctional Nanomedicines: Insights into Anti-Inflammatory Effects, Growth Signaling and Apoptosis Mechanism in Cancer. Semin. Cancer Biol. 2022;86:310–324. doi: 10.1016/j.semcancer.2022.06.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.semcancer.2022.06.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35787941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bozorgi A., Khazaei M., Soleimani M., Jamalpoor Z. Application of Nanoparticles in Bone Tissue Engineering; a Review on the Molecular Mechanisms Driving Osteogenesis. Biomater. Sci. 2021;9:4541–4567. doi: 10.1039/D1BM00504A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1BM00504A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34075945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rani G.N., Rao B.N., Shamili M., Padmaja J. Combined Effect of Silver Nanoparticles and Honey in Experimental Wound Healing Process in Rats. Biomed. Res. 2018;29:3074–3078. doi: 10.4066/biomedicalresearch.29-18-898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4066/biomedicalresearch.29-18-898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Es-haghi A., Mashreghi M., Bazaz M.R., Tabrizi M.H., Darroudi M. Fabrication of Biopolymer Based Nanocomposite Wound Dressing: Evaluation of Wound Healing Properties and Wound Microbial Load. IET Nanobiotechnol. 2017;11:517–522. doi: 10.1049/iet-nbt.2016.0160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1049/iet-nbt.2016.0160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8676507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28745283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee P., Satapathy M.K., Mukhopahayay A., Das P. Leaf Extract Mediated Green Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles from Widely Available Indian Plants: Synthesis, Characterization, Antimicrobial Property and Toxicity Analysis. Bioresour. Bioprocess. 2014;1:3. doi: 10.1186/s40643-014-0003-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40643-014-0003-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akpınar I., Ünal M., Sar T. Potential Antifungal Effects of Silver Nanoparticles (AgNPs) of Different Sizes against Phytopathogenic Fusarium Oxysporum F. Sp. Radicis-Lycopersici (FORL) Strains. SN Appl. Sci. 2021;3:506. doi: 10.1007/s42452-021-04524-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42452-021-04524-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosidze E., Mshvildadze V., Legault J., Berashvili D., Jokhadze M., Bakuridze L., Bakuridze A. Green Synthesis Os Silver Nanoparticles Using Methanolic Extracts of Gentiana Septemfida, Erysimum Contractum and Chelidonium Majus and Evaluation of Antibacterial, Antifungal and Cytotoxic Activities of Obtained Agnps. Exp. Clin. Med. Ga. 2022;7:1–7. doi: 10.52340/jecm.2022.07.36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.52340/jecm.2022.07.36</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arif R., Uddin R. A Review on Recent Developments in the Biosynthesis of Silver Nanoparticles and Its Biomedical Applications. Med. Devices Sens. 2020;4:e10158. doi: 10.1002/mds3.10158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mds3.10158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antony V.S., Silky V., Raji P., SaiPriya C., Selvarani J.A. Bioactivity Studies of Datura Metel, Aegle Marmelos, Annona Reticulata and Saraca Indica and Their Green Synthesized Silver Nanoparticle. J. Pure Appl. Microbiol. 2019;13:329–338. doi: 10.22207/jpam.13.1.36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22207/jpam.13.1.36</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero-Urbina D., Lara H.H., Velázquez-Salazar J.J., Arellano-Jiménez M.J., Larios E., Srinivasan A., Lopez-Ribot J.L., Yacamán M.J. Ultrastructural Changes in Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococcus aureus induced by Positively Charged Silver Nanoparticles. Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2015;6:2396–2405. doi: 10.3762/bjnano.6.246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3762/bjnano.6.246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4685924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26734530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castellano J.J., Shafii S.M., Ko F., Donate G., Wright T.E., Mannari R.J., Payne W.G., Smith D.J., Robson M.C. Comparative Evaluation of Silver-containing Antimicrobial Dressings and Drugs. Int. Wound J. 2007;4:114–122. doi: 10.1111/j.1742-481X.2007.00316.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1742-481X.2007.00316.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7951235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17651227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daphedar A., Taranath T.C. Characterization and Cytotoxic Effect of Biogenic Silver Nanoparticles on Mitotic Chromosomes of Drimia Polyantha (Blatt. &amp; McCann) Stearn. Toxicol. Rep. 2018;5:910–918. doi: 10.1016/j.toxrep.2018.08.018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2018.08.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6129697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30211013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asharani P.V., Mun G.L.K., Hande M.P., Valiyaveettil S. Cytotoxicity and Genotoxicity of Silver Nanoparticles in Human Cells. ACS Nano. 2008;3:279–290. doi: 10.1021/nn800596w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/nn800596w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19236062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farahani Z.A., Parivar K., Roodbari N.H., Farhadi M. Comparative Study of the Cytotoxic Effect of Silver Nanoparticles on Human Lymphocytes and HPB-ALL Cell Line: As an in Vitro Study. Iran. Red Crescent Med. J. 2020;22:e98803. doi: 10.5812/ircmj.98803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5812/ircmj.98803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nashaat Y.M., Hassan S.A., Labib A.H., Elaasar M.S., Negm A. Comparative Study of the Cytotoxicty and Genotoxicity of Silver Zeolite and Nano Silver. Egypt. Dent. J. 2018;64:3995–4002. doi: 10.21608/edj.2018.79515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21608/edj.2018.79515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maki A., Lin Y., Aoyama M., Sato K., Gao J., Tsujino H., Nagano K., Higashisaka K., Tsutsumi Y. Silver Nanoparticles Induce DNA Hypomethylation Through Proteasome-Mediated Degradation of DNA Methyltransferase 1. Biol. Pharm. Bull. 2020;43:1924–1930. doi: 10.1248/bpb.b20-00631.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1248/bpb.b20-00631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33268710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baras B.H., Melo M.A.S., Thumbigere-Math V., Tay F.R., Fouad A.F., Oates T.W., Weir M.D., Cheng L., Xu H.H. Novel Bioactive and Therapeutic Root Canal Sealers with Antibacterial and Remineralization Properties. Materials. 2020;13:1096. doi: 10.3390/ma13051096.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma13051096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7084849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32121595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah K.N., Shah P., Mullen A.R., QingQuan C., Southerland M.R., Chirra B., DeBerardinis R.J., Cannon C.L. N-Acetyl Cysteine Abrogates Silver-Induced Reactive Oxygen Species in Human Cells without Altering Silver-Based Antimicrobial Activity. Toxicol. Lett. 2020;332:118–129. doi: 10.1016/j.toxlet.2020.07.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2020.07.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7643162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32659471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foldbjerg R., Dang D.A., Autrup H. Cytotoxicity and Genotoxicity of Silver Nanoparticles in the Human Lung Cancer Cell Line, A549. Arch. Toxicol. 2010;85:743–750. doi: 10.1007/s00204-010-0545-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00204-010-0545-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20428844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y., Li J., Liu L., Wang Y., Jiang Y., Zeng C., Lu Z., Xie D., Guo J. Zinc-Based Tannin-Modified Composite Microparticulate Scaffolds with Balanced Antimicrobial Activity and Osteogenesis for Infected Bone Defect Repair. Adv. Healthc. Mater. 2023;12:e2300303. doi: 10.1002/adhm.202300303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adhm.202300303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36964976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlson C., Hussain S.M., Schrand A.M., Braydich-Stolle L.K., Hess K.L., Jones R.L., Schlager J.J. Unique Cellular Interaction of Silver Nanoparticles: Size-Dependent Generation of Reactive Oxygen Species. J. Phys. Chem. B. 2008;112:13608–13619. doi: 10.1021/jp712087m.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jp712087m</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18831567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu D., Yang D.-X., Li Y., Bi G., Qian M., Li Y., Zhu Y., Chen L., Luo W.-X. Nano-Silver Medical Antibacterial Dressing Combined with High-Flow Oxygen Therapy Facilitates Ulcer Wound Healing of Superficial Malignant Tumors. Cancer Manag. Res. 2021;13:9007–9013. doi: 10.2147/CMAR.S341448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S341448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8664651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34908876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang H., Zhang Y., Lü Z., Lebrun R., Gontero B., Li W. Interaction Between Silver Nanoparticles and Two Dehydrogenases: Role of Thiol Groups. Small. 2019;15:e1900860. doi: 10.1002/smll.201900860.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/smll.201900860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31111667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abo-Elmaaty S.A., Shati A.A., Alfaifi M.Y., Elbehairi S.E.I., Sheraba N.S., Hassan M., Badawy M.S.E.M., Ghareeb A., Hamed A.A., Gabr E. Biofilm Inhibitory Activity of Actinomycete-Synthesized AgNPs with Low Cytotoxic Effect: Experimental and in Silico Study. Microorganisms. 2022;11:102. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms11010102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms11010102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9866079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36677395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phan K.S., Le T.T.H., Nguyen T.M.H., Trang T.T., Hoang P.H., To X.T., Nguyen T.T., Kim D.P., Ha P.T. Co-delivery of Doxycycline, Florfenicol and Silver Nanoparticles Using Alginate/Chitosan Nanocarriers. ChemistrySelect. 2022;7:e202201954. doi: 10.1002/slct.202201954.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/slct.202201954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapadia C., Alhazmi A., Patel N., Elesawy B.H., Sayyed R.Z., Lokhandwala F., Haque S., Datta R. Nanoparticles Combined with Cefixime as an Effective Synergistic Strategy Against Salmonella Enterica Typhi. Saudi J. Biol. Sci. 2021;28:4164–4172. doi: 10.1016/j.sjbs.2021.05.032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2021.05.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8324992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34354396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou L., Wang J., Gao Y., Ren X., Rottenberg M.E., Lu J., Holmgren A. Synergistic Antibacterial Activity of Silver with Antibiotics Correlating with the Upregulation of the ROS Production. Sci. Rep. 2018;8:11131. doi: 10.1038/s41598-018-29313-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-29313-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6057937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30042429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rather M.A., Mandal M. Attenuation of Biofilm and Quorum Sensing Regulated Virulence Factors of an Opportunistic Pathogen Pseudomonas Aeruginosa by Phytofabricated Silver Nanoparticles. Microb. Pathog. 2023;185:106433. doi: 10.1016/j.micpath.2023.106433.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2023.106433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37913826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S., Cao S., Guo J., Luo L., Zhou Y., Lin C., Shi J., Fan C., Lv M., Wang L. Graphene Oxide–Silver Nanocomposites Modulate Biofilm Formation and Extracellular Polymeric Substance (EPS) Production. Nanoscale. 2018;10:19603–19611. doi: 10.1039/C8NR04064H.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C8NR04064H</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30325394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed B., Hashmi A., Khan M.S., Musarrat J. ROS Mediated Destruction of Cell Membrane, Growth and Biofilms of Human Bacterial Pathogens by Stable Metallic AgNPs Functionalized from Bell Pepper Extract and Quercetin. Adv. Powder Technol. 2018;29:1601–1616. doi: 10.1016/j.apt.2018.03.025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apt.2018.03.025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno Ruiz Y.P., de Almeida Campos L.A., Alves Agreles M.A., Galembeck A., Macário Ferro Cavalcanti I. Advanced Hydrogels Combined with Silver and Gold Nanoparticles against Antimicrobial Resistance. Antibiotics. 2023;12:104. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics12010104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12010104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9855178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36671305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mori Y., Ono T., Miyahira Y., Nguyen V., Matsui T., Ishihara M. Antiviral Activity of Silver Nanoparticle/Chitosan Composites Against H1N1 Influenza a Virus. Nanoscale Res. Lett. 2013;8:93. doi: 10.1186/1556-276X-8-93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1556-276X-8-93</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3606407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23421446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim S.W., Jung J.H., Lamsal K., Kim Y.S., Min J.S., Lee Y.S. Antifungal Effects of Silver Nanoparticles (AgNPs) Against Various Plant Pathogenic Fungi. Mycobiology. 2012;40:53–58. doi: 10.5941/MYCO.2012.40.1.053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5941/MYCO.2012.40.1.053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3385153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22783135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almansob A., Bahkali A.H., Albarrag A., Alshomrani M., Binjomah A., Hailan W.A., Ameen F. Effective Treatment of Resistant Opportunistic Fungi Associated with Immuno-Compromised Individuals Using Silver Biosynthesized Nanoparticles. Appl. Nanosci. 2022;12:3871–3882. doi: 10.1007/s13204-022-02539-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13204-022-02539-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9307438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35909460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi H., Ding J., Chen C., Yao Q., Zhang W., Fu Y., Wang X., Ruan J. Antimicrobial Action of Biocompatible Silver Microspheres and Their Role in the Potential Treatment of Fungal Keratitis. ACS Biomater. Sci. Eng. 2021;7:5090–5098. doi: 10.1021/acsbiomaterials.1c00815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsbiomaterials.1c00815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34634199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashrafi M., Bayat M., Mortazavi P., Hashemi S.J., Meimandipour A. Antimicrobial Effect of Chitosan–Silver–Copper Nanocomposite on Candida Albicans. J. Nanostruct. Chem. 2020;10:87–95. doi: 10.1007/s40097-020-00331-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40097-020-00331-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hameed A.A., Alheety M.A. Synthesis, Characterization and Antifungal Activity of Coated Silver Nanoparticles-Nystatin and Coated Silver Nanoparticles-Clotrimazol. Tikrit J. Pure Sci. 2018;23:63–70. doi: 10.25130/tjps.v23i7.698.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.25130/tjps.v23i7.698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Obaidi H., Petraityte I., Hibbard T., Majumder M., Kalgudi R., Zariwala M.G. Antifungal Nanosuspensions with Surfactants and Silver for the Treatment of Onychomycosis. Eur. J. Pharm. Biopharm. 2022;179:194–205. doi: 10.1016/j.ejpb.2022.09.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejpb.2022.09.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36099971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palanisamy D., Gounder B.S., Selvaraj K., Kandhasamy S., Alqahtani T., Alqahtani A., Chidambaram K., Arunachalam K., Alkahtani A.M., Chandramoorthy H.C., et al. Synergistic Antibacterial and Mosquitocidal Effect of Passiflora Foetida Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles. Braz. J. Biol. 2024;84:e263391. doi: 10.1590/1519-6984.263391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1519-6984.263391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36651434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zein R., Alghoraibi I., Soukkarieh C., Alahmad A. Investigation of Cytotoxicity of Biosynthesized Colloidal Nanosilver Against Local Leishmania Tropica: In Vitro Study. Materials. 2022;15:4880. doi: 10.3390/ma15144880.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma15144880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9318884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35888346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gajera G., Godse C., DeSouza A., Mehta D., Kothari V. Potent Anthelmintic Activity of a Colloidal Nano-Silver Formulation (Silversol®) Against the Model Worm Caenorhabditis Elegans. BMC Res. Notes. 2023;16:130. doi: 10.1186/s13104-023-06392-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13104-023-06392-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10318827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37400872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goel V., Kaur P., Singla L.D., Choudhury D. Biomedical Evaluation of Lansium Parasiticum Extract-Protected Silver Nanoparticles Against Haemonchus Contortus, a Parasitic Worm. Front. Mol. Biosci. 2020;7:595646. doi: 10.3389/fmolb.2020.595646.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmolb.2020.595646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7773940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33392256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shalaby M., Anwar M.M., Saeed H. Nanomaterials for Application in Wound Healing: Current State-of-the-Art and Future Perspectives. J. Polym. Res. 2022;29:91. doi: 10.1007/s10965-021-02870-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10965-021-02870-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim S., Choi I.H. Phagocytosis and Endocytosis of Silver Nanoparticles Induce Interleukin-8 Production in Human Macrophages. Yonsei Med. J. 2012;53:654–657. doi: 10.3349/ymj.2012.53.3.654.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3349/ymj.2012.53.3.654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3343436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22477013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elsabahy M., Wooley K.L. Cytokines as Biomarkers of Nanoparticle Immunotoxicity. Chem. Soc. Rev. 2013;42:5552–5576. doi: 10.1039/c3cs60064e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c3cs60064e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3665642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23549679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris D.R., Ansar M., Speshock J., Ivanciuc T., Qu Y., Casola A., Garofalo R.P. Antiviral and Immunomodulatory Activity of Silver Nanoparticles in Experimental RSV Infection. Viruses. 2019;11:732. doi: 10.3390/v11080732.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v11080732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6723559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31398832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elfaky M.A., Sirwi A., Ismail S.H., Awad H.H., Gad S.S. Hepatoprotective Effect of Silver Nanoparticles at Two Different Particle Sizes: Comparative Study with and without Silymarin. Curr. Issues Mol. Biol. 2022;44:2923–2938. doi: 10.3390/cimb44070202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cimb44070202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9321183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35877426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwasaki A., Medzhitov R. Control of Adaptive Immunity by the Innate Immune System. Nat. Immunol. 2015;16:343–353. doi: 10.1038/ni.3123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ni.3123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4507498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25789684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aderibigbe B.A. Metal-Based Nanoparticles for the Treatment of Infectious Diseases. Molecules. 2017;22:1370. doi: 10.3390/molecules22081370.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules22081370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6152252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28820471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yahya E.B., Jummaat F., Adnan A.S., Olaiya N.G., Amirul A.-A.A., Rizal S., Haafiz M.K.M., Khalil H.P.S.A. A Review on Revolutionary Natural Biopolymer-Based Aerogels for Antibacterial Delivery. Antibiotics. 2020;9:648. doi: 10.3390/antibiotics9100648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9100648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7601537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32998197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tripathi S.K., Kesharwani K., Kaul G., Akhir A., Saxena D., Singh R., Mishra N.K., Pandey A., Chopra S., Joshi K.B. Amyloid-β Inspired Short Peptide Amphiphile Facilitates Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles as Potential Antibacterial Agents. ChemMedChem. 2022;17:e202200251. doi: 10.1002/cmdc.202200251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cmdc.202200251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35684988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanati M., Afshari A.R., Kesharwani P., Sukhorukov V.N., Sahebkar A. Recent Trends in the Application of Nanoparticles in Cancer Therapy: The Involvement of Oxidative Stress. J. Control. Release. 2022;348:287–304. doi: 10.1016/j.jconrel.2022.05.035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jconrel.2022.05.035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35644289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elmetwalli A., Abdel-Monem M.O., El-Far A.H., Ghaith G.S., Albalawi N.A.N., Hassan J., Ismail N.F., El-Sewedy T., Alnamshan M.M., ALaqeel N.K. Probiotic-Derived Silver Nanoparticles Target MTOR/MMP-9/BCL-2/Dependent AMPK Activation for Hepatic Cancer Treatment. Med. Oncol. 2024;41:106. doi: 10.1007/s12032-024-02330-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12032-024-02330-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10995097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38575697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattarai P., Hameed S., Dai Z. Recent Advances in Anti-Angiogenic Nanomedicines for Cancer Therapy. Nanoscale. 2018;10:5393–5423. doi: 10.1039/C7NR09612G.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C7NR09612G</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29528075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sambhy V., MacBride M.M., Peterson B.R., Sen A. Silver Bromide Nanoparticle/Polymer Composites: Dual Action Tunable Antimicrobial Materials. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2006;128:9798–9808. doi: 10.1021/ja061442z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ja061442z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16866536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becaro A.A., Puti F.C., Corrêa D.S., Paris E.C., Marconcini J.M., Ferreira M.D. Polyethylene Films Containing Silver Nanoparticles for Applications in Food Packaging: Characterization of Physico-Chemical and Anti-Microbial Properties. J. Nanosci. Nanotechnol. 2015;15:2148–2156. doi: 10.1166/jnn.2015.9721.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1166/jnn.2015.9721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26413633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed O., Sibuyi N.R.S., Fadaka A.O., Madiehe M.A., Maboza E., Meyer M., Geerts G. Plant Extract-Synthesized Silver Nanoparticles for Application in Dental Therapy. Pharmaceutics. 2022;14:380. doi: 10.3390/pharmaceutics14020380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics14020380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8875651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35214112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Li J., Shi Q., Guo G., Wang Q., Tang J., Shen H., Liu X., Zhang X., Chu P.K. Antibacterial Surface Design of Titanium-Based Biomaterials for Enhanced Bacteria-Killing and Cell-Assisting Functions Against Periprosthetic Joint Infection. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2016;8:11162–11178. doi: 10.1021/acsami.6b02803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.6b02803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27054673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casolaro M., Casolaro I., Akimoto J., Ueda M., Ito Y. Antibacterial Properties of Silver Nanoparticles Embedded on Polyelectrolyte Hydrogels Based on A-Amino Acid Residues. Gels. 2018;4:42. doi: 10.3390/gels4020042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/gels4020042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6209242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30674818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krupa A.N.D., Raghavan V. AgNPs Doped TEOS Sol–Gel Coatings to Prevent the Adhesion of Marine Fouling Organisms. IET Nanobiotechnol. 2017;12:99–105. doi: 10.1049/iet-nbt.2017.0047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1049/iet-nbt.2017.0047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Díez-Pascual A.M. Surface Engineering of Nanomaterials with Polymers, Biomolecules, and Small Ligands for Nanomedicine. Materials. 2022;15:3251. doi: 10.3390/ma15093251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma15093251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9104878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35591584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malindi Z., Barth S., Abrahamse H. The Potential of Antibody Technology and Silver Nanoparticles for Enhancing Photodynamic Therapy for Melanoma. Biomedicines. 2022;10:2158. doi: 10.3390/biomedicines10092158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biomedicines10092158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9495799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36140259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villalpando-Rodriguez G.E., Gibson S.B. Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS) Regulates Different Types of Cell Death by Acting as a Rheostat. Oxid. Med. Cell. Longev. 2021;2021:9912436. doi: 10.1155/2021/9912436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2021/9912436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8380163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34426760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noga M., Milan J., Frydrych A., Jurowski K. Toxicological Aspects, Safety Assessment, and Green Toxicology of Silver Nanoparticles (AgNPs)—Critical Review: State of the Art. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2023;24:5133. doi: 10.3390/ijms24065133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms24065133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10049346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36982206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao B.-H., Chen Z.-Y., Wang Y.-J., Yan S.-J. Silver Nanoparticles Have Lethal and Sublethal Adverse Effects on Development and Longevity by Inducing ROS-Mediated Stress Responses. Sci. Rep. 2018;8:2445. doi: 10.1038/s41598-018-20728-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20728-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5799281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29402973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi L., Zhang J., Zhao M., Tang S., Cheng X., Zhang W., Li W., Liu X., Peng H., Wang Q. Effects of Polyethylene Glycol on the Surface of Nanoparticles for Targeted Drug Delivery. Nanoscale. 2021;13:10748–10764. doi: 10.1039/D1NR02065J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1NR02065J</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34132312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhandi S., Mehta D.S., Mashyakhy M., Chohan H., Testarelli L., Thomas J., Dhillon H., Raj A.T., Balaji T.M., Varadarajan S., et al. Antimicrobial Efficacy of Silver Nanoparticles as Root Canal Irrigant’s: A Systematic Review. J. Clin. Med. 2021;10:1152. doi: 10.3390/jcm10061152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm10061152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7999954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33801820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parvekar P., Palaskar J., Metgud S., Maria R., Dutta S.D. The Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) and Minimum Bactericidal Concentration (MBC) of Silver Nanoparticles Against Staphylococcus aureus. Biomater. Investig. Dent. 2020;7:105–109. doi: 10.1080/26415275.2020.1796674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/26415275.2020.1796674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7470068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32939454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suárez V.T., Karepina E., Chevallet M., Gallet B., Cottet-Rousselle C., Charbonnier P., Moriscot C., Michaud-Soret I., Bal W., Fuchs A.H., et al. Nuclear Translocation of Silver Ions and Hepatocyte Nuclear Receptor Impairment Upon Exposure to Silver Nanoparticles. Environ. Sci. Nano. 2020;7:1373–1387. doi: 10.1039/C9EN01348B.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C9EN01348B</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng N., Li H., Li Y., Mo F., Wang M., Li Z., Chen X., Xu J., Chai R., Wang H. Physiological Homeostasis Alteration and Cellular Structure Damage of Chlorella Vulgaris Exposed to Silver Nanoparticles with Various Microstructure Morphologies. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 2022;29:26011–26020. doi: 10.1007/s11356-022-19193-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-022-19193-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35254620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R., Gupta A., Patade V.Y., Balakrishna G., Pandey H.K., Singh A.K. Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles Using Extract of Ocimum Kilimandscharicum and Its Antimicrobial Activity Against Plant Pathogens. SN Appl. Sci. 2019;1:1652. doi: 10.1007/s42452-019-1703-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42452-019-1703-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakakhel M.A., Wu F., Sajjad W., Zhang Q., Khan I., Ullah K., Wang W. Long-Term Exposure to High-Concentration Silver Nanoparticles Induced Toxicity, Fatality, Bioaccumulation, and Histological Alteration in Fish (Cyprinus carpio) Environ. Sci. Eur. 2021;33:14. doi: 10.1186/s12302-021-00453-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12302-021-00453-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younus A.I., Yousef M.I., Abdel-NabiKamel M., Alrawi R., Abdulrahman J.M. Changes in Semen Characteristics and Sex Hormones of Rats Treated with Iron Oxide Nanoparticles, Silver Nanoparticles and Their Mixture. GSC Biol. Pharm. Sci. 2020;12:229–237. doi: 10.30574/gscbps.2020.12.2.0272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30574/gscbps.2020.12.2.0272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith J.N., Thomas D., Jolley H., Kodali V., Littke M.H., Munusamy P., Baer D.R., Gaffrey M.J., Thrall B.D., Teeguarden J.G. All That Is Silver Is Not Toxic: Silver Ion and Particle Kinetics Reveals the Role of Silver Ion Aging and Dosimetry on the Toxicity of Silver Nanoparticles. Part. Fibre Toxicol. 2018;15:47. doi: 10.1186/s12989-018-0283-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12989-018-0283-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6282353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30518385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliaei R., Keshtmand Z., Shabani R. The Effect of Lactobacillus casei and Bacillus coagulans Probiotics on Liver Damage Induced by Silver Nanoparticles and Expression of Bax, Bcl2 and Caspase 3 Genes in Male Rats. Eur. J. Transl. Myol. 2022;33:10673. doi: 10.4081/ejtm.2022.10673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/ejtm.2022.10673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36101996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calcaterra H., Shin N., Quirk P.L., Tsai C.S. Low Concentration Analysis of Silver Nanoparticles in Consumer Spray Products. Atmosphere. 2020;11:403. doi: 10.3390/atmos11040403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/atmos11040403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fehaid A., Elazab S.T., Elhadidy M.G., Nashar E.M.E., Abdalla A.M., Al-Khater K.M., Alghamdi M.A., Elalfy M.M. Zinc Chloride Ameliorates the Adverse Effects of Silver Nitrates Compared to Silver Nanoparticle in Post-Natal Model of Toxicity. Mater. Sci. Res. India. 2022;19:17–25. doi: 10.13005/msri/190102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13005/msri/190102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabitha Y., Fatima S. Evaluatoin of Genotoxicity of Ricinus Communis (Leaves and Seeds) by Their Silver Nano-Particles Using Comet Assay. J. Adv. Sci. Res. 2022;13:146–150. doi: 10.55218/JASR.202213518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.55218/JASR.202213518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L., Kong L. Research Progress on the Carcinogenicity of Metal Nanomaterials. J. Appl. Toxicol. 2021;41:1334–1344. doi: 10.1002/jat.4145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jat.4145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33527484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonca S., Özidemir S., Isik Z., M’barek I., Shaik F., Dizge N. Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles from Red and Green Parts of the Pistachio Hulls and Their Various In-Vitro Biological Activities. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2022;165:113170. doi: 10.1016/j.fct.2022.113170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2022.113170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35613679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dove A.S., Dzurny D.I., Dees W.R., Qin N., Nunez Rodriguez C.C., Alt L.A., Ellward G.L., Best J.A., Rudawski N.G., Fujii K. Silver Nanoparticles Enhance the Efficacy of Aminoglycosides against Antibiotic-Resistant Bacteria. Front. Microbiol. 2023;13:1064095. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2022.1064095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.1064095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9927651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36798870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luna-Vázquez-Gómez R., Arellano-García M.E., Toledano-Magaña Y., García-Ramos J.C., Radilla-Chávez P., Salas-Vargas D.S., Casillas-Figueroa F., Ruiz-Ruiz B., Pestryakov A., Bogdanchikova N. Bell Shape Curves of Hemolysis Induced by Silver Nanoparticles: Review and Experimental Assay. Nanomaterials. 2022;12:1066. doi: 10.3390/nano12071066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano12071066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9000491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35407184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chávez-Hernández J.A., Velarde-Salcedo A.J., Navarro-Tovar G., Gonzalez C. Safe Nanomaterials: From Their Use, Application and Disposal to Regulations. Nanoscale Adv. 2024;6:1583–1610. doi: 10.1039/D3NA01097J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D3NA01097J</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10929592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38482025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sudarman F., Shiddiq M., Armynah B., Tahir D. Silver Nanoparticles (AgNPs) Synthesis Methods as Heavy-Metal Sensors: A Review. Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2023;20:9351–9368. doi: 10.1007/s13762-022-04745-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13762-022-04745-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bashiri G., Padilla M.S., Swingle K.L., Shepherd S.J., Mitchell M.J., Wang K. Nanoparticle Protein Corona: From Structure and Function to Therapeutic Targeting. Lab Chip. 2023;23:1432–1466. doi: 10.1039/D2LC00799A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D2LC00799A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10013352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36655824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baruah K., Konthoujam I., Lyndem S., Aguan K., Roy A.S. Complexation of Turmeric and Curcumin Mediated Silver Nanoparticles with Human Serum Albumin: Further Investigation into the Protein-Corona Formation, Anti-Bacterial Effects and Cell Cytotoxicity Studies. Spectrochim. Acta Part A Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc. 2023;294:122540. doi: 10.1016/j.saa.2023.122540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.saa.2023.122540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36848856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younis M.A. Silver Nanoparticles for Drug Delivery. Elsevier; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2024. Clinical Translation of Silver Nanoparticles into the Market; pp. 395–432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L., Wu H., Le L., Yang P., Fu F., Liu W., Xu H. Exposure to Silver Nanoparticles Induces Immunological Dysfunction in Pregnant Mice. Environ. Toxicol. 2020;35:1161–1169. doi: 10.1002/tox.22981.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/tox.22981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32515542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun L., Liu H., Ye Y., Lei Y., Islam R., Tan S., Tong R., Miao Y.-B., Cai L. Smart Nanoparticles for Cancer Therapy. Signal Transduct. Target. Ther. 2023;8:418. doi: 10.1038/s41392-023-01642-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-023-01642-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10622502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37919282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Serwi R.H., Eladl M.A., El-Sherbiny M., Saleh M.A., Othman G., Alshahrani S.M., Alnefaie R., Jan A.M., Alnasser S.M., Albalawi A.E. Targeted Drug Administration onto Cancer Cells Using Hyaluronic Acid–Quercetin-Conjugated Silver Nanoparticles. Molecules. 2023;28:4146. doi: 10.3390/molecules28104146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28104146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10221215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37241888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajawat S., Koutu V., Saha S., Malik M.M. Biopolymers as Silver Nanoparticle Carriers for Targeted Drug Delivery. Mater. Today Proc. 2023. in press .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaushal A., Khurana I., Yadav P., Allawadhi P., Banothu A.K., Neeradi D., Thalugula S., Barani P.J., Naik R.R., Navik U. Advances in Therapeutic Applications of Silver Nanoparticles. Chem.-Biol. Interact. 2023;382:110590. doi: 10.1016/j.cbi.2023.110590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2023.110590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37268200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gul A.R., Shaheen F., Rafique R., Bal J., Waseem S., Park T.J. Grass-Mediated Biogenic Synthesis of Silver Nanoparticles and Their Drug Delivery Evaluation: A Biocompatible Anti-Cancer Therapy. Chem. Eng. J. 2020;407:127202. doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2020.127202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2020.127202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pawar A.B., Korde S.K., Rakshe D.S., William P., Jawale M.A., Deshpande N. Analysis of Silver Nanoparticles as Carriers of Drug Delivery System. J. Nano-Electron. Phys. 2023;15:04015. doi: 10.21272/jnep.15(4).04015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21272/jnep.15(4).04015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karami M.H., Abdouss M., Maleki B. The State of the Art Metal Nanoparticles in Drug Delivery Systems: A Comprehensive Review. Nanomed. J. 2024;11:222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S.K., Parihar S., Jain S., Ho J.-A.A., Vankayala R. Light-Responsive Functional Nanomaterials as Pioneering Therapeutics: A Paradigm Shift to Combat Age-Related Disorders. J Mater. Chem. B. 2024;12:8212–8234. doi: 10.1039/D4TB00578C.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D4TB00578C</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39058026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abashkin V., Pędziwiatr-Werbicka E., Horodecka K., Zhogla V., Ulashchik E., Shmanai V., Shcharbin D., Bryszewska M. Silver Nanoparticles Modified by Carbosilane Dendrons and PEG as Delivery Vectors of Small Interfering RNA. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2023;24:840. doi: 10.3390/ijms24010840.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms24010840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9820844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36614277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubey A.K., Mostafavi E. Biomaterials-Mediated CRISPR/Cas9 Delivery: Recent Challenges and Opportunities in Gene Therapy. Front. Chem. 2023;11:1259435. doi: 10.3389/fchem.2023.1259435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fchem.2023.1259435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10568484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37841202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franci G., Falanga A., Galdiero S., Palomba L., Rai M., Morelli G., Galdiero M. Silver Nanoparticles as Potential Antibacterial Agents. Molecules. 2015;20:8856–8874. doi: 10.3390/molecules20058856.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules20058856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6272636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25993417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pop D., Buzatu R., Moacă E.-A., Watz C., Pinzaru S.C., Tudoran L.B., Nekvapil F., Avram S., Dehelean C., Cretu M., et al. Development and Characterization of Fe3O4@Carbon Nanoparticles and Their Biological Screening Related to Oral Administration. Materials. 2021;14:3556. doi: 10.3390/ma14133556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma14133556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8269588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34202095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paladini F. Antimicrobial Silver Nanoparticles for Wound Healing Application: Progress and Future Trends. Materials. 2019;12:2540. doi: 10.3390/ma12162540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma12162540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6719912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31404974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>May A., Kopecki Z., Carney B., Cowin A.J. Antimicrobial Silver Dressings: A Review of Emerging Issues for Modern Wound Care. ANZ J. Surg. 2021;92:379–384. doi: 10.1111/ans.17382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ans.17382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34806300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levard C., Hotze E.M., Lowry G.V., Brown G.E. Environmental Transformations of Silver Nanoparticles: Impact on Stability and Toxicity. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2012;46:6900–6914. doi: 10.1021/es2037405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es2037405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22339502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>