<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39335884</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2304-8158</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>18</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Foods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhancing Gluten-Free Crispy Waffles with Soybean Residue (Okara) Flour: Rheological, Nutritional, and Sensory Impacts.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2951</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/foods13182951</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The incorporation of okara, a by-product of soybean milk production, into gluten-free products such as crispy waffles poses challenges due to the absence of gluten's viscoelastic properties and the high fiber content of okara. This study aimed to evaluate the effects of okara flour on the rheological properties, physical attributes, and sensory qualities of gluten-free waffles. Waffle batters with varying levels of okara flour (10%, 20%, 30%, and 40%) were prepared, and their rheological properties were analyzed using oscillatory shear and creep-recovery tests. Physical properties, proximate composition, cholesterol and glucose adsorption capacities, storage stability, and sensory attributes were also assessed. The results demonstrated that increasing okara flour content improved batter elasticity and viscosity (with complex viscosity reaching up to 10,923 Pa·s for 40% okara flour) but decreased spread ratio by up to 45% and increased moisture content by approximately 2.7%. Higher okara content also led to a 16% decrease in brightness (L*) and increased hardness, reaching 325.26 g/s at 40% substitution. Sensory evaluation revealed that waffles with 30% okara flour were preferred for their texture and overall liking, with a score of 7.43 compared to higher substitution levels. Cholesterol and glucose adsorption capacities were high in okara flour, contributing to potential health benefits. Storage stability tests showed acceptable moisture content, water activity, and microbiological safety over 60 days, though hardness decreased by about 42%. In conclusion, okara flour enhances the nutritional profile of gluten-free waffles, but its impact on texture and flavor requires careful formulation adjustments to optimize consumer acceptance.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aussanasuwannakul</LastName><ForeName>Aunchalee</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0033-9779</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Chemistry and Physics, Institute of Food Research and Product Development, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10903, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Puntaburt</LastName><ForeName>Kassamaporn</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5034-5897</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Processing and Preservation, Institute of Food Research and Product Development, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10903, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pantoa</LastName><ForeName>Thidarat</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Chemistry and Physics, Institute of Food Research and Product Development, Kasetsart University, Bangkok 10903, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>Project no. 110883</GrantID><Agency>National Research Council of Thailand</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Foods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101670569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2304-8158</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Check-All-That-Apply</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cholesterol adsorption</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">circular economy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dietary fiber</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food sustainability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food waste valorization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">glucose adsorption</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">protein enrichment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">texture analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viscoelasticity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. The funders had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript; or in the decision to publish the results.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39335884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11431479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13182951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">foods13182951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kamble D.B., Rani S. Bioactive components, in vitro digestibility, microstructure and application of soybean residue (okara): A review. Legume Sci. 2020;2:e32. doi: 10.1002/leg3.32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/leg3.32</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Office of Agricultural Economics, Ministry of Agriculture and Cooperatives  Soybean Production and Demand Statistics.  [(accessed on 10 June 2024)];2024  Available online:  https://www.oae.go.th/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davy P., Vuong Q.V. Soy Milk By-product: Its Composition and Utilisation. Food Rev. Int. 2022;38((Suppl. S1)):147–169. doi: 10.1080/87559129.2020.1855191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/87559129.2020.1855191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aussanasuwannakul A., Treesuwan W., Butsuwan P., Puntaburt K., Teangpook C. Okara Waste Reduction from Community and Industry by Recycling into High-Value Flour Used as Food Ingredient. National Research Council of Thailand; Bangkok, Thailand: 2022. p. 189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ginting E., Elisabeth D.A.A., Khamidah A., Rinaldi J., Ambarsari I., Antarlina S.S. The nutritional and economic potential of tofu dreg (okara) and its utilization for high protein food products in Indonesia. J. Agric. Food Res. 2024;16:101175. doi: 10.1016/j.jafr.2024.101175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jafr.2024.101175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aussanasuwannakul A., Teangpook C., Treesuwan W., Puntaburt K., Butsuwan P. Effect of the Addition of Soybean Residue (Okara) on the Physicochemical, Tribological, Instrumental, and Sensory Texture Properties of Extruded Snacks. Foods. 2022;11:2967. doi: 10.3390/foods11192967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11192967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9564180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36230041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aussanasuwannakul A., Boonbumrung S., Pantoa T. Valorization of Soybean Residue (Okara) by Supercritical Carbon Dioxide Extraction: Compositional, Physicochemical, and Functional Properties of Oil and Defatted Powder. Foods. 2023;12:2698. doi: 10.3390/foods12142698.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12142698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10378935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37509790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pešić M.B., Pešić M.M., Bezbradica J., Stanojević A.B., Ivković P., Milinčić D.D., Demin M., Kostić A., Dojčinović B., Stanojević S.P. Okara-Enriched Gluten-Free Bread: Nutritional, Antioxidant and Sensory Properties. Molecules. 2023;28:4098. doi: 10.3390/molecules28104098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28104098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10224361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37241841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatmawati S., Nur’aini V., Karyantina M. Ice Cream Cone Formulations from Wheat Flour and Tofu Dregs Flour Added with Beetroot (Beta vulgaris L.) Extract. Agric. 2023;35:85–98. doi: 10.24246/agric.2023.v35.i1.p85-98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.24246/agric.2023.v35.i1.p85-98</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aussanasuwannakul A., Pondicherry K., Saengprakai J. Rheological and tribological characterization of herbal sweet sauce with different stabilizing systems. CyTA J. Food. 2022;20:158–171. doi: 10.1080/19476337.2022.2107706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19476337.2022.2107706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mezger T.G. The Rheology Handbook. 4th ed. Vincentz Network; Hanover, Germany: 2014. p. 432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>American_Association_of_Cereal_Chemists_International . Approved Methods of Analysis. Cereals &amp; Grains Association; St. Paul, MN, USA: 2010. Method 10-50.05.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCleary B.V. Measurement of Dietary Fiber: Which AOAC Official Method of Analysis to Use. J. AOAC Int. 2023;106:917–930. doi: 10.1093/jaoacint/qsad051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jaoacint/qsad051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10350623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37129539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ge Q., Mao J.-W., Cai C., Huang J., Zhou Y., Fang J., Sun Y., Sha R. Effects of twin-screw extrusion on physicochemical properties and functional properties of bamboo shoots dietary fiber. J. Biobased Mater. Bioenergy. 2017;11:385–390. doi: 10.1166/jbmb.2017.1685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1166/jbmb.2017.1685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aussanasuwannakul A., Butsuwan P. Evaluating Microbiological Safety, Sensory Quality, and Packaging for Online Market Success of Roasted Pickled Fish Powder. Foods. 2024;13:861. doi: 10.3390/foods13060861.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13060861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10969797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38540851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira I., Marinho B., Szymanowska U., Karas M., Vilela A. Chemical and Sensory Properties of Waffles Supplemented with Almond Skins. Molecules. 2023;28:5674. doi: 10.3390/molecules28155674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28155674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10419912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37570644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tridtitanakiat P.C., Hernández-Estrada Z.J., Rayas-Duarte P. Modeling the Influence of Okara Flour Supplementation from Time-Temperature Drying Treatment on the Quality of Gluten-Free Roll Produced from Rice Flour. Foods. 2023;12:3421. doi: 10.3390/foods12183421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12183421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10527693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37761130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agu H.O., Ihionu J.C., Mba J.C. Sensory and physicochemical properties of biscuit produced from blends of whole wheat, soy okara and tigernut residue flours. Heliyon. 2023;9:e15318. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e15318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e15318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10130213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37123941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department_of_Medical_Sciences . Microbiological Quality Criteria for Food and Food Contact Containers. Department of Medical Sciences; Nonthaburi, Thailand: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lumivero XLSTAT . Statistical and Data Analysis Solution. QSR International; Burlington, MA, USA: 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brites L.T.G.F., Schmiele M., Steel C.J. Chapter 13—Gluten-Free Bakery and Pasta Products. In: Holban A.M., Grumezescu A.M., editors. Alternative and Replacement Foods. Academic Press; Cambridge, MA, USA: 2018. pp. 385–410.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-811446-9.00013-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demirkesen I., Ozkaya B. Recent strategies for tackling the problems in gluten-free diet and products. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022;62:571–597. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2020.1823814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2020.1823814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32981341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egea M.B., De Sousa T.L., Dos Santos D.C., De Oliveira Filho J.G., Guimarães R.M., Yoshiara L.Y., Lemes A.C. Application of Soy, Corn, and Bean By-products in the Gluten-free Baking Process: A Review. Food Bioprocess Technol. 2023;16:1429–1450. doi: 10.1007/s11947-022-02975-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11947-022-02975-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guimarães R.M., Pimentel T.C., de Rezende T.A.M., Silva J.d.S., Falcão H.G., Ida E.I., Egea M.B. Gluten-free bread: Effect of soy and corn co-products on the quality parameters. Eur. Food Res. Technol. 2019;245:1365–1376. doi: 10.1007/s00217-019-03261-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00217-019-03261-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park J., Choi I., Kim Y. Cookies formulated from fresh okara using starch, soy flour and hydroxypropyl methylcellulose have high quality and nutritional value. LWT Food Sci. Technol. 2015;63:660–666. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2015.03.110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2015.03.110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aussanasuwannakul A., Puntaburt K., Treesuwan W. Rheological, tribological, and sensory analysis of coconut-oil-modified coconut milk kefir. Curr. Res. Nutr. Food Sci. 2020;8:496–503. doi: 10.12944/CRNFSJ.8.2.15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12944/CRNFSJ.8.2.15</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olakanmi S.J., Jayas D.S., Paliwal J. Implications of Blending Pulse and Wheat Flours on Rheology and Quality Characteristics of Baked Goods: A Review. Foods. 2022;11:3287. doi: 10.3390/foods11203287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11203287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9601813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37431033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cappelli A., Oliva N., Cini E. A Systematic Review of Gluten-Free Dough and Bread: Dough Rheology, Bread Characteristics, and Improvement Strategies. Appl. Sci. 2020;10:6559. doi: 10.3390/app10186559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app10186559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asghar A., Afzaal M., Saeed F., Ahmed A., Ateeq H., Shah Y.A., Islam F., Hussain M., Akram N., Shah M.A. Valorization and food applications of okara (soybean residue): A concurrent review. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;11:3631–3640. doi: 10.1002/fsn3.3363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fsn3.3363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10345676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37457185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen B., Cai Y., Zhao X., Wang S., Zhuang Y., Zhao Q., Zhao M., Van der Meeren P. A novel set-type yogurt with improved rheological and sensory properties by the sole addition of insoluble soybean fiber. Food Biosci. 2024;58:103739. doi: 10.1016/j.fbio.2024.103739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2024.103739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng X., Chen H., Liang Y., Geng M., He M., Huang Y., Li Y., Teng F. Effects of electron beam irradiation treatment on the structural and functional properties of okara insoluble dietary fiber. J. Sci. Food Agric. 2023;103:195–204. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.12131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.12131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35860991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyu B., Wang H., Swallah M.S., Fu H., Shen Y., Guo Z., Tong X., Li Y., Yu H., Jiang L. Structure, properties and potential bioactivities of high-purity insoluble fibre from soybean dregs (Okara) Food Chem. 2021;364:130402. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34175627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang Z., Li K., Huang W., Li Z., Xu X., Xu H., Li S. Production, structural and functional characteristics of soluble dietary fiber from fermented okara by Penicillium expansum. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2023;253:126621. doi: 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.126621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.126621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37657574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian Y., Wu T., Sheng Y., Li L., Wang C. Effects of cavitation-jet technology combined with enzyme treatment on the structure properties and functional properties of OKARA insoluble dietary fiber. Food Chem. 2023;423:136286. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.136286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.136286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37178598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang G., Hao M., He Y., Ahmad I., Ding Y., Lyu F. Structural, physicochemical, and functional properties of insoluble dietary fiber derived from okara by Viscozyme®L. J. Food Sci. 2023;88:1994–2008. doi: 10.1111/1750-3841.16565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.16565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37038307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Z.-Q., Zhang N., Zhai X.-T., Tan B. Structural, physicochemical and functional properties of dietary fiber from brown rice products treated by different processing techniques. LWT. 2023;182:114789. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu K., Chen D., Sun Z. Structures, physicochemical properties, and hypoglycemic activities of soluble dietary fibers from white and black glutinous rice bran: A comparative study. Food Res. Int. 2022;159:111423. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111423.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35940748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreger J.W., Lee Y., Lee S.-Y. Perceptual Changes and Drivers of Liking in High Protein Extruded Snacks. J. Food Sci. 2012;77:S161–S169. doi: 10.1111/j.1750-3841.2012.02634.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2012.02634.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22515253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee D.P.S., Gan A.X., Kim J.E. Incorporation of biovalorised okara in biscuits: Improvements of nutritional, antioxidant, physical, and sensory properties. LWT. 2020;134:109902. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109902.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Yi S., Ye T., Leng Y., Alomgir Hossen M., Sameen D.E., Dai J., Li S., Qin W. Effects of ultrasonic treatment and homogenization on physicochemical properties of okara dietary fibers for 3D printing cookies. Ultrason. Sonochemistry. 2021;77:105693. doi: 10.1016/j.ultsonch.2021.105693.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ultsonch.2021.105693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8348173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34343823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao R., Zhao R., Li Q., Li K., Liu Q., Liu W., Hu H. Improvement effect of different protein powder on cooking characteristics of gluten-free pasta and the establishment of quality evaluation based on principal component analysis. Int. J. Food Sci. Technol. 2024;59:1138–1149. doi: 10.1111/ijfs.16728.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijfs.16728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>