<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39334452</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2055-0928</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Nutritional quality and diversity in Ghana's school feeding programme: a mixed-methods exploration through caterer interviews in the Greater Accra Region.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>127</StartPage><MedlinePgn>127</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">127</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s40795-024-00936-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The Ghana School Feeding Programme (GSFP) provides public primary school pupils with a free daily meal. Each meal is expected to follow set menus, providing 30% of children's' (6-12 years) energy requirements. This study assessed the nutritional quality and diversity of planned and provided GSFP meals, engaging school caterers to identify how meal quality in the Greater Accra Region could be enhanced.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A cross-sectional mixed methods study design was used. Multistage sampling was used to select 129 schools implementing the GSFP in six districts of the Greater Accra Region. GSFP district menus were collected as well as a one-week school caterer recall of provided school meals. The meal served on the day of data collection was recorded and photographed. Nutritional quality was evaluated based on nutrient profiling methods: energy density (low&lt;125kcal/100g; medium 125-225kcal/100g; high&gt;225kcal/100g) and nutrient density (low&lt;5%; medium 5-10%; high&gt;10%). Meal diversity was assessed by a simple count composed of 5 food groups: cereals, pulses/nuts/seeds, animal-source, vegetables and fruits. Caterers' views on programme facilitators and barriers were also explored.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Planned menus included 14-20 weekly options, composed of eight minimally processed traditional dishes. All meals, except white rice, had a high nutrient density/100g. Energy density was varied (low, n=2; medium, n=2; high, n=4). Meals included only 2/5 or 3/5 food groups, mainly starchy staples, pulses/nuts/seeds, and sometimes vegetables. Fruit was never reported. About half of caterers (51.1%) reported deviating from the planned menus: 11.7% served alternative meals, with some including animal-sourced food (17.0%), and 39.4% repeated meals provided during the week, often based on starchy staples, influencing overall nutritional quality. Most caterers reported food item cost and lack of food purchase guidelines as barriers to providing school meals, while food safety training and guidelines for food preparation were facilitators.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">While school meals are composed of minimally processed, nutrient dense, local foods, there are notable gaps in meal diversity and compliance, as reflected in provided meals. Caterer compliance to planned menus varied greatly, reflecting recent food price inflation. Upwardly adjusting the current meal allocation of 1.2 cedis (0.22USD) per child per day could enhance access to more affordable, nutritious and diverse foods in school meals.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liguori</LastName><ForeName>Julia</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UMR MoISA (Montpellier Interdisciplinary centre on Sustainable Agri-food systems), Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, CIHEAM-IAMM, INRAE, Institut Agro Montpellier, IRD, Montpellier, France. jjliguori@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amevinya</LastName><ForeName>Gideon Senyo</ForeName><Initials>GS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UMR MoISA (Montpellier Interdisciplinary centre on Sustainable Agri-food systems), Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, CIHEAM-IAMM, INRAE, Institut Agro Montpellier, IRD, Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Ghana, Department of Population, Family &amp; Reproductive Health, School of Public Health, Accra, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Holdsworth</LastName><ForeName>Michelle</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UMR MoISA (Montpellier Interdisciplinary centre on Sustainable Agri-food systems), Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, CIHEAM-IAMM, INRAE, Institut Agro Montpellier, IRD, Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Savy</LastName><ForeName>Mathilde</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UMR MoISA (Montpellier Interdisciplinary centre on Sustainable Agri-food systems), Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, CIHEAM-IAMM, INRAE, Institut Agro Montpellier, IRD, Montpellier, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laar</LastName><ForeName>Amos</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Ghana, Department of Population, Family &amp; Reproductive Health, School of Public Health, Accra, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672434</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2055-0928</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food procurement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food provision</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ghana</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nutritional quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">School caterers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">School meal programmes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39334452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11437908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40795-024-00936-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s40795-024-00936-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>GNR. Global Nutrition Report: the state of global nutrition. Country profile: Ghana. Bristol: Development Initiatives; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes M, Folson G, Aurino E, Gelli A. A free lunch or a walk back home? The school food environment and dietary behaviours among children and adolescents in Ghana. Food Secur. 2017;5:1073–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7473073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32983282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogum-Alangea D, Aryeetey RNO, Gray HL, Laar AK, Adanu RMK. Basic school pupils’ food purchases during mid-morning break in urban Ghanaian schools. Zereyesus Y, editor. PLOS ONE. 2020;15(9):e0238308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7462272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32870945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WFP. State of School Feeding Worldwide 2022. Rome: World Food Programme; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GoG. Government of Ghana. Ghana School Feeding Programme: Programme Document 2007-2010. 2006. Available from: https://schoolfeeding.gov.gh/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/GSFP_Programme_Document_2007_2010-2.07.53-PM-2.07.53-PM-2.07.53-PM.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drake L, Woolnough A, Burbano C, Bundy D, editors. Global school feeding sourcebook: lessons from 14 countries. London: Imperial College Press. 2016. p. 446.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laar A. Ghana food systems summit dialogues synthesis paper. From Dialogues to Action: Ghana’s food systems actors identify food systems challenges and opportunities for transformation. Accra: Government of Chana Commissioned Food Systems Diaolgues; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GCNF. Global Child Nutrition Foundation. School Meal Programs Around the World: results from the 2021 Global Survey of School Meal Programs. 2022. Available from: https://gcnf.org/global-reports/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNICEF. United Nations Children’s Fund (UNICEF). Programming Guidance: Nutrition in Middle Childhood and Adolescence. New York; 2021. Available form: https://www.unicef.org/nutrition/middle-childhood-and-adolescence.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saavedra JM, Prentice AM. Nutrition in school-age children: a rationale for revisiting priorities. Nutr Rev. 2023;81(7):823–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10251301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36346900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO/WHO/UNU. Food and Agriculture Organisation of the United Nations, World Health Organisation, United Nations University. Human energy requirements. 2004. Available from: https://www.fao.org/3/y5686e/y5686e00.htm.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martens T. Impact of the Ghana School Feeding Programme in 4 districts in Central Region, Ghana. Wageningen University. 2007. Available from: https://www.scribd.com/document/467325952/thesis-impact-of-the-ghana-school-feeding-programme-in-4-districts-in-central-region-ghana-web.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abizari AR, Buxton C, Kwara L, Mensah-Homiah J, Armar-Klemesu M, Brouwer ID. School feeding contributes to micronutrient adequacy of Ghanaian schoolchildren. Br J Nutr. 2014;112(6):1019–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24990068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danquah AO, Amoah AN, Steiner-Asiedu M, Opare-Obisaw C. Nutritional status of participating and non-participating pupils in the Ghana school feeding programme. J Food Res. 2012;1(3):263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldsmith P, Andrade J, Cornelius M, Asigbee M, Atim P, Tamimie C. National school lunch nutrition and cost profile: a case study of the Ghana school feeding programme. Food Nutr Bull. 2019;40(1):41–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30734574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owusu J, Colecraft E, Aryeetey R, Vaccaro J, Huffman F. Contribution of school meals to nutrient intakes of school-age children enrolled in two feeding programs in Ghana. TFASEB J. 2016;30:669–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parish A, Gelli A. Trade-offs in costs, diet quality and regional diversity: an analysis of the nutritional lvalue of school meals in Ghana. Afr J Food Agric Nutr Dev. 2015;15(4):10217–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes M, Galloway R, Gelli A, Mumuni D, Hamdani S, Kiamba J, et al. Enhancing linkages between healthy diets, local agriculture, and sustainable food systems: the school meals planner package in Ghana. Food Nutr Bull. 2016;37(4):571–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27435223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GoG (Government of Ghana). Ministry of Food and Agriculture. Ghana: Food-Based Dietary Guidelines. Accra: University of Ghana School of Public Health; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aliyar R, Gelli A, Hamdani SH. A Review of Nutritional Guidelines and Menu Compositions for School Feeding Programs in 12 Countries. Front Public Health. 2015;3. Available from: http://journal.frontiersin.org/Article/10.3389/fpubh.2015.00148/abstract.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2015.00148/abstract</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4524891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26301209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niebylski M, Lu T, Campbell N, Arcand J, Schermel A, Hua D, et al. Healthy food procurement policies and their impact. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2014;11(3):2608–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3986994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24595213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SwenssonLuana FJ, Tartanac F. Public food procurement for sustainable diets and food systems: the role of the regulatory framework. Glob Food Secur. 2020;25:100366.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GSS. Ghana Statistical Service. Ghana 2021 Population and Housing Census. General Report Volume 3A: Population of Regions and Districrs. 2021. Available from: https://statsghana.gov.gh/gssmain/fileUpload/pressrelease/2021%20PHC%20General%20Report%20Vol%203A_Population%20of%20Regions%20and%20Districts_181121.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laar A, Kelly B, Holdsworth M, Quarpong W, Aryeetey R, Amevinya GS, et al. Providing Measurement, Evaluation, Accountability, and Leadership Support (MEALS) for non-communicable diseases prevention in Ghana: project implementation protocol. Front Nutr. 2021;8:644320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8416277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34485355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swinburn B, Sacks G, Vandevijvere S, Kumanyika S, Lobstein T, Neal B, et al. INFORMAS (International Network for Food and Obesity/non-communicable diseases Research, Monitoring and Action Support): overview and key principles. Obes Rev. 2013;14(S1):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24074206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GSS. Ghana Statistical Service; Ghana Poverty Mapping Report. 2015. Available from: https://www2.statsghana.gov.gh/docfiles/publications/POVERTY%20MAP%20FOR%20GHANA-05102015.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amevinya GS, Vandevijvere S, Kelly B, Afagbedzi SK, Aryeetey R, Adjei AP, et al. Advertising of unhealthy foods and beverages around primary and junior high schools in Ghana’s most urbanized and populous region. Front Public Health. 2022;23(10):917456.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9539976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36211683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holdsworth M, Pradeilles R, Tandoh A, Green M, Wanjohi M, Zotor F, et al. Unhealthy eating practices of city-dwelling Africans in deprived neighbourhoods: evidence for policy action from Ghana and Kenya. Glob Food Secur. 2020;26:100452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7726234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33324537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drewnowski A, Fulgoni V. Nutrient profiling of foods: creating a nutrient-rich food index: nutrition reviews©, Vol. 66, No. 1. Nutr Rev. 2008;66(1):23–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18254882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fulgoni VL, Keast DR, Drewnowski A. Development and validation of the nutrient-rich foods index: a tool to measure nutritional quality of foods. J Nutr. 2009;139(8):1549–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19549759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herforth A. Diet Quality Questionnaire (DQQ) Indicator Guide. Global Diet Quality Project. 2022. Available from: https://drive.google.com/file/d/1eplRm9i5_109-a5Ac1Lqj-lUI3VgVIFx/view.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabinsky MS, Toft U, Andersen KK, Tetens I. Development and validation of a Meal Index of dietary Quality (Meal IQ) to assess the dietary quality of school lunches. Public Health Nutr. 2012;15(11):2091–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10271702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22717318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastorino S, Bundy D, Springmann M, Burbano C, Hughes D, Schultz L, et al. School meals and food systems: rethinking the consequences for climate, environment, biodiversity and food sovereignty. London: Research Consortium for School Health and Nutrition, School Meals Coalition; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorgulho BM, Pot GK, Sarti FM, Marchioni DM. Indices for the assessment of nutritional quality of meals: a systematic review. Br J Nutr. 2016;115(11):2017–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27045960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GSS. Ghana Statistical Service. Consumer Price Index and Inflation. 2023. Available from: https://www.statsghana.gov.gh/gssmain/storage/img/marqueeupdater/CPI%20December_2022_final.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ankrah E. School Feeding Caterers call off nationwide strike. Joy Online. 2023; Available from: https://www.myjoyonline.com/school-feeding-caterers-call-off-nationwide-strike/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wineman A, Ekwueme MC, Bigayimpunzi L, Martin-Daihirou A, De Gois VN, Rodrigues EL, Etuge P, et al. School meal programs in Africa: regional results from the 2019 Global Survey of School Meal Programs. Front Public Health. 2019;2022(10):871866.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9178184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35692321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WFP. World Food Program. SMP PLUS: feeding more children with better meals. 2023. Available from: https://innovation.wfp.org/project/smp-plus.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Folson GK, Bannerman B, Atadze V, Ador G, Kolt B, McCloskey P, et al. Validation of mobile artificial intelligence technology-assisted dietary assessment tool against weighed records and 24-hour recall in adolescent females in Ghana. J Nutr. 2023;153(8):2328–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37276939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>