<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39339407</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1420-3049</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>29</Volume><Issue>18</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Molecules (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Molecules</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Application of Electrospun Nanofiber-Based Electrochemical Sensors in Food Safety.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">4412</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/molecules29184412</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Food safety significantly impacts public health and social welfare. Recently, issues such as heavy metal ions, drug residues, food additives, and microbial contamination in food have become increasingly prominent. Electrochemical sensing technology, known for its low cost, simplicity, rapid response, high sensitivity, and excellent selectivity, has been crucial in food safety detection. Electrospun nanofibers, with their high specific surface area, superior mechanical properties, and design flexibility, offer new insights and technical platforms for developing electrochemical sensors. This study introduces the fundamental principles, classifications, and detection mechanisms of electrochemical sensors, along with the principles and classifications of electrospinning technology. The applications of electrospun nanofiber-based electrochemical sensors in food safety detection over the past five years are detailed, and the limitations and future research prospects are discussed. Continuous innovation and optimization are expected to make electrospun nanofiber-based electrochemical sensors a key technology in rapid food safety detection, providing valuable references for expanding their application and advancing food safety detection methods.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Changdong</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Intelligent Systems Science and Engineering, Hubei Minzu University, Enshi 445000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tan</LastName><ForeName>Jianfeng</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Intelligent Systems Science and Engineering, Hubei Minzu University, Enshi 445000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yingru</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3258-9230</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Intelligent Systems Science and Engineering, Hubei Minzu University, Enshi 445000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Molecules</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100964009</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1420-3049</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057139" MajorTopicYN="Y">Nanofibers</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059022" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Safety</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055664" MajorTopicYN="Y">Electrochemical Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015374" MajorTopicYN="N">Biosensing Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">contaminants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">electrochemical sensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">electrospun nanofiber</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">freshness</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39339407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11434313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules29184412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">molecules29184412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Liu T., Zheng N., Ma Y., Zhang Y., Lei H., Zhen X., Wang Y., Gou D., Zhao J. Recent advancements in chitosan-based intelligent food freshness indicators: Categorization, advantages, and applications. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2024;275:133554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38950804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Z., Boyarkina V., Liao Z., Lin M., Zeng W., Lu X. Boosting food system sustainability through intelligent packaging: Application of biodegradable freshness indicators. ACS Food Sci. Technol. 2023;3:199–212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee A.G., Renu K., Gopalakrishnan A.V., Veeraraghavan V.P., Vinayagam S., Paz-Montelongo S., Dey A., Vellingirl B., George A., Madhyastha H., et al. Heavy metal and metalloid contamination in food and emerging technologies for its detection. Sustainability. 2023;15:1195. doi: 10.3390/su15021195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su15021195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vonnie J.M., Rovina K., Mariah A.M.A., Erna K.H., Felicia W.X.L., ‘Aqilah M.N.N. Trends in nanotechnology techniques for detecting heavy metals in food and contaminated water: A review. Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2023;20:8041–8072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elafify M., Marwa E.L.T., Sallam K.I., Sadoma N.M., Abd-Elghany S.M., Abdelkhalek A., El-Baz A.H. Heavy metal residues in milk and some dairy products with insight into their health risk assessment and the role of Lactobacillus rhamnosus in reducing the lead and cadmium load in cheese. Food Chem. Adv. 2023;2:100261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . Achieving Well-Being: A Global Framework for Integrating Well-Being into Public Health Utilizing a Health Promotion Approach. World Health Organization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savoie-Roskos M.R., Hood L.B., Hagedorn-Hatfield R.L., Landry M.J., Patton-López M.M., Richards R., Vogelzang J.L., Qamar Z., OoNorasak K., Mann G. Creating a culture that supports food security and health equity at higher education institutions. Public Health Nutr. 2023;26:503–509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9989698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36321438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmah F.A., Nurlaela N., Anugrah R., Putri Y. Safe food treatment technology: The key to realizing the sustainable development goals (SDGs) zero hunger and optimal health. ASEAN J. Agric. Food Eng. 2024;3:57–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salam M.A., Al-Amin M.Y., Pawar J.S., Akhter N., Lucy I.B. Conventional methods and future trends in antimicrobial susceptibility testing. Saudi J. Biol. Sci. 2023;30:103582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9958398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36852413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassoun A., Jagtap S., Garcia-Garcia G., Trollman H., Pateiro M., Lorenzo J.M., Trif M., Rusu A.V., Aadil R.M., Šimat V., et al. Food quality 4.0: From traditional approaches to digitalized automated analysis. J. Food Eng. 2023;337:111216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattarozzi M., Laski E., Bertucci A., Giannetto M., Bianchi F., Zoani C., Careri M. Metrological traceability in process analytical technologies and point-of-need technologies for food safety and quality control: Not a straightforward issue. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2023;415:119–135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9816273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36367573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling Z., Yang J., Zhang Y., Tang Y., Wang S., Liu H., Zhao G., Zhang Y., Wu Q. Applications of advanced materials in the pretreatment and rapid detection of small molecules in foods: A review. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2023;141:104175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du R., Zhang Y., Bian Y., Yu Z., Liu W., Wang Q. Rhodamine and related substances in food: Recent updates on pretreatment and analysis methods. Food Chem. 2024;459:140384.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38996634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L., Guo W., Lv C., Yu Z., Wang X., Li H., Chen J., Liu M. Electrochemical biosensors represent promising detection tools in medical field. Adv. Sens. Energy Mater. 2023;2:100081.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang B., Wang H., Lu X., Zheng X., Yang Z. Recent advances in electrochemical biosensors for the detection of foodborne pathogens: Current perspective and challenges. Foods. 2023;12:2795. doi: 10.3390/foods12142795.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12142795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10379338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37509887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song J., Lin X., Ee L.Y., Li S.F.Y., Huang M. A review on electrospinning as versatile supports for diverse nanofibers and their applications in environmental sensing. Adv. Fiber Mater. 2023;5:429–460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9734373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36530770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng R., Zhang S., Yao Y., Wang J., Zhu X., Jiang R., Zhang J., Zhang W., Wang C. MOFs meet electrospinning: New opportunities for water treatment. Chem. Eng. J. 2023;453:139669.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leote R.J.B., Beregoi M., Enculescu I., Diculescu V.C. Metallized electrospun polymeric fibers for electrochemical sensors and actuators. Curr. Opin. Electrochem. 2022;34:101024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Si Y., Shi S., Hu J. Applications of electrospinning in human health: From detection, protection, regulation to reconstruction. Nano Today. 2023;48:101723.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanjwal M.A., Ghaferi A.A. Graphene incorporated electrospun nanofiber for electrochemical sensing and biomedical applications: A critical review. Sensors. 2022;22:8661. doi: 10.3390/s22228661.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s22228661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9697565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36433257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Feng Y., Zhao X., Tian Y., Duan Y. Electrospun nanofiber-based indicator paper sensing platform for fluorescence and visualization detection of norfloxacin. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2023;238:115562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37586262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanaraj R., Arumugam B., Mayakrishnan G., Kim I.S., Kim S.C. A review on electrospun nanofiber composites for efficient electrochemical sensor applications. Sensors. 2023;23:6705. doi: 10.3390/s23156705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s23156705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10422532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37571489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maleki F., Razmi H., Rashidi M.R., Yousefi M., Ghorbani M. Recent advances in developing electrochemical (bio) sensing assays by applying natural polymer-based electrospun nanofibers: A comprehensive review. Microchem. J. 2023;197:109799.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye C., Lukas H., Wang M., Lee Y., Gao W. Nucleic acid-based wearable and implantable electrochemical sensors. Chem. Soc. Rev. 2024;53:7960–7982.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11308452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38985007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue R., Liu Y.S., Huang S.L., Yang G.Y. Recent progress of covalent organic frameworks applied in electrochemical sensors. ACS Sens. 2023;8:2124–2148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37276465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Y., Sima Y., Liu L., Zhou C., Shi S., Wan K., Chen A., Tang N., He Q., Liu J. Research progress on portable electrochemical sensors for detection of mycotoxins in food and environmental samples. Chem. Eng. J. 2024;485:149860.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barhoum A., Hamimed S., Slimi H., Othmani A., Abdel-Haleem F.M., Bechelany M. Modern designs of electrochemical sensor platforms for environmental analyses: Principles, nanofabrication opportunities, and challenges. Trends Environ. Anal. Chem. 2023;38:e00199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sow W.T., Ye F., Zhang C., Li J., Li H. Smart materials for point-of-care testing: From sample extraction to analyte sensing and readout signal generator. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2020;170:112682.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33035898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv L., Wang X. Recent advances in ochratoxin A electrochemical biosensors: Recognition elements, sensitization technologies, and their applications. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2020;68:4769–4787.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32243155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Q., Wang B., Liang J., Liu J., Bo L., Li G., Long Y., Zhang G., Liu H. Research on the construction of portable electrochemical sensors for environmental compounds quality monitoring. Mater. Today Adv. 2023;17:100340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu N., Liang Q., Hao W., Jiang Y., Liang P., Zeng R.J.X. Microbial electrochemical sensor for water biotoxicity monitoring. Chem. Eng. J. 2021;404:127053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33503515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X., Ma P., Sun Y., Du F., Song D., Xu G. Application of MXene in electrochemical sensors: A review. Electroanalysis. 2021;33:1827–1851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni M.B., Ayachit N.H., Aminabhavi T.M. Recent advances in microfluidics-based electrochemical sensors for foodborne pathogen detection. Biosensors. 2023;13:246. doi: 10.3390/bios13020246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bios13020246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9954504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36832012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadon N., Tomar P., Shrivastava S., Hosseinzadeh B., Kaya S.I., Ozkan S.A. Monitoring of specific phytoestrogens by dedicated electrochemical sensors: A review. Food Chem. 2024;460:140404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39068721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fritea L., Banica F., Costea T.O., Moldovan L., Dobjanschi L., Muresan M., Cavalu S. Metal nanoparticles and carbon-based nanomaterials for improved performances of electrochemical (bio)sensors with biomedical applications. Materials. 2021;14:6319. doi: 10.3390/ma14216319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ma14216319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8585379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34771844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tehrani M.A., Ahmadi S.H., Alimohammadi S., Sasanpour P., Batvani N., Kazemi S.H., Kiani M.A. Continuous glucose monitoring using wearable non-enzymatic sensors in a physiological environment. Biosens. Bioelectron. X. 2024;18:100482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalambate R.P., Kalambate P.K., Khosropour H., Thummarati P., Chiabchalard A., Boonlue W., Laiwattanapaisal W. Exploring advanced functional nanomaterial-based electrochemical sensors for the detection of mycotoxins in food matrices: A comprehensive review. Chem. Inorg. Mater. 2024;3:100044.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loguercio L.F., Thesing A., Demingos P., de Albuquerque C.D., Rodrigues R.S., Brolo A.G., Santos J.F. Efficient acetylcholinesterase immobilization for improved electrochemical performance in polypyrrole nanocomposite-based biosensors for carbaryl pesticide. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2021;339:129875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Saravia L.P., Núñez C., Castroagudín M., Bertotti M., Vizcarra A., Arriaza B., Nelson R. Development of a fast and simple electrochemical sensor for trace determination of sulfite using copper (II) triazole complexes. Microchem. J. 2024;201:110560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tu J., Torrente-Rodríguez R.M., Wang M., Gao W. The era of digital health: A review of portable and wearable affinity biosensors. Adv. Funct. Mater. 2020;30:1906713.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keirouz A., Wang Z., Reddy V.S., Nagy Z.K., Vass P., Buzgo M., Ramakrishna S., Radacsi N. The history of electrospinning: Past, present, and future developments. Adv. Mater. Technol. 2023;8:2201723.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Dhahebi A.M., Ling J.K., Krishnan S.G., Yousefzadeh M., Elumalai N.K., Mohamed Saheed M.S., Ramakrishna S., Jose R. Electrospinning research and products: The road and the way forward. Appl. Phys. Rev. 2022;9:011319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L., Niu C., Cao X., Wang Y., Zhu Z., Sun H., Liang W., Li J., Li A. Mechanically robust conjugated microporous polymer membranes prepared using polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP) electrospun nanofibers as a template for efficient PM capture. J. Colloid Interface Sci. 2023;637:305–316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36706726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angel N., Li S., Yan F., Kong L. Recent advances in electrospinning of nanofibers from bio-based carbohydrate polymers and their applications. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2022;120:308–324.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Q., Yan K., Chen J., Xia M., Li M., Liu K., Wang D., Wu C., Xie Y. Recent advances in novel aerogels through the hybrid aggregation of inorganic nanomaterials and polymeric fibers for thermal insulation. Aggregate. 2021;2:e30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y., Wang X., Shen Y., Dong K., Shen L., Alzalab A.A.A. Research progress, models and simulation of electrospinning technology: A review. J. Mater. Sci. 2022;57:58–104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8513391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34658418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadian A., Shafiee A., Aliahmad N., Agarwal M. Overview of nano-fiber mats fabrication via electrospinning and morphology analysis. Textiles. 2021;1:206–226. doi: 10.3390/textiles1020010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/textiles1020010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szewczyk P.K., Stachewicz U. The impact of relative humidity on electrospun polymer fibers: From structural changes to fiber morphology. Adv. Colloid Interface Sci. 2020;286:102315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33197707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abir S.S.H., Hasan M.T., Alcoutlabi M., Lozano K. The effect of solvent and molecular weight on the morphology of centrifugally spun poly (vinylpyrrolidone) nanofibers. Fibers Polym. 2021;22:2394–2403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez-Cid P., Rubio-Valle J.F., Jiménez-Rosado M., Pérez-Puyana V., Romero A. Effect of solution properties in the development of cellulose derivative nanostructures processed via electrospinning. Polymers. 2022;14:665. doi: 10.3390/polym14040665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym14040665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8874405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35215578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behroozi A.H., Al-Shaeli M., Vatanpour V. Fabrication and modification of nanofiltration membranes by solution electrospinning technique: A review of influential factors and applications in water treatment. Desalination. 2023;558:116638.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanaeepur H., Amooghin A.E., Shirazi M.M.A., Pishnamazi M., Shirazian S. Water desalination and ion removal using mixed matrix electrospun nanofibrous membranes: A critical review. Desalination. 2022;521:115350.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan S., Qian Y., Haghayegh M., Xia Y., Yang S., Cao R., Zhu M. Electrospun organic/inorganic hybrid nanofibers for accelerating wound healing: A review. J. Mater. Chem. B. 2024;12:3171–3190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38488129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu X., Si Y., Zhao Y., Ke Q., Hu J. Electrospun textile strategies in tendon to bone junction reconstruction. Adv. Fiber Mater. 2023;5:764–790.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirvan A.R., Nouri A., Sutti A.A. perspective on the wet spinning process and its advancements in biomedical sciences. Eur. Polym. J. 2022;181:111681.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan J., Khan A., Khan M.Q., Khan H. Applications of co-axial electrospinning in the biomedical field. Next Mater. 2024;3:100138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J., Liu S., Zhang M., Wu G., Yu H., Li H., Li F., Jia L. Coaxial electrospinning preparation and antibacterial property of polylactic acid/tea polyphenol nanofiber membrane. J. Ind. Text. 2022;51((Suppl. S2)):1778S–1792S.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Chen X., Lin X., Yan J., Yu D.G., Liu P., Yang H. Electrospun multi-chamber core-shell nanofibers and their controlled release behaviors: A review. Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Nanomed. Nanobiotechnol. 2024;16:e1954.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38479982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kailasa S., Reddy M.S.B., Maurya M.R., Rani B.G., Rao K.V., Sadasivuni K.K. Electrospun nanofibers: Materials, synthesis parameters, and their role in sensing applications. Macromol. Mater. Eng. 2021;306:2100410.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang S., Zhao K., Yu D.G., Zheng X., Huang C. Advances in biosensing and environmental monitoring based on electrospun nanofibers. Adv. Fiber Mater. 2022;4:404–435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Yokota T., Someya T. Electrospun nanofiber-based soft electronics. NPG Asia Mater. 2021;13:22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayerdurai V., Cieplak M., Kutner W. Molecularly imprinted polymer-based electrochemical sensors for food contaminants determination. TrAC Trends Anal. Chem. 2023;158:116830.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhammad F., Dik G., Kolak S., Karadaş Gedik K., Bakar B., Ulu A., Ateş B. Design of highly selective, and sensitive screen-printed electrochemical sensor for detection of uric acid with uricase immobilized polycaprolactone/polyethylene imine electrospun nanofiber. Electrochim. Acta. 2023;439:141675.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanisree C.R., Sankhla M.S., Singh P., Jadhav E.B., Verma R.K., Awasthi K.K., Awasthi G., Nagar V. Environmental Impact and Remediation of Heavy Metals. Springer International Publishing; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2022. Heavy metal contamination of food crops: Transportation via food chain, human consumption, toxicity and management strategies.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Núñez C., Triviño J.J., Arancibia V. An electrochemical biosensor for As (III) detection based on the catalytic activity of Alcaligenes faecalis immobilized on a gold nanoparticle–modified screen–printed carbon electrode. Talanta. 2021;223:121702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33298256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson A., Anbarasu A., Pasupuleti R.R., Manigandan S., Praveenkumar T.R., Kumar J.A. Treatment of heavy metals containing wastewater using biodegradable adsorbents: A review of mechanism and future trends. Chemosphere. 2022;295:133724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35101432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pachaiappan R., Cornejo-Ponce L., Rajendran R., Manavalan K., Rajan V.F., Awad F. A review on biofiltration techniques: Recent advancements in the removal of volatile organic compounds and heavy metals in the treatment of polluted water. Bioengineered. 2022;13:8432–8477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9161908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35260028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S., Zhang X. Preparation of nitrogen doped carbon nanofibers for electrochemical determination of Cd (II) and Pb (II) ions. Int. J. Electrochem. Sci. 2020;15:9838–9848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machate D.J. Anthropogenic hyperactivity for natural resources increases heavy metals concentrations in the environment: Toxicity of healthy food and cancer risks estimated. J. Trace Elem. Min. 2023;4:100057.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashid A., Schutte B.J., Ulery A., Deyholos M.K., Sanogo S., Lehnhoff E.A., Beck L. Heavy metal contamination in agricultural soil: Environmental pollutants affecting crop health. Agronomy. 2023;13:1521. doi: 10.3390/agronomy13061521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agronomy13061521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li B., Xie X., Meng T., Guo X., Li Q., Yang Y., Jin H., Jin C., Meng X., Pang H. Recent advance of nanomaterials modified electrochemical sensors in the detection of heavy metal ions in food and water. Food Chem. 2023;440:138213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38134834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pichún B., Núñez C., Arancibia V., Martí A.A., Aguirre M.J., Pizarro J., Segura R., Flores E. Enhanced voltammetric sensing platform based on gold nanorods and electrochemically reduced graphene oxide for As (III) determination in seafood samples. J. Appl. Electrochem. 2024;54:1595–1606.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang Q., Zhu G., Ge Y., Yang J., Huang M., Liu J. AuNPs-polyaniline nanosheet array on carbon nanofiber for the determination of As (III) J. Electroanal. Chem. 2020;873:114381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raina J., Kaur G., Singh I. Recent progress in nanomaterial-based aptamers as biosensors for point of care detection of Hg2+ ions and its environmental applications. Talanta. 2024;277:126372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38865954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teodoro K.B.R., Migliorini F.L., Facure M.H.M., Correa D.S. Conductive electrospun nanofibers containing cellulose nanowhiskers and reduced graphene oxide for the electrochemical detection of mercury (II) Carbohydr. Polym. 2019;207:747–754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30600061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehzari H., Safari M., Shahlaei M. A new sensing strategy based on thymine bases-Hg2+-methylene blue coordination on the electrospun PES-QDs platform for detection of Hg2+ in fruit juice samples. J. Iran. Chem. Soc. 2019;16:2269–2279.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie H., Niu Y., Deng Y., Cheng H., Ruan C., Li G., Sun W. Electrochemical aptamer sensor for highly sensitive detection of mercury ion with Au/Pt@carbon nanofiber-modified electrode. J. Chin. Chem. Soc. 2021;68:114–120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotake D., Goswami P.P., Singh S.G. Ultraselective, ultrasensitive, point-of-care electrochemical sensor for detection of Hg (II) ions with electrospun-InZnO nanofibers. J. Electroanal. Chem. 2022;915:116350.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilian A.T.E., Ranjith K.S., Hwang S.K., Bhaskaran G., Alhammadi M., Park S.Y., Huh Y.S., Han Y.-K. Interface engineering of MoS2 nanopetal grown on carbon nanofibers for the electrocatalytic sensing of mercury (II) and efficient hydrogen evolution. Mater. Today Nano. 2022;20:100262.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi X., Wang Z. Graphene quantum dots functionalized Ce-ZnO nanofibers with enriched oxygen vacancy sites morphology to improve the efficiency of selective electrochemical detection of Hg (II) Diam. Relat. Mater. 2023;139:110241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeghi E., Rahimi F., Azizi Z., Kaki S., Babakhanian A. Fabrication of a sensitive electrochemical sensor based on hybrid polyamide/chromotropic acid nanofibers electrospun on glassy carbon electrode for Hg2+ sensing in drinking water and canned fish samples. Food Chem. 2023;414:135467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36842206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jyothilakshmi V.P., Manu R., Swaminathan S. The fabrication of TiO2/AgCNF/Nafion/GC electrodes for simultaneous electrochemical detection of Cd (II), Pb (II), Cu (II), and Hg (II) by optimizing the porosity of electrospun TiO2 nanofibers. J. Appl. Electrochem. 2024;54:2377–2387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Cai Q., Liu K., Yan G., Chen J., Wu Y., Li Z., Wang L., Li H. Flexible and robust Eu/cellulose acetate nanofibrous membrane for the rapid detection of Hg2+ with ultra-stable recycle capability. Measurement. 2023;222:113660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romaguera-Barcelay Y., Gandarilla A., Alves J.F.M., Tavares A.P.M., de Souza T.C.S., Segala K., Farias T., Cunha J., Sales M.G.F., Brito W.R. Electrochemical Hg2+ sensor based on electrospun cellulose acetate nanofibers doped with Ag nanoparticles. Microchem. J. 2024;204:111069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan H.W., Seen D.L.T., Xu Y.-M., Lau A.T.Y. Cadmium, Cellular Senescence, and Cancer. Rev. Environ. Contam. Toxicol. 2023;261:21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parida L., Patel T.N. Systemic impact of heavy metals and their role in cancer development: A review. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2023;195:766.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37249740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Li Z., Zhang H., Wu W., Wu Y., Liu M., Ao Y., Li M. Multistage pore structure legume-like UiO-66-NH2@carbon nanofiber aerogel modified electrode as an electrochemical sensor for high sensitivity detection of HMIs. J. Environ. Chem. Eng. 2023;11:111488.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Girija S., Sankar S.S., Thenrajan T., Kundu S., Wilson J. Bi-metallic zeolite imidazole framework nanofibers for the selective determination of Cd2+ ions. J. Mater. Chem. B. 2021;9:5656–5663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34190309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngoensawat U., Pisuchpen T., Sritana-Anant Y., Rodthongkum N., Hoven V.P. Conductive electrospun composite fibers based on solid-state polymerized poly(3,4-ethylenedioxythiophene) for simultaneous electrochemical detection of metal ions. Talanta. 2022;241:123253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35121539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fakude C.T., Arotiba O.A., Arduini F., Mabuba N. Flexible polyester screen-printed electrode modified with carbon nanofibers for the electrochemical aptasensing of cadmium (II) Electroanalysis. 2020;32:2650–2658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousefi A., Aghaie H., Giahi M., Maleknia L. Determination of Cd2+ and Pb2+ by polyindole/Mn2O3 nanocomposite and polyindole/Mn2O3/polyaniline nanofibers modified glassy carbon electrode. Chem. Pap. 2023;77:733–743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong J., Wen L., Zhao D., Yang H., Zhao J., Hu Z., Ma Y., Hou C., Huo D. Flexible carbon fiber cloth supports decorated with cerium metal-organic frameworks and multi-walled carbon nanotubes for simultaneous on-site detection of Cd2+ and Pb2+ in food and water samples. Food Chem. 2023;418:135869.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37001351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira V.H.B., Rechotnek F., da Silva E.P., Marques V.S., Rubira A.F., Silva R., Lourenço S.A., Muniz E.C. A sensitive electrochemical sensor for Pb2+ ions based on ZnO nanofibers functionalized by L-cysteine. J. Mol. Liq. 2020;309:113041.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fotia A., Frontera P., Bonaccorsi L., Sciacca B., Malara A. Encapsulation of Disodium-EDTA in Electrospun Polymeric Fibers for the Detection of Heavy Metals. Adv. Sustain. Syst. 2024;8:2300463.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kogularasu S., Lee Y.Y., Chang-Chien G.P., Govindasamy M., Sheu J.K. Nanofibers: Empowering electrochemical sensors for reliable detection of food and environmental toxins. J. Electrochem. Soc. 2023;170:077514.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sindhu S., Manickavasagan A. Nondestructive testing methods for pesticide residue in food commodities: A review. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2023;22:1226–1256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36710657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumaravel A., Aishwarya S., Sathyamoorthi S. Emerging Technologies for Sensitive Detection of Organophosphate Pesticides: A Review. Curr. Anal. Chem. 2024;20:383–409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q., Wang M., Zhang N., Huang X., Wang X., Wang S. A novel electrochemical sensor based on MoS2 electrospun nanofibers and polyoxometalate composite for the simultaneous detection of ractopamine and clenbuterol. Microchem. J. 2023;189:108434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shan X., Lu J., Wu Q., Li C., Li H., Yang S., Tian L. Solid-state electrochemiluminescence sensor of CQDs based on ZIFs electrospun carbon fiber for malathion detection. Microchem. J. 2023;195:109496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cacciotti I., Pallotto F., Scognamiglio V., Moscone D., Arduini F. Reusable optical multi-plate sensing system for pesticide detection by using electrospun membranes as smart support for acetylcholinesterase immobilisation. Mater. Sci. Eng. C. 2020;111:110744.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32279763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Migliorini F.L., Sanfelice R.C., Mercante L.A., Facure M.H.M., Correa D.S. Electrochemical sensor based on polyamide 6/polypyrrole electrospun nanofibers coated with reduced graphene oxide for malathion pesticide detection. Mater. Res. Express. 2020;7:015601.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu J., Wen P., Wang Y., Yang J., Xiao Z., Xu Z., Shen Y., Wang H., Hammock B.D. Fabrication of a label-free electrochemical immunosensor by functionalized nanofiber membrane for the ultrasensitive detection of quinalphos. Food Control. 2024;162:110423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin W., Zhang J., Wang H., Wang Y., Zeng X., Xu Z., Yang J., Xiao Z., Hammock B.D., Wen P. A highly sensitive electrochemical immunosensor based on electrospun nanocomposite for the detection of parathion. Food Chem. 2023;404:134371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36244073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topsoy O.K., Muhammad F., Kolak S., Ulu A., Güngör Ö., Şimşek M., Köytepe S., Ateş B. Fabrication of electrospun polycaprolactone/chitosan nanofiber-modified screen-printed electrode for highly sensitive detection of diazinon in food analysis. Measurement. 2022;187:110250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatamluyi B., Sadeghzadeh S., Rezayi M., Sany S.B.T. Diazinon electrochemical biosensor mediated by aptamer and nanoscale porous carbon derived from ZIF-8. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2023;381:133424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Supraja P., Tripathy S., Vanjari S.R.K., Singh V., Singh S.G. Electrospun tin (IV) oxide nanofiber based electrochemical sensor for ultra-sensitive and selective detection of atrazine in water at trace levels. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2019;141:111441.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31229795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Supraja P., Singh V., Vanjari S.R.K., Singh S.G. Electrospun CNT embedded ZnO nanofiber based biosensor for electrochemical detection of atrazine: A step closure to single molecule detection. Microsyst. Nanoeng. 2020;6:3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8433164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34567618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey B., Ahmad M.W., Syed A., Bahkali A.H., Verma M., Choudhury A. Iron metal organic framework decorated carbon nanofiber-based electrode for electrochemical sensing platform of chlorpyrifos in fruits and vegetables. Mater. Sci. Semicond. Process. 2024;181:108669.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv Y., Yang T., Hou X., Fang Z., Rajan K., Di Y., Peng W., Deng Y., Liang T. Zirconia nanofibers-loaded reduced graphene oxide fabrication for specific electrochemical detection of methyl parathion. J. Alloys Compd. 2022;904:163798.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z., Ma B., Shen C., Cheong L.Z. Direct, selective and ultrasensitive electrochemical biosensing of methyl parathion in vegetables using Burkholderia cepacia lipase@MOF nanofibers-based biosensor. Talanta. 2019;197:356–362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30771947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kokulnathan T., Vishnuraj R., Chen S.-M., Pullithadathil B., Ahmed F., Hasan P.M.Z., Bilgrami A.L., Kumar S. Tailored construction of one-dimensional TiO2/Au nanofibers: Validation of an analytical assay for detection of diphenylamine in food samples. Food Chem. 2022;380:132052.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35105505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rayappa M.K., Kavya K.S., Rattu G., Krishna P.M. Advances and effectiveness of metal-organic framework based bio/chemical sensors for rapid and ultrasensitive probing of antibiotic residues in foods. Sustain. Food Technol. 2023;1:152–184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakimova Z., Zharykbasova K., Kakimov A., Mirasheva G., Toleubekova S., Zharykbasov Y., Tulkebayeva G., Muratbayev A., Utegenova A. Study on the detection of antibiotics in food based on enzyme-free labelless aptamer sensor. Food Sci. Technol. 2022;42:e70421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang S.J., Gokulkumar K., Govindasamy M., Albaqami M.D., Wabaidur S.M. Nanoarchitectonics of europium vanadate nanoparticles decorated carbon nanofibers for electrochemical detection of fungicide in fruits. J. Taiwan Inst. Chem. Eng. 2024;161:105563.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song J., Huang M., Lin X., Li S.F.Y., Jiang N., Liu Y., Guo H., Li Y. Novel Fe-based metal-organic framework (MOF) modified carbon nanofiber as a highly selective and sensitive electrochemical sensor for tetracycline detection. Chem. Eng. J. 2022;427:130913.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadi S., Pooshang Bagheri K., Mousavi Nadushan R., Adabi M. Nanoarchitectonics of electrochemical aptasensor based on electrospun carbon nanofibers and gold nanoparticles for tetracycline detection in chicken ham. Appl. Phys. A. 2023;129:176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebastian N., Yu W.C., Balram D., Hong G.T., Alharthi S.S., Al-Saidi H.M. Ultrasensitive detection and photocatalytic degradation of polyketide drug tetracycline in environment and food samples using dual-functional Ag doped zinc ferrite embedded functionalized carbon nanofibers. Chemosphere. 2024;348:140692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37952826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kokulnathan T., Vishnuraj R., Wang T.J., Pullithadathil B. Multidimensional nanoarchitectures of TiO2/Au nanofibers with O-doped C3N4 nanosheets for electrochemical detection of nitrofurazone. Appl. Surf. Sci. 2022;604:154474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei X., Sun Y., Luo Y., Shu R., Lin H., Xu D. Electrochemical biosensor Bi2O3@Au@Apta based on Bi2O3 nanofibers for sensitive detection of ampicillin. Biochem. Eng. J. 2023;200:109107</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mariappan K., Alagarsamy S., Chen S.-M., Sakthinathan S. Electrochemical detection of metronidazole by the fabricated composites of orthorhombic iron tungsten oxide decorated with carbon nanofiber composites electrode. J. Electrochem. Soc. 2023;170:037514.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilian A.T.E., Ranjith K.S., Lee S.J., Umapathi R., Hwang S.-K., Oh C.W., Huh Y.S., Han Y.-K. Hierarchical dense Ni−Co layered double hydroxide supported carbon nanofibers for the electrochemical determination of metronidazole in biological samples. Electrochim. Acta. 2020;354:136723.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muthukutty B., Arumugam B., Chen S.-M., Kannan S.R. Low potential detection of antiprotozoal drug metronidazole with aid of novel dysprosium vanadate incorporated oxidized carbon nanofiber modified disposable screen-printed electrode. J. Hazard. Mater. 2021;407:124745.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33341580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shoba S., Mambanda A., Booysen I.N. Electrospun Nanofiber Composite Utilized as an Electrocatalyst for the Detection of Acetaminophen in Multifarious Water Samples. ACS Omega. 2024;9:5734–5750.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10851381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38343966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S., Deep A., Wangoo N., Bhardwaj N. Recent advancements in nanomaterials based optical detection of food additives: A review. Analyst. 2023;148:5322–5339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37750046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur I., Batra V., Bogireddy N.K.R., Landa S.D.T., Agarwal V. Detection of organic pollutants, food additives and antibiotics using sustainable carbon dots. Food Chem. 2023;406:135029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36463597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagirani M.S., Zhou W., Nazir A., Akram M.Y., Huo P., Yan Y. A Recent Advancement in Food Quality Assessment: Using MOF-Based Sensors: Challenges and Future Aspects. Crit. Rev. Anal. Chem. 2024. online ahead of print .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38252119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang F., Li Y., Yan C., Ma Q., Yang X., Peng H., Wang H., Du J., Zheng B., Guo Y. Bismuth-Decorated Honeycomb-like Carbon Nanofibers: An Active Electrocatalyst for the Construction of a Sensitive Nitrite Sensor. Molecules. 2023;28:3881. doi: 10.3390/molecules28093881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28093881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10180303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37175296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le H.T., Tran D.T., Kim N.H., Lee J.H. Worm-like gold nanowires assembled carbon nanofibers-CVD graphene hybrid as sensitive and selective sensor for nitrite detection. J. Colloid Interface Sci. 2021;583:425–434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33011411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjith K.S., Ezhil Vilian A.T., Ghoreishian S.M., Umapathi R., Huh Y.S., Han Y.-K. An ultrasensitive electrochemical sensing platform for rapid detection of rutin with a hybridized 2D-1D MXene-FeWO4 nanocomposite. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2021;344:130202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L., Qin D., Feng J., Tang T., Cheng H. Rapid quantitative detection of luteolin using an electrochemical sensor based on electrospinning of carbon nanofibers doped with single-walled carbon nanoangles. Anal. Methods. 2023;15:3073–3083.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37318338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vinoth S., Wang S.F. Rhombohedral type of LaCoO3 with carbon nanofiber composite as an electrocatalyst enables the amperometry detection of vanillin in food samples. New J. Chem. 2023;47:9229–9238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nixon E.J., Sakthivel R., ALOthman Z.A., Ganesh P.S., Chung R.J. Lanthanum nickelate spheres embedded acid functionalized carbon nanofiber composite: An efficient electrocatalyst for electrochemical detection of food additive vanillin. Food Chem. 2023;409:135324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36586249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gokulkumar K., Huang S.J., Kogularasu S., Aljuwayid A.M., Maheshwaran S., Govindasamy M. Enhanced electrochemical detection of tartrazine in beverages and liquid soap via nickel phosphide-adorned functionalized carbon nanofibers. J. Taiwan Inst. Chem. Eng. 2024;157:105420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenisha Daisy Priscillal I., Wang S.F. Designing nano ranged electrode modifier comprised of samarium niobate anchored carbon nanofibers for trace level detection of food colourant: Tartrazine. Food Chem. 2023;422:136230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37141761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radha A., Wang S.F. Neodymium (III) Vanadate-Decorated functionalized carbon nanofiber nanocomposite: An electrochemical tool for tartrazine monitoring. ACS Appl. Nano Mater. 2023;6:18036–18044.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari S.H., Arvand M. Electrospun ruthenium oxide nanofibers/poly(sulfosalicylic acid) nanocomposite as an highly sensitive electrochemical platform for determination of sunset yellow in food samples. J. Food Meas. Charact. 2023;17:1616–1627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atilgan H., Unal B., Yalcinkaya E.E., Evren G., Atik G., Ozturk Kirbay F., Kilic N.M., Odaci D. Development of an enzymatic biosensor using glutamate oxidase on organic-inorganic-structured, electrospun nanofiber-modified electrodes for monosodium glutamate detection. Biosensors. 2023;13:430. doi: 10.3390/bios13040430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bios13040430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10135961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37185504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyedeji A.B., Green E., Adebiyi J.A., Ogundele O.M., Gbashi S., Adefisoye M.A., Oyeyinka S.A., Adebo O.A. Metabolomic approaches for the determination of metabolites from pathogenic microorganisms: A review. Food Res. Int. 2021;140:110042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33648268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesan A.R., Mohan K., Rajan D.K., Pillay A.A., Palanisami T., Sathishkumar P., Conterno L. Distribution, toxicity, interactive effects, and detection of ochratoxin and deoxynivalenol in food: A review. Food Chem. 2022;378:131978.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35033712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui Q., Gan S., Zhong Y., Yang H., Wan Y., Zuo Y., Yang H., Li M., Zhang S., Negahdary M., et al. High-throughput and specific detection of microorganisms by intelligent modular fluorescent photoelectric microbe detector. Anal. Chim. Acta. 2023;1265:341282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37230579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R.F., Wang R. Modification of polyacrylonitrile-derived carbon nanofibers and bacteriophages on screen-printed electrodes: A portable electrochemical biosensor for rapid detection of Escherichia coli. Bioelectrochemistry. 2022;148:108229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35987062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaibani P.M., Jiang K., Haghighat G., Hassanpourfard M., Etayash H., Naicker S., Thundat T. The detection of Escherichia coli (E. coli) with the pH sensitive hydrogel nanofiber-light addressable potentiometric sensor (NF-LAPS) Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2016;226:176–183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares A.C., Soares J.C., dos Santos D.M., Migliorini F.L., Popolin-Neto M., Pinto D.S.C., Carvalho W.A., Brandão H.M., Paulovich F.V., Correa D.S., et al. Nanoarchitectonic E-tongue of electrospun zein/curcumin carbon dots for detecting Staphylococcus aureus in milk. ACS Omega. 2023;8:13721–13732.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10116536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37091421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z., Du M., Cheng X., Dou X., Zhou J., Wu J., Xie X., Zhu M. A disposable paper-based electrochemical biosensor decorated by electrospun cellulose acetate nanofibers for highly sensitive bio-detection. Analyst. 2024;149:2436–2444.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38498083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moradi S., Azizi-Lalabadi M., Bagheri V., Sadeghi E. Fabrication of electrospun sensor based on a synthesized component doped into PAN (polyacrylonitrile) nanofibers for electrochemical detection of zearalenone mycotoxin in foods simulant. Sens. Bio-Sens. Res. 2020;28:100321</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang S.-J., Gokulkumar K., Mani G., Lee Y.-Y., Kogularasu S., Chang-Chien G.-P. Synthesis and characterization of Bi2S3-embedded carbon nanofibers as a novel electrochemical biosensor for the detection of mycotoxin zearalenone in food crops. FlatChem. 2024;45:100652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmani H.R., Adabi M., Bagheri K.P., Karim G. Development of electrochemical aptasensor based on gold nanoparticles and electrospun carbon nanofibers for the detection of aflatoxin M1 in milk. J. Food Meas. Charact. 2021;15:1826–1833.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahimi Vafaye S., Rahman A., Safaeian S., Adabi M. An electrochemical aptasensor based on electrospun carbon nanofiber mat and gold nanoparticles for the sensitive detection of Penicillin in milk. J. Food Meas. Charact. 2021;15:876–882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Moghazy A.Y., Amaly N., Istamboulie G., Nitin N., Sun G. A signal-on electrochemical aptasensor based on silanized cellulose nanofibers for rapid point-of-use detection of ochratoxin A. Microchim. Acta. 2020;187:535.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7780854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32870397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Dhahebi A.M., Jose R., Mustapha M., Saheed M.S.M. Ultrasensitive aptasensor using electrospun MXene/polyvinylidene fluoride nanofiber composite for Ochratoxin A detection. Food Chem. 2022;390:133105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35580522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dos Santos D.M., Migliorini F.L., Soares A.C., Mattoso L.H.C., Oliveira O.N., Jr., Correa D.S. Electrochemical Immunosensor Made with Zein-based Nanofibers for On-site Detection of Aflatoxin B1. Electroanalysis. 2023;35:e202100672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekhit A.E.D.A., Giteru S.G., Holman B.W.B., Hopkins D.L. Total volatile basic nitrogen and trimethylamine in muscle foods: Potential formation pathways and effects on human health. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2021;20:3620–3666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34056832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi N., Pransu G., Adam Conte-Junior C. Critical review and recent advances of 2D materials-Based gas sensors for food spoilage detection. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;63:10536–10559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35647714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das J., Mishra H.N. A comprehensive review of the spoilage of shrimp and advances in various indicators/sensors for shrimp spoilage monitoring. Food Res. Int. 2023;173:113270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37803582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashiq J., Saeed U., Li Z., Nawaz M.H. Advances in Meat Spoilage Detection: A Review of Methods Involving 2D-Based Nanomaterials for Detection of Spoiled Meat. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2024;132:106295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H., Chu S., Ma Q., Fang Y., Wang J., Che Q., Wang G., Yang P. Novel construction of morphology-tunable C-N/SnO2/ZnO/Au microspheres with ultrasensitivity and high selectivity for triethylamine under various temperature detections. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2019;11:8601–8611.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30702279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rianjanu A., Aflaha R., Khamidy N.I., Djamal M., Triyana K., Wasisto H.S. Room-temperature ppb-level trimethylamine gas sensors functionalized with citric acid-doped polyvinyl acetate nanofibrous mats. Mater. Adv. 2021;2:3705–3714.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma S., Guo J., Zhang H., Shao X., Zhang D. A Room Temperature Trimethylamine Gas Sensor Based on Electrospun Molybdenum Oxide Nanofibers/Ti3C2Tx MXene Heterojunction. Nanomaterials. 2024;14:537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10975576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38535685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu C., Zhao P., Wu C., Zhuang Y., Liu J., Li W., Liu Z., Liu J. Electrospun PAN/PANI fiber film with abundant active sites for ultrasensitive trimethylamine detection. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2021;338:129822.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Liu J., Zhang J., Liang X., Zhang X., Qi Q. Deposition of In2O3 nanofibers on polyimide substrates to construct high-performance and flexible trimethylamine sensor. Chin. Chem. Lett. 2020;31:2142–2144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J., Han W., Ma J., Wang C., Shimanoe K., Zhang S., Sun Y., Cheng P., Wang Y., Zhang H., et al. Sn doping effect on NiO hollow nanofibers based gas sensors about the humidity dependence for triethylamine detection. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2021;340:129971.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai L.X., Chen L., Sun X.Q., Geng J., Liu C.C., Wang Y., Guo Z. Ultra-sensitive triethylamine gas sensors based on polyoxometalate-assisted synthesis of ZnWO4/ZnO hetero-structured nanofibers. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2022;370:132422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Q., Li H., Chu S., Liu Y., Liu M., Fu X., Li H., Guo J. In2O3 hierarchical structures of one-dimensional electrospun fibers with in situ growth of octahedron-like particles with superior sensitivity for triethylamine at near room temperature. ACS Sustain. Chem. Eng. 2020;8:5240–5250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie Q., Ding Y., Wang Q., Song P. Fabrication of 1D/2D In2O3 nanofibers/Ti3C2Tx MXene composites for high performance detection of trimethylamine at low temperature. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2024;405:135338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Liu Z., Li Y., Liu Y., Liang X., Liu F., Lu G. Trace PdO and Co-MOF derivative modified SnO2 nanofibers for rapid triethylamine detection with little humidity disturbance. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2024;403:135239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conti P.P., dos Santos D.M., Goldthorpe I.A., Correa D.S. TiO2 hollow nanofiber/polyaniline nanocomposites for ammonia detection at room temperature. ChemNanoMat. 2022;8:e202200154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu D., Shi Q., Jin S., Shao Y., Huang J. Self-assembled core-shell structured organic nanofibers fabricated by single-nozzle electrospinning for highly sensitive ammonia sensors. InfoMat. 2019;1:525–532.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aflaha R., Sari N.L.I., Katriani L., As’ari A.H., Kusumaatmaja A., Rianjanu A., Roto R., Wasisto H.S., Triyana K. Maltodextrin-overlaid polyvinyl acetate nanofibers for highly sensitive and selective room-temperature ammonia sensors. Microchem. J. 2023;193:109237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rianjanu A., Rayhan M.A.A.P., Aulya M., Aflaha R., Triyana K., Taher T., Wasisto H.S. Early spoilage detection of cultured Pacific white shrimp using quartz crystal microbalance gas sensors. ChemistrySelect. 2024;9:e202304694.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andre R.S., Facure M.H.M., Mercante L.A., Correa D.S. Electronic nose based on hybrid free-standing nanofibrous mats for meat spoilage monitoring. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2022;353:131114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey B., Ahmad M.W., Kim B.H., Kamal T., Yang D.J., Patra C.N., Hossain S.K.S., Choudhury A. Manganese cobalt-MOF@ carbon nanofiber-based non-enzymatic histamine sensor for the determination of food freshness. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2023;415:3487–3501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37219581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Zhang D., Gao Y., Chen F., Wang T., Xia H., Sui X., Wang Z. Fast-response hydrogen sulfide gas sensor based on electrospinning Co3O4 nano-fibers-modified CuO nanoflowers: Experimental and DFT calculation. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2023;396:134579.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huo Y., Qiu L., Wang T., Yu H., Yang W., Dong X., Yang Y. P-N Heterojunction formation: Metal Sulfide@ Metal Oxide Chemiresistor for ppb H2S Detection from Exhaled Breath and Food Spoilage at Flexible Room Temperature. ACS Sens. 2024;9:3433–3443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38872232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei Y., Zhang Y., Wang B., Zhang Z., Yuan L., Li J. A lab-on-injector device with Au nanodots confined in carbon nanofibers for in situ electrochemical BPA sensing in beverages. Food Control. 2022;134:108747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shoukat N., Anzar S., Asad M., Al-Sulami A.I., Khalid H., Choudhary A.A., Sherin L., Akhtar N. Fabrication of CuO-NiO wrapped cellulose acetate/polyaniline electrospun nanofibers for sensitive monitoring of bisphenol-A. ACS Sustain. Chem. Eng. 2023;11:4299–4307.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey B., Ahmad M.W., Al-Shannaq R., Al-Humaidi J.Y., Hossain S.K.S., Patra C.N., Althomali R.H., Rahman M.M., Choudhury A. Non-Enzymatic Electrochemical Sensing of Bisphenol A in Drinking Water and Milk Using Bimetallic Nickel-Copper Metal-Organic Framework. J. Anal. Test. 2024:1–15. doi: 10.1007/s41664-024-00312-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41664-024-00312-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quezada V., Martinez T., Nelson R., Pérez-Fehrmann M., Zaragoza G., Vizcarra A., Kesternich V., Hernández-Saravia L.P. A novel platform of using copper (II) complex with triazole-carboxilated modified as bidentated ligand SPCE for the detection of hydrogen peroxide in milk. J. Electroanal. Chem. 2020;879:114763.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T., Guo Y., Zhang Z., Miao Z., Zhang X., Su Z. Fabrication of hollow CuO/PANI hybrid nanofibers for non-enzymatic electrochemical detection of H2O2 and glucose. Sens. Actuators B Chem. 2019;286:370–376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y., Miao Q., Han B. Electrospinning Synthesis of Ag Nanoparticles-doped Carbon Nanofibers for Voltammetric Determination of H2O2. Int. J. Electrochem. Sci. 2021;16:210226.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>