<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39346581</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2296-2565</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>12</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring public opinion on health effects of prepared dishes in China through social media comments.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1424690</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1424690</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1424690</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fpubh.2024.1424690</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In the 2020s, particularly following 2022, the Chinese government introduced a series of initiatives to foster the development of the prepared dishes sector, accompanied by substantial investments from industrial capital. Consequently, China's prepared dishes industry has experienced rapid growth. Nevertheless, this swift expansion has elicited varied public opinions, particularly concerning the potential health effects of prepared dishes. Therefore, this study aims to gather and analyze comments from social media on prepared dishes using machine learning techniques. The objective is to ascertain the perspectives of the Chinese populace on the health implications of consuming prepared dishes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Social media comments, characterized by their broad distribution, objectivity, and timeliness, served as the primary data source for this study. Initially, the data underwent preprocessing to ensure its suitability for analysis. Subsequent steps in this study involved conducting sentiment analysis and employing the BERTopic model for topic clustering. These methods aimed to identify the principal concerns of the public regarding the impact of prepared dishes on health. The final phase of the study involved a comparative analysis of changes in public sentiment and thematic focus across different time frames. This approach provides a dynamic view of evolving public perceptions related to the health implications of prepared dishes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study analyzed over 600,000 comments gathered from various social media platforms from mid-July 2022 to the end of March 2024. Following data preprocessing, 200,993 comments were assessed for sentiment, revealing that more than 64% exhibited negative emotions. Subsequent topic clustering using the BERTopic model identified that 11 of the top 50 topics were related to public health concerns. These topics primarily scrutinized the safety of prepared dish production processes, raw materials, packaging materials, and additives. Moreover, significant public's interest was in the right to informed consumption across different contexts. Notably, the most pronounced public opposition emerged regarding introducing prepared dishes into primary and secondary school canteens, with criticisms directed at the negligence of educational authorities and the ethics of manufacturers. Additionally, there were strong recommendations for media organizations to play a more active role in monitoring public opinion and for government agencies to enhance regulatory oversight.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The findings of this study indicate that more than half of the Chinese public maintain a negative perception towards prepared dishes, particularly concerning about health implications. Chinese individuals display considerable sensitivity and intense reactions to news and events related to prepared dishes. Consequently, the study recommends that manufacturers directly address public psychological perceptions, proactively enhance production processes and service quality, and increase transparency in public communications to improve corporate image and people acceptance of prepared dishes. Additionally, supervisory and regulatory efforts must be intensified by media organizations and governmental bodies, fostering the healthy development of the prepared food industry in China.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Shu, Yang, Lin, Chen, Zhou and Wang.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shu</LastName><ForeName>Tao</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Software Engineering, Chengdu University of Information Technology, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Han</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computer Science, Chengdu University of Information Technology, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computing and Artificial Intelligence, Southwestern University of Finance and Economics, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Blockchain Industry, Chengdu University of Information Technology, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Jian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Software Engineering, Chengdu University of Information Technology, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Jixian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Computing and Artificial Intelligence, Southwestern University of Finance and Economics, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Management Science and Engineering, Southwestern University of Finance and Economics, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101616579</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-2565</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D061108" MajorTopicYN="Y">Social Media</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011639" MajorTopicYN="Y">Public Opinion</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prepared dishes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public opinion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sentiment analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social media comments</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">topic modeling</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39346581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11427877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2024.1424690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Chen LA, House L. Food lifestyle patterns among contemporary food shoppers. Int J Consum Stud. (2022) 46:944–63. doi: 10.1111/ijcs.12739</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijcs.12739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imtiyaz H, Soni P, Yukongdi V. Understanding Consumer’s purchase intention and consumption of convenience food in an emerging economy: role of marketing and commercial determinants. J Agric Food Res. (2022) 10:100399. doi: 10.1016/j.jafr.2022.100399</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jafr.2022.100399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statista  (2024). Convenience Food – Worldwide. Available at: https://www.statista.com/outlook/cmo/food/convenience-food/worldwide#revenue (Accessed February 26, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>iiMedia  (2023). China’s pre-made food industry: Multiple policy benefits, comprehensive acceleration of China’s pre-made food industry. Available at: https://www.iimedia.cn/c1020/92136.html/ (Accessed February 26, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhatt Y, Jyothi Lakshmi AS. Effect of processing treatments on digestibility and physicochemical properties of ready-to-cook breakfast mixes. Food Proces Preserv. (2022) 46:e16324. doi: 10.1111/jfpp.16324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.16324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo J, Zhang M, Law CL, Luo Z. 3D printing technology for prepared dishes: printing characteristics, applications, challenges and prospects. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. (2023) 63:1–17. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2023.2238826, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2023.2238826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37480290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang T, Zhang M, Lim Law C, Mujumdar AS. Novel strategies for controlling nitrite content in prepared dishes: current status, potential benefits, limitations and future challenges. Food Res Int. (2023) 170:112984. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2023.112984, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2023.112984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37316019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Q, Zhang M, Ju R, Mujumdar AS, Wang H. Advances in prepared dish processing using efficient physical fields: a review. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. (2022) 64:4031–45. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2022.2138260</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2022.2138260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang M, Zhang M, Bhandari B. Recent development in the application of alternative sterilization technologies to prepared dishes: a review. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. (2019) 59:1188–96. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2017.1421140, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2017.1421140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29359947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav B, Spinelli AC, Misra NN, Tsui YY, McMullen LM, Roopesh MS. Effect of in-package atmospheric cold plasma discharge on microbial safety and quality of ready-to-eat ham in modified atmospheric packaging during storage. J Food Sci. (2020) 85:1203–12. doi: 10.1111/1750-3841.15072, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.15072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32118300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinu M, Tristan Asensi M, Pagliai G, Lotti S, Martini D, Colombini B, et al. . Consumption of ultra-processed foods is inversely associated with adherence to the Mediterranean diet: a cross-sectional study. Nutrients. (2022) 14:2073. doi: 10.3390/nu14102073, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14102073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9147239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35631214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petimar J, Grummon AH, Simon D, Block JP. Nutritional composition and purchasing patterns of supermarket prepared foods over time. Am J Prev Med. (2023) 64:213–20. doi: 10.1016/j.amepre.2022.08.021, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2022.08.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9976399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36280402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namdar A, Naghizadeh MM, Zamani M, Montazeri A. Exploring the relationship between health literacy and fast food consumption: a population-based study from southern Iran. BMC Public Health. (2021) 21:757. doi: 10.1186/s12889-021-10763-3, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-021-10763-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8056591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33879106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Zhang M, Bhandari B, Bai B. Nanoemulsion-based edible coatings loaded with fennel essential oil/cinnamaldehyde: characterization, antimicrobial property and advantages in pork meat patties application. Food Control. (2021) 127:108151. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi B, Xu H. Research and Development status of prepared foods in China: a review. Appl Sci. (2023) 13:7998. doi: 10.3390/app13147998</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app13147998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Gao Q, Lou W. Development status and trends of the pre-prepared food industry in China. Modern Food Sci Technol. (2023) 39:99–103. doi: 10.13982/j.mfst.1673-9078.2023.2.0388</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13982/j.mfst.1673-9078.2023.2.0388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong Y, Lin X, Wen X, Wang Y, Liang W, Xing T. The analysis of residents’ intention to consume pre-made dishes in China: a grounded theory. Food Secur. (2023) 12:3798. doi: 10.3390/foods12203798, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12203798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10606755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37893691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Li H, Meng T, Wu X. A consumer survey on cognition and purchase intention of pre-prepared food. Food Nut China. (2023):1–9. doi: 10.19870/j.cnki.11-3716/ts.20230315.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19870/j.cnki.11-3716/ts.20230315.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Zheng J, Li Y. Explaining Chinese consumers’ continuous consumption intention toward prepared dishes: the role of perceived risk and trust. Food Secur. (2023) 13:88. doi: 10.3390/foods13010088, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13010088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10778665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38201116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q. Analysis of consumption trends and influencing mechanisms of prepared dishes based on SOR-SEM model. Manag Admin. (2023):1–12. doi: 10.16517/j.cnki.cn12-1034/f.20230712.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16517/j.cnki.cn12-1034/f.20230712.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong X. (2022). Prepared dishes must be not only popular but also tasty. China Consumer News. Available at: https://www.ccn.com.cn/Content/2022/02-23/0101520159.html (Accessed February 26, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>iiMedia  (2023). Consumer awareness survey data on the safety of pre-prepared food in China. Available at: https://www.iimedia.cn/c1077/95893.html (Accessed February 26, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbate S, Centobelli P, Cerchione R. The digital and sustainable transition of the Agri-food sector. Technol Forecast Soc Chang. (2023) 187:122222. doi: 10.1016/j.techfore.2022.122222</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2022.122222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoo R, Kim S-Y, Kim D-H, Kim J, Jeon YJ, Park JHY, et al. . Exploring the nexus between food and veg*n lifestyle via text mining-based online community analytics. Food Qual Prefer. (2023) 104:104714. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104714</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gefen D, Larsen K. Controlling for lexical closeness in survey research: a demonstration on the technology acceptance model. JAIS. (2017) 18:727–57. doi: 10.17705/1jais.00469</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17705/1jais.00469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Podsakoff PM, MacKenzie SB, Podsakoff NP. Sources of method bias in social science research and recommendations on how to control it. Annu Rev Psychol. (2012) 63:539–69. doi: 10.1146/annurev-psych-120710-100452</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-120710-100452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21838546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elfenbein HA. Emotion in organizations: theory and research. Annu Rev Psychol. (2023) 74:489–517. doi: 10.1146/annurev-psych-032720-035940</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-032720-035940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36104000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oatley K, Keltner D, Jenkins JM. Understanding emotions, vol. xxvi. 2nd ed. Malden: Blackwell Publishing; (2006). 508 p.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh A, Glińska-Neweś A. Modeling the public attitude towards organic foods: a big data and text mining approach. J Big Data. (2022) 9:2. doi: 10.1186/s40537-021-00551-6, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40537-021-00551-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8733915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35013700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao D, Yang P, Feng H. Utilization of text mining as a big data analysis tool for food science and nutrition. Comp Rev Food Sci Food Safe. (2020) 19:875–94. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12540, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33325182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Wang W, Feng J, Fan X, Guo J, Lei J. A novel user-generated content-driven and Kano model focused framework to explore the impact mechanism of continuance intention to use mobile APPs. Comput Hum Behav. (2024):108252. doi: 10.1016/j.chb.2024.108252</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2024.108252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C. (2023). With 4.74 billion users, what kind of social media is needed? Available at: https://www.huxiu.com/article/807827.html (Accessed February 26, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inwood O, Zappavigna M. Conspiracy theories and white supremacy on YouTube: exploring affiliation and legitimation strategies in YouTube comments. Soc Media Soc. (2023) 9:205630512211504. doi: 10.1177/20563051221150410</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20563051221150410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trillo JR, Herrera-Viedma E, Morente-Molinera JA, Cabrerizo FJ. A large scale group decision making system based on sentiment analysis cluster. Inform Fusion. (2023) 91:633–43. doi: 10.1016/j.inffus.2022.11.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.inffus.2022.11.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, Zhang Y, Chen Q, Wang H. Attitude of Chinese public towards municipal solid waste sorting policy: a text mining study. Sci Total Environ. (2021) 756:142674. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142674, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33071141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazir S, Khadim S, Ali Asadullah M, Syed N. Exploring the influence of artificial intelligence technology on consumer repurchase intention: the mediation and moderation approach. Technol Soc. (2023) 72:102190. doi: 10.1016/j.techsoc.2022.102190</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.techsoc.2022.102190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martí P, Serrano-Estrada L, Nolasco-Cirugeda A. Social media data: challenges, opportunities and limitations in urban studies. Comput Environ Urban Syst. (2019) 74:161–74. doi: 10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2018.11.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2018.11.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen Z. Mining sustainable fashion e-commerce: social media texts and consumer behaviors. Electron Commer Res. (2023) 23:949–71. doi: 10.1007/s10660-021-09498-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10660-021-09498-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carr J, Decreton L, Qin W, Rojas B, Rossochacki T, Yang YW. Social media in product development. Food Qual Prefer. (2015) 40:354–64. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2014.04.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2014.04.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Niu Y, Wang L. How to win the green market? Exploring the satisfaction and sentiment of Chinese consumers based on text mining. Comput Hum Behav. (2023) 148:107890. doi: 10.1016/j.chb.2023.107890</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2023.107890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilro RG, Loureiro SMC, Dos Santos JF. Masstige strategies on social media: the influence on sentiments and attitude toward the brand. Int J Consum Stud. (2022) 46:1113–26. doi: 10.1111/ijcs.12747</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijcs.12747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M, Luo X, Lu W-Z. Public perceptions of environmental, social, and governance (ESG) based on social media data: evidence from China. J Clean Prod. (2023) 387:135840. doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.135840</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.135840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatemi H, Kao E, Schillo RS, Li W, Du P, Jian-Yun N, et al. . Using social media to analyze consumers’ attitude toward natural food products. BFJ. (2023) 125:3145–59. doi: 10.1108/BFJ-06-2022-0511</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/BFJ-06-2022-0511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samoggia A, Riedel B, Ruggeri A. Social media exploration for understanding food product attributes perception: the case of coffee and health with twitter data. BFJ. (2020) 122:3815–35. doi: 10.1108/BFJ-03-2019-0172</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/BFJ-03-2019-0172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Zhang Z. Exploring public perceptions on alternative meat in China from social media data using transfer learning method. Food Qual Prefer. (2022) 98:104530. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Zhang D, Wei Z, Li Y, Wu S, Mao Z, et al. . Analysis of public opinion on food safety in greater China with big data and machine learning. Curr Res Food Sci. (2023) 6:100468. doi: 10.1016/j.crfs.2023.100468, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.crfs.2023.100468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9988419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36891545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou L, Zhang C, Liu F, Qiu Z, He Y. Application of deep learning in food: a review. Comp Rev Food Sci Food Safe. (2019) 18:1793–811. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12492</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33336958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton LM, Lahne J. Fast and automated sensory analysis: using natural language processing for descriptive lexicon development. Food Qual Prefer. (2020) 83:103926. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2020.103926</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2020.103926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirschberg J, Manning CD. Advances in natural language processing. Science. (2015) 349:261–6. doi: 10.1126/science.aaa8685</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.aaa8685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26185244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mostafa MM. Mining and mapping halal food consumers: a geo-located twitter opinion polarity analysis. J Food Prod Mark. (2018) 24:858–79. doi: 10.1080/10454446.2017.1418695</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10454446.2017.1418695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Couldry N, Powell A. Big data from the bottom up. Big Data Soc. (2014) 1:205395171453927. doi: 10.1177/2053951714539277</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/2053951714539277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong L, Morrison AM, Zheng C, Li X. Destination image: a consumer-based, big data-enabled approach. TR. (2023) 78:1060–77. doi: 10.1108/TR-04-2022-0190</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/TR-04-2022-0190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghani NA, Hamid S, Targio Hashem IA, Ahmed E. Social media big data analytics: a survey. Comput Hum Behav. (2019) 101:417–28. doi: 10.1016/j.chb.2018.08.039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2018.08.039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee I. Social media analytics for enterprises: typology, methods, and processes. Bus Horiz. (2018) 61:199–210. doi: 10.1016/j.bushor.2017.11.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bushor.2017.11.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Xu M, Zeng W, Tse YK, Chan HK. Exploring customer concerns on service quality under the COVID-19 crisis: a social media analytics study from the retail industry. J Retail Consum Serv. (2023) 70:103157. doi: 10.1016/j.jretconser.2022.103157</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jretconser.2022.103157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stieglitz S, Mirbabaie M, Ross B, Neuberger C. Social media analytics – challenges in topic discovery, data collection, and data preparation. Int J Inf Manag. (2018) 39:156–68. doi: 10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2017.12.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2017.12.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cyberspace Administration of China  (2016). Cybersecurity Law of the People’s republic of China. Available at: http://www.cac.gov.cn/2016-11/07/c_1119867116.htm (Accessed August 1, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glasze G, Cattaruzza A, Douzet F, Dammann F, Bertran M-G, Bômont C, et al. . Contested Spatialities of digital sovereignty. Geopolitics. (2023) 28:919–58. doi: 10.1080/14650045.2022.2050070</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14650045.2022.2050070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su C, Tang W. Data sovereignty and platform neutrality – a comparative study on TikTok’s data policy. Glob Media China. (2023) 8:57–71. doi: 10.1177/20594364231154340</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20594364231154340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>KAWO Guide to China Social Media Platforms  (2023). Available at: https://share-eu1.hsforms.com/1CMfc4j7SQiWeNCE9GwdzmAfbvon?__hstc=14499944.39e4be92856ed27bbc8eead7b38fd437.1722682185678.1722682185678.1722682185678.1&amp;__hssc=14499944.11.1722682185678&amp;__hsfp=1989798536 (Accessed August 1, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell R. (2018). Web scraping with Python: Collecting more data from the modern web. Sebastopol, CA, US: O’Reilly Media.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma S, Gupta P. (2015). “The anatomy of web crawlers.” in International conference on computing, Communication &amp; Automation. Greater Noida, India. IEEE pp. 849–853.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao B. Web scraping In: Schintler LA, McNeely CL, editors. Encyclopedia of big data. Cham: Springer International Publishing; (2017). 1–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M, Bindal A, Gautam R, Bhatia R. Keyword query based focused web crawler. Proc Comp Sci. (2018) 125:584–90. doi: 10.1016/j.procs.2017.12.075</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.procs.2017.12.075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jarmul K, Lawson R. Python web scraping. Second ed. Birmingham: Packt Publishing; (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q, Zhang W, Li J, Mai F, Ma Z. Effect of online review sentiment on product sales: the moderating role of review credibility perception. Comput Hum Behav. (2022) 133:107272. doi: 10.1016/j.chb.2022.107272</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2022.107272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang H, Long R, Chen H, Sun K, Li Q. Exploring public attention about green consumption on Sina Weibo: using text mining and deep learning. Sustain Prod Consump. (2022) 30:674–85. doi: 10.1016/j.spc.2021.12.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.spc.2021.12.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salvatore C, Biffignandi S, Bianchi A. Social media and twitter data quality for new social indicators. Soc Indic Res. (2021) 156:601–30. doi: 10.1007/s11205-020-02296-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11205-020-02296-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim NF, Wang X. Decoding the sentiment dynamics of online retailing customers: time series analysis of social media. Comput Hum Behav. (2019) 96:32–45. doi: 10.1016/j.chb.2019.02.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2019.02.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barde BV, Bainwad AM. (2017). “An overview of topic modeling methods and tools.” in 2017 international conference on intelligent computing and control systems (ICICCS) Madurai. IEEE. pp. 745–750.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blei DM, Ng AY, Jordan MI. Latent Dirichlet allocation In: Dietterich TG, Becker S, Ghahramani Z, editors. Advances in neural information processing systems 14: Cambridge, MA, US: The MIT Press; (2002). 601–608.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofmann T. (2013). Probabilistic Latent Semantic Analysis. doi: 10.48550/ARXIV.1301.6705 (Accessed February 26, 2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grootendorst M. (2024). BERTopic: Neural topic modeling with a class-based TF-IDF procedure. (Accessed February 26, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang H, Long R, Chen H, Sun K, Sun Q, Li Q. Why don’t more people engage in green practices in China? A policy-oriented approach to promoting green transformation in five consumption areas. Environ Impact Assess Rev. (2023) 101:107099. doi: 10.1016/j.eiar.2023.107099</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eiar.2023.107099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh YK, Yi J, Kim J. (2023). What enhances or worsens the user-generated metaverse experience? An application of BERTopic to Roblox user eWOM. INTR.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebeling R, Nobre J, Becker K. A multi-dimensional framework to analyze group behavior based on political polarization. Expert Syst Appl. (2023) 233:120768. doi: 10.1016/j.eswa.2023.120768</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2023.120768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uncovska M, Freitag B, Meister S, Fehring L. Rating analysis and BERTopic modeling of consumer versus regulated mHealth app reviews in Germany. NPJ Digit Med. (2023) 6:115. doi: 10.1038/s41746-023-00862-3, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41746-023-00862-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10285024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37344556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen C, Wang A, Fang Z, Zhang Q. Trend mining of product requirements from online reviews. Chin J Manag Sci. (2021) 29:211–20. doi: 10.16381/j.cnki.issn1003-207x.2018.1508</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16381/j.cnki.issn1003-207x.2018.1508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geary RC, Kendall MG. Rank correlation methods. Econ J. (1949) 59:575. doi: 10.2307/2226580</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2226580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann HB. Nonparametric tests against trend. Econometrica. (1945) 13:245. doi: 10.2307/1907187</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/1907187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danner H, Menapace L. Using online comments to explore consumer beliefs regarding organic food in German-speaking countries and the United States. Food Qual Prefer. (2020) 83:103912. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2020.103912</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2020.103912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DT Business Observer  (2024). Only 9.1% of people are against pre-prepared meals. Available at: https://inf.news/en/news/dc5f84ebfd39a294c86385bade626b4b.html (Accessed July 31, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Jin Y, Liu Y, Li D, Zhang B. Comparing social media data and survey data in assessing the attractiveness of Beijing Olympic Forest Park. Sustain For. (2018) 10:382. doi: 10.3390/su10020382</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su10020382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng G, Chen Z, Zhong S. “We Chinese just want meat!” an analysis of Chinese netizens’ reactions to vegetarian advocacy. Food Qual Prefer. (2024) 115:105128. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2024.105128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2024.105128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Zhou F, Zhou C. The bottleneck restriction and path selection of China’s prepared meals industry from the perspective of high-quality development. Food Ferment Indust. (2024) 50:381–8. doi: 10.13995/j.cnki.11-1802/ts.037771</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13995/j.cnki.11-1802/ts.037771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jing L, Liao Q, Luo W, Jian Q, Zhuang Y. Research on the development status and countermeasures of prepared dishes industry. China Food Safety Magazine. (2024) 6:187–9. doi: 10.16043/j.cnki.cfs.2024.06.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16043/j.cnki.cfs.2024.06.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>