<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39348266</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1474-9726</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Aging cell</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Aging Cell</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sirtuin 3 reinforces acylcarnitine metabolism and maintains thermogenesis in brown adipose tissue of aging mice.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e14332</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e14332</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/acel.14332</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Acylcarnitine (ACar) is a novel fuel source for activating thermogenesis in brown adipose tissue (BAT). However, whether ACar metabolism underlies BAT thermogenesis decline with aging remain unclear. Here, the L-carnitine-treated young and aging mice were used to investigate the effects of activation of ACar metabolism on BAT thermogenesis during aging. We showed that long term L-carnitine feeding, which results in an elevation in circulating ACar levels, failed to improve cold sensitivity of aging mice, which still displayed impaired thermogenesis and ACar metabolism in interscapular BAT (iBAT). The RNA-sequencing was used to identify the key regulator for the response of aging mice to LCar induced activation of ACar metabolism in BAT, and we identified Sirt3 as a key regulator for the response of aging mice to L-carnitine induced activation of ACar metabolism in iBAT. Then the adipose-specific Sirt3 knockout (Sirt3 AKO) mice were used to investigate the role of Sirt3 in ACar metabolism and thermogenesis of BAT and explore the underlying mechanism, and the results showed that Sirt3 AKO mice displayed defective ACar metabolism and thermogenesis in iBAT. Mechanically, Sirt3 regulated ACar metabolism via HIF1α-PPARα signaling pathway to promote iBAT thermogenesis, and knockdown or inhibition of HIF1α ameliorated impaired ACar metabolism and thermogenesis of iBAT in the absence of Sirt3. Collectively, we propose that Sirt3 regulated ACar metabolism is critical in maintaining thermogenesis in BAT of aging mice, which can promote the development of anti-aging intervention strategy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Aging Cell published by Anatomical Society and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Kuiliang</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yucheng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Xuhui Central Hospital of Shanghai, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Yujie</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xue</LastName><ForeName>Lamei</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nie</LastName><ForeName>Chenzhipeng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fan</LastName><ForeName>Mingcong</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qian</LastName><ForeName>Haifeng</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ying</LastName><ForeName>Hao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CAS Key Laboratory of Nutrition, Metabolism and Food Safety, Shanghai Institute of Nutrition and Health, Chinese Academy of Sciences, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9402-1093</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>JUSRP221001</GrantID><Agency>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021YFA1100500</GrantID><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2023YFA1801100</GrantID><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CARS08G19</GrantID><Agency>Earmarked Fund for China Agriculture Reasearch System</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>32071166</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>92357303</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Shanghai Municipal Science and Technology Major Project (GTP project)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>202231</GrantID><Acronym>WT_</Acronym><Agency>Wellcome Trust</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2020QNRC001</GrantID><Agency>Young Elite Scientists Sponsorship Program by CAST</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SHXH202211</GrantID><Agency>General Program of Xuhui Health Commission of Shanghai</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Aging Cell</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101130839</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1474-9718</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sirt3</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acylcarnitine metabolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">aging</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">brown adipose tissue</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thermogenesis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39348266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/acel.14332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abumrad, N. A. (2017). The liver as a hub in thermogenesis. Cell Metabolism, 26, 454–455. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2017.08.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal, S., Loder, S., Brownley, C., Cholok, D., Mangiavini, L., Li, J., Breuler, C., Sung, H. H., Li, S., Ranganathan, K., Peterson, J., Tompkins, R., Herndon, D., Xiao, W., Jumlongras, D., Olsen, B. R., Davis, T. A., Mishina, Y., Schipani, E., &amp; Levi, B. (2016). Inhibition of Hif1alpha prevents both trauma‐induced and genetic heterotopic ossification. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA, 113, E338–E347. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1515397113</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bianco, A. C., &amp; McAninch, E. A. (2013). The role of thyroid hormone and brown adipose tissue in energy homoeostasis. The Lancet Diabetes &amp; Endocrinology, 1(3), 250–258. https://doi.org/10.1016/s2213‐8587(13)70069‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covarrubias, A. J., Perrone, R., Grozio, A., &amp; Verdin, E. (2021). NAD+ metabolism and its roles in cellular processes during ageing. Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology, 22, 119–141. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41580‐020‐00313‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dambrova, M., Makrecka‐Kuka, M., Kuka, J., Vilskersts, R., Nordberg, D., Attwood, M. M., Smesny, S., Sen, Z. D., Guo, A. C., Oler, E., Tian, S., Zheng, J., Wishart, D. S., Liepinsh, E., Schiöth, H. B., &amp; Hakkola, J. (2022). Acylcarnitines: Nomenclature, biomarkers, therapeutic potential, drug targets, and clinical trials. Pharmacological Reviews, 74, 506–551. https://doi.org/10.1124/pharmrev.121.000408</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dzeja, P., &amp; Terzic, A. (2009). Adenylate kinase and AMP signaling networks: Metabolic monitoring, signal communication and body energy sensing. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 10(4), 1729–1772. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms10041729</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finley, L. W., Carracedo, A., Lee, J., Souza, A., Egia, A., Zhang, J., Teruya‐Feldstein, J., Moreira, P. I., Cardoso, S. M., Clish, C. B., Pandolfi, P. P., &amp; Haigis, M. C. (2011). SIRT3 opposes reprogramming of cancer cell metabolism through HIF1alpha destabilization. Cancer Cell, 19, 416–428. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ccr.2011.02.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Floyd, B. J., Wilkerson, E. M., Veling, M. T., Minogue, C. E., Xia, C., Beebe, E. T., Wrobel, R. L., Cho, H., Kremer, L. S., Alston, C. L., Gromek, K. A., Dolan, B. K., Ulbrich, A., Stefely, J. A., Bohl, S. L., Werner, K. M., Jochem, A., Westphall, M. S., Rensvold, J. W., … Pagliarini, D. J. (2016). Mitochondrial protein interaction mapping identifies regulators of respiratory chain function. Molecular Cell, 63(4), 621–632. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2016.06.033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, P., Jiang, Y., Wu, H., Sun, F., Li, Y., He, H., Wang, B., Lu, Z., Hu, Y., Wei, X., Cui, Y., He, C., Wang, L., Zheng, H., Yang, G., Liu, D., Yan, Z., &amp; Zhu, Z. (2020). Inhibition of mitochondrial calcium overload by SIRT3 prevents obesity‐ or age‐related whitening of brown adipose tissue. Diabetes, 69, 165–180. https://doi.org/10.2337/db19‐0526</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gnad, T., Navarro, G., Lahesmaa, M., Reverte‐Salisa, L., Copperi, F., Cordomi, A., Naumann, J., Hochhauser, A., Haufs‐Brusberg, S., Wenzel, D., Suhr, F., Jespersen, N. Z., Scheele, C., Tsvilovskyy, V., Brinkmann, C., Rittweger, J., Dani, C., Kranz, M., Deuther‐Conrad, W., … Pfeifer, A. (2020). Adenosine/A2B receptor signaling ameliorates the effects of aging and counteracts obesity. Cell Metabolism, 32, 56–70. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2020.06.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gohlke, S., Zagoriy, V., Cuadros Inostroza, A., Meret, M., Mancini, C., Japtok, L., Schumacher, F., Kuhlow, D., Graja, A., Stephanowitz, H., Jahnert, M., Krause, E., Wernitz, A., Petzke, K. J., Schurmann, A., Kleuser, B., &amp; Schulz, T. J. (2019). Identification of functional lipid metabolism biomarkers of brown adipose tissue aging. Molecular Metabolism, 24, 1–17. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molmet.2019.03.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomes, P., Viana, S. D., Nunes, S., Rolo, A. P., Palmeira, C. M., &amp; Reis, F. (2020). The yin and yang faces of the mitochondrial deacetylase sirtuin 3 in age‐related disorders. Ageing Research Reviews, 57, 100983. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.arr.2019.100983</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirschey, M. D., Shimazu, T., Goetzman, E., Jing, E., Schwer, B., Lombard, D. B., Grueter, C. A., Harris, C., Biddinger, S., Ilkayeva, O. R., Stevens, R. D., Li, Y., Saha, A. K., Ruderman, N. B., Bain, J. R., Newgard, C. B., Farese, R. V., Jr., Alt, F. W., Kahn, C. R., &amp; Verdin, E. (2010). SIRT3 regulates mitochondrial fatty‐acid oxidation by reversible enzyme deacetylation. Nature, 464, 121–125. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature08778</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, C., Lancaster, C. S., Zuo, Z., Hu, S., Chen, Z., Rubnitz, J. E., Baker, S. D., &amp; Sparreboom, A. (2012). Inhibition of OCTN2‐mediated transport of carnitine by etoposide. Molecular Cancer Therapeutics, 11, 921–929. https://doi.org/10.1158/1535‐7163.MCT‐11‐0980</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Y. L., DeLay, M., Jahangiri, A., Molinaro, A. M., Rose, S. D., Carbonell, W. S., &amp; Aghi, M. K. (2012). Hypoxia‐induced autophagy promotes tumor cell survival and adaptation to antiangiogenic treatment in glioblastoma. Cancer Research, 72, 1773–1783. https://doi.org/10.1158/0008‐5472.CAN‐11‐3831</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jun, J. C., Devera, R., Unnikrishnan, D., Shin, M. K., Bevans‐Fonti, S., Yao, Q., Rathore, A., Younas, H., Halberg, N., Scherer, P. E., &amp; Polotsky, V. Y. (2017). Adipose HIF‐1alpha causes obesity by suppressing brown adipose tissue thermogenesis. Journal of Molecular Medicine, 95, 287–297. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00109‐016‐1480‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, K., Kang, J. E., Park, S. K., Jin, Y., Chung, K. S., Kim, H. M., Lee, K., Kang, M. R., Lee, M. K., Song, K. B., Yang, E. G., Lee, J. J., &amp; Won, M. (2010). LW6, a novel HIF‐1 inhibitor, promotes proteasomal degradation of HIF‐1alpha via upregulation of VHL in a colon cancer cell line. Biochemical Pharmacology, 80, 982–989. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2010.06.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lettieri‐Barbato, D., &amp; Aquilano, K. (2020). Aging and immunometabolic adaptations to thermogenesis. Ageing Research Reviews, 63, 101143. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.arr.2020.101143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, N., &amp; Zhao, H. (2021). Role of carnitine in non‐alcoholic fatty liver disease and other related diseases: An update. Frontiers of Medicine, 8, 689042. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmed.2021.689042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Zhang, D., Wang, X., Yao, X., Ye, C., Zhang, S., Wang, H., Chang, C., Xia, H., Wang, Y. C., Fang, J., Yan, J., &amp; Ying, H. (2015). Hypoxia‐inducible miR‐182 enhances HIF1alpha signaling via targeting PHD2 and FIH1 in prostate cancer. Scientific Reports, 5, 12495. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep12495</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, S., Shen, S., Yan, Y., Sun, C., Lu, Z., Feng, H., Ma, Y., Tang, Z., Yu, J., Wu, Y., Gereben, B., Mohacsik, P., Fekete, C., Feng, X., Yuan, F., Guo, F., Hu, C., Shao, M., Gao, X., … Ying, H. (2022). Triiodothyronine (T3) promotes brown fat hyperplasia via thyroid hormone receptor alpha mediated adipocyte progenitor cell proliferation. Nature Communications, 13, 3394. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐022‐31154‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez‐Otin, C., Blasco, M. A., Partridge, L., Serrano, M., &amp; Kroemer, G. (2013). The hallmarks of aging. Cell, 153, 1194–1217. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.05.039</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, J., Wu, Y., Cen, L., Wang, Z., Jiang, K., Lian, B., &amp; Sun, C. (2023). Cold‐inducible lncRNA266 promotes browning and the thermogenic program in white adipose tissue. EMBO Reports, 24(12), e55467. https://doi.org/10.15252/embr.202255467</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mancini, C., Gohlke, S., Garcia‐Carrizo, F., Zagoriy, V., Stephanowitz, H., &amp; Schulz, T. J. (2021). Identification of biomarkers of brown adipose tissue aging highlights the role of dysfunctional energy and nucleotide metabolism pathways. Scientific Reports, 11, 19928. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐021‐99362‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozaki, K., Sano, T., Tsuji, N., Matsuura, T., &amp; Narama, I. (2011). Carnitine is necessary to maintain the phenotype and function of brown adipose tissue. Laboratory Investigation, 91, 704–710. https://doi.org/10.1038/labinvest.2011.6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereyra, A. S., Rajan, A., Ferreira, C. R., &amp; Ellis, J. M. (2020). Loss of muscle carnitine Palmitoyltransferase 2 prevents diet‐induced obesity and insulin resistance despite long‐chain Acylcarnitine accumulation. Cell Reports, 33(6), 108374. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2020.108374</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Persson, B., &amp; Kallberg, Y. (2013). Classification and nomenclature of the superfamily of short‐chain dehydrogenases/reductases (SDRs). Chemico‐Biological Interactions, 202(1–3), 111–115. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cbi.2012.11.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porter, L. C., Franczyk, M. P., Pietka, T., Yamaguchi, S., Lin, J. B., Sasaki, Y., Verdin, E., Apte, R. S., &amp; Yoshino, J. (2018). NAD+‐dependent deacetylase SIRT3 in adipocytes is dispensable for maintaining normal adipose tissue mitochondrial function and whole body metabolism. American journal of physiology. Endocrinology and Metabolism, 315, E520–E530. https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpendo.00057.2018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rolver, M. G., Holland, L. K. K., Ponniah, M., Prasad, N. S., Yao, J., Schnipper, J., Kramer, S., Elingaard‐Larsen, L., Pedraz‐Cuesta, E., Liu, B., Pardo, L. A., Maeda, K., Sandelin, A., &amp; Pedersen, S. F. (2023). Chronic acidosis rewires cancer cell metabolism through PPARalpha signaling. International Journal of Cancer, 152, 1668–1684. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijc.34404</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebaa, R., Johnson, J., Pileggi, C., Norgren, M., Xuan, J., Sai, Y., Tong, Q., Krystkowiak, I., Bondy‐Chorney, E., Davey, N. E., Krogan, N., Downey, M., &amp; Harper, M. E. (2019). SIRT3 controls brown fat thermogenesis by deacetylation regulation of pathways upstream of UCP1. Molecular Metabolism, 25, 35–49. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molmet.2019.04.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simcox, J., Geoghegan, G., Maschek, J. A., Bensard, C. L., Pasquali, M., Miao, R., Lee, S., Jiang, L., Huck, I., Kershaw, E. E., Donato, A. J., Apte, U., Longo, N., Rutter, J., Schreiber, R., Zechner, R., Cox, J., &amp; Villanueva, C. J. (2017). Global analysis of plasma lipids identifies liver‐derived acylcarnitines as a fuel source for brown fat thermogenesis. Cell Metabolism, 26, 509–522. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2017.08.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, C., Ke, M., Yu, X., Sun, S., Luo, X., Liu, X., Zhou, Y., Wang, Z., Cui, X., Gu, C., &amp; Yang, Y. (2023). GART functions as a novel Methyltransferase in the RUVBL1/β‐catenin signaling pathway to promote tumor Stemness in colorectal cancer. Advanced Science, 10(25), 2301264. https://doi.org/10.1002/advs.202301264</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verkerke, A. R. P., &amp; Kajimura, S. (2021). Oil does more than light the lamp: The multifaceted role of lipids in thermogenic fat. Developmental Cell, 56, 1408–1416. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2021.04.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, A. G., Diamond, M., Waddell, J., &amp; McKenna, M. C. (2019). Effect of acetyl‐l‐carnitine used for protection of neonatal hypoxic‐ischemic brain injury on acute kidney changes in male and female rats. Neurochemical Research, 44, 2405–2412. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11064‐019‐02807‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, G., Song, A., Bae, M., &amp; Wang, Q. A. (2022). Adipose tissue plasticity in aging. Comprehensive Physiology, 12, 4119–4132. https://doi.org/10.1002/cphy.c220005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, H., Sun, Y., Pi, C., Yu, X., Gao, X., Zhang, C., Sun, H., Zhang, H., Shi, Y., &amp; He, X. (2022). Nicotinamide mononucleotide supplementation improves mitochondrial dysfunction and rescues cellular senescence by NAD+/Sirt3 pathway in mesenchymal stem cells. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 23, 14739. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms232314739</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Chen, X., Fan, W., Zhang, X., Zhan, S., Zhong, T., Guo, J., Cao, J., Li, L., Zhang, H., &amp; Wang, L. (2021). Integrated application of metabolomics and RNA‐seq reveals thermogenic regulation in goat brown adipose tissues. FASEB Journal, 35(9), e21868. https://doi.org/10.1096/fj.202100493RR</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen, G., Ringseis, R., &amp; Eder, K. (2010). Mouse OCTN2 is directly regulated by peroxisome proliferator‐activated receptor alpha (PPARalpha) via a PPRE located in the first intron. Biochemical Pharmacology, 79, 768–776. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2009.10.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, P., Chen, C., Zhang, Y., Dzieciatkowska, M., Brown, B. C., Zhang, W., Xie, T., Abdulmalik, O., Song, A., Tong, C., Qi, H., Roach, R., Kellems, R. E., D'Alessandro, A., &amp; Xia, Y. (2022). Erythrocyte transglutaminase‐2 combats hypoxia and chronic kidney disease by promoting oxygen delivery and carnitine homeostasis. Cell Metabolism, 34, 299–316. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2021.12.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., He, Z., Fedorova, J., Logan, C., Bates, L., Davitt, K., Le, V., Murphy, J., Li, M., Wang, M., Lakatta, E. G., Ren, D., &amp; Li, J. (2021). Alterations in mitochondrial dynamics with age‐related Sirtuin1/Sirtuin3 deficiency impair cardiomyocyte contractility. Aging Cell, 20, e13419. https://doi.org/10.1111/acel.13419</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, S., Cao, H., Li, Y., Jing, Y., Liu, S., Ye, C., Wang, H., Yu, S., Peng, C., Hui, L., Wang, Y. C., Zhang, H., Guo, F., Zhai, Q., Wang, H., Huang, R., Zhang, L., Jiang, J., Liu, W., &amp; Ying, H. (2018). Metabolic benefits of inhibition of p38alpha in white adipose tissue in obesity. PLoS Biology, 16, e2004225. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.2004225</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X., Lam, K. S. L., Ye, H., Chung, S. K., Zhou, M., Wang, Y., &amp; Xu, A. (2010). Adipose tissue‐specific inhibition of hypoxia‐inducible factor 1alpha induces obesity and glucose intolerance by impeding energy expenditure in mice. Journal of Biological Chemistry, 285, 32869–32877. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M110.135509</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, Y., Ling, S., Li, J., Zhong, G., Du, R., Li, Y., Wang, Y., Liu, C., Jin, X., Liu, W., Liu, T., Li, Y., Zhao, D., Sun, W., Liu, Z., Liu, Z., Pan, J., Yuan, X., Gao, X., &amp; Li, Y. (2021). 3′ untranslated region of Ckip‐1 inhibits cardiac hypertrophy independently of its cognate protein. European Heart Journal, 42, 3786–3799. https://doi.org/10.1093/eurheartj/ehab503</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>