<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39343838</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2761</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of fish diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Fish Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Use of cardiac cell cultures from salmonids to measure the cardiotoxic effect of environmental pollutants.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e14018</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e14018</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jfd.14018</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Environmental stressors such as micro- and nanosized plastic particles (MNPs) or crude oil have a detrimental effect on aquatic animals; however, the impact upon the cardiovascular system of fish remains relatively under-researched. This study presents a novel approach for investigating the effect of crude oil and MNPs on the cardiac system of fish. We used salmonid larvae and cardiac cell cultures derived from hearts of salmonid fish and exposed them to environmental stressors. Following exposure to plastic particles or crude oil, the larvae exhibited some variation in contraction rate. In contrast, significant alterations in the contraction rate were observed in all cardiac cell cultures. The greatest differences between the control and treatment groups were observed in cardiac cell cultures derived from older brown trout. Following 7 days of exposure to MNPs or crude oil in Atlantic salmon larval hearts or cardiac cell cultures, there were only minor responses noted in mRNA expression of the selected marker genes. These findings show the use of a novel in vitro technique contributing to the existing body of knowledge on the impact of MNPs and crude oil on the cardiovascular system of salmonids and the associated risk.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Fish Diseases published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Krebs</LastName><ForeName>Torben</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-9920-7982</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fish Disease Research Unit, Centre for Infection Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bauer</LastName><ForeName>Julia</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3765-5759</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fish Disease Research Unit, Centre for Infection Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Graff</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Working Group Fish Health and Welfare, Section Aquaculture and Aquatic Resources, Fraunhofer Research Institution for Individualized and Cell-Based Medical Engineering IMTE, Lübeck, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Teich</LastName><ForeName>Lukas</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fish Disease Research Unit, Centre for Infection Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sterneberg</LastName><ForeName>Markus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fish Disease Research Unit, Centre for Infection Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gebert</LastName><ForeName>Marina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Working Group Fish Health and Welfare, Section Aquaculture and Aquatic Resources, Fraunhofer Research Institution for Individualized and Cell-Based Medical Engineering IMTE, Lübeck, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seibel</LastName><ForeName>Henrike</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Working Group Fish Health and Welfare, Section Aquaculture and Aquatic Resources, Fraunhofer Research Institution for Individualized and Cell-Based Medical Engineering IMTE, Lübeck, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seeger</LastName><ForeName>Bettina</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4653-2841</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Food Quality and Food Safety, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Steinhagen</LastName><ForeName>Dieter</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2303-8533</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fish Disease Research Unit, Centre for Infection Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jung-Schroers</LastName><ForeName>Verena</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fish Disease Research Unit, Centre for Infection Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adamek</LastName><ForeName>Mikolaj</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4890-3164</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fish Disease Research Unit, Centre for Infection Medicine, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hannover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Fish Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9881188</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0140-7775</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cell cultures</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">crude oil</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">heart</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microplastic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nanoplastic</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39343838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfd.14018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Akdogan, Z., &amp; Guven, B. (2019). Microplastics in the environment: A critical review of current understanding and identification of future research needs. Environmental Pollution, 254, 113011. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali, A. O., Hohn, C., Allen, P. J., Ford, L., Dail, M. B., Pruett, S., &amp; Petrie‐Hanson, L. (2014). The effects of oil exposure on peripheral blood leukocytes and splenic melano‐macrophage centers of Gulf of Mexico fishes. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 79(1–2), 87–93. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2013.12.036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrady, A. L. (2022). Weathering and fragmentation of plastic debris in the ocean environment. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 180, 113761. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2022.113761</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aronson, R. B., Thatje, S., McClintock, J. B., &amp; Hughes, K. A. (2011). Anthropogenic impacts on marine ecosystems in Antarctica. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences, 1223, 82–107. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1749‐6632.2010.05926.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnes, D. K. A., Galgani, F., Thompson, R. C., &amp; Barlaz, M. (2009). Accumulation and fragmentation of plastic debris in global environments. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society, B: Biological Sciences, 364(1526), 1985–1998. https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2008.0205</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Besseling, E., Redondo‐Hasselerharm, P., Foekema, E. M., &amp; Koelmans, A. A. (2019). Quantifying ecological risks of aquatic micro‐ and nanoplastic. Critical Reviews in Environmental Science and Technology, 49(1), 32–80. https://doi.org/10.1080/10643389.2018.1531688</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borrelle, S. B., Ringma, J., Law, K. L., Monnahan, C. C., Lebreton, L., McGivern, A., Murphy, E., Jambeck, J., Leonard, G. H., Hilleary, M. A., Eriksen, M., Possingham, H. P., De Frond, H., Gerber, L. R., Polidoro, B., Tahir, A., Bernard, M., Mallos, N., Barnes, M., &amp; Rochman, C. M. (2020). Predicted growth in plastic waste exceeds efforts to mitigate plastic pollution. Science, 369(6510), 1515–1518. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aba3656</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Browne, M. A., Galloway, T., &amp; Thompson, R. (2007). Microplastic—An emerging contaminant of potential concern? Integrated Environmental Assessment and Management, 3(4), 559–561. https://doi.org/10.1002/ieam.5630030412</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Liang, Q., Zheng, Y., Lei, Y., Gan, X., Mei, H., Bai, C., Wang, H., Ju, J., Dong, Q., &amp; Song, Y. (2024). Polystyrene nanoplastics induced size‐dependent developmental and neurobehavioral toxicities in embryonic and juvenile zebrafish. Aquatic Toxicology, 267, 106842. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquatox.2024.106842</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Zhang, W., Wan, Z., Li, S., Huang, T., &amp; Fei, Y. (2019). Oil spills from global tankers: Status review and future governance. Journal of Cleaner Production, 227, 20–32. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.04.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Q., Gundlach, M., Yang, S., Jiang, J., Velki, M., Yin, D., &amp; Hollert, H. (2017). Quantitative investigation of the mechanisms of microplastics and nanoplastics toward zebrafish larvae locomotor activity. Science of the Total Environment, 584‐585, 1022–1031. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.01.156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, H., Feng, Y., Duan, Z., Duan, X., Zhao, S., Wang, Y., Gong, Z., &amp; Wang, L. (2021). Toxicities of microplastic fibers and granules on the development of zebrafish embryos and their combined effects with cadmium. Chemosphere, 269, 128677. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128677</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Couillard, C. M., Lee, K., Légaré, B., &amp; King, T. L. (2005). Effect of dispersant on the composition of the water‐accommodated fraction of crude oil and its toxicity to larval marine fish. Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, 24(6), 1496–1504. https://doi.org/10.1897/04‐267r.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, J., Zhang, S., Razanajatovo, R. M., Zou, H., &amp; Zhu, W. (2018). Accumulation, tissue distribution, and biochemical effects of polystyrene microplastics in the freshwater fish red tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus). Environmental Pollution, 238, 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2018.03.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fodrie, F. J., Able, K. W., Galvez, F., Heck, K. L., Jr., Jensen, O. P., López‐Duarte, P. C., Martin, C. W., Turner, R. E., &amp; Whitehead, A. (2014). Integrating organismal and population responses of estuarine fishes in Macondo spill research. Bioscience, 64(9), 778–788. https://doi.org/10.1093/biosci/biu123</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, X., Han, H., Yang, H., Xu, B., Dai, W., Liu, L., He, T., Du, X., &amp; Pei, X. (2024). Nrf2‐mediated ferroptosis of spermatogenic cells involved in male reproductive toxicity induced by polystyrene nanoplastics in mice. Journal of Zhejiang University. Science. B, 25(4), 307–323. https://doi.org/10.1631/jzus.B2300138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gigault, J., Halle, A. T., Baudrimont, M., Pascal, P.‐Y., Gauffre, F., Phi, T.‐L., El Hadri, H., Grassl, B., &amp; Reynaud, S. (2018). Current opinion: What is a nanoplastic? Environmental Pollution, 235, 1030–1034. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2018.01.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hjermann, D. Ø., Melsom, A., Dingsør, G. E., Durant, J. M., Eikeset, A. M., Røed, L. P., Ottersen, G., Storvik, G., &amp; Stenseth, N. C. (2007). Fish and oil in the Lofoten–Barents Sea system: Synoptic review of the effect of oil spills on fish populations. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 339, 283–299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, W., Yang, Y., Tang, S., Yin, H., Yu, X., Yu, Y., &amp; Wei, K. (2024). The combined toxicity of polystyrene nano/micro‐plastics and triphenyl phosphate (TPHP) on HepG2 cells. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 279, 116489. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2024.116489</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hurt, R., O'Reilly, C. M., &amp; Perry, W. L. (2020). Microplastic prevalence in two fish species in two U.S. reservoirs. Limnology and Oceanography Letters, 5(1), 147–153. https://doi.org/10.1002/lol2.10140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incardona, J. P., &amp; Scholz, N. L. (2016). The influence of heart developmental anatomy on cardiotoxicity‐based adverse outcome pathways in fish. Aquatic Toxicology, 177, 515–525.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakubowska, M., Białowąs, M., Stankevičiūtė, M., Chomiczewska, A., Jonko‐Sobuś, K., Pažusienė, J., Hallmann, A., Bučaitė, A., &amp; Urban‐Malinga, B. (2022). Effects of different types of primary microplastics on early life stages of rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss). Science of the Total Environment, 808, 151909. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151909</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakubowska, M., Białowąs, M., Stankevičiūtė, M., Chomiczewska, A., Pažusienė, J., Jonko‐Sobuś, K., Hallmann, A., &amp; Urban‐Malinga, B. (2020). Effects of chronic exposure to microplastics of different polymer types on early life stages of sea trout Salmo trutta. Science of the Total Environment, 740, 139922. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.139922</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin, F., Wang, Y., Yu, F., Liu, X., Zhang, M., Li, Z., Yao, Z., Cong, Y., &amp; Wang, J. (2023). Acute and chronic effects of crude oil water‐accommodated fractions on the early life stages of marine medaka (Oryzias melastigma, McClelland, 1839). Toxics, 11(3), 236. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxics11030236</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnston, E. F., &amp; Gillis, T. E. (2018). Transforming growth factor‐β1 induces differentiation of rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) cardiac fibroblasts into myofibroblasts. Journal of Experimental Biology, 221(24), jeb189167. https://doi.org/10.1242/jeb.189167</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keen, A. N., Klaiman, J. M., Shiels, H. A., &amp; Gillis, T. E. (2017). Temperature‐induced cardiac remodelling in fish. Journal of Experimental Biology, 220(2), 147–160. https://doi.org/10.1242/jeb.128496</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, Y.‐N., Yoon, J.‐H., &amp; Kim, K.‐H. J. (2020). Microplastic contamination in soil environment – A review. Soil Science Annual, 71(4), 300–308. https://doi.org/10.37501/soilsa/131646</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamberto, F., Shashikadze, B., Elkhateib, R., Lombardo, S. D., Horánszky, A., Balogh, A., Kistamás, K., Zana, M., Menche, J., Fröhlich, T., &amp; Dinnyés, A. (2023). Low‐dose bisphenol a exposure alters the functionality and cellular environment in a human cardiomyocyte model. Environmental Pollution, 335, 122359. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2023.122359</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei, L., Wu, S., Lu, S., Liu, M., Song, Y., Fu, Z., Shi, H., Raley‐Susman, K. M., &amp; He, D. (2018). Microplastic particles cause intestinal damage and other adverse effects in zebrafish Danio rerio and nematode Caenorhabditis elegans. Sci Total Environ, 619‐620, 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.11.103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Weng, H., Liu, S., Li, F., Xu, K., Wen, S., Chen, X., Li, C., Nie, Y., Liao, B., Wu, J., Kantawong, F., Xie, X., Yu, F., &amp; Li, G. (2024). Embryonic exposure of polystyrene nanoplastics affects cardiac development. Science of the Total Environment, 906, 167406. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.167406</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, J., Wang, W., Xu, W., Zhang, C., Zhang, C., Tao, L., Li, Z., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2022). Induction of developmental toxicity and cardiotoxicity in zebrafish embryos by Emamectin benzoate through oxidative stress. Science of the Total Environment, 825, 154040.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, J., Wu, J., Gong, L., Cheng, Y., Yuan, Q., &amp; He, Y. (2022). Combined toxicity of polystyrene microplastics and sulfamethoxazole on zebrafish embryos. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 29, 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malafaia, G., de Souza, A. M., Pereira, A. C., Gonçalves, S., da Costa Araújo, A. P., Ribeiro, R. X., &amp; Rocha, T. L. (2020). Developmental toxicity in zebrafish exposed to polyethylene microplastics under static and semi‐static aquatic systems. Science of the Total Environment, 700, 134867. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134867</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez‐Gómez, C., Campillo, J. A., Benedicto, J., Fernández, B., Valdés, J., García, I., &amp; Sánchez, F. (2006). Monitoring biomarkers in fish (Lepidorhombus boscii and Callionymus lyra) from the northern Iberian shelf after the prestige oil spill. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 53(5), 305–314. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2006.03.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meador, J. P., &amp; Nahrgang, J. (2019). Characterizing crude oil toxicity to early‐life stage fish based on a complex mixture: Are we making unsupported assumptions? Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 53(19), 11080–11092. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.9b02889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendoza, L. M. R., &amp; Balcer, M. (2019). Microplastics in freshwater environments: A review of quantification assessment. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 113, 402–408.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller, C. (2021). Not as bad as it seems? A literature review on the case of microplastic uptake in fish. Frontiers in Marine Science, 8, 672768. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2021.672768</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murawski, S. A., Hollander, D. J., Gilbert, S., &amp; Gracia, A. (2020). Deepwater oil and gas production in the Gulf of Mexico and related global trends. In S. A. Murawski, C. H. Ainsworth, S. Gilbert, D. J. Hollander, C. B. Paris, M. Schlüter, &amp; D. L. Wetzel (Eds.), Scenarios and responses to future deep oil spills: Fighting the next war (pp. 16–32). Springer International Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nahrgang, J., Granlund, C., Bender, M. L., Sørensen, L., Greenacre, M., &amp; Frantzen, M. (2023). No observed developmental effects in early life stages of capelin (Mallotus villosus) exposed to a water‐soluble fraction of crude oil during embryonic development. Journal of Toxicology and Environmental Health. Part A, 86(12), 404–419. https://doi.org/10.1080/15287394.2023.2209115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson, D., Stieglitz, J. D., Cox, G. K., Heuer, R. M., Benetti, D. D., Grosell, M., &amp; Crossley, D. A. (2017). Cardio‐respiratory function during exercise in the cobia, Rachycentron canadum: The impact of crude oil exposure. Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part C: Toxicology &amp; Pharmacology, 201, 58–65. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cbpc.2017.08.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, T.‐J., Lee, S.‐H., Lee, M.‐S., Lee, J.‐K., Lee, S.‐H., &amp; Zoh, K.‐D. (2020). Occurrence of microplastics in the Han River and riverine fish in South Korea. Science of the Total Environment, 708, 134535. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134535</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker, B., Andreou, D., Green, I. D., &amp; Britton, J. R. (2021). Microplastics in freshwater fishes: Occurrence, impacts and future perspectives. Fish and Fisheries, 22(3), 467–488. https://doi.org/10.1111/faf.12528</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pitt, J. A., Kozal, J. S., Jayasundara, N., Massarsky, A., Trevisan, R., Geitner, N., Wiesner, M., Levin, E. D., &amp; Di Giulio, R. T. (2018). Uptake, tissue distribution, and toxicity of polystyrene nanoparticles in developing zebrafish (Danio rerio). Aquatic Toxicology, 194, 185–194. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquatox.2017.11.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pitt, J. A., Trevisan, R., Massarsky, A., Kozal, J. S., Levin, E. D., &amp; Di Giulio, R. T. (2018). Maternal transfer of nanoplastics to offspring in zebrafish (Danio rerio): A case study with nanopolystyrene. Science of the Total Environment, 643, 324–334. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.06.186</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>PlasticsEurope. (2023). Plastics—The the fast Facts 2023. https://plasticseurope.org/knowledge‐hub/plastics‐the‐fast‐facts‐2023/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prata, J. C., Venâncio, C., Girão, A. V., da Costa, J. P., Lopes, I., Duarte, A. C., &amp; Rocha‐Santos, T. (2022). Effects of virgin and weathered polystyrene and polypropylene microplastics on Raphidocelis subcapitata and embryos of Danio rerio under environmental concentrations. Science of the Total Environment, 816, 151642. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151642</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao, R., Sheng, C., Lu, Y., Zhang, Y., Ren, H., &amp; Lemos, B. (2019). Microplastics induce intestinal inflammation, oxidative stress, and disorders of metabolome and microbiome in zebrafish. Science of the Total Environment, 662, 246–253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramachandran, S. D., Hodson, P. V., Khan, C. W., &amp; Lee, K. (2004). Oil dispersant increases PAH uptake by fish exposed to crude oil. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 59(3), 300–308. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2003.08.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribeiro, F., O'Brien, J. W., Galloway, T., &amp; Thomas, K. V. (2019). Accumulation and fate of nano‐ and micro‐plastics and associated contaminants in organisms. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 111, 139–147. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2018.12.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sander, V., Suñe, G., Jopling, C., Morera, C., &amp; Izpisua Belmonte, J. C. (2013). Isolation and in vitro culture of primary cardiomyocytes from adult zebrafish hearts. Nature Protocols, 8(4), 800–809. https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2013.041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanni, S., Björkblom, C., Jonsson, H., Godal, B. F., Liewenborg, B., Lyng, E., &amp; Pampanin, D. M. (2017). I: Biomarker quantification in fish exposed to crude oil as input to species sensitivity distributions and threshold values for environmental monitoring. Marine Environmental Research, 125, 10–24. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marenvres.2016.12.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, A. L., Rodrigues, L. C., Rodrigues, C. C., Cirqueira, F., Malafaia, G., &amp; Rocha, T. L. (2024). Polystyrene nanoplastics induce developmental impairments and vasotoxicity in zebrafish (Danio rerio). Journal of Hazardous Materials, 464, 132880. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2023.132880</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schein, A., Scott, J. A., Mos, L., &amp; Hodson, P. V. (2009). Oil dispersion increases the apparent bioavailability and toxicity of diesel to rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss). Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, 28(3), 595–602. https://doi.org/10.1897/08‐315.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sørhus, E., Donald, C. E., da Silva, D., Thorsen, A., Karlsen, Ø., &amp; Meier, S. (2021). Untangling mechanisms of crude oil toxicity: Linking gene expression, morphology and PAHs at two developmental stages in a cold‐water fish. Science of the Total Environment, 757, 143896. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143896</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, M., Ding, R., Ma, Y., Sun, Q., Ren, X., Sun, Z., &amp; Duan, J. (2021). Cardiovascular toxicity assessment of polyethylene nanoplastics on developing zebrafish embryos. Chemosphere, 282, 131124. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.131124</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Y., Zhang, G., He, Z., Wang, Y., Cui, J., &amp; Li, Y. (2016). Effects of copper oxide nanoparticles on developing zebrafish embryos and larvae. International Journal of Nanomedicine, 11, 905–918.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Y., Zhao, X., Sui, Q., Sun, X., Zhu, L., Booth, A. M., Chen, B., Qu, K., &amp; Xia, B. (2024). Polystyrene nanoplastics affected the nutritional quality of Chlamys farreri through disturbing the function of gills and physiological metabolism: Comparison with microplastics. Science of the Total Environment, 910, 168457. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.168457</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson, R. (2017). Future of the sea: Plastic pollution. Foresight, Government Office for Science.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres‐Ruiz, M., De la Vieja, A., de Alba Gonzalez, M., Esteban Lopez, M., Castaño Calvo, A., &amp; Cañas Portilla, A. I. (2021). Toxicity of nanoplastics for zebrafish embryos, what we know and where to go next. Science of the Total Environment, 797, 149125. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.149125</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veneman, W. J., Spaink, H. P., Brun, N. R., Bosker, T., &amp; Vijver, M. G. (2017). Pathway analysis of systemic transcriptome responses to injected polystyrene particles in zebrafish larvae. Aquatic Toxicology, 190, 112–120. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquatox.2017.06.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, K., Du, Y., Li, P., Guan, C., Zhou, M., Wu, L., Liu, Z., &amp; Huang, Z. (2024). Nanoplastics causes heart aging/myocardial cell senescence through the Ca2+/mtDNA/cGAS‐STING signaling cascade. Journal of Nanobiotechnology, 22(1), 96. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12951‐024‐02375‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Wang, Q., Xiao, G., Chen, G., Han, L., &amp; Hu, T. (2020). Adverse effect of cylindrospermopsin on embryonic development in zebrafish (Danio rerio). Chemosphere, 241, 125060.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Q., Chen, G., Tian, L., Kong, C., Gao, D., Chen, Y., Junaid, M., &amp; Wang, J. (2023). Neuro‐ and hepato‐toxicity of polystyrene nanoplastics and polybrominated diphenyl ethers on early life stages of zebrafish. Science of the Total Environment, 857, 159567. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159567</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, H., Guo, J., Yao, Y., &amp; Xu, S. (2022). Polystyrene nanoplastics induced cardiomyocyte apoptosis and myocardial inflammation in carp by promoting ROS production. Fish &amp; Shellfish Immunology, 125, 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsi.2022.04.048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, Y., Li, L., Tang, L., Peijnenburg, W., Zhang, H., Xie, D., Geng, R., Zheng, T., Bi, L., Wei, X., Chae, H. J., Wang, L., Zhao, L., Li, B., &amp; Zheng, Q. (2024). Ototoxicity of polystyrene nanoplastics in mice, HEI‐OC1 cells and zebrafish. Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience, 17, 1345536. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnmol.2024.1345536</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, H., Xiong, H., Mi, K., Xue, W., Wei, W., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2020). Toxicity comparison of nano‐sized and micron‐sized microplastics to goldfish Carassius auratus larvae. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 388, 122058.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, W., Gao, P., Li, H., Huang, J., Zhang, Y., Ding, H., &amp; Zhang, W. (2021). Mechanism of the inhibition and detoxification effects of the interaction between nanoplastics and microalgae Chlorella pyrenoidosa. Science of the Total Environment, 783, 146919. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146919</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Q., Wang, F., Xu, S., Cui, J., Li, K., Shiwen, X., &amp; Guo, M.‐Y. (2023). Polystyrene microplastics induce myocardial inflammation and cell death via the TLR4/NF‐κB pathway in carp. Fish &amp; Shellfish Immunology, 135, 108690. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsi.2023.108690</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, R., Zhou, D., Yang, S., Shi, Z., Pan, H., Jin, Q., &amp; Ding, Z. (2023). Neurotoxicity of polystyrene nanoplastics with different particle sizes at environment‐related concentrations on early zebrafish embryos. Science of the Total Environment, 872, 162096. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162096</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>