<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39345875</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1617-9625</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>22</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Tobacco induced diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Tob Induc Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Examining longitudinal associations between initial perceptions and experiences with electronic nicotine delivery system (ENDS) use and use patterns among adults who smoke and recently initiated ENDS.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.18332/tid/193009</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Limited data exist on factors associated with concurrent use patterns of electronic nicotine delivery systems (ENDS) and cigarettes. We examined longitudinally perceptions and experiences with ENDS in relationship to concurrent use patterns among established, recent smokers who recently initiated ENDS.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Participant recruitment took place using paid digital advertisements on social media. Between December 2020 and October 2021, 303 adults aged ≥21 years from across the US who currently or recently smoked and had initiated ENDS use within the past 30 days or reinitiated ENDS use after more than one year of non-use were surveyed. Multinomial logistic regressions were conducted to analyze association between the outcome of current use pattern at follow-up at 1 month [rejectors (discontinued ENDS, continued smoking), primary smokers (concurrent users, mostly smoke), dual user (similar smoking and ENDS use), primary vapers (concurrent users, mostly vape), and switchers (discontinued smoking, continued using ENDS) or quitters (discontinued both smoking and ENDS] and perceptions of and experiences with ENDS predictors at baseline.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">At follow-up at 1 to 2 months after initiating ENDS, 20% were rejectors, 31% were primary smokers, 13% were dual users, 19% were primary vapers, and 17% were switchers/quitters. Perceiving ENDS as less harmful than smoking or being uncertain and as equally or more enjoyable smoking, experiencing a lot or complete reduction in cravings to smoking and in irritability with ENDS use, liking the taste of ENDS, and being satisfied with vaping were associated with higher odds of quitting smoking compared to rejecting ENDS or mostly smoking at follow-up at 1 month.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Findings highlight the importance of initial ENDS perceptions and experiences when examining tobacco outcomes and potentially for developing policies and interventions targeting smoking cessation. ENDS initiators are differentiating into distinct use patterns based on these factors within a short period of time.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Mavreles Ogrodnick M. et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Ogrodnick</LastName><ForeName>Michelle Mavreles</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, School of Public Health, Georgia State University, Atlanta, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Kute</LastName><ForeName>Nikita G</ForeName><Initials>NG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, School of Public Health, Georgia State University, Atlanta, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Do</LastName><ForeName>Vuong Van</ForeName><Initials>VV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Tobacco Control Research and Education, University of California, San Francisco, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wiley</LastName><ForeName>Paige</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, School of Public Health, Georgia State University, Atlanta, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Henderson</LastName><ForeName>Katherine</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, School of Public Health, Georgia State University, Atlanta, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Spears</LastName><ForeName>Claire A</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Policy and Behavioral Sciences, School of Public Health, Georgia State University, Atlanta, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pechacek</LastName><ForeName>Terry F</ForeName><Initials>TF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Policy and Behavioral Sciences, School of Public Health, Georgia State University, Atlanta, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weaver</LastName><ForeName>Scott R</ForeName><Initials>SR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, School of Public Health, Georgia State University, Atlanta, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Greece</Country><MedlineTA>Tob Induc Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101201591</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1617-9625</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dual users</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">electronic nicotine delivery systems (ENDS)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tobacco regulatory science</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tobacco users</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have completed and submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest. The authors declare that they have no competing interests, financial or otherwise, related to the current work. M. Mavreles Ogrodnick, N.G. Kute, K. Henderson, C.A. Spears, T.F. Pechacek and S.R. Weaver report that since the initial planning of the work, they have received support from the National Cancer Institute of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Center for Tobacco Products (CTP) under Award Number R01CA235719. M. Mavreles Ogrodnick reports that Georgia State University received the grant funds from NIH/FDA which supported this work. N.G. Kute reports Georgia State University received the grant funds from NIH/ FDA which supported her travel and attendance to SRNT 2023 annual meeting to present the poster of this work. K. Henderson reports that Georgia State University received the grant funds from NIH/FDA which supported this work via a salary. C.A. Spears reports that in the past 36 months she has received grants or contracts from the National Cancer Institute, National Institute of Mental Health, Georgia Center for Oncology Research &amp; Education, National Center for Complementary &amp; Integrative Health, Fogarty International Center. She has also received consulting fees from the Stephenson Cancer Center at the University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center, and has participated on Data and Safety Monitoring Boards for NIH-funded studies (National Center for Complementary &amp; Integrative Health and National Institute on Drug Abuse), and is a Member of Community Advisory Board for the Center for Urban Research, Development, Sustainability, and Evaluation Initiative, DeKalb County Board of Health. Additionally, she has been a Fellow of the Society of Behavioral Medicine. T.F. Pechacek reports providing advice on legal cases involving electronic cigarettes as a paid expert, in the past 36 months. S.R. Weaver reports that in the past 36 months he has received grants or contracts from the National Cancer Institute, National Institute of Drug Abuse, Food &amp; Drug Administration, Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention (CDC), CDC Foundation, Georgia Family Connection Partnership, National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (via Underwriters Laboratory), Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, Fulton County Board of Health. Additionally, he declares receiving payment from the Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention (US) and New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene for teaching, scientific writing, and workshops.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39345875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11427937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18332/tid/193009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">TID-22-164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Coleman SRM, Piper ME, Byron MJ, Bold KW. Dual use of combustible cigarettes and e-cigarettes: a narrative review of current evidence. Curr Addict Rep. 2022;9(4):353-362. doi:10.1007/s40429-022-00448-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40429-022-00448-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9718538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36467719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owusu D, Huang J, Weaver SR, et al. . Patterns and trends of dual use of e-cigarettes and cigarettes among U.S. adults, 2015-2018. Prev Med Rep. 2019;16:101009. doi:10.1016/j.pmedr.2019.101009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2019.101009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6861646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31763161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cornelius ME, Loretan CG, Jamal A, et al. . Tobacco product use among adults - United States, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2023;72(18):475-483. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7218a1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7218a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10168602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37141154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson L, Hoek J, Blank ML, Richards R, Ling P, Popova L. Dual use of electronic nicotine delivery systems (ENDS) and smoked tobacco: a qualitative analysis. Tob Control. 2019;28(1):13-19. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2017-054070</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2017-054070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6317506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29419488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temourian AA, Song AV, Halliday DM, Gonzalez M, Epperson AE. Why do smokers use e-cigarettes? A study on reasons among dual users. Prev Med Rep. 2022;29:101924. doi:10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.101924</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.101924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9334340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35911573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gravely S, Yong HH, Reid JL, et al. . An examination of quitting smoking as a reason for vaping by the type of nicotine vaping device used most often among adults who smoke and vape: findings from the Canada, England and the United States 2020 ITC Smoking and Vaping Survey. Prev Med Rep. 2023;33:102201. doi:10.1016/j.pmedr.2023.102201</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2023.102201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10201827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37223550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartmann-Boyce J, McRobbie H, Lindson N, et al. . Electronic cigarettes for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2021;4(4):CD010216. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD010216.pub5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD010216.pub5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8092424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33913154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalkhoran S, Glantz SA. E-cigarettes and smoking cessation in real-world and clinical settings: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Respir Med. 2016;4(2):116-128. doi:10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00521-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00521-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4752870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26776875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierce JP, Chen R, Kealey S, et al. . Incidence of cigarette smoking relapse among individuals who switched to e-cigarettes or other tobacco products. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(10):e2128810. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.28810</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.28810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8527352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34665239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pechacek TF. Can e-cigarettes help adults who smoke successfully quit all combusted tobacco products? JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(10):e2130924. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.30924</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.30924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9231645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34665244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai H, Benowitz NL, Achutan C, Farazi PA, Degarege A, Khan AS. Exposure to toxicants associated with use and transitions between cigarettes, e-cigarettes, and no tobacco. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5(2):e2147891. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.47891</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.47891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8832174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35142830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisinger C, Rasmussen SKB. The health effects of real-world dual use of electronic and conventional cigarettes versus the health effects of exclusive smoking of conventional cigarettes: a systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(20):13687. doi:10.3390/ijerph192013687</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph192013687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9603628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36294263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention . E-cigarette use among U.S. Adults. May
15, 2024. Accessed September 7, 2024. https://www.cdc.gov/tobacco/e-cigarettes/adults.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhoades DA, Comiford AL, Dvorak JD, et al. . Vaping patterns, nicotine dependence and reasons for vaping among American Indian dual users of cigarettes and electronic cigarettes. BMC Public Health. 2019;19(1):1211. doi:10.1186/s12889-019-7523-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-019-7523-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6721166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31477072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piper ME, Baker TB, Benowitz NL, Jorenby DE. Changes in use patterns over 1 year among smokers and dual users of combustible and electronic cigarettes. Nicotine Tob Res. 2020;22(5):672-680. doi:10.1093/ntr/ntz065</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntz065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7457322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31058284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gravely S, Meng G, Cummings KM, et al. . Changes in smoking and vaping over 18 months among smokers and recent ex-smokers: longitudinal findings from the 2016 and 2018 ITC Four Country smoking and vaping surveys. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(19):7084. doi:10.3390/ijerph17197084</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17197084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7579485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32992667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedeker D, Brooks J, Diviak K, Jao N, Mermelstein RJ. Pleasure and satisfaction as predictors of future cigarette and e-cigarette use: a novel two-stage modeling approach. Nicotine Tob Res; 2024. doi:10.1093/ntr/ntae121</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntae121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38775349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kong G, Morean ME, Cavallo DA, Camenga DR, Krishnan-Sarin S. Reasons for electronic cigarette experimentation and discontinuation among adolescents and young adults. Nicotine Tob Res. 2015;17(7):847-854. doi:10.1093/ntr/ntu257</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntu257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4674436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25481917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoek J, Thrul J, Ling P. Qualitative analysis of young adult ENDS users’ expectations and experiences. BMJ Open. 2017;7(3):e014990. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-014990</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-014990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5353280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28270392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans AT, Henderson KC, Geier A, et al. . What motivates smokers to switch to ENDS? A qualitative study of perceptions and use. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(23):8865. doi:10.3390/ijerph17238865</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17238865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7729446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33260570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartmann-Boyce J, McRobbie H, Butler AR, et al. . Electronic cigarettes for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2021;9(9):CD010216. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD010216.pub6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD010216.pub6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8438601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34519354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim S, Shiffman S, Sembower MA. US adult smokers’ perceived relative risk on ENDS and its effects on their transitions between cigarettes and ENDS. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1):1771. doi:10.1186/s12889-022-14168-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-14168-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9484256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36123722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malas M, van der Tempel J, Schwartz R, et al. . Electronic cigarettes for smoking cessation: a systematic review. Nicotine Tob Res. 2016;18(10):1926-1936. doi:10.1093/ntr/ntw119</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntw119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27113014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SH, Han DH, Seo DC. Toward a better understanding of adult dual use of cigarettes and e-cigarettes based on use intensity and reasons for dual use. Addict Behav. 2023;137:107517. doi:10.1016/j.addbeh.2022.107517</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2022.107517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36228363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gravely S, Meng G, Hammond D, et al. . Differences in cigarette smoking quit attempts and cessation between adults who did and did not take up nicotine vaping: Findings from the ITC four country smoking and vaping surveys. Addict Behav. 2022;132:107339. doi:10.1016/j.addbeh.2022.107339</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2022.107339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9202449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35605409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warner KE, Kiessling KA, Douglas CE, Liber AC. A proposed policy agenda for electronic cigarettes in the US: product, price, place, and promotion. Health Aff (Millwood). 2022;41(9):1299-1306. doi:10.1377/hlthaff.2022.00187</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2022.00187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36067433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pechacek TF, Nayak P, Gregory KR, Weaver SR, Eriksen MP. The potential that Electronic Nicotine Delivery Systems can be a disruptive technology: results from a national survey. Nicotine Tob Res. 2016;18(10):1989-1997. doi:10.1093/ntr/ntw102</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntw102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5016845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27142201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borland R, Murray K, Gravely S, et al. . A new classification system for describing concurrent use of nicotine vaping products alongside cigarettes (so-called ‘dual use’): findings from the ITC-4 Country Smoking and Vaping wave 1 Survey. Addiction. 2019;114(suppl 1):24-34. doi:10.1111/add.14570</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/add.14570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6669110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30702175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutton SK, Brandon KO, Harrell PT, et al. . Identifying prospective subpopulations of combustible and electronic cigarette dual users in the United States via finite mixture modeling. Addiction. 2022;117(9):2493-2503. doi:10.1111/add.15906</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/add.15906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9795793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35491736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weaver SR, Henderson KC, Pechacek TF. Data from: Adult Consumers of Tobacco Study 1: longitudinal study data. Public Health Datasets; 2024. doi:10.57709/ed4q-d040</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.57709/ed4q-d040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welsch SK, Smith SS, Wetter DW, Jorenby DE, Fiore MC, Baker TB. Development and validation of the Wisconsin Smoking Withdrawal Scale. Exp Clin Psychopharmacol. 1999;7(4):354-361. doi:10.1037/1064-1297.7.4.354</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/1064-1297.7.4.354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10609970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Green JG, Gruber MJ, et al. . Screening for serious mental illness in the general population with the K6 screening scale: results from the WHO World Mental Health (WMH) survey initiative. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2010;19(suppl 1):4-22. doi:10.1002/mpr.310</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mpr.310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3659799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20527002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rass O, Pacek LR, Johnson PS, Johnson MW. Characterizing use patterns and perceptions of relative harm in dual users of electronic and tobacco cigarettes. Exp Clin Psychopharmacol. 2015;23(6):494-503. doi:10.1037/pha0000050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/pha0000050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4658305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26389638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Public Health Service Office of the Surgeon General; National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion (US) Office on Smoking and Health . Smoking Cessation: A Report of the Surgeon General. US Department of Health and Human Services; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Killen JD, Fortmann SP. Craving is associated with smoking relapse: findings from three prospective studies. Exp Clin Psychopharmacol. 1997;5(2):137-142. doi:10.1037/1064-1297.5.2.137</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/1064-1297.5.2.137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9234050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>East K, Vu G, Sun T, et al. . Harm perceptions across vaping product features: an on-line cross-sectional survey of adults who smoke and/or vape in the United Kingdom. Addiction. doi:10.1111/add.16572</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/add.16572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38839597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>