<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39345735</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1976-8257</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>40</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Toxicological research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Toxicol Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Application potential of albendazole as an aquatic animal drug based on its safety, efficacy, and residue profiles.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>519</StartPage><EndPage>531</EndPage><MedlinePgn>519-531</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s43188-024-00244-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The number of available drugs for treating aquatic animals is insufficient, given the occurrence of a variety of parasites and difficulties in developing appropriate treatments, such as vaccines or immunostimulants. Consequently, repurposing livestock drugs for treating aquatic animals is a viable alternative. Several studies have demonstrated that albendazole (ABZ) is a good anthelmintic for humans and animals such as ruminants, poultry, and honeybees. Therefore, we investigated the toxicological studies, metabolic and residue depletion studies, and efficacy trials of ABZ in aquatic animals to identify its application potential as a drug for aquatic animals. ABZ was depleted within 24 h in the muscle tissues of hybrid striped bass, rainbow trout, and tilapia. In muscle tissue with adhering skin obtained from tilapia and largemouth bass, a significant quantity of the amino-sulfone metabolite of ABZ (ABZ-SO<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>) was present, while no ABZ-SO<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> was detected in hybrid striped bass, channel catfish, and patinga. Fish exposed only to high doses of ABZ showed reduced red blood cell counts and hemoglobin levels and increased lymphocytes. Such signs of toxicity have also been observed in human patients and animal studies. At a dose of 100 mg/L, ABZ showed 100% efficacy in eels. In addition, albendazole sulfoxide (ABZSO) demonstrated efficacies of 96.1% and 100% in pirapatinga and ray-finned fish, respectively, at a dose 500 mg/L. ABZ was also highly effective in treating an intracellular parasite <i>E. hepatopenaei</i> in white shrimp. The application of ABZ in aquatic animals under the low-dose and short-term conditions is considered a reasonable solution to manage parasite infections. The types and residual periods of degradation products differed among fish species, suggesting dissimilar metabolic pathways. With a high demand for new alternative veterinary drugs in aquaculture by fish farmers, this review offers important evidence for considering the use of ABZ in Korean farmed fish, taking food safety issues into account.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) under exclusive licence to Korean Society of Toxicology 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Min Ji</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3952-033X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide and Veterinary Drug Residues Division, National Institute of Food and Drug Safety Evaluation, Ministry of Food and Drug Safety, Osong, Chungcheongbuk-do 28159 Republic of Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.467691.b</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 0675</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Ji Young</ForeName><Initials>JY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6330-6731</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide and Veterinary Drug Residues Division, National Institute of Food and Drug Safety Evaluation, Ministry of Food and Drug Safety, Osong, Chungcheongbuk-do 28159 Republic of Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.467691.b</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 0675</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shin</LastName><ForeName>Dong Woo</ForeName><Initials>DW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-4867-8953</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide and Veterinary Drug Residues Division, National Institute of Food and Drug Safety Evaluation, Ministry of Food and Drug Safety, Osong, Chungcheongbuk-do 28159 Republic of Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.467691.b</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 0675</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eom</LastName><ForeName>Mi Ok</ForeName><Initials>MO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesticide and Veterinary Drug Residues Division, National Institute of Food and Drug Safety Evaluation, Ministry of Food and Drug Safety, Osong, Chungcheongbuk-do 28159 Republic of Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.467691.b</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 0675</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Singapore</Country><MedlineTA>Toxicol Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101483324</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1976-8257</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Albendazole</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anthelmintic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aquatic animal drug</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Efficacy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Safety</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestThe authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39345735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11436531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43188-024-00244-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>OECD, FAO (2023) OECD-FAO agricultural outlook 2023–2032. OCED iLibarary. https://www.fao.org/documents/card/en/c/cc6361en. Accessed 6 July 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Y, Hu X, Miao L, Chen J (2022) Current status and development prospects of aquatic vaccines. Front Immunol 13:1040336. 10.3389/fimmu.2022.1040336</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9684733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36439092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mondal H, Thomas J (2022) A review on the recent advances and application of vaccines against fish pathogens in aquaculture. Aquacult Int 30:1971–2000. 10.1007/s10499-022-00884-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9059915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35528247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowak BF (2007) Parasitic diseases in marine cage culture–an example of experimental evolution of parasites? Int J Parasitol 37:581–588. 10.1016/j.ijpara.2007.01.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17316650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shivam S, El-Matbouli M, Kumar G (2021) Development of fish parasite vaccines in the OMICs Era: progress and opportunities. Vaccines 9:179. 10.3390/vaccines9020179</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7923790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33672552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karvonen A, Rintamäki P, Jokela J, Valtonen ET (2010) Increasing water temperature and disease risks in aquatic systems: climate change increases the risk of some, but not all, diseases. Int J Parasitol 40:1483–1488. 10.1016/j.ijpara.2010.04.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20580904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulkkinen K, Ketola T, Laakso J, Mappes J, Sundberg LR (2022) Rich resource environment of fish farms facilitates phenotypic variation and virulence in an opportunistic fish pathogen. Evol Appl 15:417–428. 10.1111/eva.13355</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8965373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35386393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto N, Naik MG, Naveen Kumar BT, Shankar KM, Rakesh K, Abhiman PB, Sathish RP, Ramesh KS (2023) Oxytetracycline efficacy and preliminary establishment of pharmacokinetic residues in tropical fish, Catla catla (Hamilton, 1822). Aquaculture 571:739481. 10.1016/j.aquaculture.2023.739481</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The European Agency for the Evaluation of Medicinal Products (EMEA) (2004) Albendazole (summary report 3). EMEA/MRL/865/03-FINAL. The European Medicines Agency, London. https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/mrl-report/albendazole-summary-report-3-committee-veterinary-medicinal-products_en.pdf. Accessed June 2004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh B, Rummel N, Gieseker C, Serfling S, Reimschuessel R (2003) Metabolism and residue depletion of albendazole and its metabolites in rainbow trout, tilapia and Atlantic salmon after oral administration. J Vet Pharmacol Ther 26:421–427. 10.1046/j.0140-7783.2003.00534.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14962053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh B, Rummel N, Gieseker C, Cheely CS, Reimschuessel R (2009) Residue depletion of albendazole and its metabolites in the muscle tissue of large mouth and hybrid striped bass after oral administration. J Chromatogr A 1216:8173–8176. 10.1016/j.chroma.2009.04.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19406409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Busatto Z, Gonçalves de França W, Cyrino JEP, Paschoal JAR (2017) Assessment of elimination profile of albendazole residues in fish. Food Addit Contam 35:77–85. 10.1080/19440049.2017.1400186</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29095112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchmann K, Bjerregaard J (1990) Comparative efficacies of commercially available benzimidazoles against Pseudodactylogyrus infestations in eels. Dis Aquat Org 9:117–120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlsson G, Patring J, Ullerås E, Oskarsson A (2011) Developmental toxicity of albendazole and its three main metabolites in zebrafish embryos. Reprod Toxicol 32:129–137. 10.1016/j.reprotox.2011.05.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21683134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang YJ, Kim DS, Kim KH (2013) Evaluation of treatment efficacy of doxycycline and albendazole against scuticociliatosis in olive flounder (Paralichthys olivaceus). Aquaculture 416:192–195. 10.1016/j.aquaculture.2013.09.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nwani CD, Odo GE, Nwadinigwe AO, Onyeke CC, Atama CI, Ngwu G, Oluah SN, Ukonze JA, Ezeibe BCA (2016) Short-term effects of albendazole on the oxidative stress markers and hematological parameters in tissues of African Catfish Clarias gariepinus. J Aquat Anim Health 28:222–228. 10.1080/08997659.2016.1194908</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27754768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mykola Z, Inna K, Liudmyla C (2018) Evaluation of the toxic effect of nandrolone and albendazole on fish according to the morphological parameters of blood. ScienceRise Biol Sci 1:4–8. 10.15587/2519-8025.2018.123900</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negreiros LP, Souza EX, Lima TA, Tavares-Dias M (2022) Albendazole is effective for controlling monogenean parasites of the gills of Piaractus brachypomus (Serrasalmidae) and Megaleporinus macrocephalus (Anostomidae). Rev Bras Parasitol Vet 31:e010322. 10.1590/S1984-29612022057</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9901879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36383788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subash P, Uma A, Ahilan B, Kannan SS (2023) In vivo and in silico investigations on the efficacy of albendazole against Enterocytozoon hepatopenaei (EHP) infecting Penaeus vannamei. Aquaculture 575:739801. 10.1016/j.aquaculture.2023.739801</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh B, Rummel N, Reimschuessel R (2003) Determination of albendazole and its major metabolites in the muscle tissues of atlantic Salmon, Tilapia, and rainbow trout by high performance liquid chromatography with fluorometric detection. J Agric Food Chem 51:3254–3259. 10.1021/jf021176i</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12744651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh B, Rummel N, Gieseker C, Reimschuessel R (2006) Metabolism and depletion of albendazole in the muscle tissue of channel catfish following oral treatment. J Vet Pharmacol Ther 29:525–530. 10.1111/j.1365-2885.2006.00799.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17083456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu D, Evans ER, Hasbrouck N, Reimschuessel R, Shaikh B (2012) Residue depletion of albendazole and its metabolites in aquacultured yellow perch (Perca flavescens). J Vet Pharmacol Ther 35:560–562. 10.1111/j.1365-2885.2011.01354.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22150530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Chen C, Ai D, Wang C, Li J, Qi Y, Yi W, Shen H, Cao J (2012) Pharmacokinetics and tissue residues of hydrochloric acid albendazole sulfoxide and its metabolites in crucian carp (Carassius auratus) after oral administration. Environ Toxicol Pharmacol 33:197–204. 10.1016/j.etap.2011.12.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22227164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Portela ACV, Silveira JGF, Damaceno MA, da Silva AFB, de Jesus RB, Pilarski F, Gadaj A, Mooney MH, Paschoal JAR (2020) Food safety evaluation for the use of albendazole in fish: residual depletion profile and withdrawal period estimation. Food Addit Contam 37:596–606. 10.1080/19440049.2020.1719285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32023180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira Cordeiro R, de Campos A, Braga P, Souza Rocha MJ, Campos Chagas E, Reyes Reyes FG (2021) Depletion study and estimation of the withdrawal period for albendazole in tambaqui (Colossoma macropomum) parasitised by acanthocephalan (Neoechinorhynchus buttnerae) treated with albendazole-containing feed. Food Addit Contam 38:1883–1896. 10.1080/19440049.2021.1954700</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34477497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onaka E, Martins M, Moraes F (2003) Albendazole and praziquantel efficacy against Anacanthorus penilabiatus (Monogenea: Dactylogyridae), gill parasite of Piaractus mesopotamicus (Osteichthyes: Characidae). I. Therapeutic baths. Bol Inst Pesca 29:101–107</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alves CMG, Nogueira JN, Barriga IB, Dos Santos JR, Santos GG, Tavares-Dias M (2019) Albendazole, levamisole and ivermectin are effective against monogeneans of Colossoma macropomum (Pisces: Serrasalmidae). J Fish Dis 42:405–412. 10.1111/jfd.12952</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30659617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Opatrny L, Snell L, Prichard RW, Maclean J (2005) Death related to albendazole-induced pancytopenia: case report and review. Am J Trop Med Hyg 72:291–294. 10.4269/AJTMH.2005.72.291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15772324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dow GS, O’Hara AJ, Newton SC, Reynoldson JA, Thompson RCA (2000) Plasmodium berghei: the antimalarial activity of albendazole in rats is mediated via effects on the hematopoietic system. Exp Parasitol 94:259–263. 10.1006/expr.2000.4491</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10831394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harm TA, Radke SL, Burns LE, Schrunk DE (2022) Enteropathy and bone marrow hypoplasia associated with presumptive albendazole toxicosis in a juvenile Boer goat. J Vet Diagn Invest 34:1015–1019. 10.1177/10406387221121122</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9597350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36039773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard LL, Papendick R, Stalis IH, Allen JL, Sutherland-Smith M, Zuba JR, Ward DL, Rideout BA (2002). Fenbendazole and albendazole toxicity in pigeons and doves. J Avian Med Surg 16:203–210. http://www.jstor.org/stable/30133222</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Puerta LA, Carrasco J, Vargas-Calla A, López-Urbina MT, González AE (2019) Alopecia a potential adverse side effect of albendazole use in alpacas. Vet Parasitol Reg Stud Rep 17:100297. 10.1016/j.vprsr.2019.100297</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31303236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JH, Lee C, Jeon HJ, Kim BK, Lee NK, Choi SK, Han JE (2021) First report of Enterocytozoon hepatopenaei infection in Pacific whiteleg shrimp (Litopenaeus vannamei) cultured in Korea. Animals 11:3150. 10.1016/j.aquaculture.2021.737525</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8614486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34827883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jang GI, Kim SM, Oh YK, Lee SJ, Hong SY, Lee HE, Kwon MG, Kim BS (2022) First report of Enterocytozoon hepatopenaei infection in giant freshwater prawn (Macrobrachium rosenbergii de Man) cultured in the Republic of Korea. Animals 12:3149. 10.3390/ani12223149</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9686700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36428377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang KF, Pantoja CR, Redman RM, Han JE, Tran LH, Lightner DV (2015) Development of in situ hybridization and PCR assays for the detection of Enterocytozoon hepatopenaei (EHP), a microsporidian parasite infecting penaeid shrimp. J Invertebr Pathol 130:37–41. 10.1016/j.jip.2015.06.009-</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26146228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>