<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39352513</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-7438</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>56</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Tropical animal health and production</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Trop Anim Health Prod</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>High dietary Mucuna pruriens utilis seed meal compromises growth performance, carcass traits, haemato-biochemistry, and meat quality of broilers.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>310</StartPage><MedlinePgn>310</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">310</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11250-024-04120-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Usage of soyabean meal (SBM) in broiler diets is economically and environmentally unsustainable thus necessitating investigation of alternative protein sources. Therefore, this study investigated effects of incremental inclusion levels of Mucuna pruriens utilis seed meal (MSM) for partial substitution of SBM in broiler diets. In a completely randomized design (CRD), 400 day-old Ross 308 chicks were allotted to 5 iso-caloric-nitrogenous MSM-containing (0, 5, 10, 15, and 20%) dietary treatments. Each treatment was replicated 8 times, with each pen having 10 birds, during starter (d1 - 14), grower (d15 - 28), and finisher (d29 - 42) phases. Results showed that dietary MSM decreased feed intake (FI: quadratic: P &lt; 0.001), body weight gain (BWG: linear: P &lt; 0.001), and feed conversion efficiency (FCE: linear: P &lt; 0.001) as it linearly decreased slaughter weight (SW: P &lt; 0.001), hot carcass weight (HCW: P &lt; 0.001), cold carcass weight (CCW: P &lt; 0.001), dressing percentage (P &lt; 0.001), and breast weight (P &lt; 0.05). In contrast, dietary MSM linearly increased the weights of the liver (P &lt; 0.01), proventriculus (P &lt; 0.001), gizzard (P &lt; 0.001), duodenum (P = 0.01), jejunum (P &lt; 0.001), ileum (P &lt; 0.001), caecum (P &lt; 0.01), and colon (P &lt; 0.01). Also, dietary MSM quadratically increased blood heterophils (P &lt; 0.05) and alkaline phosphatase activity (P &lt; 0.05) of the chickens whilst linearly increasing their serum amylase (P = 0.001) and lipase (P = 0.001) activities and linearly decreasing their serum symmetric dimethylarginine (SDMA: P = 0.001) and cholesterol (P &lt; 0.05). Further, dietary MSM linearly decreased chicken breast meat ultimate pH (P &lt; 0.05) whilst linearly increasing its cooking loss (P &lt; 0.01), drip loss (P &lt; 0.05) and shear force (P &lt; 0.01). In conclusion, dietary MSM compromised growth performance, carcass characteristics, and meat quality of broilers as it increased the weights of their digestive-metabolic organs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mthana</LastName><ForeName>Makiwa Simeon</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Science, School of Agricultural Sciences, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, North-West University (Mahikeng Campus), Private Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mthiyane</LastName><ForeName>Doctor Mziwenkosi Nhlanhla</ForeName><Initials>DMN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8743-9304</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Science, School of Agricultural Sciences, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, North-West University (Mahikeng Campus), Private Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa. kakade2000@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Security and Safety Focus Area, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, North-West University (Mahikeng Campus), Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa. kakade2000@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>141668</GrantID><Agency>National Research Foundation of South Africa</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Trop Anim Health Prod</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>1277355</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0049-4747</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002645" MajorTopicYN="Y">Chickens</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012639" MajorTopicYN="Y">Seeds</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Animal Feed</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008460" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meat</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D031299" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mucuna</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004032" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diet</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000824" MajorTopicYN="Y">Animal Nutritional Physiological Phenomena</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011897" MajorTopicYN="N">Random Allocation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mucuna pruriens utilis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Broilers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Haemato-biochemistry</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meat quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Performance</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There is no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39352513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11445329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11250-024-04120-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11250-024-04120-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abramowitz M, Muntner P, Coco M, Southern W, Lotwin I, Hostetter TH, Melamed ML (2010) Serum alkaline phosphatase and phosphate and risk of mortality and hospitalization. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol 5:1064. https://doi.org/10.2215/CJN.08621209</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2879313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20378645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinmutimi A, Okwu N (2006) Effect of quantitative substitution of cooked Mucuna utilis seed meal for soybean meal in broiler finisher diet. Int J Poult Sci 5:477–481. 10.3923/ijps.2006.477.481</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akure C, Sekoni A, Abeke F, Vantsawa P, Babasanya B, Olukotun O, Ayodele J (2021) Growth performance and nutrient digestibility of broiler finishers fed processed Mucuna pruriens seed meal. Nigerian J Animal Prod 48:86–92. 10.51791/njap.v48i3.2956</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alabi FA, Mlambo V, Mnisi CM (2024) Dietary inclusion of marama bean (Tylosema esculentum) in broiler chicken diets compromises feed utilization, growth performance, and carcass traits. Anim Feed Sci Technol 308:115854. 10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2023.115854</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alleman RJ Jr, Canale RE, McCarthy CG, Bloomer RJ (2011) A blend of chlorophytum borivilianum and velvet bean increases serum growth hormone in exercise-trained men. Nutr Metab Insights 4:S8127. 10.4137/nmi.s8127</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3738483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23946662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Meat Science Association (AMSA) (2012) Meat color measurement guidelines. American Meat Science Association (AMSA), National Live Stock and Meat Board 444 North Michigan Avenue Chicago, Illinois 60611, USA</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association of Official Analytical Chemists (AOAC) (2005) Official methods of analysis of AOAC international, 16th edn. Association of Official Analytical Chemists, Arlington, VA</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayodele S, Oloruntola O, Ayeyeye S, Jimoh O, Falowo A, Omoniyi I (2021) Supplementation value of Mucuna seed powder on performance, antioxidant enzymes, meat cholesterol and peroxidation, and serum metabolites of broiler chickens. Malaysian J Anim Sci 24:11–22</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baby C, Kaur S, Singh J, Prasad R (2023) Velvet bean (Mucuna pruriens): A sustainable protein source for tomorrow. Legume Sci 5:e178. 10.1002/leg3.178</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banaszkiewicz T (2011) Nutritional value of soybean meal. Soybean Nutr 12:1–20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beiriger J, Khan A, Yan B, Ross H, Wang M, Carducci M, Parra NS, Chowdhury S, Erwin R, Forrest P (2023) Comprehensive review of acute pancreatitis pain syndrome. Gastrointestinal Dis 5:144–166. 10.3390/gidisord5020014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belewu M, Olajide J (2010) Lesser known seed a renewable pathway for sustainable animal production in Africa. J Sustain Dev Africa 12:179–188</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belluzzi A, Boschi S, Brignola C, Munarini A, Cariani G, Miglio F (2000) Polyunsaturated fatty acids and inflammatory bowel disease. Am J Clin Nutr 71:339s–342s</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10617993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breewood H, Garnett T (2020) What is feed-food competition? (Foodsource: building blocks). Food Climate Research Network, University of Oxford</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choct M, Dersjant-Li Y, McLeish J, Peisker M (2010) Soy oligosaccharides and soluble non-starch polysaccharides: a review of digestion, nutritive and anti-nutritive effects in pigs and poultry. Asian Australas J Anim Sci 23:1386–1398. 10.5713/ajas.2010.90222</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahouda M, Toleba SS, Youssao A, Mama Ali A, Dangou-Sapoho R, Ahounou S, Hambuckers A, Hornick J-L (2009) The effects of raw and processed Mucuna pruriens seed based diets on the growth parameters and meat characteristics of benin local guinea fowl (Numida meleagris, L.). Int J Poult Sci 8:882–889. 10.3923/ijps.2009.882.889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Silva PS, Olsen A, Christensen J, Schmidt EB, Overvaad K, Tjonneland A, Hart AR (2010) An association between dietary arachidonic acid, measured in adipose tissue, and ulcerative colitis. Gastroenterology 139:1912–1917. 10.1053/j.gastro.2010.07.065</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20950616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Carmen J, Gernat A, Myhrman R, Carew L (1999) Evaluation of raw and heated velvet beans (Mucuna pruriens) as feed ingredients for broilers. Poult Sci 78:866–872. 10.1093/ps/78.6.866</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10438131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>den Hertog-Meischke M, Van Laack R, Smulders F (1997) The water-holding capacity of fresh meat. Vet Quart 19:175–181. 10.1080/01652176.1997.9694767</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9413116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding W, Kou L, Cao B, Wei Y (2010) Meat quality parameters of descendants by grading hybridization of Boer goat and Guanzhong Dairy goat. Meat Sci 84:323–328. 10.1016/j.meatsci.2009.04.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20374792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dörper A, Veldkamp T, Dicke M (2021) Use of black soldier fly and house fly in feed to promote sustainable poultry production. J Insects Food Feed 7:761–780. 10.3920/JIFF2020.0064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekpo J, Etuk I, Solomon I (2008) Influence of sex on growth and carcass traits of rabbits fed unpeeled cassava tuber meal, peeled cassava tuber meal and cassava peel meal as energy sources. J Agric Forest Soc Sci 6:1–16. 10.4314/joafss.v6i1.48634</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elfar M, Gaber LW, Sabek O, Fischer CP, Gaber AO (2007) The inflammatory cascade in acute pancreatitis: relevance to clinical disease. Surg Clin North Am 87:1325–1340. 10.1016/j.suc.2007.09.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18053834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ericson LE, Hhkanson R, Lundquist I (1977) Accumulation of dopamine in mouse pancreatic B-cells following injection of L-DOPA: Localization to secretory granules and inhibition of insulin secretion. Diabetologia 13:117–124</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">404204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO (2016) Handbook on agricultural cost of production statistics: guidelines for data collection, compilation and dissemination (Food and Agriculture Organisation)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fathima K, Soris PT, Mohan V (2010) Nutritional and antinutritional assessment of Mucuna pruriens (L.) DC var. pruriens an underutilized tribal pulse. Adv Biores 1:79–89</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gemede HF, Ratta N (2018) Anti dietary factors in plant foods: Potential health benefits and adverse effects. Adv Res J Microbiol 5:100–113. 10.11648/j.ijnfs.20140304.18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunya B, Muchenje V, Masika P (2019) The effect of earthworm Eisenia foetida meal as a protein source on carcass characteristics and physico-chemical attributes of broilers. Pak J Nutr 18:657–664. 10.3923/pjn.2019.657.664</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haque MH, Sarker S, Islam MS, Islam MA, Karim MR, Kayesh MEH, Shiddiky MJ, Anwer MS (2020) Sustainable antibiotic-free broiler meat production: Current trends, challenges, and possibilities in a developing country perspective. Biology 9:411. 10.3390/biology9110411</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7700346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33238534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardt PD, Hauenschild A, Jaeger C, Teichmann J, Bretzel RG, Kloer HU (2003) High prevalence of steatorrhea in 101 diabetic patients likely to suffer from exocrine pancreatic insufficiency according to low fecal elastase 1 concentrations: a prospective multicenter study. Dig Dis Sci 48:1688–1692. 10.1023/a:1025422423435</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14560984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashem AD, Kaviani B (2010) In vitro proliferation of an important medicinal plant Aloe-A method for rapid production. Aust J Crop Sci 4:216–222</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Orihuela AL, Castro-Cerritos KV, López MG, Martínez-Antonio A (2022) Compound characterization of a Mucuna seed extract: L-Dopa, Arginine, Stizolamine, and some Fructooligosaccharides. Compounds 3:1–16. 10.3390/compounds3010001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hertanto BS, Nurmalasari CDA, Nuhriawangsa AMP, Cahyadi M, Kartikasari LR (2018) The physical and microbiological quality of chicken meat in the different type of enterprise poultry slaughterhouse: a case study in Karanganyar district. IOP Conf Ser Earth Environ Sci 102(1):12–51. 10.1088/1755-1315/102/1/012051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honikel KO (1998) Reference methods for the assessment of physical characteristics of meat. Meat Sci 49:447–457. 10.1016/S0309-1740(98)00034-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22060626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>IDEXX (2023) Interpreting your SDMA results. IDEXX SDMA resource center. https://www.idexx.co.za/en-za/veterinary/reference-laboratories/sdma/interpreting-your-sdma-results/. (Accessed 20 Oct 2023)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyayi E, Kluth H, Rodehutscord M (2006) Precaecal crude protein digestibility, organs relative weight and performance in broilers fed diets containing Enterolobium cyclocarpum and Mucuna pruriens seed flour in place of soybean meal. Archiv fur Geflugelkunde 70:161</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayaweera T, Cyril H, Ruwandeepika H, Wickramanayake D, Thotawaththe T (2007) Effect of feeding velvet beans (Mucuna pruriens) on the lipid profile of broiler chickens. Sabaragamuwa Univ J 7:78–85. 10.4038/suslj.v7i1.1845</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong SM, Choi S, Kim K, Kim SM, Lee G, Park SY, Kim YY, Son JS, Yun JM, Park SM (2018) Effect of change in total cholesterol levels on cardiovascular disease among young adults. J Am Heart Assoc 7:e008819. 10.1161/jaha.118.008819</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6220545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29899019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jha R, Mishra P (2021) Dietary fiber in poultry nutrition and their effects on nutrient utilization, performance, gut health, and on the environment: a review. J Animal Sci Biotechnol 12:1–16. 10.1186/s40104-021-00576-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8054369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33866972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jitkritsadakul O, Jagota P, Petchrutchatachart S, Sansopha L, Rerknimitr R, Bhidayasiri R (2013) Recurrent pancreatitis as a rare complication of duodenal levodopa infusion treatment. Mov Disord 28:1208–1310. 10.1002/mds.25347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23389834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>JøRgensen H, Zhao X-Q, Knudsen KEB, Eggum BO (1996) The influence of dietary fibre source and level on the development of the gastrointestinal tract, digestibility and energy metabolism in broiler chickens. Br J Nutr 75:379–395. 10.1079/bjn19960141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8785212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazmi N, Wallen GR, Yang L, Alkhatib J, Schwandt ML, Feng D, Gao B, Diazgranados N, Ramchandani VA, Barb JJ (2022) An exploratory study of pro-inflammatory cytokines in individuals with alcohol use disorder: MCP-1 and IL-8 associated with alcohol consumption, sleep quality, anxiety, depression, and liver biomarkers. Front Psych 13:931280. 10.3389/fpsyt.2022.931280</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9405018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36032219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khatun J, Loh T, Foo H, Akit H, Mohamad R, Shazali N (2020) Effects of vitamin E, an oil blend and L-Arginine on breast meat from broiler chickens. South African J Animal Sci 50:745–757. 10.4314/sajas.v50i5.13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kielstein JT, Salpeter SR, Bode-Boeger SM, Cooke JP, Fliser D (2006) Symmetric dimethylarginine (SDMA) as endogenous marker of renal function—a meta-analysis. Nephrol Dial Transplant 21:2446–2451. 10.1093/ndt/gfl292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16766542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konishi F, Furusho T, Soeda Y, Yamauchi J, Kobayashi S, Ito M, Araki T, Kogure S, Takashima A, Takekoshi S (2022) Administration of mucuna beans (Mucunapruriences (L.) DC. var. utilis) improves cognition and neuropathology of 3× Tg-AD mice. Sci Rep 12:996. 10.1038/s41598-022-04777-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8770455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35046433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus SS, Volk BW (1961) Pancreas in maturity-onset diabetes: pathogenetic considerations. Arch Pathol 71:44–59</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13759774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Zheng M, Zhao G, Wang J, Liu J, Wang S, Feng F, Liu D, Zhu D, Li Q (2021) Identification of QTL regions and candidate genes for growth and feed efficiency in broilers. Genet Sel Evol 53:1–17. 10.1186/s12711-021-00608-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7866652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33549052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Cao GY, Jing WZ, Liu J, Liu M (2023) Global trends and regional differences in incidence and mortality of cardiovascular disease, 1990–2019: findings from 2019 global burden of disease study. Eur J Prev Cardiol 30:276–286. 10.1093/eurjpc/zwac285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36458973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lieu CA, Venkiteswaran K, Gilmour TP, Rao AN, Petticoffer AC, Gilbert EV, Deogaonkar M, Manyam BV, Subramanian T (2012) The antiparkinsonian and antidyskinetic mechanisms of Mucuna pruriens in the MPTP-treated nonhuman primate. Evid-Based Complement Alter Med 2012:840247. 10.1155/2012/840247</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3445014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22997535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Livesey G (1989) A perspective on food energy standards for nutrition labelling. Br J Nutr 85:271–287</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11299073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mallick P, Muduli K, Biswal JN, Pumwa J (2020) Broiler poultry feed cost optimization using linear programming technique. J Oper Strategic Plann 3:31–57. 10.1177/2516600X19896910</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manhivi VE, Slabbert RM, Sivakumar D (2022) Co-Ingestion of Natal Plums (Carissa macrocarpa) and Marula Nuts (Sclerocarya birrea) in a snack bar and its effect on phenolic compounds and bioactivities. Molecules 27:310. 10.3390/molecules27010310</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8746984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35011541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mashau ME, Kgatla TE, Makhado MV, Mikasi MS, Ramashia SE (2022) Nutritional composition, polyphenolic compounds and biological activities of marula fruit (Sclerocarya birrea) with its potential food applications: A review. Int J Food Prop 25:1549–1575. 10.1080/10942912.2022.2064491</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonald P, Edwards R, Greenhalgh J, Morgan C, Sinclair L, Wilkinson R (2010) Animal nutrition, 7th edn. Pearson Education Ltd., Harlow</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mores MG, Fikry EM, El-Gendy AO, Mohamed WR, Badary OA (2023) Probiotics mixture and taurine attenuate L-arginine-induced acute pancreatitis in rats: Impact on transient receptor potential vanilloid-1 (TRPV-1)/IL-33/NF-κB signaling and apoptosis. Tissue Cell 102234. 10.1016/j.tice.2023.102234</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37844391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mthana MS, Gajana CS, Moyo B, Hugo A, Makhamba N, Thabethe F (2022) Response in growth performance, physico-chemical properties, and fatty acid composition of broiler meat to different levels of Mucuna pruriens seed meal. 10.21203/rs.3.rs-1127078/v1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musthafa MS, Asgari SM, Kurian A, Elumalai P, Ali ARJ, Paray BA, Al-Sadoon MK (2018) Protective efficacy of Mucuna pruriens (L.) seed meal enriched diet on growth performance, innate immunity, and disease resistance in Oreochromis mossambicus against Aeromonas hydrophila. Fish Shellfish Immunol 75:374–380. 10.1016/j.fsi.2018.02.031</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29458093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nath H, Samtiya M, Dhewa T (2022) Beneficial attributes and adverse effects of major plant-based foods anti-nutrients on health: A review. Human Nutr Metab 28:200147. 10.1016/j.hnm.2022.200147</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navegantes LCC, Resano NM, Migliorini RH, Kettelhut ÍC (2000) Role of adrenoceptors and cAMP on the catecholamine-induced inhibition of proteolysis in rat skeletal muscle. Am J Physiol-Endocrinol Metab 279:E663–E668. 10.1152/ajpendo.2000.279.3.e663</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10950836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndudzo A, Pullen J, Magwaba T, Ndlovu S, Moyo M, Sibanda S, Chimbo J, Mugoti A (2023) Incorporation of functional feed ingredients to substitute antimicrobials in animal nutrition: Opportunities for livestock production in developing countries. Int J Livestock Prod 14:44–57. 10.5897/IJLP2023.0820</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngatchic JTM, Njintang N, Bernard C, Oben J, Mbofung CM (2016) Lipid-lowering properties of protein-rich mucuna product. Nutrire 41:1–10. 10.1186/s41110-016-0003-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojha ML, Chadha NK, Saini VP, Damroy S, Chandraprakash SP, Sawant PB (2014) Effect of ethanolic extract of Mucuna pruriens on growth, metabolism and immunity of Labeo rohita (Hamilton, 1822) fingerlings. Int J Fauna Biol Stud 1:01–09</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oloruntola OD, Ayodele SO, Adeyeye SA, Agbede J (2018) Performance, haemato-biochemical indices and antioxidant status of growing rabbits fed on diets supplemented with Mucuna pruriens leaf meal. World Rabbit Sci 26:277–285. 10.4995/wrs.2018.10182</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omidiwura B, Agboola A, Iyayi E (2016) Effect of L-dopa on performance and carcass characteristics in broiler chickens. Int J Animal Vet Sci 10:87–91</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ono N, Horikoshi J, Izawa T, Nishiyama K, Tanaka M, Kuwamura M, Azuma YT (2023) L-arginine-induced pancreatitis aggravated by inhibiting Na+/Ca2+ exchanger 1. J Vet Med Sci 85:657–666. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37100607/</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10315542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37100607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osei S, Dei H (1998) The nutritive value of raw Mucuna pruriens (var. utilis) for broiler finishers. Ghana J Agric Sci 31:55–59. 10.4314/gjas.v31i1.1945</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otiang E, Campbell ZA, Thumbi SM, Njagi LW, Nyaga PN, Palmer GH (2020) Mortality as the primary constraint to enhancing nutritional and financial gains from poultry: A multi-year longitudinal study of smallholder farmers in western Kenya. PLoS One 15:e0233691. 10.1371/journal.pone.0233691</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7259595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32470070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathania R, Chawla P, Khan H, Kaushik R, Khan MA (2020) An assessment of potential nutritive and medicinal properties of Mucuna pruriens: a natural food legume. 3 Biotech 10:261. 10.1007/s13205-020-02253-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7239958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32477848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petronijević M, Petronijević N, Ivković M, Stefanović D, Radonjić N, Glišić B, Ristić G, Damjanović A, Paunović V (2008) Low bone mineral density and high bone metabolism turnover in premenopausal women with unipolar depression. Bone 42:582–590. 10.1016/j.bone.2007.11.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18226593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pexas G, Doherty B, Kyriazakis I (2023) The future of protein sources in livestock feeds: implications for sustainability and food safety. Front Sustain Food Syst 7:1188467. 10.3389/fsufs.2023.1188467</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pieper-Bigelow C, Strocchi A, Levitt MD (1990) Where does serum amylase come from and where does it go? Gastroenterol Clin North Am 19:793–810. 10.1016/S0889-8553(21)00514-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1702756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulikkalpura H, Kurup R, Mathew PJ, Baby S (2015) Levodopa in Mucuna pruriens and its degradation. Sci Rep 5:11078. 10.1038/srep11078</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4460905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26058043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raksha B, Pooja S, Babu S (2014) Bioactive compounds and medicinal properties of Aloe vera L.: an update. J Plant Sci 2:102–107. 10.23880/oajvsr-16000237</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao W, Shi Z, Liu S, Shu Y, Chai X, Zhang Z (2022) Shrinkage properties and their relationship with degradation of proteins linking the endomysium and myofibril in lamb meat submitted to heating or air drying. Foods 11:2242. 10.3390/foods11152242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9368109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35954013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reeves PG, Nielsen FH, Fahey GC Jr (1993) AIN-93 purified diets for laboratory rodents: final report of the American Institute of Nutrition ad hoc writing committee on the reformulation of the AIN-76A rodent diet. J Nutr 123:1939–1951. 10.1093/jn/123.11.1939</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8229312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regasa T, Dinku Y, Gezahegn B, Feleke Z, Regassa Z, Mamo A, Assefa T, Gezahegn H, Solomon D, Atlaw D (2022) The elevation of pancreatic enzymes in serum and their distribution at different stages of renal insufficiency among diabetic patients attending Goba Referral Hospital. Diabetes Metab Synd Obes: Targets and Therapy 2087–2093. 10.2147/dmso.s363714</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9307908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35880135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu Y, Kim B (2006) Comparison of histochemical characteristics in various pork groups categorized by postmortem metabolic rate and pork quality. J Anim Sci 84:894–901. 10.2527/2006.844894x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16543567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salami SA, Luciano G, O’Grady MN, Biondi L, Newbold CJ, Kerry JP, Priolo A (2019) Sustainability of feeding plant by-products: A review of the implications for ruminant meat production. Anim Feed Sci Technol 251:37–55. 10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2019.02.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarmiento-Franco L, López-Sántiz F, Santos-Ricalde R, Sandoval-Castro C (2019) Mucuna pruriens seeds given in broiler diets on growth performance and carcass yield. Ecosistemas y Recursos Agropecuarios 6:121–127. 10.19136/era.a6n16.1815</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SAS (2012) SAS/STAT User’s Guide. SAS Institute Inc, Statistics</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi J, Arunasalam K, Yeung D, Kakuda Y, Mittal G, Jiang Y (2004) Saponins from edible legumes: chemistry, processing, and health benefits. J Med Food 7:67–78</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15117556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soetan K (2018) Antinutritional factors of five selected underutilized legumes. Food Sci Qual Manag 76:92–100. 10.1186/s43014-020-0020-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spector T, Hart D, Nandra D, Doyle D, Mackillop N, Gallimore J, Pepys M (1997) Low-level increases in serum C-reactive protein are present in early osteoarthritis of the knee and predict progressive disease. Arthr Rheumatism: Official Journal of the American College of Rheumatology 40:723–727. 10.1002/art.1780400419</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9125256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh-Hesary F, Rasoulinezhad E, Yoshino N (2019) Energy and food security: Linkages through price volatility. Energy Policy 128:796–806. 10.1016/j.enpol.2018.12.043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takasaki S, Kawakishi S (1997) Formation of protein-bound 3, 4-dihydroxyphenylalanine and 5-S-cysteinyl-3, 4-dihydroxyphenylalanine as new cross-linkers in gluten. J Agric Food Chem 45:3472–3475. 10.1021/jf9701594</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakur A, Sharma V, Thakur A (2019) An overview of anti-nutritional factors in food. Int J Chem Stud 7:2472–2479</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuleun C, Igba F (2008) Growth and carcass characteristics of broiler chickens fed water soaked and cooked velvet bean (Mucuna utilis) meal. Afr J Biotech 7:2676–2681</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuleun C, Patrick J, Tiamiyu L (2009) Evaluation of raw and boiled velvet bean (Mucuna utilis) as feed ingredient for broiler chickens. Pak J Nutr 8:601–606. 10.3923/pjn.2009.601.606</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UN (2023) Global issues: Population. Retrieved 01/07 from https://www.un.org/en/global-issues/population#:~:text=The%20world%20population%20is%20projected,and%2010.4%20billion%20by%202100. (Accessed 14 Sep 2023)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vadivel V, Pugalenthi M (2010) Evaluation of growth performance of broiler birds fed with diet containing different levels of velvet bean meal as an alternative protein ingredient. Livest Sci 127:76–83. 10.1016/j.livsci.2009.09.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Soest P, Robertson JB, Lewis BA (1991) Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition. J Dairy Sci 74:3583–3597. 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1660498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webber M, Krishnan A, Thomas NG, Cheung BM (2010) Association between serum alkaline phosphatase and C-reactive protein in the United States National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2005–2006. Clin Chem Lab Med 48:167–173. 10.1515/cclm.2010.052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19958209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia H, Guo J, Shen J, Jiang S, Han S, Li L (2023) Ketogenic diet exacerbates L-Arginine-Induced acute pancreatitis and reveals the therapeutic potential of butyrate. Nutrients 15:4427. 10.3390/nu15204427</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10609823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37892502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zungu PN, Mthiyane DMN, Mazibuko-Mbeje SE, Ogwuegbu MC (2023) Dietary supplementation of low levels of unprocessed Mucuna pruriens utilis seed meal induces mild antinutritional entero-physio-metabolic perturbations without compromising performance and meat quality in finisher broilers. Trop Anim Health Prod 55:336. 10.1007/s11250-023-03760-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10539458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37770670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>