<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39358927</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1863-2378</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Zoonoses and public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Zoonoses Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Campylobacter Diversity Along the Farm-to-Fork Continuum of Pastured Poultry Flocks in the Southeastern United States.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/zph.13184</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Consumer demand for pasture raised, antibiotic-free poultry products has led to an increase in pastured poultry operations within the United States. Given the level of environmental interaction and the potential increase in exposure to foodborne pathogens in these settings, a greater understanding of the prevalence and diversity of Campylobacter populations inherent within pastured poultry flocks is needed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">To achieve this, 40 pastured poultry flocks from nine farms were sampled using a farm-to-fork strategy, and Campylobacter was isolated and characterised from preharvest (faeces, soil) through postharvest (caeca, whole carcass rinse) to the final product the consumer would purchase (whole carcass rinse).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Campylobacter was isolated from 872 of 1820 samples, showing an overall prevalence of 47.91%. The caeca showed the highest (p &lt; 0.05) Campylobacter load (4.64 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/mL) and prevalence (95.5%), while the final product whole carcass rinses had the lowest (p &lt; 0.05) Campylobacter load (0.32 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/mL) and prevalence (15.45%), suggesting that the Campylobacter load in the caeca may not be indicative of the Campylobacter load on the final product. Of the 872 positive samples, 337 Campylobacter isolates were selected for further characterisation. Campylobacter jejuni and Campylobacter coli comprised 74.18% (250/337) and 21.95% (74/337) of the selected isolates respectively. While the Campylobacter isolates displayed resistance to several antibiotics, the most common resistance for both C. jejuni and C. coli was against tetracycline (55.86% and 70.31% respectively). Multidrug resistance phenotypes (≥ 3 antibiotic classes) were relatively low for both C. jejuni (2.80%) and C. coli (9.45%).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Campylobacter load, prevalence and diversity were more affected by farm location than by the type of sample from which the Campylobacter was isolated. Overall, these results indicated a need for farm-specific Campylobacter mitigation strategies to ensure the safety of these increasingly in-demand poultry products.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Zoonoses and Public Health published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH. This article has been contributed to by U.S. Government employees and their work is in the public domain in the USA.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Hakeem</LastName><ForeName>Walid G</ForeName><Initials>WG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1225-561X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Egg &amp; Poultry Production Safety Research Unit, USDA-ARS, US National Poultry Research Center, Athens, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>US-DOE, Oak Ridge Institute for Science and Education, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oladeinde</LastName><ForeName>Adelumola</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Egg &amp; Poultry Production Safety Research Unit, USDA-ARS, US National Poultry Research Center, Athens, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Xiang</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Egg &amp; Poultry Production Safety Research Unit, USDA-ARS, US National Poultry Research Center, Athens, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cho</LastName><ForeName>Sohyun</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Egg &amp; Poultry Production Safety Research Unit, USDA-ARS, US National Poultry Research Center, Athens, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kassem</LastName><ForeName>Issmat I</ForeName><Initials>II</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Center for Food Safety, University of Georgia, Griffin, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rothrock</LastName><ForeName>Michael J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><Suffix>Jr</Suffix><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4248-6478</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Egg &amp; Poultry Production Safety Research Unit, USDA-ARS, US National Poultry Research Center, Athens, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Zoonoses Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101300786</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1863-1959</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial resistance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">campylobacter</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pasture‐raised poultry</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39358927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/zph.13184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Al Hakeem, W. G., S. Fathima, R. Shanmugasundaram, and R. K. Selvaraj. 2022. “Campylobacter Jejuni in Poultry: Pathogenesis and Control Strategies.” Microorganisms 10, no. 11: 2134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailey, M. A., R. M. Taylor, J. S. Brar, et al. 2019. “Prevalence and Antimicrobial Resistance of Campylobacter From Antibiotic‐Free Broilers During Organic and Conventional Processing.” Poultry Science 98, no. 3: 1447–1454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. 2019a. “Antibiotics Tested by NARMS.” https://www.cdc.gov/narms/antibiotics‐tested.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. 2019b. “Outbreaks Involving Campylobacter.” https://www.cdc.gov/campylobacter/outbreaks/outbreaks.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dávalos‐Almeyda, M., A. Guerrero, G. Medina, et al. 2022. “Antibiotic Use and Resistance Knowledge Assessment of Personnel on Chicken Farms With High Levels of Antimicrobial Resistance: A Cross‐Sectional Survey in Ica, Peru.” Antibiotics 11, no. 2: 190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Economou, V., N. Zisides, P. Gousia, et al. 2015. “Prevalence and Antimicrobial Profile of Campylobacter Isolates From Free‐Range and Conventional Farming Chicken Meat During a 6‐Year Survey.” Food Control 56: 161–168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA. 2024. “NARMS Now.” https://www.fda.gov/animal‐veterinary/national‐antimicrobial‐resistance‐monitoring‐system/narms‐now‐integrated‐data.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ford, L., J. M. Healy, Z. Cui, et al. 2023. “Epidemiology and Antimicrobial Resistance of Campylobacter Infections in the United States, 2005–2018.” Open Forum Infectious Diseases 10, no. 8: ofad378. https://doi.org/10.1093/ofid/ofad378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta, A., J. M. Nelson, T. J. Barrett, et al. 2004. “Antimicrobial Resistance Among Campylobacter Strains, United States, 1997–2001.” Emerging Infectious Diseases 10, no. 6: 1102–1109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hald, B., M. N. Skov, E. M. Nielsen, et al. 2015. “Campylobacter Jejuni and Campylobacter Coli in Wild Birds on Danish Livestock Farms.” Acta Veterinaria Scandinavica 58: 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanning, I., D. Biswas, P. Herrera, M. Roesler, and S. C. Ricke. 2010. “Prevalence and Characterization of Campylobacter jejuni Isolated From Pasture Flock Poultry.” Journal of Food Science 75, no. 7: M496–M502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hara‐Kudo, Y., and K. Takatori. 2011. “Contamination Level and Ingestion Dose of Foodborne Pathogens Associated With Infections.” Epidemiology and Infection 139, no. 10: 1505–1510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heuer, O. E., K. Pedersen, J. Andersen, and M. Madsen. 2001. “Prevalence and Antimicrobial Susceptibility of Thermophilic Campylobacter in Organic and Conventional Broiler Flocks.” Letters in Applied Microbiology 33, no. 4: 269–274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann, S., M. B. Batz, and J. G. Morris Jr. 2012. “Annual Cost of Illness and Quality‐Adjusted Life Year Losses in the United States Due to 14 Foodborne Pathogens.” Journal of Food Protection 75, no. 7: 1292–1302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassem, I. I., O. Kehinde, A. Kumar, and G. Rajashekara. 2016. “Antimicrobial‐Resistant Campylobacter in Organically and Conventionally Raised Layer Chickens.” Foodborne Pathogens and Disease 14, no. 1: 29–34. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2016.2161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassem, I. I., O. Kehinde, A. Kumar, and G. Rajashekara. 2017. “Antimicrobial‐Resistant Campylobacter in Organically and Conventionally Raised Layer Chickens.” Foodborne Pathogens and Disease 14, no. 1: 29–34. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2016.2161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Locatelli, A., M. A. Lewis, and M. J. Rothrock Jr. 2017. “The Distribution of Listeria in Pasture‐Raised Broiler Farm Soils Is Potentially Related to University of Vermont Medium Enrichment Bias Toward Listeria Innocua Over Listeria monocytogenes.” Frontiers in Veterinary Science 4: 227.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luangtongkum, T., T. Y. Morishita, A. J. Ison, S. Huang, P. F. McDermott, and Q. Zhang. 2006. “Effect of Conventional and Organic Production Practices on the Prevalence and Antimicrobial Resistance of Campylobacter spp. in Poultry.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 72, no. 5: 3600–3607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luangtongkum, T., T. Y. Morishita, L. Martin, I. Choi, O. Sahin, and Q. Zhang. 2008. “Prevalence of Tetracycline‐Resistant Campylobacter in Organic Broilers During a Production Cycle.” Avian Diseases 52, no. 3: 487–490.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matlock, T. 2019. “The Ever‐Expanding Industry of Certified Organics.” https://www.usda.gov/media/blog/2023/01/18/ever‐expanding‐industry‐certified‐organics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwansa, M., M. Mukuma, E. Mulilo, et al. 2023. “Determination of Antimicrobial Resistance Patterns of Escherichia coli Isolates From Farm Workers in Broiler Poultry Production and Assessment of Antibiotic Resistance Awareness Levels Among Poultry Farmers in Lusaka, Zambia.” Frontiers in Public Health 10: 998860.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newell, D., and C. Fearnley. 2003. “Sources of Campylobacter Colonization in Broiler Chickens.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 69, no. 8: 4343–4351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicholson, F. A., S. J. Groves, and B. J. Chambers. 2005. “Pathogen Survival During Livestock Manure Storage and Following Land Application.” Bioresource Technology 96, no. 2: 135–143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olonitola, O. S., N. Fahrenfeld, and A. Pruden. 2015. “Antibiotic Resistance Profiles Among Mesophilic Aerobic Bacteria in Nigerian Chicken Litter and Associated Antibiotic Resistance Genes.” Poultry Science 94, no. 5: 867–874.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overbeke, I. V., L. Duchateau, L. D. Zutter, G. Albers, and R. Ducatelle. 2006. “A Comparison Survey of Organic and Conventional Broiler Chickens for Infectious Agents Affecting Health and Food Safety.” Avian Diseases 50, no. 2: 196–200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires, A., L. Patterson, E. Kukielka, P. Aminabadi, N. Navarro‐Gonzalez, and M. Jay‐Russell. 2019. “Prevalence and Risk Factors Associated With Campylobacter spp. and Salmonella enterica in Livestock Raised on Diversified Small‐Scale Farms in California.” Epidemiology and Infection 147: e321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poudel, S., T. Li, S. Chen, et al. 2022. “Prevalence, Antimicrobial Resistance, and Molecular Characterization of Campylobacter Isolated From Broilers and Broiler Meat Raised Without Antibiotics.” Microbiology Spectrum 10, no. 3: e00251‐00222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rama, E. N., M. Bailey, S. Kumar, et al. 2022. “Prevalence and Antimicrobial Resistance of Salmonella in Conventional and no Antibiotics Ever Broiler Farms in the United States.” Food Control 135: 108738.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reisch, L., U. Eberle, and S. Lorek. 2013. “Sustainable Food Consumption: An Overview of Contemporary Issues and Policies.” Sustainability: Science, Practice and Policy 9, no. 2: 7–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothrock, M. J., Jr., K. E. Gibson, A. C. Micciche, and S. C. Ricke. 2019. “Pastured Poultry Production in the United States: Strategies to Balance System Sustainability and Environmental Impact.” Frontiers in Sustainable Food Systems 3: 74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothrock, M. J., Jr., J. Y. Guard, and A. Oladeinde. 2021. “Salmonella Diversity Along the Farm‐to‐Fork Continuum of Pastured Poultry Flocks in the Southeastern United States.” Frontiers in Animal Science 2: 761930.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothrock, M. J., Jr., and A. Locatelli. 2019. “Importance of Farm Environment to Shape Poultry‐Related Microbiomes Throughout the Farm‐to‐Fork Continuum of Pasture‐Raised Broiler Flocks.” Frontiers in Sustainable Food Systems 3: 48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahin, O., I. I. Kassem, Z. Shen, J. Lin, G. Rajashekara, and Q. Zhang. 2015. “Campylobacter in Poultry: Ecology and Potential Interventions.” Avian Diseases 59, no. 2: 185–200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahin, O., J. Pang, N. Pavlovic, et al. 2024. “A Longitudinal Study on Campylobacter in Conventionally Reared Commercial Broiler Flocks in the United States: Prevalence and Genetic Diversity.” Avian Diseases 67, no. 4: 317–325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanderson, R. A., J. A. Maas, A. P. Blain, et al. 2018. “Spatio‐Temporal Models to Determine Association Between Campylobacter Cases and Environment.” International Journal of Epidemiology 47, no. 1: 202–216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shane, S. M., M. S. Montrose, and K. S. Harrington. 1985. “Transmission of Campylobacter jejuni by the Housefly (Musca Domestica).” Avian Diseases 29: 384–391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sher, A. A., M. A. Ashraf, B. E. Mustafa, and M. M. Raza. 2021. “Epidemiological Trends of Foodborne Campylobacter Outbreaks in The United States of America, 1998–2016.” Food Microbiology 97: 103751.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skov, M., A. Spencer, B. Hald, et al. 2004. “The Role of Litter Beetles as Potential Reservoir for Salmonella enterica and Thermophilic Campylobacter spp. Between Broiler Flocks.” Avian Diseases 48, no. 1: 9–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, O. M., K. A. Cornell, M. S. Crossley, et al. 2023. “Wind Speed and Landscape Context Mediate Campylobacter Risk Among Poultry Reared in Open Environments.” Animals 13, no. 3: 492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stern, N. J., B. Wojton, and K. Kwiatek. 1992. “A Differential‐Selective Medium and Dry Ice‐Generated Atmosphere for Recovery of Campylobacter jejuni.” Journal of Food Protection 55, no. 7: 514–517.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Workman, S. N., G. E. Mathison, and M. C. Lavoie. 2005. “Pet Dogs and Chicken Meat as Reservoirs of Campylobacter spp. in Barbados.” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 43, no. 6: 2642–2650.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeh, H.‐Y., N. A. Cox, A. Hinton Jr., M. E. Berrang, J. R. P. Lawrence, and T. M. Thompson. 2022. “Prevalence and Characterization of Quinolone Resistance in Campylobacter spp. Isolates in Chicken Livers From Retail Stores in Georgia, USA.” Journal of Food Protection 85, no. 3: 406–413.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>