<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39355272</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1932-0248</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of hunger &amp; environmental nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Hunger Environ Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Perceived Food-Related Responsibilities Among Adults Aged 60 Years and Older.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>571</StartPage><EndPage>586</EndPage><MedlinePgn>571-586</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1080/19320248.2022.2088264</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Food citizenship states individuals, organizations, and governments have responsibilities for their actions and policies around food. We conducted twenty semi-structured interviews with older adults as an exploratory study about perceived food-related responsibilities. The government and agribusiness were seen as responsible for food safety and how healthy foods are. The government, agribusiness, and emergency food providers were seen as responsible for availability and accessibility. Individuals were seen as having a personal responsibility to access and choose healthy, safe foods. These results have important implications for understanding how older adults think about the roles themselves and others play in the food system.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brady</LastName><ForeName>Patrick J</ForeName><Initials>PJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5492-7333</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Epidemiology and Community Health, University of Minnesota School of Public Health, 1300 S 2 Street Suite 300, Minneapolis, MN, 55455.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Askelson</LastName><ForeName>Natoshia M</ForeName><Initials>NM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3464-8214</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community and Behavioral Health, University of Iowa College of Public Health, 145 N. Riverside Drive, Iowa City, IA 52246.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Iowa Public Policy Center, 310 S Grand Ave, Iowa City, IA 52242.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thompson</LastName><ForeName>Helaina</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8278-6753</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community and Behavioral Health, University of Iowa College of Public Health, 145 N. Riverside Drive, Iowa City, IA 52246.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashida</LastName><ForeName>Sato</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5644-8523</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community and Behavioral Health, University of Iowa College of Public Health, 145 N. Riverside Drive, Iowa City, IA 52246.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nothwehr</LastName><ForeName>Faryle</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7343-0552</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community and Behavioral Health, University of Iowa College of Public Health, 145 N. Riverside Drive, Iowa City, IA 52246.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Janssen</LastName><ForeName>Brandi</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7889-3633</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Occupational and Environmental Health, University of Iowa College of Public Health, 145 N. Riverside Drive, Iowa City, IA 52246.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frisvold</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8720-8995</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics, Tippie College of Business, University of Iowa, 21 E Market Street, Iowa City, IA, 52242.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Iowa Public Policy Center, 310 S Grand Ave, Iowa City, IA 52242.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>T32 DK083250</GrantID><Acronym>DK</Acronym><Agency>NIDDK NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Hunger Environ Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285290</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-0256</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food access</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food insecurity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Perceived responsibilities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Qualitative research</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Disclosure: The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39355272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1815822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11441630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19320248.2022.2088264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Coleman-Jensen A, Rabbitt M, Gregory C, Singh A Household Food Security in the United States in 2019. Washington, DC, United States: United States Department of Agriculture Economic Research Service; 2020. Economic Research Report Number 275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharya J, Currie J, Haider S. Poverty, food insecurity, and nutritional outcomes in children and adults. Journal of Health Economics. 2004;23(4):839–862.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15587700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JS, Frongillo EA. Nutritional and health consequences are associated with food insecurity among US elderly persons. The Journal of Nutrition. 2001;131(5):1503–1509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11340107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung SE, Kim S, Bishop A, Hermann J. Poor Nutritional Status among Low-Income Older Adults: Examining the Interconnection between Self-Care Capacity, Food Insecurity, and Depression. Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics. 2018;119(10):1687–1694.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29921540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seligman HK, Laraia BA, Kushel MB. Food insecurity is associated with chronic disease among low-income NHANES participants. The Journal of Nutrition. 2009;140(2):304–310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2806885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20032485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziliak JP, Gundersen C. The Health Consequences of Senior Hunger in The United States: Evidence from the 1999–2014 NHANES. Washington, DC, United States: Feeding America; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan L, Sherry B, Njai R, Blanck HM. Food insecurity is associated with obesity among US adults in 12 states. Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics. 2012;112(9):1403–1409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4584410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22939441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Research &amp; Educational Trust. Social determinants of health series: Food insecurity and the role of hospitals. Chicago, IL: Health Research &amp; Educational Trust; 2017. Accessed at www.aha.org/foodinsecurity</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JS. Food insecurity and healthcare costs: research strategies using local, state, and national data sources for older adults. Advances in Nutrition. 2013;4(1):42–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3648738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23319122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattarai GR, Duffy PA, Raymond J. Use of food pantries and food stamps in low-income households in the United States. Journal of Consumer Affairs. 2005;39(2):276–298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gergerich E, Shobe M, Christy K. Sustaining our nation’s seniors through federal food and nutrition programs. Journal of Nutrition in Gerontology and Geriatrics. 2015;34(3): 273–291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26267441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoerr KA, Francis SL, Margrett JA, Peterson M, Franke WD. Promoting the congregate meal program to the next generation of rural-residing older adults. Journal of Nutrition in Gerontology and Geriatrics. 2016;35(2):113–123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27153251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker LE. Tending cultural landscapes and food citizenship in Toronto’s community gardens. Geographical Review. 2004;94(3):305–325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rojas A, Valley W, Mansfield B, Orrego E, Chapman GE, Harlap Y. Toward food system sustainability through school food system change: Think&amp;EatGreen@ School and the making of a community-university research alliance. Sustainability. 2011;3(5):763–788.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welsh J, MacRae R. Food citizenship and community food security: lessons from Toronto, Canada. Canadian Journal of Development Studies/Revue Canadienne d’Etudes du Développement. 1998:19(4);237–255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozano-Cabedo C, Gómez-Benito C. A theoretical model of Food citizenship for the analysis of social praxis. Journal of Agricultural and Environmental Ethics. 2017;30(1): 1–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brownell KD. Personal responsibility and control over our bodies: When expectation exceeds reality. Health Psychology. 1991:10(5);303–310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1935864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hart Research Associates &amp; Chesapeake Beach Consulting. American’s View on Hunger. Washington DC, United States: Food Research and Access Center; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kersh R, Morone J. How the personal becomes political: prohibitions, public health, and obesity. Studies in American Political Development. 2002:16(2);162–175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leichter HM. “Evil habits” and “personal choices”: assigning responsibility for health in the 20th century. The Milbank Quarterly, 2003;81(4):603–626.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2690243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14678481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kriflik LS, Yeatman H. Food scares and sustainability: a consumer perspective. Health, Risk &amp; Society. 2005;7(1):11–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowler EA, O’Connor D. Rights-based approaches to addressing food poverty and food insecurity in Ireland and UK. Social Science &amp; Medicine. 2012;74(1):44–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22000764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowler EA, Kneafsey M, Lambie H, Inman A, Collier R. Thinking about ‘food security’: engaging with UK consumers. Critical Public Health. 2011;21(4):403–416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elms MB. Economic Inequality, Food Insecurity, and the Erosion of Equality of Capabilities in the United States. Business &amp; Society. 2018;57(6):1045–1074.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hager ER, Quigg AM, Black MM, Coleman SM, Heeren T, Rose-Jacobs R, et al. Development and validity of a 2-item screen to identify families at risk for food insecurity. Pediatrics. 2010;126(1):e26–e32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20595453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson OC. Sampling in interview-based qualitative research: A theoretical and practical guide. Qualitative Research in Psychology. 2014;11(1):25–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandelowski M Sample size in qualitative research. Research in Nursing &amp; Health, 1995;18(2):179–183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7899572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SocioCultural Research Consultants, LLC. Dedoose web application for managing, analyzing, and presenting qualitative and mixed method research data [computer software]. Version 8.3.41. Los Angeles, CA, United States: SocioCultural Research Consultants, LLC; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qualitative Research in Psychology. 2006;3(2):77–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Vries H, Elliott MN, Kanouse DE, Teleki SS. Using pooled kappa to summarize interrater agreement across many items. Field methods. 2008;20(3):272–282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Landis JR, Koch GG. The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data. Biometrics. 1977;159–174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">843571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rose D, Richards R. Food store access and household fruit and vegetable use among participants in the US Food Stamp Program. Public health nutrition. 2004;7(8):1081–1088.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15548347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Treuhaft S, Karpyn A. The grocery gap: Who has access to healthy food and why it matters. Oakland, CA, United States of America: PolicyLink; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poppendieck J Food assistance, hunger and the end of welfare in the USA. In First world hunger revisited. Palgrave Macmillan, London. 2014; 176–190</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaplan KH, Kirk KJ, Lich KM, et al. Accessibility to emergency food systems in south-central Indiana evaluated by spatiotemporal indices of pressure at county and pantry level. Nature Food. 2020;1(5):284–291.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nam Y, &amp; Jung HJ Welfare reform and older immigrants: Food stamp program participation and food insecurity. The Gerontologist. 2008;48(1):42–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18381831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunewardena N Pathologizing poverty: Structural forces versus personal deficit theories in the feminization of poverty. Journal of Educational Controversy. 2009;4(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pemberton S, Fahmy E, Sutton E, Bell K. Navigating the stigmatised identities of poverty in austere times: Resisting and responding to narratives of personal failure. Critical Social Policy. 2016;36(1):21–37.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>