<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39357079</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0372</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>91</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current opinion in immunology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Opin Immunol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Role of allergen immunotherapy and biologics in allergic diseases.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>102494</StartPage><MedlinePgn>102494</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.coi.2024.102494</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0952-7915(24)00084-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The rise in the prevalence of allergic diseases has become a global health burden. Allergic diseases are a group of immune-mediated disorders characterized by IgE-mediated conditions resulting from a type 2 helper T cell (Th2)-skewed immune response. This review aims to comprehensively summarize recent research on the roles of allergen immunotherapy (AIT) and biologics in allergic diseases. Specifically, we review the mechanisms of AIT and biologics in modulating innate and adaptive immunity involved in allergic disease pathogenesis, as well as their safety and efficacy in the treatment of allergic diseases. We also discuss current new AIT strategies such as recombinant allergen-based vaccines and allergen extract nanoencapsulation. Further research is needed to understand immune tolerance mechanisms beyond the Th2 pathway and to characterize immunological changes in responders and nonresponders to AIT or biologics. This additional research may uncover new targets for monitoring treatment responses and developing personalized treatment strategies for allergic diseases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoying</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simonin</LastName><ForeName>Elisabeth M</ForeName><Initials>EM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jung</LastName><ForeName>Youn S</ForeName><Initials>YS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Galli</LastName><ForeName>Stephen J</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, CA, USA; Sean N. Parker Center for Allergy and Asthma Research, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, CA, USA; Department of Pathology, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nadeau</LastName><ForeName>Kari C</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA. Electronic address: knadeau@hsph.harvard.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Opin Immunol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8900118</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0952-7915</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest Dr. Nadeau reports grants from National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID), National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI), National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS), and Food Allergy Research &amp; Education (FARE); Stock options from IgGenix, Seed Health, ClostraBio, Cour, Alladapt; Advisor at Cour Pharma; Consultant for Excellergy, Red tree ventures, Before Brands, Alladapt, Cour, Latitude, Regeneron, and IgGenix; Co-founder of Before Brands, Alladapt, Latitude, and IgGenix; National Scientific Committee member at Immune Tolerance Network (ITN), and National Institutes of Health (NIH) clinical research centers; patents include ‘Mixed allergen com-position and methods for using the same,’ ‘Granulocyte-based methods for detecting and monitoring immune system disorders,’ and ‘Methods and Assays for Detecting and Quantifying Pure Subpopulations of White Blood Cells in Immune System Disorders.’ The other authors have no conflicts of interest to report.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39357079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2024.102494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0952-7915(24)00084-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>