<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39354884</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Ferulic acid: extraction, estimation, bioactivity and applications for human health and food.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13931</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Ferulic acid ((E)-3-(4-hydroxy-3-methoxy-phenyl) prop-2-enoic acid) is a derivative of caffeic acid found in most plants. This abundant phenolic compound exhibits significant antioxidant capacity and a broad spectrum of therapeutic effects, including anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, anticancer, antidiabetic, cardiovascular and neuroprotective activities. It is absorbed more quickly by the body and stays in the bloodstream for a longer period compared with other phenolic acids. It is widely used in the food (namely whole grains, fruits, vegetables and coffee), pharmaceutical and cosmetics industries. The current review highlights ferulic acid and its pharmacological activities, reported mechanisms of action, food applications (food preservative, food additive, food processing, food supplements and in food packaging in the form of edible films) and role in human health. In the future, the demand for ferulic acid in the food and pharmaceutical industries will increase. © 2024 The Author(s). Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Mukul</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0550-262X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology and Nutrition, Lovely Professional University, Phagwara, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaushik</LastName><ForeName>Deepika</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Faculty of Applied Sciences and Biotechnology, Shoolini University, Solan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shubham</LastName><ForeName>Shubham</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Innovation Engineering, University of Salento, Brindisi, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Ashwani</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food Technology, Bundelkhand University, Jhansi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Vishal</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology and Nutrition, Lovely Professional University, Phagwara, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oz</LastName><ForeName>Emel</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3766-2713</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering, Agriculture Faculty, Ataturk University, Erzurum, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brennan</LastName><ForeName>Charles</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>RMIT University, School of Science, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Maomao</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9259-1992</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Joint Laboratory on Food Safety, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Proestos</LastName><ForeName>Charalampos</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3450-5969</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Food Chemistry, Department of Chemistry, School of Sciences, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Athens, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Çadırcı</LastName><ForeName>Kenan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Erzurum Regional Training and Research Hospital, Health Sciences University, Erzurum, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bayrak</LastName><ForeName>Muharrem</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Erzurum Regional Training and Research Hospital, Health Sciences University, Erzurum, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elobeid</LastName><ForeName>Tahra</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1448-9815</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Human Nutrition Department, College of Health Sciences, QU Health, Qatar University, Doha, Qatar.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Karav</LastName><ForeName>Sercan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Çanakkale Onsekiz Mart University, Çanakkale, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oz</LastName><ForeName>Fatih</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5300-7519</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering, Agriculture Faculty, Ataturk University, Erzurum, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiapoptotic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antifibrosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antioxidant</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anti‐inflammatory</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bioactive component</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ferulic acid</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39354884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Li S, Ma J, Li J, Qu X and Lei B, Sprayable self‐assembly multifunctional bioactive poly (ferulic acid) hydrogel for rapid MRSA infected wound repair. J Biomed Mater Res Part A 112:390–401 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song W, Xin J and Yu C, Alkyl ferulic acid esters: evaluating their structure and antibacterial properties. Front Microbiol 14:10–13 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D, Rui YX, Guo SD, Luan F, Liu R and Zeng N, Ferulic acid: a review of its pharmacology, pharmacokinetics and derivatives. Life Sci 284:119921 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai Y, Wang T, Fu Y, Yu T, Ding Y and Nie H, Ferulic acid: a review of pharmacology, toxicology, and therapeutic effects on pulmonary diseases. Int J Mol Sci 24:8011 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zduńska K, Dana A, Kolodziejczak A and Rotsztejn H, Antioxidant properties of ferulic acid and its possible application. Skin Pharmacol Physiol 31:332–336 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao L, Xue D, Liu X, Wang C, Fang D, Zhang J et al., Ferulic acid production from wheat bran by integration of enzymatic pretreatment and a cold‐adapted carboxylesterase catalysis. Bioresour Technol 385:129435 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhuang XM, Lin CHEN, Yan TAN, Hai‐Ying YANG, Chuang LU, Yue GAO et al., Identification of human cytochrome P450 and UGT enzymes involved in the metabolism of ferulic acid, a major bioactive component in traditional Chinese medicines. CJNM 15:695–702 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zduńska‐Pęciak K, Kołodziejczak A and Rotsztejn H, Two superior antioxidants: ferulic acid and ascorbic acid in reducing signs of photoaging—a split‐face comparative study. Dermatol Ther 35:15254 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu P, Xia B, Pienaar J and Zhao X, The past, present and future of carbon labelling for construction materials–a review. Build Environ 77:160–168 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng X, Li R, Ma Y, Fan Q and Huang W, The synthesis of highly electroactive N‐doped carbon nanotube/polyaniline/Au nanocomposites and their application to the biosensor. Synth Mets 161:1940–1945 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh V, Joung D, Zhai L, Das S, Khondaker SI and Seal S, Graphene based materials: past, present and future. Prog Mater Sci 56:1178–1271 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuilla T, Bhadra S, Yao D, Kim NH, Bose S and Lee JH, Recent advances in graphene based polymer composites. Prog Poly Sci 35:1350–1375 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y, Jia M, Zhang M and Wen Q, Preparation of stable aqueous dispersion of graphene nanosheets and their electrochemical capacitive properties. Appl Surface Sci 264:787–793 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendoza‐Sanchez B, Rasche B, Nicolosi V and Grant PS, Scaleable ultra‐thin and high power density graphene electrochemical capacitor electrodes manufactured by aqueous exfoliation and spray deposition. Carbon 52:337–346 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu LJ, Gao X, Zhang P, Feng SL, Hu FD, Li YD et al., Ultrasensitive detection of ferulic acid using poly (diallyldimethylammonium chloride) functionalized graphene‐based electrochemical sensor. J Analyt Met Chem 2014:1–9 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buffon E and Stradiotto NR, A molecularly imprinted polymer on reduced graphene oxide‐gold nanoparticles modified screen‐printed electrode for selective determination of ferulic acid in orange peels. Microchem J 167:106339 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orhan E, Aydın B, Açık L, Oz F and Varzakas T, Antibacterial efficiencies of CVD‐PECVD graphene nanostructures synthesized onto glass and nickel substrates against Escherichia coli and Staphylococcus aureus bacteria. Appl Sci 11:7922 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng MH, Nu'man AH and Hasliyanti A, Recycling of deep eutectic solvent in the extraction of ferulic acid from oil palm empty fruit bunch. J Separat Sci 47:1–23 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stavova E, Porizka J, Stursa V, Enev V and Divis P, Extraction of ferulic acid from wheat bran by alkaline hydrolysis. MendelNet 24:574–579 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris R, Spectrophotometry. Curr Protoc Essent Lab 11:1–12 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadhav AP, Kareparamban JA, Nikam PH and Kadam VJ, Spectrophotometric estimation of ferulic acid from Ferula asafoetida by Folin‐ciocalteu's reagent. Der Pharm Sin 3:680–684 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aguilar‐Hernández I, Afseth NK, López‐Luke T, Contreras‐Torres FF, Wold JP and Ornelas‐Soto N, Surface enhanced Raman spectroscopy of phenolic antioxidants: a systematic evaluation of ferulic acid, p‐coumaric acid, caffeic acid and sinapic acid. Vib Spectrosc 89:113–122 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian W, Chen G, Gui Y, Zhang G and Li Y, Rapid quantification of total phenolics and ferulic acid in whole wheat using UV–vis spectrophotometry. Food Control 123:107691 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Divakaran SA and Anitha CT, Estimation of ferulic acid from selected plant materials by spectrophotometry and high performance liquid chromatography. J Appl Nat Sci 13:815–819 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozano‐Sánchez J, Borrás‐Linares I, Sass‐Kiss A and Segura‐Carretero A, Chromatographic technique: high‐performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), in Modern techniques for food authentication. Academic Press, United States, pp. 459–526 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kareparamban JA, Nikam PH, Jadhav AP and Kadam VJ, A validated high‐performance liquid chromatograhy method for estimation of ferulic acid in asafoetida and polyherbal preparation. Indian J Pharm Sci 75:493 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jankovska PETRA, Copikova J and Sinitsya ANDRIY, The determination of ferulic acid in sugar beet pulp. Czech. J Food Sci 19:143–147 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira M, Lang GH, de Oliveira RC and Lovegrove A, Ferulic acid, in A Centum of Valuable Plant Bioactives. Academic Press, United States, pp. 631–657 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shakeel F, Salem‐Bekhit MM, Haq N and Siddiqui NA, Solubility and thermodynamics of ferulic acid in different neat solvents: measurement, correlation and molecular interactions. J Molec Liq 236:144–150 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karademir Y, Mackie A, Tuohy K and Dye L, Effects of ferulic acid on cognitive function: a systematic review. Mol Nutr Food Res 68:1–16 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira SE and Batista R, Ferulic acid and naturally occurring compounds bearing a feruloyl moiety: a review on their structures, occurrence, and potential health benefits. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 16:580–616 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bezerra GSN, Pereira MAV, Ostrosky EA, Barbosa EG, de Moura MDFV, Ferrari M et al., Compatibility study between ferulic acid and excipients used in cosmetic formulations by TG/DTG, DSC and FTIR. J Therm Anal Calorim 127:1683–1691 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Setayeshnasab M, Sabzalian MR and Rahimmalek M, The relation between apomictic seed production and morpho‐physiological characteristics in a world collection of castor bean (Ricinus communis L.). Sci Rep 14:5013 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary N and Dangi P, Fruit and vegetable waste: a taste of future foods, in Edible Food Packaging: Applications, Innovations and Sustainability. Springer Nature Singapore, Singapore, pp. 115–147 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sethi S, Kaur L, Nath P and Yadav DN, Bioactive Compounds and Phytonutrients From Cereals, in Plant‐Based Bioactive Compounds and Food Ingredients. Apple Academic Press, United States, pp. 155–205 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tramontina R, Ciancaglini I, Roman EK, Chacón MG, Corrêa TL, Dixon N et al., Sustainable biosynthetic pathways to value‐added bioproducts from hydroxycinnamic acids. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 107:4165–4185 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos‐Buelga C, González‐Paramás AM and González‐Manzano S, Phenolic acids and derivatives: description, sources, properties, and applications, in Natural Secondary Metabolites: From Nature, through Science, to Industry. Springer International Publishing, Cham, pp. 37–72 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhor C, Wafaa L, Ghzaiel I, Kessas K, Zarrouk A, Ksila M et al., Effects of polyphenols and their metabolites on age‐related diseases. Biochem Pharmacol 115674:115674 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tee‐ngam P, Nunant N, Rattanarat P, Siangproh W and Chailapakul O, Simple and rapid determination of ferulic acid levels in food and cosmetic samples using paper‐based platforms. Sensors 13:13039–13053 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar N and Pruthi V, Potential applications of ferulic acid from natural sources. Biotechnol Rep 4:86–93 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikołajczak N, Pilarski W, Gęsiński K and Tańska M, Effect of ferulic acid and its derivatives on cold‐pressed flaxseed oil oxidative stability and bioactive compounds retention during oxidation. Foods 12:1088 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moldovan M, Lahmar A, Bogdan C, Părăuan S, Tomuţă I and Crişan M, Formulation and evaluation of a water‐in‐oil cream containing herbal active ingredients and ferulic acid. Clujul Med 90:212–219 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sova M and Saso L, Natural sources, pharmacokinetics, biological activities and health benefits of hydroxycinnamic acids and their metabolites. Nutrients 12:2190 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Teng W, Wang J, Wang Y, Zhang Y and Cao J, The intestinal delivery systems of ferulic acid: absorption, metabolism, influencing factors, and potential applications. Food Fronts 5:1–19 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam MA, Anti‐hypertensive effect of cereal antioxidant ferulic acid and its mechanism of action. Front Nutr 6:121 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisoschi AM and Pop A, The role of antioxidants in the chemistry of oxidative stress: a review. Eur J Med Chem 97:55–74 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi R, Kim BH, Naowaboot J, Lee MY, Hyun MR, Cho EJ et al., Effects of ferulic acid on diabetic nephropathy in a rat model of type 2 diabetes. Exp Mol Med 43:676–683 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury S, Ghosh S, Rashid K and Sil PC, Deciphering the role of ferulic acid against streptozotocin‐induced cellular stress in the cardiac tissue of diabetic rats. Food Chem Toxicol 97:187–198 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He S, Guo Y, Zhao J, Xu X, Song J, Wang N et al., Ferulic acid protects against heat stress‐induced intestinal epithelial barrier dysfunction in IEC‐6 cells via the PI3K/Akt‐mediated Nrf2/HO‐1 signaling pathway. Int J Hyperther 35:112–121 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y, Wen L, Sun J, Bai W, Jiao R, Hu Y et al., Cytoprotective mechanism of ferulic acid against high glucose‐induced oxidative stress in cardiomyocytes and hepatocytes. Food Nutr Res 60:30323 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bami E, Ozakpınar OB, Ozdemir‐Kumral ZN, Köroglu K, Ercan F, Cirakli Z et al., Protective effect of ferulic acid on cisplatin induced nephrotoxicity in rats. Environ Toxicol Pharmacol 54:105–111 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catino S, Paciello F, Miceli F, Rolesi R, Troiani D, Calabrese V et al., Ferulic acid regulates the Nrf2/heme oxygenase‐1 system and counteracts trimethyltin‐induced neuronal damage in the human neuroblastoma cell line SH‐SY5Y. Front Pharmacol 6:305 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neopane D, Ansari VA and Singh A, Ferulic acid: signaling pathways in aging. Drug Res 73:318–324 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson EM, Jayabalan R, Patra S and Suh JW, Anticancer, anti‐inflammatory, and immune modulatory activity of ferulic acid fructo‐oligosaccharide conjugated microparticle. bioRxiv 5:1–58 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury S, Ghosh S, Das AK and Sil PC, Ferulic acid protects hyperglycemia‐induced kidney damage by regulating oxidative insult, inflammation and autophagy. Front Pharmacol 10:27 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Sun X, Mariga AM, Yang Q, Fang Y, Hu Q et al., Effects of ferulic acid on the polymerization behavior of gluten protein and its components. Food Hydrocoll 147:109388 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary A, Jaswal VS, Choudhary S, Sharma A, Beniwal V, Tuli HS et al., Ferulic acid: a promising therapeutic phytochemical and recent patents advances. Recent Pat Inflamm 13:115–123 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar SN, Nair H and Prakash Kumar B, Anti‐inflammatory effect of ferulic acid, in Proceedings of International Conference on Recent Advances in Biological Science, Vol. 187. University of Kerala, India (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad MF, Aziz T, Naseem N, Shadab GHA, Ahsan H, Younus H et al., Beneficial effects of ferulic acid in streptozotocin‐induced diabetic neuropathy in male Wistar rats. Forum Nutr 49:8 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srinivasan M, Sudheer AR and Menon VP, Ferulic acid: therapeutic potential through its antioxidant property. J Clin Biochem Nutr 40:92–100 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu YM, Shen JD, Xu LP, Li HB, Li YC and Yi LT, Ferulic acid inhibits neuro‐inflammation in mice exposed to chronic unpredictable mild stress. Int Immunopharmacol 45:128–134 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman SU, Ali T, Alam SI, Ullah R, Zeb A, Lee KW et al., Ferulic acid rescues LPS‐induced neurotoxicity via modulation of the TLR4 receptor in the mouse hippocampus. Mol Neurobiol 56:2774–2790 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan J, Ge K, Mu J, Rong J, Zhang L, Wang B et al., Ferulic acid attenuated acetaminophen‐induced hepatotoxicity though down‐regulating the cytochrome P 2E1 and inhibiting toll‐like receptor 4 signaling‐mediated inflammation in mice. Am J Transl Res 8:4205–4214 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin P, Zhang Z, Li J, Shi Y, Jin N, Zou W et al., Ferulic acid inhibits bovine endometrial epithelial cells against LPS‐induced inflammation via suppressing NK‐κB and MAPK pathway. Res Vet Sci 126:164–169 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H, Ruan XZ, Powis SH, Fernando R, Mon WY, Wheeler DC et al., EPA and DHA reduce LPS‐induced inflammation responses in HK‐2 cells: evidence for a PPAR‐γ–dependent mechanism. Kidney Int 67:867–874 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoud AM, Hussein OE, Abd El‐Twab SM and Hozayen WG, Ferulic acid protects against methotrexate nephrotoxicity via activation of Nrf2/ARE/HO‐1 signaling and PPARγ, and suppression of NF‐κB/NLRP3 inflammasome axis. Food Funct 10:4593–4607 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghasemi‐Dehnoo M, Amini‐Khoei H, Lorigooini Z, AnjomShoa M and Rafieian‐Kopaei M, Ferulic acid ameliorates ulcerative colitis in a rat model via the inhibition of two LPS‐TLR4‐NF‐κB and NF‐κB‐INOS‐NO signaling pathways and thus alleviating the inflammatory, oxidative and apoptotic conditions in the colon tissue. Inflammopharmacology 31:2587–2597 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kesavardhana S, Malireddi RS and Kanneganti TD, Caspases in cell death, inflammation, and pyroptosis. Ann Rev Immunol 38:567–595 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng JH, Viacava Follis A, Kriwacki RW and Moldoveanu T, Discoveries and controversies in BCL‐2 protein‐mediated apoptosis. FEBS J 283:2690–2700 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volkmann N, Marassi FM, Newmeyer DD and Hanein D, The rheostat in the membrane: BCL‐2 family proteins and apoptosis. Cell Death Differ 21:206–215 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y and Ma K, NLRC4 inflammasome activation regulated by TNF‐α promotes inflammatory responses in nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 511:524–530 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Jin X, Yang Z, Hu Z, Li Q, Dong J et al., Ferulic acid attenuates difenoconazole exposure induced liver injury in carp by modulating oxidative damage, inflammation and apoptosis. Comp Biochem Physiol C: Toxicol Pharmacol 109885:109885 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng CY, Tang NY, Kao ST and Hsieh CL, Ferulic acid administered at various time points protects against cerebral infarction by activating p38 MAPK/p90RSK/CREB/Bcl‐2 anti‐apoptotic signaling in the subacute phase of cerebral ischemia‐reperfusion injury in rats. PLoS One 11:1–20 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiskirchen R, Weiskirchen S and Tacke F, Organ and tissue fibrosis: molecular signals, cellular mechanisms and translational implications. Mol Aspects Med 65:2–15 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu C, Guo X, Cui X, Su G and Wang H, Functional food chemical ingredient strategies for non‐alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and hepatic fibrosis: chemical properties, health benefits, action, and application. Curr Nutr Rep 13:1–14 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rockey DC, Bell PD and Hill JA, Fibrosis—a common pathway to organ injury and failure. N Engl J Med 372:1138–1149 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Y and Shi L, Molecular mechanism and research progress on pharmacology of ferulic acid in liver diseases. Front Pharmacol 14:1–20 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayamani J, Naisini A, Madhan B and Shanmugam G, Ferulic acid, a natural phenolic compound, as a potential inhibitor for collagen fibril formation and its propagation. Int J Biol Macromol 113:277–284 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali SA, Saifi MA, Pulivendala G, Godugu C and Talla V, Ferulic acid ameliorates the progression of pulmonary fibrosis via inhibition of TGF‐β/smad signalling. Food Chem Toxicol 149:111980 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei MG, Sun W, He WM, Ni L and Yang YY, Ferulic acid attenuates TGF‐β1‐induced renal cellular fibrosis in NRK‐52E cells by inhibiting Smad/ILK/snail pathway. eCAM 2015:1–7 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rukkumani R, Priyanka A, Sankar P and Menon VP, Ferulic acid influences hepatic expression pattern of matrix metalloproteinases during alcohol and PUFA induced toxicity. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci 16:2147–2153 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staniforth V, Huang WC, Aravindaram K and Yang NS, Ferulic acid, a phenolic phytochemical, inhibits UVB‐induced matrix metalloproteinases in mouse skin via posttranslational mechanisms. J Nutr Biochem 23:443–451 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao PQ, Zhang XY, Guo H, Yang Y, An S, Liu Y et al., Research progress on pathophysiological function of SOS1 protein. Sheng li xue bao:[Acta Physiol Sin] 70:565–570 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawie HG, Ahmed OM, Shabana ME, Elqattan GM, EL‐Kassaby MI and Abou‐Seif HS, Ferulic acid attenuated diethylnitrosamine‐provoked hepato‐renal damage and malfunction by suppressing oxidative stress, abating inflammation and upregulating nuclear factor erythroid related factor‐2 signaling. Egypt Pharm J 23:16–27 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou YZ, Yang J, Zhao GR and Yuan YJ, Ferulic acid inhibits vascular smooth muscle cell proliferation induced by angiotensin II. Eur J Pharmacol 499:85–90 (2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X and Gao ZP, Research progress in ferulic acid. Mod Chin Med 22:138–147 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raj PS, Nair A, Rani MP, Rajankutty K, Ranjith S and Raghu KG, Ferulic acid attenuates high glucose‐induced MAM alterations via PACS2/IP3R2/FUNDC1/VDAC1 pathway activating proapoptotic proteins and ameliorates cardiomyopathy in diabetic rats. Intl J Cardiol 372:101–109 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang XX, Zhao DS, Wang J, Zhou H, Wang L, Mao JL et al., The treatment of cardiovascular diseases: a review of ferulic acid and its derivatives. Pharmazie‐ Int J Pharmaceu Sci 76:55–60 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salau VF, Erukainure OL, Olofinsan KA, Msomi NZ, Ijomone OK and Islam MS, Ferulic acid mitigates diabetic cardiomyopathy via modulation of metabolic abnormalities in cardiac tissues of diabetic rats. Fundam Clin Pharmacol 37:44–59 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Wu J, Xu F, Chu C, Li X, Shi X et al., Use of ferulic acid in the management of diabetes mellitus and its complications. Molecules 27:6010 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batista R, Uses and potential applications of ferulic acid, in Ferulic Acid: Antioxidant Properties, Uses and Potential Health Benefits, ed. by Warren B, Nova Science Publishers, Inc., New York, USA, pp. 39–70 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicolau‐Lapeña I, Aguiló‐Aguayo I, Kramer B, Abadias M, Viñas I and Muranyi P, Combination of ferulic acid with Aloe vera gel or alginate coatings for shelf‐life prolongation of fresh‐cut apples. Food Packag Shelf Life 27:100620 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang G, Liu Y, Yong H, Zong S, Jin C and Liu J, Effect of ferulic acid‐grafted‐chitosan coating on the quality of pork during refrigerated storage. Foods 10:1374 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ordoñez R, Atarés L and Chiralt A, Multilayer antimicrobial films based on starch and PLA with superficially incorporated ferulic or cinnamic acids for active food packaging purposes. Food Chem Adv 2:100250 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das AB, Goud VV and Das C, Phenolic compounds as functional ingredients in beverages, in Value‐Added Ingredients and Enrichments of Beverages. Academic Press, United States, pp. 285–323 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turcov D, Barna S, Profire LEN, Iacob AT, Lisa G, Puitel A et al., Physico‐chemical characterization of the antioxidant mixture resveratrol‐ferulic acid for applications in dermato‐cosmetic products. Farmacia 70:3–416 (2022).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>