<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39359621</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2753-8095</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Sustainable food technology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sustain Food Technol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Resilient sustainable current and emerging technologies for foodborne pathogen detection.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1039/d4fb00192c</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Foodborne pathogens such as <i>Salmonella</i>, <i>Escherichia coli</i> and <i>Listeria</i> pose significant risks to human health. The World Health Organization estimates that 2.2 million deaths per year are directly caused by foodborne and waterborne bacterial diseases worldwide. Accordingly, detecting pathogens in food is essential to ensure that our food is safe. This review explores the critical role of novel technologies in enhancing food safety practices whilst delving into adopting and integrating innovative, resilient and sustainable approaches in the food supply chain. Further, applying novel, emerging advanced analytical techniques such as Raman spectroscopy and nanotechnology based biosensors in food contamination detection is discussed. These advanced technologies show the promise of real-time monitoring, traceability, and predictive analytics to identify and mitigate potential hazards before they reach consumers. They can provide rapid and accurate results and ensure the integrity of food products. Furthermore, the herein-highlighted synergistic integration of these technologies offers a promising path toward a safer and more transparent food system, thereby addressing the challenges of today's globalised food market and laying the platform for developing multimodal technologies for affordable, sensitive and rapid pathogen detection along the different stages of the food chain, from "farm to fork".</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>This journal is © The Royal Society of Chemistry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhowmik</LastName><ForeName>Debarati</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Chemical Engineering, University of Birmingham Birmingham B15 2TT UK p.goldbergoppenheimer@bham.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rickard</LastName><ForeName>Jonathan James Stanely</ForeName><Initials>JJS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Chemical Engineering, University of Birmingham Birmingham B15 2TT UK p.goldbergoppenheimer@bham.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physics, Cavendish Laboratory, University of Cambridge Cambridge UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jelinek</LastName><ForeName>Raz</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0336-1384</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Ben Gurion University of the Negev 84105 Beer Sheva Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goldberg Oppenheimer</LastName><ForeName>Pola</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1014-4724</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Chemical Engineering, University of Birmingham Birmingham B15 2TT UK p.goldbergoppenheimer@bham.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Healthcare Technologies Institute Mindelsohn Way Birmingham B15 2TH UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sustain Food Technol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918900799406676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2753-8095</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39359621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11443698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/d4fb00192c</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">d4fb00192c</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>
Mycotoxins | FDA, [cited 2024 Aug 21], available from: https://www.fda.gov/food/natural-toxins-food/mycotoxins</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Y. Liu X. Bao Y. Niu L. Recent Advances in Photoelectrochemical Sensors for Analysis of Toxins and Abused Drugs in the Environment. Chemosensors. 2023;11:412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Official Statistics United Kingdom Food Security Report 2021: Theme 5: Food Safety and Consumer Confidence, 2021, [cited 2022 Oct 12]. available from: https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/united-kingdom-food-security-report-2021/united-kingdom-food-security-report-2021-theme-5-food-safety-and-consumer-confidence</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Z. Qiu C. Huang L. Gao Y. Tang D. Microelectromechanical Microsystems-Supported Photothermal Immunoassay for Point-of-Care Testing of Aflatoxin B1 in Foodstuff. Anal. Chem. 2023;95(8):4212–4219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36780374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nehra M. Kumar V. Kumar R. Dilbaghi N. Kumar S. Current Scenario of Pathogen Detection Techniques in Agro-Food Sector. Biosensors. 2022;12:489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9313409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35884292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giordano C. Franco S. Household food waste from an international perspective. Sustainability. 2021;13(9):1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dib O. H. Assaf A. Pean A. Durand M. J. Jouanneau S. Ramanathan R. et al., Raman Spectroscopy Application in Food Waste Analysis: A Step towards a Portable Food Quality-Warning System. Sustainability. 2023;15(1):188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
The World Bank, 2022, [cited 2022 Oct 8], available from: https://www.worldbank.org/en/programs/food-systems-2030/food-systems-transformation</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misiou O. Koutsoumanis K. Climate change and its implications for food safety and spoilage. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2022;26:142–152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Ingram J., Zurek M., Sykes R. and O'Kane E., Exploring the resilience of the UK food system in a global context, 2019, vol. 16, available from: https://www.foodsecurity.ac.uk/publications/exploring-the-resilience-of-the-uk-food-system-in-a-global-context.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
UNIDO, 2022, available from, https://www.unido.org/stories/helping-developing-countries-get-speed-food-safety-standards</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White R. J. Razgour O. Emerging zoonotic diseases originating in mammals: a systematic review of effects of anthropogenic land-use change. Mamm Rev. 2020;50(4):336–352.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7300897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32836691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stöckel S. Kirchhoff J. Neugebauer U. Rösch P. Popp J. The application of Raman spectroscopy for the detection and identification of microorganisms. J. Raman Spectrosc. 2016;47(1):89–109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berbegal C. Fragasso M. Russo P. Bimbo F. Grieco F. Spano G. et al., Climate changes and food quality: The potential of microbial activities as mitigating strategies in the wine sector. Fermentation. 2019;5(4):1–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Food ingredients, 2022, [cited 2022 Sep 19]. available from: https://www.foodingredientsfirst.com/news/uk-still-battles-with-food-regulation-post-brexit-investigation-warns-of-more-delays-and-uncertainty.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sperber W. H., Microbiological Spoilage of Acidified Specialty Products, in Compendium of the Microbiological Spoilage of Foods and Beverages, Springer, New York, 2009, pp. 285–299</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petruzzi L., Corbo M. R., Sinigaglia M. and Bevilacqua A., Microbial Spoilage of Foods: Fundamentals, The Microbiological Quality of Food: Foodborne Spoilers, Elsevier Ltd, 2017, pp. 1–21, 10.1016/B978-0-08-100502-6.00002-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-08-100502-6.00002-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alpers T. Kerpes R. Frioli M. Nobis A. Hoi K. I. Bach A. et al., Impact of storing condition on staling and microbial spoilage behavior of bread and their contribution to prevent food waste. Foods. 2021;10(1):76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7824337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33401747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
UN. Food security and nutrition and sustainable agriculture, [cited 2023 Jun 10]. available from: https://sdgs.un.org/topics/food-security-and-nutrition-and-sustainable-agriculture</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
World Health Organization Food Safety, [cited 2023 Jun 10]. available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/food-safety</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bintsis T. Foodborne pathogens. AIMS Microbiol. 2017;3(3):529–563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6604998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31294175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food Safety and Inspection Service U.S. Department of Agriculture, [cited 2023 Apr 27], Foodborne Illness and Disease, 2020, available from: Foodborne Illness and Disease | Food Safety and Inspection Service (usda.gov)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, [cited 2023 Apr 20], Foodborne Pathogens, 2023, Available from: Foodborne Pathogens-USFDA</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vågsholm I. Arzoomand N. S. Boqvist S. Food Security, Safety, and Sustainability—Getting the Trade-Offs Right. Front. Sustain. Food Syst. 2020;4:16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holland D. Thomson L. Mahmoudzadeh N. Khaled A. Estimating deaths from foodborne disease in the UK for 11 key pathogens. BMJ Open Gastroenterol. 2020;7(1):1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7319714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32586945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreevskaya M. Jääskeläinen E. Johansson P. Ylinen A. Paulin L. Björkroth J. et al., Food Spoilage-Associated Leuconostoc, Lactococcus, and Lactobacillus Species Display Different Survival Strategies in Response to Competition. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2018;84:e00554–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6007109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29678911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Rogalla D. and Affiliations P. A. B., Listeria Monocytogenes Continuing Education Activity, available from, https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK534838/?report=printable</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ecdc. Campylobacteriosis Annual Epidemiological Report for 2021 Key facts, 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finsterer J. Triggers of Guillain–Barré Syndrome: Campylobacter jejuni Predominates. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2022;23(22):14222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9696744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36430700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Partridge J., Müller recalls six Cadbury desserts over listeria concerns Flake and Crunchie chocolate products among those potentially contaminated with bacteria, available from, https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/may/02/muller-recalls-six-cadbury-desserts-listeria-flake-crunchie</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saravanan A. Kumar P. S. Hemavathy R. V. Jeevanantham S. Kamalesh R. Sneha S. et al., Methods of detection of food-borne pathogens: a review. Environ. Chem. Lett. 2021;19:189–207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Food Safety News, 2022, [cited 2022 Sep 9]. Available from: https://www.foodsafetynews.com/2022/10/rise-in-hepatitis-a-cases-in-eu-and-uk-could-partly-be-foodborne/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Centres for Disease Control and Prevention, 2022, [cited 2022 Oct 9]. available from: https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/outbreaks/2022/hav-contaminated-food/index.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kmiha S. Aouadhi C. Klibi A. Jouini A. Béjaoui A. Mejri S. et al., Seasonal and regional occurrence of heat-resistant spore-forming bacteria in the course of ultra-high temperature milk production in Tunisia. J. Dairy Sci. 2017;100(8):6090–6099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28571988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Environmental Protection Agency, Attachment I-Final Risk Assessment of Bacillus Subtili, United States Environmental Protection Agency, US EPA, 1997, vol. 21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su Y. Liu C. Fang H. Zhang D. Bacillus subtilis: A universal cell factory for industry, agriculture, biomaterials and medicine. Microb. Cell Factories. 2020;19:1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7650271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32883293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng L. Zhang R. Dong L. Hu H. Liu H. Zheng N. et al., Characterization and spoilage potential of Bacillus cereus isolated from farm environment and raw milk. Front. Microbiol. 2022;13:1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9514233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36177462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apetroaie-Constantin C. Mikkola R. Andersson M. A. Teplova V. Suominen I. Johansson T. et al., Bacillus subtilis and B. mojavensis strains connected to food poisoning produce the heat stable toxin amylosin. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2009;106(6):1976–1985.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19228254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández-No I. C. Guarddon M. Böhme K. Cepeda A. Calo-Mata P. Barros-Velázquez J. Detection and quantification of spoilage and pathogenic Bacillus cereus, Bacillus subtilis and Bacillus licheniformis by real-time PCR. Food Microbiol. 2010;28(3):605–610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21356471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özdemir F. Arslan S. Molecular Characterization and Toxin Profiles of Bacillus spp. Isolated from Retail Fish and Ground Beef. J. Food Sci. 2019;84(3):548–556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30690739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathur H. Beresford T. P. Cotter P. D. Health benefits of lactic acid bacteria (Lab) fermentates. Nutrients. 2020;12(6):1–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7352953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32512787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorenzo J. M., Munekata P. E., Dominguez R., Pateiro M., Saraiva J. A. and Franco D., Main Groups of Microorganisms of Relevance for Food Safety and Stability: General Aspects and Overall Description, Innovative Technologies for Food Preservation: Inactivation of Spoilage and Pathogenic Microorganisms, 2018, vol. 1, pp. 53–107</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Z. Luo Y. Mao Y. Peng R. Chen J. Soteyome T. et al., Spoilage lactic acid bacteria in the brewing industry. J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2020;30:955–961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9728350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comi G., Spoilage of Meat and Fish, in The Microbiological Quality of Food: Foodborne Spoilers, Elsevier Inc., 2017, pp. 179–210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fidan H. Esatbeyoglu T. Simat V. Trif M. Tabanelli G. Kostka T. et al., Recent developments of lactic acid bacteria and their metabolites on foodborne pathogens and spoilage bacteria: Facts and gaps. Food Biosci. 2022;47:101741.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayalekshmi S. K. Krishna A. R. Antony T. M. P. Ramasamy S. Isolation of Shewanella putrefaciens GRD 03 from Fish and Explication of Biofilm Adherence Potency on Different Substrates. J. Pure Appl. Microbiol. 2022;16(1):157–166.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W. Yu Y. He H. Lv X. Liu Z. Ni L. The Adhesion and Spoilage of Shewanella putrefaciens in Tilapia. Foods. 2022;11(13):1913.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9266031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35804729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durak-Dados A. Michalski M. Osek J. Histamine and other biogenic amines in food. J. Adv. Vet. Res. 2020;64(2):281–288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7305651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32587916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng Y. Jiang H. Li X. Lv X. Recent advances in sensitivity enhancement for lateral flow assay. Microchim. Acta. 2021;188:1–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8513549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34647157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
iSense. The need for early detection of infectious diseases, [cited 2023 Jun 10]. available from: https://www.i-sense.org.uk/infectious-diseases/need-early-detection-infectious-diseases</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Why early detection of outbreaks is so important, 2017, [cited 2023 Jun 10]. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5395386/</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5395386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28209680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimenez-Carretero M. Rodríguez-López J. Ropero-Moreno C. Granada J. Delgado-Martín J. Martinez-Bueno M. et al., Biomimetic magnetic nanoparticles for bacterial magnetic concentration in liquids and qPCR-detection. Food Control. 2023;147:109623.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Nemis Technologies, 2018, [cited 2024 Jan 13]. available from: https://www.nemistech.com/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
SBT Instruments, [cited 2024 Apr 17]. available from: https://sbtinstruments.com/bactobox</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
BactoScan FC_Foss Analytics, [cited 2024 Apr 17]. available from: https://www.fossanalytics.com/en/products/bactoscan</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao X. Lin C. W. Wang J. Oh D. H. Advances in rapid detection methods for foodborne pathogens. J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2014;24:297–312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24375418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mangal M. Bansal S. Sharma S. K. Gupta R. K. Molecular Detection of Foodborne Pathogens: A Rapid and Accurate Answer to Food Safety. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2016;56(9):1568–1584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25830555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu K. C. Wei Y. H. Fang G. R. Tan J. X. Jia Y. M. Genetic diversity of isolates of foodborne Listeria monocytogenes by RAPD-PCR. Ann. Microbiol. 2016;66(3):1057–1064.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X. Hameed U. Zhang A. F. Zang H. Y. Gu C. Y. Chen Y. et al., Development of a nested-PCR assay for the rapid detection of Pilidiella granati in pomegranate fruit. Sci. Rep. 2017;7:40954.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5247718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28106107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kou Q. Meland K. Li X. He L. Wang Y. Deepest record of Eucopia sculpticauda (Crustacea: Lophogastrida: Eucopiidae) and the order, with new insights into the distribution and genetic diversity of the species. Bull. Mar. Sci. 2019;95(2):327–335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du X. J. Zang Y. X. Liu H. B. Li P. Wang S. Recombinase Polymerase Amplification Combined with Lateral Flow Strip for Listeria monocytogenes Detection in Food. J. Food Sci. 2018;83(4):1041–1047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29524216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires N. M. M. Dong T. Yang Z. da Silva L. F. B. A. Recent methods and biosensors for foodborne pathogen detection in fish: progress and future prospects to sustainable aquaculture systems. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2021;61:1852–1876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32539431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allard M. W. Bell R. Ferreira C. M. Gonzalez-Escalona N. Hoffmann M. Muruvanda T. et al., Genomics of foodborne pathogens for microbial food safety. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2018;49:224–229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29169072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Q. Zhang C. Liu F. Ma H. Wang Y. Chen G. Easy detection of karlodinium veneficum using PCR-based dot chromatography strip. Harmful Algae. 2020;99:101908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33218434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoser M. J. Mansukoski H. K. Morrical S. W. Eboigbodin K. E. Strand Invasion Based Amplification (SIBA®): A novel isothermal DNA amplification technology demonstrating high specificity and sensitivity for a single molecule of target analyte. PLoS One. 2014;9(11):e112656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4242538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25419812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karg M. Frickmann H. Hotzel H. Lugert R. Groß U. Hagen R. M. et al., Identification of Campylobacter fetus by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) J. Microbiol. Methods. 2018;151:44–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29803718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suar M., Misra N. and Bhanjadeo M. M., Molecular diagnostics: past, present, and future, in Evolving Landscape of Molecular Diagnostics, Elsevier, 2024, pp. 3–23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang K. Lv S. Zhou Q. Tang D. CoOOH nanosheets-coated g-C3N4/CuInS2 nanohybrids for photoelectrochemical biosensor of carcinoembryonic antigen coupling hybridization chain reaction with etching reaction. Sens. Actuators, B. 2020;307:127631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gavrilov M. Yang J. Y. C. Zou R. S. Ma W. Lee C. Y. Mohapatra S. et al., Engineered helicase replaces thermocycler in DNA amplification while retaining desired PCR characteristics. Nat. Commun. 2022;13(1):6312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9588791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36274095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T. Wu M. Tian Y. Liu X. Liu C. Xu Q. et al., Detection of trh+ Vibrio parahaemolyticus in seafood by lac dye coloration-based label-free lateral flow immunoassay strip. J. Fish Dis. 2022;45(11):1699–1709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35920381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J. E. Mun H. Kim S. R. Kim M. G. Chang J. Y. Shim W. B. A colorimetric Loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP) assay based on HRP-mimicking molecular beacon for the rapid detection of Vibrio parahaemolyticus. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2020;151:111968.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31999578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang K. Lv S. Lin Z. Li M. Tang D. Bio-bar-code-based photoelectrochemical immunoassay for sensitive detection of prostate-specific antigen using rolling circle amplification and enzymatic biocatalytic precipitation. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2018;101:159–166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29065341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su W. Liang D. Tan M. Nucleic acid-based detection for foodborne virus utilizing microfluidic systems. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2021;113:97–109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarengaowa Hu W. Feng K. Jiang A. Xiu Z. Lao Y. et al., An in situ-Synthesized Gene Chip for the Detection of Food-Borne Pathogens on Fresh-Cut Cantaloupe and Lettuce. Front. Microbiol. 2020;10:3089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7012807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32117079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee Y. Kang B. H. Kang M. Chung D. R. Yi G. S. Lee L. P. et al., Nanoplasmonic On-Chip PCR for Rapid Precision Molecular Diagnostics. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 2020;12(11):12533–12540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32101396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aman R. Mahas A. Mahfouz M. Nucleic Acid Detection Using CRISPR/Cas Biosensing Technologies. ACS Synth. Biol. 2020;9(6):1226–1233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32159950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng R. Gong H. Li Y. Li Y. Lin W. Tang D. et al., CRISPR-Cas12a-Derived Photoelectrochemical Biosensor for Point-Of-Care Diagnosis of Nucleic Acid. Anal. Chem. 2022;94(20):7442–7448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35549163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong H. Hu X. Zeng R. Li Y. Xu J. Li M. et al., CRISPR/Cas12a-based photoelectrochemical sensing of microRNA on reduced graphene oxide-anchored Bi2WO6 coupling with catalytic hairpin assembly. Sens. Actuators, B. 2022;369:132307.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao S. Liu J. Li Z. Ma Y. Wang J. Sensitive detection of foodborne pathogens based on CRISPR-Cas13a. J. Food Sci. 2021;86(6):2615–2625.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33931854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Koster C. G. Brul S. MALDI-TOF MS identification and tracking of food spoilers and food-borne pathogens. Curr. Opin. Food Sci. 2016;10:76–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vrioni G. Tsiamis C. Oikonomidis G. Theodoridou K. Kapsimali V. Tsakris A. MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry technology for detecting biomarkers of antimicrobial resistance: current achievements and future perspectives. Ann. Transl. Med. 2018;6(12):240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6046294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30069442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li N. Zhang W. Lin J. Xing G. Li H. Lin J. M. A Specific Mass-Tag Approach for Detection of Foodborne Pathogens Using MALDI-TOF Mass Spectrometry. Anal. Chem. 2022;94(9):3963–3969.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35195984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tengs T. Rimstad E. Emerging pathogens in the fish farming industry and sequencing-based pathogen discovery. Dev. Comp. Immunol. 2017;75:109–119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28167074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Reckem E. De Vuyst L. Weckx S. Leroy F. Next-generation sequencing to enhance the taxonomic resolution of the microbiological analysis of meat and meat-derived products. Curr. Opin. Food Sci. 2021;37:58–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Avarre J. C. and Avarre J. C., Next-generation sequencing: a revolution in the field of fish diseases MOLTRAQ: Molecular tracing of viral diseases in aquaculture View project Identification and Distribution of Dinoflagellates cysts in coastal marine ecosystems, identification of toxic species responsible of Harmful Algal Blooms in Indonesia View project Next-generation sequencing: a revolution in the field of fish diseases, 2020, available from: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/341868675</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoelzer K. Moreno Switt A. I. Wiedmann M. Boor K. J. Emerging needs and opportunities in foodborne disease detection and prevention: From tools to people. Food Microbiol. 2018;75:65–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30056965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Whole Genome Sequencing, 2022.  [cited 2023 Oct 16]. available from, https://www.cdc.gov/pulsenet/pathogens/wgs.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu D. Tang D. Recent advances on portable photoelectrochemical biosensors for diagnostics. Electroanalysis. 2023;35:e202300265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Z. Wu D. Gao Y. Wang Y. Zeng Y. Tang D. et al., Cutting-Edge Technology for Early Intervention in Myocardial Infarction: Portable Fingertips-Based Immunobiosensor. Adv. Sens. Res. 2024;3(7):1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu L. Zeng R. Lin Q. Huang X. Tang D. Cation Exchange Reaction-Mediated Photothermal and Polarity-Switchable Photoelectrochemical Dual-Readout Biosensor. Anal. Chem. 2023;95(44):16335–16342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37878838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng R. Xu J. Liang T. Li M. Tang D. Photocurrent-Polarity-Switching Photoelectrochemical Biosensor for Switching Spatial Distance Electroactive Tags. ACS Sens. 2023;8(1):317–325.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36617728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J. Zeng R. Huang L. Qiu Z. Tang D. Dual-Signaling Photoelectrochemical Biosensor Based on Biocatalysis-Induced Vulcanization of Bi2MoO6Nanosheets. Anal. Chem. 2022;94(32):11441–11448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35922420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Z. Gong H. Xue F. Zeng Y. Liu X. Tang D. Flexible and High-Throughput Photothermal Biosensors for Rapid Screening of Acute Myocardial Infarction Using Thermochromic Paper-Based Image Analysis. Anal. Chem. 2022;94(38):13233–13242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36099057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu Z. Shu J. Tang D. Bioresponsive Release System for Visual Fluorescence Detection of Carcinoembryonic Antigen from Mesoporous Silica Nanocontainers Mediated Optical Color on Quantum Dot-Enzyme-Impregnated Paper. Anal. Chem. 2017;89(9):5152–5160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28376620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv S. Tang Y. Zhang K. Tang D. Wet NH3-Triggered NH2-MIL-125(Ti) Structural Switch for Visible Fluorescence Immunoassay Impregnated on Paper. Anal. Chem. 2018;90(24):14121–14125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30462475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y. Zuo X. Li Q. Chen F. Chen Y. R. Deng J. et al., Nucleic Acids Analysis. Sci. China Chem. 2021;64:171–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7716629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33293939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S. Dou L. Yao X. Zhang W. Zhao M. Yin X. et al., Nanozyme amplification mediated on-demand multiplex lateral flow immunoassay with dual-readout and broadened detection range. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2020;1:169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32961498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li G. Zhang X. Wu Y. Chen J. Yang Y. Bioinspired artificial ‘clickase’ for the catalytic click immunoassay of foodborne pathogens. Anal. Chem. 2021;93(6):3217–3225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33525867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das R. Dhiman A. Kapil A. Bansal V. Sharma T. K. Aptamer-mediated colorimetric and electrochemical detection of Pseudomonas aeruginosa utilizing peroxidase-mimic activity of gold NanoZyme. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2019;411(6):1229–1238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30637436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bi J. Tian C. Zhang G. L. Hao H. Hou H. M. Detection of histamine based on gold nanoparticles with dual sensor system of colorimetric and fluorescence. Foods. 2020;9(3):316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7143402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32182887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jijie R. Kahlouche K. Barras A. Yamakawa N. Bouckaert J. Gharbi T. et al., Reduced graphene oxide/polyethylenimine based immunosensor for the selective and sensitive electrochemical detection of uropathogenic Escherichia coli. Sens. Actuators, B. 2018;260:255–263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z. Zhou J. Du X. Electrochemical biosensors for detection of foodborne pathogens. Micromachines. 2019;10:222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6523478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30925806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Güner A. Çevik E. Şenel M. Alpsoy L. An electrochemical immunosensor for sensitive detection of Escherichia coli O157:H7 by using chitosan, MWCNT, polypyrrole with gold nanoparticles hybrid sensing platform. Food Chem. 2017;229:358–365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28372186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raj P. Oh M. H. Han K. Lee T. Y. Label-free electrochemical biosensor based on au@mos2–pani for escherichia coli detection. Chemosensors. 2021;9(3):1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stratford J. P. Edwards C. L. A. Ghanshyam M. J. Malyshev D. Delise M. A. Hayashi Y. et al., Electrically induced bacterial membrane-potential dynamics correspond to cellular proliferation capacity. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 2019;116(19):9552–9557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6511025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31000597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng L. Meng Q. H. Lilienthal A. J. Qi P. F. Development of compact electronic noses: A review. Meas. Sci. Technol. 2021;32:062002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrillo-Gómez J. K. Durán Acevedo C. M. García-Rico R. O. Detection of the bacteria concentration level in pasteurized milk by using two different artificial multisensory methods. Sens. Biosensing Res. 2021;33:100428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yahaya M. L., Noordin R. and Abdul Razak K., Advanced Nanoparticle-Based Biosensors for Diagnosing Foodborne Pathogens, in Advanced Biosensors for Health Care Applications, Elsevier, 2019, pp. 1–43</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shauloff N. Morag A. Yaniv K. Singh S. Malishev R. Paz-Tal O. et al., Sniffing Bacteria with a Carbon-Dot Artificial Nose. Nanomicro Lett. 2021;13(1):1–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8058130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34138310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghrissi H. Veloso A. C. A. Marx Í. M. G. Dias T. Peres A. M. A potentiometric electronic tongue as a discrimination tool of water-food indicator/contamination bacteria. Chemosensors. 2021;9(6):143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrillo Gómez J. K., Durán Acevedo C. M. and Rico R. O. G., E-nose and E-tongue systems for the Bacteria Detection in milk, in Proceedings of the LACCEI International Multi-Conference for Engineering, Education and Technology. Latin American and Caribbean Consortium of Engineering Institutions, 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moudgil A. Singh S. Mishra N. Mishra P. Das S. MoS2/TiO2 Hybrid Nanostructure-Based Field-Effect Transistor for Highly Sensitive, Selective, and Rapid Detection of Gram-Positive Bacteria. Adv. Mater. Technol. 2020;5(1):1900615.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Y. Shi Z. Liu Q. Smartphone-based biosensors for portable food evaluation. Curr. Opin. Food Sci. 2019;28:74–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
IR Biotyper®, [cited 2024 Apr 17]. available from, https://www.bruker.com/en/applications/microbiology-and-diagnostics/food-beverage-microbiology/ir-biotyper-for-food-microbiology.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banwell C. N., Fundamentals of Molecular Spectroscopy, 1972</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jehlička J. Edwards H. G. M. Oren A. Raman spectroscopy of microbial pigments. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2014;80:3286–3295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4018853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24682303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakar A. Pistiki A. Ryabchykov O. Bocklitz T. Rösch P. Popp J. Detection of multi-resistant clinical strains of E. coli with Raman spectroscopy. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2022;414(4):1481–1492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8761712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34982178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logan N. Haughey S. A. Liu L. Burns D. T. Quinn B. Cao C. et al., Handheld SERS coupled with QuEChERs for the sensitive analysis of multiple pesticides in basmati rice. npj Sci. Food. 2022;6(1):1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8758682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35027565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X. Hu Z. Yang D. Xie S. Jiang Z. Niessner R. et al., Bacteria Detection: From Powerful SERS to Its Advanced Compatible Techniques. Adv. Sci. 2020;7(23):2001739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7710000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33304748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y. Wasiewska L. A. Burgess C. M. Duffy G. Lovera P. O'Riordan A. Detection of stx2 from Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) by a surface enhanced Raman spectroscopy (SERS) sensor using recycled silicon chips. Sens. Actuators, B. 2022;373:132618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H. Ma X. Liu Y. Duan N. Wu S. Wang Z. et al., Gold nanoparticles enhanced SERS aptasensor for the simultaneous detection of Salmonella typhimurium and Staphylococcus aureus. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2015;74:872–877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26241735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y. Xu B. Haverstick J. Ibtehaz N. Muszyński A. Chen X. et al., Differentiation and classification of bacterial endotoxins based on surface enhanced Raman scattering and advanced machine learning. Nanoscale. 2022;14(24):8806–8817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9575096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35686584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X. Xu C. Tripp R. A. Huang Y. W. Zhao Y. Detection and differentiation of foodborne pathogenic bacteria in mung bean sprouts using field deployable label-free SERS devices. Analyst. 2013;138(10):3005–3012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23563168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Premasiri W. R. Lee J. C. Sauer-Budge A. Théberge R. Costello C. E. Ziegler L. D. The biochemical origins of the surface-enhanced Raman spectra of bacteria: a metabolomics profiling by SERS. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2016;408(17):4631–4647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4911336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27100230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Lorenzo L. Garrido-Maestu A. Bhunia A. K. Espiña B. Prado M. Diéguez L. et al., Gold Nanostars for the Detection of Foodborne Pathogens via Surface-Enhanced Raman Scattering Combined with Microfluidics. ACS Appl. Nano Mater. 2019;2(10):6081–6086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y. Guo Y. Ye B. Zhuang Z. Lan P. Zhang Y. et al., Rapid label-free SERS detection of foodborne pathogenic bacteria based on hafnium ditelluride-Au nanocomposites. J. Innovative Opt. Health Sci. 2020;13(5):2041004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banbury C. Mason R. Styles I. Eisenstein N. Clancy M. Belli A. et al., Development of the Self Optimising Kohonen Index Network (SKiNET) for Raman Spectroscopy Based Detection of Anatomical Eye Tissue. Sci. Rep. 2019;9(1):1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6658481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31346227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang H. Hopkins D. L. Zhang Y. Zhu L. Dong P. Wang X. et al., Preliminary investigation of the use of Raman spectroscopy to predict beef spoilage in different types of packaging. Meat Sci. 2020;165:108136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32272341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zając A. Dymińska L. Lorenc J. Hanuza J. Fourier Transform Infrared and Raman Spectroscopy Studies of the Time-Dependent Changes in Chicken Meat as a Tool for Recording Spoilage Processes. Food Anal. Methods. 2017;10(3):640–648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C. Liu M. Wang Z. Li S. Deng Y. He N. Point-of-care diagnostics for infectious diseases: From methods to devices. Nano Today. 2021;37:101092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7864790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33584847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farber C. Kurouski D. Detection and Identification of Plant Pathogens on Maize Kernels with a Hand-Held Raman Spectrometer. Anal. Chem. 2018;90(5):3009–3012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29461798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egging V. Nguyen J. Kurouski D. Detection and Identification of Fungal Infections in Intact Wheat and Sorghum Grain Using a Hand-Held Raman Spectrometer. Anal. Chem. 2018;90(14):8616–8621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29898358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekvapil F. Brezestean I. Barchewitz D. Glamuzina B. Chiş V. Cintă Pinzaru S. Citrus fruits freshness assessment using Raman spectroscopy. Food Chem. 2018;242:560–567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29037730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heuler J. He S. Ambardar S. Voronine D. V. Point-of-care detection, characterization, and removal of chocolate bloom using a handheld Raman spectrometer. Sci. Rep. 2020;10(1):9833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7299933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32555247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellis D. I. Muhamadali H. Xu Y. Eccles R. Goodall I. Goodacre R. Rapid through-container detection of fake spirits and methanol quantification with handheld Raman spectroscopy. Analyst. 2019;144(1):324–330.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30516175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karunathilaka S. R. Yakes B. J. He K. Brückner L. Mossoba M. M. First use of handheld Raman spectroscopic devices and on-board chemometric analysis for the detection of milk powder adulteration. Food Control. 2018;92:137–146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nieuwoudt M. K. Holroyd S. E. McGoverin C. M. Simpson M. C. Williams D. E. Raman spectroscopy as an effective screening method for detecting adulteration of milk with small nitrogen-rich molecules and sucrose. J. Dairy Sci. 2016;99(4):2520–2536.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26874427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y. Li H. Dou H. Wen H. Dong Y. Prediction and Visual Analysis of Food Safety Risk Based on TabNet-GRA. Foods. 2023;12(16):3113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10453234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37628112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang D. Zhuang Z. Wang Z. Li S. Zhong H. Liu Z. et al., Black phosphorus-Au filter paper-based three-dimensional SERS substrate for rapid detection of foodborne bacteria. Appl. Surf. Sci. 2019;15:497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu A. Ali S. Xu Y. Ouyang Q. Wang Z. Chen Q. SERS-based Au@Ag NPs Solid-phase substrate combined with chemometrics for rapid discrimination of multiple foodborne pathogens. Spectrochim. Acta, Part A. 2022;270:120814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34973615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhuang J. Zhao Z. Lian K. Yin L. Wang J. Man S. et al., SERS-based CRISPR/Cas assay on microfluidic paper analytical devices for supersensitive detection of pathogenic bacteria in foods. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2022;207:114167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35325722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang Y. L. Su C. J. Lu L. C. Wan D. Aluminum Plasmonic Nanoclusters for Paper-Based Surface-Enhanced Raman Spectroscopy. Anal. Chem. 2022;94(47):16319–16327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36372951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma S. Tharani L. Optical sensing for real-time detection of food-borne pathogens in fresh produce using machine learning. Sci. Prog. 2023;107(2):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11113042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38773741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu R. Zhao Y. Kong D. Wu N. He Y. Development and comparison of classification models on VIS-NIR hyperspectral imaging spectra for qualitative detection of the Staphylococcus aureus in fresh chicken breast. Spectrochim. Acta, Part A. 2023;285:121838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36108407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma L. Yi J. Wisuthiphaet N. Earles M. Nitin N. Accelerating the Detection of Bacteria in Food Using Artificial Intelligence and Optical Imaging. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2023;89(1):e01828.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9888199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36533914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q. Qiu L. A snail species identification method based on deep learning in food safety. Math. Biosci. Eng. 2024;21(3):3652–3667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38549300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>