<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39356051</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1740-8709</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Maternal &amp; child nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Matern Child Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Use of multiple micronutrient supplementation integrated into routine antenatal care: A discussion of research priorities.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13722</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13722</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/mcn.13722</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Optimal maternal nutrition, including adequate intake and status of essential micronutrients, is important for the health of women and developing infants. Currently, the World Health Organization (WHO) Antenatal care recommendations for a positive pregnancy experience recommend daily iron and folic acid (IFA) supplementation as the standard of care. The use of multiple micronutrient supplements (MMSs) is recommended in the context of rigorous research as more evidence was needed regarding the impact of switching from IFA supplements to MMS, including evaluation of critical clinical maternal and perinatal outcomes, acceptability, feasibility, sustainability, equity and cost-effectiveness. WHO convened a technical consultation of key stakeholders to discuss research priorities with the objective of providing guidance and clarity to donors, implementers and researchers about this recommendation. The overarching principles of the research agenda include the use of clinical indicators and impact measures that are applicable across studies and settings and the inclusion of outcomes that are important to women. Future studies should consider using standardized protocols based on current best practices to measure critical outcomes such as gestational age (GA) and birthweight (BW) in studies. As GA and BW are influenced by multiple factors, more research is needed to understand the biological impact pathways, and how initiation and considerations for timing of MMS influence these outcomes. A set of core clinical indicators was agreed upon during the technical consultation. For implementation research, the Evidence-to-Decision framework was used as a resource for discussing components of implementation research. The implementation research questions, key indicators and performance measures will depend on country-specific context and bottlenecks that require further research and improved solutions to enable the successful implementation of iron-containing supplements.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 World Health Organization; licensed by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. Maternal &amp; Child Nutrition published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Firoz</LastName><ForeName>Tabassum</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yale New Haven Health, New Haven, Connecticut, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Daru</LastName><ForeName>Jahnavi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wolfson Institute for Population Health, Queen Mary University of London, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Busch-Hallen</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sexual and Reproductive Health and Research including UNDP/UNFPA/UNICEF/WHO/World Bank Special Programme of Research, Development and Research Training in Human Reproduction (HRP), World Health Organization (WHO), Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tunçalp</LastName><ForeName>Özge</ForeName><Initials>Ö</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Technical Services, Nutrition International, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rogers</LastName><ForeName>Lisa M</ForeName><Initials>LM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Food Safety, World Health Organization (WHO), Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Matern Child Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101201025</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1740-8695</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">maternal nutrition</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiple micronutrient supplementation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39356051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/mcn.13722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adu‐Afarwuah, S., Lartey, A., Okronipa, H., Ashorn, P., Zeilani, M., Peerson, J. M., Arimond, M., Vosti, S., &amp; Dewey, K. G. (2015). Lipid‐based nutrient supplement increases the birth size of infants of primiparous women in Ghana. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 101(4), 835–846. https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.114.091546</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashorn, P., Alho, L., Ashorn, U., Cheung, Y. B., Dewey, K. G., Gondwe, A., Harjunmaa, U., Lartey, A., Phiri, N., Phiri, T. E., Vosti, S. A., Zeilani, M., &amp; Maleta, K. (2015). Supplementation of maternal diets during pregnancy and for 6 months postpartum and infant diets thereafter with small‐quantity lipid‐based nutrient supplements does not promote child growth by 18 months of age in rural Malawi: A randomized controlled trial. The Journal of Nutrition, 145(6), 1345–1353. https://doi.org/10.3945/jn.114.207225</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashorn, P., Ashorn, U., Muthiani, Y., Aboubaker, S., Askari, S., Bahl, R., Black, R. E., Dalmiya, N., Duggan, C. P., Hofmeyr, G. J., Kennedy, S. H., Klein, N., Lawn, J. E., Shiffman, J., Simon, J., Temmerman, M., Krasevec, J., Bradley, E., Conkle, J., … Hayashi, C., UNICEF‐WHO Low Birthweight Estimates Group. (2023). Small vulnerable newborns‐big potential for impact. The Lancet, 401(10389), 1692–1706. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00354-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Onis, M., Cheikh Ismail, L., Chumlea, C., Onyango, A., Bhutta, Z., Luna, M. S., &amp; Knight, H. (2012). INTERGROWTH‐21st: International fetal and newborn growth standards for the 21st century: Anthropometry handbook. https://media.tghn.org/articles/Anthropometry_Handbook_April_2012.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DiTomasso, D., &amp; Cloud, M. (2019). Systematic review of expected weight changes after birth for full‐term, breastfed newborns. Journal of Obstetric, Gynecologic &amp; Neonatal Nursing, 48(6), 593–603. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jogn.2019.09.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duffy, J. M. N., Cairns, A. E., Magee, L. A., von Dadelszen, P., van 't Hooft, J., Gale, C., Brown, M., Chappell, L. C., Grobman, W. A., Fitzpatrick, R., Karumanchi, S. A., Lucas, D. N., Mol, B., Stark, M., Thangaratinam, S., Wilson, M. J., Williamson, P. R., Ziebland, S., &amp; McManus, R. J., International Collaboration to Harmonise Outcomes for Pre‐eclampsia (iHOPE). (2020). Standardising definitions for the pre‐eclampsia core outcome set: A consensus development study. Pregnancy Hypertension, 21, 208–217. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.preghy.2020.06.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gernand, A. D. (2019). The upper level: Examining the risk of excess micronutrient intake in pregnancy from antenatal supplements. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences, 1444(1), 22–34. https://doi.org/10.1111/nyas.14103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomes, F., Agustina, R., Black, R. E., Christian, P., Dewey, K. G., Kraemer, K., Shankar, A. H., Smith, E. R., Thorne‐Lyman, A., Tumilowicz, A., &amp; Bourassa, M. W. (2022a). Multiple micronutrient supplements versus iron‐folic acid supplements and maternal anemia outcomes: An iron dose analysis. The Lancet Global Health, 1512(1), 114–125. https://doi.org/10.1111/nyas.14756</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomes, F., Agustina, R., Black, R. E., Christian, P., Dewey, K. G., Kraemer, K., Shankar, A. H., Smith, E., Tumilowicz, A., &amp; Bourassa, M. W. (2022b). Effect of multiple micronutrient supplements vs iron and folic acid supplements on neonatal mortality: A reanalysis by iron dose. Public Health Nutrition, 25(8), 1–13. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980022001008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomes, F., Askari, S., Black, R. E., Christian, P., Dewey, K. G., Mwangi, M. N., Rana, Z., Reed, S., Shankar, A. H., Smith, E. R., &amp; Tumilowicz, A. (2023). Antenatal multiple micronutrient supplements versus iron‐folic acid supplements and birth outcomes: Analysis by gestational age assessment method. Maternal &amp; Child Nutrition, 19(3), e13509. https://doi.org/10.1111/mcn.13509</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Killeen, S. L., Donnellan, N., O'reilly, S. L., Hanson, M. A., Rosser, M. L., Medina, V. P., Jacob, C. M., Divakar, H., Hod, M., Poon, L. C., Bergman, L., O'brien, P., Kapur, A., Jacobsson, B., Maxwell, C. V., McIntyre, H. D., Regan, L., Algurjia, E., Ma, R. C., … The FIGO Committee on Impact of Pregnancy on Long‐term Health and the FIGO Division of Maternal and Newborn Health. (2023). Using FIGO nutrition checklist counselling in pregnancy: A review to support healthcare professionals. International Journal of Gynaecology and obstetrics: The Official Organ of the International Federation of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, 160(Suppl 1), 10–21. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijgo.14539</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinshella, M. L. W., Pickerill, K., Bone, J. N., Prasad, S., Campbell, O., Vidler, M., Craik, R., Volvert, M. L., Mistry, H. D., Tsigas, E., Magee, L. A., von Dadelszen, P., Moore, S. E., &amp; Elango, R., PRECISE Conceptual Framework Working Group. (2023). An evidence review and nutritional conceptual framework for pre‐eclampsia prevention. British Journal of Nutrition, 130(6), 1065–1076. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114522003889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiserud, T., Piaggio, G., Carroli, G., Widmer, M., Carvalho, J., Neerup Jensen, L., Giordano, D., Cecatti, J. G., Abdel Aleem, H., Talegawkar, S. A., Benachi, A., Diemert, A., Tshefu Kitoto, A., Thinkhamrop, J., Lumbiganon, P., Tabor, A., Kriplani, A., Gonzalez Perez, R., Hecher, K., … Platt, L. D. (2017). The World Health Organization fetal growth charts: A multinational longitudinal study of ultrasound biometric measurements and estimated fetal weight. PLoS Medicine, 14(1), e1002220. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1002220</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurpad, A. V., &amp; Sachdev, H. S. (2022). Precision in prescription: Multiple micronutrient supplements in pregnancy. The Lancet Global Health, 10(6), e780–e781. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(22)00207-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrtash, H., Stein, K., Barreix, M., Bohren, M. A., &amp; Tuncalp, O. (2023). Measuring women's experiences during antenatal care (ANC): Scoping review of measurement tools. Reproductive Health, 20(1), 150. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12978-023-01653-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrtash, H., Stein, K., Barreix, M., Bonet, M., Bohren, M. A., &amp; Tunçalp, Ö. (2023). Measuring women's experiences during antenatal care (ANC): Scoping review of measurement tools. Reproductive Health, 20(1), 150. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12978-023-01653-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Napolitano, R., Dhami, J., Ohuma, E., Ioannou, C., Conde‐Agudelo, A., Kennedy, S., Villar, J., &amp; Papageorghiou, A. (2014). Pregnancy dating by fetal crown‐rump length: A systematic review of charts. BJOG: An International Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology, 121(5), 556–565. https://doi.org/10.1111/1471-0528.12478</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Library of Medicine (U.S.). (2024). Multiple micronutrient supplementation for maternal anemia prevention in Tanzania (MMS‐MAP). Identifier NCT06079918. https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT06079918</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noguchi, L., Bucagu, M., &amp; Tunçalp, Ö. (2023). Strengthening antenatal care services for all: Implementing imaging ultrasound before 24 weeks of pregnancy. BMJ Global Health, 8(5), e011170. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2022-011170</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papageorghiou, A. T., Kemp, B., Stones, W., Ohuma, E. O., Kennedy, S. H., Purwar, M., Salomon, L. J., Altman, D. G., Noble, J. A., Bertino, E., Gravett, M. G., Pang, R., Cheikh Ismail, L., Barros, F. C., Lambert, A., Jaffer, Y. A., Victora, C. G., Bhutta, Z. A., &amp; Villar, J., International Fetal and Newborn Growth Consortium for the Century. (2016). Ultrasound‐based gestational‐age estimation in late pregnancy. Ultrasound in Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology: The Official Journal of the International Society of Ultrasound in Obstetrics and Gynecology, 48(6), 719–726. https://doi.org/10.1002/uog.15894</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papageorghiou, A. T., Kennedy, S. H., Salomon, L. J., Ohuma, E. O., Cheikh Ismail, L., Barros, F. C., Lambert, A., Carvalho, M., Jaffer, Y. A., Bertino, E., Gravett, M. G., Altman, D. G., Purwar, M., Noble, J. A., Pang, R., Victora, C. G., Bhutta, Z. A., Villar, J., &amp; International Fetal and Newborn Growth Consortium for the Century, (2014). International standards for early fetal size and pregnancy dating based on ultrasound measurement of crown–rump length in the first trimester of pregnancy. Ultrasound in Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology: The Official Journal of the International Society of Ultrasound in Obstetrics and Gynecology, 44(6), 641–648. https://doi.org/10.1002/uog.13448</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schulze, K. J., Mehra, S., Shaikh, S., Ali, H., Shamim, A. A., Wu, L. S. F., Mitra, M., Arguello, M. A., Kmush, B., Sungpuag, P., Udomkesmelee, E., Merrill, R., Klemm, R. D. W., Ullah, B., Labrique, A. B., West, Jr. K. P., &amp; Christian, P. (2019). Antenatal multiple micronutrient supplementation compared to iron‐folic acid affects micronutrient status but does not eliminate deficiencies in a randomized controlled trial among pregnant women of rural Bangladesh. The Journal of Nutrition, 149(7), 1260–1270. https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/nxz046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, E. R., He, S., Klatt, K. C., Barberio, M. D., Rahnavard, A., Azad, N., Brandt, C., Harker, B., Hogan, E., Kucherlapaty, P., Moradian, D., Gernand, A. D., &amp; Ahmadzia, H. K. (2021). Limited data exist to inform our basic understanding of micronutrient requirements in pregnancy. Science Advances, 7(43), eabj8016. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abj8016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevens, G. A., Beal, T., Mbuya, M. N. N., Luo, H., Neufeld, L. M., Addo, O. Y., Adu‐Afarwuah, S., Alayón, S., Bhutta, Z., Brown, K. H., Jefferds, M. E., Engle‐Stone, R., Fawzi, W., Hess, S. Y., Johnston, R., Katz, J., Krasevec, J., McDonald, C. M., Mei, Z., … Young, M. F. (2022). Micronutrient deficiencies among preschool‐aged children and women of reproductive age worldwide: A pooled analysis of individual‐level data from population‐representative surveys. The Lancet Global Health, 10(11), e1590–e1599. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(22)00367-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuncalp, Ö., Rogers, L. M., Lawrie, T. A., Barreix, M., Peña‐Rosas, J. P., Bucagu, M., Neilson, J., &amp; Oladapo, O. T. (2020). WHO recommendations on antenatal nutrition: An update on multiple micronutrient supplements. BMJ Global Health, 5(7), e003375. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2020-003375</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNICEF, UNU, WHO Study Team. (2002). Multiple micronutrient supplementation during pregnancy (MMSDP): Efficacy trials. University College London. https://mjmp.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Multiple-Micronutrient-Supplementation-During-Pregnancy-MMSDP-Efficacy-Trials-WHO-UNICEF-UNU1.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel, J. P., Dowswell, T., Lewin, S., Bonet, M., Hampson, L., Kellie, F., Portela, A., Bucagu, M., Norris, S. L., Neilson, J., Gülmezoglu, A. M., &amp; Oladapo, O. T. (2019). Developing and applying a ‘living guidelines’ approach to WHO recommendations on maternal and perinatal health. BMJ Global Health, 4(4), e001683. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2019-001683</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, United Nations University, &amp; United Nations Children's Fund (‎UNICEF). (1999). Composition of a multi‐micronutrient supplement to be used in pilot programmes among pregnant women in developing countries: Report of a United Nations Children's Fund (‎UNICEF)‎. World Health Organization (‎WHO)‎ and United Nations University workshop. UNICEF. https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/75358</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2016a). International statistical classification of diseases and related health problems 10th revision. https://icd.who.int/browse10/2019/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2016b). WHO recommendations on antenatal care for a positive pregnancy experience: Web annexes. https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/250796/9789241549912-webannexes-eng.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2016c). WHO recommendations on antenatal care for a positive pregnancy experience. http://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241549912</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2020). WHO antenatal care recommendations for a positive pregnancy experience: Nutritional interventions update: Multiple micronutrient supplements during pregnancy. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240007789</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>