<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39359729</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1664-3224</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in immunology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Immunol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of the efficacy and safety of first- and second-line immunotherapy in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer: a systematic review and network meta-analysis based on randomized controlled trials.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1439624</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1439624</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1439624</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fimmu.2024.1439624</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A multitude of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) conducted in both the initial and subsequent treatment settings for patients diagnosed with metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC) have provided clinical evidence supporting the efficacy of immunotherapy with the use of immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs). In light of these findings, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has authorized the use of several ICIs in specific subpopulations of mCRC patients. Nevertheless, there remains a dearth of direct comparative RCTs evaluating various treatment options. Consequently, the most effective ICI therapeutic strategy for microsatellite-stable (MSS) subgroup and microsatellite instability (MSI) subgroup in the first- and second-line therapies remains undefined. To address this gap, the present study employs a Bayesian network meta-analysis to ascertain the most effective first- and second-line ICI therapeutic strategies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A comprehensive literature search was conducted across multiple databases, including PubMed, EMBASE, Cochrane Library, and Web of Science, with the retrieval date ranging from the databases' inception to August 20, 2024. A total of 875 studies were identified, and seven were ultimately included in the analysis after a screening process. A systematic review and network meta-analysis were conducted on the basis of the search results.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This comprehensive analysis, comprising seven RCTs, evaluated first-line and second-line immunotherapy regimens in 1,358 patients diagnosed with mCRC. The treatments under investigation consisted of five initial treatments, including three focusing on MSS patients and two on MSI patients, as well as two secondary immunotherapy regimens, both focusing on MSS patients. A total of 1051 individuals underwent first-line treatment, while 307 received second-line treatment. The application of ICIs proved to offer varying degrees clinical benefits when compared to standard-of-care therapy alone, both in two subgroups of the first and the second treatment phases. Of particular note is the performance of Nivolumab combination with ipilimumab, which demonstrated superior efficacy in improving progression-free survival (PFS) (HR=0.21; 95% CI, 0.13-0.34),. Moreover, the treatment demonstrated an optimal safety profile, with a relatively low risk of adverse events (OR = 0.33; 95% CI, 0.19-0.56), compared to other first-line treatment modalities for MSI subgroup. Regarding MSS subgroup, the improvement of PFS by Nivolumab plus standard-of-care (SOC) was relatively significant (HR = 0.74; 95% CI, 0.53-1.02). In the realm of second-line therapies for MSS subgroup, the administration of Atezolizumab plus SOC has proven to be an effective approach for prolonging PFS, exhibiting an HR of 0.66 (95% CI, 0.44-0.99). These findings underscore the clinical benefits and safety profiles of ICIs in the treatment of mCRC across various treatment lines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The clinical application of ICIs in both first- and second-line treatment strategies for patients with mCRC yields substantial therapeutic benefits. A detailed assessment in this study indicates that first-line treatment with Nivolumab combination with ipilimumab may represent an efficacious and well-tolerated therapeutic approach for MSI subgroup. In terms of MSS subgroup in first-line therapy, Nivolumab plus SOC may be a relative superior choice. In the context of second-line therapy for MSS subgroup, it is evident that a combination of Atezolizumab and SOC represents a preferable option for enhancing PFS. Furthermore, it is noteworthy that other ICIs treatment regimens also exhibit great value in various aspects, with the potential to inform the development of future clinical treatment guidelines and provide a stronger rationale for the selection of ICIs in both first- and second-line therapeutic strategies for mCRC.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SYSTEMATIC REVIEW REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/#recordDetails, identifier CRD42024543400.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Chen, Chen, Yue, Zhu, Cui, Zhang, Jin and Xiao.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Kaiqi</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Basic Medical, Chengdu University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Emergency General Hospital, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yue</LastName><ForeName>Rui</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chongqing Changhang Hospital, Chongqing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Danping</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Endocrinology, Chongqing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chongqing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cui</LastName><ForeName>Shikui</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Endocrinology, Chongqing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chongqing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Xijian</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Endocrinology, Chongqing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chongqing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Zhao</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Basic Medical, Chengdu University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chengdu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiao</LastName><ForeName>Tong</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Basic Medical Sciences, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Immunol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101560960</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1664-3224</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000082082">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015179" MajorTopicYN="Y">Colorectal Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016032" MajorTopicYN="Y">Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000082082" MajorTopicYN="Y">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007167" MajorTopicYN="Y">Immunotherapy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071076" MajorTopicYN="Y">Network Meta-Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016896" MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009362" MajorTopicYN="N">Neoplasm Metastasis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053842" MajorTopicYN="N">Microsatellite Instability</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001499" MajorTopicYN="N">Bayes Theorem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">efficacy and safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">first- and second-line</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunotherapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metastatic colorectal cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microsatellite status</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">network meta-analysis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39359729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11444977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2024.1439624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, Laversanne M, Soerjomataram I, Jemal A, et al. . Global cancer statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin. (2021) 71:209–49. doi: 10.3322/caac.21660</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3322/caac.21660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33538338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnold M, Sierra MS, Laversanne M, Soerjomataram I, Jemal A, Bray F. Global patterns and trends in colorectal cancer incidence and mortality. Gut. (2017) 66:683–91. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2015-310912</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2015-310912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26818619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biller LH, Schrag D. Diagnosis and treatment of metastatic colorectal cancer: A review. JAMA. (2021) 325:669–85. doi: 10.1001/jama.2021.0106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.0106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33591350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards BK, Ward E, Kohler BA, Eheman C, Zauber AG, Anderson RN, et al. . Annual report to the nation on the status of cancer, 1975-2006, featuring colorectal cancer trends and impact of interventions (risk factors, screening, and treatment) to reduce future rates. Cancer. (2010) 116:544–73. doi: 10.1002/cncr.24760</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cncr.24760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3619726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19998273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Foch C, Messinger D, Esser R, Lamy FX, Rothe V, et al. . Noninferiority of cetuximab every-2-weeks versus standard once-weekly administration schedule for the first-line treatment of RAS wild-type metastatic colorectal cancer. Eur J Cancer. (2021) 144:291–301. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2020.11.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2020.11.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33383349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin AE, Giancotti FG, Rustgi AK. Metastatic colorectal cancer: mechanisms and emerging therapeutics. Trends Pharmacol Sci. (2023) 44(4):222–36. doi: 10.1016/j.tips.2023.01.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tips.2023.01.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10365888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36828759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris VK, Kennedy EB, Baxter NN, Benson AB 3rd, Cercek A, Cho M, et al. . Treatment of Metastatic Colorectal Cancer: ASCO Guideline. J Clin Oncol. (2023) 41(3):678–700. doi: 10.1200/JCO.22.01690</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.22.01690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10506310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36252154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jonker DJ, Maroun JA, Kocha W. Survival benefit of chemotherapy in metastatic colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Br J Cancer. (2000) 82:1789–94. doi: 10.1054/bjoc.1999.1254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1054/bjoc.1999.1254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2363220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10839292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirstein MM, Lange A, Prenzler A, Manns MP, Kubicka S, Vogel A. Targeted therapies in metastatic colorectal cancer: a systematic review and assessment of currently available data. Oncologist. (2014) 19:1156–68. doi: 10.1634/theoncologist.2014-0032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.2014-0032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4221380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25326159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botrel TEA, Clark LGO, Paladini L, Clark OAC. Efficacy and safety of bevacizumab plus chemotherapy compared to chemotherapy alone in previously untreated advanced or metastatic colorectal cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Cancer. (2016) 16:677. doi: 10.1186/s12885-016-2734-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12885-016-2734-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4997727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27558497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Cutsem E, Cervantes A, Adam R, Sobrero A, Van Krieken JH, Aderka D, et al. . ESMO consensus guidelines for the management of patients with metastatic colorectal cancer. Ann Oncol. (2016) 27:1386–422. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdw235</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdw235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27380959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz-Duarte R, Rebelo de Almeida C, Negrão M, Fernandes A, Borralho P, Sobral D, et al. . Predictive and therapeutic implications of a novel PLCγ1/SHP2-driven mechanism of cetuximab resistance in metastatic colorectal cancer. Clin Cancer Res. (2022) 28:1203–16. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-21-1992</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-21-1992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9365369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34980600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesh K. Optimizing immunotherapy for colorectal cancer. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. (2022) 19:93–4. doi: 10.1038/s41575-021-00569-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41575-021-00569-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9487162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34907331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan J, Li J, Gao C, Jiang C, Xiang Z, Wu J. Immunotherapies catering to the unmet medical need of cold colorectal cancer. Front Immunol. (2022) 13:1022190. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2022.1022190</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.1022190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9579278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36275766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ros J, Balconi F, Baraibar I, Saoudi Gonzalez N, Salva F, Tabernero J, et al. . Advances in immune checkpoint inhibitor combination strategies for microsatellite stable colorectal cancer. Front Oncol. (2023) 13:1112276. doi: 10.3389/fonc.2023.1112276</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fonc.2023.1112276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9932591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36816981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz LA, Jr, Shiu KK, Kim TW, Jensen BV, Jensen LH, Punt C, et al. . Pembrolizumab versus chemotherapy for microsatellite instability-high or mismatch repair-deficient metastatic colorectal cancer (KEYNOTE-177): final analysis of a randomised, open-label, phase 3 study. Lancet Oncol. (2022) 23:659–70. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(22)00197-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(22)00197-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9533375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35427471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenz HJ, Van Cutsem E, Luisa Limon M, Wong KYM, Hendlisz A, Aglietta M, et al. . First-line nivolumab plus low-dose ipilimumab for microsatellite instability-high/mismatch repair-deficient metastatic colorectal cancer: the phase II checkMate 142 study. J Clin Oncol. (2022) 40:161–70. doi: 10.1200/JCO.21.01015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.21.01015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34637336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirano H, Takashima A, Hamaguchi T, Shida D, Kanemitsu Y. Colorectal Cancer Study Group (CCSG) of the Japan Clinical Oncology Group (JCOG). Current status and perspectives of immune checkpoint inhibitors for colorectal cancer. Jpn J Clin Oncol. (2021) 51:10–9. doi: 10.1093/jjco/hyaa200</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jjco/hyaa200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33205813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taieb J, Karoui M. FOxTROT: are we ready to dance? J Clin Oncol. (2023) 41:1514–7. doi: 10.1200/JCO.22.02108</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.22.02108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36657090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchler T. Microsatellite instability and metastatic colorectal cancer - A clinical perspective. Front Oncol. (2022) 12:888181. doi: 10.3389/fonc.2022.888181</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fonc.2022.888181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9097548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35574322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maajani K, Khodadost M, Fattahi A, Shahrestanaki E, Pirouzi A, Khalili F, et al. . Survival rate of colorectal cancer in Iran: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev. (2019) 20:13–21. doi: 10.31557/APJCP.2019.20.1.13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31557/APJCP.2019.20.1.13</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6485573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30677864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le DT, Durham JN, Smith KN, Wang H, Bartlett BR, Aulakh LK, et al. . Mismatch repair deficiency predicts response of solid tumors to PD-1 blockade. Science. (2017) 357:409–13. doi: 10.1126/science.aan6733</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.aan6733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5576142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28596308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barzi A, Azad NS, Yang Y, Tsao-Wei D, Rehman R, Fakih M, et al. . Phase I/II study of regorafenib (rego) and pembrolizumab (pembro) in refractory microsatellite stable colorectal cancer (MSSCRC). J Clin Oncol. (2022) 40:15. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2022.40.4_suppl.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.2022.40.4_suppl.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huyghe N, Benidovskaya E, Stevens P, Van den Eynde M. Biomarkers of response and resistance to immunotherapy in microsatellite stable colorectal cancer: toward a new personalized medicine. Cancers (Basel). (2022) 14:2241. doi: 10.3390/cancers14092241</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cancers14092241</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9105843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35565369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomar M, Najafi M, Aghili M, Cozzi S, Jahanbakhshi A. Durable complete response to pembrolizumab in microsatellite stable colorectal cancer. Daru. (2021) 29:501–6. doi: 10.1007/s40199-021-00404-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40199-021-00404-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8602589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34254265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>PLOS ONE Staff . Correction: Network meta-analysis using R: a review of currently available automated packages. PloS One. (2015) 10:e0123364. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0123364</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4383511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25836669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shim SR, Kim SJ, Lee J, Rücker G. Network meta-analysis: application and practice using R software. Epidemiol Health. (2019) 41:e2019013. doi: 10.4178/epih.e2019013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4178/epih.e2019013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6635665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30999733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenz HJ, Parikh A, Spigel DR, Cohn AL, Yoshino T, Kochenderfer M, et al. . Modified FOLFOX6 plus bevacizumab with and without nivolumab for first-line treatment of metastatic colorectal cancer: phase 2 results from the CheckMate 9X8 randomized clinical trial. J Immunother Cancer. (2024) 12:e008409. doi: 10.1136/jitc-2023-008409</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jitc-2023-008409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10941175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38485190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antoniotti C, Rossini D, Pietrantonio F, Catteau A, Salvatore L, Lonardi S, et al. . Upfront FOLFOXIRI plus bevacizumab with or without atezolizumab in the treatment of patients with metastatic colorectal cancer (AtezoTRIBE): a multicentre, open-label, randomised, controlled, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol. (2022) 23:876–87. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(22)00274-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(22)00274-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35636444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ree AH, Šaltytė Benth J, Hamre HM, Kersten C, Hofsli E, Guren MG, et al. . First-line oxaliplatin-based chemotherapy and nivolumab for metastatic microsatellite-stable colorectal cancer-the randomised METIMMOX trial. Br J Cancer. (2024) 130:1921–8. doi: 10.1038/s41416-024-02696-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41416-024-02696-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11183214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38664577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenz HJ, Lonardi S, Elez E, Van Cutsem E, Jensen LH, Bennouna J, et al. . Nivolumab (NIVO) plus ipilimumab (IPI) vs chemotherapy (chemo) as first-line (1L) treatment for microsatellite instability-high/mismatch repair-deficient (MSI-H/dMMR) metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC): Expanded efficacy analysis from CheckMate 8HW. J Clin Oncol. (2024) 42:LBA768–8. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2024.42.16_suppl.3503</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.2024.42.16_suppl.3503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen EX, Jonker DJ, Loree JM, Kennecke HF, Berry SR, Couture F, et al. . Effect of combined immune checkpoint inhibition vs best supportive care alone in patients with advanced colorectal cancer: the canadian cancer trials group CO.26 study. JAMA Oncol. (2020) 6:831–8. doi: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2020.0910</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2020.0910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7206536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32379280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mettu NB, Ou FS, Zemla TJ, Halfdanarson TR, Lenz HJ, Breakstone RA, et al. . Assessment of capecitabine and bevacizumab with or without atezolizumab for the treatment of refractory metastatic colorectal cancer: A randomized clinical trial. JAMA Netw Open. (2022) 5:e2149040. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.49040</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.49040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8857687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35179586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cann CG, LaPelusa MB, Cimino SK, Eng C. Molecular and genetic targets within metastatic colorectal cancer and associated novel treatment advancements. Front Oncol. (2023) 13:1176950. doi: 10.3389/fonc.2023.1176950</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fonc.2023.1176950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10319053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37409250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overman MJ, McDermott R, Leach JL, Lonardi S, Lenz HJ, Morse MA, et al. . Nivolumab in patients with metastatic DNA mismatch repair-deficient or microsatellite instability-high colorectal cancer (CheckMate 142): an open-label, multicentre, phase 2 study [published correction appears in Lancet Oncol. 2017 Sep;18(9):e510. Lancet Oncol. (2017) 18:1182–91. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(17)30422-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(17)30422-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6207072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28734759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Llosa NJ, Cruise M, Tam A, Wicks EC, Hechenbleikner EM, Taube JM, et al. . The vigorous immune microenvironment of microsatellite instable colon cancer is balanced by multiple counter-inhibitory checkpoints. Cancer Discov. (2015) 5:43–51. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-14-0863</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-14-0863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4293246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25358689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Y, Zhao M, Tang W, Zheng X. Impacts of systemic treatments on health-related quality of life for patients with metastatic colorectal cancer: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. BMC Cancer. (2024) 24:188. doi: 10.1186/s12885-024-11937-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12885-024-11937-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10854105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38336718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boukouris AE, Theochari M, Stefanou D, Papalambros A, Felekouras E, Gogas H, et al. . Latest evidence on immune checkpoint inhibitors in metastatic colorectal cancer: A 2022 update. Crit Rev Oncol Hematol. (2022) 173:103663. doi: 10.1016/j.critrevonc.2022.103663</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.critrevonc.2022.103663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35351582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou S, Khanal S, Zhang H. Risk of immune-related adverse events associated with ipilimumab-plus-nivolumab and nivolumab therapy in cancer patients. Ther Clin Risk Manage. (2019) 15:211–21. doi: 10.2147/TCRM.S193338</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/TCRM.S193338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6362938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30774357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yarchoan M, Hopkins A, Jaffee EM. Tumor mutational burden and response rate to PD-1 inhibition. N Engl J Med. (2017) 377:2500–1. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1713444</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc1713444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6549688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29262275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panda A, Betigeri A, Subramanian K, Ross JS, Pavlick DC, Ali S, et al. . Identifying a clinically applicable mutational burden threshold as a potential biomarker of response to immune checkpoint therapy in solid tumors. JCO Precis Oncol. (2017) 2017:PO.17.00146. doi: 10.1200/PO.17.00146</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/PO.17.00146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6016848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29951597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan A, Wang B, Wang X, Nie Y, Fan D, Zhao X, et al. . Immunotherapy in colorectal cancer: current achievements and future perspective. Int J Biol Sci. (2021) 17:3837–49. doi: 10.7150/ijbs.64077</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7150/ijbs.64077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8495390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34671202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor CT, Colgan SP. Regulation of immunity and inflammation by hypoxia in immunological niches. Nat Rev Immunol. (2017) 17:774–85. doi: 10.1038/nri.2017.103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nri.2017.103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5799081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28972206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salas-Benito D, Pérez-Gracia JL, Ponz-Sarvisé M, Rodriguez-Ruiz ME, Martínez-Forero I, Castañón E, et al. . Paradigms on immunotherapy combinations with chemotherapy. Cancer Discov. (2021) 11:1353–67. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-20-1312</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-20-1312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33712487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boku N, Ryu MH, Kato K, Chung HC, Minashi K, Lee KW, et al. . Safety and efficacy of nivolumab in combination with S-1/capecitabine plus oxaliplatin in patients with previously untreated, unresectable, advanced, or recurrent gastric/gastroesophageal junction cancer: interim results of a randomized, phase II trial (ATTRACTION-4). Ann Oncol. (2019) 30:250–8. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdy540</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdy540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6386029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30566590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>