<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39364123</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2186-6953</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>43</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bioscience of microbiota, food and health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biosci Microbiota Food Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>α-ketoglutarate produced by lactic acid bacteria inhibits hyaluronidase activity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>391</StartPage><EndPage>400</EndPage><MedlinePgn>391-400</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.12938/bmfh.2024-017</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In Japan, the growing interest in anti-aging skin care is associated with the unprecedented aging society. Skin aging can be attributed to various factors, including the activation of hyaluronidase enzyme in subcutaneous tissues exposed to ultraviolet radiation. This enzyme breaks down hyaluronic acid, leading to skin sagging. Therefore, hyaluronidase inhibitors can effectively prevent skin aging. Previously, food components have been actively explored to search for hyaluronidase inhibitors considering the high safety of these materials. Although lactic acid bacteria (LAB)-fermented foods inhibit this enzyme, their active compounds responsible for hyaluronidase inhibition remain unknown. Thus, in this study, we aimed to explore the mechanism underlying the LAB-mediated inhibition of hyaluronidase activity. Supernatants of a LAB-fermented milk-based beverage were subjected to a hyaluronidase inhibition assay, followed by purification and separation using hydrophobic adsorbents and high-performance liquid chromatography, respectively. Subsequently, liquid chromatograph time-of-flight mass analysis was performed, revealing α-ketoglutarate (AKG) as the inhibitor of this enzyme. The half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) of AKG was approximately 0.13-fold that of the known strong hyaluronidase inhibitor disodium cromoglycate (DSCG). To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on hyaluronidase inhibition mediated by AKG, a metabolic product of LAB. Additionally, <i>Lactobacillus acidophilus</i> JCM1132 was identified as a highly effective AKG-producing LAB (63.9 µg/mL) through LC-MS/MS-based quantitative analyses using various LAB-fermented milk samples. We anticipate that the findings of this study will potentially support the development of functional foods and cosmetics enriched with AKG.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©2024 BMFH Press.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sato</LastName><ForeName>Taiki</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Development Laboratories, Nissin York Co., Ltd., 272 Kamimurakimi, Hanyu, Saitama 348-8549, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Matsuda</LastName><ForeName>Takahiro</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of Food Safety, Nissin Foods Holdings Co., Ltd., 2100 Tobuki-cho, Hachioji-shi, Tokyo 192-0001, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tagawa</LastName><ForeName>Keisuke</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Development Laboratories, Nissin York Co., Ltd., 272 Kamimurakimi, Hanyu, Saitama 348-8549, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Segawa</LastName><ForeName>Shuichi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Development Laboratories, Nissin York Co., Ltd., 272 Kamimurakimi, Hanyu, Saitama 348-8549, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Japan</Country><MedlineTA>Biosci Microbiota Food Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101578264</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2186-3342</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lactobacillus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Streptococcus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anti-aging</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fermented milk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hyaluronidase</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">skin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">α-ketoglutarate</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>This study was financially supported by Nissin York Co., Ltd. and Nissin Foods Holdings Co., Ltd. Taiki SATO, Keisuke TAGAWA, and Shuichi SEGAWA are associated with Nissin York Co., Ltd. Takahiro MATSUDA is affiliated with Nissin Foods Holdings Co., Ltd.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39364123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11444863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12938/bmfh.2024-017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024-017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Quan T, Fisher GJ. 2015. Role of age-associated alterations of the dermal extracellular matrix microenvironment in human skin aging: a mini-review. Gerontology 61: 427–434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4524793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25660807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masaki H, Atsumi T, Sakurai H. 1995. Detection of hydrogen peroxide and hydroxyl radicals in murine skin fibroblasts under UVB irradiation. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 206: 474–479.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7826364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masaki H. 2010. Role of antioxidants in the skin: anti-aging effects. J Dermatol Sci 58: 85–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20399614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed EM, Hetta MH, Rateb ME, Selim MA, AboulMagd AM, Badria FA, Abdelmohsen UR, Alhadrami HA, Hassan HM. 2020. Bioassay-guided isolation, metabolic profiling, and docking studies of hyaluronidase inhibitors from Ravenala madagascariensis. Molecules 25: 1714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7180949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32276509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshida H, Yamazaki K, Komiya A, Aoki M, Kasamatsu S, Murata T, Sayo T, Cilek MZ, Okada Y, Takahashi Y. 2019. Inhibitory effects of Sanguisorba officinalis root extract on HYBID (KIAA1199)-mediated hyaluronan degradation and skin wrinkling. Int J Cosmet Sci 41: 12–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30485450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madan K, Nanda S. 2018. In-vitro evaluation of antioxidant, anti-elastase, anti-collagenase, anti-hyaluronidase activities of safranal and determination of its sun protection factor in skin photoaging. Bioorg Chem 77: 159–167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29353733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaiyana W, Chansakaow S, Intasai N, Kiattisin K, Lee KH, Lin WC, Lue SC, Leelapornpisid P. 2020. Chemical constituents, antioxidant, anti-MMPs, and anti-hyaluronidase activities of Thunbergia laurifolia Lindl. leaf extracts for skin aging and skin damage prevention. Molecules 25: 1923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7221723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32326348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JH, Moon SH, Hong Y, Ahn DU, Paik HD. 2020. Anti-elastase and anti-hyaluronidase activity of phosvitin isolated from hen egg yolk. Br Poult Sci 61: 17–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31661977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arunkumar K, Raj R, Raja R, Carvalho IS. 2021. Brown seaweeds as a source of anti-hyaluronidase compounds. S Afr J Bot 139: 470–477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Maurya AK, Meena A, Mishra N, Luqman S. 2023. Narirutin. A flavonoid found in citrus fruits modulates cell cycle phases and inhibits the proliferation of hormone-refractory prostate cancer cells by targeting hyaluronidase. Food Chem Toxicol 174: 113638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36708865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oba C, Morifuji M, Ichikawa S, Ito K, Kawahata K, Yamaji T, Asami Y, Itou H, Sugawara T. 2015. Dietary milk sphingomyelin prevents disruption of skin barrier function in hairless mice after UV-B irradiation. PLoS One 10: e0136377.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4547804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26302442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mori N, Kano M, Masuoka N, Konno T, Suzuki Y, Miyazaki K, Ueki Y. 2016. Effect of probiotic and prebiotic fermented milk on skin and intestinal conditions in healthy young female students. Biosci Microbiota Food Health 35: 105–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4965514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27508111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morifuji M, Kitade M, Fukasawa T, Yamaji T, Ichihashi M. 2017. Exopolysaccharides isolated from milk fermented with lactic acid bacteria prevent ultraviolet-induced skin damage in hairless mice. Int J Mol Sci 18: 146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5297779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28098755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaheen AE, Gebreel HM, Moussa LA, Zakaria AE, Nemr WA. 2023. Photoprotection against UV-induced skin damage using hyaluronic acid produced by Lactiplantibacillus plantarum and Enterococcus durans. Curr Microbiol 80: 262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10299924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37369929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbas Mohammed A, Niamah AK. 2022. Production and optimization of hyaluronic acid extracted from Streptococcus thermophilus isolates. Arch Razi Inst 77: 2395–2405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10237568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37274889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Li Y, Xie X, Chen M, Xue L, Wang J, Ye Q, Wu S, Yang R, Zhao H, et al. 2022. Exploration of the molecular mechanisms underlying the anti-photoaging effect of Limosilactobacillus fermentum XJC60. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 12: 838060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9104571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35573770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noda M, Shiraga M, Kumagai T, Danshiitsoodol N, Sugiyama M. 2018. Characterization of the SN35N strain-specific exopolysaccharide encoded in the whole circular genome of a plant-derived Lactobacillus plantarum. Biol Pharm Bull 41: 536–545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29607926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noda M, Sultana N, Hayashi I, Fukamachi M, Sugiyama M. 2019. Exopolysaccharide produced by Lactobacillus paracasei IJH-SONE68 prevents and improves the picryl chloride-induced contact dermatitis. Molecules 24: 2970.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6720527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31426284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maeda Y, Yamamoto M, Masui T, Sugiyama K, Yokota M, Nakagomi K, Tanaka H, Takahashi U, Kobayashi T, Kobayashi E. 1990. Inhibitory effect of tea extracts on hyaluronidase. Food Hyg Saf Sci 31: 233–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayliak MM, Lushchak VI. 2021. Pleiotropic effects of alpha-ketoglutarate as a potential anti-ageing agent. Ageing Res Rev 66: 101237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33340716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katsuno N, Fujimura M, Ishikawa M, Okamoto-Kainuma A, Fukuda Y, Koizumi Y. 2013. Properties of novel products of vinegar produced using roasted sesame seeds. J Brew Soc Japan 108: 361–367.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osuji GO, Cuero RG, Washington AC. 1991. Effects of α-ketoglutarate on the activities of the glutamate synthase, glutamate dehydrogenase, and aspartate transaminase of sweet potato, yam tuber, and cream pea. J Agric Food Chem 39: 1590–1596.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flores P, Hellín P, Fenoll J. 2012. Determination of organic acids in fruits and vegetables by liquid chromatography with tandem-mass spectrometry. Food Chem 132: 1049–1054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Son ED, Choi GH, Kim H, Lee B, Chang IS, Hwang JS. 2007. Alpha-ketoglutarate stimulates procollagen production in cultured human dermal fibroblasts, and decreases UVB-induced wrinkle formation following topical application on the dorsal skin of hairless mice. Biol Pharm Bull 30: 1395–1399.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17666792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Deng P, Liu Y, Wu Y, Chen Y, Guo Y, Zhang S, Zheng X, Zhou L, Liu W, et al. 2020. Alpha-ketoglutarate ameliorates age-related osteoporosis via regulating histone methylations. Nat Commun 11: 5596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7645772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33154378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asadi Shahmirzadi A, Edgar D, Liao CY, Hsu YM, Lucanic M, Asadi Shahmirzadi A, Wiley CD, Gan G, Kim DE, Kasler HG, et al. 2020. Alpha-ketoglutarate, an endogenous metabolite, extends lifespan and compresses morbidity in aging mice. Cell Metab 32: 447–456.e6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8508957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32877690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su Y, Wang T, Wu N, Li D, Fan X, Xu Z, Mishra SK, Yang M. 2019. Alpha-ketoglutarate extends Drosophila lifespan by inhibiting mTOR and activating AMPK. Aging (Albany NY) 11: 4183–4197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6629006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31242135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang F, Zhou Z, Guo M, Zhou Z. 2022. The study of skin hydration, anti-wrinkles function improvement of anti-aging cream with alpha-ketoglutarate. J Cosmet Dermatol 21: 1736–1743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9299201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34817909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morishita T, Yajima M. 1995. Incomplete operation of biosynthetic and bioenergetic functions of the citric acid cycle in multiple auxotrophic lactobacilli. Biosci Biotechnol Biochem 59: 251–255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peralta GH, Bergamini CV, Hynes ER. 2016. Aminotransferase and glutamate dehydrogenase activities in lactobacilli and streptococci. Braz J Microbiol 47: 741–748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4927640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27266631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández de Palencia P, De La Plaza M, Amárita F, Requena T, Peláez C. 2006. Diversity of amino acid converting enzymes in wild lactic acid bacteria. Enzyme Microb Technol 38: 88–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams AG, Withers SE, Brechany EY, Banks JM. 2006. Glutamate dehydrogenase activity in lactobacilli and the use of glutamate dehydrogenase-producing adjunct Lactobacillus spp. cultures in the manufacture of cheddar cheese. J Appl Microbiol 101: 1062–1075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17040230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kieronczyk A, Skeie S, Langsrud T, Yvon M. 2003. Cooperation between Lactococcus lactis and nonstarter lactobacilli in the formation of cheese aroma from amino acids. Appl Environ Microbiol 69: 734–739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC143583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12570989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>