<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39368591</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhanced emulsification properties of microalgae protein through gellan gum conjugation: Mechanistic insights and applications in curcumin encapsulation and delivery.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136275</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136275</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136275</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)07084-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The emulsification properties of microalgae protein (MP) are poor, especially under acidic and neutral conditions, which may limit the broad applications of MP in food processing. This study aims to explore the effects of gellan gum (GG) on the emulsification properties of MP. Firstly, MP-GG complexes were prepared and their structures characterized. Subsequently, MP-GG complexes stabilized emulsions were prepared and their stability evaluated. Finally, these emulsions were employed for the encapsulation and delivery of curcumin to evaluate their potential as an efficient nutrient delivery medium. Results indicated that MP-GG complexes were formed under various pH conditions, with pH 6 identified as optimal for complexes stability (zeta-potential value was -31 mV). UV-vis and fluorescence spectroscopy demonstrated that GG did not significantly alter the MP's structure but induced slight conformational changes, leading to the burial of some amino acid residues. Zeta potential measurements confirmed that MP-GG complexes were stabilized by strong electrostatic repulsions. The increase of GG content was conducive to providing more negative charge and promoting the dissolution and dispersion of the MP-GG complexes (MP: GG = 1: 1). Emulsions stabilized by MP-GG complexes exhibited smaller droplet sizes and improved stability compared to those stabilized by MP alone, especially at oil phase volume fractions of 60 % and 70 %. Rheological analysis indicated that GG enhanced emulsion stability by increasing viscosity, and higher oil phase volume fractions facilitated better MP-GG complexes adsorption on oil droplets, strengthening network structures of emulsions. During in vitro simulated gastrointestinal digestion, emulsions with a 70 % oil phase exhibited higher curcumin retention rate (31.09 %) and lower curcumin bioaccessibility (13.23 %) compared to those with a 60 % oil phase. This suggests that emulsions with higher oil phase volume fractions may be more suitable for colon-targeted curcumin delivery, with potential applications in promoting colon health. These findings confirm that the complexation of MP and GG was an effective way to improve the emulsification properties of MP. Emulsions stabilized by MP-GG complexes can serve as stable nutritional delivery systems for fat-soluble bioactive compounds.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Xiao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Deep Processing of Major Grain and Oil, The Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Food Science and Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan 430023, Hubei, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qiao</LastName><ForeName>Yuqian</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Deep Processing of Major Grain and Oil, The Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Food Science and Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan 430023, Hubei, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Zhicheng</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of Agricultural Products Processing and Nuclear-Agricultural Technology, Hubei Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Wuhan 430064, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gong</LastName><ForeName>Zhiyong</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Deep Processing of Major Grain and Oil, The Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Food Science and Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan 430023, Hubei, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Qian</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Deep Processing of Major Grain and Oil, The Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Food Science and Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan 430023, Hubei, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jinjie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Systems Engineering Institute, AMS, PLA, Bejing 100010, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Yongning</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Deep Processing of Major Grain and Oil, The Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Food Science and Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan 430023, Hubei, China; NHC Key Laboratory of Food Safety Risk Assessment, China National Center for Food Safety Risk Assessment, Beijing 100021, China; Department of Nutrition and Food Safety, Peking Union Medical College, Research Unit of Food Safety, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Beijing 100021, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Xin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Deep Processing of Major Grain and Oil, The Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Food Science and Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan 430023, Hubei, China. Electronic address: liuxinhook@whpu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Jin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Systems Engineering Institute, AMS, PLA, Bejing 100010, China. Electronic address: 13810513561@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Curcumin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emulsion stability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gellan gum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Microalgae protein</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39368591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)07084-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>