<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39360270</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2296-861X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The role of duel hydrolysis of soybean on functional properties and protein digestibility: a sustainable approach.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1444329</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1444329</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1444329</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fnut.2024.1444329</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Protein hydrolysates derived from food sources contains enormous number of peptides which are composed of amino acid possessess various bioactive properties. However, the use of protein hydrolysates as a nutraceutical is hindered due to their unpleasant flavour. The study aims to enhance the biological activity and palatability of protein hydrolysates.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODOLOGY" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In the present study, soybean protein hydrolysate (SPH) was prepared using alcalase for 4 h (control). Modification of hydrolysis (MPH) was carried out by reiterating the hydrolysis of the supernatant obtained after 2 h of hydrolysis using an enzyme to 50% of alcalase during each successive hydrolysis. Samples were characterised by their physio-chemical and functional properties. Furthermore, the effect of modification on the protein digestibility and bitterness intensity using e-tongue was studied. The suppressive effect on retrogradation of corn starch was analysed using texture profile analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The results demonstrated increased protein content by 1.6 and 1.9% in MPH compared to SPH and UNH, respectively. MPH showed 1.5- and 1.6-fold higher DH% than SPH before and after gastrointestinal digestion (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05). A decrease in molecular weight was found in the order of UNH &gt; SPH &gt; MPH. Nevertheless, MPH displayed significantly higher functional properties (<i>p</i> ≤ 0.05). The hardness of retrograded corn starch was significantly reduced in the MPH (1.21N) than SPH (1.55 N) and UNH (1.81N) compared to control (1.71N) during 7-day storage at 4°C <i>(p</i> ≤ 0.05). E-tongue analysis of MPH showed a 4-fold reduction in bitterness than SPH.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Modification of hydrolysis of soybean has demonstrated its significance in improved DH% functional properties and palatability. In addition, improved protein digestibility with promising benefits in deferral action on retrogradation of starch over the traditional process of hydrolysis was observed. The outcome of this study contributes to the potential utilisation of MPH as an ingredient in the formulation of nutraceutical products.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Jogi, Adusumilli, Nagesh, Yannam and Mamatha.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jogi</LastName><ForeName>Nishithkumar</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NITTE (Deemed to be University), Department of Food Safety and Nutrition, Nitte University Centre for Science Education and Research (NUCSER), Mangalore, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adusumilli</LastName><ForeName>Somya</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Traditional Foods and Applied Nutrition, Central Food Technological Research Institute (CFTRI), Mysore, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nagesh</LastName><ForeName>Madhukar</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Freeze Drying and Animal Product Technology Division, Defence Food Research Laboratory, DRDO, Ministry of Defence, Mysore, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yannam</LastName><ForeName>Sudheer Kumar</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Traditional Foods and Applied Nutrition, Central Food Technological Research Institute (CFTRI), Mysore, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mamatha</LastName><ForeName>Bangera Sheshappa</ForeName><Initials>BS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NITTE (Deemed to be University), Department of Food Safety and Nutrition, Nitte University Centre for Science Education and Research (NUCSER), Mangalore, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101642264</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-861X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bitternes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">duel hydrolysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">functional food</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">modification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">soybean</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>37</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39360270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11444959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2024.1444329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lassissi TA, Hettiarachchy NS, Rayaprolu SJ, Kannan A, Davis M. Functional properties and Angiotensin-I converting enzyme inhibitory activity of soy – whey proteins and fractions. FRIN. (2014) 64:598–602. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2014.07.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2014.07.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30011693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jogi N, Yathisha UG, Bhat I. Antihypertensive activity of orally consumed ACE-I inhibitory peptides. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. (2021) 62:8986–99. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2021.1938508, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.1938508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34213991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma AK, Chatli MK, Kumar P, Mehta N. Antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of porcine liver hydrolysate in meat emulsion and their influence on Physico-chemical and color deterioration during refrigeration storage. J Food Sci. (2019) 84:1844–53. doi: 10.1111/1750-3841.14683</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.14683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31218699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yathisha UG, Karunasagar I, Mamatha BS. Bioactivity and functional properties of protein hydrolysate from muscle and visceral waste of ribbon fish (Lepturacanthus savala). Extracted Three Differ Proteolytic Enzymes. (2021) 11:363–79. doi: 10.1080/22311866.2021.1953399</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/22311866.2021.1953399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterjee C, Gleddie S, Xiao CW. Soybean bioactive peptides and their functional properties. Nutrients. (2018) 10:8–11. doi: 10.3390/nu10091211, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu10091211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6164536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30200502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanafi MA, Hashim SN, Chay SY, Ebrahimpour A, Zarei M, Muhammad K, et al. . High angiotensin-I converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitory activity of Alcalase-digested green soybean (Glycine max) hydrolysates. Food Res Int. (2018) 106:589–97. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2018.01.030, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2018.01.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29579964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q, Cheng Z, Wang Y, Zheng S, Wang Y, Fu L. Combining Alcalase hydrolysis and transglutaminase-cross-linking improved bitterness and techno-functional properties of hypoallergenic soybean protein hydrolysates through structural modifications. LWT. (2021) 151:112096. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112096</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idowu AT, Benjakul S. Bitterness of fish protein hydrolysate and its debittering prospects. J Food Biochem. (2019) 43:e12978–10. doi: 10.1111/jfbc.12978, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31489658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yarnpakdee S, Benjakul S, Kristinsson HG, Kishimura H. Antioxidant and sensory properties of protein hydrolysate derived from Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) by one- and two-step hydrolysis. J Food Sci Technol. (2015) 52:3336–49. doi: 10.1007/s13197-014-1394-7, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-014-1394-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4444872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26028714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daukšas E, Šližyte R, Rustad T, Storrø I. Bitterness in fish protein hydrolysates and methods for removal. J. Aquatic Food Product Technol. (2004) 13:101–14. doi: 10.1300/J030v13n02_09</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1300/J030v13n02_09</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humiski LM, Aluko RE. Physicochemical and bitterness properties of enzymatic pea protein hydrolysates. J Food Sci. (2007) 72:S605–11. doi: 10.1111/j.1750-3841.2007.00475.x, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2007.00475.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17995627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, He C, Zhang M, Zhang L, Xiong H, Zhao Q. Inhibition from whey protein hydrolysate on the retrogradation of gelatinized rice starch. Food Hydrocoll. (2020) 108:105840. doi: 10.1016/j.foodhyd.2020.105840</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2020.105840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Y, Niu L, Zhang S, Xiao J. Effect of grass carp skin protein hydrolysates on the Retrogradation tendency of gelatinized Rice starch in the presence of non-ionic and ionic hydrocolloids during cold storage. Starch/Staerke. (2019) 71:1–29. doi: 10.1002/star.201800260</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/star.201800260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samutsri W, Suphantharika M. Effect of salts on pasting, thermal, and rheological properties of rice starch in the presence of non-ionic and ionic hydrocolloids. Carbohydr Polym. (2012) 87:1559–68. doi: 10.1016/j.carbpol.2011.09.055</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2011.09.055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang M, Hong Y, Gu Z, Zhang Y, Cai X. The effect of xanthan on short and long-term retrogradation of rice starch. Starch/Staerke. (2013) 65:702–8. doi: 10.1002/star.201200170</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/star.201200170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yathisha UG, Vaidya S, Sheshappa MB. Functional properties of protein Hydrolyzate from ribbon fish (Lepturacanthus Savala) as prepared by enzymatic hydrolysis. Int J Food Prop. (2022) 25:187–203. doi: 10.1080/10942912.2022.2027964</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10942912.2022.2027964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idowu AT, Benjakul S, Sinthusamran S, Sookchoo P, Kishimura H. Protein hydrolysate from salmon frames: production, characteristics and antioxidative activity. J Food Biochem. (2018) 43:e12734–12. doi: 10.1111/jfbc.12734, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31353651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vashishth R, Semwal AD, Naika M, Sharma GK, Kumar R. Influence of cooking methods on antinutritional factors, oligosaccharides and protein quality of underutilized legume Macrotyloma uniflorum. Food Res Int. (2021) 143:110299. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110299, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33992319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suryabhan P, Lohith K, Anu-Appaiah KA. Sucrose and sorbitol supplementation on maltodextrin encapsulation enhance the potential probiotic yeast survival by spray drying. LWT. (2019) 107:243–8. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2019.03.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2019.03.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das M, Mayookha VP, Geetha V, Chetana R, Suresh Kumar G. Influence of different drying techniques on quality parameters of mushroom and its utilization in development of ready to cook food formulation. J Food Sci Technol. (2023) 60:1342–54. doi: 10.1007/s13197-023-05680-9, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-023-05680-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10020389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36936127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh V, Kushwaha R, Kaur D. Optimization study of sweeteners for preparation of syrup for sugar free traditional sweet: Gulab jamun. Int J Curr Res Rev. (2017) 9:45–53. doi: 10.7324/ijcrr.2017.9217</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7324/ijcrr.2017.9217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leni G, Soetemans L, Caligiani A, Sforza S, Bastiaens L. Degree of hydrolysis affects the techno-functional properties of lesser mealworm protein hydrolysates. Food Secur. (2020) 9:381. doi: 10.3390/foods9040381, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods9040381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7230224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32218377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanjukta S, Rai AK, Muhammed A, Jeyaram K, Talukdar NC. Enhancement of antioxidant properties of two soybean varieties of Sikkim Himalayan region by proteolytic Bacillus subtilis fermentation. Elsevier. (2015) 14:650–8. doi: 10.1016/j.jff.2015.02.033</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2015.02.033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saisavoey T, Sangtanoo P, Reamtong O, Karnchanatat A. Antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of defatted Rice bran (Oryza Sativa L.) protein hydrolysates on raw 264.7 macrophage cells. J Food Biochem. (2016) 40:731–40. doi: 10.1111/jfbc.12266</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CPCSEA . CPCSEA guidelines for laboratory animal facility. Indian J. Pharmacol. (2003) 35:257–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussein FA, Chay SY, Ghanisma SBM, Zarei M, Auwal SM, Hamid AA, et al. . Toxicity study and blood pressure–lowering efficacy of whey protein concentrate hydrolysate in rat models, plus peptide characterization. J Dairy Sci. (2020) 103:2053–64. doi: 10.3168/jds.2019-17462, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2019-17462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31882211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasri M. (2017) Protein hydrolysates and biopeptides: production, biological activities, and applications in foods and health benefits. 1stst edn, ed. F. Toldrá (Department of Food Science, Instituto de Agroquímica y Tecnología de Alimentos (CSIC)). 81. Advances in food and nutrition research. San diego, CA: United States: Elsevier Inc</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28317603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhandari D, Rafiq S, Gat Y, Gat P, Waghmare R, Kumar V. A review on bioactive peptides: physiological functions, bioavailability and safety. Int J Pept Res Ther. (2020) 26:139–50. doi: 10.1007/s10989-019-09823-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10989-019-09823-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Embiriekah S, Bulatović M, Borić M, Zarić D, Rakin M. Antioxidant activity, functional properties and bioaccessibility of whey protein hydrolysates. Int J Dairy Technol. (2018) 71:243–52. doi: 10.1111/1471-0307.12428</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1471-0307.12428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim SY, Park PSW, Rhee KC. Functional properties of proteolytic enzyme modified soy protein isolate. J Agric Food Chem. (2002) 38:651–6. doi: 10.1021/JF00093A014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/JF00093A014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalamaiah M, Jyothirmayi T, Diwan PV, Dinesh Kumar B. Antioxidant activity and functional properties of enzymatic protein hydrolysates from common carp (Cyprinus carpio) roe (egg). J Food Sci Technol. (2015) 52:5817–25. doi: 10.1007/s13197-015-1714-6, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-015-1714-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4554606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26344996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamora-sillero J, Gharsallaoui A, Prentice C. Peptides from fish by-product protein hydrolysates and its functional properties: an overview. New York, NY: Marine Biotechnology. (2018) 20:118–130. doi: 10.1007/s10126-018-9799-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10126-018-9799-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29532335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balti R, Bougatef A, el-Hadj Ali N, Zekri D, Barkia A, Nasri M. Influence of degree of hydrolysis on functional properties and angiotensin I-converting enzyme-inhibitory activity of protein hydrolysates from cuttlefish (Sepia officinalis) by-products. J Sci Food Agric. (2010) 90:2006–14. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.4045, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.4045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20583200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karimi A, Azizi MH, Ahmadi Gavlighi H. Frationation of hydrolysate from corn germ protein by ultrafiltration: in vitro antidiabetic and antioxidant activity. Food Sci Nutr. (2020) 8:2395–405. doi: 10.1002/fsn3.1529, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7215226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32405396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawdkuen S, Rodzi N, Pinijsuwan S. Characterization of sacha inchi protein hydrolysates produced by crude papain and Calotropis proteases. LWT. (2018) 98:18–24. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2018.08.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2018.08.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh PV. Protein hydrolysate from duck egg white by Flavourzyme® digestion: process optimisation by model design approach and evaluation of antioxidant capacity and characteristic properties. LWT. (2022) 156:113018. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2021.113018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.113018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yathisha UG, Bhat I, Karunasagar I, Mamatha BS. Antihypertensive activity of fish protein hydrolysates and its peptides. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. (2019) 59:2363–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29533693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan W, Tan X, Xu X, Li G, Wang Z, du M. Relationship between enzyme, peptides, amino acids, ion composition, and bitterness of the hydrolysates of Alaska Pollock frame. J Food Biochem. (2019) 43:e12801–9. doi: 10.1111/jfbc.12801, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31353581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman J, Harbourne N, O’Riordan D, Jacquier JC, O’Sullivan M. Comparison of a trained sensory panel and an electronic tongue in the assessment of bitter dairy protein hydrolysates. J Food Eng. (2014) 128:127–31. doi: 10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2013.12.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2013.12.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horax R, Vallecios MS, Hettiarachchy N, Osorio LF, Chen P. Solubility, functional properties, ACE-I inhibitory and DPPH scavenging activities of Alcalase hydrolysed soy protein hydrolysates. Int J Food Sci Technol. (2017) 52:196–204. doi: 10.1111/ijfs.13267</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijfs.13267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterjee R, Dey TK, Ghosh M, Dhar P. Enzymatic modification of sesame seed protein, sourced from waste resource for nutraceutical application. Food Bioprod Process. (2015) 94:70–81. doi: 10.1016/j.fbp.2015.01.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbp.2015.01.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moghadam M, Salami M, Mohammadian M, Emam-Djomeh Z, Jahanbani R, Moosavi-Movahedi AA. Physicochemical and bio-functional properties of walnut proteins as affected by trypsin-mediated hydrolysis. Food Biosci. (2020) 36:100611. doi: 10.1016/j.fbio.2020.100611</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2020.100611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mokni Ghribi A, Maklouf Gafsi I, Sila A, Blecker C, Danthine S, Attia H, et al. . Effects of enzymatic hydrolysis on conformational and functional properties of chickpea protein isolate. Food Chem. (2015) 187:322–30. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.04.109, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.04.109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25977033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cingöz A, Yildirim M. Effects of hydrolysis degree on the functional properties of hydrolysates from sour cherry kernel protein concentrate. Foods Raw Materials. (2023) 11:197–205. doi: 10.21603/2308-4057-2023-2-566</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21603/2308-4057-2023-2-566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan X, Yao H, Chen Z, Shan L, Zhang M. Some functional properties of oat bran protein concentrate modified by trypsin. Food Chem. (2007) 101:163–70. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2006.01.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2006.01.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aryee ANA, Boye JI. Improving the digestibility of lentil flours and protein isolate and characterization of their enzymatically prepared hydrolysates. Int J Food Prop. (2016) 19:2649–65. doi: 10.1080/10942912.2015.1123269</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10942912.2015.1123269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popović L, Peričin D, Vaštag Ž, Popović S, Krimer V, Torbica A. Antioxidative and functional properties of pumpkin oil cake globulin hydrolysates. J Am Oil Chemists Soc. (2013) 90:1157–65. doi: 10.1007/s11746-013-2257-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11746-013-2257-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jogi N, Mathew A, Mamatha BS. Modification of bioactive properties in food protein hydrolysates by Alcalase and trypsin. J Health Allied Sci. (2024) 2024. doi: 10.1055/s-0044-1782643</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0044-1782643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu R, Wang L, Liu Y, Wu T, Zhang M. Fabricating soy protein hydrolysate/xanthan gum as fat replacer in ice cream by combined enzymatic and heat-shearing treatment. Food Hydrocoll. (2018) 81:39–47. doi: 10.1016/j.foodhyd.2018.01.031</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2018.01.031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umayaparvathi S, Meenakshi S, Vimalraj V, Arumugam M, Sivagami G, Balasubramanian T. Antioxidant activity and anticancer effect of bioactive peptide from enzymatic hydrolysate of oyster (Saccostrea cucullata). Biomed Prevent Nutr. (2014) 4:343–53. doi: 10.1016/j.bionut.2014.04.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bionut.2014.04.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>