<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39362262</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1474-5488</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>25</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Lancet. Oncology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet Oncol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A brave new framework for glioma drug development.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e512</StartPage><EndPage>e519</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e512-e519</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/S1470-2045(24)00190-6</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1470-2045(24)00190-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Patients with brain tumours are motivated to participate in clinical trials involving repeat tissue sampling. Normalising the use of neoadjuvant and staged surgical trials necessitates collaboration among patients, regulatory agencies, and researchers. Initial and repetitive tissue sampling plays a crucial role in enhancing our understanding of resistance mechanisms and vulnerabilities in brain tumour therapy. Standardising biopsy techniques and ensuring technical uniformity across institutions are vital for effective interinstitutional collaboration. Although liquid biopsy technologies hold promise, they are not yet ready to replace tissue analysis. Clear communication about the risks and benefits of biopsies is essential, particularly regarding potential postoperative deficits. Changes in mindset and neurosurgical culture are imperative to achieve much needed breakthroughs in the development of new, effective therapies for brain tumours.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hotchkiss</LastName><ForeName>Kelly M</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke, Department of Neurosurgery, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Karschnia</LastName><ForeName>Philipp</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Friedrich-Alexander University, Erlangen, Germany; Ludwig-Maximilians-University, Munich, Germany; German Cancer Consortium (DKTK), Partner Site Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schreck</LastName><ForeName>Karisa C</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA; Department of Oncology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Geurts</LastName><ForeName>Marjolein</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Erasmus MC Cancer Center, Rotterdam, Netherlands; Department of Medical Oncology, Erasmus MC Cancer Center, Rotterdam, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cloughesy</LastName><ForeName>Timothy F</ForeName><Initials>TF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>David Geffen School of Medicine at UCLA, Los Angeles, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huse</LastName><ForeName>Jason</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA; Department of Translational Molecular Pathology, University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duke</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth S</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Oncology 2, Office of Oncologic Diseases, Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, US Food and Drug Administration, Silver Spring, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lathia</LastName><ForeName>Justin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH, USA; Rose Ella Burkhardt Brain Tumor and Neuro-Oncology Center, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH, USA; Case Comprehensive Cancer Center, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashley</LastName><ForeName>David M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke, Department of Neurosurgery, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nduom</LastName><ForeName>Edjah K</ForeName><Initials>EK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Long</LastName><ForeName>Georgina</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Melanoma Institute Australia, The University of Sydney, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Faculty of Medicine and Health, Charles Perkins Centre, The University of Sydney, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Mater and Royal North Shore Hospitals, Sydney, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Kirit</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke, Department of Neurosurgery, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chalmers</LastName><ForeName>Anthony</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Cancer Sciences, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahluwalia</LastName><ForeName>Manmeet S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Baptist Health South Florida, Miami, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heimberger</LastName><ForeName>Amy</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, Northwestern University, Chicago, IL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bagley</LastName><ForeName>Stephen</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine, Philadelphia, PA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Todo</LastName><ForeName>Tomoki</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Neuro-Oncology, The Institute of Medical Science, The University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verhaak</LastName><ForeName>Roel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Neuro-Oncology, Yale University, New Haven, CT, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kelly</LastName><ForeName>Patrick D</ForeName><Initials>PD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hervey-Jumper</LastName><ForeName>Shawn</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, UCSF Brain Tumor Center, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA; Weill Institute for Neuroscience, Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center, San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Groot</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, UCSF Brain Tumor Center, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA; Weill Institute for Neuroscience, Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center, San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Anoop</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke, Department of Neurosurgery, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fecci</LastName><ForeName>Peter</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke, Department of Neurosurgery, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parney</LastName><ForeName>Ian</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wykes</LastName><ForeName>Victoria</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Cancer and Genomic Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK; Department of Neurosurgery, Queen Elizabeth Hospital Birmingham, University Hospitals Birmingham NHS Foundation Trust, Birmingham, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Watts</LastName><ForeName>Colin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Cancer and Genomic Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK; Department of Neurosurgery, Queen Elizabeth Hospital Birmingham, University Hospitals Birmingham NHS Foundation Trust, Birmingham, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burns</LastName><ForeName>Terry C</ForeName><Initials>TC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sanai</LastName><ForeName>Nader</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Barrow Neurological Institute, Phoenix, AZ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Preusser</LastName><ForeName>Matthias</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine I, Division of Oncology, Medical University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tonn</LastName><ForeName>Joerg Christian</ForeName><Initials>JC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ludwig-Maximilians-University, Munich, Germany; German Cancer Consortium (DKTK), Partner Site Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Drummond</LastName><ForeName>Katharine J</ForeName><Initials>KJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Royal Melbourne Hospital, Parkville, VIC, Australia; Department of Surgery, University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Platten</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Mannheim Center for Translational Neuroscience, Medical Faculty Mannheim, Heidelberg University, Heidelberg, Germany; Clinical Cooperation Unit Brain Tumor Immunology (D170), German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Das</LastName><ForeName>Sunit</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Neurosurgery, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tanner</LastName><ForeName>Kirk</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Brain Tumor Society, Newton, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vogelbaum</LastName><ForeName>Michael A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>H Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute, Tampa, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weller</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA; Department of Neurology, University Hospital Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Whittle</LastName><ForeName>James R</ForeName><Initials>JR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biology, University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC, Australia; Department of Medical Oncology, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Melbourne, VIC, Australia; Personalised Oncology Division, Walter and Eliza Hall Institute, Parkville, VIC, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berger</LastName><ForeName>Mitchel S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, UCSF Brain Tumor Center, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA; Weill Institute for Neuroscience, Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center, San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khasraw</LastName><ForeName>Mustafa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke, Department of Neurosurgery, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC, USA. Electronic address: mustafa.khasraw@duke.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet Oncol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100957246</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1470-2045</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000970">Antineoplastic Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001932" MajorTopicYN="Y">Brain Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005910" MajorTopicYN="Y">Glioma</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000076722" MajorTopicYN="Y">Drug Development</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000970" MajorTopicYN="N">Antineoplastic Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests MG declares research grant support from Evgen Pharm. KCS declares honoraria from Springworks Therapeutics and Novartis; declares research funding to her institution from Springworks Therapeutics; and serves on a data and safety monitoring board for Advarra. TFC is cofounder, major stock holder, consultant, and board member of Katmai Pharmaceuticals; holds stock for Erasca; is a member of the board and paid consultant for the 501c3 Global Coalition for Adaptive Research; holds stock in Chimerix and receives milestone payments and possible future royalties; is a member of the scientific advisory board for Break Through Cancer foundation and Cure Brain Cancer Foundation; has provided paid consulting services to Symbio, Mundipharma, Tango BlueRock, Vida Ventures, Lista Therapeutics, Stemline, Novartis, Roche, Sonalasense, Sagimet, Clinical Care Options, Ideology Health, Servier, Jubilant, Immvira, Gan &amp; Lee, BrainStorm, Katmai, Sapience, Inovio, Vigeo Therapeutics, DNATrix, Tyme, SDP, Kintara, Bayer, Merck, Boehringer Ingelheim, VBL, Amgen, Kiyatec, AbbVie, VBI, Deciphera, Agios, Novocure, and Medscape; and has contracts with UCLA for the Brain Tumour Programme with Roche, VBI, Merck, Novartis, and Bristol Myers Squibb. The Regents of the University of California, TFC's employer, has licensed intellectual property co-invented by TFC to Katmai Pharmaceuticals. GL is consultant advisor for Agenus, Amgen, Array Biopharma, AstraZeneca, Bayer, BioNTech, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol Myers Squibb, Evaxion, Hexal AG (Sandoz Company), Highlight Therapeutics, IOBiotech, Immunocore, Innovent Biologics USA, Merck Sharpe &amp; Dohme, Novartis, PHMR, Pierre Fabre, and Regeneron. AC declares research funding and honoraria from AstraZeneca, Benevolent AI, Duke Street Bio, and Evgen Pharmaceuticals; and has received honoraria from Storm Therapeutics. MSA declares a grant from Seagen; declares consulting fees from Bayer, Kiyatec, Insightec, GSK, Xoft, Nuvation, SDP Oncology, Apollomics, Prelude, Janssen, Voyager Therapeutics, Viewray, Caris Lifesciences, Pyramid Biosciences, Varian Medical Systems, Cairn Therapeutics, Anheart Therapeutics, Theraguix, Menarini Ricerche, Sumitomo Pharma Oncology, Autem Therapeutics, GT Medical Technologies, Allovir, and Equillium Bio; is on the data and safety monitoring board for VBI Vaccines; is on the scientific advisory board of Modifi biosciences and Bugworks; and is a shareholder for Mimivax, Cytodyn, MedInnovate Advisors, and Trisalus Lifesciences. SB reports consulting fees from and is a member of the advisory boards of Telix, Servier, Bayer, and Novocure; and research grants from Incyte, GSK, Lilly, Kite, and Novocure. JdG reports being an advisory board member for Kintara Pharmaceuticals, Kazia, MundiPharma, Insightec, Monteris, Carthera, Samus, Sapience, DSP Pharma, Telix, Servier, Alpha Pharmaceuticals, Nervianos, and CapitalOne; is a data safety monitoring board member for Chimerix and VBI; and has consulted for MundiPharma, Insightec, Carthera, Kintara, Deciphera, Kazia, and Nervianos. IP reports research funding from Merck. TCB reports consulting roles for Predicine; has received financial support from AbbVie and Predicine, with consulting fees paid to Mayo Clinic; and has been a member of the advisory board for Neurametrix. MPr reports honoraria from the following for-profit companies: Bayer, Bristol Myers Squibb, Novartis, Gerson Lehrman Group, CMC Contrast, GSK, Mundipharma, Roche, BMJ Journals, MedMedia, AstraZeneca, AbbVie, Lilly, Medahead, Daiichi Sankyo, Sanofi, Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme, Tocagen, Adastra, Gan &amp; Lee Pharmaceuticals, Janssen, Servier, Miltenyi, Boehringer Ingelheim, Telix, and Medscape. JCT reports research grants from Novocure and Munich Surgical Imaging; being on the advisory board of Advanced Accelerator Applications, Novartis; and Servier; and has received royalties from Springer Publishing. MPl reports being a founder of Tcelltech; has received research support from Bayer, Roche, Pfizer, and Merck; and is an advisory board member of Bayer and Servier. SD is speaker for the Congress of Neurological Surgeons (CNS) and the American Association of Neurological Surgeons; receives research funding from Alkermes; is a member of the Subcortical Surgery Group advisory board; has received royalties from Oxford University Press; and is provincial lead for CNS Oncology at Ontario Health. KT reports consulting fees from Oncohereos Biosciences; and advisory board roles for Advanced Accelerator Applications, Novartis; Sage Therapeutics; FYR Diagnostics; Cordance Medical; Telo Therapeutics; and Modifi Bio. MAV reports clinical trial funding to their institution from DeNovo Pharma, Infuseon, and Oncosynergy; and received honoraria fees from Biodexa and Servier Pharma. MW reports research grants from Novartis, Quercis, and Versameb; honoraria for advisory boards from Roche and Servier; and honoraria for consultation from Bayer, Curevac, Medac, Neurosense, Novartis, Novocure, Orbus, Philogen, and Servier. JRW reports research funding from AnHeart Therapeutics to their institution; received consulting fees from AnHeart Therapeutics and Servier; being on advisory boards for Roche and Merck; is a data safety monitoring member for Telix Pharmaceuticals; and is an employee of The Walter and Eliza Hall Institute and could be eligible for milestone and royalty payments related to Venetoclax. MK reports research grants from Bristol Myers Squibb, AbbVie, BioNTech, CNS Pharmaceuticals, Daiichi Sankyo, Immorna Therapeutics, Immvira Therapeutics, and Personalis; received consulting fees from The Jackson Lab for Genomic Research, AnHeart Therapeutics, Berg Pharma, George Clinical, Manarini Stemline, and Servier; received honoraria from GSK; and is on a data safety monitoring board for BPGbio. All other authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39362262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(24)00190-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1470-2045(24)00190-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>