<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39362910</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Diagnosing skin cancer using social spider optimization (SSO) and error correcting output codes (ECOC) with weighted hamming distance.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>22997</StartPage><MedlinePgn>22997</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">22997</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-73219-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Skin cancer is a common disease resulting from genetic defects, and early detection is critical to improve treatment outcomes. Diagnostic programs that use computer aid especially those that use supervised learning are very useful in early diagnosis of skin cancer. This research therefore presents a new approach that integrates optimization methods with supervised learning to improve skin cancer diagnosis using machine vision approach. The presented method is initiated by data pre-processing that involves the removal of unnecessary data. Then, to segment the images, a combination of K-means clustering and social spider optimization technique is employed. The region of interest is then extracted from the segmented image and from this region a convolutional neural network extracts the significant features. To enhance the classification performance as compared with the standard classifiers, this research introduces a new concept of error correcting output codes coupled with a weighted Hamming distance in the group of gamma classifiers. The ability of the proposed approach in segmentation of skin lesions and classifying them was tested using samples from the ISIC-2017 and ISIC-2016 databases. The introduced method obtained state-of-the-art accuracy on both datasets (ISIC-2016: 97.10%, ISIC-2017: 95.17%). In particularly, the accuracy of the introduced approach for both these databases is at least 1.17% higher than the compared methods. This proves the high performance of the suggested method based on the usage of the convolutional neural networks for feature extraction and gamma classifiers with error correcting output codes for classification in skin cancer detection.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahin</LastName><ForeName>Jafaridarabjerdi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, The Second Hospital of Dalian Medical University, Dalian, 116023, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Xuezhu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, The Second Hospital of Dalian Medical University, Dalian, 116023, China. xuxzdl@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, The Second Hospital of Dalian Medical University, Dalian, 116023, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Cong</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Nutrition and Safety, Dalian Medical University, Dalian, 116044, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>No.2021JH1/10400051</GrantID><Agency>Liaoning Provincial Department of Science and Technology "Unveiled" Science and Technology Plan Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012878" MajorTopicYN="Y">Skin Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016571" MajorTopicYN="Y">Neural Networks, Computer</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000465" MajorTopicYN="N">Algorithms</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007091" MajorTopicYN="N">Image Processing, Computer-Assisted</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016208" MajorTopicYN="N">Databases, Factual</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003936" MajorTopicYN="N">Diagnosis, Computer-Assisted</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055088" MajorTopicYN="N">Early Detection of Cancer</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Convolutional neural network</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gamma classifier</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Skin cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social spider optimization</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39362910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11450013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-73219-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-73219-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Narayanamurthy, V. et al. Skin cancer detection using non-invasive techniques. RSC Adv.8 (49), 28095–28130 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9084287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35542700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achakanalli, S. &amp; Sadashivappa, G. Statistical analysis of skin cancer image–a case study. Int. J. Electron. Commun. Eng. (IJECE)3(3), 1–10 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, P. K., Agarwal, D. &amp; Gupta, A. A systematic review on software defect prediction. In 2015 2nd international conference on computing for sustainable global development (INDIACom) (pp. 1793–1797). IEEE, 2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaleel, J. A., Salim, S. &amp; Aswin, R. B. Computer aided detection of skin cancer. In 2013 international conference on circuits, power and computing technologies (ICCPCT) (pp. 1137–1142) (IEEE, 2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daghrir, J., Tlig, L., Bouchouicha, M. &amp; Sayadi, M. Melanoma skin cancer detection using deep learning and classical machine learning techniques: A hybrid approach. In 2020 5th international conference on advanced technologies for signal and image processing (ATSIP), pp. 1–5 (IEEE, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demir, A., Yilmaz, F. &amp; Kose, O. Early detection of skin cancer using deep learning architectures: resnet-101 and inception-v3. In 2019 medical technologies congress (TIPTEKNO), pp. 1–4 (IEEE, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majtner, T., Yildirim-Yayilgan, S. &amp; Hardeberg, J. Y. Optimised deep learning features for improved melanoma detection. Multimed. Tools Appl.78, 11883–11903 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vipin, V. et al. Detection of melanoma using deep learning techniques: A review. In 2021 international conference on communication, control and information sciences (ICCISc), Vol. 1, pp. 1–8 (IEEE, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanketh, R. S., Bala, M. M., Reddy, P. V. N. &amp; Kumar, G. P. Melanoma disease detection using convolutional neural networks. In 2020 4th international conference on intelligent computing and control systems (ICICCS), pp. 1031–1037 (IEEE, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahi, M. M. I. et al. Detection of skin cancer using deep neural networks. In 2019 IEEE Asia-pacific conference on computer science and data engineering (CSDE), pp. 1–7 (IEEE,  2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulati, S. &amp; Bhogal, R. K. Detection of malignant melanoma using deep learning. In International conference on advances in computing and data sciences, pp. 312–325 (Springer Singapore, Singapore, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Razmjooy, N., Sheykhahmad, F. R. &amp; Ghadimi, N. A hybrid neural network–world cup optimization algorithm for melanoma detection. Open Med.13 (1), 9–16 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29577090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadhav, A. R., Ghontale, A. G. &amp; Shrivastava, V. K. Segmentation and border detection of melanoma lesions using convolutional neural network and SVM. In Computational Intelligence: Theories, Applications and Future directions-volume I: ICCI-2017, pp. 97–108 (Springer, Singapore, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman, A. et al. Microscopic melanoma detection and classification: a framework of pixel-based fusion and multilevel features reduction. Microsc. Res. Tech.83 (4), 410–423 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31898863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jojoa Acosta, M. F., Tovar, C., Garcia-Zapirain, L. Y., Percybrooks, W. S. &amp; M. B., &amp; Melanoma diagnosis using deep learning techniques on dermatoscopic images. BMC Med. Imaging. 21 (1), 1–11 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7789790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33407213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mustafa, S. &amp; Kimura, A. A SVM-based diagnosis of melanoma using only useful image features. In 2018 international workshop on advanced image technology (IWAIT), pp. 1–4 (IEEE, 2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>İlkin, S. et al. hybSVM: bacterial colony optimization algorithm based SVM for malignant melanoma detection. Eng. Sci. Technol. Int. J.24 (5), 1059–1071 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora, G., Dubey, A. K., Jaffery, Z. A. &amp; Rocha, A. Bag of feature and support vector machine based early diagnosis of skin cancer. Neural Comput. Appl. 1–8 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bi, D., Zhu, D., Sheykhahmad, F. R. &amp; Qiao, M. Computer-aided skin cancer diagnosis based on a new meta-heuristic algorithm combined with support vector method. Biomed. Signal Process. Control. 68, 102631 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawaz, M. et al. Skin cancer detection from dermoscopic images using deep learning and fuzzy k-means clustering. Microsc. Res. Tech.85 (1), 339–351 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34448519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabrizchi, H., Parvizpour, S. &amp; Razmara, J. An improved VGG model for skin cancer detection. Neural Process. Lett.55 (4), 3715–3732 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutman, D. et al. Skin lesion analysis toward melanoma detection: A challenge at the international symposium on biomedical imaging (ISBI) 2016, hosted by the international skin imaging collaboration (ISIC). arXiv preprint arXiv:1605.01397. (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codella, N. C. et al. Skin lesion analysis toward melanoma detection: A challenge at the 2017 international symposium on biomedical imaging (ISBI), hosted by the international skin imaging collaboration (ISIC). In 2018 IEEE 15th international symposium on biomedical imaging (ISBI 2018), pp. 168–172 (IEEE, 2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, Z., Chen, Y., Gavves, E., Mettes, P. &amp; Snoek, C. G. Unsharp mask guided filtering. IEEE Trans. Image Process.30, 7472–7485 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34449363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luque-Chang, A., Cuevas, E., Fausto, F., Zaldivar, D. &amp; Pérez, M. Social spider optimization algorithm: modifications, applications, and perspectives. Math. Probl. Eng.2018, 1–29 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uriarte-Arcia, A. V., López-Yáñez, I., Yáñez-Márquez, C., Gama, J. &amp; Camacho-Nieto, O. Data stream classification based on the gamma classifier. Math. Probl. Eng. (2015).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>