<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39368540</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-6351</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>193</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food and chemical toxicology : an international journal published for the British Industrial Biological Research Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem Toxicol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dietary exposure to metals/metalloids and persistent organic pollutants in Spanish preschool and primary school children.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>115030</StartPage><MedlinePgn>115030</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.fct.2024.115030</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0278-6915(24)00596-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Diet is a primary source of pollutant exposure. Given children's vulnerability to their effects, this study assessed dietary intake of metals/metalloids and different persistent organic pollutants in children in Tarragona (Spain), compared it with the health-based guideline values (HBGV), and identified the main dietary sources. The analysis included 533 preschoolers and 443 primary school children from the EPINED and ECLIPSES studies. Dietary intake of cadmium (Cd), methylmercury (MeHg), lead (Pb), inorganic arsenic (inAs), polychlorinated dibenzo-p-dioxins and dibenzofurans (PCDD/Fs), dioxin-like polychlorinated biphenyls (DL-PCBs), and non-dioxin-like polychlorinated biphenyls (NDL-PCBs) was estimated using validated food frequency questionnaires and a database from the Catalan Agency for Food Safety. Preschoolers and primary school children exceeded the relevant reference value for InAs and DL-PCBs. Only preschoolers exceeded the limit for MeHg and PCDD/Fs. Cd, Pb, and NDL-PCBs intakes did not exceed the limits in either age group. Salted cereals/potatoes were the main source of InAs; fish for MeHg and DL-PCBs; and milk/yogurt for PCDD/Fs, followed by white fish in preschoolers and fatty fish in primary school children. The findings highlight that dietary exposure to some pollutants poses a significant risk to these children, emphasizing the need for public health policies to reduce pollutants in their diets.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Becerra-Tomás</LastName><ForeName>Nerea</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Ciències Mèdiques Bàsiques, Nutrition and Mental Health (NUTRISAM) Research Group, Unitat de Salut Pública i Epidemiologia Nutricional, Reus, Spain; Institut D'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), 43005, Tarragona, Spain. Electronic address: nerea.becerra@urv.cat.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arija</LastName><ForeName>Victoria</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Ciències Mèdiques Bàsiques, Nutrition and Mental Health (NUTRISAM) Research Group, Unitat de Salut Pública i Epidemiologia Nutricional, Reus, Spain; Institut D'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), 43005, Tarragona, Spain; Institut Català de La Salut (ICS), Collaborative Group on Lifestyles, Nutrition, and Tobacco (CENIT), Institut D'Investigació en Atenció Primària IDIAP Jordi Gol, Reus, Spain; Institut D'Investigació en Atenció Primària IDIAP Jordi Gol, Institut Català de La Salut (ICS), Barcelona, Spain; University Research Institute on Sustainablility, Climate Change and Energy Transition (IU-RESCAT), Universitat Rovira i Virgili, 43003, Tarragona, Spain. Electronic address: victoria.arija@urv.cat.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jardí</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Ciències Mèdiques Bàsiques, Nutrition and Mental Health (NUTRISAM) Research Group, Unitat de Salut Pública i Epidemiologia Nutricional, Reus, Spain; Institut D'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), 43005, Tarragona, Spain. Electronic address: cristina.jardi@urv.cat.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Riggioni-Saborío</LastName><ForeName>Lucía</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Ciències Mèdiques Bàsiques, Nutrition and Mental Health (NUTRISAM) Research Group, Unitat de Salut Pública i Epidemiologia Nutricional, Reus, Spain. Electronic address: lurisa1495@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bedmar</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Ciències Mèdiques Bàsiques, Nutrition and Mental Health (NUTRISAM) Research Group, Unitat de Salut Pública i Epidemiologia Nutricional, Reus, Spain; Institut D'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), 43005, Tarragona, Spain. Electronic address: cristina.bedmar@urv.cat.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Canals-Sans</LastName><ForeName>Josefa</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut D'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), 43005, Tarragona, Spain; University Research Institute on Sustainablility, Climate Change and Energy Transition (IU-RESCAT), Universitat Rovira i Virgili, 43003, Tarragona, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Department of Psychology, Nutrition and Mental Health (NUTRISAM) Research Group, Research Center for Behavioral Assessment (CRAMC), Tarragona, Spain. Electronic address: josefa.canals@urv.cat.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem Toxicol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8207483</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0278-6915</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metalloids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metals</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Persistent organic pollutants</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39368540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2024.115030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0278-6915(24)00596-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>