<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39367998</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1179-2019</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Paediatric drugs</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Paediatr Drugs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adverse Event Profile of First-line Drugs for Treating Patent Ductus Arteriosus in Neonates: A Disproportionality Analysis Study of USFDA Adverse Event Reporting System.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40272-024-00657-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Acetaminophen, ibuprofen, and indomethacin are widely used as first-line drugs for patent ductus arteriosus (PDA) closure in preterm neonates. However, their relative safety profiles remain unclear.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Adverse event reports related to the first-line drugs used in PDA and neonates in general were retrieved from the US Food and Drug Authority (FDA) Adverse Event Reporting System. Deduplicated reports were analyzed using proportional reporting ratios and reporting odds ratios to identify disproportionality safety signals between drugs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 969 unique reports related to the first-line drugs used in PDA and 499 reports in the neonatal period were included. Acetaminophen signals primarily involved the liver, while ibuprofen and indomethacin signals pertained to gastrointestinal, renal, vascular, and mortality outcomes. Higher occurrences of death were reported with indomethacin and ibuprofen compared with acetaminophen.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This first comparison of PDA drug safety profiles from spontaneous reports highlights some differences, with acetaminophen potentially conferring a safer adverse effect profile overall. While limitations include missing data and reporting biases, the signals warrant further validation. Given its comparable efficacy to ibuprofen, as demonstrated in other studies, acetaminophen has the potential to be preferred as an initial medical therapy for PDA.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature Switzerland AG.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sridharan</LastName><ForeName>Kannan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3811-6503</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Arabian Gulf University, Manama, Kingdom of Bahrain. skannandr@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sivaramakrishnan</LastName><ForeName>Gowri</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dental Post Graduate Training Department, PHCC, Manama, Kingdom of Bahrain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Paediatr Drugs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100883685</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1174-5878</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39367998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40272-024-00657-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s40272-024-00657-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Sellmer A, Bjerre JV, Schmidt MR, McNamara PJ, Hjortdal VE, Høst B, Bech BH, Henriksen TB. Morbidity and mortality in preterm neonates with patent ductus arteriosus on day 3. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2013;98(6):F505–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2013-303816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Backes CH, Hill KD, Shelton EL, Slaughter JL, Lewis TR, Weisz DE, Mah ML, Bhombal S, Smith CV, McNamara PJ, Benitz WE, Garg V. Patent ductus arteriosus: a contemporary perspective for the pediatric and adult cardiac care provider. J Am Heart Assoc. 2022;11(17): e025784.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/JAHA.122.025784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9496432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park J, Yoon SJ, Han J, Song IG, Lim J, Shin JE, Eun HS, Park KI, Park MS, Lee SM. Patent ductus arteriosus treatment trends and associated morbidities in neonates. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1):10689.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-89868-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8139968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eursiriwan S, Okascharoen C, Vallibhakara SA, Pattanaprateep O, Numthavaj P, Attia J, Thakkinstian A. Comparison of various pharmacologic agents in the management of hemodynamically significant patent ductus arteriosus in preterm: a network meta-analysis and risk-benefit analysis. Biomed Hub. 2022;7(3):125–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000526318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9710462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marconi E, Bettiol A, Ambrosio G, Perduca V, Vannacci A, Troiani S, Dani C, Mugelli A, Lucenteforte E. Efficacy and safety of pharmacological treatments for patent ductus arteriosus closure: a systematic review and network meta-analysis of clinical trials and observational studies. Pharmacol Res. 2019;148: 104418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2019.104418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavertu A, Vora B, Giacomini KM, Altman R, Rensi S. A new era in pharmacovigilance: toward real-world data and digital monitoring. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2021;109(5):1197–202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cpt.2172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8058244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell JE, Gossell-Williams M, Lee MG. A review of pharmacovigilance. West Indian Med J. 2014;63(7):771–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palleria C, Leporini C, Chimirri S, Marrazzo G, Sacchetta S, Bruno L, Lista RM, Staltari O, Scuteri A, Scicchitano F, Russo E. Limitations and obstacles of the spontaneous adverse drugs reactions reporting: two “challenging” case reports. J Pharmacol Pharmacother. 2013;4(Suppl 1):S66-72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0976-500X.120955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3853673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potential Signals of Serious Risks/New Safety Information Identified from the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS). Available at: https://www.fda.gov/drugs/questions-and-answers-fdas-adverse-event-reporting-system-faers/potential-signals-serious-risksnew-safety-information-identified-fda-adverse-event-reporting-system (Accessed on 18th June 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leitzen S, Dubrall D, Toni I, Stingl J, Schulz M, Schmid M, Neubert A, Sachs B. Analysis of the reporting of adverse drug reactions in children and adolescents in Germany in the time period from 2000 to 2019. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(3): e0247446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0247446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7928460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sridharan K, Madhoob AA, Jufairi MA, Ansari EA, Marzooq RA, Hubail Z, Hasan SJ. Gentamicin in neonates with hemodynamically significant patent ductus arteriosus. J Pharm Bioallied Sci. 2023;15(2):95–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jpbs.jpbs_420_22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10353665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sivanandan S, Agarwal R. Pharmacological closure of patent ductus arteriosus: selecting the agent and route of administration. Paediatr Drugs. 2016;18(2):123–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40272-016-0165-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) Public Dashboard. Available at: https://www.fda.gov/drugs/questions-and-answers-fdas-adverse-event-reporting-system-faers/fda-adverse-event-reporting-system-faers-public-dashboard (Accessed on 14th June 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faillie JL. Case-non-case studies: principle, methods, bias and interpretation. Therapie. 2019;74(2):225–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.therap.2019.01.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park G, Jung H, Heo SJ, Jung I. Comparison of data mining methods for the signal detection of adverse drug events with a hierarchical structure in postmarketing surveillance. Life (Basel). 2020;10(8):138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7460123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans SJ, Waller PC, Davis S. Use of proportional reporting ratios (PRRs) for signal generation from spontaneous adverse drug reaction reports. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2001;10(6):483–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pds.677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Practical aspects of signal detection in pharmacovigilance. Report of CIOMS working group VIII. Geneva. Available at: https://cioms.ch/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/WG8-Signal-Detection.pdf (Accessed on August 19, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinson JA, Roberts DW, James LP. Mechanisms of acetaminophen-induced liver necrosis. Handb Exp Pharmacol. 2010;196:369–405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-00663-0_12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beath SV. Hepatic function and physiology in the newborn. Semin Neonatol. 2003;8(5):337–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1084-2756(03)00066-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flint RB, Roofthooft DW, van Rongen A, van Lingen RA, van den Anker JN, van Dijk M, Allegaert K, Tibboel D, Knibbe CAJ, Simons SHP. Exposure to acetaminophen and all its metabolites upon 10, 15, and 20 mg/kg intravenous acetaminophen in very-preterm infants. Pediatr Res. 2017;82(4):678–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/pr.2017.129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terrin G, Di Chiara M, Boscarino G, Metrangolo V, Faccioli F, Onestà E, Giancotti A, Di Donato V, Cardilli V, De Curtis M. Morbidity associated with patent ductus arteriosus in preterm newborns: a retrospective case-control study. Ital J Pediatr. 2021;47(1):9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13052-021-00956-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7809822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acetaminophen. Summary of product characteristics. Available at: https://www.medicines.org.uk/emc/product/5164/smpc/print (accessed on 11th August 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibuprofen. Summary of product characteristics. Available at: https://www.medicines.org.uk/emc/product/3876/smpc/print (accessed on 11th August 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Indomethacin. Summary of product characteristics. Available at: https://www.medicines.org.uk/emc/product/2946/smpc/print (accessed on August 11, 2024).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>