<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39363222</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Haematococcus pluvialis meets gellan gum: Rheological and thermal exploration of a new resource food and biomedical gel matrix.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17433</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The increasing interest in hydrogel matrices and their diverse applications has fueled extensive research. However, single-component gels have a limited adjustable performance range, and multi-component gels raise concerns about biological safety, hindering their widespread use. This study focuses on harnessing high-speed shearing and ultrasound-assisted methods to incorporate active natural Haematococcus pluvialis (HP), creating novel composite hydrogels in conjunction with biological macromolecule gellan gum, and eliminating the need for structural modifications or chemical crosslinking. Rich astaxanthin, proteins, polysaccharides, and other components in HP can fill and promote the formation of a unified functional network. The study aims to explore the potential of HP as a rheology regulator and investigate its impact on the rheological properties of the gels. Various rheological models, including Power-Law, Herschel-Bulkley, and Arrhenius, were employed for comparative analysis. This pioneering report on gellan/HP hydrogels holds significant importance as they exhibit optimized elasticity, thermal stability, enhanced injectability, and self-recovery, making them suitable for a wide range of applications in specialized medical food and biomedicine.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Guangming</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of BioPharmaceutical Research, Liaocheng University, Quality Department, Liaocheng, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Ping</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Liaocheng High-Tech Biotechnology Co., Ltd, Liaocheng, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Zhengping</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of BioPharmaceutical Research, Liaocheng University, Quality Department, Liaocheng, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Han</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of BioPharmaceutical Research, Liaocheng University, Quality Department, Liaocheng, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fan</LastName><ForeName>Zhiping</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1935-5461</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of BioPharmaceutical Research, Liaocheng University, Quality Department, Liaocheng, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Taishan Scholar Foundation of Shandong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Liaocheng University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Shandong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Haematococcus pluvialis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hydrogel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microalgae</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rheology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ultrasound</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39363222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adedeji, O. E., Choi, J.‐Y., Park, G. E., Kang, H. J., Aminu, M. O., Min, J. H., Chinma, C. E., Moon, K.‐D., &amp; Jung, Y. H. (2022). Formulation and characterization of an interpenetrating network hydrogel of locust bean gum and cellulose microfibrils for 3D printing. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 80, 103086. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2022.103086</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakar, B., Pekdemir, S. S., Birhanlı, E., Ulu, A., Pekdemir, M. E., &amp; Ateş, B. (2024). Unveiling the effect of molecular weight of vanillic acid grafted chitosan hydrogel films on physical, antioxidant, and antimicrobial properties for application in food packaging. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 256, 128397. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.128397</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basak, S., &amp; Singhal, R. S. (2024). Composite hydrogels fabricated from konjac glucomannan and gellan gum: Rheological characterization and their potential application in sustainable agriculture. Carbohydrate Polymers, 336, 122091. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2024.122091</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Başyiğit, B., Altun, G., Yücetepe, M., Karaaslan, A., &amp; Karaaslan, M. (2023). Locust bean gum provides excellent mechanical and release attributes to soy protein‐based natural hydrogels. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 231, 123352. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.123352</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cebrián‐Lloret, V., Martínez‐Abad, A., López‐Rubio, A., &amp; Martínez‐Sanz, M. (2024). Exploring alternative red seaweed species for the production of agar‐based hydrogels for food applications. Food Hydrocolloids, 146, 109177. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2023.109177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary, S. (2023). Seaweed polysaccharide coatings/films for meat based foods. Food and Humanity, 1, 777–792. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foohum.2023.07.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cofelice, M., Messia, M. C., Marconi, E., Cuomo, F., &amp; Lopez, F. (2023). Effect of the xanthan gum on the rheological properties of alginate hydrogels. Food Hydrocolloids, 142, 108768. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2023.108768</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corker, A., Ng, H. C. H., Poole, R. J., &amp; García‐Tuñón, E. (2019). 3D printing with 2D colloids: Designing rheology protocols to predict ‘printability’ of soft‐materials. Soft Matter, 15(6), 1444–1456. https://doi.org/10.1039/C8SM01936C</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng, Z., Zhu, J., Chen, Y., Zhong, N., Huang, C., &amp; Hu, Y. (2024). Controlled release of dual food functional ingredients from octenyl succinic anhydride/β‐cyclodextrin nanoparticles integrated carrageenan/polyvinyl alcohol hydrogels. Journal of Molecular Liquids, 393, 123646. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molliq.2023.123646</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Droop, M. R. (1955). Carotenogenesis in Haematococcus pluvialis. Nature, 175(4444), 42–42. https://doi.org/10.1038/175042a0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, Z., Cheng, P., Gao, Y., Wang, D., Jia, G., Zhang, P., Prakash, S., Wang, Z., &amp; Han, J. (2022). Understanding the rheological properties of a novel composite salecan/gellan hydrogels. Food Hydrocolloids, 123, 107162. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2021.107162</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, Z., Cheng, P., Zhang, P., Gao, Y., Zhao, Y., Liu, M., Gu, J., Wang, Z., &amp; Han, J. (2022). A novel multifunctional Salecan/κ‐carrageenan composite hydrogel with anti‐freezing properties: Advanced rheology, thermal analysis and model fitting. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 208, 1–10. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2022.03.054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gago‐Guillán, M., García‐Otero, X., Anguiano‐Igea, S., &amp; Otero‐Espinar, F. J. (2023). Compression pressure‐induced synergy in xanthan and locust bean gum hydrogels. Effect in drug delivery. Journal of Drug Delivery Science and Technology, 89, 105025. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jddst.2023.105025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharibzahedi, S. M. T., Ahmadigol, A., Khubber, S., &amp; Altintas, Z. (2022). Whey protein isolate/jujube polysaccharide‐based edible nanocomposite films reinforced with starch nanocrystals for the shelf‐life extension of banana: Optimization and characterization. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 222, 1063–1077. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2022.09.232</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomes, D., Batista‐Silva, J. P., Sousa, A., &amp; Passarinha, L. A. (2023). Progress and opportunities in Gellan gum‐based materials: A review of preparation, characterization and emerging applications. Carbohydrate Polymers, 311, 120782. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2023.120782</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goudoulas, T. B., &amp; Germann, N. (2017). Phase transition kinetics and rheology of gelatin‐alginate mixtures. Food Hydrocolloids, 66, 49–60. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2016.12.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Günter, E. A., Melekhin, A. K., Belozerov, V. S., Martinson, E. A., &amp; Litvinets, S. G. (2024). Preparation, physicochemical characterization and swelling properties of composite hydrogel microparticles based on gelatin and pectins with different structure. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 258, 128935. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.128935</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Z., Liu, Y., An, H., Kovacs, Z., Abddollahi, M., Sun, Z., Zhang, G., &amp; Li, C. (2024). Utilizing Haematococcus pluvialis to simulate animal meat color in high‐moisture meat analogues: Texture quality and color stability. Food Research International, 175, 113685. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2023.113685</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim, T. N. B. T., Feisal, N. A. S., Kamaludin, N. H., Cheah, W. Y., How, V., Bhatnagar, A., Ma, Z., &amp; Show, P. L. (2023). Biological active metabolites from microalgae for healthcare and pharmaceutical industries: A comprehensive review. Bioresource Technology, 372, 128661. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2023.128661</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal, Y., Amin, F., &amp; Gilani, N. u. H. (2023). Freeze‐gelated sodium alginate incorporated GO hydrogel membrane fabrication, thermal and mechanical studies. Materials Letters, 351, 135060. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matlet.2023.135060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, Q., Wang, Y., Du, L., Li, S., Liu, Y., &amp; Meng, Z. (2022). Catastrophic phase inversion of bigels characterized by fluorescence intensity‐based 3D modeling and the formability for decorating and 3D printing. Food Hydrocolloids, 126, 107461. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2021.107461</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoch, A., &amp; Roy Choudhury, A. (2020). Understanding the rheology of novel guar‐gellan gum composite hydrogels. Materials Letters, 263, 127234. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matlet.2019.127234</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoobbakht, F., Khorshidi, S., Bahmanyar, F., Hosseini, S. M., Aminikhah, N., Farhoodi, M., &amp; Mirmoghtadaie, L. (2024). Modification of mechanical, rheological and structural properties of agar hydrogel using xanthan and locust bean gum. Food Hydrocolloids, 147, 109411. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2023.109411</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Zhu, M., Gu, L., Su, Y., Yang, Y., Chang, C., &amp; Han, Q. (2023). Freeze‐thaw stability of konjac glucomannan hydrogels supplemented with natural tapioca/corn starch. Lwt, 182, 114841. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114841</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, M., Hou, X., Lin, L., Jiang, F., Qiao, D., &amp; Xie, F. (2023). Legume protein/polysaccharide food hydrogels: Preparation methods, improvement strategies and applications. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 243, 125217. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.125217</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Dou, X., Pang, J., Liang, M., Feng, C., Kong, M., Liu, Y., Cheng, X., Wang, Y., &amp; Chen, X. (2019). Improvement of fucoxanthin oral efficacy via vehicles based on gum Arabic, gelatin and alginate hydrogel: Delivery system for oral efficacy enhancement of functional food ingredients. Journal of Functional Foods, 63, 103573. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2019.103573</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Wang, R., Wang, D., Sun, Z., Liu, F., Zhang, D., &amp; Wang, D. (2022). Development of a food packaging antibacterial hydrogel based on gelatin, chitosan, and 3‐phenyllactic acid for the shelf‐life extension of chilled chicken. Food Hydrocolloids, 127, 107546. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2022.107546</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair, R., &amp; Roy Choudhury, A. (2020). Synthesis and rheological characterization of a novel shear thinning levan gellan hydrogel. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 159, 922–930. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.05.119</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishshanka, G. K. S. H., Liyanaarachchi, V. C., Nimarshana, P. H. V., Ariyadasa, T. U., &amp; Chang, J.‐S. (2022). Haematococcus pluvialis: A potential feedstock for multiple‐product biorefining. Journal of Cleaner Production, 344, 131103. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.131103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pogorzelska, E., Godziszewska, J., Brodowska, M., &amp; Wierzbicka, A. (2018). Antioxidant potential of Haematococcus pluvialis extract rich in astaxanthin on colour and oxidative stability of raw ground pork meat during refrigerated storage. Meat Science, 135, 54–61. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2017.09.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richa, &amp; Roy Choudhury, A. (2020). pH mediated rheological modulation of chitosan hydrogels. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 156, 591–597. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.04.049</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sägesser, C., Kallfelz, J. M., Boulos, S., Hammer, L., Böcker, L., Portmann, R., Nyström, L., &amp; Mathys, A. (2023). A novel approach for the protein determination in food‐relevant microalgae. Bioresource Technology, 390, 129849. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2023.129849</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, J., Rong, L., Li, J., Shen, M., Yu, Q., Chen, Y., Kong, J., &amp; Xie, J. (2024). Effects of three different polysaccharides on the sol gel‐behavior, rheological, and structural properties of tapioca starch. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 254, 128053. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.128053</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sultan, M., Mohamed, O. A., El‐Masry, H. M., &amp; Taha, G. (2023). Fabrication and evaluation of antimicrobial cellulose/Arabic gum hydrogels as potential drug delivery vehicle. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 242, 125083. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.125083</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teng, H., He, Y., Fu, L., Xiong, H., Lu, M., Zhang, C., Ai, C., Cao, H., Zhong, S., &amp; Chen, L. (2023). Effects of blackberry (Rubus spp.) polysaccharide on the structure and thermal behavior of the myofibrillar protein of chicken breast meat. Food Chemistry: X, 20, 100914. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fochx.2023.100914</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vancoillie, F., Verkempinck, S. H. E., Sluys, L., De Mazière, S., Delbaere, S. M., Van Poucke, C., Hendrickx, M. E., Van Loey, A. M., &amp; Grauwet, T. (2024). Impact of refrigerated storage on (bio)chemical conversions of health‐related compounds in pretreated, pasteurized Brussels sprouts and leek. Food Research International, 175, 113764. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2023.113764</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidhyavathi, R., Venkatachalam, L., Kamath, B. S., Sarada, R., &amp; Ravishankar, G. A. (2007). Differential expression of carotenogenic genes and associated changes in pigment profile during regeneration of Haematococcus pluvialis cysts. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 75(4), 879–887. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253‐007‐0876‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Dong, Y., Wang, L., Cui, M., Zhang, Y., Jiang, L., &amp; Sui, X. (2023). Elucidating the effect of the Hofmeister effect on formation and rheological properties of soy protein/κ‐carrageenan hydrogels. Food Hydrocolloids, 143, 108905. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2023.108905</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X., Dai, M., Peng, Y., Huang, M., Han, X., Cao, J., Qiao, J., Song, Z., &amp; Shi, J. (2023). Development of a novel 1‐octen‐3‐ol‐loaded agar/curdlan hydrogel for inhibiting peach fruit diseases. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 251, 126411. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.126411</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waresindo, W. X., Priyanto, A., Sihombing, Y. A., Hapidin, D. A., Edikresnha, D., Aimon, A. H., Suciati, T., &amp; Khairurrijal, K. (2023). Konjac glucomannan‐based hydrogels with health‐promoting effects for potential edible electronics applications: A mini‐review. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 248, 125888. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.125888</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, S., Xue, Y., Xue, C., Jiang, X., &amp; Li, J. (2022). Structural and rheological properties of meat analogues from Haematococcus pluvialis residue‐pea protein by high moisture extrusion. Lwt, 154, 112756. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112756</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanes, M., Durán, L., &amp; Costell, E. (2002). Effect of hydrocolloid type and concentration on flow behaviour and sensory properties of milk beverages model systems. Food Hydrocolloids, 16(6), 605–611. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0268‐005X(02)00023‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, H., Kim, H., &amp; Chang, P.‐S. (2024). Fabrication and characterization of chitosan‐pectin emulsion‐filled hydrogel prepared by cold‐set gelation to improve bioaccessibility of lipophilic bioactive compounds. Food Chemistry, 437, 137927. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.137927</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, T., Wu, D., Liang, B., Wang, J., Shang, X., &amp; Wu, Q. (2023). Preparation, characterization of Auricularia auricula polysaccharide‐based films and application in meat preservation. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 244, 125242. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.125242</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, X., Wang, Y., Zhao, W., Li, S., Pan, J., Prakash, S., &amp; Dong, X. (2023). Hydrophilic colloids (konjac gum/xanthan gum) in 3D printing of transitional food from fish paste. Food Hydrocolloids, 137, 108333. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2022.108333</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhan, J., Liao, X., Fan, X., Zhang, J., Li, H., Cai, Y., &amp; Qiu, X. (2022). An injectable and conductive TEMPOL/polypyrrole integrated peptide co‐assembly hydrogel promotes functional maturation of cardiomyocytes for myocardial infarction repair. Composites Part B: Engineering, 236, 109794. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compositesb.2022.109794</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, C., Wang, C.‐S., Girard, M., Therriault, D., &amp; Heuzey, M.‐C. (2024). 3D printed protein/polysaccharide food simulant for dysphagia diet: Impact of cellulose nanocrystals. Food Hydrocolloids, 148, 109455. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2023.109455</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, B., Du, J., Zhang, Y., Gu, Z., Li, Z., Cheng, L., Li, C., &amp; Hong, Y. (2022). Polysaccharide‐coated porous starch‐based oral carrier for paclitaxel: Adsorption and sustained release in colon. Carbohydrate Polymers, 291, 119571. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2022.119571</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>