<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39363349</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2180</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of Salmonella biofilm attachment and hydrophobicity characteristics on food contact surfaces.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>387</StartPage><MedlinePgn>387</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">387</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12866-024-03556-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Salmonella forms biofilms, and persist on food contact surfaces. Once a biofilm is formed cleaning and sanitation protocols may be inadequate for effective removal. This study evaluated attachment characteristics, surface properties, and structure of Salmonella biofilms on food contact surfaces commonly used in the tree-fruit industry. Multi-strain Salmonella biofilms were grown in a Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) biofilm reactor at 22 ± 2 °C and sampling was conducted at 2, 24 and 96-h. After each incubation period, coupons weregently rinsed and the remaining cells enumerated. Biofilms were analyzed with Laser Scanning Confocal Microscopy (LSCM). Hydrophobicity was evaluated by measuring the contact angles of reference liquids method using a drop tensiometer instrument. Material type and biofilm age significantly influenced attachment and biofilm hydrophobicity (P &lt; 0.05). The strength of attachment, across all time points, was highest on nylon followed by wood and high-density polyethylene. The highest contact angle measurements were observed after 96-h of biofilm formation for each material. All the results and observations from this study contribute to a better understanding of the attachment and hydrophobicity characteristics of Salmonella and might help producers make informed decisions when selecting containers for harvesting and storing in order to minimize biofilm formation and potential for cross-contamination.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ivers</LastName><ForeName>Colton</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Nutrition Dietetics and Health Department, Kansas State University, 1310 Research Drive Park, Manhattan, KS, 66502, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaya</LastName><ForeName>Eda C</ForeName><Initials>EC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Nutrition Dietetics and Health Department, Kansas State University, 1310 Research Drive Park, Manhattan, KS, 66502, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yucel</LastName><ForeName>Umut</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Nutrition Dietetics and Health Department, Kansas State University, 1310 Research Drive Park, Manhattan, KS, 66502, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boyle</LastName><ForeName>Dan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Biology, Kansas State University, 6 Ackert Hall, Manhattan, KS, 66506, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Trinetta</LastName><ForeName>Valentina</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Nutrition Dietetics and Health Department, Kansas State University, 1310 Research Drive Park, Manhattan, KS, 66502, United States. vtrinetta@ksu.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100966981</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2180</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018441" MajorTopicYN="Y">Biofilms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057927" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hydrophobic and Hydrophilic Interactions</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012475" MajorTopicYN="Y">Salmonella</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001422" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bacterial Adhesion</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013499" MajorTopicYN="N">Surface Properties</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018613" MajorTopicYN="N">Microscopy, Confocal</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Attachment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biofilm</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hydrophobicity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39363349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11447956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12866-024-03556-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12866-024-03556-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann, Sandra, and Jae-Wan Ahn. Updating Economic Burden of Foodborne Diseases Estimates for Inflation and Income Growth, ERR-297, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Economic Research Service. 2021. https://www.ers.usda.gov/webdocs/publications/102640/err-297.pdf?v=632.7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interagency Food Safety Analytics Collaboration (IFSAC). Foodborne illness source attribution estimates for 2020 for Salmonella, Escherichia coli O157, and Listeria monocytogenes using multi-year outbreak surveillance data, United States. GA and D.C.: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Food and Drug Administration, U.S. Department of Agriculture’s Food Safety and Inspection Service. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joseph B, Otta SK, Karunasagar I, Karunasagar I. Biofilm formation by Salmonella spp. On food contact surfaces and their sensitivity to sanitizers. Int J Food Microbiol. 2001;64(3):367–72. 10.1016/S0168-1605(00)00466-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11294359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donlan RM. Biofilms: microbial life on surfaces. Emerg Infect Dis. 2002;8(9):881–90. 10.3201/eid0809.020063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2732559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12194761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flemming H-C, Wingender J, Szewzyk U, Steinberg P, Rice SA, Kjelleberg S. Biofilms: an emergent form of bacterial life. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2016;14(9):Article 9. 10.1038/nrmicro.2016.94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27510863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vestby LK, Møretrø T, Langsrud S, Heir E, Nesse LL. Biofilm forming abilities of Salmonella are correlated with persistence in fish meal- and feed factories. BMC Vet Res. 2009;5(1):20. 10.1186/1746-6148-5-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2693496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19473515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berne C, Ellison CK, Ducret A, Brun YV. Bacterial adhesion at the single-cell level. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2018;16(10):Article 10. 10.1038/s41579-018-0057-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30008468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casarin LS, de Oliveira Casarin F, Brandelli A, Novello J, Ferreira SO, Tondo EC. Influence of free energy on the attachment of Salmonella Enteritidis and Listeria monocytogenes on stainless steels AISI 304 and AISI 316. LWT - Food Sci Technolo. 2016;69:131–8. 10.1016/j.lwt.2016.01.035.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chia TWR, Goulter RM, McMeekin T, Dykes GA, Fegan N. Attachment of different Salmonella serovars to materials commonly used in a poultry processing plant. Food Microbiol. 2009;26(8):853–9. 10.1016/j.fm.2009.05.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19835771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obe T, Richards AK, Shariat NW. Differences in biofilm formation of Salmonella serovars on two surfaces under two temperature conditions. J Appl Microbiol. 2022;132(3):2410–20. 10.1111/jam.15381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34821433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy PK, Ha AJ-W, Mizan MdFR, Hossain MdI, Ashrafudoulla Md, Toushik SH, Nahar S, Kim YK, Ha S-D. Effects of environmental conditions (temperature, pH, and glucose) on biofilm formation of Salmonella enterica serotype Kentucky and virulence gene expression. Poult Sci. 2021;100(7):101209. 10.1016/j.psj.2021.101209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8182266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34089933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Speranza B, Corbo MR, Sinigaglia M. Effects of Nutritional and Environmental Conditions on Salmonella spp. Biofilm Formation. J Food Sci. 2011;76(1):M12–6. 10.1111/j.1750-3841.2010.01936.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21535687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duffy EA, Lucia LM, Kells JM, Castillo A, Pillai SD, Acuff GR. Concentrations of Escherichia coli and Genetic Diversity and Antibiotic Resistance Profiling of Salmonella Isolated from Irrigation Water, Packing Shed Equipment, and Fresh Produce in Texas. J Food Prot. 2005;68(1):70–9. 10.4315/0362-028X-68.1.70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15690806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman KL, Bartz FE, Johnston L, Moe CL, Jaykus L-A, Leon JS. Microbial Load of Fresh Produce and Paired Equipment Surfaces in Packing Facilities Near the U.S. and Mexico Border. J Food Prot. 2017;80(4):582–9. 10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-16-365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28271928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amrutha B, Sundar K, Shetty PH. Study on E. coli and Salmonella biofilms from fresh fruits and vegetables. J Food Sci Technol. 2017;54(5):1091–7. 10.1007/s13197-017-2555-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5380633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28416858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R, King DA, Kalchayanand N. Evaluation of Salmonella biofilm cell transfer from common food contact surfaces to beef products. J Food Prot. 2022;85(4):632–8. 10.4315/JFP-21-334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34935943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendez E, Walker DK, Vipham J, Trinetta V. The use of a CDC biofilm reactor to grow multi-strain Listeria monocytogenes biofilm. Food Microbiol. 2020;92:103592. 10.1016/j.fm.2020.103592.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32950174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manville E, Kaya EC, Yucel U, Boyle D, Trinetta V. Evaluation of Listeria monocytogenes biofilms attachment and formation on different surfaces using a CDC biofilm reactor. Int J Food Microbiol. 2023;399:110251. 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37244228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ASTM. E2871–19 Test Method for Evaluating Disinfectant Efficacy Against Pseudomonas aeruginosa Biofilm Grown in CDC Biofilm Reactor Using Single Tube Method. ASTM International. 2019. 10.1520/E2871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan Norhana MN, Goulter RM, Poole SE, Deeth HC, Dykes GA. Relationship between the Physicochemical Properties of Nonchitinolytic Listeria and Salmonella and Their Attachment to Shrimp Carapace. J Food Prot. 2009;72(6):1181–9. 10.4315/0362-028X-72.6.1181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19610328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinde E, Carballo J. Attachment of Salmonellaspp. and Listeria monocytogenes to stainless steel, rubber and polytetrafluorethylene: The influence of free energy and the effect of commercial sanitizers. Food Microbiol. 2002;17(4):439–47. 10.1006/fmic.2000.0339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Sodagari M, Chen Y, He X, Newby BZ, Ju L-K. Initial bacterial attachment in slow flowing systems: Effects of cell and substrate surface properties. Colloids Surf, B. 2011;87(2):415–22. 10.1016/j.colsurfb.2011.05.053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21715146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel J, Singh M, Macarisin D, Sharma M, Shelton D. Differences in biofilm formation of produce and poultry Salmonella enterica isolates and their persistence on spinach plants. Food Microbiol. 2013;36(2):388–94. 10.1016/j.fm.2013.06.019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24010621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schlisselberg DB, Yaron S. The effects of stainless steel finish on Salmonella Typhimurium attachment, biofilm formation and sensitivity to chlorine. Food Microbiol. 2013;35(1):65–72. 10.1016/j.fm.2013.02.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23628616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verplanck N, Coffinier Y, Thomy V, Boukherroub R. Wettability Switching Techniques on Superhydrophobic Surfaces. Nanoscale Res Lett. 2007;2(12):577. 10.1007/s11671-007-9102-4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munir MT, Maneewan N, Pichon J, Gharbia M, Oumarou-Mahamane I, Baude J, Thorin C, Lepelletier D, Le Pape P, Eveillard M, Irle M, Pailhoriès H, Aviat F, Belloncle C, Federighi M, Dubreil L. Confocal spectral microscopy, a non-destructive approach to follow contamination and biofilm formation of mCherry Staphylococcus aureus on solid surfaces. Sci Rep. 2021;11:15574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8329050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34341378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>James GA, Boegli L, Hancock J, Bowersock L, Parker A, Kinney BM. Bacterial adhesion and biofilm formation on textured breast implant shell materials. Aesthetic Plast Surg. 2019;43(2):490–7. 10.1007/s00266-018-1234-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6420479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30276456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakker DP, van der Plaats A, Verkerke GJ, Busscher HJ &amp; van der Mei HC. Comparison of Velocity Profiles for Different Flow Chamber Designs Used in Studies of Microbial Adhesion to Surfaces. 2003. 10.1128/AEM.69.10.6280-6287.2003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC201240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14532092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saur T, Morin E, Habouzit F, Bernet N, Escudié R. Impact of wall shear stress on initial bacterial adhesion in rotating annular reactor. PLoS One. 2017;12(2):e0172113. 10.1371/journal.pone.0172113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5312967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28207869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>