<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39369869</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-6424</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental pollution (Barking, Essex : 1987)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Pollut</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Combating micro/nano plastic pollution with bioplastic: Sustainable food packaging, challenges, and future perspectives.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>125077</StartPage><MedlinePgn>125077</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.125077</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0269-7491(24)01794-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The widespread use of plastic in food packaging provides significant challenges due to its non-biodegradability and the risk of hazardous chemicals seeping into food and the environment. This highlights the pressing need to come up with alternatives to traditional plastic that prioritize environmental sustainability, food quality, and safety. The current study presents an up-to-date examination of micro/nano plastic (MP/NP) consumption and their associated toxicity to human health, while also considering bioplastic as safer and eco-friendly alternative materials for packaging. The study contributes to a deeper comprehension of the primary materials utilized for bioplastic manufacturing and their potential for large-scale use. The key findings underscore the distinctive features of bioplastics, such as starch, polyhydroxyalkanoates, polylactic acid, and polybutylene succinate, as well as their blends with active agents, rendering them suitable for innovative food packaging applications. Moreover, the study includes a discussion of insights from various scientific literature, agency reports (governmental and non-governmental), and industry trends in bioplastic production and their potential to combat MP/NP pollution. In essence, the review highlights future research directions for the safe integration of bioplastics in food packaging, addresses outstanding questions, and proposes potential solutions to challenges linked with plastic usage.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Subhash</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea; Institute of Cell Culture, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dubey</LastName><ForeName>Namo</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, College of Life and Applied Sciences, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Vishal</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choi</LastName><ForeName>Inho</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Cell Culture, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea; Department of Medical Biotechnology, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jeon</LastName><ForeName>Junhyun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, College of Life and Applied Sciences, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea. Electronic address: jjeon@yu.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Myunghee</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea; Institute of Cell Culture, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongsangbuk-do 38541, Republic of Korea. Electronic address: foodtech@ynu.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Pollut</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8804476</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0269-7491</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioplastic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Circular bioeconomy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental pollution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food packaging</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health hazards</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Toxicity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest ☒ The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. ☐The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests:</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39369869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.125077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0269-7491(24)01794-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>