<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39369892</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-3198</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of dairy science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Dairy Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>INVITED REVIEW: Advances in Yogurt Development: Microbiological Safety, Quality, Functionality, Sensory Evaluation, and Consumer Perceptions across Different Dairy and Plant-based Alternative Sources.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0022-0302(24)01195-0</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3168/jds.2024-25322</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Yogurt, as a globally prevalent fermented dairy product, is renowned for its substantial nutritional value and a myriad of health benefits, particularly pertaining to the digestive system. This narrative review elucidates the latest advancements in yogurt development from 2019 to 2024, addressing aspects of microbiological safety, quality, functionality, sensory evaluation, and consumer perceptions across diverse protein sources. The intrinsic quality of yogurt is significantly influenced by its primary ingredient, milk, traditionally derived from animals such as cows, goats, and sheep. In recent years, plant-based yogurts (PBYs) have emerged as a popular alternative to traditional dairy yogurts, that are made from plant sources and offer similar textures and flavors, catering to those seeking non-dairy options. This discussion encompasses the advantages and limitations of various sources and explores methodologies to enhance yogurt quality using these diverse sources. Ensuring the microbiological safety of yogurt is thus paramount to its quality, as it involves both preventing the presence of harmful pathogens and managing spoilage to maintain freshness. This article encapsulates the potential hazards and corresponding antibacterial strategies that safeguard yogurt consumption. These strategies include the use of natural preservatives, advancements in packaging technologies, and the implementation of stringent hygiene practices throughout the production process. Morever, the quality of yogurt is not only dependent on the source but also on the fermentation process and additional ingredients used. By addressing both the prevention of pathogen contamination and the control of spoilage organisms, this article explores not only explores comprehensive approaches but also examines the use of high-quality starter cultures, the role of prebiotics in enhancing probiotic efficacy, and genetic advancements, as well as improvements in the overall nutritional profile and shelf life of yogurt. Techniques to improve texture, flavor, and nutrient content are also discussed, providing a comprehensive overview of current quality enhancement methods.This analysis delves into the intricate mechanisms underpinning probiotic development, including the roles of prebiotics, supplementary starter cultures, and genetic factors that facilitate probiotic proliferation. These benefits include improved digestive health, enhanced immune function, and potential reductions in the risk of certain chronic diseases. Beyond quality and functionality, the sensory evaluation of yogurt remains crucial for consumer acceptance. In recent years, the incorporation of diverse additional ingredients into yogurt has been observed, aimed at augmenting its sensory attributes. This examination reveals these ingredients and their respective functions, such as natural flavorings, sweeteners, and texturizing agents, with the ultimate goal of enhancing overall consumer satisfaction. Consumer preferences exert a profound influence on yogurt production, rendering the understanding of customer opinions essential for devising competitive industry strategies. This article consolidates consumer feedback and preferences, striving to elevate yogurt quality and promote dietary diversity. The analysis includes trends such as the growing demand for organic and non-dairy yogurts, the importance of sustainable practices, and the impact of marketing and packaging on consumer choices. This comprehensive overview serves as a valuable reference for the dairy industry and researchers dedicated to the advancement of yogurt development.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2025, The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of the American Dairy Science Association®. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaojun</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yantai Key Laboratory of Special Medical Food, School of Food and Biological Engineering, Yantai Institute of Technology, Yantai, Shandong, 264003, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Linlin</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100085, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wei</LastName><ForeName>Xinyao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biological Science and Engineering, Fuzhou University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Changmou</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Human Nutrition, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL 61801, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cavender</LastName><ForeName>George</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food, Nutrition and Packaging Sciences, Clemson University, Clemson, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Walker</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Prestage Department of Poultry Science, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC 27695, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Shengqian</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yantai Key Laboratory of Special Medical Food, School of Food and Biological Engineering, Yantai Institute of Technology, Yantai, Shandong, 264003, PR China. Electronic address: sunshengqian@yitsd.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Dairy Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985126R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-0302</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Functionality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Protein Sources,Safety and Quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sensory Evaluation and Consumer Perceptions</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39369892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2024-25322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0022-0302(24)01195-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>