<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39364371</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2296-875X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in surgery</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Surg</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Retrospective analysis of immediate and long-term results of NOSES technique and conventional laparoscopic-assisted resection in patients with colorectal cancer.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1444942</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1444942</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1444942</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fsurg.2024.1444942</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The aim of research was to study the feasibility and safety of surgery providing specimen extraction through natural orifices in patients with colorectal cancer.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study is a comparative retrospective analysis of findings obtained from 265 patients who underwent surgical treatment using NOSES technique and 275 patients who underwent laparoscopic-assisted (LA) resection. Data included preoperative patients' information, intraoperative findings, results of postoperative pathological examination of surgical specimens, early postoperative period analysis, and follow-up.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Both groups were comparable in terms of gender, age and BMI. The duration of surgery was similar in both groups (<i>p</i> = 0.94). Intraoperative blood loss under NOSES interventions was slightly lower than in laparoscopic-assisted surgeries (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.001). There was no significant difference in the number of lymph nodes removed and anal function scores between the two groups (<i>p</i> &gt; 0.05). It was revealed that in the NOSES group, the function of the gastrointestinal tract normalized at an earlier time, slightly the time to start liquid food intake and the duration of postoperative hospital stay were reduced (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.001). A statistically significant difference between groups was found in complications, such as pneumonia (<i>p</i> = 0.03). The absolute number of complications was observed more often in the LA surgery group (10.4%) than in the NOSES group (5.8%). Local recurrence was less common in the NOSES group (<i>p</i> = 0.01). There were no statistically significant differences in disease progression (<i>p</i> = 0.16). When analyzing disease-free and overall survival rate in this study, there was no statistically significant difference between the two surgical techniques in terms of their effect on postoperative survival (<i>p</i> &gt; 0.05).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The results of this study demonstrate that NOSES technique is a relatively safe and effective surgical option in patients with colorectal cancer. It has high surgical efficiency providing no increased risk of surgical intervention, reducing total number of postoperative complications, reducing duration of postoperative hospital stay, reducing the time for gastrointestinal function recovery and the start of food intake. This study supports that NOSES has clear advantages over conventional laparoscopic-assisted surgery.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Malev, Zhang, Yuan, Tang, Wang, Oganezov, Huang and Wang.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malev</LastName><ForeName>Sergei</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Hao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Ziming</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Qingchao</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Guiyu</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oganezov</LastName><ForeName>Giorgi</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Breast Surgery, The Affiliated Tumor Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Rui</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xishan</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, National Cancer Center/National Clinical Research Center of Cancer/Cancer Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Surg</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101645127</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-875X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NOSES</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">colorectal cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">laparoscopy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">retrospective analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">treatment results</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39364371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11446899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsurg.2024.1444942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Peritoneal Tumor Committee of the Chinese Anti-Cancer Association. Chinese guidelines for integrated diagnosis and treatment of tumors: peritoneal tumors (gastrointestinal tumors). Chin J Gastrointest Surg. (2023) 26(2):111–20. 10.3760/cma.j.cn441530-20221221-00533</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3760/cma.j.cn441530-20221221-00533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36797555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleshman J, Sargent DJ, Green E, Anvari M, Stryker SJ, Beart RW Jr, et al. Clinical Outcomes of Surgical Therapy Study Group. Laparoscopic colectomy for cancer is not inferior to open surgery based on 5-year data from the COST Study Group trial. Ann Surg. (2007) 246(4):655–62. discussion 662–4. 10.1097/SLA.0b013e318155a762</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SLA.0b013e318155a762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17893502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awad ZT, Qureshi I, Seibel B, Sharma S, Dobbertien MA. Laparoscopic right hemicolectomy with transvaginal colon extraction using a laparoscopic posterior colpotomy: a 2-year series from a single institution. Surg Laparosc Endosc Percutan Tech. (2011) 21(6):403–8. 10.1097/SLE.0b013e31823945ac</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SLE.0b013e31823945ac</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22146161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Omiccioli A, Hegge S, McKinley C. Does the extraction-site location in laparoscopic colorectal surgery have an impact on incisional hernia rates? Surg Endosc. (2008) 22:2596–600. 10.1007/s00464-008-9845-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00464-008-9845-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18347858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez JE, Rasheid SH, Krieger BR, Frattini JC, Marcet JE. Laparoscopic-assisted transvaginal approach for sigmoidectomy and rectocolpopexy. JSLS. (2009) 13(2):217–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3015929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19660219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung AL, Cheung HY, Fok BK, Chung CC, Li MK, Tang CN. Prospective randomized trial of hybrid NOTES colectomy versus conventional laparoscopic colectomy for left-sided colonic tumors. World J Surg. (2013) 37(11):2678–82. 10.1007/s00268-013-2163-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00268-013-2163-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23942527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacy AM, Delgado S, Rojas OA, Almenara R, Blasi A, Llach J. MA-NOS radical sigmoidectomy: report of a transvaginal resection in the human. Surg Endosc. (2008) 22(7):1717–23. 10.1007/s00464-008-9956-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00464-008-9956-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18461385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kai P, Ligan X. Minimally invasive laparoscopic surgery for specimen extraction through natural orifices in the treatment of rectal cancer [J/CD]. J Minim Invasive Surg. (2012) 5(3):180–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xishan W. Current status and prospects of NOTES-type operations for rectal tumors [J/CD]. Electron J Rectal Dis. (2015) 4(4):11–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacobs M, Verdeja JC, Goldstein HS. Minimally invasive colon resection (laparoscopic colectomy). Surg Laparosc Endosc. (1991) 1(3):144–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1688289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim HJ, Choi GS, Park JS, Park SY, Ryuk JP, Yoon SH. Transvaginal specimen extraction versus conventional minilaparotomy after laparoscopic anterior resection for colorectal cancer: mid-term results of a case-matched study. Surg Endosc. (2014) 28(8):2342–8. 10.1007/s00464-014-3466-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00464-014-3466-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24566749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park JS, Choi GS, Kim HJ, Park SY, Jun SH. Natural orifice specimen extraction versus conventional laparoscopically assisted right hemicolectomy. Br J Surg. (2011) 98(5):710–5. 10.1002/bjs.7419</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bjs.7419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21305535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zilong G, Yuliuming W, Hanqing H, Hao Z, Zhengliang L, Chao X, et al. Efficacy comparison of natural orifice specimen extraction surgery (NOSES) and conventional laparoscopic surgery for left colon cancer. Chin J Colorec Dis (Electron Ed). (2022) 11(1):36–43. 10.3877/cma.j.issn.2095-3224.2022.01.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3877/cma.j.issn.2095-3224.2022.01.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulikov EP, Bublikov ID, Yu GE, Semionkin EI. Various surgical approaches to the treatment of patients with advanced colorectal cancer. Onkokhirurgiya. (2011) 3(5):29–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nepogodiev D, Martin J, Biccard B, Makupe A, Bhangu A, National Institute for Health Research Global Health Research Unit on Global Surgery. Global burden of postoperative death. Lancet. (2019) 393(10170):401. 10.1016/S0140-6736(18)33139-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)33139-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30722955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markaryan DR. Multidisciplinary Approach to the Treatment of Colorectal Cancer in Elderly Patients: Tesis Candidate of Medical Sciences. Moscow: Moscow State University of Medicine and Dentistry; (2012). p. 151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akasu T, Takawa M, Yamamoto S, Yamaguchi T, Fujita S, Moriya Y. Risk factors for anastomotic leakage following intersphincteric for very low rectal adenocarcinoma. J Gastrointest Surg. (2010) 4(1):104–11. 10.1007/s11605-009-1067-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11605-009-1067-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19841989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kube R, Mroczkowski P, Granowski D, Benedix F, Sahm M, Schmidt U, et al. Anastomotic leakage after colon cancer surgery: a predictor of significant morbidity and hospital mortality, and diminished tumour-free survival. Eur J Surg Oncol. (2010) 36(2):120–4. 10.1016/j.ejso.2009.08.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejso.2009.08.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19775850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petukhova IN, Dmitrieva NV, Bagirowa NS, Grigoryevskaya ZV, Shilnikova II, Varlan GV, et al. Postoperative infections in cancer patients. Malignant Tumors. (2016) 4(21):48–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teixeira F, Akaishi EH, Ushinohama AZ, Dutra TC, Netto SD, Utiyama EM, et al. Can we respect the principles of oncologic resection in an emergency surgery to treat colon cancer? World J Emergency Surg. (2015) 10:5. 10.1186/1749-7922-10-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1749-7922-10-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4506407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26191078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu S. A Coloproctology Clinical Recommendations. Moscow: GEOTAR-Media; (2015):491–518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hüttner FJ, Tenckhoff S, Jensen K, Uhlmann L, Kulu Y, Büchler MW, et al. Meta-analysis of reconstruction techniques after low anterior resection for rectal cancer. Br J Surg. (2015) 102(7):735–45. 10.1002/bjs.9782</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bjs.9782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25833333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sigal MZ, Romazanov MR. Method for determining the viability of the intestine in the area of anastomosis formation. Clin Surg. (1991) 2:6–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2056715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zmora O, Lebedyev A, Hoffman A, Khaikin M, Munz Y, Shabtai M, et al. Laparoscopic colectomy without mechanical bowel preparation. Int J Colorectal Dis. (2006) 21(7):683–7. 10.1007/s00384-005-0044-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00384-005-0044-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16231142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wille-Jorgensen P, Guenaga KF, Matos D, Castro AA. Preoperative mechanical bowel cleansing or not an updated meta-analysis. Colorectal Dis. (2005) 7:304–10. 10.1111/j.1463-1318.2005.00804.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1463-1318.2005.00804.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15932549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awad ZT. Laparoscopic subtotal colectomy with transrectal extraction of the colon and ileorectal anastomosis. Surg Endosc. ( 2012) 26(3):869–71. 10.1007/s00464-011-1926-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00464-011-1926-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21938571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metzger P. The laparoscopic technique of intersphincteric rectum resection. In: Schiessel R, Metzger P, eds. Intersphincteric Resection for low Rectal Tumors. Vol. 8. Vienna: Springer; (2012) p. 85–97. 10.1007/978-3-7091-0929-8_8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-7091-0929-8_8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public Health England. Surveillance of Surgical Site Infections in NHS Hospitals in England 2014/2015. London: Public Health England; (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, USA. National nosocomial infections surveillance (NNIS) system report, data summary from January through June 2004, issued October 2004. Am J Infect Control. (2004) 32:470–85. 10.1016/j.ajic.2004.10.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2004.10.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15573054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panos G, Mulita F, Akinosoglou K, Liolis E, Kaplanis C, Tchabashvili L, et al. Risk of surgical site infections after colorectal surgery and the most frequent pathogens isolated: a prospective single-centre observational study. Med Glas (Zenica). (2021) 18(2):438–43. 10.17392/1348-21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17392/1348-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34080408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulita F, Liolis E, Akinosoglou K, Tchabashvili L, Maroulis I, Kaplanis C, et al. Postoperative sepsis after colorectal surgery: a prospective single-center observational study and review of the literature. Prz Gastroenterol. (2022) 17(1):47–51. 10.5114/pg.2021.106083</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/pg.2021.106083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8942007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35371356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunaevsky IV, Gelfond VM. Preparation, provision and postoperative therapy of patients undergoing surgery for colorectal cancer. Pract Oncol. (2005) 6(2):127–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velkov VV. Use of the biomarker presepsin for early and highly specific diagnostics of sepsis. Wounds and wound infections. The Prof. B.M. Kostyuchenok Journal. (2015) 2(1):53–82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saraev AR, ShK N, Ali-Zade SG, Saburova AM. Inflammation and sepsis biomarkers in diagnosis of the generalized peritonitis stage. Avicenna Bull. (2020) 22(2):280–5. 10.25005/2074-0581-2020-22-2-280-285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.25005/2074-0581-2020-22-2-280-285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verras G-I, Mulita F. Butyrylcholinesterase levels correlate with surgical site infection risk and severity after colorectal surgery: a prospective single-center study. Front Surg. (2024) 11:1379410. 10.3389/fsurg.2024.1379410</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsurg.2024.1379410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11368738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39229253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bousis D, Verras GI, Bouchagier K, Antzoulas A, Panagiotopoulos I, Katinioti A, et al. The role of deep learning in diagnosing colorectal cancer. Prz Gastroenterol. (2023) 18(3):266–73. 10.5114/pg.2023.129494</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/pg.2023.129494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10626379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37937113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chlorogiannis DD, Verras G, Tzelepi V, Chlorogiannis A, Apostolos A, Kotis K, et al. Tissue classification and diagnosis of colorectal cancer histopathology images using deep learning algorithms. Is the time ripe for clinical practice implementation? Prz Gastroenterol. (2023) 18(4):353. 10.5114/pg.2023.130337</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/pg.2023.130337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10985751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38572457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngu J, Wong AS. Transanal natural orifice specimen extraction in colorectal surgery: bacteriological and oncological concerns. ANZ J Surg. (2016) 86(4):299–302. 10.1111/ans.13383</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ans.13383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26603221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>