<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39363884</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2470-1343</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>23</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ACS omega</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ACS Omega</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Application and Research Progress of Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy in Agricultural Product Inspection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>24203</StartPage><EndPage>24218</EndPage><MedlinePgn>24203-24218</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acsomega.4c02104</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The quality and safety of agricultural products are of paramount importance in ensuring the health of the food supply chain. Additionally, the composition and trace elements in agricultural products significantly influence their quality and nutritional value. Therefore, the need for rapid and accurate analysis techniques for agricultural product composition is particularly crucial. In the current landscape of evolving compositional analysis technologies, Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy (LIBS) technology is emerging as a promising analytical tool with broad applications in agricultural product testing. Its characteristics of being rapid, real-time, and capable of simultaneous detection of multiple elements provide an efficient and reliable means for assessing the quality, monitoring safety, and tracing the origin of agricultural products. This technology is expected to play a significant role in controlling and managing the agricultural industry chain and can offer consumers safer and healthier agricultural products. This paper provides an overview of the research status and recent developments of LIBS technology in agricultural product testing applications in recent years. Based on the current research landscape, challenges and opportunities of applying LIBS technology in fields such as agricultural product quality and safety assessment, soil analysis, assessment of crop nutrition, detection of plant diseases, and identification of agricultural product varieties have been evaluated. Moreover, recommendations for further expanding the application of LIBS technology in the agricultural sector are proposed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0001-2610-0857</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Bengbu University, Bengbu 233030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Food Technology and Quality Management of Agricultural Products, National University of Life and Environmental Sciences of Ukraine, Kyiv 03041, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tolok</LastName><ForeName>Galina</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Food Technology and Quality Management of Agricultural Products, National University of Life and Environmental Sciences of Ukraine, Kyiv 03041, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fu</LastName><ForeName>Yuanxia</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Food Technology and Quality Management of Agricultural Products, National University of Life and Environmental Sciences of Ukraine, Kyiv 03041, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Food Technology and Quality Management of Agricultural Products, National University of Life and Environmental Sciences of Ukraine, Kyiv 03041, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Information Technology, National University of Life and Environmental Sciences of Ukraine, Kyiv 03041, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Hui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Information Technology, National University of Life and Environmental Sciences of Ukraine, Kyiv 03041, Ukraine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Bengbu University, Bengbu 233030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ACS Omega</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101691658</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2470-1343</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39363884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11448804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsomega.4c02104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Duan X. L.; Zhu J. F.; Li W.; Wang K. L.; Zhang C. P. Metabolomic Analysis of Medicago sativa at Germination and Seedling Stage under Salt Stress. Chin. J. Grassland 2024, 46 (2), 35–47. 10.16742/j.zgcdxb.20230080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16742/j.zgcdxb.20230080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J. The uptake and transportation of carbon nanodots and their toxic mechanism in plants. N. East. Norm. Univ. 2017, 10.27011/d.cnki.gdbsu.2017.000031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.27011/d.cnki.gdbsu.2017.000031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun X. D. Study on Mycobiota in Traditionally Fermented Soybean Pastesin Northeast China and Metabonomics of Functional Strains. Dalian Unive. Technol. 2022, 10.26991/d.cnki.gdllu.2020.003845.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26991/d.cnki.gdllu.2020.003845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koarai K.; Matsueda M.; Aoki J.; et al. Rapid analysis of 90Sr in cattle bone and tooth samples by inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry. J. Anal. At. Spectrom. 2021, 36, 1678–1682. 10.1039/D1JA00086A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1JA00086A</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X. Z.; Xiong C.; Sun K.; et al. Optimization of ICP-OES’S parameters for uranium analysis of rock samples. J. Korean. Phys. Soc. 2021, 78, 737–742. 10.1007/s40042-021-00093-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40042-021-00093-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thubkhun N.; Tangtreamjitmun N. Determination of nickel by flame atomic absorption spectrometry after preconcentration by coprecipitation with aluminum hydroxide. Anal. Sci. 2018, 34, 849–851. 10.2116/analsci.17P582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2116/analsci.17P582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29998970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo L. B.; Niu X. C.; Zhang M. S. Analysis of the Application Progress in Laser-induced BreakdownSpectroscopy: A Review (Invited). Acta Photon. Sin. 2023, 52, 0352104.10.3788/gzxb20235203.0352104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/gzxb20235203.0352104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng Z. W.; Guo S. T.; Xu Z. S.; Zhao Z. Y.; Lu Y.; Liu L.; Hao Z. Q. Quantitative Analysis of Rare Earth Elements Based on Double-pulse LIBS Combined with Partial Least Squares Regression. Chin. J. Inorg. Anal. Chem. 2024, 14 (02), 183–190. 10.3969/j.issn.2095-1035.2024.02.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3969/j.issn.2095-1035.2024.02.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J. M.; Lu J. S.; Zheng P. C.; Liu S. J.; Li G.; Chen G. H. Study on Alkalinity Measurement of Sinter Based on LIBS Technology Combined with Internal Standard Method. Chin. J. Laser 2023, 50 (22), 175–182. 10.3788/CJL230520.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/CJL230520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J. X.; Li H. L.; Lv H. S.; Li X. T.; Wu Q. D.; Yang X. N. Detection of heavy metals based on laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy under magnetic field constraints. J. Optoelectron. Laser 2023, 34 (04), 422–428. 10.16136/j.joel.2023.04.0255.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16136/j.joel.2023.04.0255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai Y. C.; Bu Y.; Wang Y. H.; Wu F.; Yan X. N. Effect of Spatial Confinement on Plasma Evolution and Spectrum in Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy. Acta Opt. Sin. 2023, 43 (07), 269–276. 10.3788/AOS221749.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/AOS221749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng F.; Ding Y.; Chen Y. J.; et al. Quantitative analysis of the content of nitrogen and sulfur in coal based on laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy: effects of variable selection. Plasma Sci. Technol. 2020, 22, 074005.10.1088/2058-6272/ab77d5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/2058-6272/ab77d5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma S. X.; Tang Y.; Zhang S. Y.; et al. Chlorine and sulfur determination in water using indirect laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Talanta. 2020, 214, 120849.10.1016/j.talanta.2020.120849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2020.120849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32278424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q. Z.; Zhang W.; Tang Z. Y.; et al. Determination of uranium in ores using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy combined with laser-induced fluorescence. J. Anal. Atom. Spectrom 2020, 35, 626–631. 10.1039/C9JA00433E.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C9JA00433E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo L. B.; Zhang D.; Sun L. X.; et al. Development in the application of laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy in recent years: A review. Front. Phys. 2021, 16, 22500.10.1007/s11467-020-1007-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11467-020-1007-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emara E. M.; Song H.; Imam H.; et al. Detection of hypokalemia disorder and its relation with hypercalcemia in blood serum using LIBS technique for patients of colorectal cancer grade I and grade II. Laser. Med. Sci. 2022, 37, 1081–1093. 10.1007/s10103-021-03355-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10103-021-03355-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34173122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng P. C.; Li X. J.; Wang J. M.; Zheng S.; Zhao H. D. Quantitative analysis of Cu and Pb in Coptidis by reheated double pulse laser induced breakdown spectroscopy. Acta Phys. Sin. 2019, 68 (12), 198–205. 10.7498/aps.68.20190148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7498/aps.68.20190148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong M.; Wei L.; Gonzalez J. J.; et al. Coal discrimination analysis using tandem laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy and laser ablation inductively coupled plasma time-of-flight mass spectrometry. Anal. Chem. 2020, 92, 7003–7010. 10.1021/acs.analchem.0c00188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.0c00188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32281365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian Z. H.; Li X. L.; Wang G.; et al. Elemental and proximate analysis of coal by X-ray fluorescence assisted laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Plasma Sci. Technol. 2022, 24, 084007.10.1016/j.talanta.2020.120849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2020.120849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin H. Q.; Lu Z. M.; Yao S. C.; et al. Combining laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy and Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy for the analysis of coal properties. J. Anal. Atom. Spectrom. 2019, 34, 347–355. 10.1039/C8JA00381E.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C8JA00381E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao S. C.; Qin H. Q.; Wang Q.; et al. Optimizing analysis of coal property using laser-induced breakdown and near-infrared reflectance spectroscopies. Spectrochim Acta. A Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc. 2020, 239, 118492.10.1016/j.saa.2020.118492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.saa.2020.118492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32470810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong P. K.; Zhao S. Y.; Zheng K. X. Rapid identification of ginseng origin by laser induced breakdown spectroscopy combined with neural network and support vector machine algorithm. Acta Phys. Sin 2021, 70, 61–69. 10.7498/aps.70.20201520.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7498/aps.70.20201520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue Z. Q.; Sun C.; Chen F. Y.; et al. Machine learning-based LIBS spectrum analysis of human blood plasma allows ovarian cancer diagnosis. Biomed Opt Express. 2021, 12, 2559–2574. 10.1364/BOE.421961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1364/BOE.421961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8176811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34123488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J.; Li Q. Z.; Liu K.; et al. Correction of moisture interference in laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy detection of coal by combining neural networks and random spectral attenuation. J. Anal. At. Spectrom. 2022, 37, 1658–1664. 10.1039/D2JA00138A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D2JA00138A</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubey D.; Kumar R.; Dwivedi A.; Rai A. K. Study of Electronic Bands of Diatomic Molecules for the Evaluation of Toxicity of Green Crackers Using LIBS Coupled with Chemometric Method. Electron. Mater. 2023, 4, 1–14. 10.3390/electronicmat4010001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/electronicmat4010001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Y. H.; Kang J.; Wang Y. R.; et al. Rapid and Sensitive Analysis of Trace Leads in Medicinal Herbs Using Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy-Laser-Induced Fluorescence (LIBS-LIF). Appl. Spectrosc. 2019, 73, 1284–1291. 10.1177/0003702819857740.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0003702819857740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31219335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu C. W.; Tang Z. Y.; Li Q. Z.; et al. Lead of detection in rhododendron leaves using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy assisted by laser-induced fluorescence. Sci. Total Environ. 2020, 738, 139402.10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.139402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.139402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32531612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding Y.; Xia G.; Ji H.; Xiong X. Accurate quantitative determination of heavy metals in oily soil by laser induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) combined with interval partial least squares (IPLS). Anal. Methods. 2019, 11, 3657.10.1039/C9AY01030K.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C9AY01030K</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu J. M.; Lu J. Q.; Li Y. K. Cadmium Detection in Rice Using Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy Combined with Film Preparation. Laser. Optoelectron. P. 2021, 58, 421–428. 10.3788/LOP202158.1730001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/LOP202158.1730001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang L.; Chen Y. F.; Wang J. B.; et al. Online identification and classification of Gannan navel oranges with Cu contamination by LIBS with IGA-optimized SVM. Anal. Methods 2023, 15, 738–745. 10.1039/D2AY01874H.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D2AY01874H</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36655675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamela R. R.; Fontoura B. M.; Costa V. C.; et al. Matrix-Matching Calibration Using Solid Standards: A Comparison between Univariate and Multivariate Strategies for the Determination of Calcium and Magnesium in Bean Seed Samples Employing Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy. Anal. Lett. 2023, 56, 944–957. 10.1080/00032719.2022.2111573.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00032719.2022.2111573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C.; Li H. L.; Sun J. X.; et al. Study on enrichment characteristics of Chinese herbal medicine based on LIBS technology. Optoelectron. Lett. 2023, 19, 88–94. 10.1007/s11801-023-2104-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11801-023-2104-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Q.; Yu Y.; Cui P. D.; et al. Laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) for the detection of exogenous contamination of metal elements in lily bulbs. Spectrochim Acta A Mol. Biomol Spectrosc 2023, 287, 122053.10.1016/j.saa.2022.122053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.saa.2022.122053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36327800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar T.; Rai A. K.; Dwivedi A.; et al. Chemical Characterization for the Detection of Impurities in Tainted and Natural Curcuma longa from India Using LIBS Coupled with PCA. Atoms 2022, 10, 91.10.3390/atoms10030091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/atoms10030091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu C. W.; Lv J. X.; Liu K.; et al. Rapid Determination of Arsenic in Traditional Chinese Medicine by Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy (LIBS). Anal. Lett. 2022, 55, 2531–2541. 10.1080/00032719.2022.2061985.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00032719.2022.2061985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu G. F.; Li Z. X.; Xu J.; et al. Prediction of heavy metal Cd and stress on minerals in rice by analysis of LIBS spectra. Appl. Opt. 2022, 61, 2536–2541. 10.1364/AO.448454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1364/AO.448454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35471320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umar Z. A.; Liaqat U.; Ahmed R.; et al. Determination of Micronutrients and Toxic Elements in Moringa Oleifera Leaves by Calibration Free Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy (LIBS). Anal. Lett. 2022, 55, 755–769. 10.1080/00032719.2021.1966794.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00032719.2021.1966794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y.; Li G. M.; Feng T.; et al. Discrimination of Radix Astragali according to geographical regions by data fusion of laser induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) and infrared spectroscopy (IR) combined with random forest (RF). Chin. J. Anal. Chem. 2022, 50, 100057.10.1016/j.cjac.2022.100057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cjac.2022.100057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F.; Xie W. H.; Lin M.; Ye L. F.; Zhang C.; Zhao Z. F.; Liu F.; Peng J. Y.; Kong W. W. Rapid authentication of geographical origins of Baishao (Radix Paeoniae Alba) slices with laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy based on conventional machine learning and deep learning. Spectrochim. Acta, Part B 2024, 212, 106852.10.1016/j.sab.2023.106852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sab.2023.106852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao X.; Liu Y.; Wang Q.; et al. Research of the content of nutrient elements caused by anthracnose to Camellia oleifera using LIBS technology. Appl. Phys. B: Laser Opt. 2022, 10.1007/s00340-021-07726-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00340-021-07726-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehan I.; Gondal M. A.; Aldakheel R. K.; et al. Determination of Nutritional and Toxic Metals in Black Tea Leaves Using Calibration Free LIBS and ICP: AES Technique. Arab J. Sci. Eng. 2022, 47, 7531–7539. 10.1007/s13369-021-06233-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13369-021-06233-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao C.; Dong D.; Du X.; Zheng W. In-Field, In Situ, and In Vivo 3-Dimensional Elemental Mapping for Plant Tissue and Soil Analysis Using Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy. Sensors. 2016, 16, 1764.10.3390/s16101764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s16101764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5087548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27782074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu G. R.; Hu W.; Xie W. P.; Yao X. Y.; Xu j.; Yang p.; Yao M. Y. Quantitative analysis of Cd based on the stress effect of minerals in rice by laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Anal. Methods 2023, 15, 5867.10.1039/D3AY01340E.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D3AY01340E</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37902026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H. Y.; Zhang X. Q.; Zhang W.; Qiu R. Detection and analysis of Cr element in rice by laser induced breakdown spectroscopy. J. At. Mol. Phys. 2023, 40 (04), 110–115. 10.19855/j.1000-0364.2023.043001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19855/j.1000-0364.2023.043001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Z. M.; Chen Y.; Wan E. L. Online in situ detection of onion by laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. J. At. Mol. Phys. 2022, 39, 92–97. 10.19855/j.1000-0364.2022.034001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19855/j.1000-0364.2022.034001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Z. Y.; Huang L.; Huang M. H. Quantitative analysis of Cd in green vegetables by laser induced breakdown spectroscopy. Chin J. Anal. Lab. 2018, 37, 1384–1388. 10.13595/j.cnki.issn1000-0720.2018.0263.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13595/j.cnki.issn1000-0720.2018.0263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao M.; Yang H.; Huang L.; et al. Detection of heavy metal Cd in polluted fresh leafy vegetablesby laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Appl. Opt. 2017, 56, 4070.10.1364/AO.56.004070.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1364/AO.56.004070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29047538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu F.; Ye L. H.; Peng J. Y.; et al. Fast Detection of Copper Content in Rice byLaser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy with Uni- and Multivariate Analysis. Sensors. 2018, 18, 705.10.3390/s18030705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s18030705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5876664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29495445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H. L.; Wang H. B.; Kang S. S.; Fang L. D.; Li X. T. LIBS experimental study of eliminating the interference of Al element in soil base based on background subtraction method. Infra. Laser Eng. 2021, 50 (01), 257–262. 10.3788/IRLA20200136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/IRLA20200136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z. Z.; Zhao J.; Zhou C. Y.; Zhao J. Y.; Qian Li.; Li Y. Q. Research on Soil Classification Based on LIBS Technology. J. Shenyang Ligong Univer 2023, 42 (06), 89–94. 10.3969/j.issn.1003-1251.2023.06.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3969/j.issn.1003-1251.2023.06.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding Y.; Xia G.; Ji H.; Xiong X. Accurate quantitative determination of heavy metals in oily soil by laser induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) combined with interval partial least squares (IPLS). Anal. Methods 2019, 11, 3657–3664. 10.1039/C9AY01030K.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C9AY01030K</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y.; Guindo M. L.; Xu X.; et al. Deep learning associated with laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) for the prediction of lead in soil. Appl. Spectrosc. 2019, 73, 565–573. 10.1177/0003702819826283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0003702819826283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30624080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y.; Hao X. J.; Yang Y. W.; Sun P. Analysis of Ba Content in Soil Based on Cavity Confinement LIBS Combined with Multivariate Regression. Laser. Optoelectron. P 2022, 59 (5), 36–42. 10.3788/LOP202259.0530005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/LOP202259.0530005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterjee S.; Singh M.; Biswal B. P.; Sinha U. K.; Patbhaje S.; Sarkar A. Application of laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) coupled with PCA for rapid classification of soil samples in geothermal areas. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2019, 411, 2855–2866. 10.1007/s00216-019-01731-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-019-01731-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30879114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan C. C.; Zhao N. J.; Ma M. J.; Yang R. F.; Yang J. Q.; Liu J. G. Highly Sensitive Detection of Cd in Soil Using Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy. Laser Optoelectron. Prog. 2023, 60 (17), 402–408. 10.3788/LOP220961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/LOP220961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y. K.; Hao X. J.; Yang Y. W.; Hao W. Y.; Sun P.; Pan B. W. Quantitative Analysis of Soil Heavy Metal Elements Based on Cavity Confinement LIBS Combined With Machine Learning. Spectrosc. Spect. Anal 2022, 42 (08), 2387–2391. 10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho G. G. A.; Moros J.; Santos D.; et al. Direct determination of the nutrient profile in plant materials by femtosecond laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Anal. Chim. Acta 2015, 876, 26–38. 10.1016/j.aca.2015.03.018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2015.03.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25998455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunz J. N.; Voronine D. V.; Ko B. A.; et al. Interaction of femtosecond laser pulses with plants: towards distinguishing weeds and crops using plasma temperature. J. Mod. Optic. 2017, 64, 942–947. 10.1080/09500340.2017.1287434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09500340.2017.1287434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding Q. P.; Yao M. Y.; Wu S. J. Detecting Huanglongbing in citrus leaves based On laser induced breakdown spectroscopy. Acta. Agric. Univer. Jiangxiensis 2022, 44, 1015–1022. 10.13300/j.cnki.hnlkxb.2022.01.026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13300/j.cnki.hnlkxb.2022.01.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang B. Establishment of LIBS elements and Na∼ + distribution of sweet sorghum plants. Anhui Unive 2022, 10.26917/d.cnki.ganhu.2021.000159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26917/d.cnki.ganhu.2021.000159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H. P.; Zhang P. F.; Xu Z. P. Sorghum Na and Fe quantification methods of LIBS combined with VDPSO-CMW algorithm. Spectrosc. Spect. Anal. 2023, 43, 823–829. 10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ercioglu E.; Velioglu H. M.; Boyaci I. H. Chemometric Evaluation of Discrimination of Aromatic Plants by Using NIRS, LIBS. Food. Anal. Method 2018, 11, 1656–1667. 10.1007/s12161-018-1145-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-018-1145-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zivkovic S.; Savovic J.; Kuzmanovic M.; et al. Alternative analytical method for direct determination of Mn and Ba in peppermint tea based on laser induced breakdown spectroscopy. Microchem. J. 2018, 137, 410–417. 10.1016/j.microc.2017.11.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2017.11.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrade D. F.; Pereira-Filho E. R.; Konieczynski P. Comparison of ICP OES and LIBS Analysis of Medicinal Herbs Rich in Flavonoids from Eastern Europe. J. Braz. Chem. Soc. 2016, 28, 838–847. 10.21577/0103-5053.20160236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21577/0103-5053.20160236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y. C.; Jiao L.; Yan N. Y.; Yan C. H.; Qu L.; Zhang H. R.; Ma L. Identification of Salvia Miltiorrhiza From Different Origins by Laser Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy Combined with Artificial Neural Network. Spectrosc. Spect. Anal. 2023, 43 (10), 3098–3104. 10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593(2023)10-3098-07.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593(2023)10-3098-07</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modlitbová P.; Hlaváček A.; Švestková T.; et al. The effects of photon-upconversion nanoparticles on the growth of radish and duckweed: Bioaccumulation, imaging, and spectroscopic studies. Chemosphere 2019, 225, 723–734. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.03.074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.03.074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30903846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu W.; Zhou Z. Y.; Sun Z. M.; Zhang X. L.; Liu Y. Z. Real-time detection of the genus Rosa L. using LIBS technology. J. Chin. Quant. Elect 2022, 39, 494–501. 10.3969/j.issn.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3969/j.issn</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assis J.V. B.; Ferreira D da S.; Bócoli D de A.; Brait C. H. H.; Pereira-Filho E. R. Direct Determination of Ca, K, and Mg in Soy Leaf Samples Using Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy. Appl. Spectrosc. 2024, 78, 243–250. 10.1177/00037028231217974.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/00037028231217974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38083817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu C. W.; Tang Z. Y.; Li Q. Z.; et al. Lead of detection in rhododendron leaves using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy assisted by laser-induced fluorescence. Sci. Total Environ. 2020, 738, 139402.10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.139402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.139402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32531612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stenio K.; Costa V. C.; De Morais C. P.; Magalhaes A. B.; Milori D. M. B. P. Direct Determination of Nutrient Elements in Plant Leaves by Double Pulse Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy: Evaluation of Calibration Strategies Using Direct and Inverse Models for Matrix-Matching. Anal. Methods 2022, 14, 1246–1253. 10.1039/D1AY02101J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1AY02101J</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35260868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang Q.; Zhong M. J.; Yin P. K. Analysis of elements under heavy metals stress based on laser-induced breakdown spectrum. Spectrosc. Spect. Anal. 2023, 43, 1485–1488. 10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593(203)05-1485-04.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593(203)05-1485-04</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W.; Kong W.; Shen T.; Man Z.; Zhu W.; He Y.; Liu F.; Liu Y. Application of laser induced breakdown spectroscopy in detection of cadmium content in rice stems. Front. Plant Sci. 2020, 11, 2073–2084. 10.3389/fpls.2020.599616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2020.599616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7775383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33391312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fayek N.; Tawfik W.; Khalafallah A.; Hamed S.; Mousa W.; Fikry M. Evaluation of Heavy Metal Presence in Agricultural Samples of Lactuca sativaand Trifolium alexandrinum Using Picosecond Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy and Flame Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy in Banha and Giza Governorates, Egypt. Minerals 2023, 13, 1300.10.3390/min13101300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/min13101300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng J. Y.; Ye L. F.; Xie W. Y.; Liu Y. F.; Lin M.; Kong W. W.; Zhao Z. F.; Liu F.; Huang J.; Zhou F. In-situ and fast classification of origins of Baishao (Radix Paeoniae Alba) slices based on auto-focus laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Opt. lette 2023, 48, 3567–3570. 10.1364/OL.494308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1364/OL.494308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37390182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M. N.; Wang Q. Q.; Idrees B. S.; Waheed R.; Haq A. U.; Abrar M.; Jamil Y. Evaluation of medicinal plants using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) combined with chemometric techniques. Laser Med. Sci. 2023, 38, 149–149. 10.1007/s10103-023-03805-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10103-023-03805-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37365431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krajcarová L.; Novotný K.; Kummerová M.; et al. Mapping of the spatial distribution of silver nanoparticles in root tissues of Vicia faba by laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS). Talanta 2017, 173, 28–35. 10.1016/j.talanta.2017.05.055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2017.05.055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28602188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh V. K.; Tripathi D. K.; Mao X. L.; Russo R. E.; Zorba V. Elemental Mapping of Lithium Diffusion in Doped Plant Leaves Using Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy (LIBS). Appl. Spectroschim 2019, 73, 387–394. 10.1177/0003702819830394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0003702819830394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30700104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranulfi A. C.; Romano R. A.; Magalhães A. B.; et al. Evaluation of the nutritional changes caused by Huanglongbing (HLB) to citrus plants using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Appl. Spectrosc. 2017, 71, 1471–1480. 10.1177/0003702817701751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0003702817701751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28447856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouyang A. G.; Liu X. L.; Li B.; Lin T. Z.; Liu Y. D.; Huang M.; Song Y. Detecting Huang long bing in citrus leaves based on laser induced breakdown spectroscopy. J. Agri.Univer. Huazhong. 2022, 41 (1), 255–261. 10.13300/j.cnki.hnlkxb.2022.01.026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13300/j.cnki.hnlkxb.2022.01.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L. Y.; Li J.; Rao H. H. Element detection and quality identification of Huanglong navel orange based on LIBS. Laser. Optoelectron. P. 2020, 57, 371–378. 10.3788/LOP57.233002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/LOP57.233002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao G. F.; Huang L.; Liu M. H.; et al. Identification of Huanglongbing-infected navel oranges based on laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy combined with different chemometric methods. Appl. Opt. 2018, 57, 8738–8742. 10.1364/AO.57.008738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1364/AO.57.008738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30461952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponce L.; Etxeberria E.; Gonzalez P.; et al. Rapid identification of Huanlongbing-infected citrus plants using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy of phloem samples. Appl. Opt. 2018, 57, 8841–8844. 10.1364/AO.57.008841.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1364/AO.57.008841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30461866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng J. Y.; He Y.; Ye L. H.; et al. Moisture influence reducing method for heavy metals detection in plant materials using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy: a case study for chromium content detection in rice leaves. Anal. Chem. 2017, 89, 7593–7600. 10.1021/acs.analchem.7b01441.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.7b01441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28625048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao G. F.; Huang L.; He X. W. Comparison of tea variety identification models based on laser-induced breakdown spectra. Laser. Optoelectron. P. 2018, 55, 470–474. 10.3788/LOP55.023002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/LOP55.023002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng K. X. Study on the rapid identification of ginseng origin based on LIBS technology. Changchun University of Science and Technology 2022, 10.26977/d.cnki.gccgc.2022.000693.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26977/d.cnki.gccgc.2022.000693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian Y.; Yan C. H.; Zhang T. L.; et al. Classification of wines according to their production regions with the contained trace elements using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Spectrochim. Acta, Part B 2017, 135, 91–101. 10.1016/j.sab.2017.07.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sab.2017.07.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guedes W. N.; Pereira F. M. V. Classifying impurity ranges in raw sugarcane using laser-inducedbreakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) and sum fusion across a tuning parameter window. Microchem. J. 2018, 143, 331–336. 10.1016/j.microc.2018.08.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2018.08.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva T. V.; Milori D. M. B. P.; Neto J. A. G.; et al. Prediction of black, immature and sour defective beans in coffee blends by using Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy. Food. chem. 2019, 278, 223–227. 10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.11.062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.11.062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30583366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang P.; Zhou R.; Zhang W.; et al. Laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy assisted chemometricmethods for rice geographic origin classification. Appl. optics 2018, 57, 8297–8302. 10.1364/AO.57.008297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1364/AO.57.008297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30461781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang D. C.; Ding J.; Feng Z. Q.; et al. Origin identification of Ginkgo biloba leaves based on laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS). Spectrochim. Acta, Part B 2021, 180, 106192.10.1016/j.sab.2021.106192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sab.2021.106192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Y. W.; Dong D. M. Laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy combined with stoichiometry of Epimedium origin for rapid identification. J. North. Normal. Univ(Nat. Sci). 2023, 59, 54–60. 10.16783/j.cnki.nwnuz.2023.02.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16783/j.cnki.nwnuz.2023.02.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai Y.; Zhao Z. F.; Guo L. B. Study on the origin tracing of Chinese yam decoction piece based on LIBS. Spectrosc. Spect. Anal. 2023, 43, 138–144. 10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3964/j.issn.1000-0593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang X. Y.; Lu X.; Qian H. L. Study on origin identification combining laser induced breakdown spectroscopy and convolutional neural network. J. North. Normal. Univ(Nat. Sci) 2022, 58, 50–57. 10.16783/j.cnki.nwnuz.2022.04.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16783/j.cnki.nwnuz.2022.04.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu F.; Ye L. H.; Peng J. Y.; et al. Fast detection of copper content in rice by laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy with uni- and multivariate analysis. Sensors 2018, 18, 705.10.3390/s18030705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s18030705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5876664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29495445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R.; Ma H.; Zhang T. Y. Study on tea classification based on provenance via random forests and laser induced breakdown spectroscopy. SPIE 2021, 12064, 1206402.10.1117/12.2599051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1117/12.2599051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao M.; Fu G.; Chen T.; Liu M.; Xu J.; Zhou H.; He X.; Huang L. A modified genetic algorithm optimized SVM for rapid classification of tea leaves using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. J. Anal. Atom. Spectrom. 2021, 36, 361–367. 10.1039/D0JA00317D.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0JA00317D</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao L.; He X. W.; Cai G. Y. Study on harvest period differentiation of green tea based on LIBS and SSA-SVM. Acta Agric. Univ Jiangxiensis 2023, 45, 719–725. 10.13836/j.jjau.2023067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13836/j.jjau.2023067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian Y.; Yan C. H.; Zhang T. L. Classification of wines according to their production regions with the contained trace elements using laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Spectrochim. Acta Part B 2017, 425, 3353–3356. 10.1016/j.sab.2017.07.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sab.2017.07.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gazeli O.; Bellou E.; Stefas D.; Couris S. Laser-based classification of olive oils assisted by machine leaming. Food. Chem. 2020, 302, 125329.10.1016/j.foodchem.2019.125329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2019.125329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31404874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gyftokostas N.; Stefas D.; Couris S. Olive oils classification via laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy. Appl. Sci. 2020, 10, 3462.10.3390/app10103462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app10103462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magalhaes A. B.; Senesi G. S.; Ranulfi A.; et al. Discrimination of Genetically Very Close Accessions of Sweet Orange (Citrus sinensis L. Osbeck) by Laser-Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy(LIBS). Molecules 2021, 26, 3092.10.3390/molecules26113092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26113092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8196892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34064288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo M.; Huang Z. Y.; Wang J. Identification of three dry-cured ham origin based on laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy combined with machine learning algorithm. J. Chin. Insti. Food. Sci. Techno. 2022, 22, 279–285. 10.16429/j.1009-7848.2022.10.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.16429/j.1009-7848.2022.10.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao G. F.; Huang L.; Liu M. H. Origin Identification of navel orange origin based on laser-induced breakdown spectrum. Laser. Optoelectron. P. 2018, 55, 440–445. 10.3788/LOP55.093003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3788/LOP55.093003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou J. X.; Wang J. X. Identification of rice seeds based on laser-induced breakdown spectral integral signal. Las. J. 2021, 42, 37–41. 10.14016/j.cnki.jgzz.2021.02.037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14016/j.cnki.jgzz.2021.02.037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>