<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39376704</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1664-302X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Application of hot water and cold air to reduce bacterial contamination on broiler carcasses.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1429756</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1429756</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1429756</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fmicb.2024.1429756</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Two physical treatments (heat via water bath and cold air) with various temperatures (20/70/75/80°C and - 80/-90°C) and exposure times (20, 30, 40 s) were carried out to identify a decontaminating effect on zoonotic pathogens on broiler carcasses. Subsequently, carcasses were analyzed for thermotolerant <i>Campylobacter (C.)</i>, <i>Salmonella</i>, <i>Escherichia (E.). coli</i> and total colony count (TCC). Moreover, for the hot water treatment, qPCR with viable/dead differentiation (v-qPCR) was applied to detect viable but non-culturable cells (VBNC) of <i>Campylobacter,</i> referred to as intact but putatively infectious units (IPIU). Hot water immersion was tested on carcasses inoculated with <i>C. jejuni</i> and <i>Salmonella</i>, while cold air treatment was evaluated for naturally contaminated carcasses of broiler flocks colonized with <i>Campylobacter</i>. For hot water treatment, the statistically significant reducing effect was about 1 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/ml for both <i>Salmonella</i> and <i>Campylobacter</i> for 70-80°C and 20/30 s treatments. The effect of heat treatment for <i>Campylobacter</i> was smaller when samples were analyzed with v-qPCR with reductions of 0.5-0.8 log<sub>10</sub> IPIU/ml in mean. Cold air treatments at -90°C were effective in reducing the mean contamination level of <i>Campylobacter</i> by 0.4-0.5 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/ml at all exposure times (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05). Hot water treatments showed a decreasing trend on TCC by 0.6-0.9 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/ml (p &lt; 0.05). TCC counts were not significantly affected by cold air treatment. For <i>E. coli</i> no statistically significant reductions were observed by hot water treatment. The cold air treatment at -90°C for 20 and 40 s led to a reduction of <i>E. coli</i> by 0.4 and 0.8 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/ml (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05), respectively. Treatment of carcasses with higher bacterial levels tended to show higher reduction. The research demonstrated that the efficacy of physical treatments for decontamination of broiler carcasses was more pronounced for hot water immersion than for cold air exposure. In conclusion, the results shed light on the potential application of these physical treatments in practice to reduce the quantitative load of contaminating pathogens to enhance food safety in the broiler meat production.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Beterams, Kirse, Kreienbrock, Stingl, Bandick and Reich.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beterams</LastName><ForeName>Anja</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Safety, German Federal Institute for Risk Assessment, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kirse</LastName><ForeName>Alina</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biometry, Epidemiology and Information Processing (IBEI), WHO Collaborating Centre for Research and Training for Health at the Human-Animal-Environment Interface, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hanover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kreienbrock</LastName><ForeName>Lothar</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biometry, Epidemiology and Information Processing (IBEI), WHO Collaborating Centre for Research and Training for Health at the Human-Animal-Environment Interface, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Hanover, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stingl</LastName><ForeName>Kerstin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Safety, German Federal Institute for Risk Assessment, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bandick</LastName><ForeName>Niels</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Safety, German Federal Institute for Risk Assessment, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reich</LastName><ForeName>Felix</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Safety, German Federal Institute for Risk Assessment, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101548977</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1664-302X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Campylobacter spp.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PMA qPCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella spp.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">broiler slaughtering process</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hygiene indicators</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sensory analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thermal decontamination methods</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39376704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11457684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2024.1429756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Anderson A., Pietsch K., Zucker R., Mayr A., Muller-Hohe E., Messelhausser U., et al. . (2011). Validation of a duplex real-time PCR for the detection of Salmonella spp. in different food products. Food Anal Method 4, 259–267. doi: 10.1007/s12161-010-9142-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-010-9142-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anonymous . (2008). Commission Regulation (EC) No 543/2008 laying down detailed rules for the application of Council Regulation (EC) No 1234/2007 as regards the marketing standards for poultrymeat, (2008). Available at: https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32008R0543.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anonymous . (2013). Regulation (EU) No 1308/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 17 December 2013 establishing a common organisation of the markets in agricultural products and repealing Council Regulations (EEC) No 922/72, (EEC) No 234/79, (EC) No 1037/2001 and (EC) No 1234/2007. Available at: https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=celex%3A32013R1308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berrang M. E., Meinersmann R. J., Cox N. A., Fedorka-Cray P. J. (2011). Application of chlorine dioxide to lessen bacterial contamination during broiler defeathering. J. Appl. Poult. Res. 20, 33–39. doi: 10.3382/japr.2010-00178</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/japr.2010-00178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beterams A., Püning C., Wyink B., Grosse-Kleimann J., Gölz G., Schönknecht A., et al. . (2024). Status quo: Levels of Campylobacter spp. and hygiene indicators in German slaughterhouses for broiler and turkey. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 414:110610. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2024.110610, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2024.110610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38330527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beterams A., Tolksdorf T., Martin A., Stingl K., Bandick N., Reich F. (2023). Change of Campylobacter, Escherichia coli and Salmonella counts in packaged broiler breast meat stored under modified atmosphere and vacuum conditions at 4 and 10 °C based on cultural and molecular biological quantification. Food Control 145:109337. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109337</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boysen L., Rosenquist H. (2009). Reduction of thermotolerant Campylobacter species on broiler carcasses following physical decontamination at slaughter. J. Food Prot. 72, 497–502. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X-72.3.497, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X-72.3.497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19343936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burfoot D., Hall J., Nicholson K., Holmes K., Hanson C., Handley S., et al. . (2016). Effect of rapid surface cooling on Campylobacter numbers on poultry carcasses. Food Control 70, 293–301. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.05.041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.05.041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaves B. D., Han I. Y., Dawson P. L., Northcutt J. K. (2011). Survival of artificially inoculated Escherichia coli and Salmonella Typhimurium on the surface of raw poultry products subjected to crust freezing. Poult. Sci. 90, 2874–2878. doi: 10.3382/ps.2011-01640, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2011-01640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22080028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corry J. E. L., James S. J., Purnell G., Barbedo-Pinto C. S., Chochois Y., Howell M., et al. . (2007). Surface pasteurisation of chicken carcasses using hot water. J. Food Eng. 79, 913–919. doi: 10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2006.03.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2006.03.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dogan O. B., Anand A., Ortuzar J., Clarke J., Wang B. (2022). A systematic review and meta-analysis of the efficacy of processing stages and interventions for controlling Campylobacter contamination during broiler chicken processing. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. 21, 227–271. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12860, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34730272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duffy L. L., Blackall P. J., Cobbold R. N., Fegan N. (2014). Quantitative effects of in-line operations on Campylobacter and Escherichia coli through two Australian broiler processing plants. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 188, 128–134. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.07.024, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.07.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25104301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (2011). Scientific Opinion on Campylobacter in broiler meat production: control options and performance objectives and/or targets at different stages of the food chain. EFSA J. 9:2105. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2011.2105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2011.2105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (2021). The European Union One Health 2021 Zoonoses Report. EFSA J. 20:7666. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2022.7666, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2022.7666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9745727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36524203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Ministry of Food and Agriculture . (2022). Versorgungsbilanz Fleisch. Available at: https://www.bmel-statistik.de/ernaehrung/versorgungsbilanzen/fleisch.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison D., Corry J. E. L., Tchorzewska M. A., Morris V. K., Hutchison M. L. (2013). Freezing as an intervention to reduce the numbers of campylobacters isolated from chicken livers. Lett. Appl. Microbiol. 57, 206–213. doi: 10.1111/lam.12098, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/lam.12098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23647008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hauge S. J., Bjørkøy S., Holthe J., Røtterud O. J., Skjerve E., Midtsian M., et al. . (2023). Assessment of in-plant decontamination of broiler carcasses by immersion in hot water and lactic acid in Norway. Food Control 152:109873. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.109873</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.109873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hauge S. J., Johannessen G. S., Haverkamp T. H. A., Bjorkoy S., Llarena A. K., Spilsberg B., et al. . (2023). Assessment of poultry process hygiene and bacterial dynamics along two broiler slaughter lines in Norway. Food Control 146:109526. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109526</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haughton P. N., Lyng J., Cronin D., Fanning S., Whyte P. (2012). Effect of crust freezing applied alone and in combination with ultraviolet light on the survival of Campylobacter on raw chicken. Food Microbiol. 32, 147–151. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2012.05.004, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2012.05.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22850386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrmann J., Callens A., Trembley J. (2017). Indirect cryogenic chilling, an effective and proven intervention for Campylobacter reduction on poultry carcasses.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huezo R., Northcutt J. K., Smith D. P., Fletcher D. L., Ingram K. D. (2007). Effect of dry air or immersion chilling on recovery of bacteria from broiler carcasses. J. Food Prot. 70, 1829–1834. doi: 10.4315/0362-028x-70.8.1829</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028x-70.8.1829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17803138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutchison M. L., Harrison D., Tchòrzewska M. A., González-Bodí S., Madden R. H., Corry J. E. L., et al. . (2022). Quantitative Determination of Campylobacter on broilers along 22 United Kingdom processing lines to identify potential process control points and cross-contamination from colonized to uncolonized flocks. J. Food Prot. 85, 1696–1707. doi: 10.4315/jfp-22-204, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/jfp-22-204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36135722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>James C., James S. J., Hannay N., Purnell G., Barbedo-Pinto C., Yaman H., et al. . (2007). Decontamination of poultry carcasses using steam or hot water in combination with rapid cooling, chilling or freezing of carcass surfaces. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 114, 195–203. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2006.09.019, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2006.09.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17140687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy C., Miller J. (2004). A new chilling technique for processing chicken more safely and efficiently. Food Sci. Technol. 18, 30–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kure C. F., Axelsson L., Carlehog M., Mage I., Jensen M. R., Holck A. (2020). The effects of a pilot-scale steam decontamination system on the hygiene and sensory quality of chicken carcasses. Food Control 109:106948. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.106948</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.106948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazou T. P., Gelasakis A. I., Chaintoutis S. C., Iossifidou E. G., Dovas C. I. (2021). Method-dependent implications in foodborne pathogen quantification: The case of Campylobacter coli survival on meat as comparatively assessed by colony count and viability PCR. Front. Microbiol. 12:933. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2021.604933, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.604933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7956984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33732219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Yang H., Swem B. L. (2002). Effect of high-temperature inside-outside spray on survival of Campylobacter jejuni attached to prechill chicken carcasses. Poult. Sci. 81, 1371–1377. doi: 10.1093/ps/81.9.1371, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/81.9.1371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12269619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu T., Marmion M., Ferone M., Wall P., Scannell A. G. M. (2019). Processing and retail strategies to minimize Campylobacter contamination in retail chicken. J Food Proc Pres 43:14251. doi: 10.1111/jfpp.14251</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.14251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKee S.R., Townsend J. C., Bilgili S. F. (2008). Use of a scald additive to reduce levels of Salmonella Typhimurium during poultry processing. Poult. Sci. 87, 1672–1677. doi: 10.3382/ps.2008-00061, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2008-00061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18648065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musavian H. S., Krebs N. H., Nonboe U., Corry J. E. L., Purnell G. (2014). Combined steam and ultrasound treatment of broilers at slaughter: A promising intervention to significantly reduce numbers of naturally occurring campylobacters on carcasses. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 176, 23–28. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.02.001, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.02.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24561390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagel Gravning G. E., Røtterud O. J., Bjørkøy S., Forseth M., Skjerve E., Llarena A. K., et al. . (2021). Comparison of four sampling methods for microbiological quantification on broiler carcasses. Food Control 121:107589. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107589</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Northcutt J. K., Smith D. P., Musgrove M. T., Ingram K. D., Hinton A. (2005). Microbiological impact of spray washing broiler carcasses using different chlorine concentrations and water temperatures. Poult. Sci. 84, 1648–1652. doi: 10.1093/ps/84.10.1648, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/84.10.1648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16335135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacholewicz E., Buhler C., Wulsten I. F., Kraushaar B., Luu H. Q., Iwobi A. N., et al. . (2019). Internal sample process control improves cultivation-independent quantification of thermotolerant Campylobacter. Food Microbiol. 78, 53–61. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2018.09.017, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2018.09.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30497608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacholewicz E., Swart A., Schipper M., Gortemaker B. G., Wagenaar J. A., Havelaar A. H., et al. . (2015). A comparison of fluctuations of Campylobacter and Escherichia coli concentrations on broiler chicken carcasses during processing in two slaughterhouses. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 205, 119–127. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2015.04.006, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2015.04.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25950748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purnell G., Mattick K., Humphrey T. (2004). The use of 'hot wash' treatments to reduce the number of pathogenic and spoilage bacteria on raw retail poultry. J. Food Eng. 62, 29–36. doi: 10.1016/s0260-8774(03)00168-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0260-8774(03)00168-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sampers I., Habib I., De Zutter L., Dumoulin A., Uyttendaele M. (2010). Survival of Campylobacter spp. in poultry meat preparations subjected to freezing, refrigeration, minor salt concentration, and heat treatment. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 137, 147–153. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2009.11.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2009.11.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20006911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selgas D., Luisa Marín M., Pin C., Casas C. (1993). Attachment of bacteria to meat surfaces: A review. Meat Sci. 34, 265–273. doi: 10.1016/0309-1740(93)90076-t, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0309-1740(93)90076-t</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22060736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shung C. C., Hsin K. Y., Tan F. J., Chen S. E. (2022). Effects of hard and soft scalding on defeathering and carcass quality of different breeds of chickens. Animals (Basel) 12:23145. doi: 10.3390/ani12223145, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani12223145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9686902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36428373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith D. P. (2010). Sampling method and location affect recovery of coliforms and Escherichia coli from broiler carcasses. Poult. Sci. 89, 169–172. doi: 10.3382/ps.2008-00414, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.2008-00414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20008815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stingl K., Heise J., Thieck M., Wulsten I. F., Pacholewicz E., Iwobi A. N., et al. . (2021). Challenging the “gold standard” of colony-forming units - Validation of a multiplex real-time PCR for quantification of viable Campylobacter spp. in meat rinses. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 359:417. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2021.109417, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2021.109417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34624596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomson J. E., Cox N. A., Whitehead W. K., Mercuri A. J. (1974). Effect of hot spray washing on broiler carcass quality. Poult. Sci. 53, 946–952. doi: 10.3382/ps.0530946</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps.0530946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varzakas T., Feddern V. (2016). “Poultry Manufacturing Technologies” in Handbook of Food Processing: Food Safety, Quality, and Manufacturing Processes. eds. Varzakas T., Tzia C. (Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press-Taylor and Francis Group; ), 487–514.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whyte P., McGill K., Collins J. D. (2003). An assessment of steam pasteurization and hot water immersion treatments for the microbiological decontamination of broiler carcasses. Food Microbiol. 20, 111–117. doi: 10.1016/S0740-0020(02)00084-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0740-0020(02)00084-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wulsten I. F., Thieck M., Göhler A., Schuh E., Stingl K. (2022). Chicken skin decontamination of thermotolerant Campylobacter spp. and hygiene indicator Escherichia coli assessed by viability real-time PCR. Pathogens 11:706. doi: 10.3390/pathogens11060706</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens11060706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9230925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35745559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>