<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39370525</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1757-4749</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Gut pathogens</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Gut Pathog</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Overview of pathogenic Escherichia coli, with a focus on Shiga toxin-producing serotypes, global outbreaks (1982-2024) and food safety criteria.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>57</StartPage><MedlinePgn>57</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">57</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s13099-024-00641-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Classification of pathogenic E. coli has been focused either in mammalian host or infection site, which offers limited resolution. This review presents a comprehensive framework for classifying all E. coli branches within a single, unifying figure. This approach integrates established methods based on virulence factors, serotypes and clinical syndromes, offering a more nuanced and informative perspective on E. coli pathogenicity. The presence of the LEE island in pathogenic E. coli is a key genetic marker differentiating EHEC from STEC strains. The coexistence of stx and eae genes within the bacterial genome is a primary characteristic used to distinguish STEC from other pathogenic E. coli strains. The presence of the inv plasmid, Afa/Dr adhesins, CFA-CS-LT-ST and EAST1 are key distinguishing features for identifying pathogenic E. coli strains belonging to EIEC, DAEC, ETEC and EAEC pathotypes respectively. Food microbiological criteria differentiate pathogenic E. coli in food matrices. 'Zero-tolerance' applies to most ready-to-eat (RTE) foods due to high illness risk. Non-RTE foods' roles may allow limited E. coli presence, which expose consumers to potential risk; particularly from the concerning Shiga toxin-producing E. coli (STEC) strains, which can lead to life-threatening complications in humans, including haemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) and even death in susceptible individuals. These findings suggest that decision-makers should consider incorporating the separate detection of STEC serotypes into food microbiological criteria, in addition to existing enumeration methods. Contamination of STEC is mainly linked to food consumption, therefore, outbreaks of E. coli STEC has been reviewed here and showed a link also to water as a potential contamination route. Since their discovery in 1982, over 39,787 STEC cases associated with 1,343 outbreaks have been documented. The majority of these outbreaks occurred in the Americas, followed by Europe, Asia and Africa. The most common serotypes identified among the outbreaks were O157, the 'Big Six' (O26, O45, O103, O111, O121, and O145), and other serotypes such as O55, O80, O101, O104, O116, O165, O174 and O183. This review provides valuable insights into the most prevalent serotypes implicated in STEC outbreaks and identifies gaps in microbiological criteria, particularly for E. coli non-O157 and non-Big Six serotypes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Alhadlaq</LastName><ForeName>Meshari Ahmed</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1768-0976</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. MAHadlaq@sfda.gov.sa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Aljurayyad</LastName><ForeName>Othman I</ForeName><Initials>OI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Botany and Microbiology Department, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almansour</LastName><ForeName>Ayidh</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Akeel</LastName><ForeName>Saleh I</ForeName><Initials>SI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alzahrani</LastName><ForeName>Khaloud O</ForeName><Initials>KO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alsalman</LastName><ForeName>Shahad A</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yahya</LastName><ForeName>Reham</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Infection and Microbiology Basic Sciences Department, King Saudi Bin Abdulaziz University for Health Sciences, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>King Abdullah International Medical Research Center, P.O. Box 3661, 11481, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Hindi</LastName><ForeName>Rashad R</ForeName><Initials>RR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hakami</LastName><ForeName>Mohammed Ageeli</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory Sciences, Shaqra University, Shaqra, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alshahrani</LastName><ForeName>Saleh D</ForeName><Initials>SD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Department, Ministry of Interior, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alhumeed</LastName><ForeName>Naif A</ForeName><Initials>NA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Deputyship for Research &amp; Innovation, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Moneea</LastName><ForeName>Abdulaziz M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Seghayer</LastName><ForeName>Mazen S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>AlHarbi</LastName><ForeName>Abdulmohsen L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Reshoodi</LastName><ForeName>Fahad M</ForeName><Initials>FM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alajel</LastName><ForeName>Suliman</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saudi Food and Drug Authority, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Gut Pathog</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101474263</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1757-4749</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Escherichia coli</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Big Six</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food poisoning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">O157</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Outbreaks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SFDA and Microbiological Criteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">STEC</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39370525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13099-024-00641-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s13099-024-00641-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11457481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Gomes TA, Elias WP, Scaletsky IC, Guth BE, Rodrigues JF, Piazza RM, et al. Diarrheagenic Escherichia coli. Braz J Microbiol. 2016;47(1):3–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5156508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27866935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hacker J, Blum-Oehler G. In appreciation of Theodor Escherich. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2007;5(12):902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaper JB, Nataro JP, Mobley HLT. Pathogenic Escherichia coli. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2004;2(2):123–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15040260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewers C, Janßen T, Wieler LH. Avian pathogenic Escherichia coli (APEC). Berl Munch Tierarztl Wochenschr. 2003;116(9–10):381–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14526468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campos FC, Castilho IG, Rossi BF, Bonsaglia ÉCR, Dantas STA, Dias RCB, et al. Genetic and antimicrobial resistance profiles of mammary pathogenic E. coli (MPEC) isolates from bovine clinical mastitis. Pathogens. 2022;11(12):1435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9781227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36558768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swangchan-Uthai T. Defence mechanism in bovine endometrium: current concepts. Board Rev Ed. 2014;1(44):43–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govindarajan DK, Viswalingam N, Meganathan Y, Kandaswamy K. Adherence patterns of Escherichia coli in the intestine and its role in pathogenesis. Med Microecol. 2020;5: 100025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sora VM, Meroni G, Martino PA, Soggiu A, Bonizzi L, Zecconi A. Extraintestinal pathogenic Escherichia coli: virulence factors and antibiotic resistance. Pathogens. 2021;10(11):1355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8618662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34832511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarowska J, Futoma-Koloch B, Jama-Kmiecik A, Frej-Madrzak M, Ksiazczyk M, Bugla-Ploskonska G, et al. Virulence factors, prevalence and potential transmission of extraintestinal pathogenic Escherichia coli isolated from different sources: recent reports. Gut Pathog. 2019;11(1):1–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6383261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30828388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jokiranta TS. HUS and atypical HUS. Blood, J Am Soc Hematol. 2017;129(21):2847–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5445567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28416508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maltby R, Leatham-Jensen MP, Gibson T, Cohen PS, Conway T. Nutritional basis for colonization resistance by human commensal Escherichia coli strains HS and Nissle 1917 against E. coli O157: H7 in the mouse intestine. PLoS ONE. 2013;8(1):5395–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3547972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23349773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Escribano-Vazquez U, Verstraeten S, Martin R, Chain F, Langella P, Thomas M, et al. The commensal Escherichia coli CEC15 reinforces intestinal defences in gnotobiotic mice and is protective in a chronic colitis mouse model. Sci Rep. 2019;9(1):1–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6685975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31391483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Berezo T, Pujo J, Martin P, Le Faouder P, Galano JM, Guy A, et al. Identification of an analgesic lipopeptide produced by the probiotic Escherichia coli strain Nissle 1917. Nat Commun. 2017;8(1):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5670229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29101366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhnert P, Nicolet J, Frey J. Rapid and accurate identification of Escherichia coli K-12 strains. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1995;61(11):4135–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC167724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8526531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alharbi MG, Al-Hindi RR, Esmael A, Alotibi IA, Azhari SA, Alseghayer MS, et al. The “big six”: hidden emerging foodborne bacterial pathogens. Trop Med Infect Dis. 2022;7(11):356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9693546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36355898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelhalim KA, Uzel A, Ünal NG. Virulence determinants and genetic diversity of adherent-invasive Escherichia coli (AIEC) strains isolated from patients with Crohn’s disease. Microb Pathog. 2020;145: 104233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32360521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perna A, Hay E, Contieri M, De Luca A, Guerra G, Lucariello A. Adherent-invasive Escherichia coli (AIEC): cause or consequence of inflammation, dysbiosis, and rupture of cellular joints in patients with IBD? J Cell Physiol. 2020;235(6):5041–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31898324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viladomiu M, Metz ML, Lima SF, Jin WB, Chou L, Guo CJ, et al. Adherent-invasive E. coli metabolism of propanediol in Crohn’s disease regulates phagocytes to drive intestinal inflammation. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29(4):607–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8049981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33539767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Köhler CD, Dobrindt U. What defines extraintestinal pathogenic Escherichia coli? Int J Med Microbiol. 2011;301(8):642–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21982038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarker MS. Identification of faecal carriage multi drug resistance genes in E. coli isolated from captive deer from safari parks and zoo in Bangladesh. Chittagong Veterinary and Animal Sciences University. 2016. https://www.researchgate.net/profile/md-sarker-31/publication/333867064_identification_of_faecal_carriage_multi_drug_resistance_genes_in_e_coli_isolated_from_captive_deer_from_safari_parks_and_zoo_in_bangladesh/links/5d09e13c458515ea1a70b51e/identification.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donnenberg MS. Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli. In: Blaser MJ, Smith PD, Ravdin JI, Greenberg HB, Guerrant RL, editors. Infections of the Gastrointestinal Tract, Chapter 40. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2002. p. 595–612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichhorn I, Heidemanns K, Semmler T, Kinnemann B, Mellmann A, Harmsen D, et al. Highly virulent non-O157 enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC) serotypes reflect similar phylogenetic lineages, providing new insights into the evolution of EHEC. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2015;81(20):7041–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4579429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26231647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nataro JP, Kaper JB. Diarrheagenic Escherichia coli. Clin Microbiol Rev. 1998;11(1):142–201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC121379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9457432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahl E, Vold L, Lindstedt BA, Bruheim T, Afset JE. Investigation of an Escherichia coli O145 outbreak in a child day-care centre-extensive sampling and characterization of eae-and stx 1-positive E. coli yields epidemiological and socioeconomic insight. BMC Infect Dis. 2011;11(1):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3188501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21902833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Mentzer A, Connor TR, Wieler LH, Semmler T, Iguchi A, Thomson NR, et al. Identification of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) clades with long-term global distribution. Nat Genet. 2014;46(12):1321–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25383970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rana T, Hasan RJ, Nowicki S, Venkatarajan MS, Singh R, Urvil PT, et al. Complement protective epitopes and CD55–microtubule complexes facilitate the invasion and intracellular persistence of uropathogenic Escherichia coli. J Infect Dis. 2014;209(7):1066–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3975163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24259524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakache R, Levene C, Sela R, Kaufman S, Shapira Z. Dra (Cromer-related blood group antigen)-incompatible renal transplantation. Vox Sang. 1998;74(2):106–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9501409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan X, Sack DA, Zhang W. Genetic fusions of a CFA/I/II/IV MEFA (multiepitope fusion antigen) and a toxoid fusion of heat-stable toxin (STa) and heat-labile toxin (LT) of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) retain broad anti-CFA and antitoxin antigenicity. PLoS ONE. 2015;10(3): e0121623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4372207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25803825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yassine I. Population structure analysis and laboratory monitoring of Shigella using whole genome sequencing. Université Libanaise: Université Paris Cité; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt JM. Shiga toxin–producing Escherichia coli (STEC). Clin Lab Med. 2010;30(1):21–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7126671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20513540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarr CL, Large TM, Moeller CL, Lacher DW, Tarr PI, Acheson DW, et al. Molecular characterization of a serotype O121: H19 clone, a distinct Shiga toxin-producing clone of pathogenic Escherichia coli. Infect Immun. 2002;70(12):6853–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC133070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12438362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mora A, Viso S, López C, Alonso MP, García-Garrote F, Dabhi G, et al. Poultry as reservoir for extraintestinal pathogenic Escherichia coli O45: K1: H7-B2-ST95 in humans. Vet Microbiol. 2013;167(3–4):506–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24008093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milon A, Esslinger J, Camguilhem R. Oral vaccination of weaned rabbits against enteropathogenic Escherichia coli-like E. coli O103 infection: use of heterologous strains harboring lipopolysaccharide or adhesin of pathogenic strains. Infect Immun. 1992;60(7):2702–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC257224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1351880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mariani-Kurkdjian P, Denamur E, Milon A, Picard B, Cave H, Lambert-Zechovsky N, et al. Identification of a clone of Escherichia coli O103: H2 as a potential agent of hemolytic-uremic syndrome in France. J Clin Microbiol. 1993;31(2):296–301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC262753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8432815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miko A, Pries K, Haby S, Steege K, Albrecht N, Krause G, et al. Assessment of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli isolates from wildlife meat as potential pathogens for humans. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2009;75(20):6462–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2765146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19700552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor EV, Nguyen TA, Machesky KD, Koch E, Sotir MJ, Bohm SR, et al. Multistate outbreak of Escherichia coli O145 infections associated with romaine lettuce consumption, 2010. J Food Prot. 2013;76(6):939–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23726187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dulguer MV, Fabbricotti SH, Bando SY, Moreira-Filho CA, Fagundes-Neto U, Scaletsky ICA. Atypical enteropathogenic Escherichia coli strains: phenotypic and genetic profiling reveals a strong association between enteroaggregative E. coli heat-stable enterotoxin and diarrhea. J Infect Dis. 2003;188(11):1685–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14639540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baazize-Ammi D, Gassem O, Derrar F, Izri K, Brahim-Errahmani M, Gagnon J, et al. Prevalence of asymptomatic carriers of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) in dairy cattle farms in the governorate of Blida (Algeria). J Vet Res. 2015;59(1):23–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sapountzis P, Segura A, Desvaux M, Forano E. An overview of the elusive passenger in the gastrointestinal tract of cattle: the Shiga toxin producing Escherichia coli. Microorganisms. 2020;8(6):877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7355788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32531983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhadlaq MA, Mujallad MI, Alajel SMI. Detection of Escherichia coli O157: H7 in imported meat products from Saudi Arabian ports in 2017. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):4222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10015049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36918659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith BA, Fazil A, Lammerding AM. A risk assessment model for Escherichia coli O157: H7 in ground beef and beef cuts in Canada: evaluating the effects of interventions. Food Control. 2013;29(2):364–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Augustin JC, Kooh P, Bayeux T, Guillier L, Meyer T, Jourdan-Da Silva N, et al. Contribution of foods and poor food-handling practices to the burden of foodborne infectious diseases in France. Foods. 2020;9(11):1644.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7697675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33187291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jay JM, Loessner MJ, Golden DA. Modern food microbiology. Berlin: Springer; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jores J, Rumer L, Wieler LH. Impact of the locus of enterocyte effacement pathogenicity island on the evolution of pathogenic Escherichia coli. Int J Med Microbiol. 2004;294(2–3):103–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15493820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pakbin B, Brück WM, Rossen JWA. Virulence factors of enteric pathogenic Escherichia coli: a review. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(18):9922.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8468683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34576083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kolenda R, Burdukiewicz M, Schierack P. A systematic review and meta-analysis of the epidemiology of pathogenic Escherichia coli of calves and the role of calves as reservoirs for human pathogenic E. coli. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2015;5:23–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4357325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25815276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasquali F, Palma F, Trevisani M, Parisi A, Lucchi A, De Cesare A, et al. Whole genome sequencing based typing and characterisation of Shiga-toxin producing Escherichia coli strains belonging to O157 and O26 serotypes and isolated in dairy farms. Ital J food Saf. 2018;7(4):7673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6379698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30854339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lautenbach E, Malani PN, Woeltje KF, Han JH, Shuman EK, Marschall J. Practical healthcare epidemiology. Cambridge University Press. 2018. https://shahealthcare.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Practical-Healthcare-Epidemiology.pdf#page=134</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pexara A, Angelidis AS, Govaris A. Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) food-borne outbreaks. J Hell Vet Med Soc. 2012;63(1):45–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson RP, Clarke RC, Wilson JB, Read SC, Rahn K, Renwick SA, et al. Growing concerns and recent outbreaks involving non-O157: H7 serotypes of verotoxigenic Escherichia coli. J Food Prot. 1996;59(10):1112–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31195470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ota M, Kamigaki T, Mimura S, Nakashima K, Ogami T. An enterohaemorrhagic Escherichia coli outbreak spread through the environment at an institute for people with intellectual disabilities in Japan in 2005 West Pacific Surveill response. J WPSAR. 2019;10(2):14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6831959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31720050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gati NS, Temme IJ, Middendorf-Bauchart B, Kehl A, Dobrindt U, Mellmann A. Comparative phenotypic characterization of hybrid Shiga toxin-producing/uropathogenic Escherichia coli, canonical uropathogenic and Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli. Int J Med Microbiol. 2021;311(7): 151533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34425494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kintz E, Byrne L, Jenkins C, McCarthy N, Vivancos R, Hunter P. Outbreaks of Shiga toxin–producing Escherichia coli linked to sprouted seeds, salad, and leafy greens: a systematic review. J Food Prot. 2019;82(11):1950–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31638410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rangel JM, Sparling PH, Crowe C, Griffin PM, Swerdlow DL. Epidemiology of Escherichia coli O157: H7 outbreaks, United States, 1982–2002. Emerg Infect Dis. 2005;11(4):603.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3320345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15829201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heiman KE, Mody RK, Johnson SD, Griffin PM, Gould LH. Escherichia coli O157 outbreaks in the United States, 2003–2012. Emerg Infect Dis. 2015;21(8):1293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4517704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26197993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tack DM, Kisselburgh HM, Richardson LC, Geissler A, Griffin PM, Payne DC, et al. Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli outbreaks in the United States, 2010–2017. Microorganisms. 2021;9(7):1529.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8307841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34361964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks JT, Sowers EG, Wells JG, Greene KD, Griffin PM, Hoekstra RM, et al. Non-O157 Shiga toxin–producing Escherichia coli infections in the United States, 1983–2002. J Infect Dis. 2005;192(8):1422–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16170761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luna-Gierke RE, Griffin PM, Gould LH, Herman K, Bopp CA, Strockbine N, et al. Outbreaks of non-O157 Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli infection: USA. Epidemiol Infect. 2014;142(11):2270–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9151257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24398154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waltenburg MA, Schwensohn C, Madad A, Seelman SL, Peralta V, Koske SE, et al. Two multistate outbreaks of a reoccurring Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli strain associated with romaine lettuce: USA, 2018–2019. Epidemiol Infect. 2022;150: e16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8796143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35060456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. Shiga Toxin–Producing Escherichia coli O157:H7 Illness Outbreak Associated with Untreated, Pressurized, Municipal Irrigation Water—Utah, 2023 (government report). 2024. https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/73/wr/mm7318a1.htm</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11095944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38722798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>VDH. Virginia Department of Health Provides Update about the Lake Anna Area Outbreak Associated with Memorial Day Weekend (government report). 2024. https://www.vdh.virginia.gov/blog/2024/06/14/virginia-department-of-health-provides-update-about-the-lake-anna-area-outbreak-associated-with-memorial-day-weekend/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King County. Shiga toxin-producing E. coli O157:H7 infections associated with PCC Community Markets—West Seattle Co-op in Seattle. 2024; https://kingcounty.gov/en/dept/dph/health-safety/disease-illness/foodborne-illness-outbreaks/2024-march-21-pcc</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coulombe G, Catford A, Martinez-Perez A, Buenaventura E. Outbreaks of Escherichia coli O157: H7 infections linked to Romaine lettuce in Canada from 2008 to 2018: an analysis of food safety context. J Food Prot. 2020;83(8):1444–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32297933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marshall KE, Hexemer A, Seelman SL, Fatica MK, Blessington T, Hajmeer M, et al. Lessons learned from a decade of investigations of Shiga toxin–producing Escherichia coli outbreaks linked to leafy greens, United States and Canada. Emerg Infect Dis. 2020;26(10):2319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7510726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32946367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyd E, Trmcic A, Taylor M, Shyng S, Hasselback P, Man S, et al. Foodborne and animal contact disease outbreaks: Escherichia coli O121 outbreak associated with raw milk Gouda-like cheese in British Columbia, Canada, 2018. Canada Commun Dis Rep. 2021;47(2):11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7972179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33746616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morton V. Notes from the field: an outbreak of Shiga toxin–producing Escherichia coli O121 infections associated with flour—Canada, 2016–2017. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017;66(26):705–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5726237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28683061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashinze P, Banerjee S, Ademola AS, Aji N, Abdul-Rahman T, Wireko AA. Outbreak investigation and implications: assessing the severity of E. coli outbreak in Alberta, pediatric hospitalizations, and the rise of hemolytic uremic syndrome. IJS Glob Heal. 2024;7(1):e0399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivas M, Chinen I, Miliwebsky E, Galli L, Repetto HA, Masana M. Epidemiology of argentinean Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli. Popul Genet Bact a Tribut to Thomas S Whittam. 2011. 10.1128/9781555817114.ch8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva I, Andrade S, Almeida S, Barbosa K, Bispo M, Silva J, et al. E. coli O157: H7 outbreak and hemolytic uremic syndrome in a day care center in Brazil. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;101:137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fruth A, Prager R, Tietze E, Rabsch W, Flieger A. Molecular epidemiological view on Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli causing human disease in Germany: diversity, prevalence, and outbreaks. Int J Med Microbiol. 2015;305(7):697–704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26372529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braeye T, Denayer S, De Rauw K, Forier A, Verluyten J, Fourie L, et al. Lessons learned from a textbook outbreak: EHEC-O157: H7 infections associated with the consumption of raw meat products, June 2012, Limburg. Belgium Arch public Heal. 2014;72:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4373035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25810911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delmas Y, Vendrely B, Clouzeau B, Bachir H, Bui HN, Lacraz A, et al. Outbreak of Escherichia coli O104: H4 haemolytic uraemic syndrome in France: outcome with eculizumab. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2014;29(3):565–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3938298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24293658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jourdan-da Silva N, Watrin M, Weill FX, King LA, Gouali M, Mailles A, et al. Outbreak of haemolytic uraemic syndrome due to Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O104: H4 among French tourists returning from Turkey, September 2011. Eurosurveillance. 2012;17(4):20065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22297137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minary K, Tanne C, Kwon T, Faudeux C, Clavé S, Langevin L, et al. Outbreak of hemolytic uremic syndrome with unusually severe clinical presentation caused by Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O26: H11 in France. Arch pédiatrie. 2022;29(6):448–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35662540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onishchenko GG, Dyatlov IA, Svetoch EA, Volozhantsev NV, Bannov VA, Kartsev NN, et al. Molecular-genetic characterization of shiga-toxin producing Escherichia coli isolated during a food-borne outbreak in St. Petersburg in 2013. Ann Russ Acad Med Sci. 2015;70(1):70–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26027274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Severi E, Vial F, Peron E, Mardh O, Niskanen T, Takkinen J. Community-wide outbreaks of haemolytic uraemic syndrome associated with Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O26 in Italy and Romania: a new challenge for the European Union. Eurosurveillance. 2016;21(49):30420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5291129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27983509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinnula S, Hemminki K, Kotilainen H, Ruotsalainen E, Tarkka E, Salmenlinna S, et al. Outbreak of multiple strains of non-O157 Shiga toxin-producing and enteropathogenic Escherichia coli associated with rocket salad, Finland, autumn 2016. Eurosurveillance. 2018;23(35):1700666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6124187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30180926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saxena T, Kaushik P, Mohan MK. Prevalence of E. coli O157: H7 in water sources: an overview on associated diseases, outbreaks and detection methods. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2015;82(3):249–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26050932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawyer C, Vishram B, Jenkins C, Jorgensen F, Byrne L, Mikhail AFW, et al. Epidemiological investigation of recurrent outbreaks of haemolytic uraemic syndrome caused by Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli serotype O55: H7 in England, 2014–2018. Epidemiol Infect. 2021;149: e108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8161408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33866980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FSN. Uncommon E. coli outbreak in UK linked to beef (food report). 2024. https://www.foodsafetynews.com/2024/06/uncommon-e-coli-outbreak-in-uk-linked-to-beef/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greig DR, Quinn OI, Rodwell EV, Olonade I, Swift C, Douglas A, et al. Genomic analysis of an outbreak of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O183: H18 in the United Kingdom, 2023. Microb Genomics. 2024;10(5):1243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11165631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38771013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GOV.UK. E. coli advice issued amid rise in cases (government report). 2024. https://www.gov.uk/government/news/e-coli-advice-issued-amid-rise-in-cases</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mannix M, Whyte D, McNamara E, O’Connell N, Fitzgerald R, Mahony M, et al. Large outbreak of E. coli O157 in 2005, Ireland. Eurosurveillance. 2007;12(2):5–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akashi S, Joh K, Mori T, Tsuji A, Ito H, Hoshi H, et al. A severe outbreak of haemorrhagic colitis and haemolytic uraemic syndrome associated with Escherichia coli 0157: H7 in Japan. Eur J Pediatr. 1994;153(9):650–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7957423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michino H, Araki K, Minami S, Takaya S, Sakai N, Miyazaki M, et al. Massive outbreak of Escherichia coli O157: H7 infection in schoolchildren in Sakai City, Japan, associated with consumption of white radish sprouts. Am J Epidemiol. 1999;150(8):787–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10522649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang SC, Lin CH, Aljuffali IA, Fang JY. Current pathogenic Escherichia coli foodborne outbreak cases and therapy development. Arch Microbiol. 2017;199:811–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28597303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong Y, Wang P, Lan R, Ye C, Wang H, Ren J, et al. A novel Escherichia coli O157: H7 clone causing a major hemolytic uremic syndrome outbreak in China. PLoS ONE. 2012;7(4): e36144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3338595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22558360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wani SA, Bhat MA, Samanta I, Buchh AS, Nishikawa Y. Escherichia coli 016 associated with an outbreak of calf diarrhoea. Vet Rec. 2004;154(16):506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15130058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pouladfar G, Arasteh-Far A, Amin-Shahidi M, Firoozian N, Pourabbas B, Moghadami M, et al. Characterization of Diarrheagenic E. coli causing a diarrheal outbreak in the south of Iran, Summer 2015. Asian Pacific J Trop Dis. 2017;7(8):491–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vally H, Hall G, Dyda A, Raupach J, Knope K, Combs B, et al. Epidemiology of Shiga toxin producing Escherichia coli in Australia, 2000–2010. BMC Public Health. 2012;12:1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3398300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22264221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effler E, Isaäcson M, Arntzen L, Heenan R, Canter P, Barrett T, et al. Factors contributing to the emergence of Escherichia coli O157 in Africa. Emerg Infect Dis. 2001;7(5):812.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2631888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11747693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Germani Y, Cunin P, Tedjouka E, Ncharre CB, Morvan J, Martin P. Enterohaemorrhagic Escherichia coli in Ngoila (Cameroon) during an outbreak of bloody diarrhoea. Lancet. 1998;352(9128):625–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9746033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleynhans J, Kalule B, Lawrence C, McCulloch M, Coetzee A, Nourse P, et al. Outbreak report: cluster of haemolytic uraemic syndrome cases among children, Western Cape Province, South Africa, February 2017. GERMS-SA Annu Surveill Rep Lab Invasive Meningococcal, Pneumococcal Haemophilus Influ Dis South Africa, 2016;42–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ECDC. STEC infection, Annual Epidemiological Report for 2022 (surveillance report). 2022. https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/sites/default/files/documents/STEC_AER_2022_Report.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanier WA, Leeper MM, Smith KE, Tillman GE, Holt KG, Gerner-Smidt P. Pulsed-field gel electrophoresis subtypes of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O157 isolated from ground beef and humans, United States, 2001–2006. Foodborne Pathog Dis. 2009;6(9):1075–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19630512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez JL. General principles of antibiotic resistance in bacteria. Drug Discov Today Technol. 2014;11:33–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24847651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakoullis L, Papachristodoulou E, Chra P, Panos G. Shiga toxin-induced haemolytic uraemic syndrome and the role of antibiotics: a global overview. J Infect. 2019;79(2):75–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31150744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schroeder CM, Zhao C, DebRoy C, Torcolini J, Zhao S, White DG, et al. Antimicrobial resistance of Escherichia coli O157 isolated from humans, cattle, swine, and food. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2002;68(2):576–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC126736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11823193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elabbasy MT, Hussein MA, Algahtani FD, El-Rahman A, Ghada I, Morshdy AE, et al. MALDI-TOF MS based typing for rapid screening of multiple antibiotic resistance E. coli and virulent non-O157 shiga toxin-producing E. coli isolated from the slaughterhouse settings and beef carcasses. Foods. 2021;10(4):820.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8069270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33920071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Ajmi D, Rahman S, Banu S. Occurrence, virulence genes, and antimicrobial profiles of Escherichia coli O157 isolated from ruminants slaughtered in Al Ain, United Arab Emirates. BMC Microbiol. 2020;20(1):1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7364618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32677884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>i Sala RMP, de Balabarca VC, Etoundi JM, Odame-Darkwah J, Oppong-Otoo J, Hinson DCT, et al. Establishment of good hygiene practice-based microbiological criteria in food industries: guidelines using an example for meat preparations. Food Control. 2015;58:7–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motarjemi Y, Moy G, Todd ECD. Encyclopedia of food safety, vol. 1. London: Elsevier; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission Regulation. Commission Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 of 15 November 2005 on microbiological criteria for foodstuffs. 2005. https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/ALL/?uri=CELEX%3A32005R2073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GSO. GSO 1016/2015 (E) Microbiological criteria for foodstuffs. 2015. https://www.gso.org.sa/store/standards/GSO:693280/GSO1016:2015?lang=en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food Standards Australia New Zealand. Compendium of Microbiological Criteria for Food. 2022. https://www.foodstandards.gov.au/publications/Compendium-of-Microbiological-Criteria-for-Food</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Protection Agency. Guidelines for Assessing the Microbiological Safety of Ready-to-Eat Foods Placed on the Market. 2009. https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/5a7efde0e5274a2e8ab497a4/Guidelines_for_assessing_the_microbiological_safety_of_ready-to-eat_foods_on_the_market.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Food Science and Technology. Handbook of Microbiological Criteria for Foods. 2020. https://www.ifst.org/resources-policy/publications/handbook-microbiological-criteria-foods</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Department of Agriculture. Meat and Poultry Hazards and Controls Guide. 2018. https://www.fsis.usda.gov/sites/default/files/import/Meat_and_Poultry_Hazards_Controls_Guide_10042005.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HACCP. HACCP Model for Raw Ground Beef (Raw Non-Intact). 2021. https://www.fsis.usda.gov/guidelines/2021-0003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HACCP. HACCP Model for Raw Intact Beef. 2021. https://www.fsis.usda.gov/guidelines/2021-0015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HACCP. HACCP Model for Raw, Non-Intact Turkey. 2021. https://www.fsis.usda.gov/guidelines/2021-0012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HACCP. HACCP Model for Raw Non-Intact Fresh Ground Pork Sausage Patties. 2020. https://www.fsis.usda.gov/guidelines/2020-0010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada. Health Canada’s Guidance Document on E. coli O157:H7 and E. coli O157:NM in Raw Beef. 2014. https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/food-nutrition/legislation-guidelines/guidance-documents/guidance-document-coli-0157-coli-0157-beef-2014.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada. Microbial Guidelines for Ready-to-Eat Foods – A Guide for the Conveyance Industry and Environmental Health Officers (EHO). 2010. https://publications.gc.ca/collections/collection_2014/sc-hc/H164-167-2013-eng.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada. Interim guidelines for the control of verotoxinogenic Escherichia coli including E. coli O157:H7 in ready to eat fermented sausages containing beef or a beef product as an ingredient. 2000. https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/food-nutrition/legislation-guidelines/guidance-documents/interim-guidelines-control-verotoxinogenic-escherichia-coli-including-colio157-fermented-sausages-beef-product-ingredient.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada. Guidance on Mandatory Labelling for Mechanically Tenderized Beef. 2014. https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/food-nutrition/legislation-guidelines/guidance-documents/guidance-mandatory-labelling-mechanically-tenderized-beef.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada. Bacteriological guidelines for fish and fish products (end product). 2019. https://inspection.canada.ca/food-safety-for-industry/food-safety-standards-guidelines/bacteriological-guidelines/eng/1558757049068/1558757132060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gov.br. Padrões microbiológicos para alimentos, com exceção dos alimentos comercialmente estéreis. 2022. https://in.gov.br/en/web/dou/-/instrucao-normativa-in-n-161-de-1-de-julho-de-2022-413366880</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ANVISA. Agência Nacional de Vigilância Sanitária. 2019. https://bvsms.saude.gov.br/bvs/saudelegis/anvisa/2019/IN_60_2019_COMP.pdf</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3129940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21808881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sindusfarma. Estabelece os padrões microbiológicos dos alimentos. 2022. https://sindusfarma.org.br/uploads/files/6c61-jessica-neto/boletins/file-Copy3.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food Standards Scotland. Meat Industry Guide. 2017. (Chapter 13 Microbiological Criteria). https://www.foodstandards.gov.scot/downloads/MIG_-_Chapter_13.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FSAI. Guidelines for the Interpretation of Results of Microbiological Testing of Ready-to-Eat Foods Placed on the Market. 2021. https://www.fsai.ie/getmedia/74524294-d92c-4471-9d90-9633d1915c35/guidance-note-3-guidelines-for-the-interpretation-of-results-of-microbiological-testing-of-ready-to-eat-foods-placed-on-the-market-4.pdf?ext=.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Council NR. Scientific criteria to ensure safe food. National Academies Press. 2003. https://nap.nationalacademies.org/catalog/10690/scientific-criteria-to-ensure-safe-food</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25057659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarim Ve Orman Bakanliği. Regulation on turkish food codex microbiological criteria. 2011. https://www.tarimorman.gov.tr/Belgeler/ENG/Legislation/regulation_microbiological_criteria.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FSSAI. General Guidelines on Sampling for Microbiological Analysis. 2021. https://fssai.gov.in/upload/uploadfiles/files/Notice_Comments_Guidelines_Sampling_Microbiology_14_10_2021.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA. Guidelines on the Microbiological Requirements and Assessment of Certain Prepackaged Processed Food Products, FDA Circular No.2022-012. 2022. https://www.fda.gov.ph/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/FDA-Circular-No.2022-12-2.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA. Microbiological criteria for processed foods. 2016. https://www.mpi.govt.nz/dmsdocument/33376/direct</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thai agricultural standard. Safety requirements for agricultural commodity and food. 2005. https://www.acfs.go.th/standard/download/eng/Safety.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Health and Family Planning Commission. National Food Safety Standard Pathogen Limits for Food (GB 29921-2013). 2013. https://www.dgav.pt/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/GB_29921_TABLE1.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank Group. Comparison of Microbiological Criteria in Food Products in the EU and China. 2017. https://documents1.worldbank.org/curated/en/505991513161481672/pdf/WP-ChEuExpEngfinal-PUBLIC.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centre for Food Safety. Microbiological Guidelines for Food. 2014. https://www.cfs.gov.hk/english/food_leg/files/food_leg_Microbiological_Guidelines_for_Food_e.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitsubishi Research Institute. Survey on frozen food standards GB19295. 2003. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/shingi/2006/05/dl/s0522-5l.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singapore Food Agency. Consultation on draft food (amendment no. Y) regulations 2023 (proposed microbiological standards for non-ready-to-eat (non-RTE) food). 2023. https://www.sfa.gov.sg/docs/default-source/default-document-library/public-consultation-non-rte-micro-std.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singapore Food Agency. Sale of food act (chapter 283, section 56(1)) food regulations. 2005. https://www.sfa.gov.sg/docs/default-source/default-document-library/food-regulationsaaf1a5e31cf84465ac2ab014f712d281.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singapore Food Agency. Responses to comments received from the public consultation on draft food (amendment no. Y) regulations. 2023. https://www.sfa.gov.sg/docs/default-source/default-document-library/summary-response-to-comments-received-from-public-consultation-on-non-rte-micro-stds.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singapore Food Agency. Sale of food act 1973 food (amendment no. 3) regulations 2023. 2023. https://www.sfa.gov.sg/docs/default-source/default-document-library/food-(amendment-no-3)-regulations-2023.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Food and Drug Safety. Food Code. 2019. https://bcglobal.bryantchristie.com/marketinfo/reports/peanut%20aflatoxin%20limits/Korea%20Food%20Code%20JUL2019.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health in New Zealand. Microbiological reference criteria for food. 1995. https://www.mpi.govt.nz/dmsdocument/21185/send</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Australian Government. Microbiological Manual for Sampling and Testing of Export Meat and Meat Products. 2023. https://www.agriculture.gov.au/sites/default/files/sitecollectiondocuments/aqis/exporting/meat/elmer3/index/methods-microbiological-test-meat/manual-microbiological-programs.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Australian Government. Australia New Zealand Food Standards Code – Schedule 27 – Microbiological limits in food. 2021. https://www.legislation.gov.au/Details/F2021C00605</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Australian Government. Microbiological limits in food, Standard 1.6.1. 2016. https://dairy-safe.com.au/wp-content/uploads/Microbiological-Limits-in-Food.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DVP. Microbiological Reference Criteria for Meat. 2018. http://www.rmaa.co.za/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/VPN-52-Microbiological-Reference-Criteria-for-Meat-19-October-2018-Draft.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Powell MR, Ebel E, Schlosser W, Walderhaug M, Kause J. Dose-response envelope for Escherichia coli O157: H7. Quant Microbiol. 2000;2:141–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haas CN, Thayyar-Madabusi A, Rose JB, Gerba CP. Development of a dose-response relationship for Escherichia coli O157: H7. Int J Food Microbiol. 2000;56(2–3):153–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10857541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teunis PF, Ogden ID, Strachan NJ. Hierarchical dose response of E. coli O157: H7 from human outbreaks incorporating heterogeneity in exposure. Epidemiol Infect. 2008;136(6):761–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2870861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17672927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alrobaish WS, Vlerick P, Luning PA, Jacxsens L. Food safety governance in Saudi Arabia: challenges in control of imported food. J Food Sci. 2021;86(1):16–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33314129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JS, Lee MS, Kim JH. Recent updates on outbreaks of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli and its potential reservoirs. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2020;10:273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7287036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32582571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Almeida PMP, Arais LR, Andrade JRC, Prado EHRB, Irino K, Cerqueira AdMF. Characterization of atypical enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (aEPEC) isolated from dogs. Vet Microbiol. 2012;158(3–4):420–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22421111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galli L, Miliwebsky E, Irino K, Leotta G, Rivas M. Virulence profile comparison between LEE-negative Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) strains isolated from cattle and humans. Vet Microbiol. 2010;143(2–4):307–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20022185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krause M, Barth H, Schmidt H. Toxins of locus of enterocyte effacement-negative Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli. Toxins (Basel). 2018;10(6):241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6024878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29903982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boisen N, Melton-Celsa AR, Scheutz F, O’Brien AD, Nataro JP. Shiga toxin 2a and enteroaggregative Escherichia coli–a deadly combination. Gut Microbes. 2015;6(4):272–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4615819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26039753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndlovu T, Le Roux M, Khan W, Khan S. Co-detection of virulent Escherichia coli genes in surface water sources. PLoS ONE. 2015;10(2): e0116808.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4320055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25659126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsubaie ASR, Berekaa MM. Food safety in Saudi Arabia: a public health priority. Ann Med Health Sci Res. 2020;10(6):1142–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Barqi R, Al-Salem Y, Mahrous L, Abu Abat E, Al-Quraishi R, Benajiba N. Understanding barriers towards the use of food labels among Saudi female college students. Malaysian J Nutr J Nutr. 2020;26(1):19–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alghafari WT, Attar AA, Alghanmi AA, Alolayan DA, Alamri NA, Alqarni SA, et al. Responses of consumers with food allergy to the new allergen-labelling legislation in Saudi Arabia: a preliminary survey. Public Health Nutr. 2021;24(17):5941–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10195493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34108066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almughthim AM, Jradi HA. Nutritional quality of prepackaged foods carrying health or nutritional claims in KSA. J Taibah Univ Med Sci. 2022;18(3):587–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36818170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Todd ECD. Foodborne disease and food control in the Gulf States. Food Control. 2017;73:341–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7126945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32288324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sváb D, Falgenhauer L, Mag T, Chakraborty T, Tóth I. Genomic diversity, virulence gene, and prophage arrays of bovine and human shiga toxigenic and enteropathogenic Escherichia coli strains isolated in Hungary. Front Microbiol. 2022;13: 896296.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9294531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35865933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>