<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39372199</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1663-9812</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in pharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Pharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A real-world pharmacovigilance analysis of eslicarbazepine acetate using the FDA adverse events reporting system (FAERS) database from 2013 (Q4) to 2024 (Q1).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1463560</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1463560</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1463560</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fphar.2024.1463560</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The approval of eslicarbazepine acetate (ESL) by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in 2013 marked an advancement in the treatment of adult patients with partial-onset seizures. However, there still remains a paucity of real-world studies regarding the adverse events (AEs) associated with this compound. The principal aim of the present study was to scrutinize ESL-related AEs by leveraging data from the US Food and Drug Administration Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) database.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">By extracting all available data since the FDA approval of ESL (2013Q4-2024Q1), disproportionality analysis was performed using reporting odds ratio (ROR), proportional reporting ratio (PRR), Bayesian confidence propagation neural network (BCPNN) and multi-item gamma Poisson shrinker (MGPS) algorithms. AE signals that simultaneously met the requirements of all four algorithms were identified as significant positive signals. Demographic information, time of onset and gender-specific signal detection were also examined. In addition, a special screening process for designated medical events (DME) was implemented to focus on the evaluation and comparison of safety signals within DME and System Organ Classification (SOC) level, as well as SMQ (Standardised MedDRA Queries) level. Stratified analysis by logistic regression is employed to examine the variations across different gender (male and female) and age groups (&lt;18 years old, 18-64 years old, &gt;65 years old).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 5,719 AE reports and 1,907 reported cases were obtained. ESL related AEs were identified in relation to 27 SOCs, among which the significant positive SOCs were nervous system disorders, injury poisoning and procedural complications, etc. There were 86 severely disproportional preferred terms that complied with the four algorithms. Most AEs occurred within the first month after treatment. According to the 86 valuable positive signals with DME screening results, 3 signals of dermatitis exfoliative, stevens-johnson syndrome, drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms were consistent with PT signals on the DME-list, with the 3 PTs focusing on skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders and hypersensitivity. Males are more commonly affected by seizures than females. Seizures, hyponatremia, and confusional states were more frequently observed in the elderly population, while aggression, irritability, DRESS (drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms), and abnormal behavior were found to be more common in the pediatric population. Both the children and elderly groups exhibited a higher proportion of agitation than the adult group.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Our research enhances the safety and tolerability profile of ESL, but the clinical use of ESL should be noticed and avoided in relation to AEs since it raises the risk of dermatitis exfoliative, stevens-johnson syndrome. Particular attention should be paid to DRESS in children and hyponatremia in the elderly.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Tang, Xu, Zhang, Chen, Song, Ma, Zhao and Zhao.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Huafei</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, The 305 Hospital of PLA, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Daping Hospital, Army Medical University, Chongqing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Xian</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, The 305 Hospital of PLA, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Chunliang</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, The 305 Hospital of PLA, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Ge</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, The 305 Hospital of PLA, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Rui</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, The 305 Hospital of PLA, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Jinjing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, The 305 Hospital of PLA, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Qiang</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, The 305 Hospital of PLA, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Pharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101548923</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1663-9812</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AES</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ESL</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FDA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">eslicarbazepine acetate</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacovigilance analysis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39372199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11449726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2024.1463560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1463560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Almeida L., Falcão A., Maia J., Mazur D., Gellert M., Soares-da-Silva P. (2005). Single-dose and steady-state pharmacokinetics of eslicarbazepine acetate (BIA 2-093) in healthy elderly and young subjects. J. Clin. Pharmacol. 45 (9), 1062–1066. 10.1177/0091270005279364</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0091270005279364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16100301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida L., Nunes T., Sicard E., Rocha J. F., Falcão A., Brunet J. S., et al. (2010). Pharmacokinetic interaction study between eslicarbazepine acetate and lamotrigine in healthy subjects. Acta neurol. Scand. 121 (4), 257–264. 10.1111/j.1600-0404.2009.01233.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0404.2009.01233.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20047572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida L., Potgieter J. H., Maia J., Potgieter M. A., Mota F., Soares-da-Silva P. (2008). Pharmacokinetics of eslicarbazepine acetate in patients with moderate hepatic impairment. Eur. J. Clin. Pharmacol. 64 (3), 267–273. 10.1007/s00228-007-0414-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00228-007-0414-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18157705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altalib H., Grinnell T., Cantu D., Ikedo F., Vieira M., Zhang Y., et al. (2022). Psychiatric adverse events in three phase III trials of eslicarbazepine acetate for focal seizures. Epilepsia open 7 (4), 616–632. 10.1002/epi4.12635</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/epi4.12635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9712463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35908275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amstutz U., Shear N. H., Rieder M. J., Hwang S., Fung V., Nakamura H., et al. (2014). Recommendations for HLA-B*15:02 and HLA-A*31:01 genetic testing to reduce the risk of carbamazepine-induced hypersensitivity reactions. Epilepsia 55 (4), 496–506. 10.1111/epi.12564</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/epi.12564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24597466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andermann E., Biton V., Benbadis S. R., Shneker B., Shah A. K., Carreño M., et al. (2018). Psychiatric and cognitive adverse events: a pooled analysis of three phase III trials of adjunctive eslicarbazepine acetate for partial-onset seizures. Epilepsy and Behav. E&amp;B 82, 119–127. 10.1016/j.yebeh.2017.12.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2017.12.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29604484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asadi-Pooya A. A., Brigo F., Lattanzi S., Blumcke I. (2023). Adult epilepsy. Lancet (London, Engl.) 402 (10399), 412–424. 10.1016/S0140-6736(23)01048-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)01048-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37459868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doeser A., Dickhof G., Reitze M., Uebachs M., Schaub C., Pires N. M., et al. (2015). Targeting pharmacoresistant epilepsy and epileptogenesis with a dual-purpose antiepileptic drug. Brain a J. neurology 138 (Pt 2), 371–387. 10.1093/brain/awu339</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/brain/awu339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25472797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elger C., Bialer M., Falcão A., Vaz-da-Silva M., Nunes T., Almeida L., et al. (2013). Pharmacokinetics and tolerability of eslicarbazepine acetate and oxcarbazepine at steady state in healthy volunteers. Epilepsia 54 (8), 1453–1461. 10.1111/epi.12242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/epi.12242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23758485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elger C., Koepp M., Trinka E., Villanueva V., Chaves J., Ben-Menachen E., et al. (2017). Pooled efficacy and safety of eslicarbazepine acetate as add-on treatment in patients with focal-onset seizures: data from four double-blind placebo-controlled pivotal phase III clinical studies. CNS Neurosci. and Ther. 23 (12), 961–972. 10.1111/cns.12765</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cns.12765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5813188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29030894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falcão A., Maia J., Almeida L., Mazur D., Gellert M., Soares-da-Silva P. (2007). Effect of gender on the pharmacokinetics of eslicarbazepine acetate (BIA 2-093), a new voltage-gated sodium channel blocker. Biopharm. and drug Dispos. 28 (5), 249–256. 10.1002/bdd.549</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bdd.549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17443646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher R. S., Cross J. H., French J. A., Higurashi N., Hirsch E., Jansen F. E., et al. (2017). Operational classification of seizure types by the international League against epilepsy: position paper of the ILAE commission for classification and terminology. Epilepsia 58 (4), 522–530. 10.1111/epi.13670</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/epi.13670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28276060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galiana G. L., Gauthier A. C., Mattson R. H. (2017). Eslicarbazepine acetate: a new improvement on a classic drug family for the treatment of partial-onset seizures. Drugs R&amp;D 17 (3), 329–339. 10.1007/s40268-017-0197-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40268-017-0197-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5629137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28741150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GBD 2021 Nervous System Disorders Collaborators (2024). Global, regional, and national burden of disorders affecting the nervous system, 1990-2021: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. Lancet. Neurology 23 (4), 344–381. 10.1016/S1474-4422(24)00038-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(24)00038-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10949203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38493795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guedes L., Vieira M., Gama H., Magano D., Fernandes M., Calero P., et al. (2023). Thirteen years of experience with eslicarbazepine acetate in the United Kingdom and Republic of Ireland: a safety perspective. Epileptic Disord. Int. epilepsy J. videotape 25 (6), 803–814. 10.1002/epd2.20146</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/epd2.20146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37584596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta D. K., Bhoi S. K., Kalita J., Misra U. K. (2015). Hyponatremia following esclicarbazepine therapy. Seizure 29, 11–14. 10.1016/j.seizure.2015.03.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2015.03.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26076838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halász P., Cramer J. A., Hodoba D., Członkowska A., Guekht A., Maia J., et al. (2010). Long-term efficacy and safety of eslicarbazepine acetate: results of a 1-year open-label extension study in partial-onset seizures in adults with epilepsy. Epilepsia 51 (10), 1963–1969. 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2010.02660.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2010.02660.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20662896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang S., Lee S., Kim E., Hwang I., Cho J. Y., Chung J. Y., et al. (2022). The pharmacokinetic, safety, and tolerability profiles of eslicarbazepine acetate are comparable between Korean and White subjects. Clin. Transl. Sci. 15 (9), 2116–2126. 10.1111/cts.13344</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cts.13344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9468563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35727711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaculini C. M., Tate-Looney A. J., Seifi A. (2021). The history of epilepsy: from ancient mystery to modern misconception. Cureus 13 (3), e13953. 10.7759/cureus.13953</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.13953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8051941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33880289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kay L., Willems L. M., Zöllner J. P., Reif P. S., Klein K. M., Rosenow F., et al. (2017). Eslicarbazepine acetate as a therapeutic option in a patient with carbamazepine-induced rash and HLA-A*31:01. Seizure 47, 81–82. 10.1016/j.seizure.2017.02.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2017.02.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28340402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keating G. M. (2014). Eslicarbazepine acetate: a review of its use as adjunctive therapy in refractory partial-onset seizures. CNS drugs 28 (7), 583–600. 10.1007/s40263-014-0182-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40263-014-0182-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24972948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lattanzi S., Brigo F., Cagnetti C., Verrotti A., Zaccara G., Silvestrini M. (2018). Eslicarbazepine acetate in the treatment of adults with partial-onset epilepsy: an evidence-based review of efficacy, safety and place in therapy. Core Evid. 13, 21–31. 10.2147/CE.S142858</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/CE.S142858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5846310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29563858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee S. K., Lee S. A., Hong S. B., Cho Y. W., Castilla-Fernández G., Fonseca M. M., et al. (2024). Long-term effects of adjunctive eslicarbazepine acetate in adult Asian patients with refractory focal seizures: post hoc analysis of a phase III trial. Clin. Transl. Sci. 17 (5), e13802. 10.1111/cts.13802</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cts.13802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11121758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38787305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ley M., Principe A., Jiménez-Conde J., Rocamora R. (2015). Assessing long-term effects of eslicarbazepine acetate on lipid metabolism profile, sodium values and liver function tests. Epilepsy Res. 115, 147–152. 10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2015.06.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2015.06.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26220393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nevitt S. J., Sudell M., Cividini S., Marson A. G., Tudur Smith C. (2022). Antiepileptic drug monotherapy for epilepsy: a network meta-analysis of individual participant data. Cochrane database Syst. Rev. 4 (4), CD011412. 10.1002/14651858.CD011412.pub4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD011412.pub4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8974892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35363878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pitkänen A., Engel J. (2014). Past and present definitions of epileptogenesis and its biomarkers. Neurotherapeutics 11 (2), 231–241. 10.1007/s13311-014-0257-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13311-014-0257-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3996117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24492975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rocamora R., Peltola J., Assenza G., McMurray R., Villanueva V. (2020). Safety, tolerability and effectiveness of transition to eslicarbazepine acetate from carbamazepine or oxcarbazepine in clinical practice. Seizure 75, 121–128. 10.1016/j.seizure.2019.12.022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2019.12.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31981862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheffer I. E., Berkovic S., Capovilla G., Connolly M. B., French J., Guilhoto L., et al. (2017). ILAE classification of the epilepsies: position paper of the ILAE commission for classification and terminology. Epilepsia 58 (4), 512–521. 10.1111/epi.13709</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/epi.13709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5386840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28276062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shorvon S. D., Trinka E., Steinhoff B. J., Holtkamp M., Villanueva V., Peltola J., et al. (2017). Eslicarbazepine acetate: its effectiveness as adjunctive therapy in clinical trials and open studies. J. neurology 264 (3), 421–431. 10.1007/s00415-016-8338-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00415-016-8338-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5336540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28101651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sperling M. R., Abou-Khalil B., Harvey J., Rogin J. B., Biraben A., Galimberti C. A., et al. (2015b). Eslicarbazepine acetate as adjunctive therapy in patients with uncontrolled partial-onset seizures: results of a phase III, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial. Epilepsia 56 (2), 244–253. 10.1111/epi.12894</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/epi.12894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4354260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25528898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sperling M. R., Harvey J., Grinnell T., Cheng H., Blum D. 045 Study Team (2015a). Efficacy and safety of conversion to monotherapy with eslicarbazepine acetate in adults with uncontrolled partial-onset seizures: a randomized historical-control phase III study based in North America. Epilepsia 56 (4), 546–555. 10.1111/epi.12934</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/epi.12934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5016771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25689448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thijs R. D., Surges R., O'Brien T. J., Sander J. W. (2019). Epilepsy in adults. Lancet (London, Engl.) 393 (10172), 689–701. 10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32596-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32596-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30686584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verrotti A., Loiacono G., Rossi A., Zaccara G. (2014). Eslicarbazepine acetate: an update on efficacy and safety in epilepsy. Epilepsy Res. 108 (1), 1–10. 10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2013.10.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2013.10.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24225327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C., Zuo Z., Kwan P., Baum L. (2011). In vitro transport profile of carbamazepine, oxcarbazepine, eslicarbazepine acetate, and their active metabolites by human P-glycoprotein. Epilepsia 52 (10), 1894–1904. 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2011.03140.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2011.03140.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21692796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu L. N., Chen D., Tan G., Wang H. J., Chu S., Liu L. (2020). The tolerability and safety profile of eslicarbazepine acetate in neurological disorders. J. neurological Sci. 413, 116772. 10.1016/j.jns.2020.116772</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2020.116772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zubiaur P., Del Peso-Casado M., Ochoa D., Enrique-Benedito T., Mejía-Abril G., Navares M., et al. (2021). ABCB1 C3435T, G2677T/A and C1236T variants have no effect in eslicarbazepine pharmacokinetics. Biomed. and Pharmacother. = Biomedecine and Pharmacother. 142, 112083. 10.1016/j.biopha.2021.112083</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2021.112083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34463270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>