<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39377980</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1559-0283</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cell biochemistry and biophysics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cell Biochem Biophys</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Computational Drug Design Approaches for the Identification of Novel Antidiabetic Compounds from Natural Resources through Molecular Docking, ADMET, and Toxicological Studies.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12013-024-01540-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is usually depicted by relative insulin deficiency, raised blood glucose levels, and the predominant risk factor, insulin resistance. Hence, the development of insulin sensitizer drugs targeting PPAR-γ receptors has expanded enormous interest as an attractive choice for T2DM treatment. Thiazolidinediones (TZD) enhance insulin sensitivity either by directly functioning on gene transcription of the PPARγ receptor related to glucose homeostasis or by systemic sensitization of insulin and, therefore, improved hyperglycemia in a wide range of patients. However, severe complications and adverse effects of TZDs necessitate the development of an efficacious and reliable insulin sensitizer from alternative resources. On the contrary, Nature is a rich source of anticipated effective and safer medicine; more than fifty percent of drugs on the market are developed from natural products. Hence, searching for a new PPAR-γ agonist from bioactive secondary compounds of medicinal plants along with greater efficacy and safety is a recognized and consistent tactic for developing novel antidiabetic agents. Pulicaria jaubertii is a fragrant perennial aromatic plant with anti-inflammatory, antidiabetic, antimicrobial, antimalarial, and insecticidal properties. The current study was designed to use a computer-aided drug design to explore the best antidiabetic compounds from P. jaubertii. Herein, the molecular docking study of 80 investigated ligands against the PPAR-γ receptor identifies the highest docking score for five ligands ranging from -8.9 kcal/mol to 8.0 kcal/mol, which is also more significant than the standard drug pioglitazone (-7.7 kcal/mol) determined by the PyRx 8.0 virtual screening software. GLN286, CYS285, SER289, TYR473, MET364, ARG288, ILE341, and LEU333 residues are found to be significant contributors to the non-bonded interaction between ligands and receptors. Molecular electrostatic potential (MEP), DFT, molecular orbital (MO), ADMET, and toxicological analyses were performed on the selected five high-scored ligands of P. jaubertii. Results documented that all investigated ligands, especially L4, show considerably excellent profiles in molecular docking, MEP, DFT, MO, ADMET, and toxicological predictions, suggesting our drug-designing approaches may contribute to the development of a novel antidiabetic drug for the treatment of T2DM from natural resources.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akter</LastName><ForeName>Bakul</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Faculty of Biological Sciences, University of Chittagong, Chittagong, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmaceutical Sciences Research Division, BCSIR Dhaka Laboratories, Bangladesh Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (BCSIR), Dhaka, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Uddin</LastName><ForeName>Md Sohorab</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Faculty of Biological Sciences, University of Chittagong, Chittagong, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, University of Science and Technology, Chittagong, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Islam</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Rashedul</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Faculty of Biological Sciences, University of Chittagong, Chittagong, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahamed</LastName><ForeName>Kutub Uddin</ForeName><Initials>KU</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmaceutical Sciences Research Division, BCSIR Dhaka Laboratories, Bangladesh Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (BCSIR), Dhaka, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aktar</LastName><ForeName>Most Nazmin</ForeName><Initials>MN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Natural Sciences, Macquarie University, Sydney, NSW, 2109, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hossain</LastName><ForeName>Mohammed Kamrul</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Faculty of Biological Sciences, University of Chittagong, Chittagong, Bangladesh. mkhossain73@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salamatullah</LastName><ForeName>Ahmad Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Nutrition, College of Food and Agricultural Sciences, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bourhia</LastName><ForeName>Mouhammed</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Biotechnology and Natural Resources Valorization, Faculty of Sciences, , Ibn Zohr University, Agadir, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cell Biochem Biophys</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9701934</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1085-9195</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pulicaria jaubertii</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Computer-aided drug design</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PPARγ</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">T2DM</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Thiazolidinediones</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39377980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12013-024-01540-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12013-024-01540-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Javeed, N., &amp; Matveyenko, A. V. (2018). Circadian etiology of type 2 diabetes mellitus. Physiology, 33, 138–150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29412061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5899235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/physiol.00003.2018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frankel, D. S., Wilson, P. W. &amp; Meigs, J. B. (2010). Diabetes mellitus and cardiovascular disease. Atlas of atherosclerosis and metabolic syndrome (pp. 227–252).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Findling, R. L., Landersdorfer, C. B., Kafantaris, V., Pavuluri, M., McNamara, N. K., &amp; McClellan, J., et al. (2010). First-dose pharmacokinetics of lithium carbonate in children and adolescents. Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology, 30, 404–410</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20531219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2967308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/JCP.0b013e3181e66a62</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association, A. D. (2009). Diabetes and employment. Diabetes Care, 32, S80</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc09-S080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makrilakis, K. (2019). The role of DPP-4 inhibitors in the treatment algorithm of type 2 diabetes mellitus: When to select, what to expect. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 16, 2720</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31366085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6696077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph16152720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olokoba, A. B., Obateru, O. A., &amp; Olokoba, L. B. (2012). Type 2 diabetes mellitus: A review of current trends. Oman Medical Journal, 27, 269</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23071876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3464757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5001/omj.2012.68</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, Y., Ley, S. H., &amp; Hu, F. B. (2018). Global aetiology and epidemiology of type 2 diabetes mellitus and its complications. Nature Reviews Endocrinology, 14, 88–98</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29219149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrendo.2017.151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore, K. B., &amp; Saudek, C. D. (2008). Therapeutic potential of dipeptidyl peptidase-IV inhibitors in patients with diabetes mellitus. American Journal of Therapeutics, 15, 484–491</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18806525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MJT.0b013e3180ed42dc</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnett, A. (2006). DPP‐4 inhibitors and their potential role in the management of type 2 diabetes. International Journal of Clinical Practice, 60, 1454–1470</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17073841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1742-1241.2006.01178.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celi, F. S., &amp; Shuldiner, A. R. (2002). The role of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma in diabetes and obesity. Current Diabetes Reports, 2, 179–185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12643137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11892-002-0078-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vazquez, M., Silvestre, J., &amp; Prous, J. (2002). Experimental approaches to study PPAR gamma agonists as antidiabetic drugs,. Methods and Finding Experimental Clinical Pharmacology, 24, 515–523</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1358/mf.2002.24.8.705072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bermudez, V., Finol, F., Parra, N., Parra, M., Pérez, A., &amp; Penaranda, L., et al. (2010). PPAR-γ agonists and their role in type 2 diabetes mellitus management. American Journal of Therapeutics, 17, 274–283</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20216208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MJT.0b013e3181c08081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janani, C., &amp; Kumari, B. R. (2015). PPAR gamma gene–a review,. Diabetes &amp; Metabolic Syndrome: Clinical Research &amp; Reviews, 9, 46–50</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2014.09.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lebovitz, H. E. (2019). Thiazolidinediones: The forgotten diabetes medications. Current Diabetes Reports, 19, 151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31776781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6881429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11892-019-1270-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, H.-I., &amp; Ahn, Y.-H. (2004). Role of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ in the glucose-sensing apparatus of liver and β-cells. Diabetes, 53, S60–S65</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14749267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diabetes.53.2007.S60</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsen, T., Toubro, S., &amp; Astrup, A. (2003). PPARgamma agonists in the treatment of type II diabetes: is increased fatness commensurate with long-term efficacy? International Journal of Obesity, 27, 147–161</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12586994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.ijo.802223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, J., Xu, X., Cheng, F., Liu, H., Luo, X., &amp; Shen, J., et al. (2003). Virtual screening on natural products for discovering active compounds and target information. Current Medicinal Chemistry, 10, 2327–2342</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14529345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/0929867033456729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuzul Hakimi Wan SALLEH, W. M., Kassim, H. &amp; Tawang, A. (2021). Volatile components and biological activities of Pulicaria essential oils. A review. Rivista Italiana delle Sostanze Grasse, 98, 49–58</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fawzy, G. A., Al Ati, H. Y., &amp; El Gamal, A. A. (2013). Chemical composition and biological evaluation of essential oils of Pulicaria jaubertii. Pharmacognosy Magazine, 9, 28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23661990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3647390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0973-1296.108133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Maqtari, Q. A., Mahdi, A. A., Al‑Ansi, W., Mohammed, J. K., Wei, M., &amp; Yao, W. (2021). Evaluation of bioactive compounds and antibacterial activity of Pulicaria jaubertii extract obtained by supercritical and conventional methods. Journal of Food Measurement and Characterization, 15, 449–456.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11694-020-00652-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Algabr, M., Al-Hajj, N., Jaber, A., Alshotobi, A., Al-suryhi, S., &amp; Whaban, G., et al. (2016). Antibacterial and antifungal activities of the essential oil of Pulicaria jaubertii leaves. Der Pharma Chemica, 8, 224–8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mentouri, R. (2010). Antioxydant activities from the aerial parts of Pulicaria jaubertii. Advances in Natural and Applied Sciences, 4, 63–70</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed, H. A., Abdelwahab, M. F., El-Ghaly, E.-S. M., &amp; Ragab, E. A. (2021). Phytochemical characterization, in vitro anti-inflammatory, anti-diabetic, and cytotoxic activities of the edible aromatic plant; Pulicaria jaubertii. Molecules, 26, 203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33401558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7796184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26010203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Ghaly, E.-S. M., Shaheen, U., Ragab, E., El-Hila, A. A. &amp; Abd-Allah, M. R. (2016) Bioactive constituents of Pulicaria jaubertii: A promising antihypertensive activity, Pharmacognosy Journal, 8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ragab, E. A., &amp; Raafat, M. (2016). A new monoterpene glucoside and complete assignments of dihydroflavonols of Pulicaria jaubertii: Potential cytotoxic and blood pressure lowering activity. Natural Product Research, 30, 1280–1288</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26247309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14786419.2015.1055492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, D.-L., Chan, D. S.-H., &amp; Leung, C.-H. (2013). Drug repositioning by structure-based virtual screening. Chemical Society Reviews, 42, 2130–2141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23288298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c2cs35357a</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prieto-Martínez, F. D., López-López, E., Juárez-Mercado, K. E. &amp; Medina-Franco, J. L. (2019). Computational drug design methods—current and future perspectives, In silico drug design (pp. 19–44). Elsevier</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolte, R. T., Wisely, G. B., Westin, S., Cobb, J. E., Lambert, M. H., &amp; Kurokawa, R., et al. (1998). Ligand binding and co-activator assembly of the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ. Nature, 395, 137–143</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9744270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/25931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawsar, S. M., Kumer, A., Munia, N. S., Hosen, M. A., Chakma, U., &amp; Akash, S. (2022). Chemical descriptors, PASS, molecular docking, molecular dynamics and ADMET predictions of glucopyranoside derivatives as inhibitors to bacteria and fungi growth. Organic Communications, 15, 203</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Studio, D. (2008). Discovery studio. Accelrys [2.1], 420</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konc, J., &amp; Janežič, D. (2010). ProBiS algorithm for detection of structurally similar protein binding sites by local structural alignment,. Bioinformatics, 26, 1160–1168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20305268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2859123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, S., Thiessen, P. A., Bolton, E. E., Chen, J., Fu, G., &amp; Gindulyte, A., et al. (2016). PubChem substance and compound databases. Nucleic Acids Research, 44, D1202–D1213</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26400175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein, F. M. (1995). Computer software reviews. CS ChemDraw Pro, version 3.1 for windows. Journal of Chemical Information and Computer Sciences, 35, 166–167</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ci00023a026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendelsohn, L. D. (2004). ChemDraw 8 ultra, windows and macintosh versions. Journal of Chemical Information and Computer Sciences, 44, 2225–2226</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ci040123t</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yulianto, M. E., Yuniastuti, A., Rohdiana, D., Paramita, V., Ariyanto, H. D., &amp; Amalia, R., et al. (2022). Characterization in silico of bioactive compound in tea plant as a potentials inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro. Journal of Applied Pharmaceutical Science, 12, 076–085</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akash, S., Bayıl, I., Hossain, M. S., Islam, M. R., Hosen, M. E., &amp; Mekonnen, A. B., et al. (2023). Novel computational and drug design strategies for inhibition of human papillomavirus-associated cervical cancer and DNA polymerase theta receptor by Apigenin derivatives. Scientific Reports, 13, 16565</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37783745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10545697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-43175-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Boyle, N. M., Banck, M., James, C. A., Morley, C., Vandermeersch, T., &amp; Hutchison, G. R. (2011). Open Babel: An open chemical toolbox. Journal of Cheminformatics, 3, 1–14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daina, A., Michielin, O., &amp; Zoete, V. (2017). SwissADME: a free web tool to evaluate pharmacokinetics, drug-likeness and medicinal chemistry friendliness of small molecules. Scientific Reports, 7, 42717</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28256516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5335600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep42717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee, P., Eckert, A. O., Schrey, A. K., &amp; Preissner, R. (2018). ProTox-II: A webserver for the prediction of toxicity of chemicals. Nucleic Acids Research, 46, W257–W263</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29718510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6031011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gky318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandon, H., Chakraborty, T., &amp; Suhag, V. (2019). A brief review on importance of DFT in drug design. Research in Medical &amp; Engineering Science, 7, 791–795</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LaPointe, S. M., &amp; Weaver, D. F. (2007). A review of density functional theory quantum mechanics as applied to pharmaceutically relevant systems. Current Computer-Aided Drug Design, 3, 290–296</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/157340907782799390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akash, S., Kumer, A., Chandro, A., Chakma, U., &amp; Matin, M. M. (2022). Quantum calculation, docking, ADMET and molecular dynamics of ketal and non-ketal forms of D-glucofuranose against bacteria, black &amp; white fungus, and triple-negative breast cancer. Biointerface Research in Applied Chemistry, 13, 374</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.33263/BRIAC134.374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shivanika, C., Kumar, D., Ragunathan, V., Tiwari, P., &amp; Sumitha, A. (2022). Molecular docking, validation, dynamics simulations, and pharmacokinetic prediction of natural compounds against the SARS-CoV-2 main-protease. Journal of Biomolecular Structure &amp; Dynamics, 40(2), 585–611</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nirmala, R. C., &amp; Gopalakrishnan, V. (2013). Homology modeling, active site prediction and targeting the anti epileptic activity through molecular docking techniques on laforin,. International Journal of Pharma and Bio Sciences, 4, B62–B72</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konc, J., &amp; Janežič, D. (2010). ProBiS: a web server for detection of structurally similar protein binding sites,. Nucleic Acids Research, 38, W436–W440</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20504855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2896105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibi, S., &amp; Sakata, K. (2016). Current status of computer-aided drug design for type 2 diabetes. Current Computer-Aided Drug Design, 12, 167–177</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4997964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1573409912666160426120709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coleman, R. G., Carchia, M., Sterling, T., Irwin, J. J., &amp; Shoichet, B. K. (2013). Ligand pose and orientational sampling in molecular docking. PloS ONE, 8, e75992</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24098414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3787967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandrasekaran, B., Al-Joubi, H., Samarneh, S., Kassab, G., Deb, P. K., Kumar, P.,...&amp; Bataineh, Y. A. (2020). Drug-receptor interactions. Frontiers in Pharmacology of Neurotransmitters, 31–68</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mortier, J., Rakers, C., Bermudez, M., Murgueitio, M. S., Riniker, S., &amp; Wolber, G. (2015). The impact of molecular dynamics on drug design: Applications for the characterization of ligand–macromolecule complexes. Drug Discovery Today, 20, 686–702</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25615716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2015.01.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benet, L. Z., Hosey, C. M., Ursu, O., &amp; Oprea, T. I. (2016). BDDCS, the rule of 5 and drugability. Advanced Drug Delivery Reviews, 101, 89–98</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27182629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4910824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addr.2016.05.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, H., Xie, H., Ying, Y., Li, J., Wang, X., Xu, X. &amp; Zheng, X. (2018). Pioglitazone use in patients with diabetes and risk of bladder cancer: A systematic review and meta-analysis, Cancer Management and Research, 1627–1638</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, W., Cherukupalli, S., Jing, L., Liu, X., &amp; Zhan, P. (2020). Fsp3: A new parameter for drug-likeness. Drug Discovery Today, 25, 1839–1845</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32712310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2020.07.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasanna, S., &amp; Doerksen, R. J. (2009). Topological polar surface area: a useful descriptor in 2D-QSAR. Current Medicinal Chemistry, 16, 21–41</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19149561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7549127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/092986709787002817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raevsky, O. A., Polianczyk, D. E., Grigorev, V. Y., Raevskaja, O. E., &amp; Dearden, J. C. (2015). In silico prediction of aqueous solubility: A comparative study of local and global predictive models. Molecular informatics, 34, 417–430</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27490387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/minf.201400144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Curtiss, L. A., Redfern, P. C., &amp; Raghavachari, K. (2007). Gaussian-4 theory, The Journal of Chemical Physics, 126</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allouche, A. R. (2011). Gabedit—A graphical user interface for computational chemistry softwares. Journal of Computational Chemistry, 32, 174–182</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20607691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcc.21600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, C., Velpandian, T., Biswas, N. R., Nayak, N., Vajpayee, R. B., &amp; Ghose, S. (2011). Development of novel in silico model to predict corneal permeability for congeneric drugs: a QSPR approach. BioMed Research International, 2011, 483869</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2011/483869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>