<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39373849</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2198-3844</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced science (Weinheim, Baden-Wurttemberg, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Sci (Weinh)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Space-Confined Amplification for In Situ Imaging of Single Nucleic Acid and Single Pathogen on Biological Samples.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2407055</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2407055</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/advs.202407055</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Direct in situ imaging of nucleic acids on biological samples is advantageous for rapid analysis without DNA extraction. However, traditional nucleic acid amplification in aqueous solutions tends to lose spatial information because of the high mobility of molecules. Similar to a cellular matrix, hydrogels with biomimetic 3D nanoconfined spaces can limit the free diffusion of nucleic acids, thereby allowing for ultrafast in situ enzymatic reactions. In this study, hydrogel-based in situ space-confined interfacial amplification (iSCIA) is developed for direct imaging of single nucleic acid and single pathogen on biological samples without formaldehyde fixation. With a polyethylene glycol hydrogel coating, nucleic acids on the sample are nanoconfined with restricted movement, while in situ amplification can be successfully performed. As a result, the nucleic acids are lighted-up on the large-scale surface in 20 min, with a detection limit as low as 1 copy/10 cm<sup>2</sup>. Multiplex imaging with a deep learning model is also established to automatically analyze multiple targets. Furthermore, the iSCIA imaging of pathogens on plant leaves and food is successfully used to monitor plant health and food safety. The proposed technique, a rapid and flexible system for in situ imaging, has great potential for food, environmental, and clinical applications.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Advanced Science published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Tao</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biosystems Engineering and Food Science, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Dong</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biosystems Engineering and Food Science, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Rural Development Academy, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Zisheng</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biosystems Engineering and Food Science, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jingjing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biosystems Engineering and Food Science, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiao</LastName><ForeName>Fangbin</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biosystems Engineering and Food Science, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Yanqun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biosystems Engineering and Food Science, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Xingyu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0950-0736</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Biosystems Engineering and Food Science, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Fluid Power and Mechatronic Systems, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>LR22C200002</GrantID><Agency>Zhejiang Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>32372416</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Hundred Talent Program of Zhejiang University.</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Sci (Weinh)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101664569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2198-3844</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">LAMP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">in situ detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">space‐confined interfacial amplification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spatial imaging</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39373849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.202407055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>a) X. Liao, R. Deng, K. Warriner, T. Ding, Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2023, 22, 3212;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. Kuhnemund, Q. Wei, E. Darai, Y. Wang, I. Hernandez‐Neuta, Z. Yang, D. Tseng, A. Ahlford, L. Mathot, T. Sjoblom, A. Ozcan, M. Nilsson, Nat. Commun. 2017, 8, 13913;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) Y. Chen, F. Liu, L. P. Lee, Sci. Adv. 2022, 8, eabn3481;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) R. U. Sheth, M. Li, W. Jiang, P. A. Sims, K. W. Leong, H. H. Wang, Nat. Biotechnol. 2019, 37, 877;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) F. Chen, A. T. Wassie, A. J. Cote, A. Sinha, S. Alon, S. Asano, E. R. Daugharthy, J.‐B. Chang, A. Marblestone, G. M. Church, A. Raj, E. S. Boyden, Nat. Methods 2016, 13, 679;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>f) R. Deng, K. Zhang, Y. Sun, X. Ren, J. Li, Chem. Sci. 2017, 8, 3668;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>g) T. Zhang, Q. Zeng, F. Ji, H. Wu, R. Ledesma‐Amaro, Q. Wei, H. Yang, X. Xia, Y. Ren, K. Mu, Q. He, Z. Kang, R. Deng, Nat. Commun. 2023, 14, 4327.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Q. Zhang, Y. Ying, J. Ping, Adv. Sci. 2022, 9, 2103414;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. Yang, X. Liu, Y. Luo, A. J. Pearlstein, S. Wang, H. Dillow, K. Reed, Z. Jia, A. Sharma, B. Zhou, D. Pearlstein, H. Yu, B. Zhang, Nat. Food 2021, 2, 110;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) A. King, Nature 2017, 544, S21;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) A. Cassedy, E. Mullins, R. O'Kennedy, Biotechnol. Adv. 2020, 39, 107358;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) S. Asseng, F. Asche, Sci. Rob. 2019, 4, eaaw1875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E.‐C. Yeh, C.‐C. Fu, L. Hu, R. Thakur, J. Feng, L. P. Lee, Sci. Adv. 2017, 3, e1501645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) O. Bagasra, Nat. Protoc. 2007, 2, 2782;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) J. Ge, L.‐L. Zhang, S.‐J. Liu, R.‐Q. Yu, X. Chu, Anal. Chem. 2014, 86, 1808;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) F. Chen, J. Xue, M. Bai, C. Fan, Y. Zhao, Acc. Chem. Res. 2022, 55, 2248;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) C. Larsson, I. Grundberg, O. Soderberg, M. Nilsson, Nat. Methods 2010, 7, 395;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) R. Deng, L. Tang, Q. Tian, Y. Wang, L. Lin, J. Li, Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2014, 53, 2389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) N. Masuda, T. Ohnishi, S. Kawamoto, M. Monden, K. Okubo, Nucleic Acids Res. 1999, 27, 4436;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) B. Carow, T. Hauling, X. Qian, I. Kramnik, M. Nilsson, M. E. Rottenberg, Nat. Commun. 2019, 10, 1823;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) Z. Qing, J. Xu, J. Hu, J. Zheng, L. He, Z. Zou, S. Yang, W. Tan, R. Yang, Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2019, 58, 11574.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. B. Raub, C.‐C. Lee, D. Shibata, C. Taylor, E. Kartalov, Anal. Chem. 2016, 88, 2792.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Wang, K. Chen, H. Jiang, C. Chen, C. Xiong, M. Chen, J. Xu, X. Gao, S. Xu, H. Zhou, Y. Wu, Nat. Commun. 2023, 14, 5338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) J. Y. Li, D. J. Mooney, Nat. Rev. Mater. 2016, 1, 16071;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. Zheng, T. Sheng, J. Yu, Z. Gu, C. Xu, Nat. Rev. Bioeng. 2024, 2, 324;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) N. K. Singh, Y. Wang, C. Wen, B. Davis, X. Wang, K. Lee, Y. Wang, Nat. Biotechnol. 2023, 42, 1224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) Z. Fei, N. Gupta, M. Li, P. Xiao, X. Hu, Sci. Adv. 2023, 9, eadg9933.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Lin, M. Fang, C. Yi, Y. Jiang, C. Zhang, X. Pan, Z. Luo, Biomaterials 2022, 280, 121278.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. Liu, Y. Yang, X. Wan, H. Gao, Y. Wang, J. Lu, L.‐P. Xu, S. Wang, ACS Nano 2022, 16, 6266;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. Klimas, B. R. Gallagher, P. Wijesekara, S. Fekir, E. F. DiBernardo, Z. Cheng, D. B. Stolz, F. Cambi, S. C. Watkins, S. L. Brody, A. Horani, A. L. Barth, C. I. Moore, X. Ren, Y. Zhao, Nat. Biotechnol. 2023, 41, 858;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) H. Zeng, J. Huang, H. Zhou, W. J. Meilandt, B. Dejanovic, Y. Zhou, C. J. Bohlen, S.‐H. Lee, J. Ren, A. Liu, Z. Tang, H. Sheng, J. Liu, M. Sheng, X. Wang, Nat. Neurosci. 2023, 26, 430;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) X. Wang, W. E. Allen, M. A. Wright, E. L. Sylwestrak, N. Samusik, S. Vesuna, K. Evans, C. Liu, C. Ramakrishnan, J. Liu, G. P. Nolan, F.‐A. Bava, K. Deisseroth, Science 2018, 361, eaat5691;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) H. Zeng, J. Huang, J. Ren, C. K. Wang, Z. Tang, H. Zhou, Y. Zhou, H. Shi, A. Aditham, X. Sui, H. Chen, J. A. Lo, X. Wang, Science 2023, 380, 1337;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>f) J. Ren, H. Zhou, H. Zeng, C. K. Wang, J. Huang, X. Qiu, X. Sui, Q. Li, X. Wu, Z. Lin, J. A. Lo, K. Maher, Y. He, X. Tang, J. Lam, H. Chen, B. Li, D. E. Fisher, J. Liu, X. Wang, Nat. Methods. 2023, 20, 695;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>g) T. Yang, Z. Luo, T. Bewal, L. Li, Y. Xu, S. M. Jafari, X. Lin, Food Chem. 2022, 394, 133534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Lin, X. Huang, Y. Zhu, K. Urmann, X. Xie, M. R. Hoffmann, ACS Nano 2018, 12, 10281.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Yang, D. Li, Y. Yan, F.‐e. Ettoumi, R. A. Wu, Z. Luo, H. Yu, X. Lin, J. Hazard. Mater. 2023, 442, 130050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Weibrecht, E. Lundin, S. Kiflemariam, M. Mignardi, I. Grundberg, C. Larsson, B. Koos, M. Nilsson, O. Soderberg, Nat. Protoc. 2013, 8, 355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Xue, S.‐X. Zhang, C.‐H. Ouyang, D. Chang, B. J. Salena, Y. Li, Z.‐S. Wu, Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2018, 57, 9739.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Yang, D. Chen, J. Hu, X. Zheng, Z.‐J. Lin, H. Zhu, Trac‐Trends Analyt. Chem. 2022, 157, 116752.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) N. R. Markham, M. Zuker, Nucleic Acids Res. 2005, 33, W577;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) C. S. Ball, Y. K. Light, C.‐Y. Koh, S. S. Wheeler, L. L. Coffey, R. J. Meagher, Anal. Chem. 2016, 88, 3562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) A. Esteva, B. Kuprel, R. A. Novoa, J. Ko, S. M. Swetter, H. M. Blau, S. Thrun, Nature 2017, 546, 686;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. Hosny, H. J. W. L. Aerts, Science 2019, 366, 955;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) H. Im, D. Pathania, P. J. McFarland, A. R. Sohani, I. Degani, M. Allen, B. Coble, A. Kilcoyne, S. Hong, L. Rohrer, J. S. Abramson, S. Dryden‐Peterson, L. Fexonl, M. Pivovarov, B. Chabner, H. Lee, C. M. Castro, R. Weissleder, Nat. Biomed. Eng. 2018, 2, 666;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) W. Zhao, Y. Zhou, Y.‐Z. Feng, X. Niu, Y. Zhao, J. Zhao, Y. Dong, M. Tan, Y. Xianyu, Y. Chen, ACS Nano 2023, 17, 13700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) H. C. J. Godfray, J. R. Beddington, I. R. Crute, L. Haddad, D. Lawrence, J. F. Muir, J. Pretty, S. Robinson, S. M. Thomas, C. Toulmin, Science 2010, 327, 812;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) H. N. Fones, D. P. Bebber, T. M. Chaloner, W. T. Kay, G. Steinberg, S. J. Gurr, Nat. Food 2020, 1, 332;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) M. Carvajal‐Yepes, K. Cardwell, A. Nelson, K. A. Garrett, B. Giovani, D. G. O. Saunders, S. Kamoun, J. P. Legg, V. Verdier, J. Lessel, R. A. Neher, R. Day, P. Pardey, M. L. Gullino, A. R. Records, B. Bextine, J. E. Leach, S. Staiger, J. Tohme, Science 2019, 364, 1237;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) S. Savary, L. Willocquet, S. J. Pethybridge, P. Esker, N. McRoberts, A. Nelson, Nat. Ecol. Evol. 2019, 3, 430.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>