<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39375319</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-1497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of general internal medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Gen Intern Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Identifying Veterans with a Higher Risk of Social Needs Using Cluster Analysis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11606-024-08862-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="IMPORTANCE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Many social need screening to advance population health and reduce health disparities, but barriers to screening remain. Improved knowledge of patient populations at risk for social needs based on administrative data could facilitate more targeted practices, and by extension, feasible social need screening and referral efforts.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To illustrate the use of cluster analysis to identify patient population segments at risk for social needs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">We used clustering analysis to identify population segments among Veterans (N=2010) who participated in a survey assessing nine social needs (food, housing, utility, financial, employment, social disconnection, legal, transportation, and neighborhood safety). Clusters were based on eight variables (age, race, gender, comorbidity, region, no-show rate, rurality, and VA priority group). We used weighted logistic regression to assess association of clusters with the risk of experiencing social needs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PARTICIPANTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">National random sample of Veterans with and at risk for cardiovascular disease who responded to a mail survey (N=2010).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES" NlmCategory="METHODS">Self-reported social needs defined as the risk of endorsing (1) each individual social need, (2) one or more needs, and (3) a higher total count of needs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="KEY RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">From the clustering analysis process with sensitivity analysis, we identified a consistent population segment of Veterans. From regression modeling, we found that this cluster, with lower average age and higher proportions of women and racial minorities, was at higher risk of experiencing ≥ 1 unmet need (OR 1.74, CI 1.17-2.56). This cluster was also at a higher risk for several individual needs, especially utility needs (OR 3.78, CI 2.11-6.78).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The identification of characteristics associated with increased unmet social needs may provide opportunities for targeted screenings. As this cluster was also younger and had fewer comorbidities, they may be less likely to be identified as experiencing need through interactions with healthcare providers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. This is a U.S. Government work and not under copyright protection in the US; foreign copyright protection may apply.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Friedman</LastName><ForeName>Hannah</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5449-0987</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Healthcare Organization and Implementation Research (CHOIR), VA Boston Healthcare System, Boston, MA, USA. Hannah.friedman2@va.gov.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Mingfei</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CHOIR, VA Bedford Healthcare System, Bedford, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematical Sciences, Bentley University, Waltham, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harvey</LastName><ForeName>Kimberly L</ForeName><Initials>KL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Healthcare Organization and Implementation Research (CHOIR), VA Boston Healthcare System, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Griesemer</LastName><ForeName>Ida</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Rural Health Resource Center, VA Medical Center, White River Junction, VT, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohr</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Policy and Management, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Organization Development, Veteran's Health Administration, Cincinnati, OH, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Linsky</LastName><ForeName>Amy M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Healthcare Organization and Implementation Research (CHOIR), VA Boston Healthcare System, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of General Internal Medicine, School of Medicine (BUSM), Boston University, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of General Internal Medicine, VA Boston Healthcare System, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New England Geriatric Research Education Center, VA Boston Healthcare System, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gurewich</LastName><ForeName>Deborah</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Healthcare Organization and Implementation Research (CHOIR), VA Boston Healthcare System, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of General Internal Medicine, School of Medicine (BUSM), Boston University, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>XVA-11-052</GrantID><Agency>Office of Rural Health</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Gen Intern Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8605834</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0884-8734</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39375319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-024-08862-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11606-024-08862-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Gurewich D, Garg A, Kressin NR. Addressing social determinants of health within healthcare delivery systems: A framework to ground and inform health outcomes. J Gen Intern Med. 2020;35(5):1571-1575. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606-020-05720-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-020-05720-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32076989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7210348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knighton AJ, Stephenson B, Savitz LA. Measuring the effect of social determinants on patient outcomes: a systematic literature review. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2018;29(1):81-106. https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2018.0009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1353/hpu.2018.0009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29503290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marmot M. Social justice, epidemiology and health inequalities. Eur J Epidemiol. 2017;32(7):537-546. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10654-017-0286-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10654-017-0286-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28776115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5570780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilensky G. Addressing social issues affecting health to improve US health outcomes. JAMA. 2016;315(15):1552-3. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2016.3863</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2016.3863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27092821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singu S, Acharya A, Challagundla K, Byrareddy SN. Impact of social determinants of health on the emerging COVID-19 pandemic in the United States. Front Public Health. 2020;8:564623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.00406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hood CM, Gennuso KP, Swain GR, Catlin BB. County health rankings: Relationships between determinant factors and aealth outcomes. Am J Prev Med. 2016;50(2):129-35. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2015.08.024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2015.08.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26526164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nau C, Adams JL, Roblin D, Schmittdiel J, Schroeder E, Steiner JF. Considerations for identifying social needs in health care systems: A commentary on the role of predictive models in supporting a comprehensive social needs strategy. Med Care. 2019;57(9):661-666. https://doi.org/10.1097/mlr.0000000000001173</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/mlr.0000000000001173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31404012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraze TK, Brewster AL, Lewis VA, Beidler LB, Murray GF, Colla CH. Prevalence of screening for food insecurity, housing instability, utility needs, transportation needs, and interpersonal violence by US physician practices and hospitals. JAMA Netw Open. 2019;2(9):e1911514. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.11514</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer D, Lerner E, Phillips A, Zumwalt K. Universal screening of social determinants of health at a large US academic medical center, 2018. Am J Public Health. 2020;110(S2):S219-s221. https://doi.org/10.2105/ajph.2020.305747</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/ajph.2020.305747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32663083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7362698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drake C, Batchelder H, Lian T, et al. Implementation of social needs screening in primary care: A qualitative study using the health equity implementation framework. BMC Health Serv Res. 2021;21(1):975. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-021-06991-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byhoff E, De Marchis EH, Hessler D, et al. Part II: A qualitative study of social risk screening acceptability in patients and caregivers. Am J Prev Med. 2019;57(6 Suppl 1):S38-s46. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2019.07.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2019.07.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31753278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6876708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Marchis EH, Hessler D, Fichtenberg C, et al. Part I: A quantitative study of social risk screening acceptability in patients and caregivers. Am J Prev Med. 2019;57(6 Suppl 1):S25-s37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2019.07.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2019.07.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31753277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7336892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Marchis EH BE, Aceves BA, Loomba V, Molina M, Cartier Y, Wing H, Gottlieb LM. State of the science of screening in healthcare Settings. Social Interventions Research &amp; Evaluation Network. 2022. Available at: https://sirenetwork.ucsf.edu/sites/default/files/2022-06/final%20SCREEN%20State-of-Science-Report%5B55%5D.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kepper MM, Walsh-Bailey C, Prusaczyk B, Zhao M, Herrick C, Foraker R. The adoption of social determinants of health documentation in clinical settings. Health Serv Res. Feb 2023;58(1):67-77. https://doi.org/10.1111/1475-6773.14039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.14039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35862115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schickedanz A, Hamity C, Rogers A, Sharp AL, Jackson A. Clinician experiences and attitudes regarding screening for social determinants of health in a large integrated health system. Med Care. 2019;57 Suppl 6 Suppl 2(Suppl 6 2):S197-s201. https://doi.org/10.1097/mlr.0000000000001051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trochez RJ, Sharma S, Stolldorf DP, et al. Screening halth-related social needs in hospitals: A systematic review of health care professional and patient perspectives. Popul Health Manag. 2023;26(3):157-167. https://doi.org/10.1089/pop.2022.0279</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/pop.2022.0279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37092962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10278007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M, Pantell MS, Gottlieb LM, Adler-Milstein J. Documentation and review of social determinants of health data in the EHR: Measures and associated insights. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2021;28(12):2608-2616. https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocab194</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocab194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34549294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8633631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blosnich JR, Montgomery AE, Dichter ME, et al. Social determinants and military Veterans’ suicide ideation and attempt: A cross-sectional analysis of electronic health record data. J Gen Intern Med. 2020;35(6):1759-1767. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606-019-05447-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-019-05447-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31745856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frey LJ, Hughes Halbert C, Blasy CD. Supporting the capture of social needs through natural language processing. J Am Board Fam Med. 2023;36(3):513-514. https://doi.org/10.3122/jabfm.2022.220415R0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2022.220415R0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37290826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10484332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitra A, Pradhan R, Melamed RD, et al. Associations between natural language processing-enriched social determinants of health and suicide death among US Veterans. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(3):e233079. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.3079</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holcomb J, Oliveira LC, Highfield L, Hwang KO, Giancardo L, Bernstam EV. Predicting health-related social needs in Medicaid and Medicare populations using machine learning. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):4554. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-08344-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurewich D, Shoushtari SI, Ostrow R, et al. Prevalence and determinants of unmet social needs among rural and urban Veterans. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2023;34(1):275-292. https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2023.0018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1353/hpu.2023.0018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37464494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nnoaham KE, Cann KF. Can cluster analyses of linked healthcare data identify unique population segments in a general practice-registered population? BMC Public Health. 2020;20(1):798. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-020-08930-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurewich D, Linsky AM, Harvey KL, et al. Relationship between unmet social needs and care access in a Veteran cohort. J Gen Intern Med. 2023;38(Suppl 3):841-848. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606-023-08117-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-023-08117-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37340267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10356706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreuter MW, Thompson T, McQueen A, Garg R. Addressing social needs in health care settings: evidence, challenges, and opportunities for public health. Annu Rev Public Health. 2021;42:329-344. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-090419-102204</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-090419-102204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33326298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8240195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlson ME, Pompei P, Ales KL, MacKenzie CR. A new method of classifying prognostic comorbidity in longitudinal studies: development and validation. J Chronic Dis. 1987;40(5):373-83. https://doi.org/10.1016/0021-9681(87)90171-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0021-9681(87)90171-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3558716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosen AK, Wagner TH, Pettey WBP, et al. Differences in risk scores of Veterans receiving community care purchased by the Veterans Health Administration. Health Serv Res. 2018;53 Suppl 3(Suppl Suppl 3):5438-5454. https://doi.org/10.1111/1475-6773.13051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouillard CJ, Nasser MA, Hu H, Roblin DW. Evaluation of a natural language processing approach to identify social determinants of health in electronic health records in a diverse community cohort. Med Care. 2022;60(3):248-255. https://doi.org/10.1097/mlr.0000000000001683</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/mlr.0000000000001683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34984989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vest JR, Grannis SJ, Haut DP, Halverson PK, Menachemi N. Using structured and unstructured data to identify patients’ need for services that address the social determinants of health. Int J Med Inform. 2017;107:101-106. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2017.09.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2017.09.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29029685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berkowitz SA, Meigs JB, DeWalt D, et al. Material need insecurities, control of diabetes mellitus, and use of health care resources: Results of the measuring economic insecurity in diabetes study. JAMA Intern Med. 2015;175(2):257-65. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2014.6888</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parekh T, Xue H, Cheskin LJ, Cuellar AE. Food insecurity and housing instability as determinants of cardiovascular health outcomes: A systematic review. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2022;32(7):1590-1608. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.numecd.2022.03.025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.numecd.2022.03.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35487828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klingensmith K, Tsai J, Mota N, Southwick SM, Pietrzak RH. Military sexual trauma in US Veterans: Results from the national health and resilience in veterans study. J Clin Psychiatry. 2014;75(10):11944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.14m09244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson LC. The prevalence of military sexual trauma: A meta-analysis. Trauma, Violence, &amp; Abuse. 2018;19(5):584-597.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1524838016683459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nichter B, Holliday R, Monteith LL, et al. Military sexual trauma in the United States: Results from a population-based study. J Affect Disords. 2022;306:19-27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.03.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steeves-Reece AL, Totten AM, Broadwell KD, Richardson DM, Nicolaidis C, Davis MM. Social Needs resource connections: A systematic review of barriers, facilitators, and evaluation. Am J Prev Med. 2022;62(5):e303-e315. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2021.12.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2021.12.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35078672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9850790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Gurek DT, Henke C. A practical approach to screening for social determinants of health. Fam Pract Manag. 2018;25(3):7-12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen H, Bourgois P, Drucker E. Pathologizing poverty: New forms of diagnosis, disability, and structural stigma under welfare reform. Soc Sci Med. 2014;103:76-83. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2013.06.033</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2013.06.033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24507913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3920192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendenhall R. The medicalization of poverty in the lives of low-income black mothers and children. J Law Med Ethics. 2018;46(3):644-650. https://doi.org/10.1177/1073110518804218</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1073110518804218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30336076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webb BC, Matthew DB. Housing: A case for the medicalization of poverty. J Law Med Ethics. 2018;46(3):588-594. https://doi.org/10.1177/1073110518804201</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1073110518804201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30336092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weeks E. Medicalization of rural poverty: Challenges for access. J Law Med Ethics. 2018;46(3):651-657. https://doi.org/10.1177/1073110518804219</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1073110518804219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30336075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>