<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39372834</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2769-2558</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>3</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PCN reports : psychiatry and clinical neurosciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PCN Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A 2-year longitudinal study of the association between unhealthy lifestyle factors and the development of depressive symptoms in university students.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70020</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70020</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70020</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/pcn5.70020</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The aim of this study was to investigate the association between unhealthy lifestyle factors and the development of depressive symptoms with adjustment for sociodemographic characteristics in university students using health checkup data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Among information obtained from university student health checkups conducted in 2017 and 2019, we analyzed both the clinical data and responses to questionnaires. The subjects used for analysis were 3190 individuals (2382 men and 808 women, mean age 19.0 years) who had been free of depressive symptoms in the 2017 survey and were available for a 2-year follow-up. The Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-2) was used as a self-rating scale for depressive symptoms. Multivariable logistic regression analysis was conducted to investigate the association between lifestyle factors (such as body mass index, self-rated health, whether breakfast was taken, degree of exercise, satisfaction with sleep, smoking, and alcohol drinking) in the 2017 survey and any development of depressive symptoms revealed in the 2019 survey, adjusting for sociodemographic variables and other lifestyle factors.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Multivariable logistic analysis showed that poor satisfaction with sleep (odds ratio [OR), 4.09; 95% confidence interval [CI), 1.96-8.53; <i>p</i> &lt; 0.01) and female gender (OR, 2.16; 95% CI, 1.01-4.60; <i>p</i> = 0.05) were significantly associated with the development of depressive symptoms 2 years later.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study has revealed an association between poor satisfaction with sleep and the development of depressive symptoms. We believe that these findings may be useful for the prevention and treatment of depressive symptoms in university students.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Psychiatry and Clinical Neurosciences Reports published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Psychiatry and Neurology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Furihata</LastName><ForeName>Ryuji</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0809-2697</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agency for Student Support and Disability Resources Kyoto University Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ishida</LastName><ForeName>Mami</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-5056-8997</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology Kyoto Prefectural University of Medicine Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nakagami</LastName><ForeName>Yukako</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agency for Student Support and Disability Resources Kyoto University Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yanase</LastName><ForeName>Maya</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agency for Student Support and Disability Resources Kyoto University Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Uwatoko</LastName><ForeName>Teruhisa</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0002-7495-829X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry Kyoto University Hospital Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Health Center Kyoto University of Education Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okabayashi</LastName><ForeName>Satoe</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agency for Health, Safety, and Environment Kyoto University Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kiyohara</LastName><ForeName>Kosuke</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science Otsuma Women's University Tokyo Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kawamura</LastName><ForeName>Takashi</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive Services, School of Public Health, Graduate School of Medicine Kyoto University Kyoto Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>PCN Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918451287106676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2769-2558</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">depressive symptoms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lifestyle factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">satisfaction with sleep</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">university students</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">women</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39372834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11452839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pcn5.70020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PCN570020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tabor E, Patalay P, Bann D. Mental health in higher education students and non‐students: evidence from a nationally representative panel study. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol. 2021;56:879–882.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8068655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33590312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Zhao Z, Chen D, Peng Y, Lu Z. Prevalence and associated factors of depression and anxiety symptoms among college students: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2022;63:1222–1230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35297041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebert DD, Buntrock C, Mortier P, Auerbach R, Weisel KK, Kessler RC, et al. Prediction of major depressive disorder onset in college students. Depress Anxiety. 2019;36:294–304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6519292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30521136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Psychiatric Association . Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM‐5‐TR. Washington, DC: American Psychiatric Association; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furihata R, Konno C, Suzuki M, Takahashi S, Kaneita Y, Ohida T, et al. Unhealthy lifestyle factors and depressive symptoms: a Japanese general adult population survey. J Affect Disord. 2018;234:156–161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29529548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishida M, Montagni I, Matsuzaki K, Shimamoto T, Cariou T, Kawamura T, et al. The association between depressive symptoms and self‐rated health among university students: a cross‐sectional study in France and Japan. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20:549.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33228615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong VW‐H, Ho FY‐Y, Shi N‐K, Sarris J, Chung K‐F, Yeung W‐F. Lifestyle medicine for depression: a meta‐analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Affect Disord. 2021;284:203–216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33609955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha S, Okafor H, Biediger‐Friedman L, Behnke A. Association between diet and symptoms of anxiety and depression in college students: a systematic review. J Am Coll Health. 2023;71:1270–1280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34087087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan S, Jin Y, Oh Y, Choi Y. Effect of exercise on depression in university students: a meta‐analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Sports Med Phys Fitness. 2016;56:811–816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25812710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiyohara K, Kawamura T, Kitamura T, Takahashi Y. The start of smoking and prior lifestyles among Japanese college students: a retrospective cohort study. Nicotine Tob Res. 2010;12:1043–1049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20802240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spitzer RL, Kroenke K, Williams JB. Validation and utility of a self‐report version of PRIME‐MD: the PHQ primary care study. Primary care evaluation of mental disorders. Patient Health Questionnaire. JAMA. 1999;282:1737–1744.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10568646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroenke K, Spitzer RL, Williams JBW. The Patient Health Questionnaire‐2: validity of a two‐item depression screener. Med Care. 2003;41:1284–1292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14583691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheeran T, Reilly CF, Raue PJ, Weinberger MI, Pomerantz J, Bruce ML. The PHQ‐2 on OASIS‐C: a new resource for identifying geriatric depression among home health patients. Home Healthc Nurse. 2010;28:92–102</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2854827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20147803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>quiz 102–104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idler EL, Benyamini Y. Self‐rated health and mortality: a review of twenty‐seven community studies. J Health Soc Behav. 1997;38:21–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9097506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaussent I, Bouyer J, Ancelin M‐L, Akbaraly T, Peres K, Ritchie K, et al. Insomnia and daytime sleepiness are risk factors for depressive symptoms in the elderly. Sleep. 2011;34:1103–1110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3138165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21804672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furihata R, Hall MH, Stone KL, Ancoli‐Israel S, Smagula SF, Cauley JA, et al. An Aggregate measure of sleep health is associated with prevalent and incident clinically significant depression symptoms among community‐dwelling older women. Sleep. 2017;40:zsw075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6084764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28364417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maglione JE, Ancoli‐Israel S, Peters KW, Paudel ML, Yaffe K, Ensrud KE, et al. Subjective and objective sleep disturbance and longitudinal risk of depression in a cohort of older women. Sleep. 2014;37:1179–1187.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4098803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25061246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buysse DJ, Reynolds CF, Monk TH, Berman SR, Kupfer DJ. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry Res. 1989;28:193–213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2748771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buysse DJ. Sleep health: can we define it? Does it matter. Sleep. 2014;37:9–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3902880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24470692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furihata R, Tateyama Y, Nakagami Y, Akahoshi T, Itani O, Kaneita Y, et al. The validity and reliability of the Japanese version of RU‐SATED. Sleep Med. 2022;91:109–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35303631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gadam S, Pattinson CL, Rossa KR, Soleimanloo SS, Moore J, Begum T, et al. Interventions to increase sleep duration in young people: a systematic review. Sleep Med Rev. 2023;70:101807.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37413721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaskin CJ, Venegas Hargous C, Stephens LD, Nyam G, Brown V, Lander N, et al. Sleep behavioral outcomes of school‐based interventions for promoting sleep health in children and adolescents aged 5 to 18 years: a systematic review. Sleep Adv. 2024;5:zpae019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10996385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38584765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furihata R, Shimamoto T, Makino Y, Kimata S, Tateyama Y, Okabayashi S, et al. Efficacy of sleep extension therapy using a remote support system in university students with increased social jetlag: a parallel, single‐blind, randomized controlled trial. Sleep Biol Rhythms. 2023;21:359–368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10899925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38469084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furihata R, Shimamoto T, Ikeda Y, Makino Y, Nakagami Y, Tateyama Y, et al. Efficacy of digital brief behavioral treatment for insomnia using a smartphone application in conjunction with light therapy in university students with insomnia symptoms with late chronotypes: a pilot randomized controlled trial. J Sleep Res. 2024:e14361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39313332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salk RH, Hyde JS, Abramson LY. Gender differences in depression in representative national samples: meta‐analyses of diagnoses and symptoms. Psychol Bull. 2017;143:783–822.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5532074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28447828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Östberg D, Nordin S. Three‐year prediction of depression and anxiety with a single self‐rated health item. J Ment Health. 2022;31:402–409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35272543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan LLY, van Schooten KS, Lord SR, Delbaere K, Brodie M. Short daily‐life walking bouts and poor self‐reported health predict the onset of depression in community‐dwelling older people: a 2‐year longitudinal cohort study. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2022;23:1242–1247.e3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35131202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan Y, Wang D, Wang W, Chen H, Lin J, Lin W, et al. Depression, anxiety, and development of obesity from childhood to young adulthood in China. J Psychosom Res. 2024;185:111867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39151258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>