<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39377977</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1867-1314</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Probiotics and antimicrobial proteins</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the Probiotic Potential of Bacteroides spp. Within One Health Paradigm.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12602-024-10370-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Probiotics are pivotal in maintaining or restoring the balance of human intestinal microbiota, a crucial factor in mitigating diseases and preserving the host's health. Exploration into Bacteroides spp. reveals substantial promise in their development as next-generation probiotics due to their profound interaction with host immune cells and capability to regulate the microbiome's metabolism by significantly impacting metabolite production. These beneficial bacteria exhibit potential in ameliorating various health issues such as intestinal disorders, cardiovascular diseases, behavioral disorders, and even cancer. Though it's important to note that a high percentage of them are as well opportunistic pathogens, posing risks under certain conditions. Studies highlight their role in modifying immune responses and improving health conditions by regulating lymphocytes, controlling metabolism, and preventing inflammation and cancer. The safety and efficacy of Bacteroides strains are currently under scrutiny by the European Commission for authorization in food processing, marking a significant step towards their commercialization. The recent advancements in bacterial isolation and sequencing methodologies, coupled with the integration of Metagenome-Assembled Genomes (MAGs) binning from metagenomics data, continue to unveil the potential of Bacteroides spp., aiding in the broader understanding and application of these novel probiotics in health and disease management.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tufail</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Aammar</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut für Allgemeine Mikrobiologie, Christian-Albrechts-Universität zu Kiel, 24118, Kiel, Germany. mtufail@ifam.uni-kiel.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schmitz</LastName><ForeName>Ruth A</ForeName><Initials>RA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut für Allgemeine Mikrobiologie, Christian-Albrechts-Universität zu Kiel, 24118, Kiel, Germany. rschmitz@ifam.uni-kiel.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>031B0846D</GrantID><Agency>Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>031B0846D</GrantID><Agency>Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101484100</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1867-1306</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteroides spp.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Novel probiotics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">One health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Probiotics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39377977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-024-10370-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12602-024-10370-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adak A, Khan MR (2019) An insight into gut microbiota and its functionalities. Cell Mol Life Sci 76(3):473–493. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-018-2943-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00018-018-2943-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30317530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aggarwal N, Breedon AME, Davis CM, Hwang IY, Chang MW (2020) Engineering probiotics for therapeutic applications: recent examples and translational outlook. Curr Opin Biotechnol 65:171–179. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copbio.2020.02.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2020.02.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32304955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Fadhli AH, Jamal WY (2024) Recent advances in gene-editing approaches for tackling antibiotic resistance threats: a review [Mini Review]. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 14. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcimb.2024.1410115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Fakhrany OM, Elekhnawy E (2024) Next-generation probiotics: the upcoming biotherapeutics. Mol Biol Rep 51(1):505. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11033-024-09398-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11033-024-09398-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38619680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">11018693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida A, Mitchell AL, Boland M, Forster SC, Gloor GB, Tarkowska A, Lawley TD, Finn RD (2019) A new genomic blueprint of the human gut microbiota. Nature 568(7753):499–504. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-0965-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-0965-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30745586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6784870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvarez CA, Jones MB, Hambor J, Cobb BA (2020) Characterization of polysaccharide A response reveals interferon responsive gene signature and immunomodulatory marker expression [Original Research]. Front Immunol 11. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2020.556813</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anthony WE, Burnham C-AD, Dantas G, Kwon JH (2020) The gut microbiome as a reservoir for antimicrobial resistance. J Infect Dis 223(Supplement_3):S209–S213. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiaa497</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiaa497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8206794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anwar H, Iftikhar A, Muzaffar H, Almatroudi A, Allemailem KS, Navaid S, Saleem S, Khurshid M (2021) Biodiversity of Gut microbiota: impact of various host and environmental factors. Biomed Res Int 2021(1):5575245. https://doi.org/10.1155/2021/5575245</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2021/5575245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34055983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8133857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artur R, Jonathon AB, Jennifer CM, Theodora T, Nicolas T, Elisabeth CL, Arnaud B, Carl M, Alison MD, Hongjun Z, Theresa ER, Paul T, Alastair RH, Madhav PY, Bernard H, Eric CM, Paul D, Harry JG, David NB (2015) Glycan complexity dictates microbial resource allocation in the large intestine. Nat Commun. https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms8481</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ncomms8481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aziz T, Hussain N, Hameed Z, Lin L (2024) Elucidating the role of diet in maintaining gut health to reduce the risk of obesity, cardiovascular and other age-related inflammatory diseases: recent challenges and future recommendations. Gut Microbes 16(1):2297864. https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2023.2297864</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2023.2297864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38174551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10773664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>BAuA (2011) Begründungspapier zur Einstufung von Bacteroides xylanisolvens in Risikogruppe 1 nach BioStoffV. https://www.baua.de/ . Accessed 1 Apr 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garrity, GM (2005) Bergey’s manual® of systematic bacteriology: volume two. In: Brenner DJ, Krieg NR, Staley JT (eds) The proteobacteria (Part C). Springer US</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Black CJ, Ford AC (2021) Best management of irritable bowel syndrome. Frontline Gastroenterol 12(4):303–315. https://doi.org/10.1136/flgastro-2019-101298</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/flgastro-2019-101298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34249316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bordoni A, Amaretti A, Leonardi A, Boschetti E, Danesi F, Matteuzzi D, Roncaglia L, Raimondi S, Rossi M (2013) Cholesterol-lowering probiotics: in vitro selection and in vivo testing of bifidobacteria. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 97(18):8273–8281. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253-013-5088-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-013-5088-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23872958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodmann T, Endo A, Gueimonde M, Vinderola G, Kneifel W, de Vos WM, Salminen S, Gómez-Gallego C (2017) Safety of novel microbes for human consumption: practical examples of assessment in the European Union [Review]. Front Microbiol 8. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01725</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brook I (1988) Beta-lactamase-producing bacteria in head and neck infection. Laryngoscope 98(4):428–431. https://doi.org/10.1288/00005537-198804000-00015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1288/00005537-198804000-00015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3258396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown EM, Kenny DJ, Xavier RJ (2019) Gut microbiota regulation of T cells during inflammation and autoimmunity. Annu Rev Immunol 37(1):599–624. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-immunol-042718-041841</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-042718-041841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31026411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cable J, Leonard JN, Lu TK, Xie Z, Chang MW, Fernández LÁ, Lora JM, Kaufman HL, Quintana FJ, Geiger R, Lesser CF, Lynch JP, Hava DL, Cornish VW, Lee GK, DiAndreth B, Fero M, Srivastava R, De Coster T,…Chen WCW (2021) Synthetic biology: at the crossroads of genetic engineering and human therapeutics—a Keystone Symposia report. Ann NY Acad Sci 1506(1): 98-117. https://doi.org/10.1111/nyas.14710</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada (2009) Accepted claims about the nature of probiotic microorganisms in food. CFIA Guide to food labelling and advertising (Guide)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrow HC, Batachari LE, Chu H (2020) Strain diversity in the microbiome: lessons from Bacteroides fragilis. PLoS Pathog 16(12):e1009056. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1009056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1009056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7728264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro-Vargas P, Barloy-Hubler F, Acuña-Amador L (2023) Outer membrane vesicles from commensal and pathogenic anaerobic bacteria: a systematic review of literature reviews. Preprint at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.11.21.568143.abstract</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celso FB, Hugo LAS, Erick AE, Ramon SR, Jeremias M, Mariana AVC, Luciana A, Camps I, Yuri A, Celso SA, Robson Maia F, Mônica Queiroz de F, Marcia CS, Renata SLR, Graziela Bragueto E, Daniel G, Ranadheera CS, Filomena N, Adriano GC (2018) The addition of inulin and Lactobacillus casei 01 in sheep milk ice cream. Food Chem. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.12.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaminda Senaka R, Nenad N, Said A (2018) Non-bovine milk products as emerging probiotic carriers: recent developments and innovations. Curr Opin Food Sci. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2018.02.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2018.02.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L, Yang M, Zhu W, Su Y, Li D, Wang T (2022) Multi-omics analysis after vaginal administration of Bacteroides fragilis in chickens [Original Research]. Front Microbiol 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.846011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Kinouchi T, Kataoka K, Akimoto S, Ohnishi Y (1995) Purification and characterization of a fibrinogen-degrading protease in Bacteroides fragilis strain YCH46. Microbiol Immunol 39(12):967–977. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1348-0421.1995.tb03300.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1348-0421.1995.tb03300.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8789056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng J, Hu J, Geng F, Nie S (2022) Bacteroides utilization for dietary polysaccharides and their beneficial effects on gut health. Food Sci Human Wellness 11(5):1101–1110. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fshw.2022.04.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fshw.2022.04.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Claesson MJ, Jeffery IB, Conde S, Power SE, O’Connor EM, Cusack S, Harris HMB, Coakley M, Lakshminarayanan B, O’Sullivan O, Fitzgerald GF, Deane J, O’Connor M, Harnedy N, O’Connor K, O’Mahony D, van Sinderen D, Wallace M, Brennan L…O’Toole PW (2012) Gut microbiota composition correlates with diet and health in the elderly. Nature 488(7410): 178-184. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11319</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Claude PC, Adriano GC, Monica D (2018) Strategies to improve the functionality of probiotics in supplements and foods. Curr Opin Food Sci. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2018.04.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2018.04.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collinson S, Deans A, Padua-Zamora A, Gregorio GV, Li C, Dans LF, Allen SJ (2020) Probiotics for treating acute infectious diarrhoea. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 12(12):Cd003048. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD003048.pub4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD003048.pub4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33295643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cong J, Zhou P, Zhang R (2022) Intestinal microbiota-derived short chain fatty acids in host health and disease. Nutrients 14(9):1977. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu14091977</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14091977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35565943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9105144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conly JM, Johnston LB (2004) Coming full circle: from antibiotics to probiotics and prebiotics. Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol 15(3):161–163. https://doi.org/10.1155/2004/354909</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2004/354909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18159486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2094966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costello EK, Stagaman K, Dethlefsen L, Bohannan BJ, Relman DA (2012) The application of ecological theory toward an understanding of the human microbiome. Science 336(6086):1255–1262. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1224203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1224203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22674335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4208626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>David B, Claire W, Amy B (2007) Impact of consuming a milk drink containing a probiotic on mood and cognition. Eur J Clin Nutr. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602546</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>David NB, Nicole MK (2012) Glycan recognition by the Bacteroidetes Sus-like systems. Curr Opin Struct Biol. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbi.2012.06.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sbi.2012.06.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Filippis F, Esposito A, Ercolini D (2022) Outlook on next-generation probiotics from the human gut. Cell Mol Life Sci 79(2):76. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-021-04080-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00018-021-04080-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35043293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">11073307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Debnath N, Yadav P, Mehta PK, Gupta P, Kumar D, Kumar A, Gautam V, Yadav AK (2024) Designer probiotics: opening the new horizon in diagnosis and prevention of human diseases. Biotechnol Bioeng 121(1):100–117. https://doi.org/10.1002/bit.28574</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bit.28574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37881101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delday M, Mulder I, Logan ET, Grant G (2019) Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron ameliorates colon inflammation in preclinical models of Crohn’s disease. Inflamm Bowel Dis 25(1):85–96. https://doi.org/10.1093/ibd/izy281</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ibd/izy281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30215718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey G, Montet D, Thonart P (2021 ) Probiotic lactobacillus strains for enhanced health benefits (genetic engineering and microencapsulation). In: Probiotic Beverages. Academic Press, pp 309–337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donald K, Finlay BB (2023) Early-life interactions between the microbiota and immune system: impact on immune system development and atopic disease. Nat Rev Immunol 23(11):735–748. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41577-023-00874-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41577-023-00874-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37138015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donaldson GP, Lee SM, Mazmanian SK (2016) Gut biogeography of the bacterial microbiota. Nat Rev Microbiol 14(1):20–32. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro3552</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26499895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durmusoglu D, Haller DJ, Al’Abri IS, Day K, Sands C, Clark A, San-Miguel A, Vazquez-Uribe R, Sommer MOA, Crook NC (2024) Programming probiotics: diet-responsive gene expression and colonization control in engineered S boulardii. ACS Synthetic Biol 13(6):1851–1865. https://doi.org/10.1021/acssynbio.4c00145</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssynbio.4c00145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA Panel on Dietetic Products N, &amp; Allergies (2015) Scientific opinion on the safety of ‘heat‐treated milk products fermented with Bacteroides xylanisolvens DSM 23964’as a novel food. EFSA J 13(1): 3956</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eren AM, Kiefl E, Shaiber A, Veseli I, Miller SE, Schechter MS, Fink I, Pan JN, Yousef M, Fogarty EC, Trigodet F, Watson AR, Esen ÖC, Moore RM, Clayssen Q, Lee MD, Kivenson V, Graham ED, Merrill BD…Willis AD (2021) Community-led, integrated, reproducible multi-omics with anvi’o. Nature Microbiol 6(1): 3-6. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-020-00834-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eric CM, Elisabeth CL, Herbert CC, Nicholas AP, Meng-Meng W, Meng-Meng W, Nathan PM, Abbott DW, Bernard H, Harry JG, David NB, Jeffrey IG (2011) Recognition and degradation of plant cell wall polysaccharides by two human gut symbionts. PLoS Biol. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001221</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erica DS, Justin LS, Jill KM, Elizabeth EH, Herbert CC, Jeffrey IG (2006) A hybrid two-component system protein of a prominent human gut symbiont couples glycan sensing in vivo to carbohydrate metabolism. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0603249103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0603249103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO/WHO (2001) Health and nutritional properties of probiotics in food including powder milk with live lactic acid bacteria, report of a joint (FAO/WHO) expert consultation on evaluation of health and nutritional properties of probiotics in food including powed milk with live lactic acid bacteria (Prevention, Issue. http://pc.ilele.hk/public/pdf/20190225/bd3689dfc2fd663bb36def1b672ce0a4.pdf . Accessed 20 Mar 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreres-Serafini L, Castillejos L, Martín M, Le Bourgot C, Martín-Orúe SM (2023) Looking for possible benefits of combining short-chain fructo-oligosaccharides (scFOS) with Saccharomyces cerevisiae Sc 47 on weaned pigs orally challenged with Escherichia coli F4+. Animals 13(3):526.  https://doi.org/10.3390/ani13030526</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flint HJ, Scott KP, Louis P, Duncan SH (2012) The role of the gut microbiota in nutrition and health. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 9(10):577–589. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrgastro.2012.156</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2012.156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22945443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu T, Wang Y, Ma M, Dai W, Pan L, Shang Q, Yu G (2023) Isolation of alginate-degrading bacteria from the human gut microbiota and discovery of Bacteroides xylanisolvens AY11–1 as a novel anti-colitis probiotic bacterium. Nutrients 15(6): 1352.  https://doi.org/10.3390/nu15061352</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuglsang A, Nilsson D, Nyborg NCB (2002) Cardiovascular effects of fermented milk containing angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors evaluated in permanently catheterized, spontaneously hypertensive rats. Appl Environ Microbiol 68(7):3566–3569. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.68.7.3566-3569.2002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.7.3566-3569.2002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12089043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">126801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujimura KE, Sitarik AR, Havstad S, Lin DL, Levan S, Fadrosh D, Panzer AR, LaMere B, Rackaityte E, Lukacs NW, Wegienka G, Boushey HA, Ownby DR, Zoratti EM, Levin AM, Johnson CC, Lynch SV (2016) Neonatal gut microbiota associates with childhood multisensitized atopy and T cell differentiation. Nat Med 22(10):1187–1191. https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.4176</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nm.4176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27618652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5053876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gámez-Macías PE, Félix-Soriano E, Samblas M, Sáinz N, Moreno-Aliaga MJ, González-Muniesa P (2024) Intestinal permeability, gut inflammation, and gut immune system response are linked to aging-related changes in gut microbiota composition: a study in female mice. J Gerontol: Series A 79(4). https://doi.org/10.1093/gerona/glae045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Vicente R, Rodriguez-Garcia A, Gomez-Gordo R, Ortega-Hernandez A, Ancos R, Serrano S, Modrego J, Leivas A, Valeri A, Jimenez-Ubieto A, Sanchez-Pina JM, Paciello ML, Gomez-Garre D, Martinez-Lopez J, Linares M (2022) P1430: gut microbiota diversity and butyrate producers Impacts on non-Hodgkin lymphoma patients response to CD19 CAR-T therapy. HemaSphere 6:1313–1314. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.HS9.0000848576.67323.0a</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.HS9.0000848576.67323.0a</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9430719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautier T, Oliviero N, Ferron S, Le Pogam P, David-Le Gall S, Sauvager A, Leroyer P, Cannie I, Dion S, Sweidan A, Loréal O, Tomasi S, Bousarghin L (2022) Bacteroides fragilis derived metabolites, identified by molecular networking, decrease Salmonella virulence in mice model [Original Research]. Front Microbiol 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.1023315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson GR, Roberfroid MB (1995) Dietary modulation of the human colonic microbiota: introducing the concept of prebiotics. J Nutr 125(6):1401–1412. https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/125.6.1401</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jn/125.6.1401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7782892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goh YJ, Barrangou R (2021) Portable CRISPR-Cas9<sup>N</sup> system for flexible genome engineering in Lactobacillus acidophilus, Lactobacillus gasseri, and Lactobacillus paracasei. Appl Environ Microbiol 87(6):e02669-e2620. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.02669-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02669-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33397707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8105030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldenberg JZ, Yap C, Lytvyn L, Lo CK, Beardsley J, Mertz D, Johnston BC (2017) Probiotics for the prevention of Clostridium difficile-associated diarrhea in adults and children. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 12(12):Cd006095. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD006095.pub4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD006095.pub4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29257353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomaa EZ (2020) Human gut microbiota/microbiome in health and diseases: a review. Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek 113(12):2019–2040. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10482-020-01474-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10482-020-01474-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33136284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guarner F, Khan AG, Garisch J, Eliakim R, Gangl A, Thomson A, Krabshuis J, Lemair T, Kaufmann P, de Paula JA, Fedorak R, Shanahan F, Sanders ME, Szajewska H, Ramakrishna BS, Karakan T, Kim N (2012) World gastroenterology organisation global guidelines: probiotics and prebiotics October 2011. J Clin Gastroenterol 46(6):468–481. https://doi.org/10.1097/MCG.0b013e3182549092</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MCG.0b013e3182549092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22688142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo F, Cai D, Li Y, Gu H, Qu H, Zong Q, Bao W, Chen A, Liu H-Y (2021) How early-life gut microbiota alteration sets trajectories for health and inflammatory bowel disease? [Mini Review]. Front Nutr 8. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2021.690073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harsharnjit SG, Rutherfurd KJ, Martin LC, Pramod KG (2001) Enhancement of immunity in the elderly by dietary supplementation with the probiotic Bifidobacterium lactis HN019. Am J Clin Nutr. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajcn/74.6.833</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ajcn/74.6.833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinsen F-A, Knecht H, Neulinger SC, Schmitz RA, Knecht C, Kühbacher T, Rosenstiel PC, Schreiber S, Friedrichs AK, Ott SJ (2015) Dynamic changes of the luminal and mucosa-associated gut microbiota during and after antibiotic therapy with paromomycin. Gut Microbes 6(4):243–254. https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2015.1062959</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2015.1062959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26178862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4615565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill C, Guarner F, Reid G, Gibson GR, Merenstein DJ, Pot B, Morelli L, Canani RB, Flint HJ, Salminen S, Calder PC, Sanders ME (2014) The International scientific association for probiotics and prebiotics consensus statement on the scope and appropriate use of the term probiotic. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 11(8):506–514. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrgastro.2014.66</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2014.66</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24912386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiippala K, Kainulainen V, Suutarinen M, Heini T, Bowers JR, Jasso-Selles D, Lemmer D, Valentine M, Barnes R, Engelthaler DM, Satokari R (2020) Isolation of anti-inflammatory and epithelium reinforcing bacteroides and parabacteroides spp. from a healthy fecal donor. Nutrients 12(4):935</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12040935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32230951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7230855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hori T, Matsuda K, Oishi K (2020) Probiotics: a dietary factor to modulate the gut microbiome, host immune system, and gut–brain interaction. Microorganisms 8(9): 1401.  https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms8091401</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou K, Wu Z-X, Chen X-Y, Wang J-Q, Zhang D, Xiao C, Zhu D, Koya JB, Wei L, Li J, Chen Z-S (2022) Microbiota in health and diseases. Signal Transduct Target Ther 7(1):135. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392-022-00974-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-00974-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35461318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9034083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ian BJ, Denise BL, Paul WOT (2016) Composition and temporal stability of the gut microbiota in older persons. ISME J. https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2015.88</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ismej.2015.88</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain S, Chatterjee A, Panwar S, Yadav AK, Majumdar RS, Kumar A (2021) Metabolic engineering approaches for improvement of probiotics functionality. Adv Probio Sustain Food Med 225–240</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeffery IB, O’Toole PW, Öhman L, Claesson MJ, Deane J, Quigley EM, Simrén M (2012) An irritable bowel syndrome subtype defined by species-specific alterations in faecal microbiota. Gut 61(7):997–1006. https://doi.org/10.1136/gutjnl-2011-301501</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2011-301501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22180058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jian H, Liu Y, Wang X, Dong X, Zou X (2023) Akkermansia muciniphila as a next-generation probiotic in modulating human metabolic homeostasis and disease progression: a role mediated by gut–liver–brain axes? Int J Mol Sci 24(4):3900</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms24043900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36835309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9959343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julien T, Stanislas M, Florence L, Eric P, Christophe C, Jean-Pierre F, Edgardo U, Rafael M-T, Denis LEP, Denis LEP, Renaud N, Joël D, Marion L (2009) Towards the human intestinal microbiota phylogenetic core. Environ Microbiol. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.01982.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.01982.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Junjie Q, Ruiqiang L, Jeroen R, Manimozhiyan A, Kristoffer Sølvsten B, Chaysavanh M, Trine N, Nicolas P, Florence L, Takuji Y, Daniel RM, Junhua L, Junming X, Shaochuan L, Shaochuan L, Dongfang L, Jianjun C, Bo W, Bo W…Jun W (2010) A human gut microbial gene catalogue established by metagenomic sequencing. Nature https://doi.org/10.1038/nature08821</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justin LS, Jian X, Jian X, Jian X, Douglas DL, Chien-Huan C, Chien-Huan C, Benjamin PW, Jeremy W, Jeremy B, Jeffrey IG (2005) Glycan foraging in vivo by an intestine-adapted bacterial symbiont. Science. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1109051</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1109051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kedmi R, Najar TA, Mesa KR, Grayson A, Kroehling L, Hao Y, Hao S, Pokrovskii M, Xu M, Talbot J, Wang J, Germino J, Lareau CA, Satpathy AT, Anderson MS, Laufer TM, Aifantis I, Bartleson JM, Allen PM…Littman DR (2022) A RORγt+ cell instructs gut microbiota-specific Treg cell differentiation. Nature 610(7933): 737-743. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-05089-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ken K, Takehiko I, Tomomi K, Kenshiro O, Hidehiro T, Atsushi T, Hideto T, Hidetoshi M, Vineet KS, Tulika PS, Todd DT, Hideki N, Hiroshi M, Yoshitoshi O, Dusko SE, Dusko SE, Kikuji I, Toshihisa T, Yoshiyuki S…Masahira H (2007) Comparative metagenomics revealed commonly enriched gene sets in human gut microbiomes. DNA Res https://doi.org/10.1093/dnares/dsm018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim CS, Cha L, Sim M, Jung S, Chun WY, Baik HW, Shin DM (2021) Probiotic supplementation improves cognitive function and mood with changes in gut microbiota in community-dwelling older adults: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicenter trial. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci 76(1):32–40. https://doi.org/10.1093/gerona/glaa090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/gerona/glaa090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32300799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim SK, Guevarra RB, Kim YT, Kwon J, Kim H, Cho JH, Kim HB, Lee JH (2019) Role of probiotics in human gut microbiome-associated diseases. J Microbiol Biotechnol 29(9):1335–1340. https://doi.org/10.4014/jmb.1906.06064</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4014/jmb.1906.06064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31434172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King CH, Desai H, Sylvetsky AC, LoTempio J, Ayanyan S, Carrie J, Crandall KA, Fochtman BC, Gasparyan L, Gulzar N, Howell P, Issa N, Krampis K, Mishra L, Morizono H, Pisegna JR, Rao S, Ren Y, Simonyan V…Mazumder R (2019) Baseline human gut microbiota profile in healthy people and standard reporting template. PLOS ONE 14(9): e0206484. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0206484</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleniewska P, Pawliczak R (2024) Can probiotics be used in the prevention and treatment of bronchial asthma? Pharmacol Rep 76(4):740–753. https://doi.org/10.1007/s43440-024-00618-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43440-024-00618-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38951480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">11294272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M, Yadav AK, Verma V, Singh B, Mal G, Nagpal R, Hemalatha R (2016) Bioengineered probiotics as a new hope for health and diseases: an overview of potential and prospects. Future Microbiol 11(4):585–600. https://doi.org/10.2217/fmb.16.4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2217/fmb.16.4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27070955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamberte LE, van Schaik W (2022) Antibiotic resistance in the commensal human gut microbiota. Curr Opin Microbiol 68:102150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mib.2022.102150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2022.102150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35490629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee K, Raguideau S, Sirén K, Asnicar F, Cumbo F, Hildebrand F, Segata N, Cha C-J, Quince C (2023) Population-level impacts of antibiotic usage on the human gut microbiome. Nat Commun 14(1):1191. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-36633-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-36633-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36864029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9981903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R-D, Zheng W-X, Zhang Q-R, Song Y, Liao Y-T, Shi F-C, Wei X-H, Zhou F, Zheng X-H, Tan K-Y, Li Q-Y (2023) Longevity-associated core gut microbiota mining and effect of mediated probiotic combinations on aging mice: case study of a long-lived population in Guangxi. China. Nutrients 15(7):1609. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu15071609</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu15071609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37049450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Xu Y, Le Roy C, Hu J, Steves CJ, Bell JT, Spector TD, Gibson R, Menni C, Rodriguez-Mateos A (2023) Interplay between the (poly)phenol metabolome, gut microbiome, and cardiovascular health in women: a cross-sectional study from the TwinsUK cohort. Nutrients 15(8):1900. https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/15/8/1900</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Makrinioti H, Saglani S, Bowman M, Lin L-L, Camargo CA, Hasegawa K, Zhu Z (2022) Microbial dysbiosis and childhood asthma development: integrated role of the airway and gut microbiome, environmental exposures, and host metabolic and immune response [Mini Review]. Front Immunol 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.1028209</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu CH, Lee SM, VanLare JM, Kasper DL, Mazmanian SK (2008) Regulation of surface architecture by symbiotic bacteria mediates host colonization. Proc Natl Acad Sci 105(10):3951–3956. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0709266105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0709266105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18319345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2268772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Helal SE, Peng N (2023) CRISPR-Cas-based engineering of probiotics. BioDesign Res 5:0017. https://doi.org/10.34133/bdr.0017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34133/bdr.0017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Yang D, Zhang Z, Liu T, Hu G, He M, Zhao S, Peng N (2021) High-efficiency genome editing based on endogenous CRISPR-Cas system enhances cell growth and lactic acid production in Pediococcus acidilactici. Appl Environ Microbiol 87(20):e00948-e921. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.00948-21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00948-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34347520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8478465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loftie-Eaton W, Crabtree A, Perry D, Millstein J, Baytosh J, Stalder T, Robison BD, Forney LJ, Top EM (2021) Contagious antibiotic resistance: plasmid transfer among bacterial residents of the zebrafish gut. Appl Environ Microbiol 87(9):e02735-e2720. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.02735-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02735-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33637574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8091013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozupone CA, Stombaugh JI, Gordon JI, Jansson JK, Knight R (2012) Diversity, stability and resilience of the human gut microbiota. Nature 489(7415):220–230. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11550</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature11550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22972295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3577372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyons KE, Ryan CA, Dempsey EM, Ross RP, Stanton C (2020) Breast milk, a source of beneficial microbes and associated benefits for infant health. Nutrients 12(4). https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12041039</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madigan, Michael T, Martinko J (2005) Brock biology of microorganisms, 11th edn. pp 149–152</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magalhães MI, Azevedo MJ, Castro F, Oliveira MJ, Costa ÂM, Sampaio Maia B (2024) The link between obesity and the gut microbiota and immune system in early-life. Crit Rev Microbiol 1–21. https://doi.org/10.1080/1040841X.2024.2342427</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantziari A, Aakko J, Kumar H, Tölkkö S, du Toit E, Salminen S, Isolauri E, Rautava S (2017) The impact of storage conditions on the stability of Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG and Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis Bb12 in human milk. Breastfeeding Med 12(9):566–569. https://doi.org/10.1089/bfm.2017.0051</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/bfm.2017.0051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcella FS, Hugo LAS, Celso FB, Erick AE, Silvia V, Elane Schwinden P, Roberto PCN, Maria Inês Bruno T, Jaqueline CP, Filomena N, Ramon SR, Jeremias M, Aline dos Santos Garcia G, Renata SLR, Marcia CS, Daniel G, Tatiana Colombo P, Mônica Queiroz de F, Adriano GC (2018) Probiotic Minas Frescal cheese added with L. casei 01: physicochemical and bioactivity characterization and effects on hematological/biochemical parameters of hypertensive overweighted women – a randomized double-blind pilot trial. J Funct Foods. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2018.04.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MarketsandMarkets (2024) Probiotics industry worth $105.7 billion by 2029. https://www.marketsandmarkets.com/PressReleases/probiotics.asp . Accessed 3 Sept 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matzaras R, Nikopoulou A, Protonotariou E, Christaki E (2022) Gut microbiota modulation and prevention of dysbiosis as an alternative approach to antimicrobial resistance: a narrative review. Yale J Biol Med 95(4):479–494</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36568836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9765331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayorga-Ramos A, Zúñiga-Miranda J, Carrera-Pacheco SE, Barba-Ostria C, Guamán LP (2023) CRISPR-Cas-based antimicrobials: design, challenges, and bacterial mechanisms of resistance. ACS Infect Dis 9(7):1283–1302. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsinfecdis.2c00649</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsinfecdis.2c00649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37347230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10353011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazhar SF, Afzal M, Almatroudi AA, Munir S, Ashfaq UA, Rasool M, Raza H, Munir HMS, Rajoka MSR, Khurshid M (2020) The prospects for the therapeutic implications of genetically engineered probiotics. J Food Quality 2020:1–11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2020/9676452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazmanian SK, Round JL, Kasper DL (2008) A microbial symbiosis factor prevents intestinal inflammatory disease. Nature 453(7195):620–625. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature07008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature07008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18509436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazziotta C, Tognon M, Martini F, Torreggiani E, Rotondo JC (2023) Probiotics Mechanism of action on immune cells and beneficial effects on human health. Cells 12(1):184. https://doi.org/10.3390/cells12010184</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cells12010184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36611977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9818925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merenstein D, Pot B, Leyer G, Ouwehand AC, Preidis GA, Elkins CA, Hill C, Lewis ZT, Shane AL, Zmora N, Petrova MI, Collado MC, Morelli L, Montoya GA, Szajewska H, Tancredi DJ, Sanders ME (2023) Emerging issues in probiotic safety: 2023 perspectives. Gut Microbes 15(1):2185034. https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2023.2185034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2023.2185034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36919522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10026873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milani C, Duranti S, Bottacini F, Casey E, Turroni F, Mahony J, Belzer C, Delgado Palacio S, Arboleya Montes S, Mancabelli L, Lugli GA, Rodriguez JM, Bode L, de Vos W, Gueimonde M, Margolles A, van Sinderen D, Ventura M (2017) The first microbial colonizers of the human gut: composition, activities, and health implications of the infant gut microbiota. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 81(4). https://doi.org/10.1128/mmbr.00036-17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mimee M, Tucker AC, Voigt CA, Lu TK (2015) Programming a human commensal bacterium, Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron, to sense and respond to stimuli in the murine gut microbiota. Cell Syst 1(1):62–71. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cels.2015.06.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cels.2015.06.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26918244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4762051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirzaei R, Bouzari B, Hosseini-Fard SR, Mazaheri M, Ahmadyousefi Y, Abdi M, Jalalifar S, Karimitabar Z, Teimoori A, Keyvani H, Zamani F, Yousefimashouf R, Karampoor S (2021) Role of microbiota-derived short-chain fatty acids in nervous system disorders. Biomed Pharmacother 139:111661. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111661</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34243604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naamah LZ, Benjamin JA, Sarah WF, Paul DM, Scott BS, Laurie EC, Athos B (2013) Characterization of adherent bacteroidales from intestinal biopsies of children and young adults with inflammatory bowel disease. PLoS ONE. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0063686</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naamah LZ, Michael JC, Laurie EC (2011) Longitudinal analysis of the prevalence, maintenance, and IgA response to species of the order Bacteroidales in the human gut. Infect Immun. https://doi.org/10.1128/iai.01348-10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/iai.01348-10</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natalia MB, Cristophe M, Cassiana Severiano de S, Priscilla CBVB, Florian C, Vasco A, Philippe L, Jean-Marc C, Jean MC (2017) Microbial Anti-Inflammatory Molecule (MAM) from Faecalibacterium prausnitzii shows a protective effect on DNBS and DSS-Induced colitis model in mice through inhibition of NF-κB pathway. Front Microbiol. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.00114</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NCBI (2024) NCBI Database. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/ . Accessed 19 Mar 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neff CP, Rhodes ME, Arnolds KL, Collins CB, Donnelly J, Nusbacher N, Jedlicka P, Schneider JM, McCarter MD, Shaffer M, Mazmanian SK, Palmer BE, Lozupone CA (2016) Diverse intestinal bacteria contain putative zwitterionic capsular polysaccharides with anti-inflammatory properties. Cell Host Microbe 20(4):535–547. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2016.09.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2016.09.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27693306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5113727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuman H, Koren O (2016) The gut microbiome. In RA Bradshaw &amp; PD Stahl (Eds.), Encyclopedia of cell biology. Academic Press, p 799-808. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-394447-4.20083-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Toole PW, Marchesi JR, Hill C (2017) Next-generation probiotics: the spectrum from probiotics to live biotherapeutics [Article]. Nat Microbiol 2(5):17057. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.57</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.57</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28440276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Toole PW, Marchesi JR, Hill C (2017) Next-generation probiotics: the spectrum from probiotics to live biotherapeutics. Nat Microbiol 2(5):17057. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.57</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.57</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28440276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohr, L. M. (2010). Health benefits of probiotics and prebiotics. Food technology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan M, Nethery MA, Hidalgo-Cantabrana C, Barrangou R (2020) Comprehensive mining and characterization of CRISPR-Cas systems in Bifidobacterium. Microorganisms 8(5): 720.  https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms8050720</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patrice DC, Willem MDV (2017) Next-generation beneficial microbes: the case of Akkermansia muciniphila. Front Microbiol. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01765</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patrick S (2022) A tale of two habitats: Bacteroides fragilis, a lethal pathogen and resident in the human gastrointestinal microbiome. Microbiology 168(4). https://doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.001156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul AMD (2022) Bacteroides species. https://www.hopkinsguides.com/hopkins/view/Johns_Hopkins_ABX_Guide/540053/all/Bacteroides_species . Accessed 15 Mar 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pei T, Zhu D, Yang S, Hu R, Wang F, Zhang J, Yan S, Ju L, He Z, Han Z, He J, Yan Y, Wang M, Xiao W, Ma Y (2022) Bacteroides plebeius improves muscle wasting in chronic kidney disease by modulating the gut-renal muscle axis. J Cell Mol Med 26(24):6066–6078. https://doi.org/10.1111/jcmm.17626</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcmm.17626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36458537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9753468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrariu O-A, Barbu IC, Niculescu A-G, Constantin M, Grigore GA, Cristian R-E, Mihaescu G, Vrancianu CO (2024) Role of probiotics in managing various human diseases, from oral pathology to cancer and gastrointestinal diseases [Review]. Front Microbiol 14. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1296447</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plagens A, Richter H, Charpentier E, Randau L (2015) DNA and RNA interference mechanisms by CRISPR-Cas surveillance complexes. FEMS Microbiol Rev 39(3):442–463. https://doi.org/10.1093/femsre/fuv019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/femsre/fuv019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25934119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5965380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platt DJ, Lawrence D, Rodgers R, Schriefer L, Qian W, Miner CA, Menos AM, Kennedy EA, Peterson ST, Stinson WA, Baldridge MT, Miner JJ (2021) Transferrable protection by gut microbes against STING-associated lung disease. Cell Rep 35(6):109113. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109113</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33979608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8477380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plummer E, Bulach D, Carter G, Albert MJ (2020) Gut microbiome of native Arab Kuwaitis. Gut Pathogens 12(1):10. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13099-020-00351-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13099-020-00351-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32127920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7043038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pricop GR, Gheorghe I, Pircalabioru GG, Cristea V, Popa M, Marutescu L, Chifiriuc MC, Mihaescu G, Bezirtzoglou E (2020) Resistance and virulence features of Bacteroides spp. isolated from abdominal infections in Romanian patients. Pathogens 9(11). https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens9110940</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rebersek M (2021) Gut microbiome and its role in colorectal cancer. BMC Cancer 21(1):1325. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12885-021-09054-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12885-021-09054-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34895176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8666072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivière A, Selak M, Lantin D, Leroy F, De Vuyst L (2016) Bifidobacteria and Butyrate-producing colon bacteria: importance and strategies for their stimulation in the human gut [Review]. Front Microbiol 7. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2016.00979</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts A, Barrangou R (2020) Applications of CRISPR-Cas systems in lactic acid bacteria. FEMS Microbiol Rev 44(5):523–537. https://doi.org/10.1093/femsre/fuaa016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/femsre/fuaa016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32433763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rottinghaus AG, Amrofell MB, Moon TS (2020) Biosensing in smart engineered probiotics. Biotechnol J 15(10):1900319. https://doi.org/10.1002/biot.201900319</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/biot.201900319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saarela MH (2019) Safety aspects of next generation probiotics. Curr Opin Food Sci 30:8–13. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2018.09.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2018.09.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanders ME, Merenstein DJ, Ouwehand AC, Reid G, Salminen S, Cabana MD, Paraskevakos G, Leyer G (2016) Probiotic use in at-risk populations. J Am Pharm Assoc 56(6):680–686. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.japh.2016.07.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.japh.2016.07.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanders ME, Merenstein DJ, Reid G, Gibson GR, Rastall RA (2019) Probiotics and prebiotics in intestinal health and disease: from biology to the clinic. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 16(10):605–616. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41575-019-0173-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41575-019-0173-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31296969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanders ME, Shane AL, Merenstein DJ (2016) Advancing probiotic research in humans in the United States: challenges and strategies. Gut Microbes 7(2):97–100. https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2016.1138198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2016.1138198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26963522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4856453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangineto M, Grander C, Grabherr F, Mayr L, Enrich B, Schwärzler J, Dallio M, Bukke VN, Moola A, Moschetta A, Adolph TE, Sabbà C, Serviddio G, Tilg H (2022) Recovery of Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron ameliorates hepatic steatosis in experimental alcohol-related liver disease. Gut Microbes 14(1):2089006. https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2022.2089006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2022.2089006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35786161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9255095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scopus (2024) Scopus Database. Retrieved 21 February 2024 from https://www.scopus.com/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheflin AM, Whitney AK, Weir TL (2014) Cancer-promoting effects of microbial dysbiosis. Curr Oncol Rep 16(10):406. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11912-014-0406-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11912-014-0406-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25123079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4180221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidor K, Skirecki T (2023) A bittersweet kiss of gram-negative bacteria: the role of ADP-Heptose in the pathogenesis of infection. Microorganisms 11(5):1316. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms11051316</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms11051316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37317291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10221265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh RP, Shadan A, Ma Y (2022) Biotechnological applications of probiotics: a multifarious weapon to disease and metabolic abnormality. Probiotics Antimicro Prot 14(6):1184–1210. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12602-022-09992-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-022-09992-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>So Y, Park S-Y, Park E-H, Park S-H, Kim E-J, Pan J-G, Choi S-K (2017) A highly efficient CRISPR-Cas9-mediated large genomic deletion in Bacillus subtilis [Original Research]. Front Microbiol 8. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01167</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sofi MH, Wu Y, Ticer T, Schutt S, Bastian D, Choi H-J, Tian L, Mealer C, Liu C, Westwater C, Armeson KE, Alekseyenko AV, Yu X-Z (2021) A single strain of Bacteroides fragilis protects gut integrity and reduces GVHD. JCI Insight 6(3). https://doi.org/10.1172/jci.insight.136841</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song L, Huang Y, Liu G, Li X, Xiao Y, Liu C, Zhang Y, Li J, Xu J, Lu S, Ren Z (2022) A novel immunobiotics bacteroides dorei ameliorates influenza virus infection in mice [Original Research]. Front Immunol 12. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2021.828887</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steidler L (2003) Genetically engineered probiotics. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 17(5):861–876. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1521-6918(03)00072-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1521-6918(03)00072-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14507594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stojanov S, Berlec A, Štrukelj B (2020) The influence of probiotics on the Firmicutes/bacteroidetes ratio in the treatment of obesity and inflammatory bowel disease. Microorganisms 8(11):1715</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8111715</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33139627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7692443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun F, Zhang Q, Zhao J, Zhang H, Zhai Q, Chen W (2019) A potential species of next-generation probiotics? The dark and light sides of Bacteroides fragilis in health. Food Res Int 126:108590. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2019.108590</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2019.108590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31732047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Q, Yin S, He Y, Cao Y, Jiang C (2023) Biomaterials and encapsulation techniques for probiotics: current status and future prospects in biomedical applications. Nanomaterials 13(15):2185. https://doi.org/10.3390/nano13152185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano13152185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37570503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10421492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun X, Chen Z, Yu L, Zeng W, Sun B, Fan H, Bai Y (2023) Bacteroides dorei BDX-01 alleviates DSS-induced experimental colitis in mice by regulating intestinal bile salt hydrolase activity and the FXR-NLRP3 signaling pathway [Original Research]. Front Pharmacol 14. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2023.1205323</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Surana NK, Kasper DL (2012) The yin yang of bacterial polysaccharides: lessons learned from B. fragilis PSA. Immunologic Rev 245(1):13–26. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-065X.2011.01075.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.2011.01075.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajkarimi M, Wexler HM (2017) CRISPR-Cas systems in Bacteroides fragilis, an important pathobiont in the human gut microbiome [Original Research]. Front Microbiol 8. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.02234</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamura K, Stecher G, Kumar S (2021) MEGA11: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 11. Mol Biol Evol 38(7):3022–3027. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msab120</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/molbev/msab120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33892491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8233496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan H, Zhai Q, Chen W (2019) Investigations of Bacteroides spp. towards next-generation probiotics. Food Res Int 116:637–644. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2018.08.088</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2018.08.088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30716990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ternes D, Karta J, Tsenkova M, Wilmes P, Haan S, Letellier E (2020) Microbiome in colorectal cancer: how to get from meta-omics to mechanism? Trends Microbiol 28(5):401–423. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tim.2020.01.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2020.01.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32298617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turnbaugh PJ, Ley RE, Hamady M, Fraser-Liggett CM, Knight R, Gordon JI (2007) The human microbiome project. Nature 449(7164):804–810. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature06244</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature06244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17943116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3709439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulsemer P, Toutounian K, Kressel G, Schmidt J, Karsten U, Hahn A, Goletz S (2012) Safety and tolerance of Bacteroides xylanisolvens DSM 23964 in healthy adults. Beneficial Microbes 3(2):99–111. https://doi.org/10.3920/BM2011.0051</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/BM2011.0051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22417778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulsemer P, Toutounian K, Schmidt J, Karsten U, Goletz S (2012) Preliminary safety evaluation of a new Bacteroides xylanisolvens isolate. Appl Environ Microbiol 78(2):528–535. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.06641-11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.06641-11</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22101046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3255732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulsemer P, Toutounian K, Schmidt J, Leuschner J, Karsten U, Goletz S (2012) Safety assessment of the commensal strain Bacteroides xylanisolvens DSM 23964. Regul Toxicol Pharmacol 62(2):336–346. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yrtph.2011.10.014 . Accessed 21 Feb 2024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yrtph.2011.10.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22085591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaid S, Pandey VK, Singh R, Dar AH, Shams R, Thakur KS (2022) A concise review on development of probiotics from Lactobacillus using CRISPR-Cas technology of gene editing. Food Chem Adv 1:100099. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.focha.2022.100099</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.focha.2022.100099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Dijl J, Hecker M (2013) Bacillus subtilis: from soil bacterium to super-secreting cell factory. Microb Cell Fact 12(1):3. https://doi.org/10.1186/1475-2859-12-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1475-2859-12-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23311580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3564730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vital M, Howe AC, Tiedje JM (2014) Revealing the bacterial butyrate synthesis pathways by analyzing (meta)genomic data. mBio 5(2). https://doi.org/10.1128/mbio.00889-00814</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker AW, Lawley TD (2013) Therapeutic modulation of intestinal dysbiosis. Pharmacol Res 69(1):75–86. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2012.09.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2012.09.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23017673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Xiao Y, Yu L, Tian F, Zhao J, Zhang H, Chen W, Zhai Q (2022) Protective effects of different Bacteroides vulgatus strains against lipopolysaccharide-induced acute intestinal injury, and their underlying functional genes. J Adv Res 36:27–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jare.2021.06.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jare.2021.06.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35127162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Zhao J, Zhang H, Lee YK, Zhai Q, Chen W (2021) Roles of intestinal bacteroides in human health and diseases. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 61(21):3518–3536. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2020.1802695</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2020.1802695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32757948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S, Rubio L, Duncan S, Donachie G, Holtrop G, Lo G, Farquharson F, Wagner J, Parkhill J, Louis P, Walker A, Flint H (2020) Pivotal roles for pH, lactate, and lactate-utilizing bacteria in the stability of a human colonic microbial ecosystem. mSystems 5. https://doi.org/10.1128/mSystems.00645-20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Deng H, Li Z, Tan Y, Han Y, Wang X, Du Z, Liu Y, Yang R, Bai Y, Bi Y, Zhi F (2017) Safety evaluation of a novel strain of Bacteroides fragilis [Original Research]. Front Microbiol 8. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.00435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang YF, Qiao M, Zhu D, Zhu YG (2020) Antibiotic resistance in the Collembolan gut microbiome accelerated by the nonantibiotic drug carbamazepine. Environ Sci Technol 54(17):10754–10762. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.0c03075</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.0c03075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32816468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Westbrook AW, Moo-Young M, Chou CP (2016) Development of a CRISPR-Cas9 tool kit for comprehensive engineering of Bacillus subtilis. Appl Environ Microbiol 82(16):4876–4895. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01159-16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01159-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27260361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4968543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wexler AG, Goodman AL (2017) An insider’s perspective: Bacteroides as a window into the microbiome. Nat Microbiol 2:17026. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.26</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.26</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28440278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5679392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wexler Hannah M (2007) Bacteroides: the good, the bad, and the nitty-gritty. Clin Microbiol Rev 20(4):593–621. https://doi.org/10.1128/cmr.00008-07</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/cmr.00008-07</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17934076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2176045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wexler HM (2007) Bacteroides: the good, the bad, and the nitty-gritty. Clin Microbiol Rev 20(4):593–621. https://doi.org/10.1128/cmr.00008-07</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/cmr.00008-07</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17934076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2176045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieërs G, Belkhir L, Enaud R, Leclercq S, Philippart de Foy JM, Dequenne I, de Timary P, Cani PD (2019) How probiotics affect the microbiota. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 9:454. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcimb.2019.00454</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2019.00454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32010640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams NT (2010) Probiotics. Am J Health Syst Pharm 67(6):449–458. https://doi.org/10.2146/ajhp090168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2146/ajhp090168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20208051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wise R (2002) Antimicrobial resistance: priorities for action. J Antimicrob Chemother 49(4):585–586. https://doi.org/10.1093/jac/49.4.585</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/49.4.585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11909829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yagi K, Asai N, Huffnagle GB, Lukacs NW, Fonseca W (2022) Early-life lung and gut microbiota development and respiratory syncytial virus infection [Review]. Front Immunol 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.877771</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang T, Jiang Y, Tang J, Chang G, Zhao W, Hou S, Chen G (2022) Comparison of cecal microbiota and performance indices between lean-type and fatty-type Pekin ducks. Front Microbiol 13:820569. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.820569</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.820569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35350611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8957900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz G, Chan M, Lau CH-F, Capitani S, Kang M, Charron P, Hoover E, Topp E, Guan J (2024) Gut microbiome perturbation affected conjugative transfer of antimicrobial resistance genes. Preprint at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.08.03.605226.abstract</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yim S, Gwon S-Y, Hwang S, Kim NH, Jung BD, Rhee K-J (2013) Enterotoxigenic Bacteroides fragilis causes lethal colitis in Mongolian gerbils. Anaerobe 21:64–66. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anaerobe.2013.03.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2013.03.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23538057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zafar H, Saier MH Jr (2021) Gut Bacteroides species in health and disease. Gut Microbes 13(1):1–20. https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2020.1848158</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2020.1848158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33535896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Virk AK, Khan I, Qin H (2020) Gut Microbiota and Health. In: Li X, Liu P (eds) Gut remediation of environmental pollutants. Springer, Singapore. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-15-4759-1_2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Zhou Q, Liu H, Xu J, Huang R, Shen B, Guo Y, Ai X, Xu J, Zhao X, Liu Y, Wang Y, Zhi F (2023) Bacteroides fragilis strain ZY-312 facilitates colonic mucosa regeneration in colitis via motivating STAT3 signaling pathway induced by IL-22 from ILC3 secretion [Original Research]. Front Immunol 14. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1156762</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Zhu B, Xu J, Liu Y, Qiu E, Li Z, Li Z, He Y, Zhou H, Bai Y, Zhi F (2018) Bacteroides fragilis protects against antibiotic-associated diarrhea in rats by modulating intestinal defenses [Original Research]. Front Immunol 9. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2018.01040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Chen S, Zhang M, Ren F, Ren Y, Li Y, Liu N, Zhang Y, Zhang Q, Wang R (2021) Effects of fermented milk containing Lacticaseibacillus paracasei Strain Shirota on constipation in patients with depression: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Nutrients 13:2238. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13072238</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13072238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34209804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8308326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng L, Tan Y, Hu Y, Shen J, Qu Z, Chen X, Ho CL, Leung EL-H, Zhao W, Dai L (2022) CRISPR/Cas-based genome editing for human gut commensal Bacteroides species. ACS Synth Biol 11(1):464–472. https://doi.org/10.1021/acssynbio.1c00543</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssynbio.1c00543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34990118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou P, Chen C, Patil S, Dong S (2024) Unveiling the therapeutic symphony of probiotics, prebiotics, and postbiotics in gut-immune harmony [Review]. Front Nutrition 11. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2024.1355542</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Q, Shen B, Huang R, Liu H, Zhang W, Song M, Liu K, Lin X, Chen S, Liu Y, Wang Y, Zhi F (2022) Bacteroides fragilis strain ZY-312 promotes intestinal barrier integrity via upregulating the STAT3 pathway in a radiation-induced intestinal injury mouse model [Original Research]. Front Nutrition 9. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.1063699</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu L, Yu T, Wang W, Xu T, Geng W, Li N, Zan X (2024) Responsively degradable nanoarmor-assisted super resistance and stable colonization of probiotics for enhanced inflammation-targeted delivery. Adv Mater 36(18):2308728. https://doi.org/10.1002/adma.202308728</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adma.202308728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou Y, Qiu L, Xie A, Han W, Zhang S, Li J, Zhao S, Li Y, Liang Y, Hu Y (2022) Development and application of a rapid all-in-one plasmid CRISPR-Cas9 system for iterative genome editing in Bacillus subtilis. Microb Cell Fact 21(1):173. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12934-022-01896-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12934-022-01896-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35999638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9400229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuccotti G, Meneghin F, Raimondi C, Dilillo D, Agostoni C, Riva E, Giovannini M (2008) Probiotics in clinical practice: an overview. J Int Med Res 36(1_suppl):1A–53A. https://doi.org/10.1177/14732300080360s101</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>