<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39375277</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1867-1314</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Probiotics and antimicrobial proteins</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>FengycinA-M3 Inhibits Listeria monocytogenes by Binding to Penicillin-Binding Protein 2B Targets to Disrupt Cell Structure.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12602-024-10371-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The contamination of food with Listeria monocytogenes threatens food safety and human health, and developing a novel, green, and safe antimicrobial substance will offer a new food preservation strategy. FengycinA-M3 is a novel lipid peptide with low cytotoxicity and resistance and has effective antibacterial activity against L. monocytogenes with a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 4 µg/mL. Further combined transcriptomics and proteomics analysis yielded 20 differentially expressed genes (DEGs). The MICs of the combined use of FengycinA-M3 and Cefalexin on L. monocytogenes were further determined as FengycinA-M3 (2 µg/mL) and Cefalexin (8 µg/mL) using the checkerboard method. In addition, FengycinA-M3 was found to play a role in delaying pork deterioration. This study explored the inhibitory effect of FengycinA-M3 on L. monocytogenes and its mechanism of action. FengycinA-M3 interacted with penicillin-binding protein 2B on the cell membrane of L. monocytogenes, destroying the permeability of the membrane, causing cell membrane rupture, thereby inhibiting the growth of L. monocytogenes. Overall, FengycinA-M3 is a promising candidate for preventing the emergence and spread of L. monocytogenes with potential applications in food processing.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Ziruo</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Engineering, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, Zhejiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Protein Food Intensive Processing Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315800, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Mengsheng</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Engineering, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, Zhejiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Protein Food Intensive Processing Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315800, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Ming</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Engineering, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, Zhejiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Protein Food Intensive Processing Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315800, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Xiaohu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Engineering, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, Zhejiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Protein Food Intensive Processing Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315800, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xing</LastName><ForeName>Jiali</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ningbo Key Laboratory of Detection, Control, and Early Warning of Key Hazardous Materials in Food, Ningbo Academy of Product and Food Quality Inspection (Ningbo Fibre Inspection Institute), Ningbo, 315048, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Xin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Engineering, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, Zhejiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Protein Food Intensive Processing Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315800, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Chunbao</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Technology, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, PR China. chunbao.li@njau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yanan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Engineering, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, Zhejiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Protein Food Intensive Processing Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315800, PR China. yliu98@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ningbo Key Laboratory of Detection, Control, and Early Warning of Key Hazardous Materials in Food, Ningbo Academy of Product and Food Quality Inspection (Ningbo Fibre Inspection Institute), Ningbo, 315048, China. yliu98@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Technology, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, PR China. yliu98@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>32101907</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>MMLKF22-09</GrantID><Agency>Open Funding Project of the State Key Laboratory of Microbial Metabolism</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101484100</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1867-1306</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Listeria monocytogenes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antibacterial mechanisms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pork preservation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Proteomic analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Transcriptomic analysis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39375277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-024-10371-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12602-024-10371-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Xedzro C, Tano-Debrah K, Nakano H (2022) Antibacterial efficacies and time-kill kinetics of indigenous Ghanaian spice extracts against Listeria monocytogenes and some other food-borne pathogenic bacteria. Microbiol Res 258:126980. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micres.2022.126980</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2022.126980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie M, Ding C, Guo L, Chen G, Zeng H, Liu Q (2018) Evaluation of Caco-2 cells response to Listeria monocytogenes virulence factors by RT-PCR. Microb Pathog 120:79–84. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2018.04.059</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.04.059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senay TE, Ferrell JL, Garrett FG, Albrecht TM, Cho J, D’Orazio SE (2020) Neurotropic lineage III strains of Listeria monocytogenes disseminate to the brain without reaching high titer in the blood. MSphere 5(5):10–1128. https://doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00871-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00871-20</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gray JA, Chandry PS, Kaur M, Kocharunchitt C, Fox EM (2018) Novel biocontrol methods for Listeria monocytogenes biofilms in food production facilities. Front Microbiol 9:605. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2018.00605</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5891606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang YB, Zhang XS, Yuan YL, Bao Y, Xiong MH (2020) Role and modulation of the secondary structure of antimicrobial peptides to improve selectivity. Biomater Sci 8(24):6858–6866. https://doi.org/10.1039/d0bm00801j</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/d0bm00801j</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bechinger B, Gorr SU (2017) Antimicrobial peptides: mechanisms of action and resistance. J Dent Res 96(3):254–260. https://doi.org/10.1177/0022034516679973</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0022034516679973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu JH, Meng F, Du YH, Nelson E, Zhao GR, Qiao JJ et al (2020) Co-production of nisin and γ-aminobutyric acid by engineered Lactococcus lactis for potential application in food preservation. Front Microbiol 11:49. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2020.00049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7000361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharjya S, Straus SK (2020) Design, engineering and discovery of novel α-helical and β-boomerang antimicrobial peptides against drug resistant bacteria. Int J Mol Sci 21(16):5773. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21165773</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms21165773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7460851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu YN, Lu J, Sun J, Lu FX, Bie XM, Lu ZX (2019) Membrane disruption and DNA binding of Fusarium graminearum cell induced by C16-Fengycin A produced by Bacillus amyloliquefaciens. Food Control 102:206–213. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.03.031</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.03.031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Malkmes MJ, Jiang C, Wang P, Zhu L, Zhang H, Jiang L (2021) Antibacterial mechanism and transcriptome analysis of ultra-small gold nanoclusters as an alternative of harmful antibiotics against Gram-negative bacteria. J Hazard Mater 416:126236. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.126236</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.126236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen YL, Li WY, Su RZ, Yang M, Zhang N, Li XM, Tian Y et al (2022) Multi-target antibacterial mechanism of Moringin from Moringa oleifera seeds against Listeria monocytogenes. Front Microbiol 13:925291.  https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.925291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.925291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9213813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou LY, Xu M, Xia R, Zhou ZJ, Han Y (2024) Antimicrobial mechanism of recombinant enterocin CHQS on Listeria monocytogenes and its application on pasteurized milk. Food Control 159:110271. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110271</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu XY, Pang XX, Wu YS, Wu YJ, Shi Y, Zhang XL, Chen QH (2022) Synergistic antibacterial mechanism of Mannosylerythritol Lipid-A and lactic acid on Listeria monocytogenes based on transcriptomic analysis. Foods 11(17):2660. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11172660</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11172660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9455235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai X, Chen T, Wu Y, Tang M, Xu ZF (2021) Selection and validation of reference genes for qRT-PCR analysis in the oil-rich tuber crop tiger nut (Cyperus esculentus) based on transcriptome data. Int J Mol Sci 22(5):2569. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22052569</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms22052569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7961719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Ling N, Jiao R, Zhang XY, Ren YW, Ye YW et al (2023) Transcriptomic analysis reveals novel desiccation tolerance mechanism of cronobacter based on type VI secretion system inhibition. Food Res Int 113143. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2023.113143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai X, Xu Y, Shen Y, Guo N (2022) TMT proteomic analysis for molecular mechanism of Staphylococcus aureus in response to freezing stress. Appl Microbiol Biot 106(8):3139–3152. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253-022-11927-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-022-11927-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Yang Y, Chen C, Li L, Valencak TG, Ren D (2021) Differences in milk fat globule membrane proteins among Murrah, Nili-Ravi and Mediterranean buffaloes revealed by a TMT proteomic approach. Food Res Int 139:109847. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109847</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim DJ, Song JS, Lee BH, Son YK, Kim Y (2023) Qualitative and quantitative analysis of the major bioactive components of Juniperus chinensis L. using LC-QTOF-MS and LC-MSMS and investigation of antibacterial activity against pathogenic bacteria. Molecules 28(9):3937. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules28093937</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules28093937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10180426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi Y, Liu D, Yu H, Zhang G, Fan M (2020) Identification and characterization of the small heat shock protein Hsp20 from Oenococcus oeni SD-2a. Curr Microbiol 77:3595–3602. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00284-020-02168-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00284-020-02168-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An N, Li K, Zhang YK, Wen TT, Liu WX, Jin WJ et al (2021) A multiplex and regenerable surface plasmon resonance (MR-SPR) biosensor for DNA detection of genetically modified organisms. Talanta 231:122361. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2021.122361</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2021.122361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aziz T, Sarwar A, Naveed M, Shahzad M, Shabbir MA, Lin L (2022) Bio-molecular analysis of selected food derived Lactiplantibacillus strains for CLA production reveals possibly a complex mechanism. Food Res Int 154:111031. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111031</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y, Jiang Y, Chen SJ (2022) RNA–ligand molecular docking: advances and challenges. Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Comput Mol Sci 12(3):e1571. https://doi.org/10.1002/wcms.1571</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/wcms.1571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Wu H, Liu J, Hao H, Bi J, Hou H, Zhang G (2023) Synergistic effects of benzyl isothiocyanate and resveratrol against Listeria monocytogenes and their application in chicken meat preservation. Food Chem 419:135984. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.135984</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.135984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai C, Yan P, Yin X, Shu Z, Mintah, BK, He R, Ma H (2024) Surfactin and its antibacterial mechanism on Staphylococcus aureus and application in pork preservation. Food Bioprocess Tech 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947-024-03528-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng DM, Sun SN, Shi LY, Cheng L, Fan ZC (2021) Application of antimicrobial peptide mytichitin-CB in pork preservation during cold storage. Food Control 125:108041. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alirezalu K, Movlan HS, Yaghoubi M, Lorenzo JM (2021) ɛ-polylysine coating with stinging nettle extract for fresh beef preservation. Meat Sci 176:108474. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2021.108474</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2021.108474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao Y, Hao R, Guo Z, Han L, Yu Q, Zhang W (2022) Combined effects of superchilling and natural extracts on beef preservation quality. LWT 153:112520. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112520</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elrayess RA, Mohallal ME, Mobarak YM, Ebaid HM, Abdel-Rahman MA (2022) Scorpion venom antimicrobial peptides induce caspase-1 dependant pyroptotic cell death. Fron Pharmacol 12:788874. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2021.788874</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2021.788874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi D, Su W, Mu Y (2023) Quantitative proteomics study on the changes of egg white of yellow preserved primary chicken eggs soaked in alkali solution. Food Res Int 165:112346. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2022.112346</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.112346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Wang Q (2023) Three genes expressed in relation to lipid metabolism considered as potential biomarkers for the diagnosis and treatment of diabetic peripheral neuropathy. Sci Rep 13(1):8679. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-35908-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-35908-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10227002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakker R, Ellers J, Roelofs D, Vooijs R, Dijkstra T, Hoedjes KM (2023) Combining time-resolved transcriptomics and proteomics data for Adverse Outcome Pathway refinement in ecotoxicology. Sci Total Environ 869:161740. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.161740</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.161740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hackmann TJ, Firkins JL (2015) Electron transport phosphorylation in rumen butyrivibrios: unprecedented ATP yield for glucose fermentation to butyrate. Front Microbiol 6:622. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2015.00622</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00622</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4478896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Y, Li Y, Yang K, Wei G, Huang A (2022) A novel milk-derived peptide effectively inhibits Staphylococcus aureus: interferes with cell wall synthesis, peptidoglycan biosynthesis disruption reaction mechanism, and its application in real milk system. Food Control 144:109374. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109374</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sivaraman GK, Muneeb KH, Sudha S, Shome B, Holmes M (2021) Prevalence of virulent and biofilm forming ST88-IV-t2526 methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus clones circulating in local retail fish markets in Assam. India. Food Control 127:108098. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.FOODCONT.2021.108098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.FOODCONT.2021.108098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Q, Wang P, Wang M, Sun T, Jin H, Wang HB (2017) Thioredoxin and NADPH-dependent thioredoxin reductase C regulation of tetrapyrrole biosynthesis. Plant Physiol 175(2):652–666. https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.16.01500</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1104/pp.16.01500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5619880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chicote J, Yuste VJ, Boix J, Ribas J (2020) Cell death triggered by the autophagy inhibitory drug 3-methyladenine in growing conditions proceeds with DNA damage. Front Pharmacol 11:580343. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2020.580343</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2020.580343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7593545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva IJ, Barahona S, Eyraud A, Lalaouna D, Figueroa-Bossi N, Arraiano CM (2019) SraL sRNA interaction regulates the terminator by preventing premature transcription termination of rho mRNA. Pro Natl Acad Sci 116(8):3042–3051. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1811589116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1811589116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q, Zhang L, Ding W (2020) Eugenol nanocapsules embedded with gelatin-chitosan for chilled pork preservation. Int J Biol Macromol 158:837–844. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.04.182</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.04.182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao SC, Tian L, Qi Q, Hu LM, Wang MM, Gong GL et al (2023) Transcriptome analysis of protocatechualdehyde against Listeria monocytogenes and its effect on chicken quality characteristics. Foods 12(13):2625. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12132625</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12132625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10340166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouhi A, Falah F, Azghandi M, Behbahani BA, Mortazavi SA, Vasiee A (2024) Investigating the effect of Lactiplantibacillus plantarum TW57-4 in preventing biofilm formation and expression of virulence genes in Listeria monocytogenes ATCC 19115. LWT 191:115669. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.115669</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2023.115669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu XW, Yang YJ, Qin Z, Li SH, Bai LX, Ge WB, Li JY (2022) Isobavachalcone from Cullen corylifolium presents significant antibacterial activity against Clostridium difficile through disruption of the cell membrane. Front Pharmacol 13:914188. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2022.914188</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.914188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9356235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen XX, Shen MY, Yang J, Yu Q, Chen Y, Xie JH et al (2022) RNA-Seq based elucidation of mechanism underlying Mesona chinensis Benth polysaccharide protected H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative damage in L02 cells. Food Res Int 157:111383. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111383</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu W, Ye Z, Mao Q, Shan HW, Li JM, Chen JP (2023) Combined transcriptome and proteome analysis of the protein composition of the brochosomes of the leafhopper Nephotettix cincticeps. Insects 14(10):784. https://doi.org/10.3390/insects14100784</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/insects14100784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10607721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin R, Yang SP, Fu B, Chen Y, Qi YG, Xu N, Liu ZJ et al (2023) Antibacterial activity and mechanism of the sesquiterpene δ-cadinene against Listeria monocytogenes. LWT 203:116388. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2024.116388</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2024.116388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taguchi A, Welsh MA, Marmont LS, Lee W, Walker S (2019) FtsW is a peptidoglycan polymerase that is functional only in complex with its cognate penicillin-binding protein. Nat Microbiol 4(4):587–594. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-018-0345-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41564-018-0345-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6430707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M, Tripathi MK, Gupta D, Kumar S, Biswas NR, Kaur P (2023) N-acetylglucosamine-phosphatidylinositol de-N-acetylase as a novel target for probing potential inhibitor against Leishmania donovani. J Biomol Struct Dyn 41(5):1904–1918. https://doi.org/10.1080/07391102.2021.2025429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07391102.2021.2025429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahimi KM, Kumar R, Pakhira W (2023) Enhance the design and performance analysis of a highly sensitive twin-core PCF SPR biosensor with gold plating for the early detection of cancer cells. Plasmonics 18(3):995–1006. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11468-023-01825-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11468-023-01825-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem A, Waris S, Ahmed T, Tabassum R (2021) Biochemical characterization and molecular docking of cloned xylanase gene from Bacillus subtilis RTS expressed in E. coli. Inter J Biol Macromol 168:310–321. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.12.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.12.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shalaby MAW, Dokla EM, Serya RA, Abouzid KA (2020) Penicillin binding protein 2a: an overview and a medicinal chemistry perspective. Eur J Med Chem 199:112312. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2020.112312</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2020.112312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang JS, Gao MK, Bao YH (2022) Antibacterial activity of phillyrin and its effect on the preservation of minced pork. J Food Process Pres 46(10):e16904. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.16904</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.16904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng DM, Yang XM, Sun XQ, Cheng L, Fan ZC (2021) Application of antimicrobial peptide mytichitin-A in pork preservation during refrigerated storage. J Food Process Pres 45(5):e15404. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.15404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.15404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie Y, Zhang M, Gao X, Shao Y, Liu H, Zhang H (2018) Development and antimicrobial application of plantaricin BM-1 incorporating a PVDC film on fresh pork meat during cold storage. J Appl Microb 125(4):1108–1116. https://doi.org/10.1111/jam.13912</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.13912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang FQ, Xu ZP, Chen L, Qiao ZY, Hu YY, Fan XJ, Feng XC et al (2024) Super absorbent resilience antibacterial aerogel with curcumin for fresh pork preservation. Food Control 159:110289. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2024.110289</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2024.110289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng N, Hu ZQ, Li H, Li CZ, Xiao ZH, Zhang B, Cai YJ et al (2024) Physicochemical properties and pork preservation effects of lotus seed drill core powder starch-based active packaging films. Int J Biol Macromol 260:129340. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.129340</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.129340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>