<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39375686</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6750</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Optimization, characterization and biosafety of carotenoids produced from whey using Micrococcus luteus.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>74</StartPage><MedlinePgn>74</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">74</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12896-024-00899-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study aimed to optimize the production of carotenoid pigments from Micrococcus luteus (ATCC 9341) through the statistical screening of media components and the characterization of antimicrobial, antioxidant, cytogenetic and cytotoxic activities. A BOX-Behnken design was used to assess the effects of whey concentration, inoculum size, pH, temperature, and agitation speed on carotenoid yield. The optimum combination increased production to 2.19 g/L, with a productivity of 0.045 g L<sup>-1</sup> h<sup>-1</sup> and a productivity yield of 0.644 g/g, as confirmed by an observed carotene production of 2.19 g/L. The final response surface model fitting the data had an R<sup>2</sup> of 0.9461. High-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) analysis identified 12 carotenoid pigment compounds produced by M. luteus. The extracts displayed moderate antimicrobial efficacy against Gram-positive bacteria such as Bacillus cereus (ATCC 11778), Staphylococcus aureus (ATCC 6538), and E. faecalis (ATCC 19433), with inhibition zone diameters (IZD) of 29.0, 14.0, and 37.0 mm, respectively, at 1000 μg/mL. However, its effectiveness against Gram-negative bacteria is limited. In comparison, tetracycline exhibited greater antimicrobial potency. The IC<sub>50</sub> value of carotenoids was used to indicate the antioxidant activity. IC<sub>50</sub> value from the DPPH assay was 152.80 mg/100mL. An IC<sub>50</sub> cytotoxicity value greater than 300 μg/mL was found against normal mouse liver cells, with over 68% cell viability even at 300 μg/mL, indicating low toxicity. Histological structure studies revealed normal myocardial muscle tissue, lung tissue, and kidney tissue sections, whereas liver tissue sections revealed ballooning degeneration of hepatocytes and disorganization of hepatic cords. Cytogenetic parameters revealed that the carotene treatment group had a mitotic index (70%) lower than that of the control but higher than that of the positive control, mitomycin, and did not substantially increase numerical (1.2%) or structural aberrations compared with those of the control, suggesting a lack of genotoxic effects under the experimental conditions. In conclusion, optimized culture conditions enhanced carotenoid yields from M. luteus, and the extracts displayed promising bioactivity as moderate antibiotics against certain gram-positive bacteria and as antioxidants. The high IC<sub>50</sub> values demonstrate biosafety. Overall, this bioprocess for enhanced carotenoid production coupled with bioactivity profiling and low cytotoxicity support the application of M. luteus carotenoids.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Hegazy</LastName><ForeName>Aml A</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Science Department, Faculty of Agriculture, Ain Shams University, Cairo, 11241, Egypt. aml_hegazy@agr.asu.edu.eg.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Abu-Hussien</LastName><ForeName>Samah H</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Microbiology Department, Faculty of Agriculture, Ain Shams University, Cairo, 11241, Egypt. samah_hashem1@agr.asu.edu.eg.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elsenosy</LastName><ForeName>Neima K</ForeName><Initials>NK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Genetics Department, Faculty of Agriculture, Ain Shams University, Cairo, 11241, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Sayed</LastName><ForeName>Salwa M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biochemistry Department, Faculty of Agriculture, Ain Shams University, Cairo, 11241, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abo El-Naga</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed Y</ForeName><Initials>MY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Science Department, Faculty of Agriculture, Ain Shams University, Cairo, 11241, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088663</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6750</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>36-88-4</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D002338">Carotenoids</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000975">Antioxidants</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016982" MajorTopicYN="Y">Micrococcus luteus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002338" MajorTopicYN="Y">Carotenoids</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000067796" MajorTopicYN="Y">Whey</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000975" MajorTopicYN="Y">Antioxidants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006094" MajorTopicYN="N">Gram-Positive Bacteria</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008826" MajorTopicYN="N">Microbial Sensitivity Tests</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">M. luteus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antimicrobial activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antioxidant properties</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioprocess safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Carotenoid optimization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Whey</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39375686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12896-024-00899-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12896-024-00899-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11459989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rather LJ, Mir SS, Ganie SA, Shahid-ul-Islam, Li Q. Research progress, challenges, and perspectives in microbial pigment production for industrial applications - a review. Dyes Pigm. 2023;210:110989.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramesh C, Vinithkumar NV, Kirubagaran R, Venil CK, Dufossé L. Multifaceted applications of microbial pigments: current knowledge, challenges and future directions for public health implications. Microorganisms. 2019;7:7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6680428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31261756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venil CK, Dufossé L, Renuka Devi P. Bacterial pigments: sustainable compounds with market potential for Pharma and Food Industry. Front Sustainable Food Syst. 2020;4:100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orlandi VT, Martegani E, Giaroni C, Baj A, Bolognese F. Bacterial pigments: a colorful palette reservoir for biotechnological applications. Biotechnol Appl Chem. 2022;69:981–1001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9544673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33870552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senadheera TRL, Hossain A, Shahidi F. Marine bioactives and their application in the food industry: a review. Appl Sci (Switzerland). 2023;13:13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saini RK, Keum YS. Microbial platforms to produce commercially vital carotenoids at industrial scale: an updated review of critical issues. J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol. 2019;46:657–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30415292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saini RK, Prasad P, Lokesh V, Shang X, Shin J, Keum YS, et al. Carotenoids: dietary sources, extraction, encapsulation, bioavailability, and health benefits—a review of recent advancements. Antioxidants. 2022;11:11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9025559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35453480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiki MJ. Biopigments of Microbial Origin and their application in the Cosmetic Industry. Cosmetics. 2023;10:47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasubramaniam V, Gunasegavan RDN, Mustar S, Lee JC, Noh MFM. Isolation of industrial important bioactive compounds from microalgae. Molecules. 2021;26:943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7916812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33579001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umadevi K, Krishnaveni M. Antibacterial activity of pigment produced from Micrococcus luteus KF532949. Int J Chem Anal Sci. 2013;4:149–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva AF, Banat IM, Giachini AJ, Robl D. Fungal biosurfactants, from nature to biotechnological product: bioprospection, production and potential applications. Bioprocess Biosyst Eng. 2021;44:2003–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8205652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34131819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poonia A, Pandey S. Production of microbial pigments from whey and their applications: a review. Nutr Food Sci. 2023;53:265–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahin YH, Elwakil BH, Ghareeb DA, Olama ZA. Micrococcus lylae MW407006 pigment: production, optimization, nano-pigment synthesis, and biological activities. Biology (Basel). 2022;11:11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9405233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36009797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nieri P, Carpi S, Esposito R, Costantini M, Zupo V. Bioactive molecules from Marine diatoms and their value for the Nutraceutical Industry. Nutrients. 2023;15:464.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9861441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36678334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masaeli R, Zandsalimi K, Tayebi L. Biomaterials evaluation: conceptual refinements and practical reforms. Ther Innov Regul Sci. 2019;53:120–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29756484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mussagy CU, Winterburn J, Santos-Ebinuma VC, Pereira JFB. Production and extraction of carotenoids produced by microorganisms. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2019;103:1095–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30560452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raita S, Feldmane L, Kusnere Z, Spalvins K, Kuzmika I, Berzina I, et al. Microbial carotenoids production: strains, conditions, and yield affecting factors. Environ Clim Technol. 2023;27:1027–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-Elhalim BT, Gamal RF, El-Sayed SM, Abu-Hussien SH. Optimizing alpha-amylase from Bacillus amyloliquefaciens on bread waste for effective industrial wastewater treatment and textile desizing through response surface methodology. Sci Rep. 2023;13:13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10628158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37932353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang F, Chen L, Jiang S, He J, Zhang X, Peng J, et al. Optimization of methazolamide-loaded solid lipid nanoparticles for ophthalmic delivery using Box-Behnken design. J Liposome Res. 2014;24:171–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24611687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montero-Lobato Z, Ramos-Merchante A, Fuentes JL, Sayago A, Fernández-Recamales Á, Martínez-Espinosa RM, et al. Optimization of growth and carotenoid production by haloferax mediterranei using response surface methodology. Mar Drugs. 2018;16:372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6213265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30304770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biehler E, Mayer F, Hoffmann L, Krause E, Bohn T. Comparison of 3 spectrophotometric methods for carotenoid determination in frequently consumed fruits and vegetables. J Food Sci. 2010;75:C55-61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20492150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-Elhalim BT, Hemdan BA, El-Sayed SM, Ahmed MA, Maan SA, Abu-Hussien SH. Enhancing durability and sustainable preservation of Egyptian stone monuments using metabolites produced by Streptomyces exfoliatus. Sci Rep. 2023;13:13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10257707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37301893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gargouri W, Osés SM, Fernández-Muiño MA, Sancho MT, Kechaou N. Evaluation of bioactive compounds and biological activities of Tunisian propolis. LWT. 2019;111:328–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humphries RM, Ambler J, Mitchell SL, Castanheira M, Dingle T, Hindler JA, et al. CLSI methods development and standardization working group best practices for evaluation of antimicrobial susceptibility tests. J Clin Microbiol. 2018;56:e01934-17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5869819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29367292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abu-Hussien SH, Hemdan BA, Alzahrani OM, Alswat AS, Alatawi FA, Alenezi MA, et al. Microbial degradation, spectral analysis and toxicological assessment of malachite green dye by streptomyces exfoliatus. Molecules. 2022;27:6456.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9572514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36234993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norizadeh Tazehkand M, Topaktas M, Yilmaz MB. Assessment of chromosomal aberration in the bone marrow cells of Swiss albino mice treated by 4-methylimidazole. Drug Chem Toxicol. 2016;39:307–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26634952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dias MG, Borge GIA, Kljak K, Mandić AI, Mapelli-Brahm P, Olmedilla-Alonso B, et al. European database of carotenoid levels in foods factors affecting carotenoid content. Foods. 2021;10:912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8143354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33919309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan UM, Sevindik M, Zarrabi A, Nami M, Ozdemir B, Kaplan DN, et al. Lycopene: food sources, biological activities, and human health benefits. Oxid Med Cell Longev. 2021;2021:2713511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8626194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34840666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esatbeyoglu T, Rimbach G. Canthaxanthin: from molecule to function. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2017;61:1600469.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27687695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steven R, Humaira Z, Natanael Y, Dwivany FM, Trinugroho JP, Dwijayanti A, et al. Marine Microbial-Derived Resource Exploration: uncovering the hidden potential of Marine carotenoids. Mar Drugs. 2022;20:352.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9229179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35736155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogacz-Radomska L, Harasym J, Piwowar A. Commercialization aspects of carotenoids. In Carotenoids: Properties, Processing and Applications. Academic Press; 2020. p. 327–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rammuni MN, Ariyadasa TU, Nimarshana PHV, Attalage RA. Comparative assessment on the extraction of carotenoids from microalgal sources: Astaxanthin from H. pluvialis and β-carotene from D. salina. Food Chem. 2019;277:128–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30502128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sui Y, Mazzucchi L, Acharya P, Xu Y, Morgan G, Harvey PJ. A comparison of β-carotene, phytoene and amino acids production in Dunaliella salina DF 15 (CCAP 19/41) and Dunaliella salina CCAP 19/30 using different light wavelengths. Foods. 2021;10:10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8617983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34829102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu F, Yuan QP, Zhu Y. Improved production of lycopene and β-carotene by Blakeslea trispora with oxygen-vectors. Process Biochem. 2007;42:289–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harith ZT, Lima M, de Charalampopoulos A, Chatzifragkou DA. Optimised production and extraction of astaxanthin from the yeast Xanthophyllomyces Dendrorhous. Microorganisms. 2020;8:430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7143781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32204306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi K, Kumar P, Kataria R. Microbial carotenoid production and their potential applications as antioxidants: a current update. Process Biochem. 2023;128:190–205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilieva Y, Zaharieva MM, Najdenski H, Kroumov AD. Antimicrobial activity of Arthrospira (former Spirulina) and Dunaliella related to recognized antimicrobial bioactive compounds. Int J Mol Sci. 2024;25:5548.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11122404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38791586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanad M, Ramadan AHM, Hikal DM. Antimicrobial activity of natural anthocyanins and carotenoids extracted from some plants and wastes. J food dairy sci 2010; 1:7:413–427</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fadilah NIM, Ahmat N, Hao LQ, Maarof M, Rajab NF, Idrus RBH, et al. Biological safety assessments of high-purified ovine collagen type I biomatrix for future therapeutic product: International Organisation for Standardisation (ISO) and Good Laboratory Practice (GLP) settings. Polymers (Basel). 2023;15:2436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10255646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37299233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antunes A, Carmo F, Pinto S, Andrade N, Martel F. The anti-proliferative effect of β-carotene against a triple-negative breast cancer cell line is cancer cell-specific and JNK-dependent. PharmaNutrition. 2022;22:100320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vijay K, Sowmya PRR, Arathi BP, Shilpa S, Shwetha HJ, Raju M, et al. Low-dose doxorubicin with carotenoids selectively alters redox status and upregulates oxidative stress-mediated apoptosis in breast cancer cells. Food Chem Toxicol. 2018;118:675–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29920287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sowmya Shree G, Yogendra Prasad K, Arpitha HS, Deepika UR, Nawneet Kumar K, Mondal P, et al. β-carotene at physiologically attainable concentration induces apoptosis and down-regulates cell survival and antioxidant markers in human breast cancer (MCF-7) cells. Mol Cell Biochem. 2017;436:1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28550445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du C, Guo Y, Cheng Y, Han M, Zhang W, Qian H. Anti-cancer effects of torulene, isolated from Sporidiobolus Pararoseus, on human prostate cancer LNCaP and PC-3 cells via a mitochondrial signal pathway and the down-regulation of AR expression. RSC Adv. 2017;7:2466–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zagrosek A, Abdel-Aty H, Boyé P, Wassmuth R, Messroghli D, Utz W, et al. Cardiac magnetic resonance monitors reversible and irreversible myocardial Injury in Myocarditis. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2009;2:131–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19356545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dragos X, Vasilescu M, Phillion AB, Kinose D, Verleden SE, Vanaudenaerde BM, et al. Comprehensive stereological assessment of the human lung using multiresolution computed tomography. J Appl Physiol. 2020;128:1604–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7311688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32298211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venet L, Pati S, Feldman MD, Nasrallah MP, Yushkevich P, Bakas S. Accurate and robust alignment of differently stained histologic images based on greedy diffeomorphic registration. Appl Sci (Switzerland). 2021;11:1–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8291745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34290888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wyrobek A J, Eskenazi B, Young S, Arnheim N, Tiemann-Boege I, Jabs,E. W, &amp; Evenson D. Advancing age has differential effects on DNA damage, chromatin integrity, gene mutations, and aneuploidies in sperm. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2006;103:9601–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1480453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16766665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rjiba-Touati K, Ayed-Boussema I, Guedri Y, Achour A, Bacha H, Abid S. Role of recombinant human erythropoietin in mitomycin C-induced genotoxicity: analysis of DNA fragmentation, chromosome aberrations and micronuclei in rat bone-marrow cells. Mutat Res Genet Toxicol Environ Mutagen. 2013;753:48–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23376209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Guo Y, Zhang C, Wu R, Yang AY, Gaspar J, et al. Dietary phytochemicals and cancer chemoprevention: a perspective on oxidative stress, inflammation, and epigenetics. Chem Res Toxicol. 2016;29:2071–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27989132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>