<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39373837</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1614-7499</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science and pollution research international</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Harnessing the potential of copper-based nanoparticles in mitigating abiotic and biotic stresses in crops.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11356-024-35174-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The demand for crops production continues to intensify with the rapid increase in population. Agricultural crops continue to encounter abiotic and biotic stresses, which can substantially hamper their productivity. Numerous strategies have been focused to tackle the abiotic and biotic stress factors in various plants. Nanotechnology has displayed great potential to minimize the phytotoxic impacts of these environmental constraints. Copper (Cu)-based nanoparticles (NPs) have displayed beneficial effects on plant growth and stress tolerance. Cu-based NPs alone or in combination with plant growth hormones or microorganisms have been documented to induce plant tolerance and mitigate abiotic or biotic stresses in different plants. In this review, we have comprehensively discussed the uptake and translocation of Cu-based NPs in plants, and beneficial roles in improving the plant growth and development at various growth stages. Moreover, we have discussed how Cu-based NPs mechanistically modulate the physiological, biochemical, metabolic, cellular, and metabolic functions to enhance plant tolerance against both biotic (viruses, bacterial and fungal diseases, etc.) and abiotic stresses (heavy metals or metalloids, salt, and drought stress, etc.). We elucidated recent advancements, knowledge gaps, and recommendations for future research. This review would help plant and soil scientists to adapt Cu-based novel strategies such as nanofertilizers and nanopesticides to detoxify the abiotic or biotic stresses. These outcomes may contribute to the promotion of healthy food production and food security, thus providing new avenues for sustainable agriculture production.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Kaleem</LastName><ForeName>Zohaib</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Crop Science, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs Key Laboratory of Spectroscopy Sensing, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Wan</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang Institute of Subtropical Crops, Zhejiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Wenzhou, 325005, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Ulhassan</LastName><ForeName>Zaid</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Crop Science, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs Key Laboratory of Spectroscopy Sensing, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shahbaz</LastName><ForeName>Hafsah</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Animal and Dairy Sciences, University of Agriculture Faisalabad, Faisalabad, 38040, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, 212013, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Di</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Crop Science, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs Key Laboratory of Spectroscopy Sensing, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Naeem</LastName><ForeName>Shoaib</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agriculture Officer (Extension) Jauharabad, Office of Assistant Director Agriculture (Extension) Khushab, Punjab, 41000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Sharafat</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Crop Science, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs Key Laboratory of Spectroscopy Sensing, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shah</LastName><ForeName>Aamir Mehmood</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Landscape Architecture, Sichuan Agricultural University, Chengdu, 611130, Sichuan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sheteiwy</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Integrative Agriculture, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, Al-Ain, United Arab Emirates University, Abu-Dhabi, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agronomy, Faculty of Agriculture, Mansoura University, Mansoura, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Weijun</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1471-9644</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Crop Science, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs Key Laboratory of Spectroscopy Sensing, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China. wjzhou@zju.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2023C02002-3</GrantID><Agency>Science and Technology Program of Zhejiang Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2022SNJF010</GrantID><Agency>Department of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of Zhejiang Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9441769</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0944-1344</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Abiotic stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biotic stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Copper nanoparticles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Crop yield</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanotechnology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Plant tolerance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39373837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-35174-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11356-024-35174-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Kader HA, Yousef N, Hossain MA, Dawood MF (2023) Lipid production, oxidative status, antioxidant enzymes and photosynthetic efficiency of Coccomyxa chodatii SAG 216–2 in response to calcium oxide nanoparticles. Phyt-Int J Exp Bot 92:1955–1974</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Wahab DA, Othman NA, Hamada AM (2019) Effects of copper oxide nanoparticles to Solanum nigrum and its potential for phytoremediation. Plant Cell Tiss Organ Cult 137:525–539</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11240-019-01588-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adrees M, Ali S, Rizwan M, Ibrahim M, Abbas F, Farid M, Bharwana SA (2015) The effect of excess copper on growth and physiology of important food crops: a review. Environ Sci Pollut Res 22:8148–8162</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-015-4496-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed F, Javed B, Razzaq A, Mashwani ZUR (2021) Applications of copper and silver nanoparticles on wheat plants to induce drought tolerance and increase yield. IET Nanobiotechnol 15:68–78</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1049/nbt2.12002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed M, Abdel-Fattah GG, Holford P, Korany SM, Alsherif EA, AbdElgawad H, Ulhassan Z, Jośko I, Ali B, Sheteiwy MS (2023) Funneliformis constrictum modulates polyamine metabolism to enhance tolerance of Zea mays L. to salinity. Microbiol Res 266:127254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2022.127254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhaithloul HAS, Ali B, Alghanem SMS, Zulfiqar F, Al-Robai SA, Ercisli S, Yong JWH, Moosa A, Irfan E, Ali Q, Irshad MA (2023) Effect of green-synthesized copper oxide nanoparticles on growth, physiology, nutrient uptake, and cadmium accumulation in Triticum aestivum (L.). Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 268:115701</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2023.115701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali S, Gill RA, Ulhassan Z, Zhang N, Hussain S, Zhang K, Huang Q, Sagir M, Tahir MB, Gill MB, Mwamba TM (2023) Exogenously applied melatonin enhanced the tolerance of Brassica napus against cobalt toxicity by modulating antioxidant defense, osmotic adjustment, and expression of stress response genes. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 252:114624</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2023.114624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali S, Ulhassan AS, Kaleem Z, Yousaf MA, Sheteiwy MS, Ali S, Waseem M, Jalil S, Wang J, Zhou W (2024a) Differential responses of Brassica napus cultivars to dual effects of magnesium oxide nanoparticles. Environ Sci Pollut Res 31:12446–12466</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-31977-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali S, Ulhassan Z, Shahbaz H, Kaleem Z, Yousaf MA, Ali S, Sheteiwy MS, Waseem M, Ali S, Zhou W (2024b) Application of magnesium oxide nanoparticles as novel sustainable approach in enhancing crop tolerance to abiotic and biotic stresses. Environ Sci Nano 11:3250. https://doi.org/10.1039/D4EN00417E</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D4EN00417E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Khayri JM, Rashmi R, Surya Ulhas R, Sudheer WN, Banadka A, Nagella P, Aldaej MI, Rezk AAS, Shehata WF, Almaghasla MI (2023) The role of nanoparticles in response of plants to abiotic stress at physiological, biochemical, and molecular levels. Plants 12:292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants12020292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allan DL, Jarrell WM (1989) Proton and copper adsorption to maize and soybean root cell walls. Plant Physiol 89:823–832</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1104/pp.89.3.823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ando Y, Nagata S, Yanagisawa S, Yoneyama T (2013) Copper in xylem and phloem saps from rice (Oryza sativa): the effect of moderate copper concentrations in the growth medium on the accumulation of five essential metals and a speciation analysis of copper-containing compounds. Funct Plant Biol 40:89–100</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1071/FP12158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andualem WW, Sabir FK, Mohammed ET, Belay HH, Gonfa BA (2020) Synthesis of copper oxide nanoparticles using plant leaf extract of Catha edulis and its antibacterial activity. J Nano 2020:2932434</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attia MS, Balabel NM, Ababutain IM, Osman MS, Nofel MM, Abd Elkodous M, Elkhatib WF, El-Sayyad GS, El-Batal AI (2021) Protective role of copper oxide-streptomycin nano-drug against potato brown rot disease caused by ralstonia solanacearum. J Cluster Sci 33:1373–1386</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10876-021-02048-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azimi R, Jankju Borzelabad M, Feizi H, Azimi A (2014) Interaction of SiO<sub>2</sub> nanoparticles with seed prechilling on germination and early seedling growth of tall wheatgrass (Agropyron elongatum L.). Polish J Chem Technol 16:25–29</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2478/pjct-2014-0045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badawy AA, Abdelfattah NA, Salem SS, Awad MF, Fouda A (2021) Efficacy assessment of biosynthesized copper oxide nanoparticles (CuO-NPs) on stored grain insects and their impacts on morphological and physiological traits of wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) plant. Biology 10:233</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biology10030233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baskar V, Nayeem S, Kuppuraj SP, Muthu T, Ramalingam S (2018) Assessment of the effects of metal oxide nanoparticles on the growth, physiology and metabolic responses in in vitro grown eggplant (Solanum melongena). 3 Biotech 8:362</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13205-018-1386-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonilla-Bird NJ, Ye Y, Akter T, Valdes-Bracamontes C, Darrouzet-Nardi AJ, Saupe GB, Flores-Marges JP, Ma L, Hernandez-Viezcas JA, Peralta-Videa JR, Gardea-Torresdey JL (2020) Effect of copper oxide nanoparticles on two varieties of sweetpotato plants. Plant Physiol Biochem 154:277–286</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2020.06.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Mao S, Xu Z, Ding W (2019) Various antibacterial mechanisms of biosynthesized copper oxide nanoparticles against soilborne Ralstonia solanacearum. RSC Adv 9:3788–3799</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C8RA09186B</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen JN, Wu LT, Song K, Zhu YS, Ding W (2022a) Nonphytotoxic copper oxide nanoparticles are powerful “nanoweapons” that trigger resistance in tobacco against the soil-borne fungal pathogen Phytophthora nicotianae. J Inte Agri 21:3245–3262</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jia.2022.08.086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen W, Miao Y, Ayyaz A, Hannan F, Huang Q, Ulhassan Z, Zhou Y, Islam F, Hong Z, Farooq MA, Zhou W (2022b) Purple stem Brassica napus exhibits higher photosynthetic efficiency, antioxidant potential and anthocyanin biosynthesis related genes expression against drought stress. Front Plant Sci 13:936696</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.936696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cumplido-Nájera CF, González-Morales S, Ortega-Ortíz H, Cadenas-Pliego G, Benavides-Mendoza A, Juárez-Maldonado A (2019) The application of copper nanoparticles and potassium silicate stimulate the tolerance to Clavibacter michiganensis in tomato plants. Scien Horticul 245:82–89</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2018.10.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Costa MVJ, Sharma PK (2016) Effect of copper oxide nanoparticles on growth, morphology, photosynthesis, and antioxidant response in Oryza sativa. Photosynthetica 54:110–119</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11099-015-0167-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Datta Majumdar T, Ghosh CK, Mukherjee A (2021) Dual role of copper nanoparticles in bacterial leaf blight-infected rice: a therapeutic and metabolic approach. ACS Agri Sci Tech 1:160–172</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsagscitech.0c00064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng C, Wang Y, Navarro G, Sun Y, Cota-Ruiz K, Hernandez-Viezcas JA, Niu G, Li C, White JC, Gardea-Torresdey J (2022) Copper oxide (CuO) nanoparticles affect yield, nutritional quality, and auxin associated gene expression in weedy and cultivated rice (Oryza sativa L.) grains. Sci Total Environ 810:152260</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Derbalah A, Abdelsalam I, Behiry SI, Abdelkhalek A, Abdelfatah M, Ismail S, Elsharkawy MM (2022) Copper oxide nanostructures as a potential method for control of zucchini yellow mosaic virus in squash. Pest Manag Sci 78:3587–3595</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ps.7001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di X, Fu Y, Xu Y, Zheng S, Huang Q, Sun Y (2023) Assessment of CuO NPs on soil microbial community structure based on phospholipid fatty acid techniques and phytotoxicity of bok choy seedlings. Plant Physiol Biochem 197:107657</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2023.107657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dimkpa CO, Bindraban PS, Fugice J, Agyin-Birikorang S, Singh U, Hellums D (2017) Composite micronutrient nanoparticles and salts decrease drought stress in soybean. Agron Sustain Dev 37:5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13593-016-0412-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elmer WH, Zuverza-Mena N, Triplett LR, Roberts EL, Silady RA, White JC (2021) Foliar application of copper oxide nanoparticles suppresses fusarium wilt development on chrysanthemum. Environ Sci Tech 55:10805–10810</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c02323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Moneim DA, Dawood MF, Moursi YS, Farghaly AA, Afifi M, Sallam A (2021) Positive and negative effects of nanoparticles on agricultural crops. Nanotechnol Environ Eng 6:21. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41204-021-00117-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41204-021-00117-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Essa HL, Abdelfattah MS, Marzouk AS, Shedeed Z, Guirguis HA, El-Sayed MM (2021) Biogenic copper nanoparticles from Avicennia marina leaves: impact on seed germination, detoxification enzymes, chlorophyll content and uptake by wheat seedlings. PLoS One 16:0249764</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0249764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faraz A, Faizan M, Hayat S, Alam P (2022) Foliar application of copper oxide nanoparticles increases the photosynthetic efficiency and antioxidant activity in Brassica juncea. J Food Qual 2022:1–10. https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/5535100</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/5535100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faraz A, Faizan M, Rajput VD, Minkina T, Hayat S, Faisal M, Alatar AA, Abdel-Salam EM (2023) CuO nanoparticle-mediated seed priming improves physio-biochemical and enzymatic activities of Brassica juncea. Plants 12:803</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants12040803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima A, Singh S, Prasad SM (2020) Interaction between copperoxide nanoparticles and plants: uptake, accumulation and phytotoxicity. In: Hayat S, Pichtel J, Faizan M, Fariduddin Q (eds) Sustainable Agriculture Reviews 41. Sustainable Agriculture Reviews, vol 41. Springer, Cham. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-33996-8_8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-33996-8_8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleischer MA, Neill O, Ehwald R (1999) The pore size of non-graminaceous plant cell wall is rapidly decreased by borate ester cross-linking of the pectic polysaccharide rhamnogalacturon II. Plant Physiol 121:829–838</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1104/pp.121.3.829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu L, Su T, Wei D, Wu D, Zhang G, Shen Q (2022) Copper oxide nanoparticles alleviate cadmium toxicity in cereal crops. Environ Sci Nano 9:3502–3513</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D2EN00213B</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautam V, Kaur R, Kohli SK, Verma V, Kaur P, Singh R, Saini P, Arora S, Thukral AK, Karpets YV, Kolupaev YE (2017) ROS compartmentalization in plant cells under abiotic stress condition. In: Khan M, Khan N (eds) Reactive oxygen species and antioxidant systems in plants: role and regulation under abiotic stress. Springer, Singapore. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-10-5254-5_4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-981-10-5254-5_4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geppert M, Sigg L, Schirmer K (2021) Toxicity and translocation of Ag, CuO, ZnO and TiO 2 nanoparticles upon exposure to fish intestinal epithelial cells. Environ Sci: Nano 8:2249–2260</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gkanatsiou Ch, Ntalli N, Menkissoglu-Spiroudi U, Dendrinou-Samara C (2019) Essential metal-based nanoparticles (copper/iron NPs) as potent nematicidal agents against Meloidogyne spp. J Nanotech Res 1:44–58</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-García Y, Cárdenas-Álvarez C, Cadenas-Pliego G, Benavides-Mendoza A, Cabrera-de-la-Fuente M, Sandoval-Rangel A, Valdés-Reyna J, Juárez-Maldonado A (2021) Effect of three nanoparticles (Se, Si and Cu) on the bioactive compounds of bell pepper fruits under saline stress. Plants 10:217</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants10020217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Großmann D, Dreier A, Lehmann CW, Grünert W (2015) Encapsulation of copper and zinc oxide nanoparticles inside small diameter carbon nanotubes. Microporous Mesoporous Mater 202:189–197</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micromeso.2014.09.057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassanisaadi M, Barani M, Rahdar A, Heidary M, Thysiadou A, Kyzas GZ (2022) Role of agrochemical-based nanomaterials in plants: biotic and abiotic stress with germination improvement of seeds. Plant Growth Regul 97:375–418</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10725-021-00782-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Fuentes AD, López-Vargas ER, Pinedo-Espinoza JM, Campos-Montiel RG, Valdés-Reyna J, Juárez-Maldonado A (2017) Postharvest behavior of bioactive compounds in tomato fruits treated with Cu nanoparticles and NaCl stress. Appl Sci 7:980</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app7100980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Hernández H, González-Morales S, Benavides-Mendoza A, Ortega Ortiz H, Cadenas-Pliego G, Juárez-Maldonado A (2018) Effects of chitosan PVA and Cu nanoparticles on the growth and antioxidant capacity of tomato under saline stress. Molecules 23:178–192</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules23010178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M, Khan AU, Hasan MA, Yadav KK, Pinto MM, Malik N, Yadav VK, Khan AH, Islam S, Sharma GK (2021) Agro-nanotechnology as an emerging field: a novel sustainable approach for improving plant growth by reducing biotic stress. Appl Sci 11:22–82</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan A, Bani Mfarrej MF, Danish M, Shariq M, Khan MF, Ansari MS, Hashem M, Alamri S, Ahmad F (2022) Synthesized copper oxide nanoparticles via the green route act as antagonists to pathogenic root-knot nematode, Meloidogyne incognita. Green Chem Lett Rev 15:491–507</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/17518253.2022.2096416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan I, Awan SA, Rizwan M, Huizhi W, Ulhassan Z, Xie W (2024) Silicon nanoparticles improved the osmolyte production, antioxidant defense system, and phytohormone regulation in Elymus sibiricus (L.) under drought and salt stress. Environ Sci Pollut Res 31:8985–8999</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-31730-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klunklin W, Savage G (2017) Effect on quality characteristics of tomatoes grown under well-watered and drought stress conditions. Foods 6:56</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods6080056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koike N, Hyakumachi M, Kageyama M, Tsuyumu K, Doke N (2001) Induction of systemic resistance in cucumber against several diseases byplant growth-promoting fungi: lignification and superoxide generation. Eur J Plant Pathol 107:523–533</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1011203826805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V, Pandita S, Sidhu GPS, Sharma A, Khanna K, Kaur P, Bali AS, Setia R (2021) Copper bioavailability, uptake, toxicity and tolerance in plants: a comprehensive review. Chemosphere 26:2127810</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kutawa AB, Ahmad K, Ali A, Hussein MZ, Abdul Wahab MA, Adamu A, Ismaila AA, Gunasena MT, Rahman MZ, Hossain MI (2021) Trends in nanotechnology and its potentialities to control plant pathogenic fungi: a review. Biology 10:881</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biology10090881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Łaźniewska J, Macioszek VK, Kononowicz AK (2012) Plant-fungus interface: the role of surface structures in plant resistance and susceptibility to pathogenic fungi. Physiol Mol Plant Pathol 78:24–30</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pmpp.2012.01.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li JJ, Zhao XQ, Wang JL, Shen RF (2021a) Strategies of cadmium and copper uptake and translocation in different plant species growing near an E-waste dismantling site at Wenling, China. Environ Sci Pollut Res 28:62562–62571</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-15072-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Xu G, Huang F, Hou S, Liu B, Yu Y (2021b) Influence of nano CuO on uptake and translocation of bifenthrin in rape (Brassica napus L.). Food Control 130:108333</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linh TM, Mai NC, Hoe PT, Lien LQ, Ban NK, Hien LTT, Chau NH, Van NT (2020) Metal-based nanoparticles enhance drought tolerance in soybean. J Nanosci 2020:1–13. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/4056563</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2020/4056563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Dhungana B, Cobb GP (2018) Copper oxide nanoparticles and arsenic interact to alter seedling growth of rice (Oryza sativa japonica). Chemosphere 206:330–337</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.05.021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marschner H (1995) Mineral nutrition of higher plants, 2nd edn. Academic Press, New York, pp 15–22</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mrabet R (2023) Sustainable agriculture for food and nutritional security. In: Sustainable Agric Environ. Academic Press, pp 25–90. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-323-90500-8.00013-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwamba TM, Islam F, Ali B, Lwalaba JLW, Gill RA, Zhang F, Farooq MA, Ali S, Ulhassan Z, Huang Q, Zhou WJ (2020) Comparative metabolomic responses of low-and high-cadmium accumulating genotypes reveal the cadmium adaptive mechanism in Brassica napus. Chemosphere 250:126308</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.126308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naidu S, Pandey J, Mishra LC, Chakraborty A, Roy A, Singh IK, Singh A (2023) Silicon nanoparticles: synthesis, uptake and their role in mitigation of biotic stress. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 255:114783. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2023.114783</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2023.114783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natesan K, Ponmurugan P, Gnanamangai BM, Manigandan V, Joy SP, Jayakumar C, Amsaveni G (2021) Biosynthesis of silica and copper nanoparticles from Trichoderma, Streptomyces and Pseudomonas spp. evaluated against collar canker and red root-rot disease of tea plants. Arch Phytopathol Plant Prot 54:56–85</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03235408.2020.1817258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawrot N, Wojciechowska E, Pazdro K, Szmagliński J, Pempkowiak J (2021) Uptake, accumulation, and translocation of Zn, Cu, Pb, Cd, Ni, and Cr by P. australis seedlings in an urban dredged sediment mesocosm: impact of seedling origin and initial trace metal content. Sci Total Environ 768:144983</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.144983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noman M, Shahid M, Ahmed T, Tahir M, Naqqash T, Muhammad S, Song F, Abid HMA, Aslam Z (2020a) Green copper nanoparticles from a native Klebsiella pneumoniae strain alleviated oxidative stress impairment of wheat plants by reducing the chromium bioavailability and increasing the growth. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 192:110–303</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.110303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noman M, Ahmed T, Hussain S, Niazi MBK, Shahid M, Song F (2020b) Biogenic copper nanoparticles synthesized by using a copper-resistant strain Shigella flexneri SNT22 reduced the translocation of cadmium from soil to wheat plants. J Hazard Mater 398:123–175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.123175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noman M, Ahmed T, Shahid M, Niazi MBK, Qasim M, Kouadri F, Abdulmajeed AM, Alghanem SM, Ahmad N, Zafar M, Ali S (2021) Biogenic copper nanoparticles produced by using the Klebsiella pneumoniae strain NST2 curtailed salt stress effects in maize by modulating the cellular oxidative repair mechanisms. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 217:112–264</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2021.112264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ochoa L, Zuverza-Mena N, Medina-Velo IA, Flores-Margez JP, Peralta-Videa JR, Gardea-Torresdey JL (2018) Copper oxide nanoparticles and bulk copper oxide, combined with indole-3-acetic acid, alter aluminum, boron, and iron in Pisum sativum seeds. Sci Total Environ 634:1238–1245</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.04.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ovecka M, Lang I, Baluska F, Ismail A, Illes P, Lichtscheidl IK (2005) Endocytosis and vesicle trafficking during tip growth of root hairs. Protoplasma 226:39–54</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00709-005-0103-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park S, Kim KS, Kang D, Yoon H, Sung K (2013) Effects of humic acid on heavy metal uptake by herbaceous plants in soils simultaneously contaminated by petroleum hydrocarbons. Environ Earth Sci 68:2375–2384</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12665-012-1920-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelegrino MT, Kohatsu MY, Seabra AB, Monteiro LR, Gomes DG, Oliveira HC, Rolim WR, de Jesus TA, Batista BL, Lange CN (2020) Effects of copper oxide nanoparticles on growth of lettuce (Lactuca sativa L.) seedlings and possible implications of nitric oxide in their antioxidative defense. Environ Monit Assess. 12:192</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng C, Duan D, Xu C, Chen Y, Sun L, Zhang H, Yuan X, Zheng L, Yang Y, Yang J, Zhen X (2015) Translocation and biotransformation of CuO nanoparticles in rice (Oryza sativa L.) plants. Environ Pollut 197:99–107</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2014.12.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Labrada F, López-Vargas ER, Ortega-Ortiz H, Cadenas-Pliego G, Benavides-Mendoza A, Juárez-Maldonado A (2019) Responses of tomato plants under saline stress to foliar application of copper nanoparticles. Plants 8:151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants8060151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quiterio-Gutiérrez T, Ortega-Ortiz H, Cadenas-Pliego G, Hernández-Fuentes AD, Sandoval-Rangel A, Benavides-Mendoza A, Cabrera-de la Fuente M, Juárez-Maldonado A (2019) The application of selenium and copper nanoparticles modifies the biochemical responses of tomato plants under stress by Alternaria solani. Int J Mol Sci 20:1950</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms20081950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren Y, Wang W, He J, Zhang L, Wei Y, Yang M (2020) Nitric oxide alleviates salt stress in seed germination and early seedling growth of pakchoi (Brassica chinensis L.) by enhancing physiological and biochemical parameters. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 187:109–785</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.109785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salam A, Khan AR, Liu L, Yang S, Azhar W, Ulhassan Z, Zeeshan M, Wu J, Fan X, Gan Y (2022) Seed priming with zinc oxide nanoparticles downplayed ultrastructural damage and improved photosynthetic apparatus in maize under cobalt stress. J Hazard Mater 423:127021. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.127021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.127021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sancenon V, Puig S, Mateu-Andres I, Dorcey E, Thiele DJ, Peñarrubia L (2004) The Arabidopsis copper transporter COPT1 functions in root elongation and pollen development. J Biol Chem 279:15348–15355</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M313321200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarkar J, Chakraborty N, Chatterjee A, Bhattacharjee A, Dasgupta D, Acharya K (2020) Green synthesized copper oxide nanoparticles ameliorate defence and antioxidant enzymes in Lens culinaris. Nanomaterials 10:312</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano10020312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sathiyabama M, Indhumathi M, Amutha T (2020) Preparation and characterization of curcumin functionalized copper nanoparticles and their application enhances disease resistance in chickpea against wilt pathogen. Biocata Agric Biotech 29:101–823</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah IH, Ashraf M, Khan AR, Manzoor MA, Hayat K, Arif S, Sabir IA, Abdullah M, Niu Q, Zhang Y (2022) Controllable synthesis and stabilization of Tamarix aphylla-mediated copper oxide nanoparticles for the management of Fusarium wilt on musk melon. 3 Biotech 12:128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13205-022-03189-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah IH, Sabir IA, Rehman A, Hameed MK, Albashar G, Manzoor MA, Shakoor A (2023) Co-application of copper oxide nanoparticles and Trichoderma harzianum with physiological, enzymatic and ultrastructural responses for the mitigation of salt stress. Chemosphere 336:139230</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.139230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shang H, Ma C, Li C, Zhao J, Elmer W, White JC, Xing B (2021) Copper oxide nanoparticle-embedded hydrogels enhance nutrient supply and growth of lettuce (Lactuca sativa) infected with Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. lactucae. Environ Sci Tech 55:13432–13442</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c00777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw AK, Hossain Z (2013) Impact of nano-CuO stress on rice (Oryza sativa L.) seedlings. Chemosphere 93:906–915</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2013.05.044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheteiwy MS, Ali DFI, Xiong YC, Brestic M, Skalicky M, Hamoud YA, Ulhassan Z, Shaghaleh H, AbdElgawad H, Farooq M, Sharma A (2021) Physiological and biochemical responses of soybean plants inoculated with Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi and Bradyrhizobium under drought stress. BMC Plant Biol 21:195</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12870-021-02949-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheteiwy MS, Ulhassan Z, Qi W, Lu H, AbdElgawad H, Minkina T, Sushkova S, Rajput VD, El-Keblawy A, Jośko I, Sulieman S (2022) Association of jasmonic acid priming with multiple defense mechanisms in wheat plants under high salt stress. Front Plant Sci 13:886862</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.886862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh A, Singh NB, Hussain I, Singh H (2017a) Effect of biologically synthesized copper oxide nanoparticles on metabolism and antioxidant activity to the crop plants Solanum lycopersicum and Brassica oleracea var. botrytis. J Biotechnol 262:11–27</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2017.09.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh A, Singh NB, Hussain I, Singh H, Yadav V (2017b) Synthesis and characterization of copper oxide nanoparticles and its impact on germination of Vigna radiata (L.) R. Wilczek. Trop Plant Res 4:246–253</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.22271/tpr.2017.v4.i2.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh N, Bhuker A, Jeevanadam J (2021) Effects of metal nanoparticle-mediated treatment on seed quality parameters of different crops. Naunyn Schmiedeberg’s Arch Pharmacol 394:1067–1089</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00210-021-02057-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su C, Chen A, Liang W, Xie W, Xu X, Zhan X, Zhang W, Peng C (2024) Copper-based nanomaterials: opportunities for sustainable agriculture. Sci Total Environ 926:171948</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.171948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamil Elakkiya V, Meenakshi RV, Senthil Kumar P, Karthik V, Ravi Shankar K, Sureshkumar P, Hanan A (2022) Green synthesis of copper nanoparticles using Sesbania aculeata to enhance the plant growth and antimicrobial activities. Int J Environ Sci Tech 19:1313</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13762-021-03182-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taran N, Storozhenko V, Svietlova N, Batsmanova L, Shvartau V, Kovalenko M (2017) Effect of zinc and copper nanoparticles on drought resistance of wheat seedlings. Nanoscale Res Lett 12:60</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s11671-017-1839-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tauseef A, Gupta J, Rehman A, Uddin I (2021) Differential response of cowpea towards the CuO nanoparticles under Meloidogyne incognita stress. South Afr J Bot 139:175–182</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2021.02.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari PK, Singh AK, Singh VP, Prasad SM, Ramawat N, Tripathi DK, Chauhan DK, Rai AK (2019) Liquid assisted pulsed laser ablation synthesized copper oxide nanoparticles (CuO-NPs) and their differential impact on rice seedlings. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 176:321–329</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.01.120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toqeer I, Raza A, Naz MY, Ghaffar A, Hussain Z, Ghuffar A (2020) Synthesis and application of controlled size copper oxide nanoparticles for improving biochemical and growth parameters of maize seedling. J Plant Nutri 43:2622–2632</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01904167.2020.1793182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trujillo-Reyes J, Majumdar S, Botez CE, Peralta-Videa JR, Gardea-Torresdey JL (2014) Exposure studies of core–shell Fe/Fe3O4 and Cu/CuO NPs to lettuce (Lactuca sativa) plants: Are they a potential physiological and nutritional hazard? J Hazard Mat 267:255–263</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2013.11.067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulhassan Z, Ali S, Gill RA, Mwamba TM, Abid M, Li L, Zhang N, Zhou W (2018) Comparative orchestrating response of four oilseed rape (Brassica napus) cultivars against the selenium stress as revealed by physio-chemical, ultrastructural and molecular profiling. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 161:634–647</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.06.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulhassan Z, Gill RA, Huang H, Ali S, Mwamba TM, Ali B, Huang Q, Hamid Y, Khan AR, Wang J, Zhou W (2019) Selenium mitigates the chromium toxicity in Brassicca napus L. by ameliorating nutrients uptake, amino acids metabolism and antioxidant defense system. Plant Physiol Biochem 145:142–152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2019.10.035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulhassan Z, Bhat JA, Zhou W, Senan AM, Alam P, Ahmad P (2022a) Attenuation mechanisms of arsenic induced toxicity and its accumulation in plants by engineered nanoparticles: a review. Environ Pollut 302:119–38</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulhassan Z, Khan I, Hussain M, Khan AR, Hamid Y, Hussain S, Allakhverdiev SI, Zhou W (2022b) Efficacy of metallic nanoparticles in attenuating the accumulation and toxicity of chromium in plants: current knowledge and future perspectives. Environ Pollut 315:120390</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.120390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulhassan Z, Yang S, He D, Khan AR, Salam A, Azhar W, Muhammad S, Ali S, Hamid Y, Khan I, Sheteiwy MS (2023) Seed priming with nano-silica effectively ameliorates chromium toxicity in Brassica napus. J Hazard Mat 458:131906</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2023.131906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umar UUD, Naqvi SAH, Khan AA, Rehman AU, Ejaz-Ul-Haq M (2016) Man-agement of zucchini yellow mosaic virus in cucumber throughgenetic and salicylic acid induced resistance. Pak J Agric Res 53:187–194</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Nguyen D, Nguyen HM, Le NT, Nguyen KH, Nguyen HT, Le HM, Nguyen AT, Dinh NTT, Hoang SA, Van Ha C (2021) Copper nanoparticle application enhances plant growth and grain yield in maize under drought stress conditions. J Plant Growth Regul 41:364–375</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00344-021-10301-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velsankar K, Parvathy G, Mohandoss S, Kumar RM, Sudhahar S (2022) Green synthesis and characterization of CuO nanoparticles using Panicum sumatrense grains extract for biological applications. Appl Nanosci 12:1993–2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13204-022-02441-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Xie X, Zhao J, Liu X, Feng W, White JC, Xing B (2012) Xylem- and phloem-based transport of CuO nanoparticles in maize (Zea mays L.). Environ Sci Technol 17:4434–4441</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es204212z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Sun W, Ma X (2019a) Differential impacts of copper oxide nanoparticles and copper (II) ions on the uptake and accumulation of arsenic in rice (Oryza sativa). Environ Pollut 252:967–973</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Lin Y, Xu Y, Yin Y, Guo H, Du W (2019b) Divergence in response of lettuce (var. ramosa Hort.) to copper oxide nanoparticles/microparticles as potential agricultural fertilizer. Environ Pollut Bioavail 31:80–84</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.01.041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Ren Y, He J, Zhang L, Wang X, Cui Z (2020) Impact of copper oxide nanoparticles on the germination, seedling growth, and physiological responses in Brassica pekinensis L. Environ Sci Pollut Res 27:31505–31515</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09338-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Liu X, Li J, Yue L, Yang H, Zou H, Wang Z, Xing B (2021) Copper nanoclusters promote tomato (Solanum lycopersicum L.) yield and quality through improving photosynthesis and roots growth. Environ Pollut. 289:117912</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S, Fu Y, Zheng S, Xu Y, Sun Y (2022) Phytotoxicity and accumulation of copper-based nanoparticles in brassica under cadmium stress. Nanomaterials 12:1497</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano12091497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White MC, Baker FD, Chaney RL, Decker AM (1981) Metal complexation in xylem fluid. 2. Theoretical equilibrium-model and computational computer-program. Plant Physiol 67:301–310</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1104/pp.67.2.301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong T, Zhang T, Xian Y, Kang Z, Zhang S, Dumat C, Shahid M, Li S (2021) Foliar uptake, biotransformation, and impact of CuO nanoparticles in Lactuca sativa L. var. ramosa Hort. Environ Geochem Health 43:423–439</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00734-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang KY, Doxey S, McLean JE, Britt D, Watson A, Al Qassy D, Jacobson A, Anderson AJ (2018) Remodeling of root morphology by CuO and ZnO nanoparticles: effects on drought tolerance for plants colonized by a beneficial pseudomonad. Botany 96:175–186</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/cjb-2017-0124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S, Ulhassan Z, Shah AM, Khan AR, Azhar W, Hamid Y, Hussain S, Sheteiwy MS, Salam A, Zhou W (2021) Salicylic acid underpins silicon in ameliorating chromium toxicity in rice by modulating antioxidant defense, ion homeostasis and cellular ultrastructure. Plant Physiol Biochem 166:1001–1013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2021.07.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younes NA, El-Sherbiny M, Alkharpotly AA, Sayed OA, Dawood AF, Hossain MA, Abdelrhim AS, Dawood MF (2024) Rice-husks synthesized-silica nanoparticles modulate silicon content, ionic homeostasis, and antioxidants defense under limited irrigation regime in eggplants. Plant Stress 11:100330. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.stress.2023.100330</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.stress.2023.100330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yusefi-Tanha E, Fallah S, Rostamnejadi A, Pokhrel LR (2020) Particle size and concentration dependent toxicity of copper oxide nanoparticles (CuONPs) on seed yield and antioxidant defense system in soil grown soybean (Glycine max cv. Kowsar). Sci Total Environ 715:136994</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.136994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q, Yuan P, Liang W, Qiao Z, Shao X, Zhang W, Peng C (2022) Exogenous iron alters uptake and translocation of CuO nanoparticles in soil-rice system: a life cycle study. Environ Int 168:107479</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2022.107479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang N, Ali S, Huang Q, Yang C, Ali B, Chen W, Zhang K, Ali S, Ulhassan Z, Zhou W (2024) Seed pretreatment with brassinosteroids stimulates sunflower immunity against parasitic weed (Orobanche cumana) infection. Physiol Plant 176:e14324. https://doi.org/10.1111/ppl.14324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ppl.14324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zong X, Wu D, Zhang J, Tong X, Yin Y, Sun Y, Guo H (2022) Size-dependent biological effect of copper oxide nanoparticles exposure on cucumber (Cucumis sativus). Environ Sci Pollut Res 29:69517–69526</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-022-20662-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>