<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39373131</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Bioactive compounds from food-grade Bacillus.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13935</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Bacillus species have attracted significant attention in recent years due to their potential for producing various bioactive compounds with diverse functional properties. This review highlights bioactive substances from food-grade Bacillus strains and their applications in functional foods and nutraceuticals. The metabolic capacities of Bacillus species have allowed them to generate a wide range of bioactive substances, including vitamins, enzymes, anti-microbial peptides, and other non-ribosomal peptides. These substances have a variety of positive effects, including potential cholesterol-lowering and immune-modulatory qualities in addition to anti-oxidant and anti-bacterial actions. The uses and mechanisms of action of these bioactive chemicals can be used to improve the functional qualities and nutritional profile of food products. Examples include the use of anti-microbial peptides to increase safety and shelf life, as well as the use of Bacillus-derived enzymes in food processing to improve digestibility and sensory qualities. The exploitation of bioactive compounds from food-grade Bacillus strains presents a promising frontier in the development of functional foods and nutraceuticals with enhanced health benefits. Due to their wide range of activity and applications, they are considered as important resources for the development of novel medications, agricultural biocontrol agents, and industrial enzymes. Ongoing research into the biosynthetic pathways, functional properties, and applications of these compounds is essential to fully realize their potential in the food industry. This review underscores the significance of various bioactive compounds generated from Bacillus in tackling global issues like environmental sustainability, sustainable agriculture, and antibiotic resistance. Future developments in microbiology and biotechnology will enable us to fully utilize the potential of these amazing microbes, resulting in novel approaches to industry, agriculture, and health. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raphel</LastName><ForeName>Steji</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), Ghaziabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Fermentation Technology, CSIR-Central Food Technological Research Institute, Mysuru, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Halami</LastName><ForeName>Prakash Motiram</ForeName><Initials>PM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0293-1891</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), Ghaziabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Fermentation Technology, CSIR-Central Food Technological Research Institute, Mysuru, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Central Food Technological Research Institute, Council of Scientific and Industrial Research</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacillus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anti‐bacterial peptides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bioactive compounds</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enzymes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">non‐ribosomal peptides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vitamins</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39373131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Chokshi A, Sifri Z, Cennimo D and Horng H, Global contributors to antibiotic resistance. J Glob Infect Dis 11:36–42 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andryukov B, Mikhailov V and Besednova N, The biotechnological potential of secondary metabolites from marine bacteria. J Mar Sci Eng 7:176 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO), 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atanasov AG, Waltenberger B, Pferschy‐Wenzig EM, Linder T, Wawrosch C, Uhrin P et al., Discovery and resupply of pharmacologically active plant‐derived natural products: a review. Biotechnol Adv 33:1582–1614 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastor‐Villaescusa B, Rangel‐Huerta OD, Aguilera CM and Gil A, A systematic review of the efficacy of bioactive compounds in cardiovascular disease: carbohydrates, active lipids and nitrogen compounds. Ann Nutr Metab 66:168–181 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang CLT, Lin Y, Bartolome AP, Chen YC, Chiu SC and Yang WC, Herbal therapies for type 2 diabetes mellitus: chemistry, biology, and potential application of selected plants and compounds. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 2013:378657 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh M, Kumar A, Singh R and Pandey KD, Endophytic bacteria: a new source of bioactive compounds. 3 Biotech 7:315 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang HK, Seo CH and Park Y, Marine peptides and their anti‐infective activities. Mar Drugs 13:618–654 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaabouni I, Guesmi A and Cherif A, Secondary metabolites of Bacillus: potentials in biotechnology. Springer, Netherlands, pp. 347–366 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stein T, Bacillus subtilis antibiotics: structures, syntheses and specific functions. Mol Microbiol 56:845–857 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elshaghabee FMF, Rokana N, Gulhane RD, Sharma C and Panwar H, Bacillus As potential probiotics: status, concerns, and future perspectives. Front Microbiol 8:1490 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouattara HG, Reverchon S, Niamke SL and Nasser W, Regulation of the synthesis of pulp degrading enzymes in Bacillus isolated from cocoa fermentation. Food Microbiol 63:255–262 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez‐Avila GCG, Aguilera AF, Saucedo S, Rojas R, Rodriguez R and Aguilar CN, Fruit wastes fermentation for phenolic antioxidants production and their application in manufacture of edible coatings and films. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 54:303–311 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takano H, The regulatory mechanism underlying light‐inducible production of carotenoids in nonphototrophic bacteria. Biosci Biotechnol Biochem 80:1264–1273 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka K, Takanaka S and Yoshida K‐i, A second‐generation Bacillus cell factory for rare inositol production. Bioengineered 5:331–334 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimura K and Yokoyama S, Trends in the application of Bacillus in fermented foods. Curr Opin Biotechnol 56:36–42 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verardo V, Gómez‐Caravaca A and Tabanelli G, Bioactive components in fermented foods and food by‐products. Foods 9:153 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamang JP, Watanabe K and Holzapfel WH, Review: diversity of microorganisms in global fermented foods and beverages. Front Microbiol 7:377 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afzaal M, Saeed F, Islam F, Ateeq H, Asghar A, Shah YA et al., Nutritional health perspective of natto: a critical review. Biochem Res Int 2022:5863887 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim IS, Hwang CW, Yang WS and Kim CH, Current perspectives on the physiological activities of fermented soybean‐derived cheonggukjang. Int J of Mol Sci 22:5746 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park KY, Jung KO, Rhee SH and Choi YH, Antimutagenic effects of doenjang (Korean fermented soypaste) and its active compounds. Mutat Res Mol Mech Mutagen 523–524:43–53 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandhi GR, Li H, Vasconcelos ABS, Montalvão MM, de Franca MNF, He XQ et al., Chapter 26 ‐ bioactive constituents and potential health benefits of fermented seed products, in Indigenous Fermented Foods for the Tropics, ed. by Adebo OA, Chinma CE, Obadina AO, Soares AG, Panda SK and Gan RY. Academic Press, London, UK, pp. 419–431 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anand Singh T, Nongthombam G, Goksen G, Singh HB, Rajauria G and Kumar SP, Hawaijar–an ethnic vegan fermented soybean food of Manipur, India: a comprehensive review. Food Res Int 170:112983 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebiyi JA, Njobeh PB and Kayitesi E, Assessment of nutritional and phytochemical quality of Dawadawa (an African fermented condiment) produced from Bambara groundnut (Vigna subterranean). Microchem J 149:104034 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olasupo NA, Okorie CP and Oguntoyinbo FA, The biotechnology of Ugba, a Nigerian traditional fermented food condiment. Front Microbiol 7:1153 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olatunde A, Mohammed A, Ibrahim MA, Tajuddeen N and Shuaibu MN, Vanillin: A food additive with multiple biological activities. Eur J Med Chem Rep 5:100055 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu P and Wang N, Bioactive compounds in grain fermentation. Fermentation 10:95 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamang JP, Naturally fermented ethnic soybean foods of India. J Ethn Foods 2:8–17 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meerak J, Iida H, Watanabe Y, Miyashita M, Sato H, Nakagawa Y et al., Phylogeny of γ‐polyglutamic acid‐producing Bacillus strains isolated from fermented soybean foods manufactured in Asian countries. J Gen Appl Microbiol 53:315–323 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toshirou N and Fukuhiro Y, Bacillus subtilis (natto) bacteriophages isolated in Japan. Food Sci Technol Res 15:293–298 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rai AK and Anu Appaiah KA, Bioactive Compounds in Fermented Foods: Health Aspects. CRC Press, Boca Raton, US, p. 511 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senthilkumar PK, Uma C and Saranraj P, Amylase production by Bacillus sp. using cassava as substrate. Int J Pharmaceut Biol Arch 3:274–280 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang P, Wu Q, Jiang X, Wang Z, Tang J and Xu Y, Bacillus licheniformis affects the microbial community and metabolic profile in the spontaneous fermentation of Daqu starter for Chinese liquor making. Int J Food Microbiol 250:59–67 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaraî Jaouadi N, Jaouadi B, Aghajari N and Bejar S, The overexpression of the SAPB of Bacillus pumilus CBS and mutated sapB‐L31I/T33S/N99Y alkaline proteases in Bacillus subtilis DB430: new attractive properties for the mutant enzyme. Bioresour Technol 105:142–151 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sookkheo B, Sinchaikul S, Phutrakul S and Chen ST, Purification and characterization of the highly thermostable proteases from Bacillus stearothermophilus TLS33. Protein Expr Purif 20:142–151 (2000).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rozs M, Manczinger L, Vágvölgyi C and Kevei F, Secretion of a trypsin‐like thiol protease by a new keratinolytic strain of Bacillus licheniformis. FEMS Microbiol Lett 205:221–224 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adinarayana K, Ellaiah P and Prasad DS, Purification and partial characterization of thermostable serine alkaline protease from a newly isolated Bacillus subtilis PE‐11. AAPS PharmSciTech 4:56 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Contesini FJ, de Melo RR and Sato HH, An overview of Bacillus proteases: from production to application. Crit Rev Biotechnol 38:321–334 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gopikrishna T, Suresh Kumar HK, Perumal K and Elangovan E, Impact of Bacillus in fermented soybean foods on human health. Ann Microbiol 71:30 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nunes CS and Kumar V, Enzymes in Human and Animal Nutrition: Principles and Perspectives. Academic Press, London, UK, p. 592 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao T, Yong X, Zhao Z, Dolce V, Li Y and Curcio R, Research status of Bacillus phytase. 3 Biotech 11:415 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phengnuam T and Suntornsuk W, Detoxification and anti‐nutrients reduction of Jatropha curcas seed cake by Bacillus fermentation. J Biosci Bioeng 115:168–172 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava N, Rathour R, Jha S, Pandey K, Srivastava M, Thakur VK et al., Microbial beta glucosidase enzymes: recent advances in biomass conversation for biofuels application. Biomolecules 9:220 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Xu T, Liu XW, Wang X and Xia T, The expression of β‐glucosidase during natto fermentation increased the active isoflavone content. Food Biosci 43:101286 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murugan K, Sekar K and Al‐Sohaibani S, Detoxification of cyanides in cassava flour by linamarase of Bacillus subtilis KM05 isolated from cassava peel. Afr J Biotechnol 11:7232–7237 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J, Sun‐Waterhouse D, Cui C, Dong K and Wang W, Synthesis and sensory characteristics of Kokumi γ‐[Glu]n‐Phe in the presence of glutamine and phenylalanine: Glutaminase from Bacillus amyloliquefaciens or aspergillus oryzae as the catalyst. J Agric Food Chem 65:8696–8703 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsueh YH, Huang KY, Kunene SC and Lee TY, Poly‐γ‐glutamic acid synthesis, gene regulation, phylogenetic relationships, and role in fermentation. Int J Mol Sci 18:2644 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kada S, Yabusaki M, Kaga T, Ashida H and Ichi YK, Identification of two major ammonia‐releasing reactions involved in secondary natto fermentation. Biosci Biotechnol Biochem 72:1869–1876 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su Y, Liu C, Fang H and Zhang D, Bacillus subtilis: a universal cell factory for industry, agriculture, biomaterials and medicine. Microb Cell Fact 19:173 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi T, Wang Y, Wang Z, Wang G, Liu D, Fu J et al., Deregulation of purine pathway in Bacillus subtilis and its use in riboflavin biosynthesis. Microb Cell Fact 13:101 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu WJ and Ahn BY, Statistical optimization of medium components by response surface methodology to enhance Menaquinone‐7 (vitamin K2) production by Bacillus subtilis. J Microbiol Biotechnol 28:902–908 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao H, Shao D, Jiang C, Shi J, Li Q, Huang Q et al., Biological activity of lipopeptides from Bacillus. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 101:5951–5960 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang C, Shi J, Liu Y and Zhu C, Inhibition of Aspergillus carbonarius and fungal contamination in table grapes using Bacillus subtilis. Food Control 35:41–48 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arima K, Kakinuma A and Tamura G, Surfactin, a crystalline peptidelipid surfactant produced by Bacillus subtilis: isolation, characterization and its inhibition of fibrin clot formation. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 31:488–494 (1968).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakinuma A, Hori M, Isono M, Tamura G and Arima K, Determination of amino acid sequence in surfactin, a crystalline peptidelipid surfactant produced by Bacillus subtilis. Agric Biol Chem 33:971–972 (1969).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakinuma A, Sugino H, Isono M, Tamura G and Arima K, Determination of fatty acid in surfactin and elucidation of the total structure of surfactin. Agric Biol Chem 33:973–976 (1969).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakano MM, Marahiel MA and Zuber P, Identification of a genetic locus required for biosynthesis of the lipopeptide antibiotic surfactin in Bacillus subtilis. J Bacteriol 170:5662–5668 (1988).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao J, Borriss R, Sun K, Zhang R, Chen X, Liu Y et al., Research advances in the identification of regulatory mechanisms of surfactin production by Bacillus: a review. Microb Cell Fact 23:100 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarwar A, Hassan MN, Imran M, Iqbal M, Majeed S, Brader G et al., Biocontrol activity of surfactin A purified from Bacillus NH‐100 and NH‐217 against rice bakanae disease. Microbiol Res 209:1–13 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Liang Y, Wu M, Chen Z, Lin J and Yang L, Natural products from Bacillus subtilis with antimicrobial properties. Chin J Chem Eng 23:744–754 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Théatre A, Cano‐Prieto C, Bartolini M, Laurin Y, Deleu M, Niehren J et al., The surfactin‐like lipopeptides from Bacillus spp.: natural biodiversity and synthetic biology for a broader application range. Front Bioeng Biotechnol 9:623701 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi G, Zhu F, Du P, Yang X, Qiu D, Yu Z et al., Lipopeptide induces apoptosis in fungal cells by a mitochondria‐dependent pathway. Peptides 31:1978–1986 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harwood CR, Mouillon JM, Pohl S and Arnau J, Secondary metabolite production and the safety of industrially important members of the Bacillus subtilis group. FEMS Microbiol Rev 42:721–738 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A, Saini S, Wray V, Nimtz M, Prakash A and Johri BN, Characterization of an antifungal compound produced by Bacillus sp. strain A5F that inhibits Sclerotinia sclerotiorum. J Basic Microbiol 52:670–678 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasir MN and Besson F, Interactions of the antifungal mycosubtilin with ergosterol‐containing interfacial monolayers. Biochim Biophys Acta 1818:1302–1308 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B, Dong C, Shang Q, Han Y and Li P, New insights into membrane‐active action in plasma membrane of fungal hyphae by the lipopeptide antibiotic bacillomycin L. Biochim Biophys Acta 1828:2230–2237 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanittanakom N, Loeffler W, Koch U and Jung G, Fengycin‐a novel antifungal lipopeptide antibiotic produced by Bacillus subtilis F‐29‐3. J Antibiot (Tokyo) 39:888–901 (1986).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider J, Taraz K, Budzikiewicz H, Deleu M, Thonart P and Jacques P, The structure of two fengycins from Bacillus subtilis S499. Z Für Naturforschung C 54:859–866 (1999).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu CY, Chen CL, Lee YH, Cheng YC, Wu YC, Shu HY et al., Nonribosomal synthesis of fengycin on an enzyme complex formed by fengycin synthetases*. J Biol Chem 282:5608–5616 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin Y, Wang X, Zhang P, Wang P and Wen J, Strategies for improving fengycin production: a review. Microb Cell Fact 23:144 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grangemard I, Wallach J, Maget‐Dana R and Peypoux F, Lichenysin. Appl Biochem Biotechnol 90:199–210 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pueyo MT, Bloch C, Carmona‐Ribeiro AM and di Mascio P, Lipopeptides produced by a soil Bacillus Megaterium strain. Microb Ecol 57:367–378 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinborn G, Hajirezaei MR and Hofemeister J, Bac genes for recombinant bacilysin and anticapsin production in Bacillus host strains. Arch Microbiol 183:71–79 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamdache A, Azarken R, Lamarti A, Aleu J and Collado IG, Comparative genome analysis of Bacillus spp. and its relationship with bioactive nonribosomal peptide production. Phytochem Rev 12:685–716 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newton GGF, Antibiotics from a strain of B. Subtilis: Bacilipin A and B and Bacilysin. Br J Exp Pathol 30:306–319 (1949).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapp C, Jung G, Katzer W and Loeffler W, Chlorotetain from Bacillus subtilis, an antifungal dipeptide with an unusual chlorine‐containing amino acid. Angew Chem Int Ed Engl 27:1733–1734 (1988).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arguelles‐Arias A, Ongena M, Halimi B, Lara Y, Brans A, Joris B et al., Bacillus amyloliquefaciens GA1 as a source of potent antibiotics and other secondary metabolites for biocontrol of plant pathogens. Microb Cell Fact 8:63 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abriouel H, Franz CMAP, Omar NB and Gálvez A, Diversity and applications of Bacillus bacteriocins. FEMS Microbiol Rev 35:201–232 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. McIntosh J, S. Donia M and W. Schmidt E, Ribosomal peptide natural products: bridging the ribosomal and nonribosomal worlds. Nat Prod Rep 26:537–559 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein C and Entian KD, Genes involved in self‐protection against the lantibiotic subtilin produced by Bacillus subtilis ATCC 6633. Appl Environ Microbiol 60:2793–2801 (1994).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmitz S, Hoffmann A, Szekat C, Rudd B and Bierbaum G, The lantibiotic mersacidin is an autoinducing peptide. Appl Environ Microbiol 72:7270–7277 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appleyard AN, Choi S, Read DM, Lightfoot A, Boakes S, Hoffmann A et al., Dissecting structural and functional diversity of the lantibiotic mersacidin. Chem Biol 16:490–498 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C, Biswas S, Garcia De Gonzalo CV and van der Donk WA, Investigations into the mechanism of action of sublancin. ACS. Infect Dis 5:454–459 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubois JYF, Kouwen TRHM, Schurich AKC, Reis CR, Ensing HT, Trip EN et al., Immunity to the bacteriocin sublancin 168 is determined by the suni (Yolf) protein of Bacillus subtilis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 53:651–661 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arias AA, Ongena M, Devreese B, Terrak M, Joris B and Fickers P, Characterization of amylolysin, a novel lantibiotic from Bacillus amyloliquefaciens GA1. PLoS One 8:e83037 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Begley M, Cotter PD, Hill C and Ross RP, Identification of a novel two‐peptide lantibiotic, lichenicidin, following rational genome mining for lanm proteins. Appl Environ Microbiol 75:5451–5460 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbosa J, Caetano T, Mösker E, Süssmuth R and Mendo S, Lichenicidin rational site‐directed mutagenesis library: A tool to generate bioengineered lantibiotics. Biotechnol Bioeng 116:3053–3062 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babasaki K, Takao T, Shimonishi Y and Kurahashi K, Subtilosin A, a new antibiotic peptide produced by Bacillus subtilis 168: isolation, structural analysis, and biogenesis. J Biochem (Tokyo) 98:585–603 (1985).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pattnaik P, Kaushik JK, Grover S and Batish VK, Purification and characterization of a bacteriocin‐like compound (lichenin) produced anaerobically by Bacillus licheniformis isolated from water buffalo. J Appl Microbiol 91:636–645 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shleeva MO, Kondratieva DA and Kaprelyants AS, Bacillus licheniformis: a producer of antimicrobial substances, including antimycobacterials, which are feasible for medical applications. Pharmaceutics 15:1893 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoica R, Moscovici M, Tomulescu C, Cășărică A, Băbeanu N, Popa O et al., Antimicrobial compounds of the genus Bacillus: a review. Romanian Biotechnol Lett 24:1111–1119 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Zheng M, Zheng J and Gänzle MG, Bacillus species in food fermentations: an underappreciated group of organisms for safe use in food fermentations. Curr Opin Food Sci 50:101007 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dindhoria K, Kumar S, Baliyan N, Raphel S, Halami PM and Kumar R, Bacillus licheniformis MCC 2514 genome sequencing and functional annotation for providing genetic evidence for probiotic gut adhesion properties and its applicability as a bio‐preservative agent. Gene 840:146744 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ravindran A, Kiran GS and Selvin J, Revealing the effect of lipopeptide on improving the probiotics characteristics: flavor and texture enhancer in the formulated yogurt. Food Chem 375:131718 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghelardi E, Abreu y Abreu AT, Marzet CB, Álvarez Calatayud G, Perez M and Moschione Castro AP, Current progress and future perspectives on the use of Bacillus clausii. Microorganisms 10:1246 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konuray G and Erginkaya Z, Potential use of Bacillus coagulans in the food industry. Foods 7:92 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shobharani P, Padmaja RJ and Halami PM, Diversity in the antibacterial potential of probiotic cultures Bacillus licheniformis MCC2514 and Bacillus licheniformis MCC2512. Res Microbiol 166:546–554 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burgess CM, Smid EJ and van Sinderen D, Bacterial vitamin B2, B11 and B12 overproduction: an overview. Int J Food Microbiol 133:1–7 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rohith HS, Peddha MS and Halami PM, Probiotic Bacillus licheniformis MCC2514 and Bifidobacterium breve NCIM 5671 regulates GATA3 and Foxp3 expression in the elevated disease condition. Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins 16:894–910 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guallar‐Garrido S and Julián E, Bacillus Calmette‐Guérin (BCG) therapy for bladder cancer: an update. Immunotargets Ther 9:1–11 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rohith HS and Halami PM, The combined effect of potential probiotic Bacillus licheniformis MCC 2514 and Bifidobacterium breve NCIM 5671 towards anti‐inflammatory activity on HT‐29 cell lines. Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins 15:351–362 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma'or Z, Temmerman R and Zhang X, Topical application of synbiotic Bacillus preparations positively affects skin (micro) biology. J Cosmet Dermatol Sci Appl 13:107–123 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma R, Handa S, Mahajan R, De D and Sachdeva N, Evaluating the effect of supplementation with Bacillus clausii on therapeutic outcomes in atopic eczema—results of an observer‐blinded parallel‐group randomized controlled study. Indian J Dermatol 672:121–126 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majeed M, Nagabhushanam K, Paulose S, Rajalakshmi H and Mundkur L, A randomized double‐blind, placebo‐controlled study to evaluate the anti‐skin‐aging effect of LactoSporin–the extracellular metabolite from Bacillus coagulans (Weizmannia coagulans) MTCC 5856 in healthy female volunteers. Clin Cosmet Investig Dermatol 16:769–782 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halami, P. M, Sublichenin, a new subtilin‐like lantibiotics of probiotic bacterium Bacillus licheniformis MCC 2512T with antibacterial activity. Microb Pathog 128:139–146 (2023). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2018.12.044.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>