<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39374154</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1741-7899</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Reproduction (Cambridge, England)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Reproduction</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A contemporary review of machine learning to predict adverse pregnancy outcomes from pharmaceuticals, including DDIs.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">REP-24-0183</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1530/REP-24-0183</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Those undergoing pregnancy are often excluded from clinical drug trials due to the risk that participation would pose. However, they often require pharmaceuticals to manage health conditions that, if gone untreated, could harm themselves or the fetus. This can mean that such individuals take one or more pharmaceuticals during pregnancy, many of which have unknown reproductive effects. Machine learning models have been used to successfully predict a number of reproductive toxicological outcomes for pharmaceuticals, including transplacental transfer, US Food and Drug Administration safety rating, and drug interactions. Models use quantitative chemical and structural features of active compounds to make predictions concerning the outcome of interest using computational algorithms. Results from these models can be a potential source of valuable information for pregnant people and their medical providers when making decisions regarding therapeutic drug use. This review summarizes current machine learning applications to make predictions about risk and toxicity of medication use during pregnancy. Our review of the recent literature revealed that machine learning quantitative structure-activity relationship models can be used successfully to predict the transplacental transfer and the US Food and Drug Administration pregnancy safety category of pharmaceuticals; such models have also been employed to predict drug interactions, though not specifically during pregnancy. This latter topic is a potential area for future research. In this review, no single algorithm or descriptor-calculation software emerged as the most widely used, and their performances depend on a variety of factors, including outcome of interest and combination of such algorithms and software.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gardella</LastName><ForeName>Julie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>J Gardella, Environmental Medicine, NYU Langone Health, New York, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abrahamsson</LastName><ForeName>Dimitri</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>D Abrahamsson, Environmental Pediatrics, NYU Langone Health Department of Pediatrics, New York, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zelikoff</LastName><ForeName>Judith</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>J Zelikoff, Environmental Medicine, NYU Langone Health, New York, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Reproduction</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100966036</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1470-1626</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39374154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1530/REP-24-0183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">REP-24-0183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>