<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39378919</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Peanut de-oiling at room temperature by micro-aqueous hydration: Co-destabilization driven by oleosome coalescence and protein aggregation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136366</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136366</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136366</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)07175-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The peanut de-oiling industry currently lacks efficient processing technologies for de-oiling at low or room temperatures. A novel method, micro-aqueous extraction (MAE), offers over 93 % de-oiling efficiency at room temperature and is also effective for other oilseeds like sesame, camellia, and rapeseed. Despite its effectiveness, the exact mechanism behind oleosomes destabilization at a critical hydration level or oil volume fraction (φ ~ 0.75) is not fully understood. This study investigates how MAE affects peanut oleosome size, paste stability, and the interfacial properties of surfactant proteins. Results showed that micro-aqueous hydration and agitation caused small droplets (85.6 vol% &lt; 10 μm) to coalesce into larger droplets (90.0 vol% &gt; 30 μm) due to press-induced rupture of the liquid film. Simultaneously, agitation decreased water mobility and protein intrinsic fluorescence, while increasing paste viscosity, leading to protein aggregation. This aggregation further promoted oleosome coalescence. Additionally, hydration and agitation weakened the ability of membrane proteins to stabilize oleosomes by increasing interfacial tension and decreasing dilatational storage modulus. The insights into the peanut oleosome destabilization mechanism for MAE provide a foundation for scaling up the process, with the potential to replace current hot and cold pressing techniques.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tu</LastName><ForeName>Juncai</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health, College of Chemistry and Environmental Engineering, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen 518060, China; GuangDong Engineering Technology Research Center of Aquatic Food Processing and Safety Control, Shenzhen 518060, China. Electronic address: juncai.tu@szu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Shenghai</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health, College of Chemistry and Environmental Engineering, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen 518060, China; Institute for Advanced Study, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen 518060, China; GuangDong Engineering Technology Research Center of Aquatic Food Processing and Safety Control, Shenzhen 518060, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bai</LastName><ForeName>Weidong</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Light Industry and Food SciencesZhongkai University of Agriculture and Engineering, Guangzhou 510225, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brennan</LastName><ForeName>Charles</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science, RMIT University, GPO Box 2474, Melbourne, VIC 3001, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Beiwei</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health, College of Chemistry and Environmental Engineering, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen 518060, China; GuangDong Engineering Technology Research Center of Aquatic Food Processing and Safety Control, Shenzhen 518060, China. Electronic address: zhubeiwei@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Agitation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Droplet coalescence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Membrane protein</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Peanut oleosomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">micro-aqueous extraction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39378919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)07175-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>