<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39376495</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2042-0986</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Therapeutic advances in drug safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ther Adv Drug Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adverse event profiles of CDK4/6 inhibitors: data mining and disproportionality analysis of the FDA adverse event reporting system.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>20420986241278498</StartPage><MedlinePgn>20420986241278498</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">20420986241278498</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/20420986241278498</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Cyclin-dependent kinases 4 and 6 (CDK4/6) inhibitors are targeted therapies designed to selectively block CDK4/6, crucial regulators of the cell cycle. These inhibitors play a pivotal role in restoring cell cycle control, particularly in breast cancer cases marked by abnormal CDK regulation, ultimately inhibiting uncontrolled cell division and tumor growth.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This analysis aimed to comprehensively examine adverse effects in CDK4/6 inhibitors using the United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) database.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Disproportionality analysis was conducted to analyze the adverse event (AE) reports related to CDK4/6 inhibitor submitted to the FAERS database.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We collected AE reports regarding palbociclib, ribociclib, abemaciclib, trilaciclib, and dalpiciclib submitted to the FAERS from 2015Q1 to 2023Q1. We used the system organ class and the Standardized MedDRA Query to perform a comprehensive search for AEs at the preferred term (PT) level, using case reports as our data source. After removing duplicate reports, we performed disproportionality analysis and sensitivity analysis to identify safety signals.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 85,635 reports encompassing 280,211 AEs were extracted for analysis. Among 3681 scrutinized PTs, approximately 484 were detected as statistically significant signals associated with CDK4/6 inhibitors. It was noteworthy that palbociclib and ribociclib had comparable safety profiles, whereas abemaciclib exhibited distinctive safety patterns. Notably, our analysis found novel safety signals linked to CDK4/6 inhibitors, including nail-related disorders such as onychoclasis, nail disorder, and nail discoloration, and psychiatric concerns, including eating disorders and emotional disorder.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Overall, the present study identified several new safety signals of CDK4/6 inhibitors, as well as differences among various drugs within the CDK4/6 category, through the use of the FDA FAERS, which deserve more careful monitoring in the clinic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Pingli</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jianmei</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-7912-7328</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, #3 East Qingchun Road, Hangzhou, Zhejiang 310016, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Ther Adv Drug Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101549074</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2042-0986</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">A study on the adverse effects of CDK4/6 inhibitors.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">An adverse event (AE) refers to any undesirable or harmful occurrence that happens to an individual during or after the use of a medical product or intervention. These events are typically reported to regulatory authorities, such as the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), to ensure the safety and effectiveness of medical products. The United States Food and Drug Administration Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) database plays a pivotal role in identifying these adverse events. Cyclin-dependent kinases 4 and 6 (CDK4/6) inhibitors are a class of drugs used to treat certain types of cancer by inhibiting the growth and division of cancer cells. This study investigated the safety signals related to CDK4/6 inhibitors, including palbociclib, ribociclib, abemaciclib, and trilaciclib, by using the FAERS database.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We collected AE reports associated with CDK4/6 inhibitors that were submitted to the FAERS database between the first quarter of 2015 and the first quarter of 2023. Reporting odds ratio (ROR) method was used identify signals of AEs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">85,635 AE reports were identified, approximately 484 AE terms were identified as positive signals. Palbociclib and ribociclib had similar safety profiles, while abemaciclib showed a unique pattern. Our analysis also revealed previously unreported AEs, including nail-related disorders such as onychoclasis, nail disorder and nail discolouration. Psychiatric concerns such as eating disorders and emotional disorder were also identified.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We discovered important safety concerns related to CDK4/6 inhibitors. Some of these concerns were consistent with previous studies, while nail-related disorders, eating disorder and emotional disorder were new and not mentioned in the drug labels or existing literature. Our findings may help physicians and pharmacists to weigh the risks and benefits of using CDK4/6 inhibitors in clinical practice.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CDK4/6 inhibitor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FAERS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">drug safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacovigilance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">signal</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>37</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39376495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11457275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20420986241278498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_20420986241278498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Zheng L, Sun Z, et al.. CDK4/6 inhibitor resistance mechanisms and treatment strategies (Review). Int J Mol Med 2022; 50: 128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9448295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36043521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braal CL, Jongbloed EM, Wilting SM, et al.. Inhibiting CDK4/6 in breast cancer with palbociclib, ribociclib, and abemaciclib: similarities and differences. Drugs 2021; 81: 317–331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7952354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33369721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Shen K. Dalpiciclib in advanced breast cancer. Lancet Oncol 2023; 24: 578–579.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37269836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhillon S. Trilaciclib: first approval. Drugs 2021; 81: 867–874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33861388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hafner M, Mills CE, Subramanian K, et al.. Multiomics profiling establishes the polypharmacology of FDA-approved CDK4/6 inhibitors and the potential for differential clinical activity. Cell Chem Biol 2019; 26: 1067–1080.e8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6936329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31178407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu MG, Deshpande A, Schlichting N, et al.. CDK6 kinase activity is required for thymocyte development. Blood 2011; 117: 6120–6131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3122937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21508411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patnaik A, Rosen LS, Tolaney SM, et al.. Efficacy and safety of abemaciclib, an inhibitor of CDK4 and CDK6, for patients with breast cancer, non–small cell lung cancer, and other solid tumors. Cancer Discov 2016; 6: 740–753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27217383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babcock A, Ali AA, Balkrishnan R, et al.. Real-world clinical and economic outcomes associated with palbociclib for HR-positive/HER2 negative metastatic breast cancer: a commentary. J Manag Care Spec Pharm 2020; 26: 826–831.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10391228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32584682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cristofanilli M, Rugo HS, Im S-A, et al.. Overall survival with palbociclib and fulvestrant in women with HR+/HER2− ABC: updated exploratory analyses of PALOMA-3, a double-blind, phase III randomized study. Clin Cancer Res 2022; 28: 3433–3442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9662922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35552673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Queiroz MM, Sacardo KP, Ribeiro MF, et al.. Real-world treatment outcomes in HR+ HER2- metastatic breast cancer patients treated with CDK4/6 inhibitors: results from a reference center in Brazil. Cancer Treat Res Commun 2023; 35: 100683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36716534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner NC, Ro J, André F, et al.. Palbociclib in hormone-receptor–positive advanced breast cancer. N Engl J Med 2015; 373: 209–219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26030518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Y-S, Im S-A, Colleoni M, et al.. Updated overall survival of ribociclib plus endocrine therapy versus endocrine therapy alone in pre- and perimenopausal patients with HR+/HER2- advanced breast cancer in MONALEESA-7: a phase III randomized clinical trial. Clin Cancer Res 2022; 28: 851–859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9377723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34965945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hortobagyi GN, Stemmer SM, Burris HA, et al.. Updated results from MONALEESA-2, a phase III trial of first-line ribociclib plus letrozole versus placebo plus letrozole in hormone receptor-positive, HER2-negative advanced breast cancer. Ann Oncol 2018; 29: 1541–1547.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29718092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slamon DJ, Neven P, Chia S, et al.. Phase III randomized study of ribociclib and fulvestrant in hormone receptor-positive, human epidermal growth factor receptor 2-negative advanced breast cancer: MONALEESA-3. J Clin Oncol 2018; 36: 2465–2472.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29860922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ettl T, Schulz D, Bauer RJ. The renaissance of cyclin dependent kinase inhibitors. Cancers (Basel) 2022; 14: 293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8773807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35053461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fennell DA, King A, Mohammed S, et al.. Abemaciclib in patients with p16ink4A-deficient mesothelioma (MiST2): a single-arm, open-label, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 2022; 23: 374–381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35157829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldman JW, Shi P, Reck M, et al.. Treatment rationale and study design for the JUNIPER Study: a randomized phase III study of abemaciclib with best supportive care versus erlotinib with best supportive care in patients with stage IV non-small-cell lung cancer with a detectable KRAS mutation whose disease has progressed after platinum-based chemotherapy. Clin Lung Cancer 2016; 17: 80–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26432508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrarotto R, Anderson I, Medgyasszay B, et al.. Trilaciclib prior to chemotherapy reduces the usage of supportive care interventions for chemotherapy-induced myelosuppression in patients with small cell lung cancer: pooled analysis of three randomized phase 2 trials. Cancer Med 2021; 10: 5748–5756.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8419768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34405547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hart LL, Ferrarotto R, Andric ZG, et al.. Myelopreservation with trilaciclib in patients receiving topotecan for small cell lung cancer: results from a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase II study. Adv Ther 2021; 38: 350–365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7854399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33123968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abraham I, Onyekwere U, Deniz B, et al.. Trilaciclib and the economic value of multilineage myeloprotection from chemotherapy-induced myelosuppression among patients with extensive-stage small cell lung cancer treated with first-line chemotherapy. J Med Econ 2021; 24: 71–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34873975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan AR, Wright GS, Thummala AR, et al.. Trilaciclib plus chemotherapy versus chemotherapy alone in patients with metastatic triple-negative breast cancer: a multicentre, randomised, open-label, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 2019; 20: 1587–1601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31575503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhati V, Kumar A, Lather V, et al.. Association of temozolomide with progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy: a disproportionality analysis integrated with network pharmacology. Expert Opin Drug Saf 2023; 1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37915230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raschi E, Fusaroli M, La Placa M, et al.. Skin toxicities with cyclin-dependent kinase 4/6 inhibitors in breast cancer: signals from disproportionality analysis of the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System. Am J Clin Dermatol 2022; 23: 247–255.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34699032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raschi E, Fusaroli M, Ardizzoni A, et al.. Thromboembolic events with cyclin-dependent kinase 4/6 inhibitors in the FDA adverse event reporting system. Cancers (Basel) 2021; 13: 1758.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8067683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33917020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raschi E, Fusaroli M, Ardizzoni A, et al.. Cyclin-dependent kinase 4/6 inhibitors and interstitial lung disease in the FDA adverse event reporting system: a pharmacovigilance assessment. Breast Cancer Res Treat 2021; 186: 219–227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7641870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33150548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
MedDRA - The Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities, https://www.meddra.org/ (2023, accessed 20 March 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothman KJ, Lanes S, Sacks ST. The reporting odds ratio and its advantages over the proportional reporting ratio. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf 2004; 13: 519–523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15317031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raghuvanshi S, Rahman MA, Posa MK, et al.. Identification of novel signals associated with US-FDA Approved Drugs (2013) using disproportionality analysis. Curr Drug Saf 2024; 19: 395–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37990902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan M-M, Wu S-S, Qi Y-P, et al.. Association between cyclin-dependent kinase 4/6 inhibitors and venous thromboembolism: analysis of F.A.E.R.S. data. Expert Opin Drug Saf 2022; 21: 277–283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34581647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawa H, Niimura T, Yagi K, et al.. Evaluation of potential complication of interstitial lung disease with abemaciclib and palbociclib treatments. Cancer Rep (Hoboken) 2022; 5: e1402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8789605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33939324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossana R, Elena P, Lorenza G, et al.. Clinical impact of body mass index on palbociclib treatment outcomes and effect on exposure. Biomed Pharmacother 2023; 164: 114906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37295250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elena P, Lorenzo G, Marcella M, et al.. Association of ADME gene polymorphisms on toxicity to CDK4/6 inhibitors in patients with HR+ HER2- metastatic breast cancer. Biomed Pharmacother 2023; 167: 115479.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37734262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roncato R, Lorenzo G, Lorenza P, et al.. An integrated pharmacological counselling approach to guide decision-making in the treatment with CDK4/6 inhibitors for metastatic breast cancer. Front Pharmacol 2022; 13: 897951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9356076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35942220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLellan B, Kerr H. Cutaneous toxicities of the multikinase inhibitors sorafenib and sunitinib. Dermatol Ther 2011; 24: 396–400.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21910797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espinosa Lara P, Bueno C, Aranegui B, et al.. Yellowish nail pigmentation caused by sunitinib. Int J Dermatol 2016; 55: e462–e463.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26971887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>