<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39370656</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2192-2659</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced healthcare materials</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Healthc Mater</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Synthesis, Biological Evaluation and Reversal of Sulfonated Di- and Triblock Copolymers as Novel Parenteral Anticoagulants.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2402191</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2402191</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/adhm.202402191</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Despite targeting different coagulation cascade sites, all Food and Drug Administration-approved anticoagulants present an elevated risk of bleeding, including potentially life-threatening intracranial hemorrhage. Existing studies have not thoroughly investigated the efficacy and safety of sulfonate polymers in animal models and fully elucidate the precise mechanisms by which these polymers act. The activity and safety of sulfonated di- and triblock copolymers containing poly(sodium styrenesulfonate) (PSSS), poly(sodium 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropanesulfonate) (PAMPS), poly(ethylene glycol) (PEG), poly(sodium methacrylate) (PMAAS), poly(acrylic acid) (PAA), and poly(sodium 11-acrylamidoundecanoate) (PAaU) blocks are synthesized and assessed. PSSS-based copolymers exhibit greater anticoagulant activity than PAMPS-based ones. Their activity is mainly affected by the total concentration of sulfonate groups and molecular weight. PEG-containing copolymers demonstrate a better safety profile than PAA-containing ones. The selected copolymer PEG<sub>47</sub>-PSSS<sub>32</sub> exhibits potent anticoagulant activity in rodents after subcutaneous and intravenous administration. Heparin Binding Copolymer (HBC) completely reverses the anticoagulant activity of polymer in rat and human plasma. No interaction with platelets is observed. Selected copolymer targets mainly factor XII and fibrinogen, and to a lesser extent factors X, IX, VIII, and II, suggesting potential application in blood-contacting biomaterials for anticoagulation purposes. Further studies are needed to explore its therapeutic applications fully.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Swieton</LastName><ForeName>Justyna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5326-3950</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miklosz</LastName><ForeName>Joanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bielicka</LastName><ForeName>Natalia</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biopharmacy and Radiopharmacy, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frackiewicz</LastName><ForeName>Aleksandra</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Depczynski</LastName><ForeName>Karol</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stolarek</LastName><ForeName>Marta</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Chemistry, Jagiellonian University, Gronostajowa 2 St., Krakow, 30-387, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Doctoral School of Exact and Natural Sciences, Jagiellonian University, prof. S. Lojasiewicza 11 St., Krakow, 30-348, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bonarek</LastName><ForeName>Piotr</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Chemistry, Jagiellonian University, Gronostajowa 2 St., Krakow, 30-387, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaminski</LastName><ForeName>Kamil</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Chemistry, Jagiellonian University, Gronostajowa 2 St., Krakow, 30-387, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rozga</LastName><ForeName>Piotr</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Drug Discovery and Early Development Department, Adamed Pharma S.A., Pienkow, Mariana Adamkiewicza 6A St., Czosnow, 05-152, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yusa</LastName><ForeName>Shin-Ichi</ForeName><Initials>SI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Applied Chemistry, Graduate School of Engineering, University of Hyogo, 167 Shosha, Himeji, 671-2280, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gromotowicz-Poplawska</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biopharmacy and Radiopharmacy, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Szczubialka</LastName><ForeName>Krzysztof</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Chemistry, Jagiellonian University, Gronostajowa 2 St., Krakow, 30-387, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pawlak</LastName><ForeName>Dariusz</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mogielnicki</LastName><ForeName>Andrzej</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kalaska</LastName><ForeName>Bartlomiej</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4968-4429</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics, Medical University of Bialystok, Mickiewicza 2C St., Bialystok, 15-089, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>B.SUB.24.331</GrantID><Agency>Uniwersytet Medyczny w Bialymstoku</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Healthc Mater</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101581613</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2192-2640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anionic block copolymers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">heparin mimetics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">novel anticoagulants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sulfonate groups</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thrombosis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39370656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adhm.202402191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World health statistics 2023: monitoring health for the SDGs, sustainable development goals, https://www.who.int/publications‐detail‐redirect/9789240074323 (accessed: May 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Ludman, U. Zeymer, N. Danchin, P. Kala, C. Laroche, M. Sadeghi, R. Caporale, S. M. Shaheen, J. Legutko, Z. Iakobishvili, K. F. Alhabib, Z. Motovska, M. Studencan, J. Mimoso, D. Becker, D. Alexopoulos, Z. Kereseselidze, S. Stojkovic, P. Zelveian, A. Goda, E. Mirrakhimov, G. Bajraktari, H. A. Farhan, P. Šerpytis, B. Raungaard, T. Marandi, A. M. Moore, M. Quinn, P. P. Karjalainen, G. Tatu‐Chitoiu, et al., Eur. Heart J. Acute Cardiovasc Care 2023, 12, 22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. I. Shen, W. C. Winkelmayer, Am. J. Kidney Dis. 2012, 60, 473.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Bianchini, L. Liverani, F. Spelta, G. Mascellani, B. Parma, Semin. Thromb. Hemost. 2007, 33, 496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. S. Weitz, J. I. Weitz, J. Thromb. Thrombolysis 2010, 29, 199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Othieno, E. Okpo, R. Forster, Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 2018, 1, CD003076.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Khatib, K. Nitti, M. McDowell, R. Szymialis, C. Blair, N. Glowacki, W. Rhoades, J. Thromb. Thrombolysis 2021, 52, 179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Xu, H. Ji, L. Xu, S. Cheng, X. Liu, Y. Li, R. Zhong, W. Zhao, J. N. Kizhakkedathu, C. Zhao, Nat. Commun. 2023, 14, 4875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Song, H. Ji, Y. Li, Y. Xiong, L. Qiu, R. Zhong, M. Tian, J. N. Kizhakkedathu, B. Su, Q. Wei, W. Zhao, C. Zhao, Nat. Biomed. Eng. 2021, 5, 1143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. A. J. Mourier, O. Y. Guichard, F. Herman, C. Viskov, Anal. Biochem. 2014, 453, 7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Petitou, J. P. Hérault, A. Bernat, P. A. Driguez, P. Duchaussoy, J. C. Lormeau, J. M. Herbert, Nature 1999, 398, 417.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Travers, R. A. Shenoi, M. T. Kalathottukaren, J. N. Kizhakkedathu, J. H. Morrissey, Blood 2014, 124, 3183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Türk, R. Haag, S. Alban, Bioconjugate Chem. 2004, 15, 162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. A. Frontera, J. J. Lewin, A. A. Rabinstein, I. P. Aisiku, A. W. Alexandrov, A. M. Cook, G. J. del Zoppo, M. A. Kumar, E. I. B. Peerschke, M. F. Stiefel, J. S. Teitelbaum, K. E. Wartenberg, C. L. Zerfoss, Neurocrit Care 2016, 24, 6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. H. Levy, K. Ghadimi, J. N. Kizhakkedathu, T. Iba, J. Thromb. Haemostasis 2023, 21, 1714.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Boer, M. I. Meesters, D. Veerhoek, A. B. A. Vonk, Br. J. Anaesth. 2018, 120, 914.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Hecht, M. Besser, F. Falter, J. Extra Corpor Technol. 2020, 52, 63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Demma, J. H. Levy, Anesth. Analg. 2012, 115, 1273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Kalaska, K. Kaminski, J. Miklosz, S. Yusa, E. Sokolowska, A. Blazejczyk, J. Wietrzyk, I. Kasacka, K. Szczubialka, D. Pawlak, M. Nowakowska, A. Mogielnicki, Transl. Res. 2016, 177, 98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Kalaska, J. Miklosz, K. Kamiński, J. Swieton, A. Jakimczuk, S.‐I. Yusa, D. Pawlak, M. Nowakowska, K. Szczubiałka, A. Mogielnicki, J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther. 2020, 373, 51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. T. Kalathottukaren, A. L. Creagh, S. Abbina, G. Lu, M. J. Karbarz, A. Pandey, P. B. Conley, J. N. Kizhakkedathu, C. Haynes, Blood Adv. 2018, 2, 2104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Sokolowska, B. Kalaska, J. Miklosz, A. Mogielnicki, Expert Opin. Drug Metab. Toxicol. 2016, 12, 897.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. A. MacArthur, J. Goswami, S. M. Navarro, S. Vappala, C. C. La, N. Yudin, J. Zietlow, S. A. Smith, J. H. Morrissey, G. M. Spears, K. R. Bailey, J.‐F. Dong, R. A. Kozar, J. N. Kizhakkedathu, M. S. Park, Shock 2024, 61, 848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. J. Milling, S. Middeldorp, L. Xu, B. Koch, A. Demchuk, J. W. Eikelboom, P. Verhamme, A. T. Cohen, J. Beyer‐Westendorf, C. M. Gibson, J. Lopez‐Sendon, M. Crowther, A. Shoamanesh, M. Coppens, J. Schmidt, P. Albaladejo, S. J. Connolly, Circulation 2023, 147, 1026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y.‐A. Heo, Drugs 2018, 78, 1049.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. A. Noordergraaf, M. Alings, Heart Int. 2020, 14, 20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Lewis, O. Iqbal, W. Jeske, D. Hoppensteadt, F. Siddiqui, J. Fareed, Clin. Appl. Thromb. Hemost. 2022, 28, 107602962210999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Sun, N. Gao, L. Ren, S. Liu, L. Lin, W. Zheng, L. Zhou, R. Yin, J. Zhao, Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2020, 207, 112796.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. A. Nahain, V. Ignjatovic, P. Monagle, J. Tsanaktsidis, G. Vamvounis, V. Ferro, Biomacromolecules 2020, 21, 1009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Ma, J. Huang, X. Zhu, B. Zhu, L. Wang, W. Zhao, L. Qiu, B. Song, C. Zhao, F. Yan, Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2019, 122, 784.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Baier, J. L. Ruppertz, M. M. Pfleiderer, B. S. Blaum, L. Hartmann, Chem. Commun. 2018, 54, 10487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. H. Nguyen, S. J. Paluck, A. J. McGahran, H. D. Maynard, Biomacromolecules 2015, 16, 2684.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. I. Takahara, K. Hosoya, M. Sunako, S. Hirohara, K. Terada, T. Ando, M. Tanihara, Acta Biomater. 2010, 6, 3138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Yusa, Y. Yokoyama, Y. Morishima, Macromolecules 2009, 42, 376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Yokoyama, S. Yusa, Polymer J. 2013, 45, 985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Mizusaki, Y. Shimada, Y. Morishima, S. I. Yusa, Polymers 2016, 8, 56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. P. Yap, X. Hao, E. Tjipto, C. Gudipati, J. F. Quinn, T. P. Davis, C. Barner‐Kowollik, M. H. Stenzel, F. Caruso, Langmuir 2008, 24, 8981.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. N. Swilley, E. M. Zajkowski, J. B. Matson, Polym. Chem. 2023, 14, 2572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Kalaska, K. Kamiński, J. Miklosz, K. Nakai, S.‐I. Yusa, D. Pawlak, M. Nowakowska, A. Mogielnicki, K. Szczubiałka, Biomacromolecules 2018, 19, 3104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Botwina, M. Obłoza, M. Zatorska‐Płachta, K. Kamiński, M. Mizusaki, S.‐I. S. I. Yusa, K. Szczubiałka, K. Pyrc, M. Nowakowska, Pharmaceutics 2022, 14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Gurnani, C. P. Bray, R. A. E. Richardson, R. Peltier, S. Perrier, Macromol. Rapid Commun. 2019, 40, 1800314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Masuzawa, M. Kitazawa, Materials 2022, 15, 3687.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Kaikita, K. Hosokawa, J. R. Dahlen, K. Tsujita, Thromb. Haemost. 2019, 119, 1554.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Al Ghaithi, J. Mori, Z. Nagy, A. Maclachlan, L. Hardy, H. Philippou, E. Hethershaw, N. V. Morgan, Y. A. Senis, P. Harrison, Platelets 2019, 30, 893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Tamada, M. Murata, T. Hayashi, K. Goto, Biomaterials 2002, 23, 1375.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Derbalah, S. Duffull, F. Newall, K. Moynihan, H. Al‐Sallami, Clin. Pharmacokinet. 2019, 58, 1015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Kandrotas, Clin. Pharmacokinet. 1992, 22, 359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Song, A. Kouta, L. M. Cera, K. Xia, F. Zhang, R. Kraemer, J. Fareed, R. J. Linhardt, W. Jeske, Carbohydr. Polym. 2023, 311, 120779.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Lippi, E. J. Favaloro, Semin. Thromb. Hemost. 2008, 34, 604.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Seyrek, P. L. Dubin, J. Henriksen, Biopolymers 2007, 86, 249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Richard, R. Swanson, S. T. Olson, J. Biol. Chem. 2009, 284, 27054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Li, G. Wu, X. Cai, Y. Ye, Radiat. Phys. Chem. 2017, 134, 27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Hamada, T. Kurosaki, J. Hashizume, H. Harasawa, H. Nakagawa, T. Nakamura, Y. Kodama, H. Sasaki, Pharmaceutics 2021, 13, 126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Schlegel, C. Largeau, P. Bigey, M. Bessodes, K. Lebozec, D. Scherman, V. Escriou, J. Controlled Release 2011, 152, 393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Setoyama, Y. Murakami, K. Inoue, H. Iwata, H. Kitamura, T. Shimada, H. Kaji, Y. Ikada, M. Imamura, Transplant. Proc. 1999, 31, 2818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Gao, B. Boylan, J. Fang, D. A. Wilcox, D. K. Newman, P. J. Newman, Blood 2011, 117, 4946.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Shojania, G. Turnbull, Am. J. Hematol. 1987, 26, 255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. M. Waples, O. E. Olorundare, S. L. Goodman, Q. J. Lai, R. M. Albrecht, J. Biomed. Mater. Res. 1996, 32, 65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J.‐C. Lin, T.‐M. Ko, S. L. Cooper, J. Colloid Interface Sci. 1994, 164, 99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. A. Skarja, J. L. Brash, J. Biomed. Mater. Res. 1997, 34, 439.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colloids Surf., B 1998, 10, 263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Han, W. Yao, X. Yang, X. Liu, X. Gao, Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2005, 36, 201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. S. Bennett, Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 2001, 936, 340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Lisman, C. Weeterings, P. G. de Groot, Front. Biosci. 2005, 10, 2504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Baumann, D. Hofmann, S. Nullmeier, P. Panther, C. Dietze, A. Musyanovych, S. Ritz, K. Landfester, V. Mailänder, Nanomedicine 2013, 8, 699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. J. Glass, L. Chen, S. Alcantara, E. J. Crampin, K. J. Thurecht, R. De Rose, S. J. Kent, ACS Macro Lett. 2017, 6, 586.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. B. Bradfield, G. V. R. Born, Cell. Immunol. 1974, 14, 22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Zhang, E. Condac, H. Qiu, J. Jiang, G. Gutierrez‐Sanchez, C. Bergmann, T. Handel, L. Wang, J. Biol. Chem. 2012, 287, 5542.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Iwanaga, R. Fukushima, T. Nagasato, I. Maruyama, N. Miura, J. Vet. Diagn. Invest. 2021, 33, 357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Yamaguchi, T. Moriki, A. Igari, Y. Matsubara, T. Ohnishi, K. Hosokawa, M. Murata, Thromb. Res. 2013, 132, 263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. Yau, P. Liao, J. C. Fredenburgh, A. R. Stafford, A. S. Revenko, B. P. Monia, J. I. Weitz, Blood 2014, 123, 2102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Naito, R. Ukita, J. Wilbs, K. Wu, X. Lin, N. M. Carleton, K. Roberts, S. Jiang, C. Heinis, K. E. Cook, Biomaterials 2021, 272, 120778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Thomas, K. Thelen, S. Kraff, S. Schwers, S. Schiffer, S. Unger, A. Yassen, S. Boxnick, Res. Pract. Thromb. Haemost. 2019, 3, 242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. S. Woodruff, I. Ivanov, I. M. Verhamme, M.‐F. Sun, D. Gailani, B. A. Sullenger, Thromb. Res. 2017, 156, 134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. J. Hayward, D. I. Goldberg, E. M. Morrel, P. M. Friden, P. M. Bokesch, Circulation 2017, 136, 1099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Schousboe, Biochem. Pharmacol. 2008, 75, 1007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Kenne, T. Renné, Drug Discov. Today 2014, 19, 1459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. I. Weitz, J. C. Fredenburgh, Front. Med. 2017, 4, 19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Gailani, T. Renné, J. Thromb. Haemost. 2007, 5, 1106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H.‐U. Pauer, T. Renné, B. Hemmerlein, T. Legler, S. Fritzlar, I. Adham, W. Müller‐Esterl, G. Emons, U. Sancken, W. Engel, P. Burfeind, Thromb. Haemost. 2004, 92, 503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Girolami, S. Ferrari, E. Cosi, B. Girolami, M. L. Randi, J. Thromb. Thrombolysis 2019, 47, 481.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Girolami, M. L. Randi, S. Gavasso, A. M. Lombardi, F. Spiezia, J. Thromb. Thrombolysis 2004, 17, 139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Lämmle, W. A. Wuillemin, I. Huber, M. Krauskopf, C. Zürcher, R. Pflugshaupt, M. Furlan, Thromb. Haemost. 1991, 65, 117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Searle, Y.‐C. Chen, M. Wallert, J. D. McFadyen, A. C. Maluenda, J. Noonan, P. Kanellakis, M. T. K. Zaldivia, A. Huang, H. Lioe, M. Biondo, M. W. Nolte, P. Rossato, A. Bobik, C. Panousis, X. Wang, H. Hosseini, K. Peter, Thromb. Haemost. 2022, 122, 196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Tillman, D. Gailani, Semin. Thromb. Hemost. 2018, 44, 060.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. Yau, A. R. Stafford, P. Liao, J. C. Fredenburgh, R. Roberts, J. I. Weitz, Blood 2011, 118, 6667.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. Yau, A. R. Stafford, P. Liao, J. C. Fredenburgh, R. Roberts, J. L. Brash, J. I. Weitz, Acta Biomater. 2012, 8, 4092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Sonntag, I. Dähnert, B. Stiller, R. Hetzer, P. E. Lange, Ann. Thorac. Surg. 1998, 65, 525.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. D. Frank, J. Weber, H. Dresbach, H. Thelen, C. Weiss, J. Floege, Kidney Int. 2001, 60, 1972.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Zeerleder, M. Schloesser, M. Redondo, W. A. Wuillemin, W. Engel, M. Furlan, B. Lämmle, Thromb. Haemost. 1999, 82, 1240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. P. Govers‐Riemslag, M. Smid, J. A. Cooper, K. A. Bauer, R. D. Rosenberg, C. E. Hack, K. Hamulyak, H. M. H. Spronk, G. J. Miller, H. ten Cate, J. Thromb. Haemost. 2007, 5, 1896.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Koster, F. R. Rosendaal, E. Briët, J. P. Vandenbroucke, Br. J. Haematol. 1994, 87, 422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Siegerink, J. W. P. Govers‐Riemslag, F. R. Rosendaal, H. Ten Cate, A. Algra, Circulation 2010, 122, 1854.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. S. Wolberg, Y. Sang, Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol 2022, 42, 931.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Chen, R. Ward, Y. Tian, F. Malizia, D. H. Gracias, Y. R. Shen, G. A. Somorjai, J. Biomed. Mater. Res. 2002, 62, 254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. G. Grasel, S. L. Cooper, J. Biomed. Mater. Res. 1989, 23, 311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. P. Santerre, P. ten Hove, N. H. VanderKamp, J. L. Brash, J. Biomed. Mater. Res. 1992, 26, 39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. S. Hur, D. S. Paul, E. G. Bouck, O. A. Negrón, J.‐M. Mwiza, L. G. Poole, H. M. Cline‐Fedewa, E. G. Clark, L. J. Juang, J. Leung, C. J. Kastrup, T. P. Ugarova, A. S. Wolberg, J. P. Luyendyk, W. Bergmeier, M. J. Flick, Blood 2022, 139, 1374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Crowther, T. E. Warkentin, Blood 2008, 111, 4871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. J. Stalker, Platelets 2020, 31, 423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Marcinczyk, A. Golaszewska, T. Misztal, A. Gromotowicz‐Poplawska, T. Rusak, E. Chabielska, Naunyn‐Schmiedeberg's Arch. Pharmacol. 2020, 393, 727.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Dinges, K. Solakyildirim, C. K. Larive, Electrophoresis 2014, 35, 1469.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Kusche, L. G. Oscarsson, R. Reynertson, L. Rodén, U. Lindahl, J. Biol. Chem. 1991, 266, 7400.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Ben Mansour, M. Dhahri, L. Vénisse, M. Jandrot‐Perrus, F. Chaubet, R. M. Maaroufi, Thromb. Res. 2009, 123, 902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Mauray, C. Sternberg, J. Theveniaux, J. Millet, C. Sinquin, J. Tapon‐Bretaudière, A. M. Fischer, Thromb. Haemost. 1995, 74, 1280.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Huang, M. A. Shaw, E. S. Mullins, T. L. Kirley, N. Ayres, Biomacromolecules 2014, 15, 4455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Huang, M. A. Shaw, M. R. Warmin, E. S. Mullins, N. Ayres, Polym. Chem. 2016, 7, 3897.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Onishi, Y. Miyashita, T. Motomura, S. Yamashita, N. Sakamoto, M. Akashi, J. Biomater. Sci., Polym. Ed. 1998, 9, 973.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z.‐M. Wang, K.‐J. Xiao, L. Li, J.‐Y. Wu, Cellulose 2010, 17, 953.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Groth, W. Wagenknecht, Biomaterials 2001, 22, 2719.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Kindness, W. F. Long, F. B. Williamson, Br. J. Pharmacol. 1980, 68, 645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Suwan, Z. Zhang, B. Li, P. Vongchan, P. Meepowpan, F. Zhang, S. A. Mousa, S. Mousa, B. Premanode, P. Kongtawelert, R. J. Linhardt, Carbohydr. Res. 2009, 344, 1190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Vikhoreva, G. Bannikova, P. Stolbushkina, A. Panov, N. Drozd, V. Makarov, V. Varlamov, L. Gal'braikh, Carbohydr. Polym. 2005, 62, 327.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. A. Nahain, V. Ignjatovic, P. Monagle, J. Tsanaktsidis, G. Vamvounis, V. Ferro, Macromol. Biosci. 2020, 20, 2000110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Paneva, O. Stoilova, N. Manolova, D. Danchev, Z. Lazarov, I. Rashkov, e‐Polymers 2003, 3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. J. Martin, J. A. Toce, P. J. Anevski, D. M. Tollefsen, D. R. Abendschein, J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther. 1999, 288, 516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. J. Desai, R. S. Boothello, A. Y. Mehta, J. N. Scarsdale, H. T. Wright, U. R. Desai, Biochemistry 2011, 50, 6973.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Muschin, D. Budragchaa, T. Kanamoto, H. Nakashima, K. Ichiyama, N. Yamamoto, H. Shuqin, T. Yoshida, Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2016, 89, 415.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. M. Mestechkina, V. D. Shcherbukhin, G. E. Bannikova, V. P. Varlamov, N. N. Drozd, A. S. Tolstenkov, V. A. Makarov, V. E. Tikhonov, Prikl. Biokhim. Mikrobiol. 2008, 44, 111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Nie, L. Ma, Y. Xia, C. He, J. Deng, L. Wang, C. Cheng, S. Sun, C. Zhao, J. Membr. Sci. 2015, 475, 455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Liekens, J. Neyts, B. Degrève, E. De Clercq, Oncol. Res. 1997, 9, 173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Liekens, D. Leali, J. Neyts, R. Esnouf, M. Rusnati, P. Dell'Era, P. C. Maudgal, E. D. Clercq, M. Presta, Mol. Pharmacol. 1999, 56, 204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Sangaj, P. Kyriakakis, D. Yang, C.‐W. Chang, G. Arya, S. Varghese, Biomacromolecules 2010, 11, 3294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Wang, Z. Lyu, G. Chen, H. Wang, Y. Yuan, K. Ding, Q. Yu, L. Yuan, H. Chen, Chem. Commun. 2015, 51, 15434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. I. Oh, G. J. Sheng, S.‐K. Chang, L. C. Hsieh‐Wilson, Angew. Chem. 2013, 125, 12012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Skóra, M. Obłoza, M. Tymecka, B. Kalaska, M. Gurgul, K. Kamiński, Microbiol. Spectr. 2023, 11, e00844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Miklosz, B. Kalaska, S. Zajaczkowski, D. Pawlak, A. Mogielnicki, Pharmaceuticals 2021, 14, 1223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Hosokawa, T. Ohnishi, T. Kondo, M. Fukasawa, T. Koide, I. Maruyama, K. A. Tanaka, J. Thromb. Haemost. 2011, 9, 2029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Hosokawa, T. Ohnishi, M. Fukasawa, T. Kondo, H. Sameshima, T. Koide, K. A. Tanaka, I. Maruyama, Microvasc. Res. 2012, 83, 154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Hosokawa, T. Ohnishi, H. Sameshima, N. Miura, T. Ito, T. Koide, I. Maruyama, Thromb. Haemost. 2013, 109, 102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Daidone, G. Barbon, M. G. Cattini, E. Pontara, C. Romualdi, I. Di Pasquale, K. Hosokawa, A. Casonato, Haemophilia 2016, 22, 949.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Kalaska, J. Miklosz, J. Swieton, A. Jakimczuk, D. Pawlak, A. Mogielnicki, Vaccine 2022, 40, 1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Marcińczyk, T. Misztal, E. Chabielska, A. Gromotowicz‐Popławska, Sci. Rep. 2023, 13, 932.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>