<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39188879</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2296-858X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Med (Lausanne)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Toward trustworthy medical device <i>in silico</i> clinical trials: a hierarchical framework for establishing credibility and strategies for overcoming key challenges.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1433372</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1433372</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1433372</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fmed.2024.1433372</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Computational models of patients and medical devices can be combined to perform an <i>in silico</i> clinical trial (ISCT) to investigate questions related to device safety and/or effectiveness across the total product life cycle. ISCTs can potentially accelerate product development by more quickly informing device design and testing or they could be used to refine, reduce, or in some cases to completely replace human subjects in a clinical trial. There are numerous potential benefits of ISCTs. An important caveat, however, is that an ISCT is a virtual representation of the real world that has to be shown to be credible before being relied upon to make decisions that have the potential to cause patient harm. There are many challenges to establishing ISCT credibility. ISCTs can integrate many different submodels that potentially use different modeling types (e.g., physics-based, data-driven, rule-based) that necessitate different strategies and approaches for generating credibility evidence. ISCT submodels can include those for the medical device, the patient, the interaction of the device and patient, generating virtual patients, clinical decision making and simulating an intervention (e.g., device implantation), and translating acute physics-based simulation outputs to health-related clinical outcomes (e.g., device safety and/or effectiveness endpoints). Establishing the credibility of each ISCT submodel is challenging, but is nonetheless important because inaccurate output from a single submodel could potentially compromise the credibility of the entire ISCT. The objective of this study is to begin addressing some of these challenges and to identify general strategies for establishing ISCT credibility. Most notably, we propose a hierarchical approach for assessing the credibility of an ISCT that involves systematically gathering credibility evidence for each ISCT submodel in isolation before demonstrating credibility of the full ISCT. Also, following FDA Guidance for assessing computational model credibility, we provide suggestions for ways to clearly describe each of the ISCT submodels and the full ISCT, discuss considerations for performing an ISCT model risk assessment, identify common challenges to demonstrating ISCT credibility, and present strategies for addressing these challenges using our proposed hierarchical approach. Finally, in the Appendix we illustrate the many concepts described here using a hypothetical ISCT example.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Aycock, Battisti, Peterson, Yao, Kreuzer, Capelli, Pant, Pathmanathan, Hoganson, Levine and Craven.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aycock</LastName><ForeName>Kenneth I</ForeName><Initials>KI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Office of Science and Engineering Laboratories, Center for Devices and Radiological Health, United States Food and Drug Administration, Silver Spring, MD, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Battisti</LastName><ForeName>Tom</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dassault Systèmes, Waltham, MA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peterson</LastName><ForeName>Ashley</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thornton Tomasetti, Inc., New York, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yao</LastName><ForeName>Jiang</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dassault Systèmes, Waltham, MA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kreuzer</LastName><ForeName>Steven</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Exponent, Inc., Menlo Park, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Capelli</LastName><ForeName>Claudio</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Cardiovascular Science, University College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pant</LastName><ForeName>Sanjay</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Science and Engineering, Swansea University, Swansea, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pathmanathan</LastName><ForeName>Pras</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Office of Science and Engineering Laboratories, Center for Devices and Radiological Health, United States Food and Drug Administration, Silver Spring, MD, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoganson</LastName><ForeName>David M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiac Surgery, Boston Children's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Levine</LastName><ForeName>Steve M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dassault Systèmes, Waltham, MA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Craven</LastName><ForeName>Brent A</ForeName><Initials>BA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Office of Science and Engineering Laboratories, Center for Devices and Radiological Health, United States Food and Drug Administration, Silver Spring, MD, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Med (Lausanne)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101648047</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-858X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ISCT</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">In silico clinical trial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">computational modeling and simulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hierarchical verification and validation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">model credibility</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>TB, JY, and SL were employed by the company Dassault Systémes, makers of the software applications 3DEXPERIENCE, Abaqus, and Dymola that were used in this study. AP was employed by Thornton Tomasetti, Inc. SK was employed by Exponent, Inc. DH receives gift-in-kind software from several modeling and simulation companies including Dassault Systémes, Ansys, Materialize, and Realize Medical. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39188879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11346031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2024.1433372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Craven B, Aycock K. Medical device total product life cycle. Figshare (2024). doi: 10.6084/m9.figshare.25996087.v1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.6084/m9.figshare.25996087.v1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison TM, Dreher ML, Nagaraja S, Angelone LM, Kainz W. The role of computational modeling and simulation in the total product life cycle of peripheral vascular devices. J Med Devices. (2017) 11:024503. doi: 10.1115/1.4035866, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1115/1.4035866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5823268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29479395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viceconti M, Emili L, Afshari P, Courcelles E, Curreli C, Famaey N, et al. . Possible contexts of use for in silico trials methodologies: A consensus-based review. IEEE J Biomed Health. (2021) 25:3977–82. doi: 10.1109/JBHI.2021.3090469, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JBHI.2021.3090469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34161248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison TM, Stitzel JD, Levine SM. Modeling and simulation in biomedical engineering: regulatory science and innovation for advancing public health. Ann Biomed Eng. (2023) 51:1–5. doi: 10.1007/s10439-022-03116-7, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10439-022-03116-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36562847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA . Enrichment Strategies for Clinical Trials to Support Determination of Effectiveness of Human Drugs and Biological Products: Guidance for Industry. (2019). Available at: https://www.fda.gov/media/121320/download.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Himes A, Haddad T, Bardot D, On Behalf of the MDIC Mock Presubmission Working Group Participants . Augmenting a clinical study with virtual patient models: Food and Drug Administration and industry collaboration. J Med Devices. (2016) 10:030947. doi: 10.1115/1.4033870</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1115/1.4033870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haddad T, Himes A, Thompson L, Irony T, Nair R, On Behalf of MDIC Computer Modeling and Simulation Working Group Participants . Incorporation of stochastic engineering models as prior information in Bayesian medical device trials. J Biopharm Stat. (2017) 27:1089–103. doi: 10.1080/10543406.2017.1300907, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10543406.2017.1300907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28281931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badano A, Graff CG, Badal A, Sharma D, Zeng R, Samuelson FW, et al. . Evaluation of digital breast tomosynthesis as replacement of full-field digital mammography using an in silico imaging trial. JAMA Netw Open. (2018) 1:e185474. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2018.5474, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2018.5474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6324392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30646401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badano A. In silico imaging clinical trials: cheaper, faster, better, safer, and more scalable. Trials. (2021) 22:64. doi: 10.1186/s13063-020-05002-w, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13063-020-05002-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7814719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33468186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gramacy RB. Surrogates: Gaussian Process Modeling, Design, and Optimization for the Applied Sciences. New York: Taylor and Francis Group, LLC; (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodner J, Kaul V. A framework for in silico clinical trials for medical devices using concepts from model verification, validation, and uncertainty quantification. J Verif Valid Uncertain Quantif. (2022) 7:021001. doi: 10.1115/1.4053565</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1115/1.4053565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Favre P, Maquer G, Henderson A, Hertig D, Ciric D, Bischoff JE. In silico clinical trials in the orthopedic device industry: From fantasy to reality? Ann Biomed Eng. (2021) 49:3213–26. doi: 10.1007/s10439-021-02787-y, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10439-021-02787-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8110242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33973129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faris O, Shuren J. An FDA viewpoint on unique considerations for medical-device clinical trials. N Engl J Med. (2017) 376:1350–7. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra1512592, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1512592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28379790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA . Assessing the Credibility of Computational Modeling and Simulation in Medical Device Submissions: Guidance for Industry and Food and Drug Administration Staff. (2023). Available at: https://www.fda.gov/media/154985/download.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathmanathan P, Aycock KI, Badal A, Bighamian R, Bodner J, Craven BA, et al. . Credibility assessment of in silico clinical trials for medical devices. PLoS Comput Biol. (2024) 2024:11. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012289</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11309390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39116026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA . Reporting of Computational Modeling Studies in Medical Device Submissions: Guidance for Industry and Food and Drug Administration Staff. (2016). Available at: https://www.fda.gov/media/87586/download.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niederer SA, Aboelkassem Y, Cantwell CD, Corrado C, Coveney S, Cherry EM, et al. . Creation and application of virtual patient cohorts of heart models. Phil Trans R Soc A. (2020) 378:20190558. doi: 10.1098/rsta.2019.0558, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsta.2019.0558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7287335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32448064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberkampf WL, Roy CJ. Verification and Validation in Scientific Computing. 1st ed. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ASME . V&amp;V 10–2019. Standard for Verification and Validation in Computational Solid Mechanics. New York: American Society of Mechanical Engineers; (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathmanathan P, Gray RA. Validation and trustworthiness of multiscale models of cardiac electrophysiology. Front Physiol. (2018) 9:106. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2018.00106, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphys.2018.00106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5818422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29497385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hills RG, Pilch M, Dowding KJ, Red-Horse J, Paez TL, Babuška I, et al. . Validation challenge workshop. Comput Methods in Appl Mech Eng. (2008) 197:2375–80. doi: 10.1016/j.cma.2007.10.016, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cma.2007.10.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ASME . V&amp;V 40–2018. Assessing Credibility of Computational Modeling Through Verification and Validation: Application to Medical Devices. New York: American Society of Mechanical Engineers; (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 14971:2019 . Medical devices — Application of risk management to medical devices. Geneva, Switzerland: International Standards Organization; (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO/TR 24971:2020 . Medical devices — Guidance on the application of ISO 14971. Geneva, Switzerland: International Standards Organization; (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roache PJ. Fundamentals of Verification and Validation. Socorro, New Mexico: Hermosa Publishers; (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aycock KI, Rebelo N, Craven BA. Method of manufactured solutions code verification of elastostatic solid mechanics problems in a commercial finite element solver. Comput Struct. (2020) 229:106175. doi: 10.1016/j.compstruc.2019.106175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.compstruc.2019.106175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paranjape HM, Aycock KI, Bonsignore C, Weaver JD, Craven BA, Duerig TW. A probabilistic approach with built-in uncertainty quantification for the calibration of a superelastic constitutive model from full-field strain data. Comput Mater Sci. (2021) 192:110357. doi: 10.1016/j.commatsci.2021.110357</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.commatsci.2021.110357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aldieri A, Curreli C, Szyszko JA, La Mattina AA, Viceconti M. Credibility assessment of computational models according to ASME V&amp;V40: Application to the Bologna Biomechanical Computed Tomography solution. Comput Methods Prog Biomed. (2023) 240:107727. doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107727, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37523955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bischoff JE, Dharia MA, Favre P. A risk and credibility framework for in silico clinical trials of medical devices. Comput Methods Prog Biomed. (2023) 242:107813. doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107813, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37734216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galappaththige S, Gray RA, Mendonca Costa C, Niederer S, Pathmanathan P. Credibility assessment of patient-specific computational modeling using patient-specific cardiac modeling as an exemplar. PLoS Comput Biol. (2022) 18:e1010541. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010541, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9550052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36215228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H, Scott PE, Yue LQ. Chapter 73: Device Trials In: Piantadosi S, Meinert CL, editors. Principles and Practice of Clinical Trials. Cham, Switzerland: Springer International Publishing; (2022). 1399–416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Favre P, Bischoff J. Identifying the patient harms to include in an in silico clinical trial. Comput Methods Prog Biomed. (2023) 241:107735. doi: 10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107735, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2023.107735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37544163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>