<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39195797</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>31</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2306-7381</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Veterinary sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vet Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A One Health Perspective on Camel Meat Hygiene and Zoonoses: Insights from a Decade of Research in the Middle East.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">344</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/vetsci11080344</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The purpose of this review was to investigatethe microbial and chemical safety of camel meat and the zoonotic diseases associated with camels in the Middle East over the past decade, emphasizing the crucial role of a One Health approach. By systematically analyzing recent studies (in the past decade, from 2014), we assessed pathogen prevalence, contamination with heavy metals and pesticide residues, and the impact of zoonotic diseases like Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV). The findings revealed significant variability in pathogen prevalence, with the frequent detection of traditional foodborne pathogens (e.g., <i>Salmonella</i> and <i>E. coli O157</i>), as well as antibiotic-resistant strains like methicillin-resistant and vancomycin-resistant <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> and extended-spectrum β-lactamase (ESBL)-producing <i>E. coli</i>, underscoring the need for stringent antibiotic use policies and robust food safety measures. Additionally, the review highlighted substantial contamination of camel meat with heavy metals and pesticide residues, posing significant public health concerns that necessitate stringent regulatory measures and regular monitoring. The persistent occurrence of zoonotic diseases, particularly MERS-CoV, along with other threats like trypanosomiasis, brucellosis, and <i>Clostridium perfringens</i>, emphasizes the importance of strengthening ongoing surveillance. Enhancing investment in diagnostic infrastructures, training programs, and planning capabilities is crucial to address these issues at the camel-human interface in the Middle East. Adopting a One Health perspective is vital to ensuring the safety and quality of camel meat and managing zoonotic risks effectively to ultimately safeguard public health and promote sustainable livestock practices.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohamed</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed-Yousif Ibrahim</ForeName><Initials>MI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9563-4393</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain P.O. Box 1555, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ASPIRE Research Institute for Food Security in the Drylands (ARIFSID), United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain P.O. Box 1555, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lakshmi</LastName><ForeName>Glindya Bhagya</ForeName><Initials>GB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6758-6040</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain P.O. Box 1555, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ASPIRE Research Institute for Food Security in the Drylands (ARIFSID), United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain P.O. Box 1555, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sodagari</LastName><ForeName>Hamidreza</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathobiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL 61802, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Habib</LastName><ForeName>Ihab</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0938-0607</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain P.O. Box 1555, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ASPIRE Research Institute for Food Security in the Drylands (ARIFSID), United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain P.O. Box 1555, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>ARIFSID</GrantID><Agency>ASPRE (AE)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Vet Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101680127</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2306-7381</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">camels</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">zoonotic diseases</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39195797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11359195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vetsci11080344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">vetsci11080344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Dorman A.E. Aspects of the Husbandry and Management of the Genus Camelus. Br. Vet. J. 1984;140:616–633. doi: 10.1016/0007-1935(84)90013-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0007-1935(84)90013-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6391603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skidmore J.A. Reproduction in Dromedary Camels: An Update. Anim. Reprod. 2005;2:161–171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouajd S., Kamel B. Physiological Particularities of Dromedary (Camelus dromedarius) and Experimental Implications. Scand. J. Lab. Anim. Sci. 2009;36:19–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faraz A., Tauqir N.A., Ishaq H.M., Hussain S.M., Akbar M.A., Mirza R.H., Sufyan A., Rashid S. Camel Production Profile and Role in Food Security. Int. J. Agric. Biosci. 2023;2:216–220. doi: 10.47278/book.oht/2023.63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47278/book.oht/2023.63</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurtu M.Y. An Assessment of the Productivity for Meat and the Carcase Yield of Camels (Camelus dromedarius) and of the Consumption of Camel Meat in the Eastern Region of Ethiopia. Trop. Anim. Health Prod. 2004;36:65–76. doi: 10.1023/B:TROP.0000009520.34657.35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/B:TROP.0000009520.34657.35</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14979560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadim I.T., Mahgoub O., Al-Marzooqi W., Al-Zadjali S., Annamalai K., Mansour M.H. Effects of Age on Composition and Quality of Muscle Longissimus Thoracis of the Omani Arabian Camel (Camelus dromedarius) Meat Sci. 2006;73:619–625. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2006.03.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2006.03.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22062561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadim I.T., Al-Amri I.S., Al Kindi A.Y., Mbaga M. Camel Meat Production and Quality: A Review. J. Camel Pract. Res. 2018;25:9. doi: 10.5958/2277-8934.2018.00002.4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5958/2277-8934.2018.00002.4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson K.S., Bwala D.A., Nuhu E.J. The Dromedary Camel; a Review on the Aspects of History, Physical Description, Adaptations, Behavior/Lifecycle, Diet, Reproduction, Uses, Genetics and Diseases. Niger. Vet. J. 2015;36:1299–1317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuadrado P.S., Young H., Vance A. Camel Racing: The Multi-Million Dollar Industry Mixing Modernity and Tradition.  [(accessed on 13 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://edition.cnn.com/2017/03/14/sport/camel-racing-robots-uae-thoroughbred-hussain-al-marzooqi/index.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations)  International Year of Camelids (IYC) 2024|Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (Fao.Org)  [(accessed on 13 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.fao.org/camelids-2024/en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kutty C.I., Yousuf A.M. Management Practices and Production Performance of Camels under Organized Farming in Abu Dhabi Emirate, United Arab Emirates. Indian J. Anim. Sci. 2017;87:1269–1273. doi: 10.56093/ijans.v87i10.75301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.56093/ijans.v87i10.75301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faye B. The Production Potential and the Importance of Camel and Camelids in the World; Proceedings of the WBC/ICAR 2008 Satellite Meeting on Camelid Reproduction; Budapest, Hungary. 12–13 July 2008; pp. 1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadim I.T., Mahgoub O., Purchas R.W. A Review of the Growth, and of the Carcass and Meat Quality Characteristics of the One-Humped Camel (Camelus dromedaries) Meat Sci. 2008;80:555–569. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2008.02.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2008.02.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22063567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baba W.N., Rasool N., Selvamuthukumara M., Maqsood S. A Review on Nutritional Composition, Health Benefits, and Technological Interventions for Improving Consumer Acceptability of Camel Meat: An Ethnic Food of Middle East. J. Ethn. Foods. 2021;8:18. doi: 10.1186/s42779-021-00089-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s42779-021-00089-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadim I.T., Al-Ani M.R., Al-Maqbaly R.S., Mansour M.H., Mahgoub O., Johnson E.H. Proximate, Amino Acid, Fatty Acid and Mineral Composition of Raw and Cooked Camel (Camelus dromedarius) Meat. Br. Food J. 2011;113:482–493. doi: 10.1108/00070701111123961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/00070701111123961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raiymbek G., Kadim I., Konuspayeva G., Mahgoub O., Serikbayeva A., Faye B. Discriminant Amino-Acid Components of Bactrian (Camelus bactrianus) and Dromedary (Camelus dromedarius) Meat. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2015;41:194–200. doi: 10.1016/j.jfca.2015.02.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2015.02.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed H.H.H., Jin G., Ma M., Khalifa I., Shukat R., Elkhedir A.E., Zeng Q., Noman A.E. Comparative Characterization of Proximate Nutritional Compositions, Microbial Quality and Safety of Camel Meat in Relation to Mutton, Beef, and Chicken. LWT. 2020;118:108714. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2019.108714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2019.108714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghazali M.H., Bakhsh M., Zainab U., Faraz A., Munir M.U., Channo A., Ahmad M., Rashid S. Camel Meat Production, Consumption and Nutritive Value: Present Status and Future Prospects. Int. J. Camel Sci. 2023;5:123–136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadim I.T., Mahgoub O., Mbaga M. Potential of Camel Meat as a Non-Traditional High Quality Source of Protein for Human Consumption. Anim. Front. 2014;4:13–17. doi: 10.2527/af.2014-0028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2527/af.2014-0028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabahat S., Nadeem A., Maryam J. Genetic and Genomic Prospects for Camel Meat Production. J. Anim. Plant Sci. 2020;31:635–649. doi: 10.36899/JAPS.2021.3.0253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36899/JAPS.2021.3.0253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yam B.A.Z., Khomeiri M., Akbarzadeh A., Heidari Z., Bashghareh H., Haghighi N. Effect of Levels of Camel Meat on Physiochemichal and Sensory Properties of Hamburger. Basic Res. J. Microbiol. 2015;2:55–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salah H., Abdu K., Elasraag Y. The Potential Contribution of Camel Meat Production to Achieve Food Security from Animal Protein in Egypt. Menoufia J. Agric. Econ. Soc. Sci. 2023;8:119–135. doi: 10.21608/mjabes.2023.232814.1046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21608/mjabes.2023.232814.1046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suliman G.M. Camel Meat as a Future Promising Protein Source. Anim. Front. 2023;13:53–55. doi: 10.1093/af/vfad065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/af/vfad065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djenane D., Aider M. The One-Humped Camel: The Animal of Future, Potential Alternative Red Meat, Technological Suitability and Future Perspectives. F1000Res. 2024;11:1085. doi: 10.12688/f1000research.125246.3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12688/f1000research.125246.3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11128057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38798303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corrò M., Saleh-Mohamed-Lamin S., Jatri-Hamdi S., Slut-Ahmed B., Mohamed-Lejlifa S., Di Lello S., Rossi D., Broglia A., Vivas-Alegre L. A Preliminary Microbiological Assessment of Process Hygiene of Traditional Outdoor Camel Slaughter in Sahrawi Refugee Camps. J. Food Prot. 2012;75:1859–1861. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-12-132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-12-132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23043838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassen K.A., Omer S.A., Hassen N.A. Assessment of Hygienic Practice on Camel Meat Handlers, and Identification of Bacterial Contamination in Abattoir and Butcheries of Nagelle Town, Southern Oromia, Ethiopia. Int. Res. J. Sci. Technol. 2021;2:384–397. doi: 10.46378/irjst.2021.020204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.46378/irjst.2021.020204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benyagoub E., Lali M.A., Lamari N. Quality of Fresh Camel Meat (Camelus dromedarius) Sold at Retail Houses in Bechar City (Southwest of Algeria): Physicochemical and Hygienic Approaches. Asian J. Dairy Food Res. 2022;41:264–271. doi: 10.18805/ajdfr.DRF-262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18805/ajdfr.DRF-262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morshdy A.E.M.A., Mehrez S.M.I., Tharwat A.E., Abdallah K.M.E., Darwish W.S., Nabawy E.E., Ali E.-S.M. Hygienic Status of the Carcass Surfaces of Cattle, Buffalo, Sheep, and Camel Carcasses and Their Contact Surfaces. J. Adv. Vet. Res. 2023;13:1294–1298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chigbu U.E., Atiku S.O., Du Plessis C.C. The Science of Literature Reviews: Searching, Identifying, Selecting, and Synthesising. Publications. 2023;11:2. doi: 10.3390/publications11010002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/publications11010002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page M.J., McKenzie J.E., Bossuyt P.M., Boutron I., Hoffmann T.C., Mulrow C.D., Shamseer L., Tetzlaff J.M., Akl E.A., Brennan S.E., et al. The PRISMA 2020 Statement: An Updated Guideline for Reporting Systematic Reviews. BMJ. 2021;372:n71. doi: 10.1136/bmj.n71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) WHO Estimates of the Global Burden of Foodborne Diseases: Foodborne Disease Bur-Epidemiology Reference Group 2007–2015. World Health Organization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman K., Orabi A., Elbehiry A., Hanafy M.H., Ali A.M. Pseudomonas Species Isolated from Camel Meat: Quorum Sensing-Dependent Virulence, Biofilm Formation and Antibiotic Resistance. Future Microbiol. 2019;14:609–622. doi: 10.2217/fmb-2018-0293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2217/fmb-2018-0293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30995873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Amery K., Elhariri M., Elsayed A., El-Moghazy G., Elhelw R., El-Mahallawy H., El Hariri M., Hamza D. Vancomycin-Resistant Staphylococcus aureus Isolated from Camel Meat and Slaughterhouse Workers in Egypt. Antimicrob. Resist. Infect. Control. 2019;8:129. doi: 10.1186/s13756-019-0585-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13756-019-0585-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6683426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31404199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sallam K.I., Abd-Elrazik Y., Raslan M.T., Imre K., Morar A., Herman V., Zaher H.A. Cefotaxime-, Ciprofloxacin-, and Extensively Drug-Resistant Escherichia coli O157:H7 and O55:H7 in Camel Meat. Foods. 2023;12:1443. doi: 10.3390/foods12071443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12071443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10094314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37048264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed H.A., Elsohaby I., Elamin A.M., El-Ghafar A.E.A., Elsaid G.A., Elbarbary M., Mohsen R.A., El Feky T.M., El Bayomi R.M. Extended-Spectrum β-Lactamase-Producing E. coli from Retail Meat and Workers: Genetic Diversity, Virulotyping, Pathotyping and the Antimicrobial Effect of Silver Nanoparticles. BMC Microbiol. 2023;23:212. doi: 10.1186/s12866-023-02948-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12866-023-02948-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10405496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37550643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkhalaf A.A., El-Ghareeb W.R., Abdel Raheem S.M., Seliem M.M., Shosha A.M., Elzawahry R.R. A Study on the Prevalence of Multidrug Resistant Food Poisoning Salmonella spp. in Camel Meat and Offal with a Reduction Trial Using Organic Acids. J. Adv. Vet. Res. 2024;14:526–530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Askari N., Momtaz H., Tajbakhsh E. Acinetobacter Baumannii in Sheep, Goat, and Camel Raw Meat: Virulence and Antibiotic Resistance Pattern. AIMS Microbiol. 2019;5:272–284. doi: 10.3934/microbiol.2019.3.272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3934/microbiol.2019.3.272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6787353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31663061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baghbaderani Z.T., Shakerian A., Rahimi E. Phenotypic and Genotypic Assessment of Antibiotic Resistance of Staphylococcus aureus Bacteria Isolated from Retail Meat. Infect. Drug Resist. 2020;13:1339–1349. doi: 10.2147/IDR.S241189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S241189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7213866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32440171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azwai S., Alfallani E., Abolghait S., Garbaj A., Naas H., Moawad A., Gammoudi F., Rayes H., Barbieri I., Eldaghayes I. Isolation and Molecular Identification of Vibrio spp. by Sequencing of 16S RDNA from Seafood, Meat and Meat Products in Libya. Open Vet. J. 2016;6:36. doi: 10.4314/ovj.v6i1.6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4314/ovj.v6i1.6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4791562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27004169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salman M.B., Zin Eldin A.I.A., Ata N.S., Abd Elfatah E.B., Eissa N. Prevalence, Antimicrobial Resistance and Risk Factors of Zoonotic Foodborne Pathogens Isolated from Camel Meat. J. Curr. Vet. Res. 2024;6:272–284. doi: 10.21608/jcvr.2024.352718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21608/jcvr.2024.352718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elkady S., Darwish W., Tharwat A., Said M., ElAtriby D., Seliem M., Alfifi A., Ghareeb W., Gad T. Prevalence and Antibiogram of Shigatoxin-Producing E. coli in Camel Meat and Offal. Open Vet. J. 2024;14:571. doi: 10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i1.52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i1.52</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11018423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38633183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosilevac J.M., Gassem M.A., Al Sheddy I.A., Almaiman S.A., Al-Mohizea I.S., Alowaimer A., Koohmaraie M. Prevalence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella in Camels, Cattle, Goats, and Sheep Harvested for Meat in Riyadh. J. Food Prot. 2015;78:89–96. doi: 10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-14-176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-14-176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25581182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raji M.A., Garaween G., Ehricht R., Monecke S., Shibl A.M., Senok A. Genetic Characterization of Staphylococcus aureus Isolated from Retail Meat in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. Front. Microbiol. 2016;7:911. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2016.00911.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4899468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27375611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yehia H.M., Elkhadragy M.F., Aljahani A.H., Alarjani K.M. Prevalence and Antibiotic Resistance of Listeria monocytogenes in Camel Meat. Biosci. Rep. 2020;40:BSR20201062. doi: 10.1042/BSR20201062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/BSR20201062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7281775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32432315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Ghareeb W.R., Abdel-Raheem S.M., Al-Marri T.M., Alaql F.A., Fayez M.M. Isolation and Identification of Extended Spectrum β-Lactamases (ESBLs) Escherichia coli from Minced Camel Meat in Eastern Province, Saudi Arabia. Thai J. Vet. Med. 2020;50:155–161. doi: 10.56808/2985-1130.3013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.56808/2985-1130.3013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fayez M., El-Ghareeb W.R., Elmoslemany A., Alsunaini S.J., Alkafafy M., Alzahrani O.M., Mahmoud S.F., Elsohaby I. Genotyping and Antimicrobial Susceptibility of Clostridium perfringens and Clostridioides difficile in Camel Minced Meat. Pathogens. 2021;10:1640. doi: 10.3390/pathogens10121640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens10121640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8708398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34959595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Husain F.M., Perveen K., Qais F.A., Ahmad I., Alfarhan A.H., El-Sheikh M.A. Naringin Inhibits the Biofilms of Metallo-β-Lactamases (MβLs) Producing Pseudomonas Species Isolated from Camel Meat. Saudi J. Biol. Sci. 2021;28:333–341. doi: 10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.10.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.10.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7785451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33424314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Asmari F., Hamad S.H., Al Hashedi S.A. Prevalence of Enterobacteriaceae in Camel, Cattle, and Sheep Carcasses at Slaughterhouses and Butcher Shops. Appl. Sci. 2023;13:11495. doi: 10.3390/app132011495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app132011495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hembrom S., Singh B., Gupta S.K., Nema A.K. Contemporary Environmental Issues and Challenges in Era of Climate Change. Springer; Singapore: 2020. A Comprehensive Evaluation of Heavy Metal Contamination in Foodstuff and Associated Human Health Risk: A Global Perspective; pp. 33–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bala A., Junaidu A.U., Salihu M.D., Agaie B.M., Saulawa M.A., Musawa A.I., Ahmad K.H. Determination of Heavy Metal Residues in Slaughtered Camels at Sokoto and Gusau Modern Abattoirs, Nigeria. J. Health Pollut. 2018;8:181204. doi: 10.5696/2156-9614-8.20.181204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5696/2156-9614-8.20.181204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6285680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30560003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdou A., Mohamed F. Estimation of Some Heavy Metals Residues in Blood Serum and Tissues of Camels. Assiut Vet. Med. J. 2015;61:221–229. doi: 10.21608/avmj.2015.170204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21608/avmj.2015.170204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morshdy A.E.M., Darwish W.S., El-Ghareeb W.R., Gouda R. Antibiotic and Heavy Metal Residues in Camel Meat; Proceedings of the 7th International Toxicology Symposium in Africa; Johannesburg, South Africa. 31 August 2015; pp. 38–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Ghareeb W.R., Mulla Z.S., Meligy A.M.A., Darwish W.S., Edris A.M. Antibiotic Residue Levels in Camel, Cattle and Sheep Tissues Using LC-MS/MS Method. J. Anim. Plant Sci. 2019;29:943–952.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asli M., Azizzadeh M., Moghaddamjafari A., Mohsenzadeh M. Copper, Iron, Manganese, Zinc, Cobalt, Arsenic, Cadmium, Chrome, and Lead Concentrations in Liver and Muscle in Iranian Camel (Camelus dromedarius) Biol. Trace Elem. Res. 2020;194:390–400. doi: 10.1007/s12011-019-01788-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12011-019-01788-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31256389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-perkhdri A.S.A. Study of the Some Heavy Metals Residues in the Camel Meat in Different Regions of Kirkuk Governorate during the Spring and Summer Seasons. IOP Conf. Ser. Earth Environ. Sci. 2021;735:012080. doi: 10.1088/1755-1315/735/1/012080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1755-1315/735/1/012080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jehad A.-H., Moawiya H., Mazen A., Sati A.-D., Khaled A.-H. Banned Organochlorine Pesticides Residues in Camel Milk, Meat, and Liver: A Case Study from Jordan. Jordan. J. Eng. Chem. Ind. 2021;4:31–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elasough J., Elgerwi A., Eldaghayes I., El-Mahmoudy A. Residual Evaluation of Oxytetracycline in Camel Edible Tissues in Tripoli Region, Libya. Curr. Res. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 2015;3:718–724.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelbasset C., Rabia E., Abdallah B., Boubker N., AbdelKhalid E. Distribution of Trace Elements and Heavy Metals in Liver, Lung, Meat, Heart and Kidney of Cattle, Sheep, Camel and Equine Slaughtered in Casablanca City-Morocco. Int. J. Sci. Eng. Res. 2014;5:294–303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman K.A. Human Health Risk of Dietary Intake of Some Organochlorine Pesticide Residues in Camels Slaughtered in the Districts of Al-Qassim Region, Saudi Arabia. J. AOAC Int. 2015;98:1199–1206. doi: 10.5740/jaoacint.SGE5-Osman.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5740/jaoacint.SGE5-Osman</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26525237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed H., Haris P., Brima E. Estimated Dietary Intakes of Toxic Elements from Four Staple Foods in Najran City, Saudi Arabia. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2017;14:1575. doi: 10.3390/ijerph14121575.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph14121575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5750993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29240693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Ghareeb W.R., Darwish W.S., Meligy A.M.A. Metal Contents in the Edible Tissues of Camel and Sheep: Human Dietary Intake and Risk Assessment in Saudi Arabia. Jpn. J. Vet. Res. 2019;67:5–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussein Y.A., Meligy A.M.A., El-Ghareeb W.R., Al-Shokair S.S., Abdel-Raheem S.M. Selected Heavy Metals and Their Risk Assessment in Camels (Camelus dromedarius) J. Camel Pract. Res. 2022;29:89–99. doi: 10.5958/2277-8934.2022.00013.3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5958/2277-8934.2022.00013.3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelrahman M.M., Alhidary I.A., Matar A.M., Alobre M.M., Ayadi M., Aljumaah R.S. Heavy Metals Levels in Soil, Water and Feed and Relation to Slaughtered Camels’ Tissues (Camelus dromedarius) from Five Districts in Saudi Arabia during Spring. Life. 2023;13:732. doi: 10.3390/life13030732.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/life13030732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10054927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36983887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meligy A., Ghareeb W., Raheem S., Ismail H., Darwish W., Kandeel M., Alfifi A., Shokair S., Hussein M. Assessment of Some Toxic Elements (Co, Cr, Mn, Se, and As) in Muscle, Offal, Hair and Blood of Camels (Camelus dromedaries) and Their Risk Assessment. Open Vet. J. 2024;14:154. doi: 10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i1.14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i1.14</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11018421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38633180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalafalla A.I. Zoonotic Diseases Transmitted from the Camels. Front. Vet. Sci. 2023;10:1244833. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2023.1244833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1244833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10620500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37929289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V. Emerging Human Coronavirus Infections (SARS, MERS, and COVID-19): Where They Are Leading Us. Int. Rev. Immunol. 2021;40:5–53. doi: 10.1080/08830185.2020.1800688.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08830185.2020.1800688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32744465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aklilu M.A., WeldeMariam D.T., Shanta S.A., Islam M.S., Akter A. Review on the Epidemiology and Public Health Importance of Camel Tuberculosis. Int. J. Agric. Vet. Sci. 2022;5:116–129. doi: 10.34104/ijavs.022.01160129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.34104/ijavs.022.01160129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib I., Mohamed M.Y.I. Food Safety in the Middle East. Elsevier; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Foodborne Infections in the Middle East; pp. 71–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed M.-Y.I., Habib I., Khalifa H.O. Salmonella in the Food Chain within the Gulf Cooperation Council Countries. AIMS Microbiol. 2024;10:468–488. doi: 10.3934/microbiol.2024023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3934/microbiol.2024023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adel M. Brucella Transmission from Domestic and Wild Animals to Dromedary Camel: Diagnostic Methods and Zoonotic Threats—A Review. Open Vet. Sci. 2022;3:1–12. doi: 10.1515/ovs-2022-0113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/ovs-2022-0113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations  FAOUN MERS-CoV Situation Update.  [(accessed on 18 May 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.fao.org/animal-health/situation-updates/mers-coronavirus.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aly M., Elrobh M., Alzayer M., Aljuhani S., Balkhy H. Occurrence of the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV) across the Gulf Corporation Council Countries: Four Years Update. PLoS ONE. 2017;12:e0183850. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0183850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5640221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29028812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sobhy H.M., Barghash S.M., Behour T.S., Razin E.A. Seasonal Fluctuation of Trypanosomiasis in Camels in North-West Egypt and Effect of Age, Sex, Location, Health Status and Vector Abundance on the Prevalence. Beni Suef Univ. J. Basic Appl. Sci. 2017;6:64–68. doi: 10.1016/j.bjbas.2017.01.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bjbas.2017.01.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcell H.G., Garcia E.G., Pueyo P.V., Martín I.R., Arias A.V., Alfonso Serrano R.N. Outbreaks of Brucellosis Related to the Consumption of Unpasteurized Camel Milk. J. Infect. Public Health. 2016;9:523–527. doi: 10.1016/j.jiph.2015.12.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2015.12.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26796768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ECDPC . Geographical Distribution of Cases of MERS-CoV in Saudi Arabia. ECDPC; Solna, Sweden: 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newey S. Mers Outbreak in Saudi Arabia Puts Health Experts on High Alert.  [(accessed on 13 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.telegraph.co.uk/global-health/science-and-disease/mers-outbreak-saudi-arabia-middle-east-respiratory-syndrome/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO  Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus—Saudi Arabia.  [(accessed on 13 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/middle-east-respiratory-syndrome-coronavirus-(mers-cov)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aleanizy F.S., Mohmed N., Alqahtani F.Y., El Hadi Mohamed R.A. Outbreak of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus in Saudi Arabia: A Retrospective Study. BMC Infect. Dis. 2017;17:23. doi: 10.1186/s12879-016-2137-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-016-2137-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5217314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28056850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee G.-H., Tan B.-H., Chi-Yuan Teo E., Lim S.-G., Dan Y.-Y., Wee A., Kim Aw P.P., Zhu Y., Hibberd M.L., Tan C.-K., et al. Chronic Infection with Camelid Hepatitis e Virus in a Liver Transplant Recipient Who Regularly Consumes Camel Meat and Milk. Gastroenterology. 2016;150:355–357.e3. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2015.10.048.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2015.10.048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26551551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>