<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39193559</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2296-861X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Food security intervention mechanisms in the drought-prone rural areas of Tigray.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1413017</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1413017</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1413017</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fnut.2024.1413017</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Tigray is one of the food-insecure regions with many people living under the condition of chronic hunger. Proper intervention mechanisms are vital for addressing food insecurity. Yet, food security intervention mechanisms of various levels are not researched well. Besides, previous studies have rarely addressed the objectives of food security intervention mechanisms in relation to the four pillars of food security: availability, access, utilization, and stability. Thus, this study aims to investigate the food security intervention mechanisms in the drought-prone rural areas of Tigray in relation with the major components of food security.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODOLOGY" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study has employed a cross-sectional study design based on a mixed research approach with primary and secondary data. For this, 363 households from three selected drought-prone rural districts, i.e., Atsbi-wenberta, Irob, and Hintalo- wejerat were studied. Primary data were collected using questionnaires and key-informant interviews. And, secondary data were collected from relevant archives and policy documents. The obtained data were analyzed descriptively and content-wise.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Findings show that there were several international interventions intended to halt food insecurity sustainably through financial aid, but many of the interventions were found to be responding to humanitarian crises mainly the food shortages. Ethiopia's Food and Nutrition Policy, Food Security Program, Food Security Strategy, and Food Security Pack program were the food security intervention mechanisms at the national level. These interventions were found to be inconsistent with each other in their intended goals. Regionally, no food security strategy or program was found intervening to the prevailing food insecurity in Tigray. More notably, the region has no food security bureau or office that deals with food security issues of the region. At a community level, food aid, and PSNP transfers have been the usual food security intervention mechanisms. 35.6% (77,010) of the population in the study rural districts were found to be rural PSNP beneficiaries. The food aid and PSNP transfers were outrageously insufficient for the recipients to cope with food insecurity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Intervention mechanisms should focus on enhancing vulnerable households' coping and adaptive capacities to deal with food security problems. In this regard, all the food security intervention mechanisms of various levels should be integrated into the common goal of achieving food security.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Gebre, Abraha, Zenebe and Zeweld.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gebre</LastName><ForeName>Tewelde</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Environment, Gender and Development Studies, Mekelle University, Mekelle, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abraha</LastName><ForeName>Zenebe</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Environment, Gender and Development Studies, Mekelle University, Mekelle, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zenebe</LastName><ForeName>Amanuel</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Environment, Gender and Development Studies, Mekelle University, Mekelle, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeweld</LastName><ForeName>Woldegebrial</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Environment, Gender and Development Studies, Mekelle University, Mekelle, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101642264</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-861X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Safety Net</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">drought</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food aid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food policy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">humanitarian assistance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">interventions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rural</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39193559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11347324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2024.1413017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>FAO . Rome Declaration on World Food Security and World Food Summit Plan of Action. World Food Summit 13–17 November 1996. Rome (1996).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jha R. Introduction: Hunger and Malnutrition as Major Challenges in the 21st Century (2019). p. 3–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO . FAOSTAT: Suite of Food Security Indicators. Rome: Food and Agricultural Organization of the United Nations; (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UN . The Sustainable Development Goals Report. New York, NY: United Nations; (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UN . UN food agency ramps up deliveries amid worsening food security in Ethiopia. UN News (2024). Available online at: https://news.un.org/en/story/2024/02/1146252</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebre T, Abraha Z, Zenebe A, Zeweld W. A comprehensive analysis of food insecurity in the drought–prone rural areas of Tigray. J Health Popul Nutr. (2024) 43:66. 10.1186/s41043-024-00564-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s41043-024-00564-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11097430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38755735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oxfam . Oxfam warns of growing hunger crisis in Tigray and Amhara regions as families resort to extreme measures to survive. Press releases (2024). Available online at: https://www.oxfam.org/en/press-releases/oxfam-warns-growing-hunger-crisis-tigray-and-amhara-regions-families-resort-extreme (accessed February 24, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahru BA, Jebena MG, Birner R, Zeller M. Impact of Ethiopia's productive safety net program on household food security and child nutrition: a marginal structural modeling approach. SSM Popul Health. (2020) 12:100660. 10.1016/j.ssmph.2020.100660</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ssmph.2020.100660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7511729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33005722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahut DB, Aryal JP, Manchanda N, Sonobe T. Chapter 6: Expectations for household food security in the coming decades: a global scenario. In: Bhat R, editor. Future Foods (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bizikova L, Jungcurt S, McDougal K, Tyler S. How can agricultural interventions enhance contribution to food security and SDG 2.1? Global Food Secur. (2020) 26:100450. 10.1016/j.gfs.2020.100450</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gfs.2020.100450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doustmohammadian A, Mohammadi-Nasrabadi F, Keshavarz-Mohammadi N, Hajjar M, Alibeyk S, Hajigholam-Saryazdi M. Community-based participatory interventions to improve food security: a systematic review. Front Nutr. (2022) 9:1028394. 10.3389/fnut.2022.1028394</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.1028394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9807164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36601081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coll-Black S, Gilligan DO, Hoddinott J, Kumar N, Taffesse AS, Wiseman W. Targeting food security interventions: the case of Ethiopia's productive safety net programme. ESSP Res Note. (2013) 26:1–2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wordofa MG, Sassi M. Impact of agricultural interventions on food and nutrition security in Ethiopia: uncovering pathways linking agriculture to improved nutrition. Cogent Food Agric. (2020) 6:1724386. 10.1080/23311932.2020.1724386</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/23311932.2020.1724386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordonnier V, Covarrubias KA, De la O Campos AP. Agricultural interventions and food security in Ethiopia-What is the role of adjusting livelihood strategies? In: FAO Agricultural Development Economics Working Paper, No. 22-23 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van der Veen A, Gebrehiwot T. Effect of policy interventions on food security in Tigray, Northern Ethiopia. Ecol Soc. (2011) 16:160118. 10.5751/ES-03895-160118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5751/ES-03895-160118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleth RM, Dinar A. The impact of multiple policy interventions on food security. J Policy Model. (2009) 31:923–38. 10.1016/j.jpolmod.2009.08.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpolmod.2009.08.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nisbet C, Lestrat KE, Vatanparast H. Food security interventions among refugees around the globe: a scoping review. Nutrients. (2022) 14:522. 10.3390/nu14030522</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14030522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8839314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35276878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weis T. Food security and food sovereignty. In: International Encyclopedia of Human Geography. Elsevier: (2020). p. 191–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebre T, Abraha Z, Zenebe A, Zeweld W. Precipitation variability and its teleconnection with the global SST and ENSO indices in the food-insecure rural areas of Tigray. Theoret Appl Climatol. (2024) 155:1699–711. 10.1007/s00704-023-04717-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00704-023-04717-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furtado X, Smith J. Ethiopia: Aid, Ownership, and Sovereignty (No. 2007/28). GEG Working Paper. The Global Economic Governance Program University College, Oxford (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Economy. Foreign Aid - Country Rankings. (2023). Available at: https://www.theglobaleconomy.com/rankings/foreign_aid/ (accessed February 12, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemi A. Anatomy of Foreign Aid to Ethiopia: 1960-2003. Economics Faculty Publication Series. 13. Boston (2007). Available online at: https://scholarworks.umb.edu/econ_faculty_pubs/13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WFP . 2012 Food Aid Flows: International Food Aid Information System. (2013). Available at: https://www.calpnetwork.org/publication/food-aid-flows-2012-report/ (accessed March 23, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OCHA . Ethiopia. Situation Report. (2024). Available at: https://reports.unocha.org/en/country/ethiopia/ (accessed February 14, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WFP . Northern Ethiopia Emergency Response Situation Report. (2022). Available at: https://reliefweb.int/report/ethiopia/northern-ethiopia-emergency-response-situation-report-07 (accessed February 12, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank . Implementation Completion and Results Report on A Grant to The Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia for The Ethiopia Rural Productive Safety Net Project. Social Protection and Jobs Global Practice, Eastern and Southern Africa Region. Report No: ICR00006154 (2023). Available online at: https://documents1.worldbank.org/curated/en/099120423100031042/pdf/BOSIB05f9c7f7f0730a6bd0a0071798cc86.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USAID . U.S. and Ethiopia Launch New $2.2 Billion Phase of the Productive Safety Net Program. (2023). Available at: https://www.usaid.gov/ethiopia/press-release/us-and-ethiopia-launch-new-22-billion-phase-productive-safety-net-program (accessed February 13, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GAFSP . Agricultural Growth Program (AGP – I). (2022). Available at: https://www.gafspfund.org/projects/agricultural-growth-program-agp-i (accessed February 14, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IED . Agricultural Growth Program Implementation Completion Report. Independent Evaluation Group. Report Number: ICRR0021055 (2019). Available online at: https://www.gafspfund.org/sites/default/files/inline-files/Ethiopia-ET-Agricultural-Growth-Program.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO . FAO in Ethiopia: Programs and Projects. (2024). Available at: https://www.fao.org/ethiopia/programmes-and-projects/fr/ (accessed February 13, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO . Investing 1 Dollar Per Person Per Year Could Save 7 Million Lives in Low- and Lower-Middle-Income Countries. (2021). Available at: https://www.who.int/news/item/13-12-2021-investing-1-dollar-per-person-per-year-could-save-7-million-lives-in-low-and-lower-middle-income-countries (accessed February 14, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute of Building Sciences . Mitigation Saves: Federal Grants Provide a $6 Benefit for Each $1 Invested. (2019). Available at: https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjnkrq7sqqEAxUyU6QEHVYSCpMQFnoECBcQAQ&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nibs.org%2Ffiles%2Fpdfs%2Fms_v3_federalgrants.pdf&amp;usg=AOvVaw3zHUCXZHjZbzEuPieuF6HY&amp;opi=89978449 (accessed March 11, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDRE . Food and Nutrition Policy of Ethiopia. Addis Ababa: Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia; (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development . Food Security Program of Ethiopia (2010-2014). Addis Ababa: (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Agriculture . PSNP: General Program Implementation Manual. Addis Ababa: Ministry of Agriculture; (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahru BA, Zeller M. Gauging the impact of Ethiopia's productive safety net programme on agriculture: application of targeted maximum likelihood estimation approach. J Agric Econ. (2022) 73:257–76. 10.1111/1477-9552.12452</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1477-9552.12452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MoUH . Urban Productive Safety Net Program implementation manual. Addis Ababa: Ministry of Urban Development and Housing; (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neglo KAW, Gebrekidan T, Lyu K. The role of agriculture and non-farm economy in addressing food insecurity in Ethiopia: a Review. Sustainability. (2021) 13:3874. 10.3390/su13073874</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su13073874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDRE . Food Security Strategy. Addis Ababa: Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia; (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MCDSS . Food Security Pack (FSP) Program. Addis Ababa: Ministry of Community Development and Social Services; (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munro RN, Woldegerima T, Hailu B, Zenebe A, Gebremedhin Z, Hailemichael A, et al. . A History of Soil and Water Conservation in Tigray. Geo-trekking in Ethiopia's Tropical Mountains: The Dogu'a Tembien District. Cham: Springer Nature; (2019). p. 477–93. 10.1007/978-3-030-04955-3_32</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-04955-3_32</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hishe S, Lyimo J, Bewket W. Effects of soil and water conservation on vegetation cover: a remote sensing based study in the Middle Suluh River Basin, northern Ethiopia. Environ Syst Res. (2017) 6:1–16. 10.1186/s40068-017-0103-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40068-017-0103-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haftom H, Haftu A, Goitom K, Meseret H. Agroclimatic zonation of Tigray region of Ethiopia based on aridity index and traditional agro-climatic zones. J Agrometeorol. (2019) 21:176–81. 10.54386/jam.v21i2.229</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.54386/jam.v21i2.229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabates-Wheeler R, Hirvonen K, Lind J, Hoddinott J. Expanding social protection coverage with humanitarian aid: lessons on targeting and transfer values from Ethiopia. J Dev Stud. (2022) 58:1981–2000. 10.1080/00220388.2022.2096443</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00220388.2022.2096443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoddard A, Harvey P, Czwarno M, Breckenridge MJ. Humanitarian Access SCORE Report: Tigray, Ethiopia. Survey on the Coverage, Operational Reach, and Effectiveness of Humanitarian Aid. Humanitarian Outcomes (2021). Available online at: https://humanitarianoutcomes.org/sites/default/files/publications/score_tigray_report_2021_v2.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durao S, Visser ME, Ramokolo V, Oliveira JM, Schmidt BM, Balakrishna Y, et al. . Community-level interventions for improving access to food in low-and middle-income countries. Cochra Database Syst Rev. (2020) 7:CD011504. 10.1002/14651858.CD011504.pub2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD011504.pub2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7390433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32722849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demsash AW, Emanu MD, Walle AD. Exploring spatial patterns, and identifying factors associated with insufficient cash or food received from a productive safety net program among eligible households in Ethiopia: a spatial and multilevel analysis as an input for international food aid programmers. BMC Public Health. (2023) 23:1141. 10.1186/s12889-023-16001-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-16001-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10265788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37312083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desalegn G, Ali SN. Review of the Impact of Productive Safety Net Program (PSNP) on Rural Welfare in Ethiopia. ZEF Working Paper Series 173, Center for Development Research, University of Bonn (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirvonen K, Hoddinott J. Beneficiary views on cash and in-kind payments: evidence from Ethiopia's Productive Safety Net Programme. World Bank Econ Rev. (2021) 35:398–413. 10.1093/wber/lhaa002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/wber/lhaa002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knippenberg E, Hoddinott J. Shocks, Social Protection, and Resilience: Evidence From Ethiopia, Strategy Support Program Working Paper 109, IFPRI/EDRI. Addis Ababa (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tadesse T, Gebremedhin Zeleke T. The impact of the productive safety net program (PSNP) on food security and asset accumulation of rural households': evidence from Gedeo zone, Southern Ethiopia. Cogent Econ Finan. (2022) 10:2087285. 10.1080/23322039.2022.2087285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/23322039.2022.2087285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haji MA, Mumed AA. Impact of productive safety net program on rural household food security in somali regional state: a case of Kebri Dehar District, Ethiopia. J Environ Issues Clim Change. (2023) 2:78–90. 10.59110/jeicc.v2i1.90</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.59110/jeicc.v2i1.90</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mustafa NM, Asfaw FF, Endris EA, Bojago E. Evaluating the impact of productive safety net program on rural household food security achievement: endogenous switching regression model. J Agric Food Res. (2023) 14:100674. 10.1016/j.jafr.2023.100674</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jafr.2023.100674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>