<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39193898</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1095-8649</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of fish biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Fish Biol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Predicting population-level impacts of projected climate heating on a temperate freshwater fish.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jfb.15889</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Climate heating has the potential to drive changes in ecosystems at multiple levels of biological organization. Temperature directly affects the inherent physiology of plants and animals, resulting in changes in rates of photosynthesis and respiration, and trophic interactions. Predicting temperature-dependent changes in physiological and trophic processes, however, is challenging because environmental conditions and ecosystem structure vary across biogeographical regions of the globe. To realistically predict the effects of projected climate heating on wildlife populations, mechanistic tools are required to incorporate the inherent physiological effects of temperature changes, as well as the associated effects on food availability within and across comparable ecosystems. Here we applied an agent-based bioenergetics model to explore the combined effects of projected temperature increases for 2100 (1.4, 2.7, and 4.4°C), and associated changes in prey availability, on three-spined stickleback (Gasterosteus aculeatus) populations representing latitudes 50, 55, and 60°N. Our results showed a decline in population density after a simulated 1.4°C temperature increase at 50°N. In all other modeled scenarios there was an increase (inflation) in population density and biomass (per unit area) with climate heating, and this inflation increased with increasing latitude. We conclude that agent-based bioenergetics models are valuable tools in discerning the impacts of climate change on wild fish populations, which play important roles in aquatic food webs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Fish Biology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Fisheries Society of the British Isles.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mintram</LastName><ForeName>Kate S</ForeName><Initials>KS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7180-9200</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, College of Engineering, Design and Physical Sciences, Brunel University London, Uxbridge, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brown</LastName><ForeName>A Ross</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biosciences, Faculty of Health and Life Sciences, University of Exeter, Exeter, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maynard</LastName><ForeName>Samuel K</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Safety, Health and Environment Astrazeneca, Cambridge, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thorbek</LastName><ForeName>Pernille</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural Solutions - Ecotoxicology, BASF SE, APD/EE, Limburgerhof, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tyler</LastName><ForeName>Charles R</ForeName><Initials>CR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biosciences, Faculty of Health and Life Sciences, University of Exeter, Exeter, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Fish Biol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0214055</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1112</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">IPCC</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">agent‐based modeling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bioenergetics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metabolic theory</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">three‐spined stickleback</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">trophic interactions</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39193898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfb.15889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Angiulli, E., Pagliara, V., Cioni, C., Frabetti, F., Pizzetti, F., Alleva, E., &amp; Toni, M. (2020). Increase in environmental temperature affects exploratory behaviour, anxiety and social preference in Danio rerio. Scientific Reports, 10(1), 1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BalticSea2020. (2014). Fishing for stickleback can reverse the negative trend in the Baltic Sea. [online]. Available at: http://www.balticsea2020.org/english/press‐room/360‐fishing‐for‐stickleback‐can‐reverse‐the‐negative‐trend‐in‐the‐baltic‐sea</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbarossa, V., Bosmans, J., Wanders, N., King, H., Bierkens, M. F., Huijbregts, M. A., &amp; Schipper, A. M. (2021). Threats of global warming to the world's freshwater fishes. Nature Communications, 12(1), 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergström, U., Olsson, J., Casini, M., Eriksson, B. K., Fredriksson, R., Wennhage, H., &amp; Appelberg, M. (2015). Stickleback increase in the Baltic Sea–a thorny issue for coastal predatory fish. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 163, 134–142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biro, P. A., Beckmann, C., &amp; Stamps, J. A. (2010). Small within‐day increases in temperature affects boldness and alters personality in coral reef fish. Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 277(1678), 71–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botsch, J. C., Book, K. R., Phillips, J. S., &amp; Ives, A. R. (2023). Aquatic insects balance growth with future supply of algal food resources. Oikos, e09902. https://doi.org/10.1111/oik.09902</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bretzel, J. B., Geist, J., Gugele, S. M., Baer, J., &amp; Brinker, A. (2021). Feeding ecology of invasive three‐Spined stickleback (Gasterosteus aculeatus) in relation to native juvenile Eurasian perch (Perca fluviatilis) in the pelagic zone of upper Lake Constance. Frontiers in Environmental Science, 9, 254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, I. C., Hill, J. K., Ohlemüller, R., Roy, D. B., &amp; Thomas, C. D. (2011). Rapid range shifts of species associated with high levels of climate warming. Science, 333(6045), 1024–1026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark, M. E., Rose, K. A., Levine, D. A., &amp; Hargrove, W. W. (2001). Predicting climate change effects on Appalachian trout: Combining GIS and individual‐based modelling. Ecological Applications, 11, 161–178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delmas, E., Brose, U., Gravel, D., Stouffer, D. B., &amp; Poisot, T. (2017). Simulations of biomass dynamics in community food webs. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, 8(7), 881–886.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Environment Agency. (2016). Indicator assessment. Water Temperature. [Online]. Available at: https://www.eea.europa.eu/data-and-maps/indicators/water-temperature-2/assessment/#_edn6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fichman, R. A. (2022). Interactive effects of temperature and food availability on fish growth, otolith accretion, and otolith geochemistry in Endangered Delta smelt (Hypomesus transpacificus) (Doctoral dissertation, UC Davis).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friberg, N., Bergfur, J., Rasmussen, J., &amp; Sandin, L. (2013). Changing northern catchments: Is altered hydrology, temperature or both going to shape future stream communities and ecosystem processes? Hydrological Processes, 27(5), 734–740.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Froese, R., &amp; Pauly, D. (2021). FishBase. World Wide Web Electronic Publication. www.fishbase.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagnon, K., Gräfnings, M., &amp; Boström, C. (2019). Trophic role of the mesopredatory three‐spined stickleback in habitats of varying complexity. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 510, 46–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimm, V., Augusiak, J., Focks, A., Frank, B. M., Gabsi, F., Johnston, A. S., Liu, C., Martin, B. T., Meli, M., Radchuk, V., &amp; Thorbek, P. (2014). Towards better modelling and decision support: Documenting model development, testing, and analysis using TRACE. Ecological Modelling, 280, 129–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimm, V., Railsback, S. F., Vincenot, C. E., Berger, U., Gallagher, C., DeAngelis, D. L., Edmonds, B., Ge, J., Giske, J., Groeneveld, J., &amp; Johnston, A. S. (2020). The ODD protocol for describing agent‐based and other simulation models: A second update to improve clarity, replication, and structural realism. Journal of Artificial Societies and Social Simulation, 23(2): 7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurung, A., Iwata, T., Nakano, D., &amp; Urabe, J. (2019). River metabolism along a latitudinal gradient across Japan and in a global scale. Scientific Reports, 9(1), 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoekman, D. (2010). Turning up the heat: Temperature influences the relative importance of top‐down and bottom‐up effects. Ecology, 91(10), 2819–2825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huryn, A. D., &amp; Benstead, J. P. (2019). Seasonal changes in light availability modify the temperature dependence of secondary production in an Arctic stream. Ecology, 100(6), e02690.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPCC. 2007. IPCC fourth assessment report: Climate change 2007. [online] Available at: https://www.ipcc.ch/site/assets/uploads/2018/02/ar4_syr_full_report.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPCC. (2018). Report SR15 – global warming of 1.5°C. An IPCC special report on the impacts of global warming of 1.5°C above pre‐industrial levels and related global greenhouse gas emission pathways, in the context of strengthening the global response to the threat of climate change, sustainable development, and efforts to eradicate poverty.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPCC. (2021). AR6 climate change 2021:The physical science basis. [online] Available at: https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/downloads/report/IPCC_AR6_WGI_Full_Report_smaller.pdf https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/downloads/report/IPCC_AR6_WGI_Full_Report_smaller.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPCC. (2023). Synthesis report of the IPCC sixth assessment report (AR6). [online] Available at: https://report.ipcc.ch/ar6syr/pdf/IPCC_AR6_SYR_LongerReport.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katsiadaki, I., Sanders, M., Sebire, M., Nagae, M., Soyano, K., &amp; Scott, A. P. (2007). Three‐spined stickleback: An emerging model in environmental endocrine disruption. Environmental Sciences, 14(5), 263–283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovach, R., Jonsson, B., Jonsson, N., Arismendi, I., Williams, J., Kershner, J., Al‐Chokhachy, R., Letcher, B., &amp; Muhlfeld, C. (2019). Climate change and the future of trout and char. In Kershner, J. L., Williams, J. E., Gresswell, R. E &amp; Lobon‐cervia, J (Eds.), Trout and Char of the World. American Fisheries Society.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenoir, J., Bertrand, R., Comte, L., Bourgeaud, L., Hattab, T., Murienne, J., &amp; Grenouillet, G. (2020). Species better track climate warming in the oceans than on land. Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution, 4(8), 1044–1059.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, S., Xie, Z., Liu, B., Wang, Y., Gao, J., Zeng, Y., Xie, J., Xie, Z., Jia, B., Qin, P., &amp; Li, R. (2020). Global river water warming due to climate change and anthropogenic heat emission. Global and Planetary Change, 193, 103289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mintram, K. S., Maynard, S. K., Brown, A. R., Boyd, R., Johnston, A. S., Sibly, R. M., Thorbek, P., &amp; Tyler, C. R. (2020). Applying a mechanistic model to predict interacting effects of chemical exposure and food availability on fish populations. Aquatic Toxicology, 224, 105483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oli, M., &amp; Zinner, B. (2003). Partial life cycle analysis: A model for pre‐breeding census data. Oikos, 93(3), 376–387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pease, J. E., Grabowski, T. B., Pease, A. A., &amp; Bean, P. T. (2018). Changing environmental gradients over forty years alter ecomorphological variation in Guadalupe bass Micropterus treculii throughout a river basin. Ecology and Evolution, 8(16), 8508–8522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phillips, J. S., McCormick, A. R., Botsch, J. C., &amp; Ives, A. R. (2021). Dependence of an aquatic insect population on contemporaneous primary production. bioRxiv 2021‐03. https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.03.22.436388</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinsky, M. L., &amp; Palumbi, S. R. (2014). Meta‐analysis reveals lower genetic diversity in overfished populations. Molecular Ecology, 23(1), 29–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Railsback, S. F. (2022). What we don't know about the effects of temperature on salmonid growth. Transactions of the American Fisheries Society, 151(1), 3–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez‐Dominguez, A., Connell, S. D., Leung, J. Y., &amp; Nagelkerken, I. (2019). Adaptive responses of fishes to climate change: Feedback between physiology and behaviour. Science of the Total Environment, 692, 1242–1249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staten, P. W., Lu, J., Grise, K. M., Davis, S. M., &amp; Birner, T. (2018). Re‐examining tropical expansion. Nature. Climate Change, 8(9), 768–775.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trimmel, H., Weihs, P., Leidinger, D., Formayer, H., Kalny, G., &amp; Melcher, A. (2018). Can riparian vegetation shade mitigate the expected rise in stream temperatures due to climate change during heat waves in a human‐impacted pre‐alpine river? Hydrology and Earth System Sciences, 22(1), 437–461.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Troia, M. J., Joshuah, S., &amp; Perkin, J. S. (2022). Can fisheries bioenergetics modelling refine spatially explicit assessments of climate change vulnerability?, conservation. Physiology, 10(1): coac035.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Vliet, M. T., Franssen, W. H., Yearsley, J. R., Ludwig, F., Haddeland, I., Lettenmaier, D. P., &amp; Kabat, P. (2013). Global river discharge and water temperature under climate change. Global Environmental Change, 23(2), 450–464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Guan, Y., Wu, L., Guan, X., Cai, W., Huang, J., Dong, W., &amp; Zhang, B. (2021). Changing lengths of the four seasons by global warming. Geophysical Research Letters, 48(6), e2020GL091753.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whoriskey, F. G. &amp; FitzGerald, G. J. (1987). Intraspecific competition in stickleback (Gasterosteidae: Pisces): Does mother nature concur?. The Journal of Animal Ecology, 56(3), 939–947.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodward, G., Brown, L. E., Edwards, F. K., Hudson, L. N., Milner, A. M., Reuman, D. C., &amp; Ledger, M. E. (2012). Climate change impacts in multispecies systems: Drought alters food web size structure in a field experiment. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 367(1605), 2990–2997.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wootton, R. J. (1973). Fecundity of the three‐spined stickleback, Gasterosteus aculeatus (L.). Journal of Fish Biology, 5(6), 683–688.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WWF. (2021). The worlds forgotten fishes. [Online] Available at: https://wwfint.awsassets.panda.org/downloads/world_s_forgotten_fishes__report_final__1.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yvon‐Durocher, G., Caffrey, J. M., Cescatti, A., Dossena, M., Del Giorgio, P., Gasol, J. M., Montoya, J. M., Pumpanen, J., Staehr, P. A., Trimmer, M., &amp; Woodward, G. (2012). Reconciling the temperature dependence of respiration across timescales and ecosystem types. Nature, 487(7408), 472–476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yvon‐Durocher, G., Jones, J.I., Trimmer, M., Woodward, G., &amp; Montoya, J.M. (2010). Warming alters the metabolic balance of ecosystems. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 365(1549), 2117‐2126. http://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2010.0038</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>