<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39200524</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2304-8158</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>16</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Foods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Consumer Perception of Food Safety and Valuation of Statistical Life: A Contingent Valuation Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2597</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/foods13162597</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The value of statistical life (VSL) reflects the trade-off between money and the risk of death. It is a key indicator for conducting regulatory impact assessments. The main purpose of this study was to estimate the VSL in the field of food safety. At the same time, it investigates respondents' willingness to pay (WTP) for reducing the risk of death from foodborne illnesses and explores the impact of factors such as the average household monthly income, health status, and education level on WTP. We conducted a survey using an open-ended contingent valuation method among 1307 respondents aged 18 and above to determine their WTP. Based on the WTP survey results, we calculated the VSL in the food safety sector. We used binary logit and Tobit models to analyze the influencing factors. The results of the study show that the median WTP for reducing the risk of foodborne illness is CNY 100 (USD 16), and the estimated VSL is approximately CNY 9.09 million (USD 141 million). Indicators such as the average household monthly income, health status, and education level are important factors affecting WTP. This study will help practitioners, researchers, and policymakers understand the current population's attitudes towards food safety regulations and determine the priorities for regulatory implementation. Future research can explore the effects of different elicitation methods, cultural differences, and regional variations on WTP and VSL.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Bingjie</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Economics, Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Na</LastName><ForeName>Yinuo</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Economics, Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8449-6522</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Economics, Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Dan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Economics, Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Xin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1383-9617</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Economics, Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Foods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101670569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2304-8158</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">contingent valuation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">value of statistical life</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">willingness to pay</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39200524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11353710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13162597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">foods13162597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . WHO Global Strategy for Food Safety 2022–2030: Towards Stronger Food Safety Systems and Global Cooperation. WHO; Geneva, Switzerland: 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaffee S., Henson S., Unnevehr L., Grace D., Cassou E. The Safe Food Imperative: Accelerating Progress in Low- and Middle-Income Countries. World Bank Publications; Chicago, IL, USA: 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao X., Hu J., Liu X. A Preliminary Study on the Disease Burden of Bacterial Foodborne Diseases in China. Chin. J. Food Hyg. 2011;23:132–136. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . Food Safety. WHO; Geneva, Switzerland: 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Central Committee of the Communist Party of China . “Healthy China 2030” Planning Outline. Central Committee of the Communist Party of China; Beijing, China: 2020. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macdonald J., Crutchfield S. Modeling the costs of food safety regulation. Am. J. Agric. Econ. 1996;78:1285–1290. doi: 10.2307/1243508.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/1243508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viscusi W. The Value of Risks to Life and Health. J. Econ. Lit. 1993;31:1912–1946.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sundström K., Andersson H. Swedish Consumers’ Willingness to Pay for Food Safety: A Contingent Valuation Study on Salmonella Risk. Volume 1 Agrifood-WP; Göteborg, Sweden: 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture . Cost Estimates of Foodborne Illnesses. U.S. Department of Agriculture; Washington, DC, USA: 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keller E., Newman J., Ortmann A., Jorm L., Chambers G. How Much Is a Human Life Worth? A Systematic Review. Value Health. 2021;24:1531–1541. doi: 10.1016/j.jval.2021.04.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2021.04.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34593177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He J., Wang H. The Value of Statistical Life: A Contingent Investigation in China. World Bank; Chicago, IL, USA: 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golan E., Kuchler F. Willingness to pay for food safety: Costs and benefits of accurate measures. Am. J. Agric. Econ. 1999;81:1185–1191. doi: 10.2307/1244105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/1244105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang R.C., Li Z. Investigation and Analysis of Purchase Intention and Influencing Factors of Green Vegetables: A Case Study of Urban Consumers in Fushun City, Liaoning Province. J. Shenyang Agric. Univ. (Soc. Sci. Ed.) 2021;23:528–534. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega D.L., Wang H., Wu L., Olynk N. Modeling Heterogeneity in Consume r Preferences for Select Food Safety Attrubutes in China. Food Policy. 2011;36:318–324. doi: 10.1016/j.foodpol.2010.11.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodpol.2010.11.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y.F. Research on Consumers’ Willingness to Pay for Safe Dairy Products. China Bus. Econ. 2011;25:82–87. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdem S. Consumers’ Preferences for Nanotechnology in Food Packaging: A Discrete Choice Experiment. J. Agric. Econ. 2015;66:259–279. doi: 10.1111/1477-9552.12088.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1477-9552.12088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y.H., Peng X.J. An Empirical Study on Urban Consumers’ Willingness to Pay for Food Safety in Jiangsu Province: A Case Study of Low-Residue Green Vegetables. China Econ. Q. 2006;03:1319–1342. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong S.H. Research on the Growth of Dairy Consumption and Its Influencing Factors among Urban and Rural Residents in China. Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences; Beijing, China: 2023. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazzaro C., Stanco M., Uliano A. Consumers’ acceptance and willingness to pay for enriched foods: Evidence from a choice experiment in Italy. Future Foods. 2024;10:100405. doi: 10.1016/j.fufo.2024.100405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fufo.2024.100405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y.Y. An Empirical Study on Shanghai Consumers’ Willingness to Pay for Food Safety: A Case Study of Pork Consumption. J. Southwest Univ. Natl. (Nat. Sci. Ed.) 2013;39:605–610. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin W. Research on Consumers’ Willingness to Pay for Safe Certified Dairy Products and Its Influencing Factors. China For. Econ. 2019;06:51–54. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haghjou M., Hayati B., Pishbahar E. Factors Affecting Consumers’ Potential Willingness to Pay for Organic Food Products in lran: Case Study of Tabriz. J. Agric. Sci. Technol. 2013;15:191–202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersson H., Hole A., Svensson M. Valuation of small and multiple health risks: Acritical analysis of SP data applied to food and water safety. J. Environ. Econ. Manag. 2016;75:41–53. doi: 10.1016/j.jeem.2015.11.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jeem.2015.11.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haninger K., Hammitt J. Diminishing willingness to pay per quality adjusted life year: Valuing acute foodborne illness. Risk Anal. 2011;31:1363–1380. doi: 10.1111/j.1539-6924.2011.01617.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1539-6924.2011.01617.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21488924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J., Adamowicz W., Dupont D.P., Krupnick A. Assessing the extent of altruism in the valuation of community drinking water quality improvements. Water Resour. Res. 2013;49:6286–6297. doi: 10.1002/wrcr.20447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/wrcr.20447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alberini A., Kanninen B., Carson R.T. Modeling response incentive effects in dichotomous choice contingent valuation data. Land Econ. 1997;73:309–324. doi: 10.2307/3147170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/3147170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh R.G., Loomis J.B., Gillman R.A. Valuing option, existence, and bequest demands for wilderness. Land Econ. 1983;59:14–29. doi: 10.2307/3146089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/3146089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan S. Research on the Purchase Intention of Traceable Chicken by Consumers in Harbin from a Heterogeneity Perspective. Jilin University; Changchun, China: 2020. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del A., Li L., Ang L., Lim N., Seow W.J. Evaluating SoJump.com as a tool for online behavioral research in China. J. Behav. Exp. Financ. 2024;41:100905.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersson H. The value of a statistical life. Adv. Transp. Policy Plan. 2020;6:75–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warner S.L. Stochastic Choice of Mode in Urban Travel: A Study in Binary Choice. Northwestern University; Evanston, IL, USA: 1962. (Metropolitan Transportation Series).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amemiya T. Tobit models: A survey. J. Econom. 1984;24:3–61. doi: 10.1016/0304-4076(84)90074-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0304-4076(84)90074-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu A. Chinese consumers food purchasing behaviors and awareness of food safety. Food Control. 2017;79:185–191. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.03.038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.03.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruby G.E., Ungku U.F., Lihan S., Jambari N.N. A cross sectional study on food safety knowledge among adult consumers. Food Control. 2019;99:98–105. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.12.045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.12.045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swinehart M.R., Feng Y. US Consumers’ Tree Nut Food Safety Knowledge, Perceptions, and Handling Practices across Demographic Groups. Foods. 2023;12:4289. doi: 10.3390/foods12234289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12234289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10706404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38231712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B., Fu Z., Huang J., Wang J., Xu S., Zhang L. Consumers’ perceptions, purchase intention, and willingness to pay a premium price for safe vegetables: A case study of Beijing, China. J. Clean. Prod. 2018;197:1498–1507. doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2018.06.273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2018.06.273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong Q., Anders S., Zhang J., Zhang L. The roles of pollution concerns and environmental knowledge in making green food choices: Evidence from Chinese consumers. Food Res. Int. 2020;130:108881. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2019.108881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2019.108881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32156344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson L.A., Hammitt J.K. Valuing Reductions in Fatal Illness Risks: Implications of Recent Research. Health Econ. 2016;25:1039–1052. doi: 10.1002/hec.3214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hec.3214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26132383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carson T.R., Flores E.N., Meade F.N. Contingent Valuation: Controversies and Evidence. Environ. Resour. Econ. 2001;19:173–210. doi: 10.1023/A:1011128332243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1011128332243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H. What is the health cost of haze pollution? Evidence from China. Int. J. Health Plan. Manag. 2019;34:1290–1303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31025396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y., Andersson H., Zhang S. Do preferences to reduce health risks related to air pollution depend on illness type? Evidence from a choice experiment in Beijing, China. J. Environ. Econ. Manag. 2020;103:102355. doi: 10.1016/j.jeem.2020.102355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jeem.2020.102355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Q., Liu P., Yang Z. Estimation of value of statistical life using willingness-to-pay method: A focus on Hangzhou, China. CICTP. 2019;2019:3810–3822.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Ren Y.Q., Cen K. Study on the statistical value of life of construction personnel under the background of the COVID-19 pandemic. China Saf. Sci. J. 2023;19:41–46. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karl J.H., Kip W.V. Dead reckoning: Demographic determinants of the accuracy of mortality risk perceptions. Risk Anal. Off. Publ. Soc. Risk Anal. 2004;24:651–664.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15209936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armantier O. Estimates of own lethal risks and anchoring effects. J. Risk Uncertain. 2006;32:37–56. doi: 10.1007/s10797-006-6665-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10797-006-6665-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M. Report on the Survey of Public Safety Perception and Sense of Security in China (2023) Natl. Gov. 2023;16:76–80. (In Chinese)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mon E., Jomnonkwao S., Khampirat B. Willingness to pay for mortality risk reduction for traffic accidents in Myanmar. Accid. Anal. Prev. 2018;118:18–28. doi: 10.1016/j.aap.2018.05.018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2018.05.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29859506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henson S. Consumer willingness to pay for reductions in the risk of food poisoning in the UK. J. Agric. Econ. 1996;47:403–420. doi: 10.1111/j.1477-9552.1996.tb00701.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1477-9552.1996.tb00701.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera D., Rochaix L. Does the Value per Statistical Life vary with age or baseline health? Evidence from a compensating wage study in France. J. Environ. Econ. Manag. 2020;103:102338. doi: 10.1016/j.jeem.2020.102338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jeem.2020.102338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viscusi K., Aldy E. The Value of a Statistical Life: A Critical Review of Market Estimates Throughout the World. J. Risk Uncertain. 2003;27:5–76. doi: 10.1023/A:1025598106257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1025598106257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kniesner T., Viscusi W. The Value of a Statistical Life. Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Economics and Finance. Oxford University Press; Oxford, UK: 2019. pp. 15–19.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>