<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39200505</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2304-8158</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>16</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Foods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Health Hazard Associated with the Presence of <i>Clostridium</i> Bacteria in Food Products.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2578</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/foods13162578</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><i>Clostridium</i> bacteria were already known to Hippocrates many years before Christ. The name of the <i>Clostridium</i> species is owed to the Polish microbiologist, Adam Prażmowski. It is now known that these <i>Clostridium</i> bacteria are widespread in the natural environment, and their presence in food products is a threat to human health and life. According to European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) reports, every year, there are poisonings or deaths due to ingestion of bacterial toxins, including those of the <i>Clostridium</i> spp. The strengthening of consumer health awareness has increased interest in consuming products with minimal processing in recent years, which has led to a need to develop new techniques to ensure the safety of microbiological food, including elimination of bacteria from the <i>Clostridium</i> genera. On the other hand, the high biochemical activity of <i>Clostridium</i> bacteria allows them to be used in the chemical, pharmaceutical, and medical industries. Awareness of microbiological food safety is very important for our health. Unfortunately, in 2022, an increase in infections with <i>Clostridium</i> bacteria found in food was recorded. Knowledge about food contamination should thus be widely disseminated.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bilska</LastName><ForeName>Agnieszka</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0908-7347</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food and Nutrition, Poznan University of Physical Education, Krolowej Jadwigi 27/39, 61-871 Poznan, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wochna</LastName><ForeName>Krystian</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9261-1332</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Swimming and Water Lifesaving, Poznan University of Physical Education, Krolowej Jadwigi 27/39, 61-871 Poznan, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Habiera</LastName><ForeName>Małgorzata</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Swimming and Water Lifesaving, Poznan University of Physical Education, Krolowej Jadwigi 27/39, 61-871 Poznan, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Serwańska-Leja</LastName><ForeName>Katarzyna</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9683-3514</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sports Dietetics, Poznan University of Physical Education, 61-871 Poznan, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Anatomy, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Sciences, Poznan University of Life Sciences, Wojska Polskiego 71c, 60-625 Poznan, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Foods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101670569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2304-8158</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">C. botulinum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clostridium spp.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food pathogen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">industrial application of Clostridium spp.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbiological food safety</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39200505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11353352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13162578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">foods13162578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mayr E. Principles of Systematic Zoology. McGraw-Hill; New York, NY, USA: 1969. pp. 34–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dürre P. From Pandora’s Box to Cornucopia: Clostridia—A Historical Perspective. In: Bahl H., Dürre P., editors. Clostridia: Biotechnology and Medical Applications. Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH; Berlin, Germany: 2001. pp. 1–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moriishi K., Koura M., Abe N., Fujii N., Fujinaga Y., Inoue K., Ogumad K. Mosaic structures of neurotoxins produced from Clostridiumbotulinum strain NCTC 2916. FEMS Microbiol. Lett. 1996;140:151–158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaroszewska E., Pietracha D., Misiewicz A. Patogeny człowieka w żywności pochodzenia roślinnego—Wady i zalety zastosowania techniki Real-Time PCR do ich wykrywania. Postępy Nauk. Technol. Przemysłu Rolno-Spożywczego. 2014;69:44–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parish M.E., Beuchat L.R., Suslow T.V., Harris L.J., Garrett E.H., Farber J.N., Busta F.F. Methods to reduce/eliminate pathogens from fresh and fresh-cut produce. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2006;2:161–173. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-4337.2003.tb00033.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2003.tb00033.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erickson M.C., Doyle M.P. The challenges of eliminating or substituting antimicrobial preservatives in foods. Annu. Rev. Food Sci. Technol. 2017;8:371–390. doi: 10.1146/annurev-food-030216-025952.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-food-030216-025952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28125350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaam O.E., Fliss I., Aïder M. Effect of electro-activated aqueous solutions, nisin and moderate heat treatment on the inactivation of Clostridiumsporogenes PA 3679 spores in green beans puree and whole green beans. Anaerobe. 2017;47:173–182. doi: 10.1016/j.anaerobe.2017.05.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2017.05.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28578132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buckel W. Clostridial enzymes and fermentation pathways. In: Duerre P., editor. Handbook on Clostridia. CRC Press LLC; Boca Raton, FL, USA: 2005. pp. 81–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leja K., Myszka K., Olkowicz M., Juzwa W., Czaczyk K. Clostridiumbifermentans as an aero-tolerant exponent of strictly anaerobe genera. Adv. Microbiol. 2014;4:216–224. doi: 10.4236/aim.2014.44028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4236/aim.2014.44028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strus M., Pakosz K., Gościniak H., Przondo-Mordarska A., Rożynek E., Pituch H., Meisel-Mikołajczyk F., Heczko P.B. Antagonistyczne działanie bakterii z rodzaju Lactobacillus wobec beztlenowych i mikroaerofilnych czynników zakażeń przewodu pokarmowego (Helicobacter pylori, Campylobacter coli, Campylobacter jejuni, Clostridiumdifficile) Med. Doświadczalna Mikrobiol. 2001;53:133–142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11757422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zyska B. Bakterie z rodzaju Clostridium. In: Libudzisz Z., Kowal K., editors. Mikrobiologia Techniczna. Wydawnictwo Politechniki Łódzkiej; Łódź, Poland: 2000. pp. 155–175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stackebrandt E., Hippe H., Dürre P. Taxonomy and Systematics. In: Bahl H., Dürre P., editors. Clostridia: Biotechnology and Medical Applications. Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH; Berlin, Germany: 2001. pp. 20–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leja K., Myszka K., Czaczyk M. Przemysłowe wykorzystanie bakterii z rodzaju Clostridium. Postep. Mikrobiol. 2014;53:15–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanaan M., Tarek A. Clostridium botulinum, a foodborne pathogen and its impact on public health. Ann. Trop. Med. Public Health. 2020;23:49–62. doi: 10.36295/ASRO.2020.2357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36295/ASRO.2020.2357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bielec D., Modrzewska R. Zatrucie jadem kiełbasianym wczoraj i dziś—Aspekty kliniczne. Przegląd Epidemiol. 2007;61:505–512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18069387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowak A., Ołtuszak-Walczak E., Świtoniak T. Zatrucia i zakażenia pokarmowe. In: Libudzisz Z., Kowal K., Żakowska Z., editors. Mikrobiologia Techniczna. Volume 2. Wydawnictwo Naukowe PWN; Warsaw, Poland: 2018. pp. 265–288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franciosa G., Ferreira J.L., Hatheway C.L. Detection of type A, B, and E botulism neurotoxin genes in Clostridiumbotulinum and other Clostridiumspecies by PCR: Evidence of unexpressed type B toxin genes in type A toxigenic organisms. J. Clin. Microbiol. 1994;32:1911–1917. doi: 10.1128/jcm.32.8.1911-1917.1994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.32.8.1911-1917.1994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC263902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7989542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bielec D., Semczuk G., Lis J., Firych J., Modrzewska R., Janowski R. Epidemiologia i klinika zatruć jadem kiełbasianym chorych leczonych w Klinice Chorób Zakaźnych w Akademii Medycznej w Lublinie w latach 1999–2000. Przegląd Epidemiol. 2002;56:435–442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12608093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindström M., Heikinheimo A., Lahti P., Korkeala H. Novel insights into the epidemiology of Clostridiumperfringens type A food poisoning. Food Microbiol. 2011;28:192–198. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2010.03.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2010.03.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21315973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ścieżyńska H., Maćkiw E., Mąka Ł., Pawłowska K. Nowe zagrożenia mikrobiologiczne w żywności. Rocz. Panstw. Zakl. Hig. 2012;63:397–402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23631259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y., Li H., Yang L., Wang L., Sun R., Shearer J.E.S., Sun F. Rapid Detection of Clostridiumbotulinum in Food Using Loop-Mediated Isothermal Amplification (LAMP) Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2021;21:4401. doi: 10.3390/ijerph18094401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18094401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8122632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33919101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenda T., Jarosz A., Sapała M., Grenda A., Patyra E., Kwiatek K. Clostridium perfringens—Opportunistic Foodborne Pathogen, Its Diversity and Epidemiological Significance. Pathogens. 2023;12:768. doi: 10.3390/pathogens12060768.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens12060768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10304509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37375458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu Y., Alenezi T., Sun X. Clostridium perfringens-Induced Necrotic Diseases: An Overview. Immuno. 2022;2:387–407. doi: 10.3390/immuno2020024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/immuno2020024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wadełek J. Diagnostyka i leczenie zgorzeli Fourniera w oddziale intensywnej terapii. Nowa Med. 2016;3:102–113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kądzielska J., Obuch-Woszczatyński P., Pituch H., Młynarczyk G. Clostridiumperfringens jako czynnik etiologiczny biegunki poantybiotykowej. Postep. Mikrobiol. 2012;51:17–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chukwu E.E., Nwaokorie F.O., Coker A.O., Avila-Campos M.J., Solis R.L., Llanco L.A., Ogunsola F.T. Detection of toxigenic Clostridiumperfringens and Clostridiumbotulinum from food sold in Lagos, Nigeria. Anaerobe. 2016;42:176–181. doi: 10.1016/j.anaerobe.2016.10.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2016.10.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27789246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehdizadeh Gohari I., A Navarro M., Li J., Shrestha A., Uzal F., A McClane B. Pathogenicity and virulence of Clostridiumperfringens. Virulence. 2021;12:723–753. doi: 10.1080/21505594.2021.1886777.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21505594.2021.1886777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8043184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33843463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clancy C.J., Buehrle D., Vu M., Wagener M.M., Nguyen M.H. Impact of revised infectious diseases Society of America and Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America clinical practice guidelines on the treatment of Clostridium difficile Infections in the United States. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2021;72:1944–1949. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciaa484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32343766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aguirre A.M., Sorg J.A. Gut associated metabolites and their roles in Clostridioides difficile pathogenesis. Gut Microbes. 2022;14:2094672. doi: 10.1080/19490976.2022.2094672.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2022.2094672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9450991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35793402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pal M., Bulcha M. Clostridium difficile as an Emerging Foodborne Pathogen of Public Health Significance. Acta Sci. Microbiol. 2021;4:46–49. doi: 10.31080/ASMI.2021.04.0834.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31080/ASMI.2021.04.0834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rupnik M., Songer J.G. Chapter 3—Clostridium difficile: Its Potential as a Source of Foodborne Disease. In: Taylor S.L., editor. Advances in Food and Nutrition Research. Volume 60. Elsevier Inc.; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: Academic Press; Cambridge, MA, USA: 2010. pp. 53–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20691953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilverstone T.W., Garland M., Cave R.J., Kelly M.L., Tholen M., Bouley D.M., Kehne S.A., Melnyk R.A. The glucosyltransferase activity of C. difficile Toxin B is required for disease pathogenesis. PLoS Pathog. 2020;16:e1008852. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1008852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7531778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32960931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith A., Jenior M., Keenan O., Hart J., Specker J., Abbas A., Rangel P., Di C., Green J., Bustin K., et al. Enterococci enhance Clostridioides difficile pathogenesis. Nature. 2022;611:780–786. doi: 10.1038/s41586-022-05438-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-05438-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9691601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36385534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weese J.S. Clostridium difficile in food—Innocent bystander or serious threat? Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2009;16:1. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-0691.2009.03108.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2009.03108.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20002685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Num S.M., Useh N.M. Clostridium: Pathogenic roles, industrial uses and medicinal prospects of natural products as ameliorative agents against pathogenic species. Jordan J. Biol. Sci. 2014;7:81–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (European Food Safety Authority) ECDC (European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2013. EFSA J. 2014;14:4634.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (European Food Safety Authority) ECDC (European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2014. EFSA J. 2015;13:4329. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2015.4329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2015.4329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (European Food Safety Authority) and ECDC (European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2015. EFSA J. 2016;14:e04634. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2016.4634.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2016.4634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7009962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32625371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA (European Food Safety Authority) ECDC (European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2016. EFSA J. 2017;15:e05077. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2017.5077.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2017.5077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7009962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32625371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA and ECDC (European Food Safety Authority and European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2017. EFSA J. 2018;16:5500. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2018.5500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2018.5500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7009540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32625785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. ECDC (European Food Safety Authority and European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union One Health 2018 Zoonoses Report. EFSA J. 2019;17:5926. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2019.5926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2019.5926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7055727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32626211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. ECDC (European Food Safety Authority and European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union One Health 2019 Zoonoses Report. EFSA J. 2021;19:6406. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2021.6406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2021.6406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7913300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33680134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. ECDC (European Food Safety Authority and European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union One Health 2020 Zoonoses Report. EFSA J. 2021;19:6971. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2021.6971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2021.6971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9624447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36329690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. ECDC (European Food Safety Authority and European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union One Health 2021 Zoonoses Report. EFSA J. 2022;20:7666. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2022.7666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2022.7666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9745727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36524203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. ECDC (European Food Safety Authority and European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control) The European Union One Health 2022 Zoonoses Report. EFSA J. 2023;21:e8442. doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2023.8442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2023.8442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10714251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38089471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peñuelas M., Guerrero-Vadillo M., Valdezate S., Zamora M.J., Leon-Gomez I., Flores-Cuéllar Á., Carrasco G., Díaz-García O., Varela C. Botulism in Spain: Epidemiology and Outcomes of Antitoxin Treatment, 1997–2019. Toxins. 2023;15:2. doi: 10.3390/toxins15010002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins15010002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9863742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36668823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowicka P., Wojdyło A., Oszmiański J. Zagrożenia powstające w żywności minimalnie przetworzonej i skuteczne metody ich eliminacji. Zywn-Nau Technol. J. 2014;2:5–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Przetaczek-Rożnowska I., Kuźniak M. Źródła zanieczyszczeń mikrobiologicznych ziół leczniczych i przypraw oraz metody ich dekontaminacji. Postępy Fitoter. 2016;1:59–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kręgiel D., Piątkiewicz A., Żakowska Z., Kunicka-Styczyńska A. Zanieczyszczenia mikrobiologiczne surowców. In: Libudzisz Z., Kowal K., Żakowska Z., editors. Mikrobiologia Techniczna. Volume 2. Wydawnictwo Naukowe PWN; Warsaw, Poland: 2018. pp. 235–252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto C.A., Mousakhani Ganjeh A., Barba F.J., Saraiva J.A. Impact of pH and High-Pressure Pasteurization on the Germination and Development of Clostridiumperfringens Spores under Hyperbaric Storage versus Refrigeration. Foods. 2024;13:1832. doi: 10.3390/foods13121832.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13121832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11202566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38928774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson C.H.D., Vazquez A.J., Hill K., Smith T.J., Nottingham R., Stone N.E., Sobek C.J., Cocking J.H., Fernández R.A., Caballero P.A., et al. Differentiating botulinum neurotoxin-producing Clostridia with a simple, multiplex PCR assay. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2017;83:e00806-17. doi: 10.1128/AEM.00806-17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00806-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5583490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28733282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popoff M.R., Brüggemann H. Regulatory Networks Controlling Neurotoxin Synthesis in Clostridiumbotulinum and Clostridiumtetani. Toxins. 2022;14:364. doi: 10.3390/toxins14060364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins14060364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9229411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35737025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahlsten E., Lindström M., Korkeala H. Mechanism of food processing and storage-related stress tolerance in Clostridiumbotulinum. Res. Microbiol. 2015;166:344–352. doi: 10.1016/j.resmic.2014.09.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2014.09.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25303833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodgers S. Survival of Clostridiumbotulinum in hot-fill meals. Food Serv. Technol. 2002;2:69–79. doi: 10.1046/j.1471-5740.2002.00038.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1471-5740.2002.00038.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danyluk B., Bilska A., Kirklo P. Ocena mikrobiologiczna wybranych produktów drobiowych z grupy żywności wygodnej. Nauka Przyr. Technol. 2015;9:3. doi: 10.17306/J.NPT.2015.3.31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17306/J.NPT.2015.3.31</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munir M.T., Mtimet N., Guillier L., Meurens F., Fravalo P., Federighi M., Kooh P. Physical Treatments to Control Clostridiumbotulinum Hazards in Food. Foods. 2023;12:1580. doi: 10.3390/foods12081580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12081580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10137509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37107375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pernu N., Keto-Timonen R., Lindström M., Korkeala H. High prevalence of Clostridiumbotulinum in vegetarian sausages. Food Microbiol. 2020;91:103512. doi: 10.1016/j.fm.2020.103512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2020.103512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32539985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duc H.M., Hoa T.T.K., Ha C.T.T., Van Hung L., Van Thang N., Minh Son H., Flory G.A. Prevalence and Antibiotic Resistance Profile of Clostridiumperfringens Isolated from Pork and Chicken Meat in Vietnam. Pathogens. 2024;13:400. doi: 10.3390/pathogens13050400.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens13050400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11123724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38787252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rendueles E., Mauriz E., Sanz-Gómez J., González-Paramás A.M., Adanero-Jorge F., García-Fernández C. Exploring Propolis as a Sustainable Bio-Preservative Agent to Control Foodborne Pathogens in Vacuum-Packed Cooked Ham. Microorganisms. 2024;12:914. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms12050914.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12050914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11124515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38792741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim S., Foster N.F., Riley T.V. Susceptibility of Clostridium difficile to the food preservatives sodium nitrite, sodium nitrate and sodium metabisulphite. Anaerobe. 2016;31:67–71. doi: 10.1016/j.anaerobe.2015.12.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2015.12.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26700884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warriner K., Xu C., Habash M., Sultan S., Weese S.J. Dissemination of Clostridium difficile in food and the environment: Significant sources of C. difficile community-acquired infection? J. Appl. Microbiol. 2016;122:542–553. doi: 10.1111/jam.13338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.13338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27813268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nalepa B., Markiewicz L.H. PCR-DGGE markers for qualitative profiling of microbiota in raw milk and ripened cheeses. Food Sci. Technol. 2017;84:168–174. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2017.05.057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2017.05.057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Libudzisz Z. Bakterie fermentacji mlekowej. In: Libudzisz Z., Kowal K., Żakowska Z., editors. Mikrobiologia Techniczna. Volume 2. Wydawnictwo Naukowe PWN; Warsaw, Poland: 2018. pp. 25–58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowak A., Piątkiewicz A. Mikrobiologiczne psucie żywności. In: Libudzisz Z., Kowal K., Żakowska Z., editors. Mikrobiologia Techniczna. Volume 2. Wydawnictwo Naukowe PWN; Warsaw, Poland: 2018. pp. 253–264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoang L.H., Nga T.T., Tram N.T., Trang L.T., Ha H.T.T., Hoang T.H., Anh D.D., Yen P.B., Nguyen N.T., Morita M., et al. First report of foodborne botulism due to Clostridiumbotulinum type A(B) from vegetarian home-canned pate in Hanoi, Vietnam. Anaerobe. 2022;77:102514. doi: 10.1016/j.anaerobe.2022.102514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2022.102514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35007729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fua’di M.T., Er B., Lee S., Chan P.P., Khoo J., Tan D., Li H., Muhammad I.R., Raj P., Kurupatham L., et al. Characteristics of Gastroenteritis Outbreaks Investigated in Singapore: 2018–2021. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2024;21:64. doi: 10.3390/ijerph21010064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph21010064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10815581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38248529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leja K., Czaczyk K., Myszka K. Biotechnological synthesis of 1,3-propanediol using Clostridium ssp. Afr. J. Biotechnol. 2011;10:11093–11101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leja K., Czaczyk K., Myszka K. The use of microorganisms in 1,3-propanediol production. Afr. J. Microbiol. Res. 2011;5:4652–4658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo P., Zhang K., Ma X., He P. Clostridium species as probiotics: Potentials and challenges. J. Anim. Sci. Biotechnol. 2020;11:24. doi: 10.1186/s40104-019-0402-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40104-019-0402-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7031906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32099648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samul D., Worsztynowicz P., Leja K., Grajek W. Beneficial and harmful roles of bacteria from the Clostridium genus. Acta Biochim. 2013;60:515–521. doi: 10.18388/abp.2013_2015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18388/abp.2013_2015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24432307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenda T., Grenda A., Domaradzki P., Krawczyk P., Kwiatek K. Probiotic Potential of Clostridium spp.—Advantages and Doubts. Curr. Issues Mol. Biol. 2022;44:3118–3130. doi: 10.3390/cimb44070215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cimb44070215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9315758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35877439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bigalke H., Shoer L.F. Clostridial neurotoxins. In: Aktories K., Just I., editors. Bacterial Protein Toxins. Springer; Berlin, Germany: 2000. pp. 407–443. Handbook of Experimental Pharmacology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schiavo G., Matteoli M., Montecucco C. Neurotoxins affecting neuroexocytosis. Physiol. Rev. 2000;80:717–766. doi: 10.1152/physrev.2000.80.2.717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/physrev.2000.80.2.717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10747206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreydon O.P., Geiges M.L., Boni R., Burg G. Botulinum toxin: From poison to medicine. A historical review. Hautarzt. 2000;51:733–737.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11153358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heap J.T., Theys J., Ehsaan M., Kubiak A.M., Dubois L., Paesmans K., Van Mellaert L., Knox R., Kuehne S.A., Lambin P., et al. Spores of Clostridium engineered for clinical efficacy and safety cause regression and cure of tumors in vivo. Oncotarget. 2014;5:1761–1769. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.1761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.1761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4039107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24732092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jankovic J., Hallet M. Therapy with Botulinum Toxin. Marcel Dekker, Inc.; New York, NY, USA: 1994. pp. 43–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brin M.F. Botulinum toxin: Chemistry, pharmacology, toxicity, and immunology. Muscle Nerve. 1997;20:156–168. doi: 10.1002/(SICI)1097-4598(1997)6+&lt;146::AID-MUS10&gt;3.0.CO;2-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4598(1997)6+&lt;146::AID-MUS10&gt;3.0.CO;2-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9826987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eklund F.T., Poysky L.M., Mseitif T., Strom M.T. Evidence for plasmid-mediated toxin and bacteriocin production in Clostridiumbotulinum type G. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1988;54:1405–1408. doi: 10.1128/aem.54.6.1405-1408.1988.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.54.6.1405-1408.1988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC202669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2843093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barber J.M., Robb F.T., Webster J.R., Woods D.R. Bacteriocin production by Clostridium acetobutylicum in an industrial fermentation process. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1979;37:433–437. doi: 10.1128/aem.37.3.433-437.1979.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.37.3.433-437.1979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC243234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarke D.J., Moyra R.R., Morris J.G. Purification of two Clostridium bacteriocins by procedures appropriate to hydrophobic proteins. Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 1975;3:256–264. doi: 10.1128/AAC.7.3.256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AAC.7.3.256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC429121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1137378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>