<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39206027</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1554-7914</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>20</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Gastroenterology &amp; hepatology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Gastroenterol Hepatol (N Y)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical Guide to Navigating the Landscape of Biosimilars for Inflammatory Bowel Disease.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>376</StartPage><EndPage>382</EndPage><MedlinePgn>376-382</MedlinePgn></Pagination><Abstract><AbstractText>Annual out-of-pocket expenditures for patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) are estimated to be as high as $41,000, with medications, such as biologics, being one of the main cost contributors. Although biologics have revolutionized IBD management, these medications are costly owing to their molecular makeup and manufacturing processes. Biosimilars, which are biologic medications that are highly similar to the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved reference product with no clinically meaningful differences in safety, purity, or potency, offer the same therapeutic benefits at a reduced cost. Other additional benefits offered with biosimilars include increased treatment access and fostered development of new therapeutic options. Despite the expansion of biosimilars in IBD, their adoption and utilization have been suboptimal in the United States. This article provides an overview of the biosimilar landscape in IBD, including FDA-approved biosimilars available, and a clinical guide to navigate switching to biosimilars in various clinical scenarios based on current evidence.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Gastro-Hep Communications, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhat</LastName><ForeName>Shubha</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Digestive Disease and Surgery Institute and Department of Pharmacy, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kane</LastName><ForeName>Sunanda V</ForeName><Initials>SV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Gastroenterol Hepatol (N Y)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101262648</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1554-7914</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biosimilars</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adalimumab</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biologics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inflammatory bowel disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infliximab</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pipeline</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39206027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11348546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Berg DR, Colombel JF, Ungaro R. The role of early biologic therapy in inflammatory bowel disease. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2019;25(12):1896–1905.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7185690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30934053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Privitera G, Pugliese D, Lopetuso LR et al. Novel trends with biologics in inflammatory bowel disease: sequential and combined approaches. Therap Adv Gastroenterol. 2021;14:17562848211006669.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8082976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33995579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kahn-Boesel O, Cautha S, Ufere NN, Ananthakrishnan AN, Kochar B. A narrative review of financial burden, distress, and toxicity of inflammatory bowel diseases in the United States. Am J Gastroenterol. 2023;118(9):1545–1553.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37224301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen NH, Khera R, Ohno-Machado L, Sandborn WJ, Singh S. Prevalence and effects of food insecurity and social support on financial toxicity in and healthcare use by patients with inflammatory bowel diseases. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2021;20(07):1377–1386.e5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7987215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32526341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis JD, Parlett LE, Jonsson Funk ML et al. Incidence, prevalence, and racial and ethnic distribution of inflammatory bowel disease in the United States. Gastroenterology. 2023;165(5):1197–1205.e2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10592313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37481117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ungaro RC, Naegeli AN, Choong CK et al. Early use of biologics reduces healthcare costs in Crohn’s disease: results from a United States population-based cohort. Dig Dis Sci. 2024;69(1):45–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36920668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://www.fda.gov/drugs/therapeutic-biologics-applications-bla/biosimilars Biosimilars. US Food and Drug Administration. Updated March 1, 2023. Accessed June 13, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mestre-Ferrandiz J, Czech M, Smolen JS et al. Capturing the holistic value of biosimilars in Europe -part 1: a historical perspective. Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res. 2024;24(2):237–250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38175140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://www.iqvia.com/-/media/iqvia/pdfs/library/white-papers/the-impact-of-biosimilarcompetition-in-europe-2022.pdf IQVIA. The impact of biosimilar competition in Europe. December 2022. Accessed June 13, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://www.iqvia.com/insights/the-iqvia-institute/reports-and-publications/reports/biosimilarsin-the-united-states-2023-2027 IQVIA. Biosimilars in the United States 2023-2027. January 31, 2023. Accessed June 13, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene L, Singh RM, Carden MJ, Pardo CO, Lichtenstein GR. Strategies for overcoming barriers to adopting biosimilars and achieving goals of the Biologics Price Competition and Innovation Act: a survey of managed care and specialty pharmacy professionals. J Manag Care Spec Pharm. 2019;25(8):904–912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10397695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31007119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feagins LA, Gold S, Steinlauf AF. and the FDA-Related Matters Committee of the American College of Gastroenterology. Overview of biosimilars in inflammatory bowel diseases. Am J Gastroenterol. 2024;119(2):229–232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37566893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angyal A, Bhat S. Biosimilars in IBD: what every clinician needs to know. Curr Gastroenterol Rep. 2024;26(3):77–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38243154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA approves interchangeable biosimilar for multiple inflammatory diseases [press release]. US Food and Drug Administration; October 31, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunleavy K. After patent settlement, Amgen scores FDA nod for its biosimilar version of J&amp;J’s Stelara. https://www.fiercepharma.com/pharma/amgen-scoresfda-nod-its-biosimilar-version-johnson-johnsons-stelara November 1, 2023. Accessed June 13, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunleavy K. In 2nd attempt, Takeda scores FDA nod for subcutaneous version of Entyvio. https://www.fiercepharma.com/pharma/takedas-scores-second-chance-subcutaneous-version-entyvio September 28, 2023. Accessed June 13, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meade S, Squirell E, Hoang TT, Chow J, Rosenfeld G. An update on anti-TNF biosimilar switching-real-world clinical effectiveness and safety. J Can Assoc Gastroenterol. 2023;7(1):30–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10836972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38314175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casanova MJ, Nantes Ó, Varela P et al. Real-world outcomes of switching from adalimumab originator to adalimumab biosimilar in patients with inflammatory bowel disease: the ADA-SWITCH study. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2023;58(1):60–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37089065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat S, Limdi JK, Cross RK, Farraye FA. Does similarity breed contempt? A review of the use of biosimilars in inflammatory bowel disease. Dig Dis Sci. 2021;66(8):2513–2532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34176024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menter A, Cohen S, Kay J et al. Switching between adalimumab reference product and BI 695501 in patients with chronic plaque psoriasis (VOLTAIRE-X): a randomized controlled trial. Am J Clin Dermatol. 2022;23(5):719–728.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9464749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35934770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleischmann RM, Saikali W, Lakhanpal S et al. Multiple switching between the biosimilar adalimumab PF-06410293 and reference adalimumab in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis: a phase 3, open-label, randomised, parallel-group study. Lancet Rheumatol. 2023;5(9):e532–e541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38251497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villanueva MN, Davis JE, Sobocinski SM. Navigating uncharted waters: developing a standardized approach for evaluating and implementing biosimilar products at a comprehensive cancer center. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2021;78(3):249–260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33289499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cisek S, Choi D, Stubbings J, Bhat S. Preparing for the market entry of adalimumab biosimilars in the US in 2023: a primer for specialty pharmacists. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2023;80(18):1223–1233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37257054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jørgensen KK, Olsen IC, Goll GL et al. NOR-SWITCH study group. Switching from originator infliximab to biosimilar CT-P13 compared with maintained treatment with originator infliximab (NOR-SWITCH): a 52-week, randomised, double-blind, non-inferiority trial. Lancet. 2017;389(10086):2304–2316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28502609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lasala R, Abrate P, Zovi A, Santoleri F. Safety and effectiveness of multiple switching between originators and biosimilars: literature review and status report on interchangeability. Ther Innov Regul Sci. 2023;57(2):352–364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36322326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gros B, Plevris N, Constantine-Cooke N et al. Multiple infliximab biosimilar switches appear to be safe and effective in a real-world inflammatory bowel disease cohort. United European Gastroenterol J. 2023;11(2):179–188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10039791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36802176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanzel J, Jansen JM, Ter Steege RWF, Gecse KB, D’Haens GR. Multiple switches from the originator infliximab to biosimilars is effective and safe in inflammatory bowel disease: a prospective multicenter cohort study. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2022;28(4):495–501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8972297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34013959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahadevan U, Long MD, Kane SV et al. Crohn’s Colitis Foundation Clinical Research Alliance. Pregnancy and neonatal outcomes after fetal exposure to biologics and thiopurines among women with inflammatory bowel disease. Gastroenterology. 2021;160(4):1131–1139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7956164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33227283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott R, Parker H, Mccartney S, Harrow P, Williams D, Giles I. Outcomes following biosimilar TNF inhibitor use for inflammatory-mediated immune disorders in pregnancy. Obstet Med. 2022;15(2):104–107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9277732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35845229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang HN, Thorpe R, Knezevic I et al. Survey participants from 19 countries. The regulatory landscape of biosimilars: WHO efforts and progress made from 2009 to 2019. Biologicals. 2020;65:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7254057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32224101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odinet JS, Day CE, Cruz JL, Heindel GA. The biosimilar nocebo effect? A systematic review of double-blinded versus open-label studies. J Manag Care Spec Pharm. 2018;24(10):952–959.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10398229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30247100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Amico F, Solitano V, Peyrin-Biroulet L, Danese S. Nocebo effect and biosimilars in inflammatory bowel diseases: what’s new and what’s next? Expert Opin Biol Ther. 2021;21(1):47–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32857634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Amico F, Pouillon L, Argollo M et al. Multidisciplinary management of the nocebo effect in biosimilar-treated IBD patients: results of a workshop from the NOCE-BIO consensus group. Dig Liver Dis. 2020;52(2):138–142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31812570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oskouei ST, Kusmierczyk AR. Biosimilar uptake: the importance of healthcare provider education. Pharmaceut Med. 2021;35(4):215–224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8421278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34420201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng K, Russo M, Maini L, Kesselheim AS, Rome BN. Patient out-of-pocket costs for biologic drugs after biosimilar competition. JAMA Health Forum. 2024;5(3):e235429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10980968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38551589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>