<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39209468</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1399-3003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The European respiratory journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur Respir J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical trial design, end-points, and emerging therapies in pulmonary arterial hypertension.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2401205</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1183/13993003.01205-2024</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Clinical trials in pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) have led to the approval of several effective treatments that improve symptoms, exercise capacity and clinical outcomes. In phase 3 clinical trials, primary end-points must reflect how a patient "feels, functions or survives". In a rare disease like PAH, with an ever-growing number of treatment options and numerous candidate therapies being studied, future clinical trials are now faced with challenges related to sample size requirements, efficiency and demonstration of incremental benefit on traditional end-points in patients receiving background therapy with multiple drugs. Novel clinical trial end-points, innovative trial designs and statistical approaches and new technologies may be potential solutions to tackle the challenges facing future PAH trials, but these must be acceptable to patients and regulatory bodies while preserving methodological rigour. In this World Symposium on Pulmonary Hypertension task force article, we address emerging trial end-points and designs, biomarkers and surrogate end-point validation, the concept of disease modification, challenges and opportunities to address diversity and representativeness, and the use of new technologies such as artificial intelligence in PAH clinical trials.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright ©The authors 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weatherald</LastName><ForeName>Jason</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0615-4575</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Division of Pulmonary Medicine, University of Alberta, Edmonton, AB, Canada weathera@ualberta.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fleming</LastName><ForeName>Thomas R</ForeName><Initials>TR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wilkins</LastName><ForeName>Martin R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3926-1171</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Heart and Lung Institute, Imperial College London, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cascino</LastName><ForeName>Thomas M</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Psotka</LastName><ForeName>Mitchell A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Inova Schar Heart and Vascular, Falls Church, VA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United States Food and Drug Administration, Silver Spring, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zamanian</LastName><ForeName>Roham</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vera Moulton Wall Center for Pulmonary Vascular Disease, Stanford University School of Medicine, Palo Alto, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seeger</LastName><ForeName>Werner</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1946-0894</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Universities of Giessen and Marburg Lung Center (UGMLC), Institute for Lung Health (ILH), Cardio-Pulmonary Institute (CPI), Member of the German Center for Lung Research (DZL), Giessen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Galiè</LastName><ForeName>Nazzareno</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiology Unit, IRCCS Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Bologna and Dipartimento DIMEC, Università di Bologna, Bologna, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gomberg-Maitland</LastName><ForeName>Mardi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Department of Medicine, George Washington University, School of Medicine, Washington, DC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Eur Respir J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8803460</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0903-1936</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Conflict of interest: J. Weatherald declares grants or contracts to their institution from Janssen, Bayer, Merck, AstraZeneca and Sanofi; consulting fees, payment or honoraria to themselves, travel support and paid membership of an Advisory Board from Janssen and Merck; payment for expert testimony from Sprigings Intellectual Property Law; unpaid membership of a Data Safety Monitoring Board drom Université Laval; and unpaid membership of the medical advisory committee of the Pulmonary Hypertension Association of Canada and the scientific medical advisory committee of the Pulmonary Vascular Research Institute. T.R. Fleming declares no competing interests. M.R. Wilkins declares grants or contracts from the British Heart Foundation (RE/18/4/34215 centre support); consulting fees from MorphogenIX (advisory committee), VIVUS (study protocol advisory meeting), Janssen and Kinaset (study advisory boards) and Chiesi, Aerami and Benevolent AI (consultancy); payment for expert testimony from Pennington Marches and Sprigings; support for travel to scientific meetings from Apollo Therapeutics; patents planned, issued or pending (Imperial Innovations: patent submitted for prognostic protein model presented in this manuscript; patent for ZIP12 as a drug target; patent for TSPO as a drug target); membership of an adjudication committee for three clinical trials for Acceleron; membership of study safety committees for GSK and Novartis; a role as a trustee of the Pulmonary Vascular Research Institute; and stock options in W12 Therapeutics. T.M. Cascino delares grants from NHLBI (K12 HL138039) and Johnson &amp; Johnson Innovative Medicine; consulting fees from and participation on a Data Safety Monitoring Board or Advisory Board for Merck; and payment or honoraria from Total CME. M.A. Psotka declares no competing interests. R. Zamanian declares grants to their institution from Gossamer Bio, Merck, United Therapeutics and Janssen; consulting fees from Gossamer Bio, Morphogen IX, Merck and Aerovate; patents planned, issued or pending for FK506 for treatment of pulmonary hypertension; participation on a Data Safety Monitoring Board or Advisory Board for Aerovate; and stock options in REVIVA. W. Seeger declares consulting fees from United Therapeutics, Abivax, Tiakis Biotech AG, Pfizer, Liquidia, Medspray BV and Pieris Pharmaceuticals. N. Galiè declares grants or contracts from Janssen, Actelion and Merck; consulting fees from Janssen, Actelion, Chiesi and Ferrer; payment or honoraria from Janssen, Actelion and Chiesi; support for attending meetings and/or travel from Dompe; and participation on a Data Safety Monitoring Board or Advisory Board from Janssen, Actelion and Ferrer. M. Gomberg-Maitland declares consulting fees from Acceleron/Merck (steering committee), Aerami (until 2023), Janssen (consultancy), JucaBio (steering committee), Keros (steering committee) and United Therapeutics (Jenesis Young Investigator Grant Chairman); support for attending the ERS Congress from Merck; participation on a Data Safety Monitoring board for Acceleron/Merck (until 2023) and Janssen (until 2023); and unpaid roles as Treasurer of ISHLT and a member of the United Therapeutics Scientific Advisory Board.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39209468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/13993003.01205-2024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">13993003.01205-2024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>