<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39204132</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1424-8247</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>17</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pharmaceuticals (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pharmaceuticals (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adverse Event Profiles of Adalimumab in Children: A Disproportionality Analysis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1028</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/ph17081028</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Adalimumab has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for the treatment of adult rheumatoid arthritis (RA), and subsequently approved for pediatric treatment of various autoimmune diseases in children of different ages. Due to genetic differences between children and adults in terms of physiology and immunity, there is a need to explore the safety of adalimumab in children in the real world. The aim of this study is to identify potential adverse event (AE) signals associated with the use of adalimumab in pediatric patients (&lt;18 years old) using data from the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">AEs associated with adalimumab in pediatric patients reported in the FAERS database from the first quarter (Q1) of 2017 to the third quarter (Q3) of 2022 were systematically gathered. Reporting odds ratio (ROR), the proportional reporting ratio (PRR), the information component (IC), and the empirical Bayes geometric mean (EBGM) were used to assess the relationship between adalimumab and AEs in children.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Out of 8,363,304 reports collected from the FAERS database during the study period, 3819 reports on children on adalimumab were identified. Adalimumab-related AEs reports were concentrated on 10 toxicity areas and a total of 202 positive signals were detected, of which injection site papule (ROR = 261.97) and intestinal fistula (ROR = 122.09) had the strongest signals. Unexpected significant AEs, including intestinal obstruction, immunodeficiency, abdominal abscess, and Takayasu's arteritis might also occur. In comparison with patients of all ages in the same time window, the median onset time of children was shorter (99 vs. 149 days). Most of the AE cases occurred in children within the first 1 (1.71%), 2 (8.12%), and 3 months (8.39%) and had early failure types after adalimumab initiation. Methotrexate, folic acid, prednisone, azathioprine, and mesalamine were the top five drugs used concomitantly for adalimumab-associated AEs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">When adalimumab is used in children, especially in the first 3 months of treatment, in addition to the AEs recorded in the drug package insert, close attention should be paid to the new potential AEs off-label to ensure the safety of adalimumab in children.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Wenting</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Tongji Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan 430030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Ziqi</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, General Hospital of Central Theater Command of Chinese People's Liberation Army, Wuhan 430060, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shu</LastName><ForeName>Yamin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Tongji Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan 430030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shu</LastName><ForeName>Sainan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatric Gastroenterology and Infection, Tongji Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, No. 1095 Jiefang Avenue, Wuhan 430030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Qilin</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4779-3875</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Union Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, No. 1277 Jiefang Avenue, Wuhan 430022, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>CPA-Z05-ZC-2023-003</GrantID><Agency>Talent Project established by Chinese Pharmaceutical Association Hospital Pharmacy department</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2023020201020501</GrantID><Agency>Dawning Program of Wuhan Knowledge Innovation Special Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>82104476</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Pharmaceuticals (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101238453</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1424-8247</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FAERS database</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adalimumab</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adverse event</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disproportionality analysis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39204132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11357133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ph17081028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ph17081028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>FDA Label for Adalimumab.  [(accessed on 18 February 2024)]; Available online:  https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2023/125057s423lbl.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leone G.M., Mangano K., Petralia M.C., Nicoletti F., Fagone P. Past, Present and (Foreseeable) Future of Biological Anti-TNF Alpha Therapy. J. Clin. Med. 2023;12:1630. doi: 10.3390/jcm12041630.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm12041630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9963154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36836166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levin A.D., Wildenberg M.E., van den Brink G.R. Mechanism of Action of Anti-TNF Therapy in Inflammatory Bowel Disease. J. Crohn’s Colitis. 2016;10:989–997. doi: 10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjw053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjw053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26896086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallis R.S. Tumour necrosis factor antagonists: Structure, function, and tuberculosis risks. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2008;8:601–611. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(08)70227-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(08)70227-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18922482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang X., Xu X., Li J., Zhao B. Cardiotoxicity in Biological Agent-Targeted Therapy for Rheumatoid Arthritis: ADR Signal Mining and Analysis of Food and Drug Administration Adverse Event Reporting System Database. Front. Pediatr. 2021;9:716648. doi: 10.3389/fped.2021.716648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fped.2021.716648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8546333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34712629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dziechciarz P., Horvath A., Kierkuś J. Efficacy and Safety of Adalimumab for Paediatric Crohn’s Disease: A Systematic Review. J. Crohn’s Colitis. 2016;10:1237–1244. doi: 10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjw077.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjw077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26995184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi S.Y., Kang B. Adalimumab in Pediatric Inflammatory Bowel Disease. Front. Pediatr. 2022;10:852580. doi: 10.3389/fped.2022.852580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fped.2022.852580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9043489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35498800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ingrasciotta Y., Spini A., L’Abbate L., Fiore E.S., Carollo M., Ientile V., Isgrò V., Cavazzana A., Biasi V., Rossi P., et al. Comparing clinical trial population representativeness to real-world users of 17 biologics approved for immune-mediated inflammatory diseases: An external validity analysis of 66,639 biologic users from the Italian VALORE project. Pharmacol. Res. 2024;200:107074. doi: 10.1016/j.phrs.2024.107074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2024.107074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38232909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M., You R., Su Y., Zhou H., Gong S. Characteristic analysis of adverse reactions of five anti-TNFɑ agents: A descriptive analysis from WHO-VigiAccess. Front. Pharmacol. 2023;14:1169327. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2023.1169327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2023.1169327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10404848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37554981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avedillo-Salas A., Corral-Cativiela S., Fanlo-Villacampa A., Vicente-Romero J. The Efficacy and Safety of Biologic Drugs in the Treatment of Moderate-Severe Crohn’s Disease: A Systematic Review. Pharmaceuticals. 2023;16:1581. doi: 10.3390/ph16111581.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ph16111581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10674451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38004446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grace E., Goldblum O., Renda L., Agada N., See K., Leonardi C., Menter A. Injection Site Reactions in the Federal Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) Post-Marketing Database Vary Among Biologics Approved to Treat Moderate-To-Severe Psoriasis. Dermatol. Ther. 2020;10:99–106. doi: 10.1007/s13555-019-00341-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13555-019-00341-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6994575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31734937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gely C., Marín L., Gordillo J., Mañosa M., Bertoletti F., Cañete F., González-Muñoza C., Calafat M., Domènech E., Garcia-Planella E. Impact of pain associated with the subcutaneous administration of adalimumab. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 2020;43:9–13. doi: 10.1016/j.gastrohep.2019.06.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gastrohep.2019.06.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31492425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman M., Aaron S., Noga M., Yacyshyn E. Takayasu’s arteritis progression on anti-TNF biologics: A case series. Clin. Rheumatol. 2011;30:703–706. doi: 10.1007/s10067-010-1658-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10067-010-1658-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21221688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eleftheriou D., Batu E.D., Ozen S., Brogan P.A. Vasculitis in children. Nephrol. Dial. Transplant. Off. Publ. Eur. Dial. Transpl. Assoc.—Eur. Ren. Assoc. 2015;30((Suppl. S1)):i94–i103. doi: 10.1093/ndt/gfu393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfu393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25550447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comarmond C., Plaisier E., Dahan K., Mirault T., Emmerich J., Amoura Z., Cacoub P., Saadoun D. Anti TNF-α in refractory Takayasu’s arteritis: Cases series and review of the literature. Autoimmun. Rev. 2012;11:678–684. doi: 10.1016/j.autrev.2011.11.025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2011.11.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22155781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Youngstein T., Peters J.E., Hamdulay S.S., Mewar D., Price-Forbes A., Lloyd M., Jeffery R., Kinderlerer A.R., Mason J.C. Serial analysis of clinical and imaging indices reveals prolonged efficacy of TNF-α and IL-6 receptor targeted therapies in refractory Takayasu arteritis. Clin. Exp. Rheumatol. 2014;32:S11–S18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24093733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souabni L., Ben Abdelghani K., Jradi S., Zakraoui L. Takayasu’s arteritis occurring under TNF-α blockers: A new paradoxical effect? BMJ Case Rep. 2014;2014:bcr2014204226. doi: 10.1136/bcr-2014-204226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bcr-2014-204226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4244516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25422327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mariani N., So A., Aubry-Rozier B. Two cases of Takayasu’s arteritis occurring under anti-TNF therapy. Jt. Bone Spine. 2013;80:211–213. doi: 10.1016/j.jbspin.2012.07.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jbspin.2012.07.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22999907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezgui A., Thabet M., Makki S., Anoun J., Hassine I.B., Karmeni M., Ben Fredj F., Mzabi A., Laouani C. Takayasu’s arteritis occurring under TNF blockers in a patient with spondyloarthritis: Is it an association or a paradoxical effect? Reumatologia. 2021;59:111–114. doi: 10.5114/reum.2021.103394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/reum.2021.103394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8103412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33976465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rojko J.L., Evans M.G., Price S.A., Han B., Waine G., DeWitte M., Haynes J., Freimark B., Martin P., Raymond J.T., et al. Formation, clearance, deposition, pathogenicity, and identification of biopharmaceutical-related immune complexes: Review and case studies. Toxicol. Pathol. 2014;42:725–764. doi: 10.1177/0192623314526475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0192623314526475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24705884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hepburn A.L., Mason J.C., Wang S., Shepherd C.J., Florey O., Haskard D.O., Davies K.A. Both Fcgamma and complement receptors mediate transfer of immune complexes from erythrocytes to human macrophages under physiological flow conditions in vitro. Clin. Exp. Immunol. 2006;146:133–145. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2249.2006.03174.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2249.2006.03174.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1809732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16968408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kavai M., Szegedi G. Immune complex clearance by monocytes and macrophages in systemic lupus erythematosus. Autoimmun. Rev. 2007;6:497–502. doi: 10.1016/j.autrev.2007.01.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2007.01.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17643939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chupin A., Perduca V., Meyer A., Bellanger C., Carbonnel F., Dong C. Systematic review with meta-analysis: Comparative risk of lymphoma with anti-tumour necrosis factor agents and/or thiopurines in patients with inflammatory bowel disease. Aliment. Pharmacol. Ther. 2020;52:1289–1297. doi: 10.1111/apt.16050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apt.16050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32840893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osterman M.T., Sandborn W.J., Colombel J.F., Robinson A.M., Lau W., Huang B., Pollack P.F., Thakkar R.B., Lewis J.D. Increased risk of malignancy with adalimumab combination therapy, compared with monotherapy, for Crohn’s disease. Gastroenterology. 2014;146:941–949. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2013.12.025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2013.12.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24361468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desai D., Jena A., Sharma V., Hibi T. Time to incorporate preemptive NUDT15 testing before starting thiopurines in inflammatory bowel disease in Asia and beyond: A review. Expert Rev. Clin. Pharmacol. 2023;16:643–653. doi: 10.1080/17512433.2023.2232300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/17512433.2023.2232300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37387532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maity T., Longo C. Pragmatic pharmacoeconomic analyses by using post-market adverse drug reaction reports: An illustration using infliximab, adalimumab, and the Canada vigilance adverse reaction database. BMC Health Serv. Res. 2021;21:1231. doi: 10.1186/s12913-021-07260-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-021-07260-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8590350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34774053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercer L.K., Galloway J.B., Lunt M., Davies R., Low A.L., Dixon W.G., Watson K.D., Symmons D.P., Hyrich K.L. Risk of lymphoma in patients exposed to antitumour necrosis factor therapy: Results from the British Society for Rheumatology Biologics Register for Rheumatoid Arthritis. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 2017;76:497–503. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2016-209389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2016-209389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5446004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27502891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>So M.W., Kim A.R., Lee S.G. Drug Persistence and Incidence of Active Tuberculosis of Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha Inhibitors Versus Tocilizumab as the First-Line Biological Treatment in Patients with Rheumatoid Arthritis: A Nationwide Population-Based Retrospective Cohort Analysis. Rheumatol. Ther. 2024;11:881–895. doi: 10.1007/s40744-024-00674-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40744-024-00674-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11265025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38769252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy N.A., Heap G.A., Green H.D., Hamilton B., Bewshea C., Walker G.J., Thomas A., Nice R., Perry M.H., Bouri S., et al. Predictors of anti-TNF treatment failure in anti-TNF-naive patients with active luminal Crohn’s disease: A prospective, multicentre, cohort study. Lancet. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 2019;4:341–353. doi: 10.1016/S2468-1253(19)30012-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(19)30012-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30824404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu Y., Ding Y., Liu Y., Wu P., He X., Zhang Q. Post-Marketing Safety Concerns with Secukinumab: A Disproportionality Analysis of the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System. Front. Pharmacol. 2022;13:862508. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2022.862508.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.862508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9214234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35754494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fusaroli M., Isgrò V., Cutroneo P.M., Ferrajolo C., Cirillo V., Del Bufalo F., Raschi E., Poluzzi E., Trifirò G. Post-Marketing Surveillance of CAR-T-Cell Therapies: Analysis of the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) Database. Drug Saf. 2022;45:891–908. doi: 10.1007/s40264-022-01194-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40264-022-01194-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9360149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35829913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu Y., Chen J., Ding Y., Zhang Q. Adverse events with risankizumab in the real world: Postmarketing pharmacovigilance assessment of the FDA adverse event reporting system. Front. Immunol. 2023;14:1169735. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1169735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1169735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10225532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37256136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu Y., Ding Y., He X., Liu Y., Wu P., Zhang Q. Hematological toxicities in PARP inhibitors: A real-world study using FDA adverse event reporting system (FAERS) database. Cancer Med. 2023;12:3365–3375. doi: 10.1002/cam4.5062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cam4.5062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9939145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35871395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Zhang X., Geng X., Shi J., Jia X., Dang S., Wang W. Risk of hepatitis B virus reactivation following treatment with abatacept: A retrospective study of international pharmacovigilance databases. EClinicalMedicine. 2022;48:101425. doi: 10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9092962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35706497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cirmi S., El Abd A., Letinier L., Navarra M., Salvo F. Cardiovascular Toxicity of Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors Used in Chronic Myeloid Leukemia: An Analysis of the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System Database (FAERS) Cancers. 2020;12:826. doi: 10.3390/cancers12040826.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cancers12040826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7226142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32235443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cutroneo P., Sartori D., Tuccori M., Crisafulli S., Battini V., Carnovale C., Rafaniello C., Capuano A., Poluzzi E., Moretti U., et al. Conducting and interpreting disproportionality analyses derived from spontaneous reporting systems. Front. Drug. Saf. Regul. 2024;3:1323057. doi: 10.3389/fdsfr.2023.1323057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fdsfr.2023.1323057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C., Wu B., Zhang C., Xu T. Immune-related adverse events associated with immune checkpoint inhibitors: An updated comprehensive disproportionality analysis of the FDA adverse event reporting system. Int. Immunopharmacol. 2021;95:107498. doi: 10.1016/j.intimp.2021.107498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2021.107498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33725634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sauzet O., Carvajal A., Escudero A., Molokhia M., Cornelius V.R. Illustration of the weibull shape parameter signal detection tool using electronic healthcare record data. Drug Saf. 2013;36:995–1006. doi: 10.1007/s40264-013-0061-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40264-013-0061-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23673816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakamura M., Umetsu R., Abe J., Matsui T., Ueda N., Kato Y., Sasaoka S., Tahara K., Takeuchi H., Kinosada Y. Analysis of the time-to-onset of osteonecrosis of jaw with bisphosphonate treatment using the data from a spontaneous reporting system of adverse drug events. J. Pharm. Health Care Sci. 2015;1:34. doi: 10.1186/s40780-015-0035-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40780-015-0035-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4728763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26819745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abe J., Umetsu R., Mataki K., Kato Y., Ueda N., Nakayama Y., Hane Y., Matsui T., Hatahira H., Sasaoka S., et al. Analysis of Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis using the Japanese Adverse Drug Event Report database. J. Pharm. Health Care Sci. 2016;2:14. doi: 10.1186/s40780-016-0048-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40780-016-0048-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4915172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27330825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>