<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39206255</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2352-7714</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>One health (Amsterdam, Netherlands)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>One Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A systematic review on global zoonotic virus-associated mortality events in marine mammals.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100872</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100872</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100872</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.onehlt.2024.100872</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Marine mammals play a critical role as sentinels for tracking the spread of zoonotic diseases, with viruses being the primary causative factor behind infectious disease induced mortality events. A systematic review was conducted to document marine mammal mortality events attributed to zoonotic viral infections in published literature across the globe. This rigorous search strategy yielded 2883 studies with 88 meeting inclusion criteria. The studies spanned from 1989 to 2023, with a peak in publications observed in 2020. Most of the included studies were retrospective, providing valuable insights into historical trends. The United States (U.S.) reported the highest number of mortality events followed by Spain, Italy, Brazil and the United Kingdom. Harbor seals were the most impacted species, particularly in regions like Anholt, Denmark and the New England Coast, U.S. Analysis revealed six main viruses responsible for mortality events, with <i>Morbillivirus</i> causing the highest proportion of deaths. Notably, the occurrence of these viral events varied geographically, with distinct patterns observed in different regions. Immunohistochemistry emerged as the most employed detection method. This study underscores the importance of global surveillance efforts in understanding and mitigating the impact of viral infections on marine mammal populations, thereby emphasizing the necessity of collaborative One Health approaches to address emerging threats at the human-animal-environment interface. Additionally, the potential transfer of zoonotic viruses to aquatic organisms used in food production, such as fish and shellfish, highlights the broader implications for food safety, food security and public health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vigil</LastName><ForeName>Katie</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Sciences, School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Huiyun</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Sciences, School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aw</LastName><ForeName>Tiong Gim</ForeName><Initials>TG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Sciences, School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>One Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101660501</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2352-7714</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Marine mammal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mortality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sentinel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Systematic review</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Zoonotic</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Tiong Gim Aw reports financial support was provided by Office of Naval Research. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39206255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11357810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2024.100872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2352-7714(24)00198-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Horefti E. The importance of the one health concept in combating zoonoses. Pathogens. 2023;12(8):977.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10460008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37623937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaheen M.N. The concept of one health applied to the problem of zoonotic diseases. Rev. Med. Virol. 2022;32(4)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35060214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milbank C., Vira B. Wildmeat consumption and zoonotic spillover: contextualising disease emergence and policy responses. Lancet Planet. Health. 2022;6(5):e439–e448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9084621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35550083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erkyihun G.A., Alemayehu M.B. One Health approach for the control of zoonotic diseases. Zoonoses. 2022;2(1):963.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones K.E., et al. Global trends in emerging infectious diseases. Nature. 2008;451(7181):990–993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5960580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18288193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tazerji S.S., et al. An overview of anthropogenic actions as drivers for emerging and re-emerging zoonotic diseases. Pathogens. 2022;11(11):1376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9692567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36422627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanderson C.E., Alexander K.A. Unchartered waters: climate change likely to intensify infectious disease outbreaks causing mass mortality events in marine mammals. Glob. Chang. Biol. 2020;26(8):4284–4301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32558115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith A.W., et al. Calicivirus emergence from ocean reservoirs: zoonotic and interspecies movements. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 1998;4(1):13–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2627659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9452394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neill J.D., Meyer R.F., Seal B.S. Genetic relatedness of the caliciviruses: San Miguel Sea lion and vesicular exanthema of swine viruses constitute a single genotype within the Caliciviridae. J. Virol. 1995;69(7):4484–4488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC189190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7769708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith A.W., et al. Vesivirus viremia and seroprevalence in humans. J. Med. Virol. 2006;78(5):693–701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7166889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16555277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waltzek T.B., et al. Marine mammal zoonoses: a review of disease manifestations. Zoonoses Public Health. 2012;59(8):521–535.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7477081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22697432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roess A.A., et al. Sealpox virus in marine mammal rehabilitation facilities, North America, 2007-2009. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2011;17(12):2203–2208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3311194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22172454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark C., et al. Human sealpox resulting from a seal bite: confirmation that sealpox virus is zoonotic. Br. J. Dermatol. 2005;152(4):791–793.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15840117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duignan P.J., et al. Phocine distemper virus: current knowledge and future directions. Viruses. 2014;6(12):5093–5134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4276944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25533658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pomeroy P., et al. Morbillivirus neutralising antibodies in Scottish grey seals Halichoerus grypus: assessing the effects of the 1988 and 2002 PDV epizootics. Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 2005;287:241–250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakai K., et al. Canine distemper virus associated with a lethal outbreak in monkeys can readily adapt to use human receptors. J. Virol. 2013;87(12):7170–7175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3676118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23596291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bieringer M., et al. Experimental adaptation of wild-type canine distemper virus (CDV) to the human entry receptor CD150. PLoS One. 2013;8(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3595274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23554862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webster R.G., et al. Characterization of an influenza a virus from seals. Virology. 1981;113(2):712–724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6267805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webster R., et al. Conjunctivitis in human beings caused by influenza a virus of seals. N. Engl. J. Med. 1981;304(15)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7207529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bossart G.D. Marine mammals as sentinel species for oceans and human health. Vet. Pathol. 2011;48(3):676–690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21160025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dierauf L., Gulland F.M. CRC Press; 2001. CRC Handbook of Marine Mammal Medicine: Health, Disease, and Rehabilitation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore K.M., Simeone C.A., Brownell R.L., Jr. Encyclopedia of Marine Mammals. Elsevier; 2018. Strandings; pp. 945–951.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osterhaus A., Vedder E. Identification of virus causing recent seal deaths. Nature. 1988;335(6185) 20-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3412456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osterhaus A., et al. The isolation and partial characterization of a highly pathogenic herpesvirus from the harbor seal (Phoca vitulina) Arch. Virol. 1985;86(3–4):239–251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4062560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross H.M., Foster G., Reid R.J., Jahans K.L., MacMillan A.P. Brucella species infection in sea-mammals. Veterinary Record (United Kingdom) 1994;134(14)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8017020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garner M.M., et al. Evidence of Brucella infection in Parafilaroides lungworms in a Pacific harbor seal (Phoca vitulina richardsi) J. Vet. Diagn. Invest. 1997;9(3):298–303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9249169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghai R.R., et al. A generalizable one health framework for the control of zoonotic diseases. Sci. Rep. 2022;12(1):8588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9124177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35597789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bossart G., Duignan P. Emerging viruses in marine mammals. CABI Rev. 2019;2018:1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Lazaro D., et al. Virus hazards from food, water and other contaminated environments. FEMS Microbiol. Rev. 2012;36(4):786–814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22091646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kibenge F.S. Emerging viruses in aquaculture. Curr. Opin. Virol. 2019;34:97–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30711892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neo J.P.S., Tan B.H. The use of animals as a surveillance tool for monitoring environmental health hazards, human health hazards and bioterrorism. Vet. Microbiol. 2017;203:40–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7130562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28619165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vigil K., Aw T.G. Comparison of de novo assembly using long-read shotgun metagenomic sequencing of viruses in fecal and serum samples from marine mammals. Front. Microbiol. 2023;14:1248323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10556685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37808316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tryland M. Zoonoses of arctic marine mammals. Infect. Disease Rev. 2000;2(2):55–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kydyrmanov A., Karamendin K. Viruses of marine mammals and metagenomic monitoring of infectious diseases. Научный журнал «Вестник НАН РК». 2019;4:147–153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page M.J., et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. Int. J. Surg. 2021;88</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33789826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulland F.M., Hall A.J. Is marine mammal health deteriorating? Trends in the global reporting of marine mammal disease. EcoHealth. 2007;4:135–150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fereidouni S., et al. Influenza virus infection of marine mammals. Ecohealth. 2016;13:161–170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25231137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simeone C.A., et al. A systematic review of changes in marine mammal health in North America, 1972-2012: the need for a novel integrated approach. PLoS One. 2015;10(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4651562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26579715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deepak D., et al. Pinniped zoonoses: a review. Int. J. Livest. Res. 2019;9(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokholm I., et al. Emergence and radiation of distemper viruses in terrestrial and marine mammals. Proc. R. Soc. B. 1961;2021(288)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8548803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34702073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jo W.K., Osterhaus A., Ludlow M. Transmission of morbilliviruses within and among marine mammal species. Curr. Opin. Virol. 2018;28:133–141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29316493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Runstadler J.A., Puryear W. 2020. A Brief Introduction to Influenza a Virus in Marine Mammals. Animal Influenza Virus: Methods and Protocols; pp. 429–450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32170708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munn C.B. Viruses as pathogens of marine organisms—from bacteria to whales. J. Mar. Biol. Assoc. U. K. 2006;86(3):453–467.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith A.W., Boyt P.M. Caliciviruses of ocean origin: a review. J. Zoo Wildl. Med. 1990:3–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burek K.A., Gulland F.M., O’Hara T.M. Effects of climate change on Arctic marine mammal health. Ecol. Appl. 2008;18(sp2):S126–S134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18494366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babineau J. Product review: Covidence (systematic review software) J. Canad. Health Librar. Assoc./J. l'Assoc. Bibliothèq. Santé du Canada. 2014;35(2):68–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta H., Kanani P., Lande P. Google maps. Int. J. Comput. Appl. 2019;178(8):41–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team, R. R Foundation for Statistical Computing; Vienna, Austria: 2021. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villanueva R.A.M., Chen Z.J. Taylor &amp; Francis; 2019. ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham H. Tidyverse: Easily install and load the ‘tidyverse’. R Package Version. 2017;1(1) 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anthony S.J., et al. Emergence of fatal avian influenza in New England harbor seals. mBio. 2012;3(4) p. e00166–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3419516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22851656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellière E.N., et al. Presence of herpesvirus in striped dolphins stranded during the cetacean morbillivirus epizootic along the Mediterranean Spanish coast in 2007. Arch. Virol. 2010;155(8):1307–1311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20495987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergman A., Järplid B., Svensson B.M. Pathological findings indicative of distemper in European seals. Vet. Microbiol. 1990;23(1–4):331–341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2402876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butina T.V., Denikina N.N., Belikov S.I. Canine distemper virus diversity in Lake Baikal seal (Phoca sibirica) population. Vet. Microbiol. 2010;144(1–2):192–197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20083361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dagleish M.P., et al. Novel dermatitis and relative viral nucleic acid tissue loads in a fin whale (Balaenoptera physalus) with systemic cetacean morbillivirus infection. J. Comp. Pathol. 2021;183:57–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33714433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frey H.R., et al. Herpesvirus in harbour seals (Phoca vitulina): isolation, partial characterization and distribution. J. Vet. Med. 1989;36(1−10):699–708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2558467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geraci J.R., et al. Mass mortality of harbor seals: pneumonia associated with influenza a virus. Science. 1982;215(4536):1129–1131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7063847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groch K.R., et al. Cetacean morbillivirus in southern right whales, Brazil. Transbound. Emerg. Dis. 2019;66(1):606–610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30365233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mamaev L.V., et al. Canine distemper virus in Lake Baikal seals (Phoca sibirica) Vet. Rec. 1996;138(18):437–439.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8735261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marutani V.H.B., et al. Systematic beach monitoring as a health assessment tool: cetacean morbillivirus under non-epizootic circumstances in stranded dolphins. Transbound. Emerg. Dis. 2022;69(4):e96–e103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34331405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philip Earle J.A., et al. Phocine distemper virus in seals, east coast, United States, 2006. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2011;17(2):215–220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3204746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21291591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio-Guerri C., et al. Unusual striped dolphin mass mortality episode related to cetacean morbillivirus in the Spanish Mediterranean Sea. BMC Vet. Res. 2013;9(1):1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3666923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23702190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soto S., et al. Post-epizootic chronic dolphin morbillivirus infection in Mediterranean striped dolphins Stenella coeruleoalba. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2011;96(3):187–194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22132497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Elk C.E., et al. Is dolphin morbillivirus virulent for white-beaked dolphins (Lagenorhynchus albirostris)? Vet. Pathol. 2014;51(6):1174–1182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24399208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesh D., et al. Detection of H3N8 influenza a virus with multiple mammalian-adaptive mutations in a rescued Grey seal (Halichoerus grypus) pup. Virus Evol. 2020;6(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7079721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32211197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashley E.A., et al. Causes of mortality in a harbor seal (Phoca vitulina) population at equilibrium. Front. Mar. Sci. 2020;7:319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter S.D., et al. Immune responses in common and grey seals during the seal epizootic. Sci. Total Environ. 1992;115(1–2):83–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1594937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fauquier D.A., et al. Evaluation of morbillivirus exposure in cetaceans from the northern Gulf of Mexico 2010-2014. Endanger. Species Res. 2017;33:211–220.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Have P., Nielsen J., Botner A. The Seal death in Danish waters 1988. Acta Vet. Scand. 1991;32(2):211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8127889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1803934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sierra E., et al. Molecular characterization of Herpesviral encephalitis in cetaceans: correlation with histopathological and Immunohistochemical findings. Animals. 2022;12(9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9105563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35565575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felipe-Jiménez I., et al. Molecular diagnosis of cetacean morbillivirus in beaked whales stranded in the Canary Islands (1999–2017) Veterin. Sci. 2022;9(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8950905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35324849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Mello Zanim Michelazzo M., et al. Canine distemper virus and canine adenovirus type-2 infections in neotropical otters (Lontra longicaudis) from southern Brazil. Braz. J. Microbiol. 2022;53(1):369–375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8882751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34709597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giorda F., et al. Neuropathological characterization of dolphin morbillivirus infection in cetaceans stranded in Italy. Animals. 2022;12(4)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8868427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35203160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas-Castro I., et al. Systematic determination of herpesvirus in free-ranging cetaceans stranded in the western mediterranean: tissue tropism and associated lesions. Viruses. 2021;13(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8621769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34834986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunha H.A., et al. Epidemiological features of the first unusual mortality event linked to cetacean morbillivirus in the South Atlantic (Brazil, 2017–2018) Mar. Mamm. Sci. 2021;37(4):1375–1390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burek Huntington K.A., et al. Causes of mortality of northern sea otters (Enhydra lutris kenyoni) in Alaska from 2002 to 2012. Front. Mar. Sci. 2021;8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wessels M.E., et al. Novel presentation of DMV-associated encephalitis in a long-finned pilot whale (Globicephala melas) J. Comp. Pathol. 2021;183:51–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33714432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puryear W., et al. Longitudinal analysis of pinnipeds in the northwest Atlantic provides insights on endemic circulation of phocine distemper virus. Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci. 2021;288(1962)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8580419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34753354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuvertoret-Sanz M., et al. Causes of cetacean stranding and death on the Catalonian coast (western Mediterranean Sea), 2012-2019. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2020;142:239–253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33331291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerutti F., et al. Specific capture and whole-genome phylogeography of dolphin morbillivirus. Sci. Rep. 2020;10(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7704663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33257791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groch K.R., et al. The pathology of cetacean morbillivirus infection and comorbidities in Guiana dolphins during an unusual mortality event (Brazil, 2017–2018) Vet. Pathol. 2020;57(6):845–857.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32964811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas N., et al. Canine distemper virus in the sea otter (Enhydra lutris) population in Washington state, USA. J. Wildl. Dis. 2020;56(4):873–883.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32609600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas-Castro I., et al. Alpha- and gammaherpesviruses in stranded striped dolphins (Stenella coeruleoalba) from Spain: first molecular detection of gammaherpesvirus infection in central nervous system of odontocetes. BMC Vet. Res. 2020;16(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7425534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32787898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamel P.E.S., et al. postmortem computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging findings in a case of coinfection of dolphin morbillivirus and Aspergillus fumigatus in a juvenile bottlenose dolphin (Tursiops truncatus) J. Zoo Wildl. Med. 2020;51(2):448–454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32549578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schick L., et al. Pathological findings in white-beaked dolphins (Lagenorhynchus albirostris) and Atlantic white-sided dolphins (Lagenorhynchus acutus) from the south-eastern North Sea. Front. Veterin. Sci. 2020:7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7326107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32671103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mira F., et al. Circulation of a novel strain of dolphin morbillivirus (DMV) in stranded cetaceans in the Mediterranean Sea. Sci. Rep. 2019;9(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6611785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31278350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pautasso A., et al. Novel dolphin morbillivirus (DMV) outbreak among Mediterranean striped dolphins Stenella coeruleoalba in Italian waters. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2019;132(3):215–220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31188137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin D.L., et al. Highly pathogenic avian influenza a(H5N8) virus in gray seals, Baltic Sea. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2019;25(12):2295–2298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6874272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31742519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banlunara W., et al. Epizootic of multi-centric, squamous cell carcinomas in populations of indo-Pacific humpbacked dolphins Sousa chinensis in Thai waters. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2019;134(2):99–106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31043577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flach L., et al. Clinical signs in free-ranging Guiana dolphins Sotalia guianensis during a morbillivirus epidemic: Case study in Sepetiba Bay, Brazil. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2019;133(3):175–180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31019130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokholm I., et al. Phylogenomic insights to the origin and spread of phocine distemper virus in European harbour seals in 1988 and 2002. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2019;133(1):47–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31089002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bento M.C., et al. Herpesvirus infection in marine mammals: a retrospective molecular survey of stranded cetaceans in the Portuguese coastline. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2019;67:222–233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30445114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Díaz-Delgado J., et al. Pathologic findings and causes of death of stranded cetaceans in the Canary Islands (2006-2012) PLoS One. 2018;13(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6173391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30289951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio-Guerri C., et al. Genetic heterogeneity of dolphin morbilliviruses detected in the Spanish Mediterranean in inter-epizootic period. BMC Vet. Res. 2018;14(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6109331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30143035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sierra E., et al. Morbillivirus infection in Risso’s dolphin Grampus griseus: a phylogenetic and pathological study of cases from the Canary Islands. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2018;129(3):165–174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30154276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groch K.R., et al. Guiana dolphin unusual mortality event and link to cetacean morbillivirus, Brazil. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2018;24(7):1349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6038766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29912687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giorda F., et al. Postmortem findings in cetaceans found stranded in the pelagos sanctuary, Italy, 2007–14. J. Wildl. Dis. 2017;53(4):795–803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28475451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denkinger J., et al. Pup mortality and evidence for pathogen exposure in Galapagos Sea lions (Zalophus wollebaeki) on San Cristobal island, Galapagos, Ecuador. J. Wildl. Dis. 2017;53(3):491–498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28318380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beffagna G., et al. Genomic and structural investigation on dolphin morbillivirus (DMV) in Mediterranean fin whales (Balaenoptera physalus) Sci. Rep. 2017:7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5278511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28134317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kemper C., et al. Morbillivirus-associated unusual mortality event in south Australian bottlenose dolphins is largest reported for the southern hemisphere. R. Soc. Open Sci. 2016;3(12)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5210697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28083115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassle S.E., et al. Coinfection by cetacean morbillivirus and Aspergillus fumigatus in a juvenile bottlenose dolphin (Tursiops truncatus) in the Gulf of Mexico. J. Vet. Diagn. Invest. 2016;28(6):729–734.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27698174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bento M.C.R.M., et al. New insight into dolphin morbillivirus phylogeny and epidemiology in the Northeast Atlantic: opportunistic study in cetaceans stranded along the Portuguese and Galician coasts. BMC Vet. Res. 2016;12(1):1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5002201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27566667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacob J.M., et al. Initial characterization of novel beaked whale morbillivirus in Hawaiian cetaceans. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2016;117(3):215–227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26758655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sierra E., et al. Fatal systemic morbillivirus infection in bottlenose dolphin, Canary Islands, Spain. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2014;20(2):269–271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3901504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24447792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casalone C., et al. Cetacean strandings in Italy: an unusual mortality event along the Tyrrhenian Sea coast in 2013. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2014;109(1):81–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24781797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stephens N., et al. Cetacean morbillivirus in coastal indo-pacific bottlenose dolphins, Western Australia. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2014;20(4):666–670.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3966363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24656203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodewes R., et al. Novel B19-like parvovirus in the brain of a harbor seal. PLoS One. 2013;8(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3818428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24223918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arbelo M., et al. Pathology and causes of death of stranded cetaceans in the canary islands (1999-2005) Dis. Aquat. Org. 2013;103(2):87–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23548359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio-Guerri C., et al. Simultaneous diagnosis of cetacean morbillivirus infection in dolphins stranded in the Spanish Mediterranean Sea in 2011 using a novel universal probe library (UPL) RT-PCR assay. Vet. Microbiol. 2013;165(1–2):109–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23380457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzariol S., et al. Dolphin morbillivirus infection in a captive harbor seal (phoca vitulina) J. Clin. Microbiol. 2013;51(2):708–711.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3553930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23224101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Guardo G., et al. Morbillivirus infection in cetaceans stranded along the Italian coastline: pathological, immunohistochemical and biomolecular findings. Res. Vet. Sci. 2013;94(1):132–137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22921372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzariol S., et al. Dolphin morbillivirus and toxoplasma gondii coinfection in a Mediterranean fin whale (Balaenoptera physalus) BMC Vet. Res. 2012;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3319419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22397492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone B.M., et al. Fatal cetacean morbillivirus infection in an Australian offshore bottlenose dolphin (Tursiops truncatus) Aust. Vet. J. 2011;89(11):452–457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22008125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng T.F.F., et al. Metagenomic identification of a novel anellovirus in Pacific harbor seal (Phoca vitulina richardsii) lung samples and its detection in samples from multiple yearsa. J. Gen. Virol. 2011;92(6):1318–1323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21402596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyoshi K., et al. Molecular identification of novel alpha- and gammaherpesviruses from cetaceans stranded on japanese coasts. Zool. Sci. 2011;28(2):126–133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21303205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keck N., et al. Resurgence of morbillivirus infection in mediterranean dolphins off the french coast. Vet. Rec. 2010;166(21):654–655.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20495168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng T.F.F., et al. Novel anellovirus discovered from a mortality event of captive California Sea lions. J. Gen. Virol. 2009;90(5):1256–1261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19264590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang W.C., et al. Morbilliviral infection in a pygmy sperm whale (Kogia breviceps) from Taiwanese waters. Vet. Microbiol. 2006;116(1–3):69–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16644147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuiken T., et al. The 2000 canine distemper epidemic in Caspian seals (Phoca caspica): pathology and analysis of contributory factors. Vet. Pathol. 2006;43(3):321–338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16672579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King D.P., et al. Humoral immune responses to phocine herpesvirus-1 in Pacific harbor seals (Phoca vitulina richardsii) during an outbreak of clinical disease. Vet. Microbiol. 2001;80(1):1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11278118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van De Bildt M.W.G., et al. Morbillivirus infection in a bottlenosed dolphin and a Mediterranean monk seal from the Atlantic coast of West Africa. Vet. Rec. 2001;148(7):210–211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11266000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taubenberger J.K., et al. Molecular genetic evidence of a novel morbillivirus in a long-finned pilot whale (Globicephalus melas) Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2000;6(1):42–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2627976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10653568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birkun A., Jr., et al. Epizootic of morbilliviral disease in common dolphins (Delphinus delphis ponticus) from the Black Sea. Vet. Rec. 1999;144(4):85–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10097312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schulman F.Y., et al. Histologic, Immunohistochemical, and polymerase chain reaction studies of bottlenose dolphins from the 1987-1988 United States Atlantic Coast epizootic. Vet. Pathol. 1997;34(4):288–295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9240837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taubenberger J.K., et al. Two morbilliviruses implicated in bottlenose dolphin epizootics. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 1996;2(3):213–216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2626800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8903232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lipscomb T.P., et al. Morbilliviral epizootic in bottlenose dolphins of the Gulf of Mexico. J. Vet. Diagn. Invest. 1996;8(3):283–290.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8844569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duignan P.J., et al. Morbillivirus infection in bottlenose dolphins: evidence for recurrent epizootics in the western Atlantic and Gulf of Mexico. Mar. Mamm. Sci. 1996;12(4):499–515.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domingo M., et al. Evidence for chronic morbillivirus infection in the Mediterranean striped dolphin (Stenella coeruleoalba) Vet. Microbiol. 1995;44(2–4):229–239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8588317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duignan P.J., et al. Morbillivirus infection in cetaceans of the western Atlantic. Vet. Microbiol. 1995;44(2–4):241–249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8588318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolt G., Blixenkrone-Møller M. Nucleic acid hybridization analyses confirm the presence of a hitherto unknown morbillivirus in mediterranean dolphins. Vet. Microbiol. 1994;41(4):363–372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7801536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Bressem M.F., et al. Dolphin morbillivirus infection in different parts of the Mediterranean Sea. Arch. Virol. 1993;129:235–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8470952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy S., et al. Histological, histochemical and ultrastructural features of hyaline inclusions in hepatocytes of striped dolphins (Stenella coeruleoalba) J. Comp. Pathol. 1993;109(2):179–185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7504003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy S., et al. Histopathologic and Immunocytochemical studies of distemper in harbor porpoises. Vet. Pathol. 1991;28(1):1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2017822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy S., et al. Histopathologic and Immunocytochemical studies of distemper in seals. Vet. Pathol. 1989;26(2):97–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2652873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas-Castro I., et al. Epidemiological and genetic analysis of cetacean morbillivirus circulating on the Italian coast between 2018 and 2021. Front. Veterin. Sci. 2023:10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10424449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37583469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leguia M., et al. Highly pathogenic avian influenza A (H5N1) in marine mammals and seabirds in Peru. Nat. Commun. 2023;14(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10484921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37679333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morick D., et al. First description of a Gammaherpesvirus in a common dolphin (Delphinus delphis) from the Eastern Mediterranean Sea. Veterinary research communications. 2023;47(4):2253–2258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37088865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomo I., Kemper C.M. Strandings in St Vincent gulf bioregion, South Australia: 12-year study monitors biology and pathology of cetaceans. Oceans. 2022;3(4):439–463.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byrne A.M., et al. H7N7 avian influenza virus mutation from low to high pathogenicity on a layer chicken farm in the UK. Viruses. 2021;13(2):259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7914596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33567525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan D.K., Tsui H.C., Kot B.C. Database documentation of marine mammal stranding and mortality: current status review and future prospects. Dis. Aquat. Org. 2017;126(3):247–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29160222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Hernández G., et al. From beach users to first responders: the role of civil society in response actions to marine mammal stranding events. Ocean Coast. Manag. 2022;219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahri A., et al. A critical review of marine mammal governance and protection in Indonesia. Mar. Policy. 2020;117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teilmann J., Galatius A. Encyclopedia of Marine Mammals. Elsevier; 2018. Harbor seal: Phoca vitulina; pp. 451–455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>London J.M., et al. Haul-out behavior of harbor seals (Phoca vitulina) in Hood Canal, Washington. PLoS One. 2012;7(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3377645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22723851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Himworth C., et al. Pathology and epidemiology of phocid herpesvirus-1 in wild and rehabilitating harbor seals (Phoca vitulina richardsi) in the northeastern Pacific. J. Wildl. Dis. 2010;46(3):1046–1051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20688721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cosby S., et al. 1989. Characterization of a Seal Morbillivirus.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavigne D.M., Schmitz O.J. Global warming and increasing population densities: a prescription for seal plagues. Mar. Pollut. Bull. 1990;21(6):280–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heide-Jørgensen M., et al. Retrospective of the 1988 European seal epizootic. Dis. Aquat. Org. 1992;13:37–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofer H., East M.L. Biological conservation and stress. Adv. Study Behav. 1998;27:405–526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisset A.T., Hoyne G.F. An outbreak of highly pathogenic avian influenza (H7N7) in Australia and the potential for novel influenza a viruses to emerge. Microorganisms. 2021;9(8):1639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8401172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34442718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koopmans M., et al. Transmission of H7N7 avian influenza a virus to human beings during a large outbreak in commercial poultry farms in the Netherlands. Lancet. 2004;363(9409):587–593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14987882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piña R., et al. Ten approaches that improve immunostaining: a review of the latest advances for the optimization of immunofluorescence. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2022;23(3):1426.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8836139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35163349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alavandi S., Poornima M. Viral metagenomics: a tool for virus discovery and diversity in aquaculture. Indian J. Virol. 2012;23:88–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3550753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23997432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munang’andu H.M. Environmental viral metagenomics analyses in aquaculture: applications in epidemiology and disease control. Front. Microbiol. 2016;7:1986.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5155513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28018317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagadeesan B., et al. The use of next generation sequencing for improving food safety: translation into practice. Food Microbiol. 2019;79:96–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6492263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30621881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>