<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39207239</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1941-2703</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of aerosol medicine and pulmonary drug delivery</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Aerosol Med Pulm Drug Deliv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of Systemic Exposure Between Epinephrine Delivered via Metered-Dose Inhalation and Intramuscular Injection.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1089/jamp.2024.0025</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><b><i>Background:</i></b> Primatene<sup>®</sup> MIST, an epinephrine metered-dose inhaler (MDI), has long been questioned by some medical professionals for asthma treatment despite having been approved by the Food and Drug Administration. One of the primary reasons for their concerns stemmed from potential cardiovascular complications following epinephrine administration. However, the majority of documented cardiovascular complications seemed to occur following the injection route of the epinephrine. The aim of this study was to evaluate the systemic exposure of epinephrine delivered through different administration routes and to understand its relationship with cardiovascular effects. Since albuterol inhalers are commonly recommended for asthma, albuterol was also studied as a comparator drug. <b><i>Method:</i></b> A randomized, evaluator-blinded, three-arm crossover study was conducted in 28 healthy adult subjects to compare the profiles of systemic exposure for epinephrine delivered by MDI versus epinephrine intramuscular (IM) injection and albuterol MDI. Serially sampled plasma epinephrine and albuterol levels were measured and compared between treatment groups. Safety was assessed by adverse events, serial vital signs, electrocardiograms (ECGs), and clinical laboratory tests obtained at each crossover dosing visit. <b><i>Results:</i></b> Systemic exogenous drug exposure for inhaled epinephrine MDI (39 pg/mL × hour) was ∼9 times lower than that of epinephrine IM (435 pg/mL × hour) and 122 times lower than that of albuterol MDI (3453 pg/mL × hour) after dose normalization. The C<sub>max</sub> in epinephrine MDI (345 pg/mL) was approximately half of that of epinephrine IM (816 pg/mL) and that of albuterol MDI (681 pg/mL). Plasma drug concentrations for epinephrine MDI dropped rapidly to baseline (∼0.6 hour), while epinephrine IM took ∼8 hours, and albuterol MDI required more than 24 hours. Epinephrine MDI and albuterol MDI resulted in minimal, clinically insignificant changes in vital signs and ECGs, whereas epinephrine IM led to mild transient increases in systolic blood pressure, heart rate, and corrected QT interval. <b><i>Conclusion:</i></b> Epinephrine MDI (Primatene MIST) had ∼9 times lower systemic drug exposure (SDE) than that of epinephrine IM and ∼122 times lower than that of albuterol MDI. The lower SDE of inhaled epinephrine also correlated with reassuring safety findings, with no significant cardiovascular adverse effects found, compared with transient effects seen after IM epinephrine. <b>Clinical trial registration number:</b> NCT04207840.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Jack Yongfeng</ForeName><Initials>JY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2524-5074</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amphastar Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Rancho Cucamonga, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Mary Ziping</ForeName><Initials>MZ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amphastar Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Rancho Cucamonga, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marrs</LastName><ForeName>Tony</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amphastar Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Rancho Cucamonga, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kerwin</LastName><ForeName>Edward M</ForeName><Initials>EM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Research Institute and Allergy &amp; Asthma Center, Medford, Oregon, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bukstein</LastName><ForeName>Don A</ForeName><Initials>DA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Allergy, Asthma, and Sinus Center, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT04207840</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Aerosol Med Pulm Drug Deliv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101475057</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1941-2711</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">albuterol</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">asthma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epinephrine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intramuscular injection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metered-dose inhaler</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">systemic exposure</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39207239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jamp.2024.0025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>