<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39206816</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1552-8618</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental toxicology and chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Toxicol Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>AOP Report: An Upstream Network for Reduced Androgen Signaling Leading to Altered Gene Expression of Androgen Receptor-Responsive Genes in Target Tissues.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/etc.5972</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Adverse outcome pathways (AOPs) can aid with chemical risk assessment by providing plausible links between chemical activity at the molecular level and effect outcomes in intact organisms. Because AOPs can be used to infer causality between upstream and downstream events in toxicological pathways, the AOP framework can also facilitate increased uptake of alternative methods and new approach methodologies to help inform hazard identification. However, a prevailing challenge is the limited number of fully developed and endorsed AOPs, primarily due to the substantial amount of work required by AOP developers and reviewers. Consequently, a more pragmatic approach to AOP development has been proposed where smaller units of knowledge are developed and reviewed independent of full AOPs. In this context, we have developed an upstream network comprising key events (KEs) and KE relationships related to decreased androgen signaling, converging at a nodal KE that can branch out to numerous adverse outcomes (AOs) relevant to androgen-sensitive toxicological pathways. Androgen signaling represents an extensively studied pathway for endocrine disruption. It is linked to numerous disease outcomes and can be affected by many different endocrine-disrupting chemicals. Still, pathways related to disrupted androgen signaling remain underrepresented in the AOP-wiki, and endorsed AOPs are lacking. Given the pivotal role of androgen signaling in development and function across vertebrate taxa and life stages of both sexes, this upstream AOP network serves as a foundational element for developing numerous AOPs. By connecting the upstream network with various downstream AOs, encompassing different species, it can also facilitate cross-species extrapolations for hazard and risk assessment of chemicals. Environ Toxicol Chem 2024;00:1-9. © 2024 The Author(s). Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of SETAC.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of SETAC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Draskau</LastName><ForeName>Monica K</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rosenmai</LastName><ForeName>Anna K</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bouftas</LastName><ForeName>Nora</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Environmental Health and Toxicology, Amsterdam Institute for Life and Environment, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johansson</LastName><ForeName>Hanna K L</ForeName><Initials>HKL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Panagiotou</LastName><ForeName>Eleftheria M</ForeName><Initials>EM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8115-9894</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Department of Clinical Science, Intervention and Technology, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gynecology and Reproductive Medicine, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Holmer</LastName><ForeName>Marie L</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elmelund</LastName><ForeName>Emilie</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zilliacus</LastName><ForeName>Johanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Environmental Medicine, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beronius</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Environmental Medicine, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Damdimopolou</LastName><ForeName>Pauliina</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Department of Clinical Science, Intervention and Technology, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gynecology and Reproductive Medicine, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Duursen</LastName><ForeName>Majorie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Environmental Health and Toxicology, Amsterdam Institute for Life and Environment, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Svingen</LastName><ForeName>Terje</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4650-7651</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>GP/EFSA/PREV/2022/01</GrantID><Agency>European Food Safety Authority</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2020-01621</GrantID><Agency>Svenska Forskningsrådet Formas</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Miljøstyrelsen</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Toxicol Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8308958</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0730-7268</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adverse outcome pathway</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Androgen signaling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anti‐androgens</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Endocrine disruptors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reproductive toxicology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Risk assessment</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39206816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/etc.5972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Aggarwal, S., Thareja, S., Verma, A., Bhardwaj, T. R., &amp; Kumar, M. (2010). An overview on 5α‐reductase inhibitors. Steroids, 75, 109–153. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.steroids.2009.10.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennesch, M. A., &amp; Picard, D. (2015). Minireview: Tipping the balance: Ligand‐independent activation of steroid receptors. Molecular Endocrinology, 29, 349–363. https://doi.org/10.1210/ME.2014-1315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergman, Å., Heindel, J. J., Jobling, S., Kidd, K. A., &amp; Zoeller, R. T. (Eds.). (2013). State of the science of endocrine disrupting chemicals. World Health Organization, United Nations Environment Programme, Inter‐Organization Programme for the Sound Management of Chemicals. https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/78101</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowman, C. J., Barlow, N. J., Turner, K. J., Wallace, D. G., &amp; Foster, P. M. D. (2003). Effects of in utero exposure to finasteride on androgen‐dependent reproductive development in the male rat. Toxicological Sciences, 74, 393–406. https://doi.org/10.1093/TOXSCI/KFG128</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campana, C., Pezzi, V., &amp; Rainey, W. E. (2015). Cell‐based assays for screening androgen receptor ligands. Seminars in Reproductive Medicine, 33, 225–234. https://doi.org/10.1055/S-0035-1552989</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y., Zhou, Q., Hankey, W., Fang, X., &amp; Yuan, F. (2022). Second generation androgen receptor antagonists and challenges in prostate cancer treatment. Cell Death &amp; Disease, 13(7), Article 632. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41419-022-05084-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damstra, T., Barlow, S., Bergman, A., Kavlock, R., &amp; Van der Kraak, G. (Eds.). (2002). Global assessment of the state‐of‐the‐science of endocrine disruptors (WHO/PCS/EDC/02.2). World Health Organization/International Programme on Chemical Safety. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-PSC-EDC-02.2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davey, R. A., &amp; Grossmann, M. (2016). Androgen receptor structure, function and biology: From bench to bedside. The Clinical Biochemist, 37, 3–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Vries, R., Angrish, M., Browne, P., Brozek, J., Rooney, A. A., Wikoff, D. S., Whaley, P., Edwards, S. W., Morgan, R. L., Druwe, I. L., Hoffmann, S., Hartung, T., Thayer, K., Avey, M. T., Beverly, B., Falavigna, M., Gibbons, C., Goyak, K., Kraft, A., … Tsaioun, K. (2021). Applying evidence‐based methods to the development and use of adverse outcome pathways. ALTEX, 38, 336–347. https://doi.org/10.14573/ALTEX.2101211</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Draskau, M. K., &amp; Svingen, T. (2022). Azole fungicides and their endocrine disrupting properties: Perspectives on sex hormone‐dependent reproductive development. Frontiers in Toxicology, 4, Article 883254. https://doi.org/10.3389/FTOX.2022.883254</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eder, I. E., Culig, Z., Putz, T., Nessler‐Menardi, C., Bartsch, G., &amp; Klocker, H. (2001). Molecular biology of the androgen receptor: From molecular understanding to the clinic. European Urology, 40, 241–251. https://doi.org/10.1159/000049782</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. (2006). Regulation (EC) 1907/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 December 2006 concerning the registration, evaluation, authorisation and restriction of chemicals (REACH), establishing a European Chemicals Agency, amending Directive 1999/45/EC and repealing Council Regulation (EEC) 793/93 and Commission Regulation (EC) No. 1488/94 as well as Council Directive 76/769/EEC and Commission Directives 91/155/EEC, 93/67/EEC, 93/105/EC and 2000/21/EC. Official Journal of the European Union, L396, 374–375.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. (2017). Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2017/2100 of 4 September 2017 setting out scientific criteria for the determination of endocrine‐disrupting properties pursuant to Regulation (EU) No 528/2012 of the European Parliament and Council. Official Journal of the European Union, L301, 1–5. https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/?uri=CELEX:32017R2100</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. (2018). Commission Regulation (EU) 2018/605 of 19 April 2018 amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 by setting out scientific criteria for the determination of endocrine disrupting properties. Official Journal of the European Union, L101, 33–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. (2023a). Commission Regulation (EU) 2023/707 of 19 December 2022 amending Regulation (EC) No 1272/2008 as regards hazard classes and criteria for the classification, labelling and packaging of substances and mixtures. Official Journal of the European Union, L93, 7–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission. (2023b). Regulation (EC) No 1272/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on classification, labelling and packaging of substances and mixtures, amending and repealing, Directives 67/548/EEC and 1999/45/EC, and amending Regulation (EC) No 1907/2006. Official Journal of the European Union, L353, 1–1550. https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/?uri=CELEX:02008R1272-20230420&amp;qid=1687765115474</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, W., Bohl, C. E., &amp; Dalton, J. T. (2005). Chemistry and structural biology of androgen receptor. Chemical Reviews, 105, 3352–3370. https://doi.org/10.1021/cr020456u</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaudriault, P., Mazaud‐Guittot, S., Lavoué, V., Coiffec, I., Lesné, L., Dejucq‐Rainsford, N., Scholze, M., Kortenkamp, A., &amp; Jégou, B. (2017). Endocrine disruption in human fetal testis explants by individual and combined exposures to selected pharmaceuticals, pesticides, and environmental pollutants. Environmental Health Perspectives, 125, Article 087004. https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP1014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerald, T., &amp; Raj, G. (2022). Testosterone and the androgen receptor. Urologic Clinics of North America, 49, 603–614. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.UCL.2022.07.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grino, P. B., Griffin, J. E., &amp; Wilson, J. D. (1990). Testosterone at high concentrations interacts with the human androgen receptor similarly to dihydrotestosterone. Endocrinology, 126, 1165–1172. https://doi.org/10.1210/endo-126-2-1165</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinlein, C. A., &amp; Chang, C. (2002). Androgen receptor (AR) coregulators: An overview. Endocrine Reviews, 23, 175–200. https://doi.org/10.1210/EDRV.23.2.0460</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, S. H., Hong, K. Y., Seo, H., Lee, H. S., &amp; Park, Y. (2021). Mechanistic insight into human androgen receptor–mediated endocrine‐disrupting potentials by a stable bioluminescence resonance energy transfer–based dimerization assay. Chemico‐Biological Interactions, 349, Article 109655. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.CBI.2021.109655</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung, C. M., de Haan, P., Ronaldson‐Bouchard, K., Kim, G. A., Ko, J., Rho, H. S., Chen, Z., Habibovic, P., Jeon, N. L., Takayama, S., Shuler, M. L., Vunjak‐Novakovic, G., Frey, O., Verpoorte, E., &amp; Toh, Y. C. (2022). A guide to the organ‐on‐a‐chip. Nature Reviews Methods Primers, 2, 1–29. https://doi.org/10.1038/s43586-022-00118-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo, S., King, I., Alléra, A., &amp; Klingmüller, D. (2007). Effects of various pesticides on human 5α‐reductase activity in prostate and LNCaP cells. Toxicology In Vitro, 21, 502–508. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TIV.2006.10.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marks, L. S. (2004). 5Alpha‐reductase: History and clinical importance. Reviews in Urology, 6(S9), S11–S21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naamneh Elzenaty, R., duToit, T., &amp; Flück, C. E. (2022). Basics of androgen synthesis and action. Best Practice &amp; Research Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism, 36, Article 101665. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.BEEM.2022.101665</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nef, S., &amp; Parada, L. F. (2000). Hormones in male sexual development. Genes and Development, 14, 3075–3086. https://doi.org/10.1101/GAD.843800</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogino, Y., Ansai, S., Watanabe, E., Yasugi, M., Katayama, Y., Sakamoto, H., Okamoto, K., Okubo, K., Yamamoto, Y., Hara, I., Yamazaki, T., Kato, A., Kamei, Y., Naruse, K., Ohta, K., Ogino, H., Sakamoto, T., Miyagawa, S., Sato, T., … Iguchi, T. (2023). Evolutionary differentiation of androgen receptor is responsible for sexual characteristic development in a teleost fish. Nature Communications, 14, Article 1428. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-37026-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogino, Y., Hirakawa, I., Inohaya, K., Sumiya, E., Miyagawa, S., Denslow, N., Yamada, G., Tatarazako, N., &amp; Iguchi, T. (2014). Bmp7 and Lef1 are the downstream effectors of androgen signaling in androgen‐induced sex characteristics development in medaka. Endocrinology, 155, 449–462. https://doi.org/10.1210/EN.2013-1507</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogino, Y., Miyagawa, S., Katoh, H., Prins, G. S., Iguchi, T., &amp; Yamada, G. (2011). Essential functions of androgen signaling emerged through the developmental analysis of vertebrate sex characteristics. Evolution &amp; Development, 13, 315–325. https://doi.org/10.1111/J.1525-142X.2011.00482.X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development. (2017). Revised guidance document on developing and assessing adverse outcome pathways (Series on Testing and Assessment, No. 184; ENV/JM/MONO[2013]6).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development. (2020). Test No. 458: Stably transfected human androgen receptor transcriptional activation assay for detection of androgenic agonist and antagonist activity of chemicals. OECD guidelines for the testing of chemicals. https://doi.org/10.1787/9789264264366-en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development. (2021). Guidance document for the scientific review of adverse outcome pathways (Series on Testing and Assessment, No. 344; ENV/CBC/MONO[2021]22). https://www.oecd.org/chemicalsafety/testing/series-testing-assessment-publicationsnumber.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development. (2022). Test No. 251: Rapid androgen disruption activity reporter (RADAR) assay. OECD guidelines for the testing of chemicals. https://doi.org/10.1787/da264d82-en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orton, F., Rosivatz, E., Scholze, M., &amp; Kortenkamp, A. (2011). Widely used pesticides with previously unknown endocrine activity revealed as in vitro antiandrogens. Environmental Health Perspectives, 119, 794–800. https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.1002895</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panagiotou, E. M., Draskau, M. K., Li, T., Hirschberg, A., Svingen, T., &amp; Damdimopoulou, P. (2022). AOP key event relationship report: Linking decreased androgen receptor activation with decreased granulosa cell proliferation of gonadotropin‐independent follicles. Reproductive Toxicology, 112, 136–147. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.REPROTOX.2022.07.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen, E. B., Christiansen, S., &amp; Svingen, T. (2022). AOP key event relationship report: Linking androgen receptor antagonism with nipple retention. Current Research in Toxicology, 3, Article 100085. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.CRTOX.2022.100085</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prizant, H., Gleicher, N., &amp; Sen, A. (2014). Androgen actions in the ovary: Balance is key. Journal of Endocrinology, 222, R141–R151. https://doi.org/10.1530/JOE-14-0296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rana, K., Davey, R. A., &amp; Zajac, J. D. (2014). Human androgen deficiency: Insights gained from androgen receptor knockout mouse models. Asian Journal of Andrology, 16, 169–177. https://doi.org/10.4103/1008-682X.122590</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Renfree, M. B., &amp; Shaw, G. (2023). The alternate pathway of androgen metabolism and window of sensitivity. Journal of Endocrinology, 258(3), Article e220296. https://doi.org/10.1530/JOE-22-0296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robitaille, J., &amp; Langlois, V. S. (2020). Consequences of steroid‐5α‐reductase deficiency and inhibition in vertebrates. General and Comparative Endocrinology, 290, Article 113400. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygcen.2020.113400</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuppe, E. R., Miles, M. C., &amp; Fuxjager, M. J. (2020). Evolution of the androgen receptor: Perspectives from human health to dancing birds. Molecular and Cellular Endocrinology, 499, Article 110577. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.MCE.2019.110577</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz, C. L., Christiansen, S., Vinggaard, A. M., Axelstad, M., Hass, U., &amp; Svingen, T. (2019). Anogenital distance as a toxicological or clinical marker for fetal androgen action and risk for reproductive disorders. Archives of Toxicology, 93, 253–272. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00204-018-2350-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz, C. L., Vinggaard, A. M., Christiansen, S., Darde, T. A., Chalmel, F., &amp; Svingen, T. (2019). Distinct transcriptional profiles of the female, male, and finasteride‐induced feminized male anogenital region in rat fetuses. Toxicological Sciences, 169, 303–311. https://doi.org/10.1093/toxsci/kfz046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sébillot, A., Damdimopoulou, P., Ogino, Y., Spirhanzlova, P., Miyagawa, S., Du Pasquier, D., Mouatassim, N., Iguchi, T., Lemkine, G. F., Demeneix, B. A., &amp; Tindall, A. J. (2014). Rapid fluorescent detection of (anti)androgens with spiggin‐gfp medaka. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 48, 10919–10928. https://doi.org/10.1021/ES5030977</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skakkebaek, N. E., Rajpert‐De Meyts, E., Buck Louis, G. M., Toppari, J., Andersson, A.‐M., Eisenberg, M. L., Jensen, T. K., Jørgensen, N., Swan, S. H., Sapra, K. J., Ziebe, S., Priskorn, L., &amp; Juul, A. (2016). Male reproductive disorders and fertility trends: Influences of environment and genetic susceptibility. Physiological Reviews, 96, 55–97. https://doi.org/10.1152/physrev.00017.2015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Svingen, T., Villeneuve, D. L., Knapen, D., Panagiotou, E. M., Draskau, M. K., Damdimopoulou, P., &amp; O'Brien, J. M. (2021). A pragmatic approach to adverse outcome pathway development and evaluation. Toxicological Sciences, 184, 183–190. https://doi.org/10.1093/TOXSCI/KFAB113</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swerdloff, R. S., Dudley, R. E., Page, S. T., Wang, C., &amp; Salameh, W. A. (2017). Dihydrotestosterone: Biochemistry, physiology, and clinical implications of elevated blood levels. Endocrine Reviews, 38, 220–254. https://doi.org/10.1210/ER.2016-1067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villeneuve, D., Meek, B., Viviani, B., Burgdorf, T., LaLone, C., O'Brien, J., Knapen, D., Angrish, M., FitzGerald, R., &amp; Tanabe, S. (2023). AOP developers’ handbook (Version 2.6): Supplement to the guidance document for developing and assessing adverse outcome pathways (AOPs) (ENV/JM/MONO[2013]6, 2nd ed.). https://aopwiki.org/handbooks/4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walters, K. A., Simanainen, U., &amp; Handelsman, D. J. (2010). Molecular insights into androgen actions in male and female reproductive function from androgen receptor knockout models. Human Reproduction Update, 16, 543–558. https://doi.org/10.1093/humupd/dmq003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welsh, M., Saunders, P. T. K., &amp; Sharpe, R. M. (2007). The critical time window for androgen‐dependent development of the Wolffian duct in the rat. Endocrinology, 148, 3185–3195. https://doi.org/10.1210/en.2007-0028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson, V. S., Blystone, C. R., Hotchkiss, A. K., Rider, C. V., &amp; Gray, Jr., L. E. (2008). Diverse mechanisms of anti‐androgen action: Impact on male rat reproductive tract development. International Journal of Andrology, 31, 178–187. https://doi.org/10.1111/J.1365-2605.2007.00861.X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamana, K., Fernand, L., Luu‐The, V., &amp; Luu‐The, V. (2010). Human type 3 5α‐reductase is expressed in peripheral tissues at higher levels than types 1 and 2 and its activity is potently inhibited by finasteride and dutasteride. Hormone Molecular Biology and Clinical Investigation, 2, 293–299. https://doi.org/10.1515/HMBCI.2010.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zilliacus, J., Draskau, M. K., Johansson, H. K., Svingen, T., &amp; Beronius, A. (2024). Building an adverse outcome pathway network for estrogen‐, androgen‐ and steroidogenesis‐mediated reproductive toxicity. Frontiers in Toxicology, 6, Article 1357717. https://doi.org/10.3389/FTOX.2024.1357717</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>