<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39207142</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-5336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>90</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied and environmental microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Environ Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Time of arrival during plant disease progression and humidity additively influence <i>Salmonella enterica</i> colonization of lettuce.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0131124</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0131124</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e01311-24</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/aem.01311-24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">The interplay between plant hosts, phytopathogenic bacteria, and enteric human pathogens in the phyllosphere has consequences for human health. <i>Salmonella enterica</i> has been known to take advantage of phytobacterial infection to increase its success on plants, but there is little knowledge of additional factors that may influence the relationship between enteric pathogens and plant disease. In this study, we investigated the role of humidity and the extent of plant disease progression on <i>S. enterica</i> colonization of plants. We found that high humidity was necessary for the replication of <i>S. enterica</i> on diseased lettuce, but not required for <i>S. enterica</i> ingress into the UV-protected apoplast. Additionally, the <i>Xanthomonas hortorum</i> pv. vitians (hereafter, <i>X. vitians</i>)<i>-</i>infected lettuce host was found to be a relatively hostile environment for <i>S. enterica</i> when it arrived prior to the development of watersoaking or following necrosis onset, supporting the existence of an ideal window during <i>X. vitians</i> infection progress that maximizes <i>S. enterica</i> survival. <i>In vitro</i> growth studies in sucrose media suggest that <i>X. vitians</i> may allow <i>S. enterica</i> to benefit from cross-feeding during plant infection. Overall, this study emphasizes the role of phytobacterial disease as a driver of <i>S. enterica</i> success in the phyllosphere, demonstrates how the time of arrival during disease progress can influence <i>S. enterica's</i> fate in the apoplast<i>,</i> and highlights the potential for humidity to transform an infected apoplast into a growth-promoting environment for bacterial colonizers.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPORTANCE">Bacterial leaf spot of lettuce caused by <i>Xanthomonas hortorum</i> pv. vitians is a common threat to leafy green production. The global impact caused by phytopathogens, including <i>X</i>. <i>vitians</i>, is likely to increase with climate change. We found that even under a scenario where increased humidity did not enhance plant disease, high humidity had a substantial effect on facilitating <i>Salmonella enterica</i> growth on <i>Xanthomonas</i>-infected plants. High humidity climates may directly contribute to the survival of human enteric pathogens in crop fields or indirectly affect bacterial survival via changes to the phyllosphere brought on by phytopathogen disease.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dixon</LastName><ForeName>Megan H</ForeName><Initials>MH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Pathology, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microbiology Doctoral Training Program, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nellore</LastName><ForeName>Dharshita</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Pathology, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zaacks</LastName><ForeName>Sonia C</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Pathology, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barak</LastName><ForeName>Jeri D</ForeName><Initials>JD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8751-9563</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Pathology, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>DGE-2137424</GrantID><Agency>NSF | National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship Program (GRFP)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>UW-Food Research Institute</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013486">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, Non-P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Environ Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7605801</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0099-2240</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018545" MajorTopicYN="Y">Lactuca</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006813" MajorTopicYN="Y">Humidity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019779" MajorTopicYN="Y">Salmonella enterica</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010935" MajorTopicYN="Y">Plant Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014974" MajorTopicYN="N">Xanthomonas</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Xanthomonas vitians</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacterial leaf spot of lettuce</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">climate change</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phyllosphere-inhabiting microbes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39207142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11409676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01311-24</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Schlechter RO, Miebach M, Remus-Emsermann MNP. 2019. Driving factors of epiphytic bacterial communities: a review. J Adv Res 19:57–65. doi:10.1016/j.jare.2019.03.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jare.2019.03.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6630024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31341670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vorholt JA. 2012. Microbial life in the phyllosphere. Nat Rev Microbiol 10:828–840. doi:10.1038/nrmicro2910</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23154261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xin XF, Nomura K, Aung K, Velásquez AC, Yao J, Boutrot F, Chang JH, Zipfel C, He SY. 2016. Bacteria establish an aqueous living space in plants crucial for virulence. Nature 539:524–529. doi:10.1038/nature20166</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature20166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5135018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27882964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Ding Y, Cai B, Qin X, Wu J, Yuan M, Wan S, Zhao Y, Xin X-F. 2022. Bacterial effectors manipulate plant abscisic acid signaling for creation of an aqueous apoplast. Cell Host Microbe 30:518–529. doi:10.1016/j.chom.2022.02.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2022.02.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35247331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roussin-Léveillée C, Lajeunesse G, St-Amand M, Veerapen VP, Silva-Martins G, Nomura K, Brassard S, Bolaji A, He SY, Moffett P. 2022. Evolutionarily conserved bacterial effectors hijack abscisic acid signaling to induce an aqueous environment in the apoplast. Cell Host Microbe 30:489–501. doi:10.1016/j.chom.2022.02.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2022.02.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9012689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35247330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schornack S, Minsavage GV, Stall RE, Jones JB, Lahaye T, Jones JB. 2006. Characterization of AvrHah1, a novel AvrBs3-like effector from Xanthomonas gardneri with virulence and avirulence activity. New Phytol 179:546–556. doi:10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02487.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02487.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19086184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cowles KN, Block AK, Barak JD. 2022. Xanthomonas hortorum pv. gardneri TAL effector AvrHah1 is necessary and sufficient for increased persistence of Salmonella enterica on tomato leaves. Sci Rep 12:7313. doi:10.1038/s41598-022-11456-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11456-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9068798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35508535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz AR, Morbitzer R, Lahaye T, Staskawicz BJ. 2017. TALE-induced bHLH transcription factors that activate a pectate lyase contribute to water soaking in bacterial spot of tomato. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 114:E897–E903. doi:10.1073/pnas.1620407114</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1620407114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5293091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28100489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dia NC, Morinière L, Cottyn B, Bernal E, Jacobs JM, Koebnik R, Osdaghi E, Potnis N, Pothier JF. 2022. Xanthomonas hortorum - beyond gardens: current taxonomy, genomics, and virulence repertoires. Mol Plant Pathol 23:597–621. doi:10.1111/mpp.13185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/mpp.13185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8995068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35068051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson PE, Jones JB, Pernezny K. 2006. Bacterial leaf spot of lettuce: relationship of temperature to infection and potential host range of Xanthomonas campestris pv. vitians. Plant Dis 90:465–470. doi:10.1094/PD-90-0465</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PD-90-0465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30786595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savary S, Willocquet L, Pethybridge SJ, Esker P, McRoberts N, Nelson A. 2019. The global burden of pathogens and pests on major food crops. Nat Ecol Evol 3:430–439. doi:10.1038/s41559-018-0793-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41559-018-0793-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30718852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goudeau DM, Parker CT, Zhou Y, Sela S, Kroupitski Y, Brandl MT. 2013. The salmonella transcriptome in lettuce and cilantro soft rot reveals a niche overlap with the animal host intestine. Appl Environ Microbiol 79:250–262. doi:10.1128/AEM.02290-12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02290-12</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3536078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23104408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwan G, Charkowski AO, Barak JD. 2013. Salmonella enterica suppresses Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. carotovorum population and soft rot progression by acidifying the microaerophilic environment. MBio 4:e00557–12. doi:10.1128/mBio.00557-12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.00557-12</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3573663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23404399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng F, Altier C, Martin GB. 2013. Salmonella colonization activates the plant immune system and benefits from association with plant pathogenic bacteria. Environ Microbiol 15:2418–2430. doi:10.1111/1462-2920.12113</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.12113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23517029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potnis N, Soto-Arias JP, Cowles KN, van Bruggen AHC, Jones JB, Barak JD. 2014. Xanthomonas perforans colonization influences Salmonella enterica in the tomato phyllosphere. Appl Environ Microbiol 80:3173–3180. doi:10.1128/AEM.00345-14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00345-14</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4018908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24632252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potnis N, Colee J, Jones JB, Barak JD. 2015. Plant pathogen-induced water-soaking promotes Salmonella enterica growth on tomato leaves. Appl Environ Microbiol 81:8126–8134. doi:10.1128/AEM.01926-15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01926-15</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4651078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26386057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dixon MH, Cowles KN, Zaacks SC, Marciniak IN, Barak JD. 2022. Xanthomonas Infection transforms the apoplast into an accessible and habitable niche for Salmonella enterica. Appl Environ Microbiol 88:e0133022. doi:10.1128/aem.01330-22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01330-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9680631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36314834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barak JD, Liang AS. 2008. Role of soil, crop debris, and a plant pathogen in Salmonella enterica contamination of tomato plants. PLoS ONE 3:e1657. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0001657</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0001657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2244709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18301739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teplitski M, de Moraes M. 2018. Of mice and men....and plants: comparative genomics of the dual lifestyles of enteric pathogens. Trends Microbiol 26:748–754. doi:10.1016/j.tim.2018.02.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2018.02.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29502873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spector MP, Kenyon WJ. 2012. Resistance and survival strategies of Salmonella enterica to environmental stresses. Food Res Int 45:455–481. doi:10.1016/j.foodres.2011.06.056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2011.06.056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H, Whitehouse CA, Li B. 2018. Presence and persistence of Salmonella in water: the impact on microbial quality of water and food safety. Front Public Health 6:159. doi:10.3389/fpubh.2018.00159</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2018.00159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5989457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29900166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam M, Morgan J, Doyle MP, Phatak SC, Millner P, Jiang X. 2004. Persistence of Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium on lettuce and parsley and in soils on which they were grown in fields treated with contaminated manure composts or irrigation water. Foodborne Pathog Dis 1:27–35. doi:10.1089/153531404772914437</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/153531404772914437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15992259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam M, Morgan J, Doyle MP, Phatak SC, Millner P, Jiang X. 2004. Fate of Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium on carrots and radishes grown in fields treated with contaminated manure composts or irrigation water. Appl Environ Microbiol 70:2497–2502. doi:10.1128/AEM.70.4.2497-2502.2004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.70.4.2497-2502.2004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC383101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15066849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandl MT. 2006. Fitness of human enteric pathogens on plants and implications for food safety. Annu Rev Phytopathol 44:367–392. doi:10.1146/annurev.phyto.44.070505.143359</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.44.070505.143359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16704355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carstens CK, Salazar JK, Darkoh C. 2019. Multistate outbreaks of foodborne illness in the United States associated with fresh produce from 2010 to 2017. Front Microbiol 10:2667. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2019.02667</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6883221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31824454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horby PW, O’Brien SJ, Adak GK, Graham C, Hawker JI, Hunter P, Lane C, Lawson AJ, Mitchell RT, Reacher MH, Threlfall EJ, Ward LR, PHLS Outbreak Investigation Team . 2003. A national outbreak of multi-resistant Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium definitive phage type (DT) 104 associated with consumption of lettuce. Epidemiol Infect 130:169–178. doi:10.1017/s0950268802008063</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0950268802008063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2869951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12729184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lienemann T, Niskanen T, Guedes S, Siitonen A, Kuusi M, Rimhanen-Finne R. 2011. Iceberg lettuce as suggested source of a nationwide outbreak caused by two Salmonella serotypes, Newport and reading, in Finland in 2008. J Food Prot 74:1035–1040. doi:10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-10-455</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-10-455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21669088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McClure M, Whitney B, Gardenhire I, Crosby A, Wellman A, Patel K, McCormic ZD, Gieraltowski L, Gollarza L, Low MSF, Adams J, Pightling A, Bell RL, Nolte K, Tijerina M, Frost JT, Beix JA, Boegler KA, Dow J, Altman S, Wise ME, Bazaco MC, Viazis S. 2023. An outbreak investigation of Salmonella typhimurium illnesses in the United States linked to packaged leafy greens produced at a controlled environment agriculture indoor hydroponic operation - 2021. J Food Prot 86:100079. doi:10.1016/j.jfp.2023.100079</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfp.2023.100079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10493856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37003534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cowles KN, Willis DK, Engel TN, Jones JB, Barak JD. 2016. Diguanylate cyclases AdrA and STM1987 regulate Salmonella enterica exopolysaccharide production during plant colonization in an environment-dependent manner. Appl Environ Microbiol 82:1237–1248. doi:10.1128/AEM.03475-15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.03475-15</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4751842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26655751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barak JD, Whitehand LC, Charkowski AO. 2002. Differences in attachment of Salmonella enterica serovars and Escherichia coli O157:h7 to alfalfa sprouts. Appl Environ Microbiol 68:4758–4763. doi:10.1128/AEM.68.10.4758-4763.2002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.10.4758-4763.2002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC126431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12324317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouzounov N. Establishment and Maintenance of Rod Shape by the Bacterial Aactin Homologue MreB. Princeton, NJ, Princeton University</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashimoto-Gotoh T, Yamaguchi M, Yasojima K, Tsujimura A, Wakabayashi Y, Watanabe Y. 2000. A set of temperature sensitive-replication/-segregation and temperature resistant plasmid vectors with different copy numbers and in an isogenic background (chloramphenicol, kanamycin, lacZ, repA, par, polA). Gene 241:185–191. doi:10.1016/s0378-1119(99)00434-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0378-1119(99)00434-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10607913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lutz R, Bujard H. 1997. Independent and tight regulation of transcriptional units in Escherichia coli via the LacR/O, the TetR/O and AraC/I1-I2 regulatory elements. Nucleic Acids Res 25:1203–1210. doi:10.1093/nar/25.6.1203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/25.6.1203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC146584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9092630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cowles KN, Groves RL, Barak JD. 2018. Leafhopper-induced activation of the jasmonic acid response benefits Salmonella enterica in a flagellum-dependent manner. Front Microbiol 9:1987. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2018.01987</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6115507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30190716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrod VL, Groves RL, Guillemette EG, Barak JD. 2022. Salmonella enterica changes macrosteles quadrilineatus feeding behaviors resulting in altered S. enterica distribution on leaves and increased populations. Sci Rep 12:8544. doi:10.1038/s41598-022-11750-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11750-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9122940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35595751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessens R, Sorensen N, Kabbage M. 2018. An inhibitor of apoptosis (SfIAP) interacts with SQUAMOSA promoter-binding protein (SBP) transcription factors that exhibit pro-cell death characteristics. Plant Direct 2:e00081. doi:10.1002/pld3.81</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pld3.81</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6508781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31245745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima U, Senthil-Kumar M. 2015. Plant and pathogen nutrient acquisition strategies. Front Plant Sci 6:750. doi:10.3389/fpls.2015.00750</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4585253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26442063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reid SJ, Abratt VR. 2005. Sucrose utilisation in bacteria: genetic organisation and regulation. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 67:312–321. doi:10.1007/s00253-004-1885-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-004-1885-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15660210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele M, Odumeru J. 2004. Irrigation water as source of foodborne pathogens on fruit and vegetables. J Food Prot 67:2839–2849. doi:10.4315/0362-028x-67.12.2839</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028x-67.12.2839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15633699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacobsen CS, Bech TB. 2012. Soil survival of Salmonella and transfer to freshwater and fresh produce. Food Res Int 45:557–566. doi:10.1016/j.foodres.2011.07.026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2011.07.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) . 2008. Outbreak of Salmonella serotype saintpaul infections associated with multiple raw produce items --- United States, 2008. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. Vol. 57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18756191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) . 2018. Surveillance for foodborne disease outbreaks United States, 2016. Annual Report. Atlanta, Georgia</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) . 2018. Multistate outbreak of E.coli O157:h7 infections linked to romaine lettuce (final update). Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/ecoli/2018/o157h7-04-18/index.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson R, Cody BA. 2015. California agricultural production and irrigated water use</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpanga IK, Idowu OJ. 2021. A decade of irrigation water use trends in Southwestern USA: the role of irrigation technology, best management practices, and outreach education programs. Agric Water Manag 243:106438. doi:10.1016/j.agwat.2020.106438</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.agwat.2020.106438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis W, Weber C, Wechsler S, Lucier G, Soria Rodriguez M, Yeh A, Fan X. 2023. Veg and pulses outlook</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirano SS, Baker LS, Upper CD. 1996. Raindrop momentum triggers growth of leaf-associated populations of Pseudomonas syringae on field-grown snap bean plants. Appl Environ Microbiol 62:2560–2566. doi:10.1128/aem.62.7.2560-2566.1996</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.62.7.2560-2566.1996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1388900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16535362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim S, Park H, Gruszewski HA, Schmale DG, Jung S. 2019. Vortex-induced dispersal of a plant pathogen by raindrop impact. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 116:4917–4922. doi:10.1073/pnas.1820318116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1820318116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6421443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30804195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Lavalle L, Carrasco E, Vallesquino-Laguna P, Cejudo-Gómez M, Posada-Izquierdo GD, Valero A. 2021. Internalization capacity of Salmonella enterica sv Thompson in strawberry plants via root. Food Control 126:108080. doi:10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108080</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes Esteves RG, Gerba CP, Slack DC. 2022. Control of viral and bacterial contamination of lettuce by subsurface drip irrigation. J Irrig Drain Eng 148. doi:10.1061/(ASCE)IR.1943-4774.0001706</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1061/(ASCE)IR.1943-4774.0001706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beattie GA. 2011. Water relations in the interaction of foliar bacterial pathogens with plants. Annu Rev Phytopathol 49:533–555. doi:10.1146/annurev-phyto-073009-114436</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-phyto-073009-114436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21438680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yunis H, Bashan Y, Okon Y, Henis Y. 1980. Weather dependence, yield losses, and control of bacterial speck of tomato caused by Pseudomonas tomato. Plant Dis 64:937. doi:10.1094/PD-64-937</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PD-64-937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toussaint V. 2001. Ecology of Xanthomonas campestris pv. vitians in relation to development of bacterial leaf spot of lettuce. McGill University, Montreal.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panchal S, Chitrakar R, Thompson BK, Obulareddy N, Roy D, Hambright WS, Melotto M. 2016. Regulation of stomatal defense by air relative humidity. Plant Physiol 172:2021–2032. doi:10.1104/pp.16.00696</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1104/pp.16.00696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5100797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27702841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stine SW, Song I, Choi CY, Gerba CP. 2005. Effect of relative humidity on preharvest survival of bacterial and viral pathogens on the surface of cantaloupe, lettuce, and bell peppers. J Food Prot 68:1352–1358. doi:10.4315/0362-028x-68.7.1352</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028x-68.7.1352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16013370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy D, Panchal S, Rosa BA, Melotto M. 2013. Escherichia coli O157:h7 induces stronger plant immunity than Salmonella enterica typhimurium SL1344. Phytopathology 103:326–332. doi:10.1094/PHYTO-09-12-0230-FI</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-09-12-0230-FI</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3982233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23301812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>López-Gálvez F, Gil MI, Allende A. 2018. Impact of relative humidity, inoculum carrier and size, and native microbiota on Salmonella ser. typhimurium survival in baby lettuce. Food Microbiol 70:155–161. doi:10.1016/j.fm.2017.09.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2017.09.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29173622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deblais L, Helmy YA, Testen A, Vrisman C, Jimenez Madrid AM, Kathayat D, Miller SA, Rajashekara G. 2019. Specific environmental temperature and relative humidity conditions and grafting affect the persistence and dissemination of Salmonella enterica subsp. enterica serotype typhimurium in tomato plant tissues. Appl Environ Microbiol 85:1–17. doi:10.1128/AEM.00403-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00403-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6532026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30926732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haley BJ, Cole DJ, Lipp EK. 2009. Distribution, diversity, and seasonality of waterborne salmonellae in a rural watershed. Appl Environ Microbiol 75:1248–1255. doi:10.1128/AEM.01648-08</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01648-08</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2648171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19124594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walters SP, Thebo AL, Boehm AB. 2011. Impact of urbanization and agriculture on the occurrence of bacterial pathogens and stx genes in coastal waterbodies of central California. Water Res 45:1752–1762. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2010.11.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2010.11.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21168181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris CS, Tertuliano M, Rajeev S, Vellidis G, Levy K. 2018. Impact of storm runoff on Salmonella and Escherichia coli prevalence in irrigation ponds of fresh produce farms in southern Georgia. J Appl Microbiol 124:910–921. doi:10.1111/jam.13689</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.13689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6287630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29316043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melotto M, Underwood W, He SY. 2008. Role of stomata in plant innate immunity and foliar bacterial diseases. Annu Rev Phytopathol 46:101–122. doi:10.1146/annurev.phyto.121107.104959</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.121107.104959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2613263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18422426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroupitski Y, Golberg D, Belausov E, Pinto R, Swartzberg D, Granot D, Sela S. 2009. Internalization of Salmonella enterica in leaves is induced by light and involves chemotaxis and penetration through open stomata. Appl Environ Microbiol 75:6076–6086. doi:10.1128/AEM.01084-09</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01084-09</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2753090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19648358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chincinska IA. 2021. Leaf infiltration in plant science: old method, new possibilities. Plant Methods 17:83. doi:10.1186/s13007-021-00782-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13007-021-00782-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8316707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34321022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rufián JS, Sánchez-Romero M-A, López-Márquez D, Macho AP, Mansfield JW, Arnold DL, Ruiz-Albert J, Casadesús J, Beuzón CR. 2016. Pseudomonas syringae differentiates into phenotypically distinct subpopulations during colonization of a plant host. Environ Microbiol 18:3593–3605. doi:10.1111/1462-2920.13497</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.13497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27516206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Newman M-A, Sundelin T, Nielsen JT, Erbs G. 2013. MAMP (microbe-associated molecular pattern) triggered immunity in plants. Front Plant Sci
4. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2013.00139</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3655273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23720666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi J, Wang J, Gong Z, Zhou J-M. 2017. Apoplastic ROS signaling in plant immunity. Curr Opin Plant Biol 38:92–100. doi:10.1016/j.pbi.2017.04.022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2017.04.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28511115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M, Ali S, Al Azzawi TNI, Saqib S, Ullah F, Ayaz A, Zaman W. 2023. The key roles of ROS and RNS as a signaling molecule in plant-microbe interactions. Antioxidants (Basel) 12:268. doi:10.3390/antiox12020268</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox12020268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9952064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36829828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferelli AMC, Bolten S, Szczesny B, Micallef SA. 2020. Salmonella enterica elicits and is restricted by nitric oxide and reactive oxygen species on tomato. Front Microbiol 11:391. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2020.00391</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7082413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32231649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García AV, Hirt H. 2014. Salmonella enterica induces and subverts the plant immune system. Front Microbiol 5:141. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2014.00141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2014.00141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3983520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24772109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steeb B, Claudi B, Burton NA, Tienz P, Schmidt A, Farhan H, Mazé A, Bumann D. 2013. Parallel exploitation of diverse host nutrients enhances Salmonella virulence. PLoS Pathog 9:e1003301. doi:10.1371/journal.ppat.1003301</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3636032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23633950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teplitski M, Barak JD, Schneider KR. 2009. Human enteric pathogens in produce: un-answered ecological questions with direct implications for food safety. Curr Opin Biotechnol 20:166–171. doi:10.1016/j.copbio.2009.03.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2009.03.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19349159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbott DW, Boraston AB. 2008. Structural biology of pectin degradation by enterobacteriaceae. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 72:301–316. doi:10.1128/MMBR.00038-07</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00038-07</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2415742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18535148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalupowicz L, Nissan G, Brandl MT, McClelland M, Sessa G, Popov G, Barash I, Manulis-Sasson S. 2018. Assessing the ability of Salmonella enterica to translocate type III effectors into plant cells. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 31:233–239. doi:10.1094/MPMI-07-17-0166-R</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/MPMI-07-17-0166-R</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28952399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng J, Allard S, Reynolds S, Millner P, Arce G, Blodgett RJ, Brown EW. 2013. Colonization and internalization of Salmonella enterica in tomato plants. Appl Environ Microbiol 79:2494–2502. doi:10.1128/AEM.03704-12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.03704-12</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3623171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23377940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith NW, Shorten PR, Altermann E, Roy NC, McNabb WC. 2019. The classification and evolution of bacterial cross-feeding. Front Ecol Evol 7. doi:10.3389/fevo.2019.00153</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fevo.2019.00153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murillo-Roos M, Abdullah HSM, Debbar M, Ueberschaar N, Agler MT. 2022. Cross-feeding niches among commensal leaf bacteria are shaped by the interaction of strain-level diversity and resource availability. ISME J 16:2280–2289. doi:10.1038/s41396-022-01271-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41396-022-01271-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9381498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35768644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palaniraj A, Jayaraman V. 2011. Production, recovery and applications of xanthan gum by Xanthomonas campestris. J Food Eng 106:1–12. doi:10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2011.03.035</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2011.03.035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lovelace AH, Ma W. 2022. How do bacteria transform plants into their oasis? Cell Host Microbe 30:412–414. doi:10.1016/j.chom.2022.03.026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2022.03.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35421331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>