<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39219001</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>89</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry analysis of metabolites in finger millet and Bambara groundnut as affected by traditional and novel food processing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>6394</StartPage><EndPage>6412</EndPage><MedlinePgn>6394-6412</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17337</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Metabolite profiling is an analytical technique used to assess metabolites in complex biological samples. This technique allows for the identification of both targeted and untargeted metabolites. In this study, the effect of traditional (fermentation and malting) and novel processing (ultrasonication) on the metabolites of finger millet (FM) and Bambara groundnut (BGN) flour was investigated using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. Various metabolite classes, including amino acids, alcohol, aldehyde, organic acid, ester, fatty acids, glycoside, and sugar, were identified in FM and BGN flours. The adopted processing techniques impacted metabolite composition, as evidenced by substantial variations in volatile compound levels and metabolite composition among the FM and BGN samples before and after traditional and novel processing. Important health-promoting compounds, such as oleic acid, linoelaidic acid, and linoleic acid, were identified at their highest levels in fermented FM and BGN flours. The results obtained from this study offer an important context for monitoring and regulating the metabolite composition of FM and BGN flours under traditional and novel processing. PRACTICAL APPLICATION: Fermentation, malting, and ultrasonication induced desirable changes in some health-promoting compounds of finger millet and Bambara groundnut flours. The food and pharmaceutical industries could benefit from these traditional- and novel-modified flours as they could be used as improved food sources with health benefits.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Food Science published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mudau</LastName><ForeName>Masala</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Innovative Food Research (CIFR), Department of Biotechnology and Food Technology, Faculty of Science, University of Johannesburg, Doornfontein, Johannesburg, Gauteng, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chinma</LastName><ForeName>Chiemela Enyinnaya</ForeName><Initials>CE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Innovative Food Research (CIFR), Department of Biotechnology and Food Technology, Faculty of Science, University of Johannesburg, Doornfontein, Johannesburg, Gauteng, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Federal University of Technology, Minna, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Africa Centre of Excellence for Mycotoxin and Food Safety, Federal University of Technology Minna, Minna, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ledbetter</LastName><ForeName>Moira</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Engineering and Food Science, School of Applied Sciences, Abertay University, Dundee, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wilkin</LastName><ForeName>Jon</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8272-6865</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Engineering and Food Science, School of Applied Sciences, Abertay University, Dundee, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adebo</LastName><ForeName>Oluwafemi Ayodeji</ForeName><Initials>OA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3757-5137</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Innovative Food Research (CIFR), Department of Biotechnology and Food Technology, Faculty of Science, University of Johannesburg, Doornfontein, Johannesburg, Gauteng, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>European Union Erasmus</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>University of Johannesburg</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>National Research Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D005227">Fatty Acids</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000596">Amino Acids</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D055549">Volatile Organic Compounds</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008401" MajorTopicYN="Y">Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005511" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Handling</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005433" MajorTopicYN="Y">Flour</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005227" MajorTopicYN="N">Fatty Acids</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D031748" MajorTopicYN="N">Eleusine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005285" MajorTopicYN="N">Fermentation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010367" MajorTopicYN="N">Arachis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000596" MajorTopicYN="N">Amino Acids</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055549" MajorTopicYN="N">Volatile Organic Compounds</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fermentation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">legume</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">malting and ultrasonication</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metabolomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">millet</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39219001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adebiyi, J. A., Njobeh, P. B., Adebo, O. A., &amp; Kayitesi, E. (2021). Metabolite profile of Bambara groundnut (Vigna subterranea) and dawadawa (an African fermented condiment) investigation using gas chromatography high resolution time‐of‐flight mass spectrometry (GC‐HRTOF‐MS). Heliyon, 7, e06666. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06666</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebiyi, J. A., Obadina, A. O., Adebo, O. A., &amp; Kayitesi, E. (2017). Comparison of nutritional quality and sensory acceptability of biscuits obtained from native, fermented, and malted pearl millet (Pennisetum glaucum) flour. Food Chemistry, 232, 210–217. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.04.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebo, O. A., Kayitesi, E., Tugizimana, F., &amp; Njobeh, P. B. (2019). Differential metabolic signatures in naturally and lactic acid bacteria (LAB) fermented ting (a Southern African food) with different tannin content, as revealed by gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GC–MS)‐based metabolomics. Food Research International, 121, 326–335. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2019.03.050</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adetokunboh, A. H., Obilana, A. O., &amp; Jideani, V. A. (2022). Physicochemical characteristics of Bambara groundnut speciality malts and extract. Molecules, 27, 4332. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27144332</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad, K., Imran, M., Ahmad, T., Ahmad, M. H., &amp; Khan, M. K. (2020). Impact of ultrasound processing on physicochemical and bioactive attributes of grape based optimized fruit beverage. Pakistan Journal of Agricultural Sciences, 57, 1117–1124. https://doi.org/10.21162/PAKJAS/20.8680</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awuchi, C. G., &amp; Echeta, K. C. (2019). Current developments in sugar alcohols: Chemistry, nutrition, and health concerns of sorbitol, xylitol, glycerol, arabitol, inositol, maltitol, and lactitol. International Journal of Advanced Academic Research, 5, 1–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banura, S., &amp; Singh, N. (2023). Effect of ultrasonication on physicochemical, amino‐acids, sugar profile, antioxidant, pasting, and dynamic rheological properties of malted mung beans and lentils. International Journal of Food Science and Technology, 58, 2476–2488. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.16388</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharjee, B., Pal, P. K., Chattopadhyay, A., &amp; Bandyopadhyay, D. (2020). Oleic acid protects against cadmium induced cardiac and hepatic tissue injury in male Wistar rats: A mechanistic study. Life Sciences, 244, 117324. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2020.117324</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byeon, Y. S., Hong, Y.‐S., Kwak, H. S., Lim, S.‐T., &amp; Kim, S. S. (2022). Metabolite profile and antioxidant potential of wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) during malting. Food Chemistry, 384, 132443. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.132443</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary, A., Verma, K., &amp; Saharan, B. S. (2020). A GC‐MS based metabolic profiling of probiotic lactic acid bacteria isolated from traditional food products. Journal of Pure and Applied Microbiology, 14, 657–672. https://doi.org/10.22207/jpam.14.1.68</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinma, C. E., Abu, J. O., Asikwe, B. N., Sunday, T., &amp; Adebo, O. A. (2021). Effect of germination on the physicochemical, nutritional, functional, thermal properties and in vitro digestibility of Bambara groundnut flours. LWT, 140, 110749. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.110749</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, R., &amp; Zhu, F. (2020). Effect of ultrasound on structural and physicochemical properties of sweet potato and wheat flours. Ultrasonics Sonochemistry, 66, 105118. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105118</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dida, K., &amp; Kebero, K. (2023). Finger millet—A possible source of human nourishment and health. Advances in Nutrition and Food Science, 8, 17–25. https://doi.org/10.11648/j.aas.20230802.13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egedigwe‐Ekeleme, C. A., Famurewa, A. C., Egedigwe, U. O., Onyeabo, C., Kanu, S. C., Ogunwa, S. C., Onuora, C. A., &amp; Agbo, A. O. (2023). Comparative studies on the amino acids, pesticide residue content, biogenic and toxic elements in an underutilized nut: Bambara groundnut (Vigna subterranea). Journal of Trace Elements and Minerals, 3, 100051. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtemin.2023.100051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erb, M., &amp; Kliebenstein, D. J. (2020). Plant secondary metabolites as defenses, regulators, and primary metabolites: The blurred functional trichotomy. Plant Physiology, 184, 39–52. https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.20.00433</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fahmy, H. A., El‐Shamy, S., &amp; Farag, M. A. (2023). Comparative GC–MS based nutrients profiling of less explored legume seeds of Melilotus, Medicago, Trifolium, and Ononis analysed using chemometric tools. Scientific Reports, 13, 18221. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐023‐45453‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faizal, F. A., Ahmad, N. H., Yaacob, J. S., Abdul Halim Lim, S., &amp; Abd Rahim, M. H. (2023). Food processing to reduce antinutrients in plant‐based foods. International Food Research Journal, 30, 25–45. https://doi.org/10.47836/ifrj.30.1.02</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox, G. P., &amp; Bettenhausen, H. M. (2023). Variation in quality of grains used in malting and brewing. Frontiers in Plant Science, 14, 1172028. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2023.1172028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, X., Cebo, M., Ikegami, T., &amp; Lämmerhofer, M. (2020). Separation of carbohydrate isomers and anomers on poly‐N‐(1H‐tetrazole‐5‐yl)‐methacrylamide‐bonded stationary phase by hydrophilic interaction chromatography as well as determination of anomer interconversion energy barriers. Journal of Chromatography A, 1620, 460981. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2020.460981</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerrano, A. S., Eifediyi, E. K., Labuschagne, M., Ogedegbe, F. O., &amp; Hassen, A. I. (2021). Production practices of Bambara groundnut. In: Food and potential industrial applications of Bambara groundnut (pp. 7–25). Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐030‐73920‐1_2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hambali, E., Fitria, R., &amp; Sari, V. I. (2022). Glycerol and derivatives. In: Biorefinery of oil producing plants for value‐added products (pp.469–491). Wiley. https://doi.org/10.1002/9783527830756.ch24</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, J., Dai, Y., Zhang, Y., Liu, G., Peng, F., Xie, M., &amp; Xiong, T. (2023). Dynamics of bacterial community, metabolites profile, and physicochemical characteristics during solid‐state fermentation of soybean meal and corn mixed substrates inoculated with Bacillus pumilus and Limosilactobacillus fermentum. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 103, 5588–5599. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.12639</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iman, M. N., Irdiani, R., Rahmawati, D., Fukusaki, E., &amp; Putri, S. P. (2023). Improvement of the functional value of green soybean (edamame) using germination and tempe fermentation: A comparative metabolomics study. Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering, 136, 205–212. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbiosc.2023.05.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagati, P., Mahapatra, I., &amp; Dash, D. (2021). Finger millet (Ragi) as an essential dietary supplement with key health benefits: A review. International Journal of Home Science, 7, 94–100. https://doi.org/10.22271/23957476.2021.v7.i2b.1152</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur, R., &amp; Prasad, K. (2022). Effect of malting and roasting of chickpea on functional and nutritional qualities of its protein fractions. International Journal of Food Science and Technology, 57, 3990–4000. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.15769</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kewuyemi, Y. O., &amp; Adebo, O. A. (2024). Complementary nutritional and health‐promoting constituents in germinated and probiotic fermented flours from cowpea, sorghum, and orange‐fleshed sweet potato. Scientific Reports, 14, 1987. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐024‐52149‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kewuyemi, Y. O., Njobeh, P. B., Kayitesi, E., Adebiyi, J. A., Oyedeji, A. B., Adefisoye, M. A., &amp; Adebo, O. A. (2020). Metabolite profile of whole grain ting (a Southern African fermented product) obtained using two strains of Lactobacillus fermentum. Journal of Cereal Science, 95, 103042. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2020.103042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khodadadi, M., &amp; Pourfarzam, M. (2020). A review of strategies for untargeted urinary metabolomic analysis using gas chromatography–mass spectrometry. Metabolomics, 16, 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11306‐020‐01687‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langenaeken, N. A., De Schepper, C. F., De Schutter, D. P., &amp; Courtin, C. M. (2020). Carbohydrate content and structure during malting and brewing: A mass balance study. Journal of the Institute of Brewing, 126, 253–262. https://doi.org/10.1002/jib.619</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Wang, Q., Liu, C., Yang, H., Jia, L., Zhao, L., &amp; He, W. S. (2023). Improved antioxidant activity of rutin via lipase‐mediated esterification with oleic acid. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 103, 3489–3500. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.12486</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maharajan, T., Antony Ceasar, S., Ajeesh Krishna, T. P., &amp; Ignacimuthu, S. (2021). Finger millet [Eleusine coracana (L.) Gaertn]: An orphan crop with a potential to alleviate the calcium deficiency in the semi‐arid tropics of Asia and Africa. Frontiers in Sustainable Food Systems, 5, 684447. https://doi.org/10.3389/fsufs.2021.684447</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majid, I., Nayik, G. A., &amp; Nanda, V. (2015). Ultrasonication and food technology: A review. Cogent Food and Agriculture, 1, 1071022. https://doi.org/10.1080/23311932.2015.1071022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meena, L., Buvaneswaran, M., Byresh, T. S., Sunil, C. K., Rawson, A., &amp; Venkatachalapathy, N. (2023). Effect of ultrasound treatment on white finger millet‐based probiotic beverage. Measurement: Food, 10, 100090. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meafoo.2023.100090</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitharwal, S., Kumar, S., &amp; Chauhan, K. (2021). Nutritional, polyphenolic composition and in vitro digestibility of finger millet (Eleusine coracana L.) with its potential food applications: A review. Food Bioscience, 44, 101382. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2021.101382</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed, S. S. D., Orukotan, A. A., &amp; Musa, J. (2017). Effect of fermentation and malting on some cereal weaning foods enriched with African locust beans. Journal of Applied Sciences and Environmental Management, 21, 911–921. https://dx.doi.org/10.4314/jasem.v21i5.17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mudau, M., Ramashia, S. E., &amp; Mashau, M. E. (2022). Mineral content, functional, thermo‐pasting, and microstructural properties of spontaneously fermented finger millet flours. Foods, 11, 2474. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11162474</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oladimeji, B. M., &amp; Adebo, O. A. (2024). Properties and metabolite profiling of Bambara groundnut flour as affected by different food processing conditions. Applied Food Research, 4, 100389. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.afres.2024.100389</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyedeji, A. B., Chinma, C. E., Green, E., &amp; Adebo, O. A. (2021). Metabolite data of germinated Bambara groundnut flour and starch extracted with two different solvents. Data in Brief, 38, 107288. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dib.2021.107288</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özcan, M. M., Aljuhaimi, F., &amp; Uslu, N. (2018). Effect of malt process steps on bioactive properties and fatty acid composition of barley, green malt and malt grains. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 55, 226–232. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐017‐2920‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S. E., Yoo, S. A., Seo, S. H., Lee, K. I., Na, C. S., &amp; Son, H. S. (2016). GC–MS based metabolomics approach of kimchi for the understanding of Lactobacillus plantarum fermentation characteristics. LWT, 68, 313–321. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2015.12.046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pexová Kalinová, J., Tříska, J., &amp; Hořejší, K. (2023). Comparison of the main constituents in two varieties of proso millet using GC–MS. Foods, 12, 2294. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12122294</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaei, S., Najafi, M. A., &amp; Haddadi, T. (2019). Effect of fermentation process, wheat bran size and replacement level on some characteristics of wheat bran, dough, and high‐fiber Tafton bread. Journal of Cereal Science, 85, 56–61. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2018.11.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santa‐María, C., López‐Enríquez, S., Montserrat‐de la Paz, S., Geniz, I., Reyes‐Quiroz, M. E., Moreno, M., Palomares, F., Sobrino, F., &amp; Alba, G. (2023). Update on anti‐inflammatory molecular mechanisms induced by oleic acid. Nutrients, 15, 224. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu15010224</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheela, P., UmaMaheswari, T., Kanchana, S., Hemalatha, G., &amp; Vellaikumar, S. (2021). Identification of volatile compounds in fermented millet‐based beverages by gas chromatography‐mass spectroscopy. Applied Biological Research, 23, 245–254. https://doi.org/10.5958/0974‐4517.2021.00031.8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szczepańska, P., Rychlicka, M., Groborz, S., Kruszyńska, A., Ledesma‐Amaro, R., Rapak, A., Gliszczyńska, A., &amp; Lazar, Z. (2023). Studies on the anticancer and antioxidant activities of resveratrol and long‐chain fatty acid esters. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 24, 7167. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms24087167</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trivedi, P. B., &amp; Gupta, N. (2023). Gas chromatography‐mass spectrometry (GC‐MS) analysis and phytochemical screening of finger millet and foxtail millet. Millets, 2023, 415–425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voelker, R. (2019). Oleic acid can make heart claim without hard evidence. JAMA, 321, 23. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2018.19747</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Ma, H., &amp; Wang, S. (2019). Application of ultrasound, microwaves, and magnetic fields techniques in the germination of cereals. Food Science and Technology Research, 25, 489–497. https://doi.org/10.3136/fstr.25.489</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Wu, J., Lv, M., Shao, Z., Hungwe, M., Wang, J., Bai, X., Xie, J., Wang, Y., &amp; Geng, W. (2021). Metabolism characteristics of lactic acid bacteria and the expanding applications in food industry. Frontiers in Bioengineering and Biotechnology, 9, 612285. https://doi.org/10.3389/fbioe.2021.612285</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Y., Liu, J., Hu, A., Nie, T., Cheng, Z., &amp; Liu, W. (2022). A critical review on engineering of d‐mannitol crystals: Properties, applications, and polymorphic control. Crystals, 12, 1080. https://doi.org/10.3390/cryst12081080</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, H., Liu, Y., Huang, Y., Liang, Q., Cai, S., &amp; Zhang, G. (2022). Time‐course comparative metabolome analysis of different barley varieties during malting. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70, 2051–2059. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.1c08346</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>