<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39216771</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1872-7573</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>337</Volume><Issue>Pt 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of ethnopharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Ethnopharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Toxicity studies of compound spermatogenic pill:Acute toxicity and subacute toxicity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>118757</StartPage><MedlinePgn>118757</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jep.2024.118757</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0378-8741(24)01056-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Spermatogenic Pill (SP) is a commonly used clinical preparation in the Third Clinical Hospital of Changchun University of Traditional Chinese Medicine. Has accumulated a good reputation for more than a decade. However, because SP is a hospital clinical agent, it has received little extensive attention from researchers, which has led to a systematic lack of basic research on it. Therefore, it is impossible to determine whether there are safety hazards that may limit its widespread clinical application, and an in-depth toxicological evaluation of SP is essential and urgent.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM OF THE STUDY" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The aim of this study was to assess the safety of SP by conducting acute and subacute toxicity examinations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Identify active compounds contained in SP by LC-MS, and determination of inorganic elements in SP using ICP-MS. The in vivo acute toxicity of SP was assessed over a duration of 14 days following administration at doses of 7.5, 15, or 30 g/kg. To evaluate subacute toxicity, mice were administered daily doses of SP (7.5, 15, or 30 g/kg) for a period of 28 days. After the treatment period, the animals were euthanized, and standard blood tests, liver and kidney function tests, as well as tests related to glycolipid metabolism, were performed. The principal organs of the mice were collected to calculate organ coefficients and undergo hematoxylin-eosin (HE) staining.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">LC-MS analysis showed that the active components of SP include Quercetin, Kaempferol, Beta-sitosterol, Stigmasterol, Diosbulbin B, Schizandrin, Naringenin, 2,3-hydroxycinnamic acid, L-proline, Histidine and Pluviatolide. The total amount of detected inorganic elements accounted for 3.0919% of SP. During the SP acute toxicity experiment, the groups that received the drug exhibited no signs of adverse reactions or poisoning symptoms. In subacute toxicity experiments, drug-treated mice showed overall favorable status, but the effects of continuous administration of the 30 g/kg group on body weight and food intake were reduced. An increase in the white marrow of spleen tissue after long-term administration of the drug treatment was also observed, suggesting that the drug can increase the maturation process and the number of mature lymphocytes in the spleen, and improve the lymphocyte immunity and humoral immunity function of the organism. Suggests that possibly this should be taken into account in clinical application. The routine blood examinations, as well as the assessments of liver and kidney functions, and the tests for glucose and lipid metabolism, did not reveal any notable toxic effects.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">SP contains more flavonoids, and terpenoid active ingredients, and is non-toxic in the body. This discovery not only strengthens the safety foundation of its clinical application, provides a solid scientific basis for the establishment of reasonable clinical dosage and the implementation of effective clinical toxicity monitoring, but also further lays a solid theoretical cornerstone for the subsequent clinical drug trials.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Ruyi</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yanlu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Junxia</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xing</LastName><ForeName>Yanchao</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Yingshan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Zhongmei</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zong</LastName><ForeName>Ying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China; Jilin Provincial Engineering Research Center for Efficient Breeding and Product Development of Sika Deer, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China. Electronic address: zongying@jlau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Rui</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China; Jilin Provincial Engineering Research Center for Efficient Breeding and Product Development of Sika Deer, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China; Key Laboratory of Animal Production and Product Quality and Safety, Ministry of Education, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, 130118, China. Electronic address: durui@jlau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Ireland</Country><MedlineTA>J Ethnopharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7903310</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0378-8741</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Active ingredient</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Acute toxicity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spermatogenic pill formula</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Subacute toxicity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39216771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2024.118757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0378-8741(24)01056-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>