<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39210581</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0029</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microscopy research and technique</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microsc Res Tech</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>First report of Morchella galilaea, an autumn species from Pakistan, based on multilocus DNA sequences, light microscopy, and scanning electron microscopy analyses.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jemt.24683</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Morchella is highly prized for its distinct and delicious taste, making it one of the most sought-after and valuable macrofungi. Despite Pakistan exporting morels to various European countries, Morchella's diversity in this South Asian country has not been cataloged using multilocus DNA sequence data. Realizing the need for their scientific identity, various collections were commissioned, including those from the low and high altitudinal zones of the Charsadda, Swat, and Poonch districts of Pakistan during autumn of 2015 through 2019. Specimens were identified by sequencing the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region and portions of the RNA polymerase II largest subunit (RPB1), second largest subunit (RPB2), and translation elongation factor 1-α (TEF1) loci. Multigene molecular phylogenetic analysis revealed the autumnal collections were Morchella galilaea Masaphy &amp; Clowez. The species was previously documented in the United States, China, Israel, and Turkey. A detailed taxonomic description, light and scanning electron microscopy, and multigene molecular phylogenetic analyses of the species are reported here for the first time from Pakistan. The study underscores the necessity for further surveys of unexplored areas of Pakistan and systematics of Morchella to augment species diversity and their geographic distribution. RESEARCH HIGHLIGHTS: Specimens of Morchella were collected from low and high altitudinal zones in Pakistan during the autumn. Specimens were assessed using multigene (ITS, RPB1, RPB2, and TEF1) molecular phylogenetic analyses for the first time in Pakistan. The specimens were identified as Morchella galilaea based on multigene molecular phylogenetic analysis. Updated taxonomic descriptions of macro- and microanatomical characters were provided for clarity and precision. Hitherto-unreported shapes of paraphyses and acroparaphyses are observed and thoroughly reported. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) of an ascospore is provided.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nisa</LastName><ForeName>Surat Un</ForeName><Initials>SU</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7580-4810</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Sciences, Faculty of Biological Sciences, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Badshah</LastName><ForeName>Hussain</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2327-2722</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Sciences, Faculty of Biological Sciences, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shah</LastName><ForeName>Sayed Afzal</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5719-3139</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, National University of Medical Sciences, Rawalpindi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mumtaz</LastName><ForeName>Abdul Samad</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7034-9203</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Sciences, Faculty of Biological Sciences, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Higher Education Commission of Pakistan</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>National Program for Food Safety, Agriculture Research Service, USDA</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Microsc Res Tech</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9203012</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1059-910X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ascomycota</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Morchellaceae</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fungi</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microscopy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phylogeny</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39210581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jemt.24683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Ali, S., Imran, A., Fiaz, M., Khalid, A. N., &amp; Khan, S. M. (2021). Molecular identification of true morels (Morchella spp.) from the Hindu Kush temperate forests leads to three new records from Pakistan. Gene Reports, 23, 101125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badshah, H., Ali, B., Shah, S., Alam, M., Aly, H., &amp; Mumtaz, A. (2018). First record of Morchella pulchella from Pakistan. Mycotaxon, 133(1), 201–207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baroni, T. J., Beug, M. W., Cantrell, S. A., Clements, T. A., Iturriaga, T., Læssøe, T., Holgado Rojas, M. E., Aguilar, F. M., Quispe, M. O., Lodge, D. J., &amp; O'Donnell, K. (2018). Four new species of Morchella from the Americas. Mycologia, 110(6), 1205–1221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clowez, P. (2012). Les morilles: Une nouvelle approche mondiale du genre Morchella. Bulletin Trimestriel de la Societe Mycologique de France, 126(3–4), 199–376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clowez, P., &amp; Moreau, P. A. (2021). Morels of Europe. Cap Régions Edition.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clowez, P., Izumi, T., Lamiable, P.‐B., Shibakusa, K., Minculeasa, C., &amp; Alvarado, P. (2022). Morchella nipponensis sp. nov. (Ascomycota, Pezizales): A paleoendemic species of section Morchella discovered in Japan. Mycoscience, 63(6), 274–283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Degreef, J., Fischer, E., Sharp, C., &amp; Raspe, O. (2009). African Morchella crassipes (Ascomycota, Pezizales) revealed by analysis of nrDNA ITS. Nova Hedwigia, 88(1/2), 11–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, X.‐H., Wu, D.‐M., He, G.‐Q., Wei, W., Xu, N., &amp; Li, T.‐L. (2019). Six new species and two new records of Morchella in China using phylogenetic and morphological analyses. Mycologia, 111(5), 857–870.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, X. H., Zhao, Q., &amp; Yang, Z. L. (2015). A review on research advances, issues, and perspectives of morels. Mycology, 6(2), 78–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, X.‐H., Zhao, Q., O'Donnell, K., Rooney, A. P., &amp; Yang, Z. L. (2012a). Multigene molecular phylogenetics reveals true morels (Morchella) are especially species‐rich in China. Fungal Genetics and Biology, 49(6), 455–469.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du, X. H., Zhao, Q., Yang, Z. L., Hansen, K., Taşkın, H., Büyükalaca, S., Dewsbury, D., Moncalvo, J. M., Douhan, G. W., Robert, V. A. R. G., Crous, P. W., Rehner, S. A., Rooney, A. P., Sink, S., &amp; O'Donnell, K. (2012b). How well do ITS rDNA sequences differentiate species of true morels (Morchella)? Mycologia, 104(6), 1351–1368.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edgar, R. C. (2004). MUSCLE: Multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput. Nucleic Acids Research, 32(5), 1792–1797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El‐Gharabawy, H. M., El‐Fallal, A. A., &amp; El‐Sayed, K. (2019). Description of a yellow morel from Egypt using morphological and molecular tools. Nova Hedwigia, 109(1–2), 95–110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardes, M., &amp; Bruns, T. D. (1993). ITS primers with enhanced specificity for basidiomycetes‐application to the identification of mycorrhizae and rusts. Molecular Ecology, 2(2), 113–118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gouy, M., Guindon, S., &amp; Gascuel, O. (2010). SeaView version 4: A multiplatform graphical user interface for sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree building. Molecular Biology and Evolution, 27(2), 221–224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalyaanamoorthy, S., Minh, B. Q., Wong, T. K., Von Haeseler, A., &amp; Jermiin, L. S. (2017). ModelFinder: Fast model selection for accurate phylogenetic estimates. Nature Methods, 14(6), 587–589.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanwal, H. K., Acharya, K., Ramesh, G., &amp; Reddy, M. S. (2011). Molecular characterization of Morchella species from the Western Himalayan region of India. Current Microbiology, 62, 1245–1252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo, M., Dewsbury, D. R., O'Donnell, K., Carter, M. C., Rehner, S. A., Moore, J. D., Moncalvo, J.‐M., Canfield, S. A., Stephenson, S. L., &amp; Methven, A. S. (2012). Taxonomic revision of true morels (Morchella) in Canada and the United States. Mycologia, 104(5), 1159–1177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Zhang, Y., Hengchao, E., He, X., Li, J., Zhao, X., &amp; Zhou, C. (2023). Characteristic fingerprints and comparison of volatile flavor compounds in Morchella sextelata under different drying methods. Food Research International, 172, 113103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y. J., Whelen, S., &amp; Hall, B. D. (1999). Phylogenetic relationships among ascomycetes: evidence from an RNA polymerse II subunit. Molecular biology and evolution, 16(12), 1799–1808.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loizides, M., Alvarado, P., Clowez, P., Moreau, P. A., de la Osa, L. R., &amp; Palazón, A. (2015). Morchella tridentina, M. rufobrunnea, and M. kakiicolor: A study of three poorly known Mediterranean morels, with nomenclatural updates in section Distantes. Mycological Progress, 14, 1–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loizides, M., Bellanger, J. M., Clowez, P., Richard, F., &amp; Moreau, P. A. (2016). Combined phylogenetic and morphological studies of true morels (Pezizales, Ascomycota) in Cyprus reveal significant diversity, including Morchella arbutiphila and M. disparilis spp. nov. Mycological Progress, 15, 1–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loizides, M., Gonou‐Zagou, Z., Fransuas, G., Drakopoulos, P., Sammut, C., Martinis, A., &amp; Bellanger, J. M. (2021). Extended phylogeography of the ancestral Morchella anatolica supports preglacial presence in Europe and Mediterranean origin of morels. Mycologia, 113(3), 559–573.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masaphy, S., Zabari, L., Goldberg, D., &amp; Jander‐Shagug, G. (2010). The complexity of Morchella systematics: A case of the yellow morel from Israel. Fungi, 3(2), 14–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matheny, P. B., Liu, Y. J., Ammirati, J. F., &amp; Hall, B. D. (2002). Using RPB1 sequences to improve phylogenetic inference among mushrooms (Inocybe, Agaricales). American Journal of Botany, 89(4), 688–698.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen, L. T., Schmidt, H. A., Von Haeseler, A., &amp; Minh, B. Q. (2015). IQ‐TREE: A fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum‐likelihood phylogenies. Molecular Biology and Evolution, 32(1), 268–274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Donnell, K., Rooney, A. P., Mills, G. L., Kuo, M., Weber, N. S., &amp; Rehner, S. A. (2011). Phylogeny and historical biogeography of true morels (Morchella) reveals an early Cretaceous origin and high continental endemism and provincialism in the Holarctic. Fungal Genetics and Biology, 48(3), 252–265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadaki, A., Diamantopoulou, P., Papanikolaou, S., &amp; Philippoussis, A. (2019). Evaluation of biomass and chitin production of Morchella mushrooms grown on starch‐based substrates. Food, 8(7), 239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilz, D. (2007). Ecology and management of morels harvested from the forests of western North America.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rai, M., Tidke, G., &amp; Wasser, S. P. (2005). Therapeutic potential of mushrooms. Natural Product Radiance, 4, 246–257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reeb, V., Lutzoni, F., &amp; Roux, C. (2004). Contribution of RPB2 to multilocus phylogenetic studies of the euascomycetes (Pezizomycotina, Fungi) with special emphasis on the lichen‐forming Acarosporaceae and evolution of polyspory. Molecular phylogenetics and evolution, 32(3), 1036–1060.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehner, S. A., &amp; Buckley, E. (2005). A Beauveria phylogeny inferred from nuclear ITS and EF1‐α sequences: evidence for cryptic diversification and links to Cordyceps teleomorphs. Mycologia, 97(1), 84–98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richard, F., Bellanger, J. M., Clowez, P., Hansen, K., O'Donnell, K., Urban, A., Sauve, M., Courtecuisse, R., &amp; Moreau, P. A. (2015). True morels (Morchella, Pezizales) of Europe and North America: Evolutionary relationships inferred from multilocus data and a unified taxonomy. Mycologia, 107(2), 359–382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sambyal, K., &amp; Singh, R. V. (2021). A comprehensive review on Morchella importuna: Cultivation aspects, phytochemistry, and other significant applications. Folia Microbiologica, 66(2), 147–157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, J. W., Jacobson, D. J., Kroken, S., Kasuga, T., Geiser, D. M., Hibbett, D. S., &amp; Fisher, M. C. (2000). Phylogenetic species recognition and species concepts in fungi. Fungal Genetics and Biology, 31(1), 21–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taşkın, H., Büyükalaca, S., Doğan, H. H., Rehner, S. A., &amp; O'Donnell, K. (2010). A multigene molecular phylogenetic assessment of true morels (Morchella) in Turkey. Fungal Genetics and Biology, 47(8), 672–682.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taşkın, H., Büyükalaca, S., Hansen, K., &amp; O'Donnell, K. (2012). Multilocus phylogenetic analysis of true morels (Morchella) reveals high levels of endemics in Turkey relative to other regions of Europe. Mycologia, 104(2), 446–461.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taşkın, H., Doğan, H. H., &amp; Büyükalaca, S. (2015). Morchella galilaea, an autumn species from Turkey. Mycotaxon, 130(1), 215–221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taşkın, H., Doğan, H. H., Büyükalaca, S., Clowez, P., Moreau, P. A., &amp; O'Donnell, K. (2016). Four new morel (Morchella) species in the elata subclade (M. sect. Distantes) from Turkey. Mycotaxon, 131(2), 467–482.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tietel, Z., &amp; Masaphy, S. (2018). True morels (Morchella)—Nutritional and phytochemical composition, health benefits and flavor: A review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 58(11), 1888–1901.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ullah, T. S., Firdous, S. S., Shier, W. T., Hussain, J., Shaheen, H., Usman, M., Akram, M., &amp; Khalid, A. N. (2022). Diversity and ethnomycological importance of mushrooms from Western Himalayas Kashmir. Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine, 18(1), 32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White, T. J., Bruns, T., Lee, S., Taylor, J. (1990). Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal RNA genes for phylogenetics. In: Innis MA, Gelfand DH, Sninsky JJ, White TJ, eds. PCR protocols: a guide to methods and applications. New York: Academic Press. p. 315–322.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>