<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39218813</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>89</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficacy of Lacticaseibacillus paracasei fermented milk on a model of constipation induced by loperamide hydrochloride in BALB/c mice.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>6733</StartPage><EndPage>6744</EndPage><MedlinePgn>6733-6744</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17338</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Currently, most studies focus on the functions of probiotic-fermented milk, whereas there are relatively few studies on the function of postbiotic-fermented milk in relieving constipation. In this study, we aimed to assess the modulation of constipation symptoms and its mechanism of action by different concentrations of Lacticaseibacillus paracasei-fermented milk as a postbiotic in a loperamide hydrochloride-induced constipation model in BALB/c mice. By comparing the relevant indexes, colon histological analysis, gene expression level, and intestinal flora structure in the constipation model of mice, we found that high and ultra-high doses of fermented milk can effectively relieve constipation. Fermented milk effectively reduced defecation time, increased the rate of small intestinal propulsion in constipated mice, and alleviated colonic inflammation, safeguarding the normal function of the intestinal tract. In addition, it can regulate the intestinal flora, downregulate the abundance of Proteobacteria, upregulate the abundance of species of Firmicutes and Actinobacteriota, and improve the overall abundance level of intestinal flora in mice.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xue</LastName><ForeName>Cheng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hunan Haoyiduo Dairy Co., Ltd, Changsha, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Ming</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Market Supervision and Administration Service Center of Lijin County, Dongying, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Min</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dongying Yidayao Dairy Co., Ltd, Dongying, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Baoping</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hunan Haoyiduo Dairy Co., Ltd, Changsha, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yifan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8378-5856</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety Key Laboratory of Zhejiang Province, School of Food Science and Biotechnology, Zhejiang Gongshang University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>6X9OC3H4II</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D008139">Loperamide</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008139" MajorTopicYN="Y">Loperamide</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003248" MajorTopicYN="Y">Constipation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000139" MajorTopicYN="N">chemically induced</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000178" MajorTopicYN="N">diet therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008807" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mice, Inbred BALB C</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Gastrointestinal Microbiome</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019936" MajorTopicYN="Y">Probiotics</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004195" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Models, Animal</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069980" MajorTopicYN="Y">Lacticaseibacillus paracasei</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005285" MajorTopicYN="N">Fermentation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D043302" MajorTopicYN="N">Cultured Milk Products</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003106" MajorTopicYN="N">Colon</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008892" MajorTopicYN="N">Milk</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003672" MajorTopicYN="N">Defecation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lacticaseibacillus paracasei</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">constipation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fermented milk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gut microbiota</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39218813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abbasi, A., Rad, A. H., Ghasempour, Z., Sabahi, S., Kafil, H. S., Hasannezhad, P., Saadat, Y. R., &amp; Shahbazi, N. (2022). The biological activities of postbiotics in gastrointestinal disorders. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 62, 8247. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2021.1922741</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattarai, Y., Williams, B. B., Battaglioli, E. J., Whitaker, W. R., Till, L., Grover, M., Linden, D. R., Akiba, Y., Kandimalla, K. K., Zachos, N. C., Kaunitz, J. D., Sonnenburg, J. L., Fischbach, M. A., Farrugia, G., &amp; Kashyap, P. C. (2018). Gut microbiota‐produced tryptamine activates an epithelial G‐protein‐coupled receptor to increase colonic secretion. Cell Host, &amp; Microbe, 23, 775–785. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2018.05.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botelho, P. B., Ferreira, M. V. R., Araújo, A. D., Mendes, M. M., &amp; Nakano, E. Y. (2020). Effect of multispecies probiotic on gut microbiota composition in individuals with intestinal constipation: A double‐blind, placebo‐ controlled randomized trial. Nutrition, 78, 110890. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nut.2020.110890</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, Y., He, Y., Wei, C., Li, J., Qu, L., Zhang, H., Cheng, Y., &amp; Qiao, B. (2018). Aquaporins alteration profiles revealed different actions of Senna, sennosides, and sennoside a in diarrhea‐rats. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 19, 3210. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms19103210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chai, M., Wang, L., Li, X., Zhao, J., Zhang, H., Wang, G., &amp; Chen, W. (2021). Different Bifidobacterium bifidum strains change the intestinal flora composition of mice via different mechanisms to alleviate loperamide‐induced constipation. Food, &amp; Function, 12, 6058–6069. https://doi.org/10.1039/d1fo00559f</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, S., Li, B., Ding, Y., Hou, B., Hung, W., He, J., Jiang, Y., Zhang, Y., &amp; Man, C. (2024). The probiotic fermented milk of Lacticaseibacillus paracasei JY062 and Lactobacillus gasseri JM1 alleviates constipation via improving gastrointestinal motility and gut microbiota. Journal of Dairy Science, 107, 1857–1876. https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.2023‐24154</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, J. H., Moon, C. M., Shin, T. S., Kim, E. K., McDowell, A., Jo, M. K., Joo, Y. H., Kim, S. E., Jung, H. K., Shim, K. N., Jung, S. A., &amp; Kim, Y. K. (2020). Lactobacillus paracasei‐derived extracellular vesicles attenuate the intestinal inflammatory response by augmenting the endoplasmic reticulum stress pathway. Experimental and Molecular Medicine, 52, 423–437. https://doi.org/10.1038/s12276‐019‐0359‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuevas‐González, P. F., Liceaga, A. M., &amp; Aguilar‐Toalá, J. E. (2020). Postbiotics and paraprobiotics: From concepts to applications. Food Research International, 136, 109502. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109502</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damodharan, K., Arunachalam Palaniyandi, S., Suh, J.‐W., &amp; Yang, S. H. (2020). Probiotic characterization of Lactobacillus paracasei subsp. paracasei KNI9 inhibiting adherence of Yersinia enterocolitica on Caco‐2 cells in vitro. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins, 12, 600–607. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12602‐019‐09535‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, X., Hu, Y., Tao, Y., Liu, S., Chen, H., Li, J., Zhao, Y., Sheng, J., Tian, Y., &amp; Fan, Y. (2022). Cymbopogon citratus (DC.) Stapf aqueous extract ameliorates loperamide‐induced constipation in mice by promoting gastrointestinal motility and regulating the gut microbiota. Frontiers in Microbiology, 13, 1017804. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.1017804</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, Y., Song, L., Huang, Y., Li, X., Xiao, Y., Wang, Z., &amp; Ren, Z. (2023). Latilactobacillus sakei Furu2019 and stachyose as probiotics, prebiotics, and synbiotics alleviate constipation in mice. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, 1039403. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.1039403</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iancu, M. A., Profir, M., Roşu, O. A., Ionescu, R. F., Cretoiu, S. M., &amp; Gaspar, B. S. (2023). Revisiting the intestinal microbiome and its role in diarrhea and constipation. Microorganisms, 11(9), 2177. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms11092177.10.3390/microorganisms11092177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iljazovic, A., Roy, U., Gálvez, E. J. C., Lesker, T. R., Zhao, B., Gronow, A., Amend, L., Will, S. E., Hofmann, J. D., Pils, M. C., Schmidt‐Hohagen, K., Neumann‐Schaal, M., &amp; Strowig, T. (2021). Perturbation of the gut microbiome by Prevotella spp. enhances host susceptibility to mucosal inflammation. Mucosal Immunology, 14, 113–124. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41385‐020‐0296‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, K.‐Y., Tsai, Y.‐C., Wang, S.‐Y., Chen, Y.‐P., &amp; Chen, M.‐J. (2021). Coculture strategy for developing Lactobacillus paracasei PS23 fermented milk with anti‐colitis effect. Foods, 10, 2337. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10102337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lembo, A. (2023). Chronic constipation. In Handbook of gastrointestinal motility and disorders of gut‐brain interactions (pp. 263–276). Academic Press Inc. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐443‐13911‐6.00009‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, Y. X., Wei, X. Y., Deng, J., Peng, C., Ren, R., Luo, Y. Y., Zhang, J. X., Wei, X. Q., Hardiman, G., Sun, Y. M., &amp; Wang, H. (2023). Integrating omics and network pharmacology reveals the anti‐constipation role of chitosan with different molecular weights in constipated mice. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 235, 123930. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.123930</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, C.‐J., Tang, X.‐D., Yu, J., Zhang, H.‐Y., &amp; Li, X.‐R. (2017). Gut microbiota alterations from different Lactobacillus probiotic‐fermented yoghurt treatments in slow‐transit constipation. Journal of Functional Foods, 38, 110–118. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2017.08.037</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maharshak, N., Packey, C. D., Ellermann, M., Manick, S., Siddle, J. P., Huh, E. Y., Plevy, S., Sartor, R. B., &amp; Carroll, I. M. (2013). Altered enteric microbiota ecology in interleukin 10‐deficient mice during development and progression of intestinal inflammation. Gut Microbes, 4, 316–324. https://doi.org/10.4161/gmic.25486</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noda, M., Danshiitsoodol, N., Kanno, K., Uchida, T., &amp; Sugiyama, M. (2021). The exopolysaccharide produced by Lactobacillus paracasei IJH‐SONE68 prevents and ameliorates inflammatory responses in DSS‐induced ulcerative colitis. Microorganisms, 9, 2243. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms9112243</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S.‐H., Lee, M.‐R., Yang, S. Y., Lee, J. Y., Lee, H. H., Seong, Y.‐J., Kim, B., Kim, H.‐J., Jin, H., Johnston, T. V., Ku, S., &amp; Park, M. S. (2022). In vivo functional effects of Weissella confusa VP30 exopolysaccharides on loperamide‐induced constipation in rats. Food Science and Biotechnology, 31, 1703–1715. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10068‐022‐01159‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao, Y. T., Qiu, Z. C., Tian, F. W., Yu, L. L., Zhao, J. X., Zhang, H., Zhai, Q. X., &amp; Chen, W. (2021). Pediococcus acidilactici strains improve constipation symptoms and regulate intestinal flora in mice. Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology, 11, 655258. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcimb.2021.655258</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu, B., Zhu, L., Zhang, S., Han, S., Fei, Y., Ba, F., Berglund, B., Li, L., &amp; Yao, M. (2023). Prevention of loperamide‐induced constipation in mice and alteration of 5‐hydroxytryotamine signaling by Ligilactobacillus salivarius Li01. Nutrients, 14, 4083. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu14194083</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabahi, S., Rad, A. H., Aghebati‐Maleki, L., Sangtarash, N., Ozma, M. A., Karimi, A., Hosseini, H., &amp; Abbasi, A. (2023). Postbiotics as the new frontier in food and pharmaceutical research. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 63, 8375–8402. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2022.2056727</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salminen, S., Collado, M. C., Endo, A., Hill, C., Lebeer, S., Quigley, E. M. M., Sanders, M. E., Shamir, R., Swann, J. R., Szajewska, H., &amp; Vinderola, G. (2021). The International Scientific Association of Probiotics and Prebiotics (ISAPP) consensus statement on the definition and scope of postbiotics. Nature Reviews Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology, 18, 671. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41575‐021‐00481‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin, N.‐R., Whon, T. W., &amp; Bae, J.‐W. (2015). Proteobacteria: Microbial signature of dysbiosis in gut microbiota. Trends in Biotechnology, 33, 496–503. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tibtech.2015.06.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, T. K., &amp; Gershon, M. D. (2015). CrossTalk proposal: 5‐HT is necessary for peristalsis. Journal of Physiology‐London, 593, 3225–3227. https://doi.org/10.1113/JP270182</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, K. Y., Xu, D. H., Xie, C., Plummer, S., Tang, J., Yang, X. F., &amp; Ji, X. H. (2017). Lactobacillus paracasei modulates LPS‐induced inflammatory cytokine release by monocyte‐macrophages via the up‐regulation of negative regulators of NF‐kappaB signaling in a TLR2‐dependent manner. Cytokine, 92, 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cyto.2017.01.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suzuki, H., Yamazaki, T., Ohshio, K., Sugamata, M., Yoshikawa, M., Kanauchi, O., &amp; Morita, Y. (2020). A specific strain of lactic acid bacteria, Lactobacillus paracasei, inhibits inflammasome activation in vitro and prevents inflammation‐related disorders. Journal of Immunology, 205, 811–821. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1900657</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teame, T., Wang, A., Xie, M., Zhang, Z., Yang, Y., Ding, Q., Gao, C., Olsen, R. E., Ran, C., &amp; Zhou, Z. (2020). Paraprobiotics and postbiotics of probiotic Lactobacilli, their positive effects on the host and action mechanisms: A review. Frontiers in Nutrition, 7, 570344. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2020.570344</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, B., Kong, Q., Li, X., Zhao, J., Zhang, H., Chen, W., &amp; Wang, G. (2020). A high‐fat diet increases gut microbiota biodiversity and energy expenditure due to nutrient difference. Nutrients, 12, 3197. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12103197</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Liang, Q., Zhao, Q., Tang, Q., Ahmed, A. F., Zhang, Y., &amp; Kang, W. (2021). The effect of microbial composition and proteomic on improvement of functional constipation by Chrysanthemum morifolium polysaccharide. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 153, 112305. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2021.112305</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J. K., Wei, W., Zhao, D. Y., Wang, H. F., Zhang, Y. L., Lei, J. P., &amp; Yao, S. K. (2022). Intestinal mucosal barrier in functional constipation: Dose it change? World Journal of Clinical Cases, 10, 6385–6398. https://doi.org/10.12998/wjcc.v10.i19.6385</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Chai, M., Wang, J., YU, Q., Wang, G., Zhang, H., Zhao, J., &amp; Chen, W. (2022). Bifidobacterium longum relieves constipation by regulating the intestinal barrier of mice. Food &amp; Function, 13, 5037–5049. https://doi.org/10.1039/D1FO04151G</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Hu, L., Yan, S., Jiang, T., Fang, S., Wang, G., Zhao, J., Zhang, H., &amp; Chena, W. (2017). Effects of different oligosaccharides at various dosages on the composition of gut microbiota and short‐chain fatty acids in mice with constipation. Food &amp; Function, 8, 1966–1978. https://doi.org/10.1039/C7FO00031F</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Chen, S., Wang, C., Zhang, Y., Zeng, H., Fu, L., &amp; Wang, Y. (2024). Oral administration of Bacillus coagulans TQ‐35 alleviates allergic responses in OVA‐sensitive BALB/c mice. Food Science and Human Wellness, 13, 1246–1257. https://doi.org/10.26599/FSHW.2022.9250104</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, L., Tang, C., Chen, L., &amp; Zhao, J. (2023). Modified dietary fiber from soybean dregs by fermentation alleviated constipation in mice. Food Chemistry: X, 19, 100810. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fochx.2023.100810</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamazaki, T., Ohshio, K., Sugamata, M., &amp; Morita, Y. (2020). Lactic acid bacterium, Lactobacillus paracasei KW3110, suppresses inflammatory stress‐induced caspase‐1 activation by promoting interleukin‐10 production in mouse and human immune cells. PloS ONE, 15, e0237754. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0237754</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamazaki, T., Yamada, S., Ohshio, K., Sugamata, M., &amp; Morita, Y. (2022). Lactobacillus paracasei KW3110 prevents inflammatory‐stress‐induced mitochondrial dysfunction in mouse macrophages. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 23, 1443. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms23031443</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, L., Wang, Y., Zhang, Y., Li, W., Jiang, S., Qian, D., &amp; Duan, J. (2022). Gut microbiota: A new avenue to reveal pathological mechanisms of constipation. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 106, 6899–6913. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253‐022‐12197‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao, Y., Cai, X., Fei, W., Ye, Y., Zhao, M., &amp; Zheng, C. (2022). The role of short‐chain fatty acids in immunity, inflammation and metabolism. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 62, 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2020.1854675</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye, Y., Ran, J., Yang, B., &amp; Mei, Z. (2023). Aquaporins in digestive system. In B. Yang (Ed.), Aquaporins (2nd ed., pp. 145–154). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi, X., Zhou, K., Jiang, P., Deng, N., Peng, X., &amp; Tan, Z. (2023). Brain‐bacteria‐gut axis and oxidative stress mediated by intestinal mucosal microbiota might be an important mechanism for constipation in mice. 3 Biotech, 13, 192. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13205‐023‐03580‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, J., Guo, H., Sun, M., Jiang, C., Jiang, S., Mu, G., Tuo, Y., &amp; Gao, P. (2023). Milk fermented by combined starter cultures comprising three Lactobacillus strains exerts an alleviating effect on loperamide‐induced constipation in BALB/c mice. Food &amp; Function, 14, 5264–5276. https://doi.org/10.1039/d3fo00222e</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M. M., &amp; Wu, C. C. (2020). The relationship between intestinal goblet cells and the immune response. Bioscience Reports, 40, BSR20201471. https://doi.org/10.1042/BSR20201471</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, S., Wang, R., Li, D., Zhao, L., &amp; Zhu, L. (2021). Role of gut microbiota in functional constipation. Gastroenterology Report, 9, 392–401. https://doi.org/10.1093/gastro/goab035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X., Chen, S., Zhang, M., Ren, F., Ren, Y., Li, Y., Liu, N., Zhang, Y., Zhang, Q., &amp; Wang, R. (2021). Effects of fermented milk containing Lacticaseibacillus paracasei strain shirota on constipation in patients with depression: A randomized, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled trial. Nutrients, 13, 2238. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13072238</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, G. X., Li, J., Wang, J. Y., Shen, X. Z., &amp; Sun, J. Y. (2014). Aquaporin 3 and 8 are down‐regulated in TNBS‐induced rat colitis. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, 443, 161–166. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2013.11.067</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>