<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39217509</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Blockchain implementation for food safety in supply chain: A review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70002</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70002</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70002</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Food safety has emerged as the topmost priority in the current fast-paced food industry era. According to the World Health Organization, around 600 million people, approximately 1 in 10 individuals worldwide, experience illness due to contaminated food consumption, resulting in nearly 0.42 million fatalities annually. The recent development in software and hardware sectors has created opportunities to improve the safety concerns in the food supply chain. The objective of this review is to explain the fundamentals of blockchain and its integration into the supply chain of various food commodities to enhance food safety. This paper presents the analysis of 31 conceptual works, 10 implementation works, 39 case studies, and other investigations in blockchain-based food supply chain from a total of 80 published papers. In this paper, the significance of adapting conceptual ideas into practical applications for effectively tracing food commodities throughout the supply chain has been discussed. This paper also describes the transformative role of blockchain platforms in the food industry, providing a decentralized and transparent ledger to access real-time and immutable records of a product's journey. In addition, both the positive impacts and challenges associated with implementing blockchain technology in the food supply chain have been evaluated. In summary, the blockchain-based food supply chains offer greater transparency, traceability, and trust, ultimately resulting in higher standards of food safety and quality.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sri Vigna Hema</LastName><ForeName>V</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Engineering, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manickavasagan</LastName><ForeName>Annamalai</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2562-9772</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Engineering, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Canada First Research Excellence Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059022" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Safety</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005523" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Supply</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000592" MajorTopicYN="N">standards</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000081186" MajorTopicYN="Y">Blockchain</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blockchain</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food supply chain</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food traceability</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39217509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Akbar, A., Rakhmawati, N. A., &amp; Vanany, I. (2022). Halal blockchain application for a chicken slaughtering factory. International Journal on Food System Dynamics, 13(3), 321–334.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhavan, P., &amp; Philsoophian, M. (2022). Improving of supply chain collaboration and performance by using block chain technology as a mediating role and resilience as a moderating variable. Journal of the Knowledge Economy, 14, 4561–4582.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali, M. H., Chung, L., Kumar, A., Zailani, S., &amp; Tan, K. H. (2021). A sustainable Blockchain framework for the halal food supply chain: Lessons from Malaysia. Technological Forecasting and Social Change, 170, 120870.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonopoulos, A. M., &amp; Harding, D. A. (2023). Mastering bitcoin. O'Reilly Media, Inc.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behnke, K., &amp; Janssen, M. F. W. H. A. (2020). Boundary conditions for traceability in food supply chains using blockchain technology. International Journal of Information Management, 52, 101969.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat, M. S., &amp; Dubey, S. (2023). An overview of the effects of blockchain technology in food chain supply: A case study on Walmart. The Online Journal of Distance Education and e‐Learning, 11(2), 1205–1209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilal, M., &amp; Kamran, M. U. (2023). Blockchain‐based soft drinks supply chain traceability by using hash algorithm. Journal of NCBAE, 2(2), 42–58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bumblauskas, D., Mann, A., Dugan, B., &amp; Rittmer, J. (2020). A blockchain use case in food distribution: Do you know where your food has been? International Journal of Information Management, 52, 102008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Busse, M., &amp; Springer, S. (2023). Grocery delivery in the united states: Trying to bag profits. Kellogg School of Management.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caltagirone, J. A., &amp; Psrkinson, T. (2000). Peapod on supply chain: How e‐commerce changed the traditional logistics model [Conference presentation]. The Council of Logistics Management Fall Meeting, Council of Logistics Management, New Orleans, LA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, S., Foth, M., Powell, W., Miller, T., &amp; Li, M. (2022). A blockchain‐based multisignature approach for supply chain governance: A use case from the Australian beef industry. Blockchain: Research and Applications, 3(4), 100091.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, S., Powell, W., Foth, M., Natanelov, V., Miller, T., &amp; Dulleck, U. (2021). Strengthening consumer trust in beef supply chain traceability with a blockchain‐based human‐machine reconcile mechanism. Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, 180, 105886.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caro, M. P., Ali, M. S., Vecchio, M., &amp; Giaffreda, R. (2018). Blockchain‐based traceability in agri‐food supply chain management: A practical implementation [Conference presentation]. The 2018 IoT Vertical and Topical Summit on Agriculture‐Tuscany (IOT Tuscany), Tuscany, Italy.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casino, F., Kanakaris, V., Dasaklis, T. K., Moschuris, S., Stachtiaris, S., Pagoni, M., &amp; Rachaniotis, N. P. (2021). Blockchain‐based food supply chain traceability: A case study in the dairy sector. International Journal of Production Research, 59(19), 5758–5770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Champion, D., Stevens, B., Ward, R., &amp; Kerridge, A. (2018). Can the ‘blockchain’ contribute to achieving global food security? A report for the Science and Technology Facilities Council, UK Research and Innovation. 1–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandan, A., John, M., &amp; Potdar, V. (2023). Achieving UN SDGs in food supply chain using blockchain technology. Sustainability, 15(3), 2109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang, Y., Iakovou, E., &amp; Shi, W. (2020). Blockchain in global supply chains and cross border trade: A critical synthesis of the state‐of‐the‐art, challenges and opportunities. International Journal of Production Research, 58(7), 2082–2099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, S., Liu, X., Yan, J., Hu, G., &amp; Shi, Y. (2021). Processes, benefits, and challenges for adoption of blockchain technologies in food supply chains: A thematic analysis. Information Systems and e‐Business Management, 19, 909–935.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua, C. S., &amp; Yoo, C. A. (2018). Future of grocery retail shopping: Challenges and opportunities in e‐commerce grocery shopping. Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cocco, L., Mannaro, K., Tonelli, R., Mariani, L., Lodi, M. B., Melis, A., Simone, M., &amp; Fanti, A. (2021). A blockchain‐based traceability system in agri‐food SME: Case study of a traditional bakery. IEEE Access, 9, 62899–62915.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Compagnucci, L., Lepore, D., Spigarelli, F., Frontoni, E., Baldi, M., &amp; Di Berardino, L. (2022). Uncovering the potential of blockchain in the agri‐food supply chain: An interdisciplinary case study. Journal of Engineering and Technology Management, 65, 101700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Courtemanche, C., &amp; Carden, A. (2014). Competing with Costco and Sam's Club: Warehouse club entry and grocery prices. Southern Economic Journal, 80(3), 565–585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz, E. F., &amp; da Cruz, A. M. R. (2020). Using blockchain to implement traceability on fishery value chain. ICSOFT, 1195, 501–508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dani, S. (2021). Food supply chain management and logistics: Understanding the challenges of production, operation and sustainability in the food industry. Kogan Page Publishers.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demestichas, K., Peppes, N., Alexakis, T., &amp; Adamopoulou, E. (2020). Blockchain in agriculture traceability systems: A review. Applied Sciences, 10(12), 4113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey, S., Saha, S., Singh, A., &amp; McDonald‐Maier, K. (2022). SmartNoshWaste: Using blockchain, machine learning, cloud computing and QR code to reduce food waste in decentralized web 3.0 enabled smart cities. Smart Cities, 5, 162–176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dillahunt, T. R., Simioni, S., &amp; Xu, X. (2019). Online grocery delivery services: An opportunity to address food disparities in transportation‐scarce areas [Conference presentation]. the Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Glasgow, UK, Article 4, 1–15. https://doi.org/10.1145/3290605.3300879</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan, J., Zhang, C., Gong, Y., Brown, S., &amp; Li, Z. (2020). A content‐analysis based literature review in blockchain adoption within food supply chain. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17(5), 1784.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eletter, S. F., Elrefae, G. A., Yasmin, T., Qasem, A., Alshehadeh, A. R., &amp; Belarbi, A. (2022). Leveraging blockchain‐based smart contracts in the management of supply chain: Evidence from Carrefour UAE [Conference presentation]. The 2022 International Arab Conference on Information Technology (ACIT), Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esper, T. L. (2021). Supply chain management amid the coronavirus pandemic. Journal of Public Policy &amp; Marketing, 40(1), 101–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fahmi, A., Maqbool, Z., Amin, F., &amp; Aslam, M. (2023). Blockchain knowledge selection under the trapezoidal fermatean fuzzy number. Soft Computing, 27(7), 3601–3621.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, C., &amp; Stone, W. Z. (2021). An ecosystem for the dairy logistics supply chain with blockchain technology [Conference presentation]. The 2021 International Conference on Electrical, Computer, Communications and Mechatronics Engineering (ICECCME), Mauritius, Mauritius.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farooq, M. S., Riaz, S., Rehman, I. U., Khan, M. A., &amp; Hassan, B. (2023). A blockchain‐based framework to make the rice crop supply chain transparent and reliable in agriculture. Systems, 11(9), 476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, H., Wang, X., Duan, Y., Zhang, J., &amp; Zhang, X. (2020). Applying blockchain technology to improve agri‐food traceability: A review of development methods, benefits and challenges. Journal of Cleaner Production, 260, 121031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, Y., Yan, W., Zuo, M., &amp; Zhang, Q. (2022). Consortium blockchains based traceability system for chicken product supply chain [Conference presentation]. The MATEC Web of Conferences. 355, 02037. https://doi.org/10.1051/matecconf/202235502037</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferdousi, T., Gruenbacher, D., &amp; Scoglio, C. M. (2020). A permissioned distributed ledger for the US beef cattle supply chain. IEEE Access, 8, 154833–154847.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Folha, R., Times, V., Carvalho, A., Araújo, A., Couto, H., &amp; Viana, F. (2022). FoodChain: A food delivery platform based on blockchain for keeping data privacy [Conference presentation]. The International Conference on Database Systems for Advanced Applications (pp. 500–504). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, H., Zhao, C., Cheng, C., &amp; Ma, H. (2020). Blockchain‐based agri‐food supply chain management: Case study in China. International Food and Agribusiness Management Review, 23(5), 667–680.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gad, A. G., Mosa, D. T., Abualigah, L., &amp; Abohany, A. A. (2022). Emerging trends in blockchain technology and applications: A review and outlook. Journal of King Saud University‐Computer and Information Sciences, 34(9), 6719–6742. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jksuci.2022.03.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galvez, J. F., Mejuto, J. C., &amp; Simal‐Gandara, J. (2018). Future challenges on the use of blockchain for food traceability analysis. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 107, 222–232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharehgozli, A., Iakovou, E., Chang, Y., &amp; Swaney, R. (2017). Trends in global E‐food supply chain and implications for transport: Literature review and research directions. Research in Transportation Business &amp; Management, 25, 2–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González‐Puetate, I., Marín Tello, C. L., &amp; Reyes Pineda, H. (2022). Agri‐food safety optimized by blockchain technology. Revista Facultad Nacional De Agronomía Medellín, 75(1), 9839–9851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, J., Cengiz, K., &amp; Tomar, R. (2021). An IOT and Blockchain approach for food traceability system in agriculture. Scalable Computing: Practice and Experience, 22(2), 127–137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harriman, C., Diaz‐Infante, M., Loayza, T., Lee, S., Detwiler, K., &amp; Awwad, M. (2020). Effects of the COVID‐19 pandemic on the grocery retail supply chains [Conference presentation]. The 5th International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Operations Management, IEOM Society, Michigan, USA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayati, H., &amp; Nugraha, I. G. B. B. (2018). Blockchain based traceability system in food supply chain [Conference presentation]. The 2018 International Seminar on Research of Information Technology and Intelligent Systems (ISRITI), Yogyakarta, Indonesia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hays, T., Keskinocak, P., &amp; De López, V. M. (2005). Strategies and challenges of internet grocery retailing logistics. Applications of supply chain management and e‐commerce research (pp. 217–252). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellani, H. (2022). Reliable platform using distributed ledger technology for IoT‐based industrial environment. Université de Pau et des Pays de l'Adour.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellani, H., Sliman, L., Samhat, A. E., &amp; Exposito, E. (2021). On blockchain integration with supply chain: Overview on data transparency. Logistics, 5(3), 46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hidayati, J., Vamelia, R., Hammami, J., &amp; Endri, E. (2023). Transparent distribution system design of halal beef supply chain. Uncertain Supply Chain Management, 11(1), 31–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobbs, J. E. (2020). Food supply chains during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Canadian Journal of Agricultural Economics/Revue Canadienne D'agroeconomie, 68(2), 171–176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howson, P. (2020). Building trust and equity in marine conservation and fisheries supply chain management with blockchain. Marine Policy, 115, 103873.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huo, H., &amp; Rui, Y. (2021). The assessment of Costco management strategy in Chinese market based on supply chain [Conference presentation]. The 2021 International Conference on E‐Commerce and E‐Management (ICECEM), Dalian, China.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivanov, D., Dolgui, A., &amp; Sokolov, B. (2019). The impact of digital technology and Industry 4.0 on the ripple effect and supply chain risk analytics. International Journal of Production Research, 57(3), 829–846.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin, N., &amp; Saucier, C. (2016). ripe.io: Reconnecting the food supply chain.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson, W. G. (2019). Blockchain meets genomics: Governance considerations for promoting food safety and public health. Journal of Food Law &amp; Policy, 15, 74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamath, R. (2018). Food traceability on blockchain: Walmart's pork and mango pilots with IBM. The Journal of the British Blockchain Association, 1(1), 1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamilaris, A., Fonts, A., &amp; Prenafeta‐Boldύ, F. X. (2019). The rise of blockchain technology in agriculture and food supply chains. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 91, 640–652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kampan, K., Tsusaka, T. W., &amp; Anal, A. K. (2022). Adoption of blockchain technology for enhanced traceability of livestock‐based products. Sustainability, 14(20), 13148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasten, J. (2019). Blockchain application: The dairy supply chain. Journal of Supply Chain Management Systems, 8(1), 45–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katsikouli, P., Wilde, A. S., Dragoni, N., &amp; Høgh‐Jensen, H. (2021). On the benefits and challenges of blockchains for managing food supply chains. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 101(6), 2175–2181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawaguchi, N. (2019). Application of blockchain to supply chain: Flexible blockchain technology. Procedia Computer Science, 164, 143–148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanna, A., Jain, S., Burgio, A., Bolshev, V., &amp; Panchenko, V. (2022). Blockchain‐enabled supply chain platform for Indian dairy industry: Safety and traceability. Foods, 11(17), 2716.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Köhler, S., &amp; Pizzol, M. (2020). Technology assessment of blockchain‐based technologies in the food supply chain. Journal of Cleaner Production, 269, 122193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer, M. P., Bitsch, L., &amp; Hanf, J. (2021). Blockchain and its impacts on agri‐food supply chain network management. Sustainability, 13(4), 2168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kravenkit, S., &amp; So‐In, C. (2022). Blockchain‐based traceability system for product recall. IEEE Access, 10, 95132–95150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kshetri, N. (2019). Blockchain and the economics of food safety. IEEE IT Professional, 21(3), 63–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kshetri, N. (2023). Blockchains with Chinese characteristics. Blockchain in the global south: Opportunities and challenges for businesses and societies (pp. 83–111). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kshetri, N., &amp; Defranco, J. (2020). The economics behind food supply blockchains. Computer, 53(12), 106–110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, A., Liu, R., &amp; Shan, Z. (2020). Is blockchain a silver bullet for supply chain management? Technical challenges and research opportunities. Decision Sciences, 51(1), 8–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larissa, S., &amp; Parung, J. (2021). Designing supply chain models with blockchain technology in the fishing industry in Indonesia. The IOP Conference Series: Materials Science and Engineering, 1072, 012020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leow, P. Y. (2023). Ingredients tracing using blockchain for rapid product recall. UTAR.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung, H. W., Chapman, A., &amp; Fadhel, N. F. (2021). Identifying food fraud using blockchain. The IoTBDS (pp. 185–192). SCITEPRESS – Science and Technology Publications, Lda.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, K., Lee, J.‐Y., &amp; Gharehgozli, A. (2023). Blockchain in food supply chains: A literature review and synthesis analysis of platforms, benefits and challenges. International Journal of Production Research, 61(11), 3527–3546.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, X., Chang, S.‐C., Chou, T.‐H., Chen, S.‐C., &amp; Ruangkanjanases, A. (2021). Consumers’ intention to adopt blockchain food traceability technology towards organic food products. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 18(3), 912.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, H., Dong, J., &amp; Ge, S. (2021). Traceability system for rare Chinese herbal medicines based on blockchain structure [Conference presentation]. The 2021 3rd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Advanced Manufacture (AIAM), Manchester, United Kingdom.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longo, F., Nicoletti, L., &amp; Padovano, A. (2019). Estimating the impact of blockchain adoption in the food processing industry and supply chain. International Journal of Food Engineering, 16(5–6), 20190109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mangla, S. K., Kazancoglu, Y., Ekinci, E., Liu, M., Özbiltekin, M., &amp; Sezer, M. D. (2021). Using system dynamics to analyze the societal impacts of blockchain technology in milk supply chainsrefer. Transportation Research Part E: Logistics and Transportation Review, 149, 102289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maouriyan, N., &amp; Krishna, A. A. (2019). Notice of violation of IEEE publication principles: AQUACHAIN‐water supply‐chain management using distributed ledger technology [Conference presentation]. The 2019 3rd International Conference on Computing and Communications Technologies (ICCCT), Chennai, India.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meidayanti, K., &amp; Arkeman, Y., &amp; Sugiarto (2019). Analysis and design of beef supply chain traceability system based on blockchain technology. The IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science, 335, 012012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michelson, H., Boucher, S., Cheng, X., Huang, J., &amp; Jia, X. (2018). Connecting supermarkets and farms: The role of intermediaries in Walmart China's fresh produce supply chains. Renewable Agriculture and Food Systems, 33(1), 47–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirabelli, G., &amp; Solina, V. (2020). Blockchain and agricultural supply chains traceability: Research trends and future challenges. Procedia Manufacturing, 42, 414–421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miraz, M. H., Gazi, M. A. I., &amp; Hasan, M. T. (2023). Fruits supply chain management using blockchain: A theoretic operation. Journal of Survey in Fisheries Sciences, 10(1S), 5438–5450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narayanan, A., Bonneau, J., Felten, E., Miller, A., &amp; Goldfeder, S. (2021). Bitcoin and cryptocurrency technologies. Curso Elaborado Pela, 1(1), 1–308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natanelov, V., Cao, S., Foth, M., &amp; Dulleck, U. (2022). Blockchain smart contracts for supply chain finance: Mapping the innovation potential in Australia‐China beef supply chains. Journal of Industrial Information Integration, 30, 100389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen, H., &amp; Do, L. (2018). The adoption of blockchain in food retail supply chain: Case: IBM food trust blockchain and the food retail supply chain in Malta, Autumn, 1–158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niya, S. R., Dordevic, D., Hurschler, M., Grossenbacher, S., &amp; Stiller, B. (2021). A blockchain‐based supply chain tracing for the Swiss dairy use case [Conference presentation]. The 2020 2nd International Conference on Societal Automation (SA), Funchal, Portugal.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nurgazina, J., Pakdeetrakulwong, U., Moser, T., &amp; Reiner, G. (2021). Distributed ledger technology applications in food supply chains: A review of challenges and future research directions. Sustainability, 13(8), 4206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel, A. S., Brahmbhatt, M. N., Bariya, A. R., Nayak, J. B., &amp; Singh, V. K. (2023). Blockchain technology in food safety and traceability concern to livestock products. Heliyon, 9(6), e16526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patro, P. K., Jayaraman, R., Salah, K., &amp; Yaqoob, I. (2022). Blockchain‐based traceability for the fishery supply chain. IEEE Access, 10, 81134–81154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson, S., May, D., Leontidis, G., Swainson, M., Brewer, S., Bidaut, L., Frey, J. G., Parr, G., Maull, R., &amp; Zisman, A. (2019). Are distributed ledger technologies the panacea for food traceability? Global Food Security, 20, 145–149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, X., Zhang, X., Wang, X., Li, H., Xu, J., &amp; Zhao, Z. (2022a). Construction of rice supply chain supervision model driven by blockchain smart contract. Scientific Reports, 12(1), 20984.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, X., Zhang, X., Wang, X., Li, H., Xu, J., &amp; Zhao, Z. (2022b). Multi‐chain collaboration‐based information management and control for the rice supply chain. Agriculture, 12(5), 689.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, X., Zhang, X., Wang, X., Li, H., Xu, J., Zhao, Z., &amp; Wang, Y. (2022c). Research on the cross‐chain model of rice supply chain supervision based on parallel blockchain and smart contracts. Foods, 11(9), 1269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, X., Zhang, X., Wang, X., Xu, J., Li, H., Zhao, Z., &amp; Qi, Z. (2022). A refined supervision model of rice supply chain based on multi‐blockchain. Foods, 11(18), 2785.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Persaud, T. (2022). Analyzing Costco's supply chain responsiveness through lean and agile strategies, Major research papers 2021‐2022, YorkSpace, York University's Institutional Repository, 1–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham, C., Nguyen, T.‐T., Adamopoulos, A., &amp; Tait, E. (2022). Blockchain‐enabled traceability in sustainable food supply chains: A case study of the pork industry in Vietnam. Information systems research in Vietnam: A shared vision and new frontiers (pp. 65–81). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Provenance. (2024). Drive growth with sustainability claims shoppers can trust. https://www.provenance.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian, J., Ruiz‐Garcia, L., Fan, B., Villalba, J. I. R., McCarthy, U., Zhang, B., Yu, Q., &amp; Wu, W. (2020). Food traceability system from governmental, corporate, and consumer perspectives in the European Union and China: A comparative review. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 99, 402–412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Queiroz, M. M., Fosso Wamba, S., De Bourmont, M., &amp; Telles, R. (2021). Blockchain adoption in operations and supply chain management: Empirical evidence from an emerging economy. International Journal of Production Research, 59(20), 1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafiq, A., Younus, M. U., Ali, A., Hamza, M., &amp; Ahmed, U. (2021). Web‐based wheat tracker system using blockchain in agriculture. Journal of Agricultural Research, 59(4), 389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rai, A., Shaikh, S., &amp; Vishwakarma, R. (2021). Secure grocery recommendation system using blockchain. Journal on Software Engineering, 16(1), 23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rana, R. L., Tricase, C., &amp; De Cesare, L. (2021). Blockchain technology for a sustainable agri‐food supply chain. British Food Journal, 123(11), 3471–3485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rathore, S., Gupta, N., Rathore, A. S., &amp; Soni, G. (2022). Blockchain‐based smart wheat supply chain model in Indian context. Agri‐food 4.0 (Vol. 27, pp. 77–96). Emerald Publishing Limited.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rejeb, A. (2018). Halal meat supply chain traceability based on HACCP, blockchain and internet of things. Acta Technica Jaurinensis, 11(1), 218–247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogerson, M., &amp; Parry, G. C. (2020). Blockchain: Case studies in food supply chain visibility. Supply Chain Management: An International Journal, 25(5), 601–614.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samanta, S., &amp; Sarkar, A. (2023). IoT and blockchain for smart water quality management in future cities: A hyperledger fabric framework for smart water quality management and distribution. Research Square, 1–28. https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-3727101/v1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sander, F., Semeijn, J., &amp; Mahr, D. (2018). The acceptance of blockchain technology in meat traceability and transparency. British Food Journal, 120(9), 2066–2079.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saurabh, S., &amp; Dey, K. (2021). Blockchain technology adoption, architecture, and sustainable agri‐food supply chains. Journal of Cleaner Production, 284, 124731.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schahczenski, J., &amp; Schahczenski, C. (2020). Blockchain and the resurrection of consumer sovereignty in a sustainable food economy. Journal of Agriculture, Food Systems, and Community Development, 9(3), 79–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sengupta, T., Narayanamurthy, G., Moser, R., Pereira, V., &amp; Bhattacharjee, D. (2021). Disruptive technologies for achieving supply chain resilience in COVID‐19 era: An implementation case study of satellite imagery and blockchain technologies in fish supply chain. Information Systems Frontiers, 24, 1107–1123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, A., Bhatia, T., Singh, R. K., &amp; Sharma, A. (2024). Developing the framework of blockchain‐enabled agri‐food supply chain. Business Process Management Journal, 30, 291–316.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, A., Sharma, A., Singh, R. K., &amp; Bhatia, T. (2023). Blockchain adoption in agri‐food supply chain management: An empirical study of the main drivers using extended UTAUT. Business Process Management Journal, 29(3), 737–756.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, M., &amp; Kumar, P. (2021). Adoption of blockchain technology: A case study of Walmart. Blockchain technology and applications for digital marketing (pp. 210–225). IGI Global.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shingh, S., Kamalvanshi, V., Ghimire, S., &amp; Basyal, S. (2020). Dairy supply chain system based on blockchain technology. Asian Journal of Economics, Business and Accounting, 14(2), 13–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, A., Gutub, A., Nayyar, A., &amp; Khan, M. K. (2023). Redefining food safety traceability system through blockchain: Findings, challenges and open issues. Multimedia Tools and Applications, 82(14), 21243–21277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava, A., Dubey, V., &amp; Hazela, B. (2021). Delivering green supply chain using blockchain technology for sustainable environment: A survey. The Emerging Technologies in Data Mining and Information Security: Proceedings of IEMIS 2020 (Vol. 1, pp. 759–768). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stewart, B. L. (2021). Pandemic panic and retail reconfiguration: Consumer and supply chain responses to COVID‐19. Journal of Family &amp; Consumer Sciences, 113(1), 7–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stranieri, S., Riccardi, F., Meuwissen, M. P. M., &amp; Soregaroli, C. (2021). Exploring the impact of blockchain on the performance of agri‐food supply chains. Food Control, 119, 107495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunmola, F., &amp; Burgess, P. (2023). Transparency by design for blockchain‐based supply chains. Procedia Computer Science, 217, 1256–1265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suroso, A. I., Rifai, B., &amp; Hasanah, N. (2021). Traceability system in hydroponic vegetables supply chain using blockchain technology. International Journal of Information &amp; Management Sciences, 32(4), 347–361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Susanty, A., Puspitasari, N. B., Rosyada, Z. F., Pratama, M. A., &amp; Kurniawan, E. (2023). Design of blockchain‐based halal traceability system applications for halal chicken meat‐based food supply chain. International Journal of Information Technology, 16, 1449–1473.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swan, M. (2015). Blockchain: Blueprint for a new economy. O'Reilly Media, Inc.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, A., Gligor, D., &amp; Ngah, A. (2022). Applying blockchain for halal food traceability. International Journal of Logistics Research and Applications, 25(6), 947–964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, A., &amp; Ngan, P. T. (2020). A proposed framework model for dairy supply chain traceability. Sustainable Futures, 2, 100034.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandon, A., Dhir, A., Kaur, P., Kushwah, S., &amp; Salo, J. (2020). Why do people buy organic food? The moderating role of environmental concerns and trust. Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services, 57, 102247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, J., Dai, H., Jiang, H., &amp; Chen, W. (2021). Dispatch optimisation in O2O on‐demand service with crowd‐sourced and in‐house drivers. International Journal of Production Research, 59(20), 6054–6068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, Q., Iftekhar, A., Cai, Z., &amp; Cui, X. (2021). Blockchain‐based rice supply chain traceability to ensure rice quality and food safety. Preprints.org, 1–10. https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202106.0223.v1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapscott, D., &amp; Tapscott, A. (2016). Blockchain revolution: How the technology behind bitcoin is changing money, business, and the world. Penguin.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tayal, A., Solanki, A., Kondal, R., Nayyar, A., Tanwar, S., &amp; Kumar, N. (2021). Blockchain‐based efficient communication for food supply chain industry: Transparency and traceability analysis for sustainable business. International Journal of Communication Systems, 34(4), e4696.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thangamayan, S., Pradhan, K., Loganathan, G. B., Sitender, S., Sivamani, S., &amp; Tesema, M. (2023). Blockchain‐based secure traceable scheme for food supply chain. Journal of Food Quality, 2023, 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thapa, S., Piras, G., Thapa, S., Rimal, P., Thapa, A., &amp; Adhikari, K. (2021). Blockchain‐based secured traceability system for the agriculture supply chain of ginger in Nepal: A case study. Archives of Agriculture and Environmental Science, 6, 391–396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiscini, R., Testarmata, S., Ciaburri, M., &amp; Ferrari, E. (2020). The blockchain as a sustainable business model innovation. Management Decision, 58(8), 1621–1642.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari, U. (2020). Application of blockchain in agri‐food supply chain. Britain International of Exact Sciences (BIoEx) Journal, 2(2), 574–589.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Environment Programme. (2024). The United Nations Environment Programme's (UNEP) 2024 food waste index report. https://www.biocycle.net/2024‐food‐waste‐index/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varavallo, G., Caragnano, G., Bertone, F., Vernetti‐Prot, L., &amp; Terzo, O. (2022). Traceability platform based on green blockchain: An application case study in dairy supply chain. Sustainability, 14(6), 3321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Zhang, X., Xu, J., Wang, X., Li, H., Zhao, Z., &amp; Kong, J. (2022). Blockchain‐based information supervision model for rice supply chains. Computational Intelligence and Neuroscience, 2022, 2914571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Chen, C. H., &amp; Zghari‐Sales, A. (2021). Designing a blockchain enabled supply chain. International Journal of Production Research, 59(5), 1450–1475.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, G., Samian, N., Faizal, M. F. M., As'ad, M. A. Z. M., Fadzil, M. F. M., Abdullah, A., Seah, W. K. G., Ishak, M., &amp; Hermadi, I. (2024). A framework for blockchain and internet of things integration in improving food security in the food supply chain. Journal of Advanced Research in Applied Sciences and Engineering Technology, 34(1), 24–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, X., Weber, I., Staples, M., Xu, X., Weber, I., &amp; Staples, M. (2019). Case study: AgriDigital: Blockchain technology in the trade and finance of agriculture supply chains. Architecture for blockchain applications (pp. 239–255). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav, V. S., Singh, A. R., Raut, R. D., &amp; Govindarajan, U. H. (2020). Blockchain technology adoption barriers in the Indian agricultural supply chain: An integrated approach. Resources, Conservation and Recycling, 161, 104877.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yakubu, B. M., Latif, R., Yakubu, A., Khan, M. I., &amp; Magashi, A. I. (2022). RiceChain: Secure and traceable rice supply chain framework using blockchain technology. PeerJ Computer Science, 8, e801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, X., Li, M., Yu, H., Wang, M., Xu, D., &amp; Sun, C. (2021). A trusted blockchain‐based traceability system for fruit and vegetable agricultural products. IEEE Access, 9, 36282–36293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yik, M. H.‐Y., Wong, V. C.‐W. T., Wong, T.‐H., &amp; Shaw, P.‐C. (2021). HerBChain, a blockchain‐based informative platform for quality assurance and quality control of herbal products. Journal of Traditional and Complementary Medicine, 11(6), 598–600.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yontar, E. (2023). Critical success factor analysis of blockchain technology in agri‐food supply chain management: A circular economy perspective. Journal of Environmental Management, 330, 117173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, C., Gong, Y., &amp; Brown, S. (2023). Case analysis: FairChain. Blockchain applications in food supply chain management: Case studies and implications (pp. 175–211). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Chen, L., Battino, M., Farag, M. A., Xiao, J., Simal‐Gandara, J., Gao, H., &amp; Jiang, W. (2022). Blockchain: An emerging novel technology to upgrade the current fresh fruit supply chain. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 124, 1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Wu, X., Ge, H., Jiang, Y., Sun, Z., Ji, X., Jia, Z., &amp; Cui, G. (2023). A blockchain‐based traceability model for grain and oil food supply chain. Foods, 12(17), 3235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, G., Liu, S., Lopez, C., Lu, H., Elgueta, S., Chen, H., &amp; Boshkoska, B. M. (2019). Blockchain technology in agri‐food value chain management: A synthesis of applications, challenges and future research directions. Computers in Industry, 109, 83–99.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>