<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39229714</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1747-0080</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nutrition &amp; dietetics : the journal of the Dietitians Association of Australia</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nutr Diet</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Foodservice strategies for reducing athlete illness at the Olympic and Paralympic Games.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1747-0080.12903</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">In 2021, infection control guidelines, including those specific to feeding environments, were introduced by the International Olympic and Paralympic Committees to reduce virus transmission at the Tokyo 2020 Summer and Beijing 2022 Winter games. This observational cross-sectional study aimed to investigate caterers' compliance to these guidelines which included measures for personal hygiene, sanitisation, and physical distancing at these events.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Expert sport dietitians attending Tokyo (n = 15) and Beijing (n = 7) games were surveyed to rate 11 COVID-19 countermeasures as fully (100%), partially or non-compliant at nine dining locations across both events. Descriptive analysis of each countermeasure based on observed compliance and location was conducted and reported as a proportion of the total responses. To better understand participant perspectives of the factors influencing compliance, open responses were systematically coded into themes and sub-themes by researchers through content analysis. Themes generated from participant comments were categorised based on their relevance to specific countermeasures and locations to identify commonalities and disparities in participant experiences, perceptions, and observations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">All main dining halls at both events were observed as 100% compliant to countermeasures on more occasions compared with Tokyo's venues and satellite villages. However, Beijing's three main dining halls, showed a greater compliance compared with Tokyo's main dining hall, likely due to overcrowding in Tokyo. Comments suggested that smaller dining spaces, with overcrowding, may have contributed to reduced compliance to physical distancing measures. Food safety concerns were raised about gastrointestinal distress in Beijing due to food cross-contamination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Findings suggest that the food service environment may influence caterers' abilities to comply with foodservice safety and infection control guidelines. In the post-pandemic era, enhanced quality control and standardised risk mitigation strategies are needed to improve athletes' health at international sporting events.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Nutrition &amp; Dietetics published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Dietitians Australia.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dufour</LastName><ForeName>Angela C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6577-0960</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health, University of the Sunshine Coast, Sippy Downs, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Canadian Olympic Committee, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pelly</LastName><ForeName>Fiona E</ForeName><Initials>FE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4735-1807</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health, University of the Sunshine Coast, Sippy Downs, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wright</LastName><ForeName>Hattie H</ForeName><Initials>HH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health, University of the Sunshine Coast, Sippy Downs, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tweedie</LastName><ForeName>Judith</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7089-0745</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health, University of the Sunshine Coast, Sippy Downs, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>University of the Sunshine Coast</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>Nutr Diet</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101143078</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1446-6368</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">athletes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">catering</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">illness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mass gathering</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39229714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1747-0080.12903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Dvorak J, Junge A, Derman W, Schwellnus M. Injuries and illnesses of football players during the 2010 FIFA world cup. Br J Sports Med. 2011;45(8):626‐630.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mountjoy M, Junge A, Alonso JM, et al. Sports injuries and illnesses in the 2009 FINA world championships (aquatics). Br J Sports Med. 2010;44(7):522‐527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwellnus M, Derman W, Page T, et al. Illness during the 2010 super 14 Rugby union tournament – a prospective study involving 22 676 player days. Br J Sports Med. 2012;46(7):499‐504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahr R, Clarsen B, Derman W, et al. International Olympic Committee consensus statement: methods for recording and reporting of epidemiological data on injury and illness in sports 2020 (including the STROBE extension for sports injury and illness surveillance (STROBE‐SIIS)). Orthop J Sports Med. 2020;8(2):2325967120902908.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwellnus M, Adami PE, Bougault V, et al. International Olympic Committee (IOC) consensus statement on acute respiratory illness in athletes part 2: non‐infective acute respiratory illness. Br J Sports Med. 2022;46(7):499‐504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhussaini NWZ, Elshaikh UAM, Hamad NA, Nazzal MA, Abuzayed M, Al‐Jayyousi GF. A scoping review of the risk factors and strategies followed for the prevention of COVID‐19 and other infectious diseases during sports mass gatherings: recommendations for future FIFA world cups. Front Public Health. 2023;10:1078834.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centre for Disease Control. Considerations for restaurants and bars. 2020. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019‐ncov/community/organizations/business‐employers/bars‐restaurants.html. (Accessed on 22 June, 2022)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moy GG, Han F, Chen J. Ensuring and promoting food safety during the 2008 Beijing Olympics. Foodborne Pathog Dis. 2010;7(8):981‐983.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Cunha DT, de Oliveira ABA, Saccol ALF, et al. Food safety of food services within the destinations of the 2014 FIFA World Cup in Brazil: development and reliability assessment of the official evaluation instrument. Food Res Int. 2014;57:95‐103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willis C, Elviss N, Aird H, Fenelon D, McLauchlin J. Evaluation of hygiene practices in catering premises at large‐scale events in the UK: identifying risks for the Olympics 2012. Public Health. 2012;126(8):646‐656.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadjichristodoulou C, Mouchtouri V, Varzakas T, et al. Standardized inspections of food premises during the 2004 Athens Olympic Games: descriptive analysis and risk factors for unsatisfactory results. J Food Prot. 2008;71(8):1632‐1640.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceylan Z, Meral R, Cetinkaya T. Relevance of SARS‐CoV‐2 in food safety and food hygiene: potential preventive measures, suggestions and nanotechnological approaches. VirusDisease. 2020;31(2):154‐160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torbjørn S, Debbie P, Kathrin S, et al. New sports, COVID‐19 and the heat: sports injuries and illnesses in the Tokyo 2020 summer Olympics. Br J Sports Med. 2023;57(1):46‐54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelly F, Tweedie J, O'Connor HT. Food provision at the Olympic Games in the new millennium: a meta‐narrative review. Sports Med Open. 2023;9(1):24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummings N, Crawford R, Cort M, Pelly F. Providing meals for athletic groups. In: Burke L, Deakin V, eds. Clinical Sports Nutrition. 3rd ed. McGraw Hill; 2006:785‐799.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelly F, O'Connor H, Denyer G, Caterson I. Catering for the athletes village at the Sydney 2000 Olympic Games: the role of sports dietitians. Int J Sport Nutr Exerc Metab. 2009;19(4):340‐354.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halson SL, Burke LM, Pearce J. Nutrition for travel: from jet lag to catering. Int J Sport Nutr Exerc Metab. 2019;29(2):228‐235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jorm LR, Thackway SV, Churches TR, Hills MW. Watching the games: public health surveillance for the Sydney 2000 Olympic Games. J Epidemiol Commun Health. 2002;57:102‐108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mountjoy M, Moran J, Ahmed H, et al. Athlete health and safety at large sport events: the development of consensus‐driven guidelines consensus statement. Br J Sport Med. 2021;55:191‐197. doi:10.1136/bjsports‐2020‐102771</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCloskey B, Zumla A, Ippolito G, et al. Mass gathering events and reducing further global spread of COVID‐19: a political and public health dilemma. Lancet. 2020;395(10230):1096‐1099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Key Planning Recommendations for Mass Gatherings in the Context of the Current COVID‐19 Outbreak: Interim Guidance, 14 February 2020. World Health Organization; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Olympic Committee (IPC). The Playbook, Athletes and Team Officials, Your Guide to a Safe and Successful Games, Version 2 December 2021. International Olympic Committee and International Paralympic Committee; 2021. Accessed June 22, 2022. https://stillmed.olympics.com/media/Documents/Olympic‐Games/Beijing‐2022/Playbooks/The‐Playbook‐Athletes‐and‐Team‐Officials‐December‐2021.pdf?_ga=2.1749425.1431499139.1660082337‐1968399819.1660082337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Olympic Committee (IPC). The Playbook, Athletes and Officials, your Guide to a Safe and Successful Games, Version 3 June, 2021. International Olympic Committee and International Paralympic Committee; 2020. Accessed June 22, 2022. https://stillmed.olympics.com/media/Documents/Olympic‐Games/Tokyo‐2020/Playbooks/The‐Playbook‐Press‐V3.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelly F, Meyer NL, Pearce J, et al. Evaluation of food provision and nutrition support at the London 2012 Olympic Games: the opinion of sports nutrition experts. Int J Sport Nutr Exerc Metab. 2014;24(6):674‐683.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelly F, Parker SS. Food provision at the Rio 2016 Olympic Games: expert review and future recommendations. Int J Sport Nutr Exerc Metab. 2019;29:382‐387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djekic I, Nikolić A, Uzunović M, et al. Covid‐19 pandemic effects on food safety – multi‐country survey study. Food Control. 2021;122:107800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. The health legacy of the 2008 Beijing Olympic Games: Success and Recommendations. World Health Organization; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Drug Administration USA. Best practices for retail food stores, restaurants, and food pick‐up/delivery services during the COVID‐19 pandemic. 2020. Accessed June 22, 2022. https://www.fda.gov/food/food‐safety‐during‐emergencies/best‐practices‐retail‐food‐stores‐restaurants‐and‐food‐pick‐updelivery‐services‐during‐covid‐19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahbaz M, Bilal M, Moiz A, Zubair S, Iqbal HMN. Food safety and COVID‐19: precautionary measures to limit the spread of coronavirus at food service and retail sector. J Pure Appl Microbiol. 2020;14(1):749‐756. 10.22207/JPAM.14.SPL1.12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mack CD, Wasserman EB, Perrine CG, et al. Implementation and evolution of mitigation measures, testing, and contact tracing in the national football league, August 9–November 21, 2020. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70(4):130‐135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelly F, Tweedie J. Stakeholder perspective of an integrated nutrition service within large scale event catering. Nutr Diet. 2019;76(Supplement 1):21‐22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soligard T, Palmer D, Steffen K, et al. Sports injury and illness incidence in the PyeongChang 2018 Olympic winter games: a prospective study of 2914 athletes from 92 countries. Br J Sports Med. 2019;53(17):1085‐1092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soligard T, Steffen K, Palmer‐Green D, et al. Sports injuries and illnesses in the Sochi 2014 Olympic Winter Games. Br J Sports Med. 2015;49(7):441‐447.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerins C, McHugh S, McSharry J, et al. Barriers and facilitators to implementation of menu labelling interventions from a food service industry perspective: a mixed methods systematic review. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2020;17(1):1‐15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jilcott Pitts S, Graham J, Mojica A, et al. Implementing healthier foodservice guidelines in hospital and federal worksite cafeterias: barriers, facilitators and keys to success. J Hum Nutr Diet. 2016;29(6):677‐686.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dufour AC, Pelly FE, Tweedie J, Wright H. Perceptions of the impact of COVID‐19 countermeasures on safe foodservice provision at international sporting competitions: a qualitative study. Sustainability. 2023;15(1):576.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelly FE, Tweedie J. Inclusion of nutrition expertise in catering operations at a major global sporting event: a qualitative case study using a foodservice systems approach. Journal of the academy of Nutr Diet. 2021;121(1):121‐133. e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Australasian College of Infection Protection and Control. Food safety. Accessed July 17, 2024. https://www.acipc.org.au/food-safety/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO Policy Brief: Gatherings in the Context of COVID‐19, 19 January 2023. World Health Organization; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Derman W, Runciman P, Eken M, et al. Incidence and burden of illness at the Tokyo 2020 Paralympic Games held during the COVID‐19 pandemic: a prospective cohort study of 66 045 athlete days. Br J Sports Med. 2023;57(1):55‐62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCloskey B, Endericks T, Catchpole M, et al. London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games: public health surveillance and epidemiology. Lancet. 2014;383(9934):2083‐2089.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>