<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39221363</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mortality and Serious Adverse Events Associated With Glucagon-Like Peptide-1 Receptor Agonists: A Pharmacovigilance Study Using the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e65989</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e65989</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e65989</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.65989</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Purpose Glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists (GLP-1RAs) are an increasingly prevalent class of drugs for managing overweight/obesity and type 2 diabetes mellitus. Postmarket surveillance is essential for characterizing their risk profiles in real-world patient populations as clinical use increases. This study investigated the association of GLP-1RAs with mortality and serious adverse events (AEs) reported to the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS). Methods A disproportionality analysis was conducted utilizing FAERS data from Q2 2005 to Q1 2024 to identify AEs listing an approved GLP-1RA as the primary suspect drug. The reporting odds ratio (ROR) was calculated for mortality and serious AEs associated with each GLP-1RA compared to the combined group of all other GLP-1RAs. A signal of disproportionate reporting indicating a potential safety concern was defined as a lower bound of the 95% CI for the ROR exceeding 1.0. Results The analysis identified 287,201 AEs associated with GLP-1RAs during the study period. Disproportionality analyses revealed statistically significant elevated signals for mortality with the earliest approved GLP-1RAs: Byetta (ROR = 2.20, 95% CI: 2.06-2.34) and Victoza (ROR = 2.12, 95% CI: 1.98-2.28). Significant elevated signals for serious AEs were identified with the semaglutide products Ozempic (ROR = 2.77, 95% CI: 2.69-2.85), Rybelsus (ROR = 2.42, 95% CI: 2.26-2.60), and Wegovy (ROR = 1.30, 95% CI: 1.22-1.39); the liraglutide products Victoza (ROR = 2.10, 95% CI: 2.04-2.15) and Saxenda (ROR = 2.21, 95% CI: 2.09-2.33); and Byetta (ROR = 1.11, 95% CI: 1.08-1.14) compared to other GLP-1RAs. The newer GLP-1RAs were associated with a higher proportion of serious AEs reported in younger patients (p &lt; 0.001) and females (p &lt; 0.001). Conclusion This pharmacovigilance study utilizing the FAERS database identified potential safety signals of increased mortality and serious AE reporting associated with certain GLP-1RAs, particularly the earlier approved liraglutide agents Byetta and Victoza. These findings highlight the importance of proactive postmarket surveillance to characterize the real-world safety profiles of individual GLP-1RA drugs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Bhattacharyya et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhattacharyya</LastName><ForeName>Mehul</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Research, Miller Scientific, Johnson City, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miller</LastName><ForeName>Larry E</ForeName><Initials>LE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Research, Miller Scientific, Johnson City, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miller</LastName><ForeName>Anna L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Research, Miller Scientific, Johnson City, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhattacharyya</LastName><ForeName>Ruemon</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Affairs and Economics, University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adverse event</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">faers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">glp-1ra</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">obesity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">safety</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39221363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11366408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.65989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hales CM, Carroll MD, Fryar CD, Ogden CL. NCHS Data Brief. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Health Statistics; 2020. Prevalence of Obesity and Severe Obesity Among Adults: United States, 2017-2018; pp. 1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trends and predictions of malnutrition and obesity in 204 countries and territories: an analysis of the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Chong B, Jayabaskaran J, Kong G, et al. EClinicalMedicine. 2023;57:101850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9971264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36864983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The global, regional and national burden of type 2 diabetes mellitus in the past, present and future: a systematic analysis of the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Ye J, Wu Y, Yang S, et al. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 2023;14:1192629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10376703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37522116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maintenance of lost weight and long-term management of obesity. Hall KD, Kahan S. Med Clin North Am. 2018;102:183–197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5764193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29156185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pharmacotherapy for obesity: moving towards efficacy improvement. Coutinho W, Halpern B. Diabetol Metab Syndr. 2024;16:6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10763391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38172940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) Müller TD, Finan B, Bloom SR, et al. Mol Metab. 2019;30:72–130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6812410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31767182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists: a narrative review of clinical pharmacology and implications for peri-operative practice. Milder DA, Milder TY, Liang SS, Kam PC. Anaesthesia. 2024;79:735–747.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38740566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The weight-loss effect of GLP-1RAs glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists in non-diabetic Individuals with overweight or obesity: a systematic review with meta-analysis and trial sequential analysis of randomized controlled trials. Liu Y, Ruan B, Jiang H, et al. Am J Clin Nutr. 2023;118:614–626.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37661106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparison of glucose-lowering drugs as second-line treatment for type 2 diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Gu S, Hu X, Zhen X, et al. J Clin Med. 2022;11:5435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9504435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36143082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monitoring report: GLP-1 RA prescribing trends-March 2024 data [PREPRINT] Gratzl S, Rodriguez PJ, Cartwright BM, Baker C, Do D, Stucky NL. medRxiv. 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GLP-1 receptor agonists in the treatment of type 2 diabetes - state-of-the-art. Nauck MA, Quast DR, Wefers J, Meier JJ. Mol Metab. 2021;46:101102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8085572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33068776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Is there a risk for semaglutide misuse? focus on the Food and Drug Administration's FDA Adverse Events Reporting System (FAERS) pharmacovigilance dataset. Chiappini S, Vickers-Smith R, Harris D, et al. Pharmaceuticals (Basel) 2023;16:994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10384093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37513906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>As semaglutide's popularity soars, rare but serious adverse effects are emerging. Ruder K. JAMA. 2023;330:2140–2142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37966850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pharmacovigilance: reporting requirements throughout a product's lifecycle. Lucas S, Ailani J, Smith TR, Abdrabboh A, Xue F, Navetta MS. Ther Adv Drug Saf. 2022;13:20420986221125006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9520146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36187302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Questions and answers on FDA's Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS)  [
May;
2024 
]. 2023. https://www.fda.gov/drugs/surveillance/questions-and-answers-fdas-adverse-event-reporting-system-faers https://www.fda.gov/drugs/surveillance/questions-and-answers-fdas-adverse-event-reporting-system-faers</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association between different GLP-1 receptor agonists and gastrointestinal adverse reactions: a real-world disproportionality study based on FDA adverse event reporting system database. Liu L, Chen J, Wang L, Chen C, Chen L. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 2022;13:1043789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9770009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36568085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Difference in gastrointestinal risk associated with use of GLP-1 receptor agonists: a real-world pharmacovigilance study. Zhou Y, Chen M, Liu L, Chen Z. Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes. 2022;15:155–163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8763271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35046686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gastrointestinal adverse events associated with semaglutide: a pharmacovigilance study based on FDA adverse event reporting system. Shu Y, He X, Wu P, Liu Y, Ding Y, Zhang Q. Front Public Health. 2022;10:996179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9631444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36339230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safety of glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists: a real-world study based on the US FDA Adverse Event Reporting System Database. Wu T, Zhang Y, Shi Y, Yu K, Zhao M, Liu S, Zhao Z. Clin Drug Investig. 2022;42:965–975.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36175609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Psychiatric adverse events associated with GLP-1 receptor agonists: a real-world pharmacovigilance study based on the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System database. Chen W, Cai P, Zou W, Fu Z. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 2024;15:1330936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10882716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38390214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exploration of the potential association between GLP-1 receptor agonists and suicidal or self-injurious behaviors: a pharmacovigilance study based on the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System database. Zhou J, Zheng Y, Xu B, et al. BMC Med. 2024;22:65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10865629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38355513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Update on FDA’s ongoing evaluation of reports of suicidal thoughts or actions in patients taking a certain type of medicines approved for type 2 diabetes and obesity.  [
May;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.fda.gov/drugs/drug-safety-and-availability/update-fdas-ongoing-evaluation-reports-suicidal-thoughts-or-actions-patients-taking-certain-type https://www.fda.gov/drugs/drug-safety-and-availability/update-fdas-ongoing-evaluation-reports-suicidal-thoughts-or-actions-patients-taking-certain-type</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conducting and interpreting disproportionality analyses derived from spontaneous reporting systems. Cutroneo PM, Sartori D, Tuccori M, et al. Front Drug Saf Regul. 2024;3:1323057.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conceiving, conducting, reporting, interpreting, and publishing disproportionality analyses: a call to action. Raschi E, Salvo F, Khouri C. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2022;88:3535–3536.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35178726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racial, ethnic, and socioeconomic inequities in glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonist use among patients with diabetes in the US. Eberly LA, Yang L, Essien UR, et al. JAMA Health Forum. 2021;2:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8796881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35977298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assessment of factors associated with completeness of spontaneous adverse event reporting in the United States: a comparison between consumer reports and healthcare professional reports. Toki T, Ono S. J Clin Pharm Ther. 2020;45:462–469.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7317542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31765498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patient preferences for glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor-agonist treatment attributes. Thieu VT, Robinson S, Kennedy-Martin T, Boye KS, Garcia-Perez LE. Patient Prefer Adherence. 2019;13:561–576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6483112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31114170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Empirical estimation of under-reporting in the U.S. Food and Drug Administration Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) Alatawi YM, Hansen RA. Expert Opin Drug Saf. 2017;16:761–767.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28447485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>