<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39220440</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2314-5765</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>2024</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of UHT Thermal Treatment on the Secondary Structures of Milk Proteins: Insights From FTIR Analysis and Potential Allergenic Activity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1880779</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1880779</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1880779</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1155/2024/1880779</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Although thermal treatments are beneficial for the preservation and safety of milk, they can also alter its immunogenic activity by affecting its protein components. To achieve precise results, it is essential to identify the specific proteins that cause food allergies. Therefore, investigating the possible alterations of cow's milk proteins (CMPs) resulting from thermal treatments is necessary. In this study, the Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) technique was used to analyze the effect of UHT thermal treatment on the secondary structures of milk casein. Using the second derivative, six characteristic peaks were identified in the Amide I region, ranging from 1700 to 1600 cm<sup>-1</sup>. It was found that thermal treatments produce shifts in absorption peaks, indicating changes in protein conformation and possibly in allergenic activity. These shifts were clearly identified in the first characteristic peak of samples M8 and M9, from 1621 to 1600 cm<sup>-1</sup>. The results suggest that thermal treatments may promote protein aggregation by increasing <i>β</i> turns and reducing <i>β</i> sheets and <i>α</i> helices, which could enhance the allergenic potential of the proteins and facilitate the formation of complexes between different milk proteins, such as <i>β</i>-lactoglobulin and <i>κ</i>-casein. Further studies are needed to experimentally validate the allergenic activity of proteins modified by thermal treatments, as only an analytical method (FTIR) was used to evaluate the secondary structures of the proteins.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Sergio-Miguel Acuña-Nelson et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Acuña-Nelson</LastName><ForeName>Sergio-Miguel</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1365-9851</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Engineering Department University of Bío-Bío, Chillán 3780000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Henríquez-González</LastName><ForeName>Leslie-Patricia</ForeName><Initials>LP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Engineering Department University of Bío-Bío, Chillán 3780000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sepúlveda-Villagra</LastName><ForeName>Vieroska-Belén</ForeName><Initials>VB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Engineering Department University of Bío-Bío, Chillán 3780000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Opazo-Navarrete</LastName><ForeName>Mauricio</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agriaquaculture Nutritional Genomic Center (CGNA), Temuco 4780000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Durán-Agüero</LastName><ForeName>Samuel</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nutrition and Dietetic School San Sebastián University, Providencia 7500000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parra-Flores</LastName><ForeName>Julio-Enrique</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nutrition and Public Health Department University of Bío-Bío, Chillán 3780000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101627297</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2314-5765</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FTIR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">allergenic activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">casein</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39220440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11362581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2024/1880779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Do A. B., Williams K., Toomer O. T. In vitro digestibility and immunoreactivity of bovine milk proteins. Food Chemistry . 2016;190:581–587. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.05.113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.05.113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26213013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villa C., Costa J., Oliveira M., Mafra I. Bovine milk allergens: a comprehensive review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety . 2018;17(1):137–164. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33350061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geiselhart S., Podzhilkova A., Hoffmann-Sommergruber K. Cow’s milk processing-friend or foe in food allergy? Food . 2021;10(3):p. 572. doi: 10.3390/foods10030572.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10030572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8000412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33803451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaiswal L., Worku M. Recent perspective on cow’s milk allergy and dairy nutrition. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition . 2022;62(27):7503–7517. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2021.1915241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.1915241</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33983082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bøgh K. L., Nielsen D. M., Mohammad-Beigi H., et al. Degree of hydrolysis is a poor predictor of the sensitizing capacity of whey- and casein-based hydrolysates in a Brown Norway rat model of cow’s milk allergy. Food Research International . 2024;181, article 114063 doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2024.114063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2024.114063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38448113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flom J., Sicherer S. H. Epidemiology of Cow’s Milk Allergy. Nutrients . 2019;11(5):p. 1051. doi: 10.3390/nu11051051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu11051051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6566637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31083388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hochwallner H., Schulmeister U., Swoboda I., Spitzauer S., Valenta R. Cow’s milk allergy: From allergens to new forms of diagnosis, therapy and prevention. Methods . 2014;66(1):22–33. doi: 10.1016/j.ymeth.2013.08.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2013.08.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3969108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23954566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramachandran B., Yang C. T., Downs M. L. Parallel reaction monitoring mass spectrometry method for detection of both casein and whey milk allergens from a baked food matrix. Journal of Proteome Research . 2020;19(8):2964–2976. doi: 10.1021/acs.jproteome.9b00844.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.9b00844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32483969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong L., Pan M., Xie X., et al. Aptamer-Based Fluorescent Biosensor for the Rapid and Sensitive Detection of Allergens in Food Matrices. Foods . 2021;10(11):p. 2598. doi: 10.3390/foods10112598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10112598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8623274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34828878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M. U., Lin H., Ahmed I., et al. Whey allergens: influence of nonthermal processing treatments and their detection methods. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety . 2021;20(5):4480–4510. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12793.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34288394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verhoeckx K. C., Vissers Y. M., Baumert J. L., et al. Food processing and allergenicity. Food and Chemical Toxicology . 2015;80:223–240. doi: 10.1016/j.fct.2015.03.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2015.03.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25778347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleber N., Hinrichs J. Antigenic response of β-lactoglobulin in thermally treated bovine skim milk and sweet whey. Milchwissenschaft . 2007;62:121–124.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bu G., Lu J., Zheng Z., Luo Y. Influence of Maillard reaction conditions on the antigenicity of bovine α-lactalbumin using response surface methodology. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture . 2009;89(14):2428–2434. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.3741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.3741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bloom K. A., Huang F. R., Bencharitiwong R., et al. Effect of heat treatment on milk and egg proteins allergenicity. Pediatric Allergy and Immunology . 2014;25(8):740–746. doi: 10.1111/pai.12283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/pai.12283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25251921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Q., Shi J., Yao M., Jiang M., Luo Y. Effects of heat treatment on the antigenicity of four milk proteins in milk protein concentrates. Food and Agricultural Immunology . 2016;27(3):401–413. doi: 10.1080/09540105.2015.1117059.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09540105.2015.1117059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat M. Y., Dar T. A., Singh L. R. Casein proteins: structural and functional aspects. In: Gigli I., editor. Milk Proteins—From Structure to Biological Properties and Health Aspects . 1st. 5 Princes Gate Court, London, SW7 2QJ, U.K.: IntechOpen Limited; 2016. pp. 1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y., Liu Y., Zhou W., et al. Effects of ohmic heating with different voltages on the quality and microbial diversity of cow milk during thermal treatment and subsequent cold storage. International Journal of Food Microbiology . 2024;410, article 110483 doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37995495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbring S., Hols G., Garssen J., van Esch B. C. A. M. Raw cow’s milk consumption and allergic diseases–The potential role of bioactive whey proteins. European Journal of Pharmacology . 2019;843:55–65. doi: 10.1016/j.ejphar.2018.11.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2018.11.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30439365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun-Fahrländer C., Von Mutius E. Can farm milk consumption prevent allergic diseases? Clinical &amp; Experimental Allergy . 2011;41(1):29–35. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2222.2010.03665.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2222.2010.03665.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21155907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahrens B., Lopes de Oliveira L. C., Grabenhenrich L., et al. Individual cow's milk allergens as prognostic markers for tolerance development? Clinical &amp; Experimental Allergy . 2012;42(11):1630–1637. doi: 10.1111/cea.12001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cea.12001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23106663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Järvinen K. M., Sicherer S. H. Diagnostic oral food challenges: procedures and biomarkers. Journal of Immunological Methods . 2012;383(1-2):30–38. doi: 10.1016/j.jim.2012.02.019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jim.2012.02.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22414488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Kruif C. G., Huppertz T., Urban V. S., Petukhov A. V. Casein micelles and their internal structure. Advances in Colloid and Interface Science . 2012;171-172:36–52. doi: 10.1016/j.cis.2012.01.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cis.2012.01.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22381008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haque M. A., Chen J., Aldred P., Adhikari B. Drying and denaturation characteristics of whey protein isolate in the presence of lactose and trehalose. Food Chemistry . 2015;177:8–16. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.12.064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.12.064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25660851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cepero-Betancourt Y., Opazo-Navarrete M., Janssen A. E. M., Tabilo-Munizaga G., Pérez-Won M. Effects of high hydrostatic pressure (HHP) on protein structure and digestibility of red abalone (Haliotis rufescens) muscle. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies . 2020;60, article 102282 doi: 10.1016/j.ifset.2019.102282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ifset.2019.102282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Etzion Y., Linker R., Cogan U., Shmulevich I. Determination of protein concentration in raw milk by mid-infrared fourier transform infrared/attenuated total reflectance spectroscopy. Journal of Dairy Science . 2004;87(9):2779–2788. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(04)73405-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(04)73405-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15375035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewavitharana A. K., van Brakel B. Fourier transform infrared spectrometric method for the rapid determination of casein in raw Milk. Analyst . 1997;122(7):701–704. doi: 10.1039/a700953d.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/a700953d</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venyaminov S. Y., Kalnin N. N. Quantitative IR spectrophotometry of peptide compounds in water (H2O) solutions. II. Amide absorption bands of polypeptides and fibrous proteins in α-, β-, and random coil conformations. Biopolymers . 1990;30(13-14):1259–1271. doi: 10.1002/bip.360301310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bip.360301310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1707690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayasooriya S. D., Torley P. J. Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy as a process analytical technology (PAT) tool for monitoring and understanding protein behaviour in dairy systems. International Dairy Journal . 2011;21:575–586.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T., Johnson W. Rapid determination of milk protein quantity and quality using Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy. Journal of Dairy Science . 1994;71:3572–3581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Su Y., Jia F., Jin H. Characterization of casein hydrolysates derived from enzymatic hydrolysis. Chemistry Central Journal . 2013;7(1):1–8. doi: 10.1186/1752-153X-7-62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1752-153X-7-62</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3626679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23556455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sierra I., González-Martin M. I., Corzo N., Carmona M. Chemical and microbiological characteristics of goat's milk produced in the Canary Islands. International Dairy Journal . 2007;17:1297–1302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Otero J. L., Hermida M., Cepeda A. Determination of fat, protein, and total solids in cheese by near-infrared reflectance spectroscopy. Journal of AOAC International . 1995;78(3):802–806. doi: 10.1093/jaoac/78.3.802.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jaoac/78.3.802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7756894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez M. M., Gomez C. A. Calidad composicional e higiénica de la leche cruda recibida en industrias lácteas de Sucre, Colombia. Biotecnología en el Sector Agropecuario y Agroindustrial . 2013;11:93–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barth A. Infrared spectroscopy of proteins. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Bioenergetics . 2007;1767(9):1073–1101. doi: 10.1016/j.bbabio.2007.06.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbabio.2007.06.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17692815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu J., Garrigues L., Van den Toorn H., Stahl B., Heck A. J. Discovery and quantification of nonhuman proteins in human milk. Journal of Proteome Research . 2018;18:225–238. doi: 10.1021/acs.jproteome.8b00550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.8b00550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6326037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30489082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta R., Sanotra S., Sheikh H. N., Kalsotra B. L. Room temperature aqueous phase synthesis and characterization of novel nano-sized coordination polymers composed of copper (II), nickel (II), and zinc (II) metal ions with p-phenylenediamine (PPD) as the bridging ligand. Journal of Nanostructure in Chemistry . 2013;3(1):p. 41. doi: 10.1186/2193-8865-3-41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/2193-8865-3-41</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniloski D., McCarthy N. A., Markoska T., Auldist M. J., Vasiljevic T. Conformational and physicochemical characteristics of bovine skim milk obtained from cows with different genetic variants of β-casein. Food Hydrocolloids . 2022;124, article 107186 doi: 10.1016/j.foodhyd.2021.107186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2021.107186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eissa A. S., Puhl C., Kadla J. F., Khan S. A. Enzymatic cross-linking of β-lactoglobulin: conformational properties using FTIR spectroscopy. Biomacromolecules . 2006;7(6):1707–1713. doi: 10.1021/bm050928p.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/bm050928p</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16768388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guevara-Garay L. A., Cuartas-Castaño D. A., Llano-Naranjo F. Kappa caseína de la leche: aspectos bioquímicos, moleculares, productivos y nutricionales. Revista Médica de Risaralda . 2014;20:29–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torii H., Tasumi M. Model calculations on the amide-I infrared bands of globular proteins. The Journal of Chemical Physics . 1992;96(5):3379–3387. doi: 10.1063/1.461939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1063/1.461939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barth A., Zscherp C. What vibrations tell about proteins. Quarterly Reviews of Biophysics . 2002;35(4):369–430. doi: 10.1017/S0033583502003815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0033583502003815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12621861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markoska T., Daniloski D., Vasiljevic T., Huppertz T. Structural changes of β-casein induced by temperature and pH Analysed by nuclear magnetic resonance, Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy, and chemometrics. Molecules . 2021;26(24):p. 7650. doi: 10.3390/molecules26247650.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26247650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8706189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34946731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrell H. M., Qi P. X., Wickham E. D., Unruh J. J. Secondary structural studies of bovine caseins: structure and temperature dependence of β-casein phosphopeptide (1-25) as analyzed by circular dichroism, FTIR spectroscopy, and analytical ultracentrifugation. Journal of Protein Chemistry . 2002;21(5):307–321. doi: 10.1023/A:1019992900455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1019992900455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12206505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Condict L., Kaur J., Hung A., Ashton J., Kasapis S. Combined spectroscopic, molecular docking and quantum mechanics study of β-casein and ferulic acid interactions following UHT-like treatment. Food Hydrocolloids . 2019;89:351–359. doi: 10.1016/j.foodhyd.2018.10.055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2018.10.055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarhan Ö., Kaya A. Investigation of the compositional and structural changes in the proteins of cow milk when processed to cheese. LWT . 2021;151, article 112102 doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordillo-Delgado F., Bedoya-Pérez A. F., Delgado-Osorio H. D. Características mecánicas y térmicas de un poliuretano elaborado a partir de aceite de higuerilla (Ricinus communis) para la adhesión de elementos estructurales de guadua angustifolia kunth. Revista UIS Ingenierías . 2020;19(4):103–114. doi: 10.18273/revuin.v19n4-2020009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18273/revuin.v19n4-2020009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed Q. A., Hassan A., Sharif S., et al. Structural and functional properties of milk proteins as affected by heating, high pressure, gamma and ultraviolet irradiation: a review. International Journal of Food Properties . 2021;24(1):871–884. doi: 10.1080/10942912.2021.1937209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10942912.2021.1937209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Zhao J., Qiao W., et al. Effect of infant formula production processes on phospholipid composition and structure of milk fat globules. LWT . 2024;195, article 115808 doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2024.115808.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2024.115808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>