<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">39221066</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>02</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2219-2840</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>30</Volume><Issue>32</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>World journal of gastroenterology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>World J Gastroenterol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Autoimmune gastritis studies and gastric cancer: True renaissance or bibliometric illusion.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3783</StartPage><EndPage>3790</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3783-3790</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3748/wjg.v30.i32.3783</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A bibliometric analysis of studies dedicated to autoimmune gastritis (AIG) recently published demonstrated a noteworthy surge in publications over the last three years. This can be explained by numerous publications from different regions of the world reporting the results of several studies that stimulated reassessment of our view of AIG as a precancerous condition. Follow-up studies and retrospective analyses showed that the risk of gastric cancer (GC) in AIG patients is much lower than expected if the patients ever being infected with <i>Helicobacter pylori</i> (<i>H. pylori</i>) were excluded. The low prevalence of precancerous lesions, such as the incomplete type of intestinal metaplasia, may explain the low risk of GC in AIG patients because the spasmolytic polypeptide-expressing metaplasia commonly observed in AIG does not involve clonal reprogramming of the gastric gland and can be considered as an adaptive change rather than a true precancerous lesion. However, changes in gastric secretion due to the progression of gastric atrophy during the course of AIG cause changes in the gastric mic-robiome, stimulating the growth of bacterial species such as streptococci, which may promote the development of precancerous lesions and GC. Thus, <i>Streptococcus anginosus</i> exhibited a robust proinflammatory response and induced the gastritis-atrophy-metaplasia-dysplasia sequence in mice, reproducing the well-established process for carcinogenesis associated with <i>H. pylori</i>. Prospective studies in <i>H. pylori</i>-naïve patients evaluating gastric microbiome changes during the long-term course of AIG might provide an explanation for the enigmatic increase in GC incidence in the last decades in younger cohorts, which has been reported in economically developed countries.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©The Author(s) 2024. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Isakov</LastName><ForeName>Vasily</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Federal Research Center of Nutrition, Biotechnology and Food Safety, Moscow 115446, Russia. vasily.isakov@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>World J Gastroenterol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100883448</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1007-9327</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013274" MajorTopicYN="Y">Stomach Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005756" MajorTopicYN="Y">Gastritis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016481" MajorTopicYN="Y">Helicobacter Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016480" MajorTopicYN="Y">Helicobacter pylori</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000472" MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenicity</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011230" MajorTopicYN="Y">Precancerous Conditions</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001327" MajorTopicYN="Y">Autoimmune Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015706" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bibliometrics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005753" MajorTopicYN="Y">Gastric Mucosa</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008679" MajorTopicYN="N">Metaplasia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012307" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013270" MajorTopicYN="N">Stomach</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069196" MajorTopicYN="N">Gastrointestinal Microbiome</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Autoimmune gastritis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gastric cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Helicobacter pylori</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intestinal metaplasia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Streptococcus anginosus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Type 1 neuroendocrine tumors</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict-of-interest statement: The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39221066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11362875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3748/wjg.v30.i32.3783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Yu YF, Tong KK, Shangguan XL, Yang XY, Wu JY, Hu G, Yu R, Tan CC. Research status and hotspots of autoimmune gastritis: A bibliometric analysis. World J Gastroenterol. 2023;29:5781–5799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10701335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38075850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whittingham S, Mackay IR. Autoimmune gastritis: historical antecedents, outstanding discoveries, and unresolved problems. Int Rev Immunol. 2005;24:1–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15763987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rugge M, Bricca L, Guzzinati S, Sacchi D, Pizzi M, Savarino E, Farinati F, Zorzi M, Fassan M, Dei Tos AP, Malfertheiner P, Genta RM, Graham DY. Autoimmune gastritis: long-term natural history in naïve Helicobacter pylori-negative patients. Gut. 2023;72:30–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35772926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rugge M, Genta RM, Malfertheiner P, Graham DY. Atrophic autoimmune gastritis: 'a muddled or misguided core concept compromises our overall comprehension of the problem'. Gut. 2023;73:207–208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36868846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rugge M, Genta RM, Malfertheiner P, Graham DY. Gastric cancer risk in autoimmune gastritis: evidence versus opinion. Gut. 2024;73:555–556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36849227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arai J, Niikura R, Hayakawa Y, Hirata Y, Ushiku T, Fujishiro M. Autoimmune gastritis may be less susceptible to cancer development than Helicobacter pylori-related gastritis based on histological analysis. Gut. 2024;73:1037–1038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37197906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waldum HL. Conclusion that autoimmune gastritis does not predispose to gastric cancer is unproven. Gut. 2024;73:379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10850709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36693711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenti MV, Broglio G, Di Sabatino A. Unravelling the risk of developing gastric cancer in autoimmune gastritis. Gut. 2023;72:1429–1430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35981867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldenring J. No H. pylori, no adenocarcinoma for patients with autoimmune gastritis. Gut. 2023;72:1–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9812852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35896359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butt J, Lehtinen M, Öhman H, Waterboer T, Epplein M. Association of Helicobacter pylori and Autoimmune Gastritis With Stomach Cancer in a Cohort of Young Finnish Women. Gastroenterology. 2022;163:305–307.e4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35301012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weise F, Vieth M, Reinhold D, Haybaeck J, Goni E, Lippert H, Ridwelski K, Lingohr P, Schildberg C, Vassos N, Kruschewski M, Krasniuk I, Grimminger PP, Waidmann O, Peitz U, Veits L, Kreuser N, Lang H, Bruns C, Moehler M, Lordick F, Gockel I, Schumacher J, Malfertheiner P, Venerito M. Gastric cancer in autoimmune gastritis: A case-control study from the German centers of the staR project on gastric cancer research. United European Gastroenterol J. 2020;8:175–184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7079279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32213076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arai J, Niikura R, Hayakawa Y, Suzuki N, Hirata Y, Ushiku T, Fujishiro M. Clinicopathological Features of Gastric Cancer with Autoimmune Gastritis. Biomedicines. 2022;10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9031450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35453635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C, Yang Y, Li P, Hu H. Incidence of Gastric Neoplasms Arising from Autoimmune Metaplastic Atrophic Gastritis: A Systematic Review and Case Reports. J Clin Med. 2023;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9918256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36769710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rugge M, Savarino E, Sbaraglia M, Bricca L, Malfertheiner P. Gastritis: The clinico-pathological spectrum. Dig Liver Dis. 2021;53:1237–1246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33785282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugano K, Moss SF, Kuipers EJ. Gastric Intestinal Metaplasia: Real Culprit or Innocent Bystander as a Precancerous Condition for Gastric Cancer? Gastroenterology. 2023;165:1352–1366.e1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37652306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González CA, Sanz-Anquela JM, Gisbert JP, Correa P. Utility of subtyping intestinal metaplasia as marker of gastric cancer risk. A review of the evidence. Int J Cancer. 2013;133:1023–1032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3732516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23280711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JWJ, Zhu F, Srivastava S, Tsao SK, Khor C, Ho KY, Fock KM, Lim WC, Ang TL, Chow WC, So JBY, Koh CJ, Chua SJ, Wong ASY, Rao J, Lim LG, Ling KL, Chia CK, Ooi CJ, Rajnakova A, Yap WM, Salto-Tellez M, Ho B, Soong R, Chia KS, Teo YY, Teh M, Yeoh KG. Severity of gastric intestinal metaplasia predicts the risk of gastric cancer: a prospective multicentre cohort study (GCEP) Gut. 2022;71:854–863.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8995828</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33975867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rugge M, Meggio A, Pravadelli C, Barbareschi M, Fassan M, Gentilini M, Zorzi M, Pretis G, Graham DY, Genta RM. Gastritis staging in the endoscopic follow-up for the secondary prevention of gastric cancer: a 5-year prospective study of 1755 patients. Gut. 2019;68:11–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29306868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genta RM, Turner KO, Robiou C, Singhal A, Rugge M. Incomplete Intestinal Metaplasia Is Rare in Autoimmune Gastritis. Dig Dis. 2023;41:369–376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36739859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petersson F, Borch K, Franzén LE. Prevalence of subtypes of intestinal metaplasia in the general population and in patients with autoimmune chronic atrophic gastritis. Scand J Gastroenterol. 2002;37:262–266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11916187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong S, Choi E, Petersen CP, Roland JT, Federico A, Ippolito R, D'Armiento FP, Nardone G, Nagano O, Saya H, Romano M, Goldenring JR. Distinct metaplastic and inflammatory phenotypes in autoimmune and adenocarcinoma-associated chronic atrophic gastritis. United European Gastroenterol J. 2017;5:37–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5384548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28405320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sáenz JB, Mills JC. Acid and the basis for cellular plasticity and reprogramming in gastric repair and cancer. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2018;15:257–273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6016373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29463907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldenring JR, Ray GS, Coffey RJ, Meunier PC, Haley PJ, Barnes TB, Car BD. Reversible drug-induced oxyntic atrophy in rats. Gastroenterology. 2000;118:1080–1093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10833483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nomura S, Yamaguchi H, Ogawa M, Wang TC, Lee JR, Goldenring JR. Alterations in gastric mucosal lineages induced by acute oxyntic atrophy in wild-type and gastrin-deficient mice. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2005;288:G362–G375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15647607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huh WJ, Khurana SS, Geahlen JH, Kohli K, Waller RA, Mills JC. Tamoxifen induces rapid, reversible atrophy, and metaplasia in mouse stomach. Gastroenterology. 2012;142:21–24.e7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3708546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22001866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye W, Nyrén O. Risk of cancers of the oesophagus and stomach by histology or subsite in patients hospitalised for pernicious anaemia. Gut. 2003;52:938–941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1773712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12801947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mellemkjaer L, Gridley G, Møller H, Hsing AW, Linet MS, Brinton LA, Olsen JH. Pernicious anaemia and cancer risk in Denmark. Br J Cancer. 1996;73:998–1000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2075829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8611439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo X, Schreurs MWJ, Marijnissen FE, Mommersteeg MC, Nieuwenburg SAV, Doukas M, Erler NS, Capelle LG, Bruno MJ, Peppelenbosch MP, Spaander MCW Proregal study group, Fuhler GM. Increased Prevalence of Autoimmune Gastritis in Patients with a Gastric Precancerous Lesion. J Clin Med. 2023;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10573100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37834796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsuboi M, Niikura R, Hayakawa Y, Hirata Y, Ushiku T, Koike K. Distinct Features of Autoimmune Gastritis in Patients with Open-Type Chronic Gastritis in Japan. Biomedicines. 2020;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7602128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33066474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osmola M, Hemont C, Chapelle N, Vibet MA, Tougeron D, Moussata D, Lamarque D, Bigot-Corbel E, Masson D, Blin J, Leroy M, Josien R, Mosnier JF, Martin J, Matysiak-Budnik T. Atrophic Gastritis and Autoimmunity: Results from a Prospective, Multicenter Study. Diagnostics (Basel) 2023;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10178247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37174990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massironi S, Gallo C, Elvevi A, Stegagnini M, Coltro LA, Invernizzi P. Incidence and prevalence of gastric neuroendocrine tumors in patients with chronic atrophic autoimmune gastritis. World J Gastrointest Oncol. 2023;15:1451–1460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10473929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37663936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu H, Li R, Shao L, Zhang Q, Xu R, Zhang S. Gastric lesions in patients with autoimmune metaplastic atrophic gastritis: a retrospective study in a single center. Scand J Gastroenterol. 2022;57:1296–1303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35645153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei Y, Jiang C, Han Y, Song W, Li X, Yin X. Characteristics and background mucosa status of early gastric cancer after Helicobacter pylori eradication: A narrative review. Medicine (Baltimore) 2022;101:e31968.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9726367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36482539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dilaghi E, Bellisario M, Esposito G, Carabotti M, Annibale B, Lahner E. The Impact of Proton Pump Inhibitors on the Development of Gastric Neoplastic Lesions in Patients With Autoimmune Atrophic Gastritis. Front Immunol. 2022;13:910077.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9353125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35935934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dilaghi E, Dottori L, Pivetta G, Dalla Bella M, Esposito G, Ligato I, Pilozzi E, Annibale B, Lahner E. Incidence and Predictors of Gastric Neoplastic Lesions in Corpus-Restricted Atrophic Gastritis: A Single-Center Cohort Study. Am J Gastroenterol. 2023;118:2157–2165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37207305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sato Y. Endoscopic diagnosis and management of type I neuroendocrine tumors. World J Gastrointest Endosc. 2015;7:346–353.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4400623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25901213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsueda K, Uedo N, Kitamura M, Shichijo S, Maekawa A, Kanesaka T, Takeuchi Y, Higashino K, Ishihara R, Michida T, Kawano S, Kawahara Y. Endoscopic features of gastric neuroendocrine carcinoma. J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2023;38:1808–1817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37527834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamada T, Watanabe H, Furuta T, Terao S, Maruyama Y, Kawachi H, Kushima R, Chiba T, Haruma K. Diagnostic criteria and endoscopic and histological findings of autoimmune gastritis in Japan. J Gastroenterol. 2023;58:185–195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9998601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36855000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung CS, Tsai CL, Chu YY, Chen KC, Lin JC, Chen BC, Sun WC, Yen HH, Chen CY, Wu IC, Kuo CH, Shih HY, Bair MJ, Wang JP, Hu WH, Yang CS, Han ML, Cheng TY, Tseng CM, Tsai MC, Hu ML, Wang HP. Clinical features and outcomes of gastric neuroendocrine tumors after endoscopic diagnosis and treatment: A Digestive Endoscopy Society of Tawian (DEST) Medicine (Baltimore) 2018;97:e12101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6160255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30235663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim Y, Ahn B, Choi KD, Kim BS, Yook JH, Lee GH, Hong SM, Lee JH. Gastric Neuroendocrine Tumors According to the 2019 World Health Organization Grading System: A Single-Center, Retrospective Study. Gut Liver. 2023;17:863–873.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10651375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36588525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inoue M. Changing epidemiology of Helicobacter pylori in Japan. Gastric Cancer. 2017;20:3–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27757699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith JP, Nadella S, Osborne N. Gastrin and Gastric Cancer. Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2017;4:75–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5439238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28560291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parsons BN, Ijaz UZ, D'Amore R, Burkitt MD, Eccles R, Lenzi L, Duckworth CA, Moore AR, Tiszlavicz L, Varro A, Hall N, Pritchard DM. Comparison of the human gastric microbiota in hypochlorhydric states arising as a result of Helicobacter pylori-induced atrophic gastritis, autoimmune atrophic gastritis and proton pump inhibitor use. PLoS Pathog. 2017;13:e1006653.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5667734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29095917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pivetta G, Dottori L, Fontana F, Cingolani S, Ligato I, Dilaghi E, Milani C, Ventura M, Borro M, Esposito G, Annibale B, Lahner E. Gastric Microbiota Gender Differences in Subjects with Healthy Stomachs and Autoimmune Atrophic Gastritis. Microorganisms. 2023;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10456958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37630498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conti L, Lenti MV, Di Sabatino A, Miceli E, Galli G, Cazzato M, Falangone F, Annibale B, Lahner E. Seronegative autoimmune atrophic gastritis is more common in elderly patients. Dig Liver Dis. 2020;52:1310–1314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32487505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coker OO, Dai Z, Nie Y, Zhao G, Cao L, Nakatsu G, Wu WK, Wong SH, Chen Z, Sung JJY, Yu J. Mucosal microbiome dysbiosis in gastric carcinogenesis. Gut. 2018;67:1024–1032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5969346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28765474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zi M, Zhang Y, Hu C, Zhang S, Chen J, Yuan L, Cheng X. A literature review on the potential clinical implications of streptococci in gastric cancer. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:1010465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9643750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36386672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu K, Cheung AHK, Wong CC, Liu W, Zhou Y, Wang F, Huang P, Yuan K, Coker OO, Pan Y, Chen D, Lam NM, Gao M, Zhang X, Huang H, To KF, Sung JJY, Yu J. Streptococcus anginosus promotes gastric inflammation, atrophy, and tumorigenesis in mice. Cell. 2024;187:882–896.e17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38295787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senthil Kumar S, Gunda V, Reinartz DM, Pond KW, Thorne CA, Santiago Raj PV, Johnson MDL, Wilson JE. Oral streptococci S. anginosus and S. mitis induce distinct morphological, inflammatory, and metabolic signatures in macrophages. Infect Immun. 2024;92:e0053623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10929413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38289109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong S, Tan P. A tough act to swallow: Streptococcusanginosus and gastric cancer. Cell Host Microbe. 2024;32:291–293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38484705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rugge M, Genta RM, Malfertheiner P, Dinis-Ribeiro M, El-Serag H, Graham DY, Kuipers EJ, Leung WK, Park JY, Rokkas T, Schulz C, El-Omar EM RE. GA.IN; RE GA IN. RE.GA.IN.: the Real-world Gastritis Initiative-updating the updates. Gut. 2024;73:407–441.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38383142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen J, Lau HC, Peppelenbosch M, Yu J. Gastric Microbiota beyond H. pylori: An Emerging Critical Character in Gastric Carcinogenesis. Biomedicines. 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8615612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34829909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnold M, Park JY, Camargo MC, Lunet N, Forman D, Soerjomataram I. Is gastric cancer becoming a rare disease? A global assessment of predicted incidence trends to 2035. Gut. 2020;69:823–829.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8520492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32001553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen M, Chen K, Hou H, Li W, Wang X, Dao Q, Wang Z. Incidence and mortality trends in gastric cancer in the United States, 1992-2019. Int J Cancer. 2023;152:1827–1836.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36562305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D, Jiang SF, Lei NY, Shah SC, Corley DA. Effect of Helicobacter pylori Eradication Therapy on the Incidence of Noncardia Gastric Adenocarcinoma in a Large Diverse Population in the United States. Gastroenterology. 2023;165:391–401.e2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37142201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson WF, Rabkin CS, Turner N, Fraumeni JF Jr, Rosenberg PS, Camargo MC. The Changing Face of Noncardia Gastric Cancer Incidence Among US Non-Hispanic Whites. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2018;110:608–615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6005150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29361173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eskander AE, Subhy NS, Abdelfattah W, Shamma RA. Antigastric parietal cell antibody as a screening test for Autoimmune gastritis in Egyptian children and adolescents with juvenile autoimmune thyroid disease and those with type 1 diabetes, single center experience. Int J Health Sci. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Besançon A, Michaud B, Beltrand J, Goncalves T, Jais JP, Polak M, Chatenoud L, Robert JJ. Revisiting autoimmune gastritis in children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes. Pediatr Diabetes. 2017;18:772–776.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28004477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orgler E, Dabsch S, Malfertheiner P, Schulz C. Autoimmune Gastritis: Update and New Perspectives in Therapeutic Management. Curr Treat Options Gastro. 2023;21:64–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Chakole S, Agrawal S, Shetty N, Prasad R, Lohakare T, Wanjari M, Yelne S. A Comprehensive Review of Upper Gastrointestinal Symptom Management in Autoimmune Gastritis: Current Insights and Future Directions. Cureus. 2023;15:e43418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10496934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37706145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duque-Buitrago LF, Tornero-Martínez A, Loera-Castañeda V, Mora-Escobedo R. Use of food and food-derived products in the treatment of gastritis: A systematic review. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2023;63:5771–5782.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34989280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kan J, Cheng J, Xu L, Hood M, Zhong D, Cheng M, Liu Y, Chen L, Du J. The combination of wheat peptides and fucoidan protects against chronic superficial gastritis and alters gut microbiota: a double-blinded, placebo-controlled study. Eur J Nutr. 2020;59:1655–1666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31230147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao X, Yin P, Ren Y, Yu L, Tian F, Zhao J, Chen W, Xue Y, Zhai Q. Predicting Personalized Diets Based on Microbial Characteristics between Patients with Superficial Gastritis and Atrophic Gastritis. Nutrients. 2023;15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10675729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38004131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>