<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39225191</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-1573</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Phytotherapy research : PTR</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Phytother Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Oroxylin A alleviates myocardial ischemia-reperfusion injury by quelling ferroptosis via activating the DUSP10/MAPK-Nrf2 pathway.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ptr.8315</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Reperfusion therapy is the primary treatment strategy for acute myocardial infarction (AMI). Paradoxically, it can lead to myocardial damage, namely myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury (MIRI). This study explored whether oroxylin A (OA) protects the myocardium after MIRI by inhibiting ferroptosis and the underlying mechanism. In vivo, we established an MIRI model to investigate the protective effect of OA. In vitro, H9C2 cells were used to explore the regulation of ferroptosis by OA through immunofluorescence staining, western blotting, assay kits, etc. Additionally, RNA sequencing analysis (RNA-seq) and network pharmacology analyses were conducted to elucidate the molecular mechanisms. Our results showed that MIRI caused cardiac structural and functional damage in rats. MIRI promoted ferroptosis, which was consistently observed in vitro. However, pretreatment with OA reversed these effects. The mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPK) signaling pathway participated in the MIRI process, with dual-specificity phosphatase 10 (DUSP10) found to regulate it. Further confirmation was provided by knocking down DUSP10 using small interfering RNA (siRNA), demonstrating the activation of the DUSP10/MAPK-Nrf2 pathway by OA to protect H9C2 cells from ferroptosis. Our research has demonstrated the mitigating effect of OA on MIRI and the improvement of myocardial function for the first time. The inhibition of ferroptosis has been identified as one of the mechanisms through which OA exerts its myocardial protective effects. Moreover, we have first unveiled that DUSP10 serves as an upstream target involved in mediating ferroptosis, and the regulation of the DUSP10/MAPK-Nrf2 pathway by OA is crucial in inhibiting ferroptosis to protect the myocardium.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Yifeng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of General Practice, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tan</LastName><ForeName>Mingyue</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Geriatrics, Southwest Hospital, The Third Military Medical University (Army Medical University), Chongqing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yin</LastName><ForeName>Yunfei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Chen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jinjihu Business District Squadron, Suzhou Industrial Park Food and Drug Safety Inspection Team, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Yongjian</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Tingbo</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Hongxia</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1440-1345</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Mingqing</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gerontology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou, Jiangsu, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>BK20190171</GrantID><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>BK20231198</GrantID><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>81100173</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>81770327</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>81901262</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>DZXYJ202302</GrantID><Agency>The Multi-center Clinical Research Project for Major Diseases in Suzhou</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Phytother Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8904486</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0951-418X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DUSP10/MAPK‐Nrf2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ferroptosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">myocardial ischemia–reperfusion injury</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oroxylin A</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">p38 MAPK</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39225191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.8315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Alonso, A., &amp; Pulido, R. (2016). The extended human PTPome: A growing tyrosine phosphatase family. The FEBS Journal, 283(8), 1404–1429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bøtker, H. E., Hausenloy, D., Andreadou, I., Antonucci, S., Boengler, K., Davidson, S. M., Deshwal, S., Devaux, Y., Di Lisa, F., Di Sante, M., Efentakis, P., Femminò, S., García‐Dorado, D., Giricz, Z., Ibanez, B., Iliodromitis, E., Kaludercic, N., Kleinbongard, P., Neuhäuser, M., … Heusch, G. (2018). Practical guidelines for rigor and reproducibility in preclinical and clinical studies on cardioprotection. Basic Research in Cardiology, 113, 39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai, W., Liu, L., Shi, X., Liu, Y., Wang, J., Fang, X., Chen, Z., Ai, D., Zhu, Y., &amp; Zhang, X. (2023). Alox15/15‐HpETE aggravates myocardial ischemia‐reperfusion injury by promoting cardiomyocyte ferroptosis. Circulation, 147, 1444–1460.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, H. J., Zhou, W., Xian, X. L., Sun, S. J., Ding, P. J., Tian, C. Y., Tian, F. L., Jiang, C. H., Fu, T. T., Zhao, S., &amp; Dai, J. Y. (2022). A mixture of baicalein, wogonin, and oroxylin‐A inhibits EMT in the A549 cell line via the PI3K/AKT‐TWIST1‐glycolysis pathway. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 12, 821485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, W., Zhang, Y., Wang, Z., Tan, M., Lin, J., Qian, X., Li, H., &amp; Jiang, T. (2023). Dapagliflozin alleviates myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury by reducing ferroptosis via MAPK signaling inhibition. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 14, 1078205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, S., Duanmu, X., Xu, L., Zhu, L., &amp; Wu, Z. (2023). Ozone pretreatment alleviates ischemiareperfusion injury‐induced myocardial ferroptosis by activating the Nrf2/Slc7a11/Gpx4 axis. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy, 165, 115185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dixon, S. J., Lemberg, K. M., Lamprecht, M. R., Skouta, R., Zaitsev, E. M., Gleason, C. E., Patel, D. N., Bauer, A. J., Cantley, A. M., Yang, W. S., Morrison, B., 3rd, &amp; Stockwell, B. R. (2012). Ferroptosis: An iron‐dependent form of nonapoptotic cell death. Cell, 149, 1060–1072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodson, M., Castro‐Portuguez, R., &amp; Zhang, D. D. (2019). NRF2 plays a critical role in mitigating lipid peroxidation and ferroptosis. Redox Biology, 23, 101107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, Z., Cai, L., Wang, S., Wang, J., &amp; Chen, B. (2021). Baicalin prevents myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury through inhibiting ACSL4 mediated ferroptosis. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 12, 628988.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, Z., Han, Y., Ye, Y., Liu, C., &amp; Cai, H. (2017). l‐Carnitine preserves cardiac function by activating p38 MAPK/Nrf2 signalling in hearts exposed to irradiation. European Journal of Pharmacology, 804, 7–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, X., Ardehali, H., Min, J., &amp; Wang, F. (2023). The molecular and metabolic landscape of iron and ferroptosis in cardiovascular disease. Nature Reviews. Cardiology, 20, 7–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, X., Wang, H., Han, D., Xie, E., Yang, X., Wei, J., Gu, S., Gao, F., Zhu, N., Yin, X., Cheng, Q., Zhang, P., Dai, W., Chen, J., Yang, F., Yang, H. T., Linkermann, A., Gu, W., Min, J., &amp; Wang, F. (2019). Ferroptosis as a target for protection against cardiomyopathy. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 116, 2672–2680.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, J., Yang, Y., Zhou, Y., Wang, B., Xiong, H., Fan, C., Jiang, S., Liu, J., Ma, Z., Hu, W., Li, T., Feng, X., Xu, J., &amp; Jin, Z. (2016). Bakuchiol attenuates myocardial ischemia reperfusion injury by maintaining mitochondrial function: The role of silent information regulator 1. Apoptosis: An International Journal on Programmed Cell Death, 21(5), 532–545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fotakis, G., &amp; Timbrell, J. A. (2006). In vitro cytotoxicity assays: Comparison of LDH, neutral red, MTT and protein assay in hepatoma cell lines following exposure to cadmium chloride. Toxicology Letters, 160, 171–177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, X., Tian, X., Huang, Y., Fang, R., Wang, G., Li, D., Zhang, J., Li, T., &amp; Yuan, R. (2022). Role of circular RNA in myocardial ischemia and ageing‐related diseases. Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Reviews, 65, 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gourine, A. V., Molosh, A. I., Poputnikov, D., Bulhak, A., Sjöquist, P. O., &amp; Pernow, J. (2005). Endothelin‐1 exerts a preconditioning‐like cardioprotective effect against ischaemia/reperfusion injury via the ET(A) receptor and the mitochondrial K(ATP) channel in the rat in vivo. British Journal of Pharmacology, 144, 331–337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granado‐Serrano, A. B., Martín, M. A., Bravo, L., Goya, L., &amp; Ramos, S. (2012). Quercetin modulates Nrf2 and glutathione‐related defenses in HepG2 cells: Involvement of p38. Chemico‐Biological Interactions, 195, 154–164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, B., Zuo, Z., Di, X., Huang, Y., Gong, G., Xu, B., Wang, L., Zhang, X., Liang, Z., Hou, Y., Liu, X., &amp; Hu, Z. (2022). Salidroside attenuates HALI via IL‐17A‐mediated ferroptosis of alveolar epithelial cells by regulating Act1‐TRAF6‐p38 MAPK pathway. Cell Communication and Signaling, 20(1), 183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, W., Liu, X., Li, J., Shen, Y., Zhou, Z., Wang, M., Xie, Y., Feng, X., Wang, L., &amp; Wu, X. (2018). Prdx1 alleviates cardiomyocyte apoptosis through ROS‐activated MAPK pathway during myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 112, 608–615.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heusch, G. (2020). Myocardial ischaemia‐reperfusion injury and cardioprotection in perspective. Nature Reviews. Cardiology, 17, 773–789.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, d. W., Sherman, B. T., &amp; Lempicki, R. A. (2009). Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources. Nature Protocols, 4, 44–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia, D., Liu, C., Zhu, Z., Cao, Y., Wen, W., Hong, Z., Liu, Y., Liu, E., Chen, L., Chen, C., Gu, Y., Jiao, B., Chai, Y., Wang, H. Y., Fu, J., &amp; Chen, X. (2022). Novel transketolase inhibitor oroxylin A suppresses the non‐oxidative pentose phosphate pathway and hepatocellular carcinoma tumour growth in mice and patient‐derived organoids. Clinical and Translational Medicine, 12, e1095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, S., Yang, Y., Li, T., Ma, Z., Hu, W., Deng, C., Fan, C., Lv, J., Sun, Y., &amp; Yi, W. (2016). An overview of the mechanisms and novel roles of Nrf2 in cardiovascular diseases. Expert Opinion on Therapeutic Targets, 20(12), 1413–1424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, X., Stockwell, B. R., &amp; Conrad, M. (2021). Ferroptosis: Mechanisms, biology and role in disease. Nature Reviews. Molecular Cell Biology, 22(4), 266–282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiménez‐Martínez, M., Stamatakis, K., &amp; Fresno, M. (2019). The dual‐specificity phosphatase 10 (DUSP10): Its role in cancer, inflammation, and immunity. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 20, 1626.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin, J. K., Blackwood, E. A., Azizi, K., Thuerauf, D. J., Fahem, A. G., Hofmann, C., Kaufman, R. J., Doroudgar, S., &amp; Glembotski, C. C. (2017). ATF6 decreases myocardial ischemia/reperfusion damage and links ER stress and oxidative stress signaling pathways in the heart. Circulation Research, 120(5), 862–875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keyse, S. M. (2008). Dual‐specificity MAP kinase phosphatases (MKPs) and cancer. Cancer Metastasis Reviews, 27(2), 253–261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, W. Y., Liu, K. W., &amp; Yeung, J. H. (2009). Reactive oxygen species‐mediated kinase activation by dihydrotanshinone in tanshinones‐induced apoptosis in HepG2 cells. Cancer Letters, 285, 46–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Miao, B., Wang, S., Dong, W., Xu, H., Si, C., Wang, W., Duan, S., Lou, J., Bao, Z., Zeng, H., Yang, Z., Cheng, W., Zhao, F., Zeng, J., Liu, X. S., Wu, R., Shen, Y., Chen, Z., … Hiplot Consortium. (2022). Hiplot: A comprehensive and easy‐to‐use web service for boosting publication‐ready biomedical data visualization. Briefings in Bioinformatics, 23, bbac261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Tong, D., Liu, J., Chen, F., &amp; Shen, Y. (2016). Oroxylin a attenuates cigarette smoke‐induced lung inflammation by activating Nrf2. International Immunopharmacology, 40, 524–529.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, S., He, Y., Chen, K., Sun, J., Zhang, L., He, Y., Yu, H., &amp; Li, Q. (2021). RSL3 drives ferroptosis through NF‐κB pathway activation and GPX4 depletion in glioblastoma. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity, 2021, 2915019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, D., Feng, Y., Zandkarimi, F., Wang, H., Zhang, Z., Kim, J., Cai, Y., Gu, W., Stockwell, B. R., &amp; Jiang, X. (2023). Ferroptosis surveillance independent of GPX4 and differentially regulated by sex hormones. Cell, 186, 2748–2764.e22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lillo‐Moya, J., Rojas‐Solé, C., Muñoz‐Salamanca, D., Panieri, E., Saso, L., &amp; Rodrigo, R. (2021). Targeting ferroptosis against ischemia/reperfusion cardiac injury. Antioxidants, 10, 667.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, M., Qin, Y., Hu, Q., Liu, W., Ji, S., Xu, W., Fan, G., Ye, Z., Zhang, Z., Xu, X., Yu, X., &amp; Zhuo, Q. (2021). SETD8 potentiates constitutive ERK1/2 activation via epigenetically silencing DUSP10 expression in pancreatic cancer. Cancer Letters, 499, 265–278.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, X., Zhang, C. S., Lu, C., Lin, S. C., Wu, J. W., &amp; Wang, Z. X. (2016). A conserved motif in JNK/p38‐specific MAPK phosphatases as a determinant for JNK1 recognition and inactivation. Nature Communications, 7, 10879.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, L., Guo, Q., &amp; Zhao, L. (2016). Overview of oroxylin A: A promising flavonoid compound. Phytotherapy Research, 30, 1765–1774.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, X. H., Liu, J. H., Liu, C. Y., Sun, W. Y., Duan, W. J., Wang, G., Kurihara, H., He, R. R., Li, Y. F., Chen, Y., &amp; Shang, H. (2022). ALOX15‐launched PUFA‐phospholipids peroxidation increases the susceptibility of ferroptosis in ischemia‐induced myocardial damage. Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy, 7, 288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyamoto, H. D., Ikeda, M., Ide, T., Tadokoro, T., Furusawa, S., Abe, K., Ishimaru, K., Enzan, N., Sada, M., Yamamoto, T., Matsushima, S., Koumura, T., Yamada, K. I., Imai, H., &amp; Tsutsui, H. (2022). Iron overload via heme degradation in the endoplasmic reticulum triggers ferroptosis in myocardial ischemia‐reperfusion injury. JACC Basic to Translational Science, 7, 800–819.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison, D. K. (2012). MAP kinase pathways. Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology, 4, a011254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, T. J., Park, J. H., Lee, G. S., Lee, J. Y., Shin, J. H., Kim, M. W., Kim, Y. S., Kim, J. Y., Oh, K. J., Han, B. S., Kim, W. K., Ahn, Y., Moon, J. H., Song, J., Bae, K. H., Kim, D. H., Lee, E. W., &amp; Lee, S. C. (2019). Quantitative proteomic analyses reveal that GPX4 downregulation during myocardial infarction contributes to ferroptosis in cardiomyocytes. Cell Death &amp; Disease, 10, 835.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porras, A., Zuluaga, S., Black, E., Valladares, A., Alvarez, A. M., Ambrosino, C., Benito, M., &amp; Nebreda, A. R. (2004). P38 alpha mitogen‐activated protein kinase sensitizes cells to apoptosis induced by different stimuli. Molecular Biology of the Cell, 15, 922–933.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sajeev, A., Hegde, M., Girisa, S., Devanarayanan, T. N., Alqahtani, M. S., Abbas, M., Sil, S. K., Sethi, G., Chen, J. T., &amp; Kunnumakkara, A. B. (2022). Oroxylin A: A promising flavonoid for prevention and treatment of chronic diseases. Biomolecules, 12, 1185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, S., He, F., Cheng, C., Xu, B., &amp; Sheng, J. (2021). Uric acid aggravates myocardial ischemia‐reperfusion injury via ROS/NLRP3 pyroptosis pathway. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy = Biomedecine &amp; Pharmacotherapie, 133, 110990.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, J., Ma, C., Zheng, Z., Zhang, T., Li, Z., Sun, X., He, Z., Zhang, Z., &amp; Zhang, C. (2023). Low‐dose antimony exposure promotes prostate cancer proliferation by inhibiting ferroptosis via activation of the Nrf2‐SLC7A11‐GPX4 pathway. Chemosphere, 339, 139716.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, N. N., Zhao, Y., Sun, C., Zhang, J., Lin, G. J., Yin, X. W., &amp; Ma, C. Y. (2023). DUSP10 alleviates ischemic stroke‐induced neuronal damage by restricting p38/JNK pathway. Behavioural Brain Research, 450, 114478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stockwell, B. R. (2022). Ferroptosis turns 10: Emerging mechanisms, physiological functions, and therapeutic applications. Cell, 185, 2401–2421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, M., Yin, Y., Ma, X., Zhang, J., Pan, W., Tan, M., Zhao, Y., Yang, T., Jiang, T., &amp; Li, H. (2023). Glutathione system enhancement for cardiac protection: Pharmacological options against oxidative stress and ferroptosis. Cell Death &amp; Disease, 14(2), 131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, D., Chen, X., Kang, R., &amp; Kroemer, G. (2021). Ferroptosis: Molecular mechanisms and health implications. Cell Research, 31, 107–125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallert, M., Ziegler, M., Wang, X., Maluenda, A., Xu, X., Yap, M. L., Witt, R., Giles, C., Kluge, S., Hortmann, M., Zhang, J., Meikle, P., Lorkowski, S., &amp; Peter, K. (2019). α‐Tocopherol preserves cardiac function by reducing oxidative stress and inflammation in ischemia/reperfusion injury. Redox Biology, 26, 101292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, S., Fan, Y., Feng, X., Sun, C., Shi, Z., Li, T., Lv, J., Yang, Z., Zhao, Z., &amp; Sun, D. (2018). Nicorandil alleviates myocardial injury and post‐infarction cardiac remodeling by inhibiting Mst1. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, 495(1), 292–299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z., Yao, M., Jiang, L., Wang, L., Yang, Y., Wang, Q., Qian, X., Zhao, Y., &amp; Qian, J. (2022). Dexmedetomidine attenuates myocardial ischemia/reperfusion‐induced ferroptosis via AMPK/GSK‐3β/Nrf2 axis. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy, 154, 113572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber, R. A., Yen, F. S., Nicholson, S. P. V., Alwaseem, H., Bayraktar, E. C., Alam, M., Timson, R. C., La, K., Abu‐Remaileh, M., Molina, H., &amp; Birsoy, K. (2020). Maintaining iron homeostasis is the key role of lysosomal acidity for cell proliferation. Molecular Cell, 77, 645–655.e7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, J., Mao, X., Cai, T., Luo, J., &amp; Wei, L. (2006). KOBAS server: A web‐based platform for automated annotation and pathway identification. Nucleic Acids Research, 34, W720–W724.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, X., Li, Y., Zhang, S., &amp; Zhou, X. (2021). Ferroptosis as a novel therapeutic target for cardiovascular disease. Theranostics, 11, 3052–3059.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing, Y., Sui, Z., Liu, Y., Wang, M. M., Wei, X., Lu, Q., Wang, X., Liu, N., Lu, C., Chen, R., Wu, M., Wang, Y., Zhao, Y. H., Guo, F., Cao, J. L., Qi, J., &amp; Wang, W. (2022). Blunting TRPML1 channels protects myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury by restoring impaired cardiomyocyte autophagy. Basic Research in Cardiology, 117(1), 20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, X., Mao, C., Zhang, C., Zhang, M., Gong, J., &amp; Wang, X. (2023). Salvianolic acid B inhibits ferroptosis and apoptosis during myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury via decreasing the ubiquitin‐proteasome degradation of GPX4 and the ROS‐JNK/MAPK pathways. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 28(10), 4117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto, T., Endo, Y., Onodera, A., Hirahara, K., Asou, H. K., Nakajima, T., Kanno, T., Ouchi, Y., Uematsu, S., Nishimasu, H., Nureki, O., Tumes, D. J., Shimojo, N., &amp; Nakayama, T. (2018). DUSP10 constrains innate IL‐33‐mediated cytokine production in ST2hi memory‐type pathogenic Th2 cells. Nature Communications, 9, 4231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, J., Li, Z., Liang, Y., Yang, C., Ou, W., Mo, H., Tang, M., Chen, D., Zhong, C., Que, D., Feng, L., Xiao, H., Song, X., &amp; Yang, P. (2023). Fucoxanthin alleviated myocardial ischemia and reperfusion injury through inhibition of ferroptosis via the NRF2 signaling pathway. Food &amp; Function, 14(22), 10052–10068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, J., Mo, J., Dai, J., Ye, C., Cen, W., Zheng, X., Jiang, L., &amp; Ye, L. (2021). Cetuximab promotes RSL3‐induced ferroptosis by suppressing the Nrf2/HO‐1 signalling pathway in KRAS mutant colorectal cancer. Cell Death &amp; Disease, 12, 1079.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Y., Zhang, S., Fan, C., Yi, W., Jiang, S., Di, S., Ma, Z., Hu, W., Deng, C., Lv, J., Li, T., Nie, Y., &amp; Jin, Z. (2016). Protective role of silent information regulator 1 against hepatic ischemia: Effects on oxidative stress injury, inflammatory response, and MAPKs. Expert Opinion on Therapeutic Targets, 20(5), 519–531.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao, Y., Li, F., Zhang, M., Jin, L., Xie, P., Liu, D., Zhang, J., Hu, X., Lv, F., Shang, H., Zheng, W., Sun, X., Duanmu, J., Wu, F., Lan, F., Xiao, R. P., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2022). Targeting CaMKII‐δ9 ameliorates cardiac ischemia/reperfusion injury by inhibiting myocardial inflammation. Circulation Research, 130, 887–903.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeitler, L., Fiore, A., Meyer, C., Russier, M., Zanella, G., Suppmann, S., Gargaro, M., Sidhu, S. S., Seshagiri, S., Ohnmacht, C., Köcher, T., Fallarino, F., Linkermann, A., &amp; Murray, P. J. (2021). Anti‐ferroptotic mechanism of IL4i1‐mediated amino acid metabolism. eLife, 10, e64806.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai, M., Li, B., Duan, W., Jing, L., Zhang, B., Zhang, M., Yu, L., Liu, Z., Yu, B., Ren, K., Gao, E., Yang, Y., Liang, H., Jin, Z., &amp; Yu, S. (2017). Melatonin ameliorates myocardial ischemia reperfusion injury through SIRT3‐dependent regulation of oxidative stress and apoptosis. Journal of Pineal Research, 63, e12419. https://doi.org/10.1111/jpi.12419</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Pan, W., Zhang, Y., Tan, M., Yin, Y., Li, Y., Zhang, L., Han, L., Bai, J., Jiang, T., &amp; Li, H. (2022). Comprehensive overview of Nrf2‐related epigenetic regulations involved in ischemia‐reperfusion injury. Theranostics, 12(15), 6626–6645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Liu, D., Hu, H., Zhang, P., Xie, R., &amp; Cui, W. (2019). HIF‐1α/BNIP3 signaling pathway‐induced‐autophagy plays protective role during myocardial ischemia‐reperfusion injury. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy, 120, 109464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, Y., Zhu, Q., Bu, X., Zhou, Y., Bai, D., Guo, Q., Gao, Y., &amp; Lu, N. (2020). Triggering apoptosis by oroxylin A through caspase‐8 activation and p62/SQSTM1 proteolysis. Redox Biology, 29, 101392.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, W., Xu, Y., Zhang, J., Zhang, P., Yao, Z., Yan, Z., Wang, H., Chu, J., Yao, S., Zhao, S., Yang, S., Guo, Y., Miao, J., Liu, K., Chan, W. C., Xia, Q., &amp; Liu, Y. (2022). MiRNA‐363‐3p/DUSP10/JNK axis mediates chemoresistance by enhancing DNA damage repair in diffuse large B‐cell lymphoma. Leukemia, 36, 1861–1869.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>