<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39229821</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Direct competitive immunoassay method for sensitive detection of the histamine in foods based on a MI-Cu-GMP nanozyme marker and molecularly imprinted biomimetic antibody.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13869</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Histamine may lead to low blood pressure, skin flushing and edema when it accumulates in large amounts in the body. Therefore, establishing sensitive methods for the detection of histamine in foods is extremely important to ensure food safety and human health.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The MI-Cu-GMP NPs (2-methylimidazole-copper-guanosine monophosphate nanozymes) with high laccase-like activity were synthesized. Using the prepared molecular imprinted membrane as biomimetic antibody and MI-Cu-GMP NPs as marker, a sensitive direct competitive biomimetic enzyme-linked immunoassay (BELISA) method for rapid detection of the histamine in foods was developed. Under optimal conditions, the limit of detection (LOD, IC<sub>15</sub>) and sensitivity (IC<sub>50</sub>) of the BELISA method for histamine was 0.05 mg L<sup>-1</sup> and 1.22 mg L<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. The liquor samples spiked with histamine was detected by the BELISA method with satisfactory recoveries ranging from 90.00% to 116.00%. Further, the level of histamine in three samples (cooking wine, rice vinegar and soy sauce) was tested by the BELISA and high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), with no significant difference found between the two methods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Given the advantages, the established BELISA method is expected to provide practical guidance for the monitoring of histamine in food and provides a foundation for the detection of other food hazards. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peng</LastName><ForeName>Xinli</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Processing Technology and Quality Control in Shandong Province, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, Tai'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Siqi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Processing Technology and Quality Control in Shandong Province, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, Tai'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Su</LastName><ForeName>Kaiyue</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Processing Technology and Quality Control in Shandong Province, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, Tai'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Yufeng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Processing Technology and Quality Control in Shandong Province, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, Tai'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Zhixiang</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8418-4182</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Processing Technology and Quality Control in Shandong Province, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, Tai'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>32372431</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2022TSGC2409</GrantID><Agency>Innovation Capability Improvement Project of Scientific and Technological Small and Medium-sized Enterprises in Shandong Province</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biomimetic immunoassay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">histamine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecularly imprinted membrane</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nanozyme</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39229821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Li YF, Lin ZZ, Hong CY and Huang ZY, Histamine detection in fish samples based on indirect competitive ELISA method using iron‐cobalt co‐doped carbon dots labeled histamine antibody. Food Chem 345:128812 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turna NS, Chung R and McIntyre L, A review of biogenic amines in fermented foods: occurrence and health effects. Heliyon 10:e24501 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa DJE, Martínez AM, Ribeiro WF, Bichinho KM, Di NMS, Pistonesi MF et al., Determination of tryptamine in foods using square wave adsorptive stripping voltammetry. Talanta 154:134–140 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barik B and Mohapatra S, Selective visual detection of histamine and ascorbic acid through the rapid gel‐sol transition of luminescent alginate hydrogel. Sensors Actuators B Chem 367:132128 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayer HK and Fiechter G, UHPLC analysis of biogenic amines in different cheese varieties. Food Control 93:9–16 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Zhuang DN, Hu XJ, Zhang S, He ZY, Zeng MM et al., Rapid determination of histamine in fish by thin‐layer chromatography‐image analysis method using diazotized visualization reagent prepared with p‐nitroaniline. Anal Methods 10:3386–3392 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eirini K, Apostolia T, Constantinos KZ and Paraskevas DT, Specific determination of histamine in cheese and cured meat products by ion chromatography coupled to fluorimetric detection. Microchem J 168:106513 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C, Wang XM, Waterhouse GIN, Qiao XG and Xu ZX, A surface‐imprinted surface‐enhanced Raman scattering sensor for histamine detection based on dual semiconductors and Ag nanoparticles. Food Chem 369:130971 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R, Xu ZQ and Yang X, Study the key biogenic amines in luncheon meat by capillary electrophoresis with indirect ultraviolet detection. J Sep Sci 45:4107–4115 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie J, Tang MQ, Chen J, Zhu YH, Lei CB, He HW et al., A sandwich ELISA‐like detection of C‐reactive protein in blood by citicoline‐bovine serum albumin conjugate and aptamer‐functionalized gold nanoparticles nanozyme. Talanta 217:121070 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu QR, Tian JX, Jiang MD, Qiao XG and Xu ZX, Direct competitive biomimetic immunoassay based on quantum dot label for simultaneous determination of two pesticide residues in fruit and vegetable samples. Food Anal Methods 11:3015–3022 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali GK and Omer KM, Molecular imprinted polymer combined with aptamer (MIP‐aptamer) as a hybrid dual recognition element for bio (chemical) sensing applications. Review. Talanta 236:122878 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nardo FD, Anfossi L and Baggiani C, MIP‐based immunoassays: a critical review. Anal Chim Acta 1277:341547 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Ma XG, Peng YQ, Liu YY and Zhang HY, Selective and fast removal and determination of β‐lactam antibiotics in aqueous solution using multiple templates imprinted polymers based on magnetic hybrid carbon material. J Hazard Mater 416:126098 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie XW, Ma XG, Guo LH, Fan YM, Zeng GL, Zhang MY et al., Novel magnetic multi‐templates molecularly imprinted polymer for selective and rapid removal and detection of alkylphenols in water. Chem Eng J 357:56–65 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battaglia F, Bonelli F, Sgorbini M, Intorre L, Minunni M, Scarano S et al., Molecularly imprinted polymers as effective capturing receptors in a pseudo‐ELISA immunoassay for procalcitonin detection in veterinary species. Anal Methods 15:27–35 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khatami SH, Vakili O, Movahedpour A, Ghesmati Z, Ghasemi H and Anganeh MT, Laccase: various types and applications. Biotechnol Appl Biochem 69:2658–2672 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang H, Lin FF, Zhang ZJ, Liu BW, Jiang SH, Yuan QP et al., Multicopper laccase mimicking nanozymes with nucleotides as ligands. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces 9:1352–1360 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li MN, Xie YF, Song DH, Huang H and Li XY, 2‐methylimidazole‐doped nanozymes with enhanced laccase activity for the (+)‐catechins detection in dairy products. Talanta 252:123853 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu Z, Guo F, Qiu JH, Zhang RC, Wang MX and Wang LP, extension of the alkyl chain length to adjust the properties of laccase‐mimicking MOFs for phenolic detection and discrimination. Spectrochim Acta A Mol Biomol Spectrosc 281:121606 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zulfikar MA, Utami AR, Handayani N, Wahyuningrum D, Setiyanto H and Azis MY, Removal of phthalate ester compound from PVC plastic samples using magnetic molecularly imprinted polymer on the surface of superparamagnetic Fe3O4 (Fe3O4@MIPs). Environ Nanotechnol Monit Manag 17:100646 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang XF, Chen YF, Yu RZ, Wang RQ and Xu ZX, A sensitive biomimetic enzyme‐linked immunoassay method based on Au@Pt@Au composite nanozyme label and molecularly imprinted biomimetic antibody for histamine detection. Food Agric Immunol 32:592–605 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv MY, Li SH, Mao H, Feng YN, Zhang AS, Xu LH et al., Promoted propylene/nitrogen separation by direct incorporating 2‐methylimidazole into PDMS membranes. J Membr Sci 661:120902 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen ZH, Li SW, Yang F and Yue W, Construction of a colorimetric sensor array for the identification of phenolic compounds by the laccase‐like activity of N‐doped manganese oxide. Talanta 268:125324 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao FJ, Xia QH, Zhang SY, Li QL, Chen D, Li HY et al., Ultrasound and defect engineering‐enhanced nanozyme with high laccase‐like activity for oxidation and detection of phenolic compounds and adrenaline. J Hazard Mater 465:133126 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, He C, Li W, Zhang J and Fu Y, Catalytic performance of oligonucleotide‐templated Pt nanozyme evaluated by laccase substrates. Catal Lett 147:2144–2152 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parate K, Pola1 CC, Rangnekar SV, Mendivelso‐Perez DL, Smith EA, Hersam MC et al., Aerosol‐jet‐printed graphene electrochemical histamine sensors for food safety monitoring. 2D Materials 7:034002 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huynh KH, Pham XH, Hahm E, An J, Kim HM, Jo A et al., Facile histamine detection by surface‐enhanced Raman scattering using SiO2@Au@Ag alloy nanoparticles. Int J Mol Sci 21:4048 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagic M, Nejdl L, Xhaxhiu K, Cernei N, Zitka O, Jamroz E et al., Fully automated process for histamine detection based on magnetic separation and fluorescence detection. Talanta 212:120789 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Singh R, Liu FZ, Marques C, Zhang BY and Kumar S, WaveFlex biosensor: a flexible‐shaped plasmonic optical fiber sensor for histamine detection. IEEE Sensors J 23:22533–22542 (2023).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>