<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39225179</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-3016</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Paediatric and perinatal epidemiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Possible determinants of physical fitness in Japanese school children: A cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/ppe.13121</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Physical fitness is one of the most important health indicators in children. Although appropriate body composition or certain lifestyle factors such as frequent physical activity are thought to improve physical fitness, results of previous studies are inconsistent, and most studies were from Western countries.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">We investigated associations of body composition and modifiable lifestyle factors such as physical activity, screen time, diet and sleep duration with physical fitness in Japanese primary school children.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">2308 children (age 10-12 years old) in 12 primary schools were analysed in this cross-sectional study. Physical fitness was evaluated by sports battery tests conducted routinely and annually at schools. The total score of sports battery tests, 20-m shuttle run (laps) and grip strength (kg) were selected as outcomes. Information about lifestyle factors was collected by two questionnaires. Associations between lifestyle factors and physical fitness were assessed by multivariable linear mixed models by sex.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Frequent exercise was related to better overall physical fitness. Regarding the 20-m shuttle run, many unfavourable lifestyle factors such as higher BMI in boys (β -7.37, 95% confidence interval [CI] -8.39, -6.35) and girls (β -3.54, 95% CI -4.50, -2.58), longer screen time (β -4.31, 95% CI -7.29, -1.34) in boys and girls (β -5.65, 95% CI -9.01, -2.30); shortest (reference) versus longest, breakfast skipping in boys (β -5.24, 95% CI -8.71, -1.77) and girls (β -3.57, 95% CI -6.84, -0.30); consumers (reference) versus skippers were associated with worse performance. Better quality of diet was associated with better results in the 20-m shuttle run only in girls (β 2.58, 95% CI 0.24, 4.93); lowest (reference) versus highest.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Frequent exercise was related to better physical fitness. Higher BMI and unfavourable lifestyle factors such as longer screen time and breakfast skipping were associated with worse results of the 20-m shuttle run.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoshikawa</LastName><ForeName>Aya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0008-3606-8708</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental and Occupational Health, Toho University Graduate School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asakura</LastName><ForeName>Keiko</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive Medicine, School of Medicine, Toho University Graduate School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mori</LastName><ForeName>Sachie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental and Occupational Health, School of Medicine, Toho University Graduate School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fujiwara</LastName><ForeName>Aya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9928-1946</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Food Safety Information, National Institutes of Health Sciences, Kawasaki City, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutritional Epidemiology and Shokuiku, National Institutes of Biomedical Innovation, Health and Nutrition, Osaka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sasaki</LastName><ForeName>Satoshi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Preventive Epidemiology, School of Public Health, The University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nishiwaki</LastName><ForeName>Yuji</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental and Occupational Health, School of Medicine, Toho University Graduate School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>20H01621</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8709766</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0269-5022</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Japan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">body composition</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">physical activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">physical fitness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">primary school children</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39225179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ppe.13121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Ortega FB, Cadenas‐Sanchez C, Lee DC, Ruiz JR, Blair SN, Sui X. Fitness and fatness as health markers through the lifespan: an overview of current knowledge. Prog Prev Med. 2018;3:e0013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega FB, Ruiz JR, Castillo MJ, Sjöström M. Physical fitness in childhood and adolescence: a powerful marker of health. Int J Obes (Lond). 2008;32:1‐11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blair SN, Kohl HW, Paffenbarger RS, Clark DG, Cooper KH, Gibbons LW. Physical fitness and all‐cause mortality. A prospective study of healthy men and women. JAMA. 1989;262:2395‐2401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mora S, Redberg RF, Cui Y, et al. Ability of exercise testing to predict cardiovascular and all‐cause death in asymptomatic women: a 20‐year follow‐up of the lipid research clinics prevalence study. JAMA. 2003;290:1600‐1607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metter EJ, Talbot LA, Schrager M, Conwit R. Skeletal muscle strength as a predictor of all‐cause mortality in healthy men. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2002;57:B359‐B365.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim Y, White T, Wijndaele K, et al. The combination of cardiorespiratory fitness and muscle strength, and mortality risk. Eur J Epidemiol. 2018;33:953‐964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Froberg K, Andersen LB. Mini review: physical activity and fitness and its relations to cardiovascular disease risk factors in children. Int J Obes (Lond). 2005;29:S34‐S39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malina RM. Tracking of physical activity and physical fitness across the lifespan. Res Q Exerc Sport. 1996;67:S48‐S57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasayama K, Adachi M. Tracking of objective physical activity and physical fitness in Japanese children. BMC Res Notes. 2019;12:252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García‐Hermoso A, Izquierdo M, Ramírez‐Vélez R. Tracking of physical fitness levels from childhood and adolescence to adulthood: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. Transl Pediatr. 2022;11:474‐486.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eberhardt T, Niessner C, Oriwol D, Buchal L, Worth A, Bös K. Secular trends in physical fitness of children and adolescents: a review of large‐scale epidemiological studies published after 2006. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:5671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fühner T, Kliegl R, Arntz F, Kriemler S, Granacher U. An update on secular trends in physical fitness of children and adolescents from 1972 to 2015: a systematic review. Sports Med. 2021;51:303‐320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masanovic B, Gardasevic J, Marques A, et al. Trends in physical fitness among school‐aged children and adolescents: a systematic review. Front Pediatr. 2020;8:627529.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Japan Sports Agency. The new National Statistical Survey on physical fitness and motor ability, and physical activities. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Japan Sports Agency. Results of the national survey on physical fitness, exercise ability, and exercise habits. 2020. https://www.mext.go.jp/prev_sports/comp/b_menu/other/__icsFiles/afieldfile/2018/12/19/1411922_061‐083.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatta N, Tada Y, Ishikawa‐Takata K, et al. Energy intake from healthy foods is associated with motor fitness in addition to physical activity: a cross‐sectional study of first‐grade schoolchildren in Japan. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:1819.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka C, Abe T, Tanaka S, et al. Results from the Japan 2022 report card on physical activity for children and youth. J Exerc Sci Fit. 2022;20:349‐354.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuenca‐García M, Ortega FB, Huybrechts I, et al. Cardiorespiratory fitness and dietary intake in European adolescents: the healthy lifestyle in Europe by nutrition in adolescence study. Br J Nutr. 2012;107:1850‐1859.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saeedi P, Black KE, Haszard JJ, et al. Dietary patterns, cardiorespiratory and muscular fitness in 9−11‐year‐old children from Dunedin, New Zealand. Nutrients. 2018;10:887.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaqout M, Vyncke K, Moreno LA, et al. Determinant factors of physical fitness in European children. Int J Public Health. 2016;61:573‐582.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka C, Tremblay MS, Okuda M, et al. Association between 24‐hour movement guidelines and physical fitness in children. Pediatr Int. 2020;62:1381‐1387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology. The new National Statistical Survey on physical fitness and motor ability. 2018. https://www.mext.go.jp/sports/b_menu/toukei/kodomo/zencyo/1411922.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lang JJ, Tremblay MS, Léger L, Olds T, Tomkinson GR. International variability in 20 m shuttle run performance in children and youth: who are the fittest from a 50‐country comparison? A systematic literature review with pooling of aggregate results. Br J Sports Med. 2018;52:276.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro‐Pinero J, Artero EG, Espana‐Romero V, et al. Criterion‐related validity of field‐based fitness tests in youth: a systematic review. Br J Sports Med. 2010;44:934‐943.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Léger L, Lambert J, Goulet A, Rowan C, Dinelle Y. Aerobic capacity of 6 to 17‐year‐old Quebecois–20 meter shuttle run test with 1 minute stages. Can J Appl Sport Sci. 1984;9:64‐69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz JR, Rizzo NS, Hurtig‐Wennlöf A, Ortega FB, Wärnberg J, Sjöström M. Relations of total physical activity and intensity to fitness and fatness in children: the European youth heart study. Am J Clin Nutr. 2006;84:299‐303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mesa JL, Ruiz JR, Ortega FB, et al. Aerobic physical fitness in relation to blood lipids and fasting glycaemia in adolescents: influence of weight status. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2006;16:285‐293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaput JP, Willumsen J, Bull F, et al. 2020 WHO guidelines on physical activity and sedentary behaviour for children and adolescents aged 5‐17 years: summary of the evidence. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2020;17:141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tremblay MS, Carson V, Chaput JP, et al. Canadian 24‐hour movement guidelines for children and youth: an integration of physical activity, sedentary behaviour, and sleep. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab. 2016;41:S311‐S327.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobayashi S, Honda S, Murakami K, et al. Both comprehensive and brief self‐administered diet history questionnaires satisfactorily rank nutrient intakes in Japanese adults. J Epidemiol. 2012;22:151‐159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobayashi S, Murakami K, Sasaki S, et al. Comparison of relative validity of food group intakes estimated by comprehensive and brief‐type self‐administered diet history questionnaires against 16 d dietary records in Japanese adults. Public Health Nutr. 2011;14:1200‐1211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okuda M, Sasaki S, Bando N, et al. Carotenoid, tocopherol, and fatty acid biomarkers and dietary intake estimated by using a brief self‐administered diet history questionnaire for older Japanese children and adolescents. J Nutr Sci Vitaminol. 2009;55:231‐241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujiwara A, Murakami K, Sasaki S. Relative validity of starch and sugar intake in Japanese adults as estimated with comprehensive and brief self‐administered diet history questionnaires. J Epidemiol. 2020;30:315‐325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Conucil for Schience and Technology. Standard tables of food composition in Japan fifth revised and enlarged edition‐2010. Official Gazette Cooperation; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujiwara A, Murakami K, Asakura K, et al. Estimation of starch and sugar intake in a Japanese population based on a newly developed food composition database. Nutrients. 2018;10(10):1474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murakami K, Miyake Y, Sasaki S, Tanaka K, Arakawa M. Fish and n‐3 polyunsaturated fatty acid intake and depressive symptoms: Ryukyus child health study. Pediatrics. 2010;126:e623‐e630.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drewnowski A, Fulgoni VL. Nutrient density: principles and evaluation tools. Am J Clin Nutr. 2014;99(5 Suppl):1223S‐1228S. doi:10.3945/ajcn.113.073395</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murakami K, Livingstone MBE, Fujiwara A, Sasaki S. Breakfast in Japan: findings from the 2012 National Health and nutrition survey. Nutrients. 2018;10(10):1551. doi:10.3390/nu10101551</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drewnowski A. The nutrient rich foods index helps to identify healthy, affordable foods. Am J Clin Nutr. 2010;91:1095S‐1101S.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fulgoni VL, Keast DR, Drewnowski A. Development and validation of the nutrient‐rich foods index: a tool to measure nutritional quality of foods. J Nutr. 2009;139:1549‐1554.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare. Dietary Reference Intakes for Japanese. 2020. https://www.mhlw.go.jp/content/10900000/001150922.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Guideline: Sugars Intake for Adults and Children. 2015. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241549028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato N, Sato K, Takimoto H, Sudo N. BMI for age references for Japanese children–based on the 2000 growth survey. Asia Pac J Public Health. 2008;20(Suppl):118‐127.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato N, Takimoto H, Sudo N. The cubic functions for spline smoothed L, S and M values for BMI reference data of Japanese children. Clin Pediatr Endocrinol. 2011;20:47‐49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reilly JJ. Diagnostic accuracy of the BMI for age in paediatrics. Int J Obes (Lond). 2006;30:595‐597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murakami K, Livingstone MBE, Fujiwara A, Sasaki S. Reproducibility and relative validity of the healthy eating Index‐2015 and nutrient‐rich food index 9.3 estimated by comprehensive and brief diet history questionnaires in Japanese adults. Nutrients. 2019;11(10):2540.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaal S, Kerr MA, Ward M, McNulty H, Livingstone MBE. Breakfast consumption in the UK: patterns, nutrient intake and diet quality. A study from the International Breakfast Research Initiative Group. Nutrients. 2018;10(8):999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamo KB, Prince SA, Tricco AC, Connor‐Gorber S, Tremblay M. A comparison of indirect versus direct measures for assessing physical activity in the pediatric population: a systematic review. Int J Pediatr Obes. 2009;4:2‐27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizzo NS, Ruiz JR, Hurtig‐Wennlöf A, Ortega FB, Sjöström M. Relationship of physical activity, fitness, and fatness with clustered metabolic risk in children and adolescents: the European youth heart study. J Pediatr. 2007;150:388‐394.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myers J, Kokkinos P, Nyelin E. Physical activity, cardiorespiratory fitness, and the metabolic syndrome. Nutrients. 2019;11(7):1652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guthold R, Stevens GA, Riley LM, Bull FC. Worldwide trends in insufficient physical activity from 2001 to 2016: a pooled analysis of 358 population‐based surveys with 1·9 million participants. Lancet Glob Health. 2018;6:e1077‐e1086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deforche B, Lefevre J, De Bourdeaudhuij I, Hills AP, Duquet W, Bouckaert J. Physical fitness and physical activity in obese and nonobese Flemish youth. Obes Res. 2003;11:434‐441.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carson V, Hunter S, Kuzik N, et al. Systematic review of sedentary behaviour and health indicators in school‐aged children and youth: an update. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab. 2016;41:S240‐S265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandercock GRH, Ogunleye A, Voss C. Screen time and physical activity in youth: thief of time or lifestyle choice? J Phys Act Health. 2012;9:977‐984.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Araújo LGM, Turi BC, Locci B, Mesquita CAA, Fonsati NB, Monteiro HL. Patterns of physical activity and screen time among Brazilian children. J Phys Act Health. 2018;15:457‐461.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edelson LR, Mathias KC, Fulgoni VL, Karagounis LG. Screen‐based sedentary behavior and associations with functional strength in 6‐15 year‐old children in the United States. BMC Public Health. 2016;16:116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fonseca APLM, de Azevedo CVM, Santos RMR. Sleep and health‐related physical fitness in children and adolescents: a systematic review. Sleep Sci. 2021;14:357‐365.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laurson KR, Lee JA, Gentile DA, Walsh DA, Eisenmann JC. Concurrent associations between physical activity, screen time, and sleep duration with childhood obesity. ISRN Obes. 2014;2014:204540.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vos MB, Kaar JL, Welsh JA, et al. Added sugars and cardiovascular disease risk in children: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2017;135:e1017‐e1034.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Education C, Sports, Science and Technology. Guideline for making the countermeasure for prevention of heatstroke in school. 2021. https://www.mext.go.jp/content/210528‐mxt_kyousei01‐000015427_02.pdf</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>