<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39220321</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2092-6456</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>33</Volume><Issue>13</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food science and biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Sci Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comprehensive antigenotoxic profile of endemic <i>Cirsium steriolepis</i> Petrak extracts against hydrogen peroxide induced toxicity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3131</StartPage><EndPage>3152</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3131-3152</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10068-024-01555-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Cyto/genotoxicity have been widespread utilized for the safety risk assessment of synthetic/natural chemicals. Plants can protect organisms from harmful effects of xenobiotics. On the other hand, plants can extract toxic molecules from the environment which may disrupt mitosis and cytokinesis. However, the precise role of <i>Cirsium steriolepis</i> during this process is unknown. We showed that <i>steriolepis</i> didn't cause cyto/genotoxicity. Findings showed powerful inhibition in micronucleus formation and they are safe for healthy human lymphocytes in terms of their capacity to generate chromosomal aberrations. They caused significant increases in sister chromatid exchange (SCE) compared to control but they were able to decrease SCE frequency caused by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Additionally, the antibacterial efficiencies of the samples against <i>Escherichia coli</i> and <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> were up to 50% of the effectivity of penicillin/streptomycin. <i>Steriolepis</i> was able to protect the organism from the oxidative damage and didn't affect the normal developmental phases of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Korean Society of Food Science and Technology 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bayhan</LastName><ForeName>Hamza</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8637-936X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Present Address: Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Faculty of Engineering and Natural Sciences, Bahcesehir University, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/00yze4d93</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.10359.3e</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2331 4764</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dogan</LastName><ForeName>Serap</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5684-3662</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Present Address: Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Faculty of Science and Literature, Balikesir University, Balikesir, Turkey.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02tv7db43</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411506.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0596 2188</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yilmaz Kardas</LastName><ForeName>Begumhan</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8446-1116</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Present Address: Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Faculty of Science and Literature, Balikesir University, Balikesir, Turkey.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02tv7db43</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411506.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0596 2188</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diken</LastName><ForeName>Mehmet Emin</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3349-939X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Present Address: Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Faculty of Science and Literature, Balikesir University, Balikesir, Turkey.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02tv7db43</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411506.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0596 2188</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dirmenci</LastName><ForeName>Tuncay</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3038-6904</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Present Address: Department of Biology Education, Necatibey Faculty of Education, Balikesir University, Balikesir, Turkey.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02tv7db43</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411506.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0596 2188</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Celikler</LastName><ForeName>Serap</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4177-3478</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Present Address: Department of Biology, Faculty of Science and Literature, Uludag University, Bursa, Turkey.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/03tg3eb07</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.34538.39</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2182 4517</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Food Sci Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9816587</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1226-7708</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chromosome aberration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cirsium steriolepis Petrak</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">In vitro</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">In vivo</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Micronucleus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sister chromatid exchange</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestAuthors declare that, there is no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39220321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11364836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10068-024-01555-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abbet C, Slacanin I, Corradi E, De Mieri M, Hamburger M, Potterat O. Comprehensive analysis of Cirsium spinosissimum Scop., a wild alpine food plant. Food Chemistry. 160: 165-170 (2014) 10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.03.068</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.03.068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24799223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel Lateif KS, Maghrabi IA, Eldeab HA. The plant natural products: their antioxidants, free radical scavengers, DNA protection and antimicrobial activities. Journal of Bioprocessing and Biotechniques. 6: 1-7 (2016)10.4172/2155-9821.1000293</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4172/2155-9821.1000293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel Migid HM, Azab YA, Ibrahim WM. Use of plant genotoxicity bioassay for the evaluation of efficiency of algal biofilters in bioremediation of toxic industrial effluent. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety. 66: 57-64 (2007) 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2005.10.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2005.10.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16376989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander EM, Aguiyi C J, Ogwu OS, Simeon O, Imoleayo OO, Debola OO, Pam D. The In vivo antioxidant protective activity of Mangifera indica cold aqueous leaf extract in Drosophila melanogaster. Journal of Advances in Biology and Biotechnology. 22: 1-7 (2019)10.9734/jabb/2019/v22i230108</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/jabb/2019/v22i230108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkhamis AI, Magaji RA, Magaji MG, Ibrahim J. Preliminary mortality and eclosion: dose-determining factors of aqueous extract of Hibiscus sabdariffa in Drosophila melanogaster. Journal of African Association of Physiological Sciences. 8: 59-61 (2020)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alothman M, Bhat R, Karim AA. Antioxidant capacity and phenolic content of selected tropical fruits from Malaysia, extracted with different solvents. Food Chemistry. 115: 785-788 (2009)10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.12.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.12.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aminjafari A, Miroliaei M, Angelova VT, Emamzadeh R, Djukic MM, Djuric A, Saso L. Antioxidant activity and protective role on protein glycation of synthetic aminocoumarins. Electronic Journal of Biotechnology. 24: 43-48 (2016)10.1016/j.ejbt.2016.08.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejbt.2016.08.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ari F, Ulukaya E, Oran S, Celikler S, Ozturk S, Ozel MZ. Promising anticancer activity of a lichen, Parmelia sulcata Taylor, against breast cancer cell lines and genotoxic effect on human lymphocytes. Cytotechnology. 67: 531-543 (2015) 10.1007/s10616-014-9713-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10616-014-9713-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4371575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24676908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydemir N, Çelikler S, Bilaloglu R. In vitro genotoxic effects of the anticancer drug gemcitabine in human lymphocytes. Mutation Research: Genetic Toxicology and Environmental Mutagenesis. 582: 35-41 (2005)10.1016/j.mrgentox.2004.12.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mrgentox.2004.12.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15781208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayhan BS, Yalçin E, Çavusoglu K, Acar A. Antidiabetic potential and multi-biological activities of Trachystemon orientalis extracts. Journal of Food Measurement and Characterization. 13: 2887-2893 (2019)10.1007/s11694-019-00209-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11694-019-00209-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barone E, Calabrese V, Mancuso C. Ferulic acid and its therapeutic potential as a hormetin for age-related diseases. Biogerontology. 10: 97-108 (2009) 10.1007/s10522-008-9160-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10522-008-9160-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18651237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basile A, Senatore F, Gargano R, Sorbo S, Del Pezzo M, Lavitola A, Ritieni A, Bruno M, Spatuzzi D, Rigano D, Vuotto ML. Antibacterial and antioxidant activities in Sideritis italica (Miller) Greuter et Burdet essential oils. Journal of Ethnopharmacology. 107: 240-248 (2006) 10.1016/j.jep.2006.03.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.03.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16690235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benhusein GM, Mutch E, Aburawi S, Williams FM. Genotoxic effect induced by hydrogen peroxide in human hepatoma cells using comet assay. Libyan Journal of Medicine. 5: 1-6 (2010)10.3402/ljm.v5i0.4637</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3402/ljm.v5i0.4637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3066752</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21483593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibiso M, Anza M, Alemayehu B. Antibacterial and antioxidant activity of Cirsium englerianum (Asteraceae), an endemic plant to Ethiopia. Research Journal of Pharmacognosy. 8: 5-12 (2021)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boligon AA, Athayde ML. Importance of HPLC in analysis of plants extracts. Austin Chromatography. 1: 1-2 (2014)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell KA, Hickman R, Fallin MD, Bakulski KM. Prenatal exposure to metals and autism spectrum disorder: current status and future directions. Current Opinion in Toxicology. 26: 39-48 (2021) 10.1016/j.cotox.2021.04.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cotox.2021.04.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11309009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39119269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celikler S, Vatan O, Yildiz G, Bilaloglu R. Evaluation of anti-oxidative, genotoxic and antigenotoxic potency of Codium tomentosum Stackhouse ethanolic extract in human lymphocytes in vitro. Food and Chemical Toxicology. 47: 796-801 (2009) 10.1016/j.fct.2009.01.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2009.01.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19167449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çelikler Kasimogullari S, Oran S, Ari F, Ulukaya E, Aztopal N, Sarimahmut M, Öztürk S. Genotoxic, cytotoxic, and apoptotic effects of crude extract of Usnea filipendula Stirt. in vitro. Turkish Journal of Biology. 38: 940-947 (2014)10.3906/biy-1405-23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3906/biy-1405-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celotti L, Bianchi V. Applications of human peripheral blood lymphocytes in genotoxicity and cytotoxicity. Alternatives to Laboratory Animals. 18: 231-241 (1990)10.1177/026119299001800123.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/026119299001800123.1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cha H, Lee S, Lee JH, Park JW. Protective effects of p-coumaric acid against acetaminophen-induced hepatotoxicity in mice. Food and Chemical Toxicology. 121: 131-139 (2018) 10.1016/j.fct.2018.08.060</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2018.08.060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30149109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung H, Sztal T, Pasricha S, Sridhar M, Batterham P, Daborn PJ. Characterization of Drosophila melanogaster cytochrome P450 genes. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 106: 5731-5736 (2009) 10.1073/pnas.0812141106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0812141106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2667016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19289821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Csupor-Löffler B, Hajdú Z, Réthy B, Zupkó I, Máthé I, Rédei T, Falkay G, Hohmann J. Antiproliferative activity of Hungarian Asteraceae species against human cancer cell lines. Part II. Phytotherapy Research. 23: 1109-1115 (2009) 10.1002/ptr.2755</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.2755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19170144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Paiva LB, Goldbeck R, dos Santos WD, Squina FM. Ferulic acid and derivatives: molecules with potential application in the pharmaceutical field. Brazilian Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences. 49: 395-411 (2013)10.1590/S1984-82502013000300002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S1984-82502013000300002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Villiers A, Lynen F, Crouch A, Sandra P. Development of a solid-phase extraction procedure for the simultaneous determination of polyphenols, organic acids and sugars in wine. Chromatographia. 59: 403-409 (2004)10.1365/s10337-004-0204-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1365/s10337-004-0204-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Depetris-Chauvin A, Galagovsky D, Chevalier C, Maniere G, Grosjean Y. Olfactory detection of a bacterial short-chain fatty acid acts as an orexigenic signal in Drosophila melanogaster larvae. Scientific Reports. 7: 1-14 (2017) 10.1038/s41598-017-14589-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-14589-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5660182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29079812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dirican E, Turkez H, Togar B. Modulatory effects of Thymbra spicata L. different extracts against the mercury induced genotoxicity in human lymphocytes in vitro. Cytotechnology. 64: 181-186 (2012) 10.1007/s10616-011-9406-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10616-011-9406-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3279579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22134772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eastmond DA. Sister chromatid exchanges. 4th edn, pp. 543-545. In: Encyclopedia of Toxicology. Wexler PJ (ed). Academic, Oxford (2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eroglu EH, Hamzaoglu E, Aksoy A, Budak U, Ozkul Y. In vitro genotoxic effects of four Helichrysum species in human lymphocytes cultures. Biological Research. 43: 177-182 (2010)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21031262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fenech M, Chang WP, Kirsch-Volders M, Holland N, Bonassi S, Zeiger E. HUMN project: detailed description of the scoring criteria for the cytokinesis-block micronucleus assay using isolated human lymphocyte cultures. Mutation Research: Genetic Toxicology and Environmental Mutagenesis. 534: 65-75 (2003)10.1016/S1383-5718(02)00249-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1383-5718(02)00249-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12504755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francielli De Oliveira P, Lima IMDS, Monteiro Neto MDAB, Bastos JK, Da Silva Filho AA, Tavares DC. Evaluation of genotoxicity and antigenotoxicity of artepillin c in V79 cells by the comet and micronucleus assays. Nutrition and Cancer. 65: 1098-1103 (2013) 10.1080/01635581.2013.815233</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01635581.2013.815233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23915392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner AM, Xu FH, Fady C, Jacoby FJ, Duffey DC, Tu Y, Lichtenstein A. Apoptotic vs. nonapoptotic cytotoxicity induced by hydrogen peroxide. Free Radical Biology and Medicine. 22: 73-83 (1997) 10.1016/S0891-5849(96)00235-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(96)00235-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8958131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamzaoglu E, Eroglu HE, Ahmet A, Budak Ü, Albayrak S. Cytogenetic effects of Helichrysum arenarium in human lymphocytes cultures. Turkish Journal of Biology. 34: 253-256 (2010)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayashi M. Opinion: regulatory genotoxicity: past, present and future. Genes and Environment. 44: 1-6 (2022) 10.1186/s41021-022-00242-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s41021-022-00242-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9026627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35449081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Ceruelos A, Madrigal-Santillán E, Morales-González JA, Chamorro-Cevallos G, Cassani-Galindo M, Madrigal-Bujaidar E. Antigenotoxic effect of Chamomilla recutita (L.) Rauschert essential oil in mouse spermatogonial cells, and determination of its antioxidant capacity in vitro. International Journal of Molecular Sciences. 11: 3793-3802 (2010) 10.3390/ijms11103793</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms11103793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2996809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21152302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Igbinosa EO, Odjadjare EE, Chigor VN, Igbinosa IH, Emoghene AO, Ekhaise FO, Igiehon NO, Idemudia OG. Toxicological profile of chlorophenols and their derivatives in the environment: the public health perspective. The Scientific World Journal. 2013: 1-12 (2013)10.1155/2013/460215</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2013/460215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3649668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23690744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaatinen T, Laine J. Isolation of mononuclear cells from human cord blood by Ficoll–Paque density gradient. Current Protocols in Stem Cell Biology. 1: 2A.1.4 (2007)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18785173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong DM, Jung HA, Choi JS. Comparative antioxidant activity and HPLC profiles of some selected Korean thistles. Archives of Pharmacal Research. 31: 28-33 (2008) 10.1007/s12272-008-1116-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12272-008-1116-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18277604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnmark N, Kinyi HW. Amaranth leaf extract protects against hydrogen peroxide induced oxidative stress in Drosophila melanogaster. BMC Research Notes. 14: 1-5 (2021) 10.1186/s13104-021-05603-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13104-021-05603-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8130338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34001252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karasakal A, Sükrü DemIrcI A, Tokatli Demirok N, Cabi E. Cirsium bulgaricum yaprak ekstresinin antioksidan, antimikrobiyal etkinligi ve toplam flavonoid içerigi. Marmara Pharmaceutical Journal. 19: 43-51 (2015)10.12991/mpj.2015198609</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12991/mpj.2015198609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kariya S, Takahashi N, Hirano M, Ueno S. Humanin improves impaired metabolic activity and prolongs survival of serum-deprived human lymphocytes. Molecular and Cellular Biochemistry. 254: 83-89 (2003) 10.1023/A:1027372519726</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1027372519726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14674685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kefelioglu H, Atli Sekeroglu Z, Cosguner G, Kontas Yedier S, Sekeroglu V. Ziprasidone induces cytotoxicity and genotoxicity in human peripheral lymphocytes. Drug and Chemical Toxicology. 40: 425-431 (2017) 10.1080/01480545.2016.1252920</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01480545.2016.1252920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27894189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim MC, Kim SJ, Kim DS, Jeon YD, Park SJ, Lee HS, Um JY, Hong SH. Vanillic acid inhibits inflammatory mediators by suppressing NF-?B in lipopolysaccharide-stimulated mouse peritoneal macrophages. Immunopharmacology and Immunotoxicology. 33: 525-532 (2011) 10.3109/08923973.2010.547500</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/08923973.2010.547500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21250779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim BR, Seo HS, Ku JM, Kim GJ, Jeon CY, Park JH, Jang BH, Park SJ, Shin YC, Ko SG. Silibinin inhibits the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines through inhibition of NF-?B signaling pathway in HMC-1 human mast cells. Inflammation Research. 62: 941-950 (2013) 10.1007/s00011-013-0640-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00011-013-0640-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3825293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24045679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kozyra M, Glowniak K. Phenolic acids in extracts obtained from the flowering herbs of Cirsium vulgare (Savi) Ten. growing in Poland. Acta Societatis Botanicorum Poloniae. 82: 325-329 (2013)10.5586/asbp.2013.039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5586/asbp.2013.039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee D, Kim KH, Lee J, Hwang GS, Lee HL, Hahm DH, Huh CK, Lee SC, Lee S, Kang KS. Protective effect of cirsimaritin against streptozotocin-induced apoptosis in pancreatic beta cells. Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmacology. 69: 875–883 (2017) 10.1111/jphp.12719</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jphp.12719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28397263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin D, Xiao M, Zhao J, Li Z, Xing B, Li X, Kong M, Li L, Zhang Q, Liu Y, Chen H, Qin W, Wu H, Chen S. An overview of plant phenolic compounds and their importance in human nutrition and management of type 2 diabetes. Molecules. 21: 1-19 (2016)10.3390/molecules21101374</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules21101374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6274266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27754463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu QF, Lee JH, Kim YM, Lee S, Hong YK, Hwang S, Oh Y, Lee K, Yun HS, Lee IS, Jeon S, Chin YW, Koo BS, Cho KS. In vivo screening of traditional medicinal plants for neuroprotective activity against Aß42 cytotoxicity by using drosophila models of Alzheimer’s disease. Biological and Pharmaceutical Bulletin. 38: 1891-1901 (2015) 10.1248/bpb.b15-00459</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1248/bpb.b15-00459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26458335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundgren B, DePierre JW. The metabolism of xenobiotics and its relationship to toxicity/genotoxicity: studies with human lymphocytes. Acta Physiologica Scandinavica Supplementum. 592: 49-59 (1990)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2267943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Q, Jiang JG, Yuan X, Qiu K, Zhu W. Comparative antitumor and anti-inflammatory effects of flavonoids, saponins, polysaccharides, essential oil, coumarin and alkaloids from Cirsium japonicum DC. Food and Chemical Toxicology. 125: 422-429 (2019) 10.1016/j.fct.2019.01.020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2019.01.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30703393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macedo GE, Gomes KK, Rodrigues NR, Martins IK, da Wallau GL, de Carvalho NR, da Cruz LC, da Costa Silva DG, Boligon AA, Franco JL, Posser T. Senecio brasiliensis impairs eclosion rate and induces apoptotic cell death in larvae of Drosophila melanogaster. Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part C: Toxicology and Pharmacology. 198: 45-57 (2017)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28529177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsumoto ST, Mantovani MS, Malaguttii MIA, Dias AL, Fonseca IC, Marin-Morales MA. Genotoxicity and mutagenicity of water contaminated with tannery effluents as evaluated by the micronucleus test and comet assay using the fish Oreochromis niloticus and chromosome aberrations in onion root-tips. Genetics and Molecular Biology. 29: 148-158 (2006)10.1590/S1415-47572006000100028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S1415-47572006000100028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonnell G. The use of hydrogen peroxide for disinfection and sterilization applications, pp. 1-34. In: PATAI'S Chemistry of Functional Groups. Wiley, New York (2009)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merlin JPJ, Rupasinghe HPV, Dellaire G, Murphy K. Role of dietary antioxidants in p53-mediated cancer chemoprevention and tumor suppression. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity. 2021: 1-18 (2021)10.1155/2021/9924328</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2021/9924328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8257365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34257824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michalková R, Šiviková K, Galdíková M. Analysis of sister chromatid exchanges and proliferation of human peripheral blood lymphocytes exposed to epoxiconazole. Folia Veterinaria. 62: 41-47 (2018)10.2478/fv-2018-0026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2478/fv-2018-0026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mostafa DG, Khaleel EF, Badi RM, Abdel-Aleem GA, Abdeen HM. Rutin hydrate inhibits apoptosis in the brains of cadmium chloride-treated rats via preserving the mitochondrial integrity and inhibiting endoplasmic reticulum stress. Neurological Research. 41: 594-608 (2019) 10.1080/01616412.2019.1596206</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01616412.2019.1596206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30973085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munari CC, Resende FA, Alves JM, De Sousa JPB, Bastos JK, Tavares DC. Mutagenicity and antimutagenicity of Baccharis dracunculifolia extract in chromosomal aberration assays in Chinese hamster ovary cells. Planta Medica. 74: 1363-1367 (2008) 10.1055/s-2008-1081306</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-2008-1081306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18683127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira PF, Neto MABM, Leandro LF, Bastos JK, da Silva Filho AA, Tavares DC. In vivo antigenotoxicity of baccharin, an important constituent of Baccharis dracunculifolia DC (Asteraceae). Basic and Clinical Pharmacology and Toxicology. 109: 35-41 (2011) 10.1111/j.1742-7843.2011.00680.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1742-7843.2011.00680.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21266012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olugbami JO, Gbadegesin MA, Odunola OA. In vitro evaluation of the antioxidant potential, phenolic and flavonoid contents of the stem bark ethanol extract of Anogeissus leiocarpus. African Journal of Medicine and Medical Sciences. 43: 101-109 (2014)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4679201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26681826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omoboyowa DA, Olugbenga ST, Adetuyi FD, Akinsulure ST, Akinwande KM, Iwuji CB, Ayekolu SF. Modulatory effects of selected compounds on oxidative stress in hydrogen peroxide-induced Drosophila melanogaster. Pharmacological Research: Modern Chinese Medicine. 5: 1-10 (2022)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pb B, Rani S, Kim YO, Ahmed Al-Ghamdi A, Elshikh MS, Al-Dosary MA, Hatamleh AA, Arokiyaraj S, Kim HJ. Prophylactic efficacy of Boerhavia diffusa L. aqueous extract in toluene induced reproductive and developmental toxicity in Drosophila melanogaster. Journal of Infection and Public Health. 13: 177-185 (2020) 10.1016/j.jiph.2019.07.020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2019.07.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31582296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phukan MM, Sangma SR, Kalita D, Pankaj PP, Das PP, Bora P, Saha J, Manoj K, Hazarika N, Kataki R. Next-generational biosurfactant and their practical application in the food industry. pp. 361–389. In: Applications of Next Generation Biosurfactants in the Food Sector. Academic, New York (2023)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Promega Corporation. CellTiter 96® AQueous One Solution Cell Proliferation Assay. https://worldwide.promega.com/products/cell-health-assays/cell-viability-and-cytotoxicity-assays/celltiter-96-aqueous-one-solution-cell-proliferation-assay-_mts_/?catNum=G3582. Accessed 19 Jan 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rand MD, Montgomery SL, Prince L, Vorojeikina D. Developmental toxicity assays using the Drosophila model. Current Protocols in Toxicology. 1: 1-27 (2014)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4036625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24789363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Re R, Pellegrini N, Proteggente A, Pannala A, Yang M, Rice-Evans C. Antioxidant activity applying an improved ABTS radical cation decolorization assay. Free Radical Biology and Medicine. 26: 1231-1237 (1999) 10.1016/S0891-5849(98)00315-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(98)00315-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10381194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riaz B, Zahoor MK, Zahoor MA, Majeed HN, Javed I, Ahmad A, Jabeen F, Zulhussnain M, Sultana K. Toxicity, phytochemical composition, and enzyme inhibitory activities of some indigenous weed plant extracts in fruit fly, Drosophila melanogaster. Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine. 2018: 1-11 (2018)10.1155/2018/2325659</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/2325659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5925020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29849696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riss TL, Moravec RA, Niles AL. Cytotoxicity testing: measuring viable cells, dead cells, and detecting mechanism of cell death. Methods in Molecular Biology (Clifton, NJ) 740: 103-114 (2011)10.1007/978-1-61779-108-6_12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-61779-108-6_12</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21468972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rojas de Arias A, Ferro E, Inchausti A, Ascurra M, Acosta N, Rodriguez E, Fournet A. Mutagenicity, insecticidal and trypanocidal activity of some Paraguayan Asteraceae. Journal of Ethnopharmacology. 45: 35-41 (1995) 10.1016/0378-8741(94)01193-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0378-8741(94)01193-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7739225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rolnik A, Olas B. The plants of the Asteraceae family as agents in the protection of human health. International Journal of Molecular Sciences. 22: 1-10 (2021)10.3390/ijms22063009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms22063009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7999649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33809449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabudak T, Gulen D, Hulya Orak HH, Ozer M, Caliskan H, Cabi E. Free radical scavenging capacity and antibacterial activity of wild Cirsium creticum from Turkey. Indian Journal of Pharmaceutical Education and Research. 51: S359-S362 (2017a)10.5530/ijper.51.3s.47</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5530/ijper.51.3s.47</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabudak T, Orak HH, Gulen D, Ozer M, Caliskan H, Bahrisefit I, Cabi E. Investigation of some antibacterial and antioxidant properties of wild Cirsium vulgare from Turkey. Indian Journal of Pharmaceutical Education and Research. 51: S363-S367 (2017b)10.5530/ijper.51.3s.48</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5530/ijper.51.3s.48</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sambruy Y, Ferruzza S, Ranaldi G, De Angelis I. Intestinal cell culture models cell culture methods for in vitro toxicology. Cell Biology and Toxicology. 17: 301-317 (2001) 10.1023/A:1012533316609</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1012533316609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11768596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanz-Serrano J, Garayoa R, Vitas AI, López de Cerain A, Azqueta A. In vitro genotoxicity assessment of French fries from mass catering companies: a preliminary study. Mutagenesis. 38: 51-57 (2023) 10.1093/mutage/geac021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/mutage/geac021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9897018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36242551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarimahmut M, Balikci N, Celikler S, Ari F, Ulukaya E, Guleryuz G, Ozel MZ. Evaluation of genotoxic and apoptotic potential of Hypericum adenotrichum Spach. in vitro. Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology. 74: 137-146 (2016) 10.1016/j.yrtph.2015.11.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yrtph.2015.11.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26617407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scartezzini P, Speroni E. Review on some plants of Indian traditional medicine with antioxidant activity. Journal of Ethnopharmacology. 71: 23-43 (2000) 10.1016/S0378-8741(00)00213-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(00)00213-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10904144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senthilkumar S, Raveendran R, Madhusoodanan S, Sundar M, Shankar SS, Sharma S, Sundararajan V, Dan P, Sheik Mohideen S. Developmental and behavioural toxicity induced by acrylamide exposure and amelioration using phytochemicals in Drosophila melanogaster. Journal of Hazardous Materials. 394: 1-10 (2020)10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.122533</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.122533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32279006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shim SM, Bae E, Kim GH. Single-dose oral acute toxicity and mutagenic effects of methanol extracts of Cirsium japonicum. Journal of Food Biochemistry. 35: 845-858 (2011)10.1111/j.1745-4514.2010.00421.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4514.2010.00421.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinués B, Sanz A, Bernal ML, Tres A, Alcala A, Lanuza J, Ceballos C, Sáenz MA. Sister chromatid exchanges, proliferating rate index, and micronuclei in biomonitoring of internal exposure to vinyl chloride monomer in plastic industry workers. Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology. 108: 37-45 (1991) 10.1016/0041-008X(91)90266-H</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0041-008X(91)90266-H</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2006505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sponchiado G, Adam ML, Silva CD, Silva Soley B, De Mello-Sampayo C, Cabrini DA, Correr CJ, Otuki MF. Quantitative genotoxicity assays for analysis of medicinal plants: a systematic review. Journal of Ethnopharmacology. 178: 289-296 (2016) 10.1016/j.jep.2015.10.026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2015.10.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26680588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srinivas US, Tan BWQ, Vellayappan BA, Jeyasekharan AD. ROS and the DNA damage response in cancer. Redox Biology. 25: 1-9 (2019)10.1016/j.redox.2018.101084</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.redox.2018.101084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6859528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30612957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strober W. Trypan blue exclusion test of cell viability. Current Protocols in Immunology. 111: 1-3 (2015)10.1002/0471142735.ima03bs111</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/0471142735.ima03bs111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6716531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26529666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan JBL, Lim YY. Critical analysis of current methods for assessing the in vitro antioxidant and antibacterial activity of plant extracts. Food Chemistry. 172: 814-822 (2015) 10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.09.141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.09.141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25442625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiley GED. Biological flora of the British Isles: Cirsium arvense (L.) Scop. Journal of Ecology. 98: 938-983 (2010)10.1111/j.1365-2745.2010.01678.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2745.2010.01678.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topashka-Ancheva M, Taskova R, Handjieva N, Mikhova B, Duddeck H. Clastogenic Effect of Carthamus lanatus L. (Asteraceae). Zeitschrift fur Naturforschung-Section C Journal of Biosciences. 58: 833-836 (2003)10.1515/znc-2003-11-1216</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/znc-2003-11-1216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14713161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tumini E, Aguilera A. The sister-chromatid exchange assay in human cells. Methods in Molecular Biology (Clifton, NJ) 2153: 383-393 (2021)10.1007/978-1-0716-0644-5_26</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-0716-0644-5_26</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32840793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yakes FM, Van Houten B. Mitochondrial DNA damage is more extensive and persists longer than nuclear DNA damage in human cells following oxidative stress. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 94: 514-519 (1997) 10.1073/pnas.94.2.514</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.2.514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC19544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9012815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yalcin AS, Yilmaz AM, Altundag EM, Koctürk S. Anti-cancer effects of curcumin, quercetin and tea catechins. Marmara Pharmaceutical Journal. 21: 19-29 (2017)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamaguchi M, Yamamoto S. Role of Drosophila in human disease research 2.0. International Journal of Molecular Sciences. 23: 10-13 (2022)10.3390/ijms23084203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms23084203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9027098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35457020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao X, Jiao S, Qin M, Hu W, Yi B, Liu D. Vanillic acid alleviates acute myocardial hypoxia/reoxygenation injury by inhibiting oxidative stress. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity. 2020: 1-12 (2020)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7191373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32377308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yen GC, Hsieh CL. Inhibitory effect of Eucommia ulmoides Oliv. on oxidative DNA damage in lymphocytes induced by H2O2. Teratogenesis Carcinogenesis and Mutagenesis. 34: 23–34 (2003)10.1002/tcm.10047</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/tcm.10047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12616594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz B, Dogan S, Celikler Kasimogullari S. Hemocompatibility, cytotoxicity, and genotoxicity of poly(methylmethacrylate)/nanohydroxyapatite nanocomposites synthesized by melt blending method. International Journal of Polymeric Materials and Polymeric Biomaterials. 67: 1-10 (2018)10.1080/00914037.2017.1331349</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00914037.2017.1331349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz Kardas B, Dogan S. The effects of mutations on pericentromeric localization of shugoshin. Journal of Balikesir University Institute of Science and Technology. 24: 869-877 (2022)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz Kardas B, Diken ME, Bayhan H, Acar M, Dogan S. Cytoprotective, antimutagenic/antirecombinogenic and antibacterial properties of Lallemantia iberica extracts. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture. 103: 1901-1911 (2023) 10.1002/jsfa.12257</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.12257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36207573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin J, Heo S-I, Wang M-H. Antioxidant and antidiabetic activities of extracts from Cirsium japonicum roots. Nutrition Research and Practice. 2: 247-251 (2008) 10.4162/nrp.2008.2.4.247</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4162/nrp.2008.2.4.247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2788202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20016726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zendehboodi Z. Cytotoxicity and genotoxicity effects of water boiled in aluminum vessels on Allium cepa root tip cells. Journal of Environmental Health Science and Engineering. 16: 337-341 (2018) 10.1007/s40201-018-0313-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40201-018-0313-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6277333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30729004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Chen H, Wang Z, Lan G, Zhang L. Comparative studies on antioxidant activities of extracts and fractions from the leaves and stem of Epimedium koreanum Nakai. Journal of Food Science and Technology. 50: 1122-1129 (2013) 10.1007/s13197-011-0447-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13197-011-0447-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3791250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24426024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang YJ, Gan RY, Li S, Zhou Y, Li AN, Xu DP, Li HB, Kitts DD. Antioxidant phytochemicals for the prevention and treatment of chronic diseases. Molecules. 20: 21138-21156 (2015) 10.3390/molecules201219753</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules201219753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6331972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26633317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>