<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39230201</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Research on enhancing the efficiency of food safety sampling inspections in China based on Pareto's law.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13822</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Food safety is pivotal for public welfare and directly impacts consumer health. Food safety sampling inspections (FSSIs) are essential in detecting unqualified food products and non-compliant manufacturers, which form an integral part of government regulatory frameworks. However, given the constraints on budgetary resources, improving the efficiency of food safety sampling inspections (EFSSIs) remains a considerable challenge in China's food quality and safety supervision. This study aims to apply Pareto's law, starting from the examination of food sample testing items and major hazard types, to theoretically analyze methods for improving the EFSSIs. Following the theoretical analysis, the research employs provincial food sampling data from China in 2022 to empirically validate the proposed improvement strategies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The research findings indicate that applying Pareto's law significantly reduces the number of items that should be tested for each food subcategory, effectively lowering testing costs for each batch of food samples. Theoretically, employing Pareto's law in sampling inspections can increase the EFSSIs to 2.78 times the current observed level. Furthermore, empirical validation using food sampling data confirms that EFSSIs can be improved to 2.12 times the existing level, consistent with theoretical predictions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Implementing Pareto's law in FSSIs facilitates the detection of more unqualified food products and non-compliant manufacturers without additional financial burden, significantly enhancing the EFSSIs. This approach provides an innovative strategy for government to bolster their food safety management efforts. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Taiping</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Economics and Management, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Yun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-1486-6384</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Economics and Management, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Tong</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Economics and Management, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pareto's law</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">efficiency of food safety sampling inspections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sampling strategy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39230201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Deng H and Kong L, Institutional characteristic, social co‐governance and the effectiveness of food safety certification. Issues Agric Econ 508:27–37 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu X and Lu Q, New food manufacturers, regulation and food safety. Collect Essays Finance Econ 215:103–112 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, From rule regulation to information regulation: new ideas for the transformation of food safety governance. Expanding Horizons 237:37–44 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Jin Y, Wang Y and Liang Q, Quality information disclosure, signal transformation and agricultural products certification: comparative analysis on meat and vegetable industries. Issues Agric Econ 489:76–87 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin C, Levi R, Liang Q, Renegar N, Springs S, Zhou J et al., Testing at the source: analytics‐enabled risk‐based sampling of food supply chains in China. Manage Sci 67:2985–2996 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Wu Z and Li K, The achievements and prospects of food quality and safety supervision. J Agrotech Econ 274:4–14 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quan S and Zeng Y, Information concealing and conspiring problems of food safety regulators in China: interpretation based on principal‐agent model and its practical verification. Manage Rev 28:210–218 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong Q, Lei L and Yuan Y, Policy burden, regulation capture and food safety. Econ Res J 50:4–15 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li T, Bo H and Nie W, A study on the evaluation of supervision sampling efficiency of food safety in China‐based on the perspective of sampling batches distribution under the pressure of government performance evaluation. J Macro‐Qual Res 9:86–98 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunford R, Su Q, Tamang E and Wintour A, The Pareto principle. Plymouth stud Sci 7:140–148 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanders R, The pareto principle: its use and abuse. J Serv Mark 1:37–40 (1987).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JK, Jeong CG, Li Q and Choi IY, The demand effect analysis of head books and tail books in book recommendation networks. Expert Syst 39:e12847 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Craft RC and Leake C, The pareto principle in organizational decision making. Manag Decis 40:729–733 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radson D and Boyd AH, The pareto principle and rate analysis. Qual Eng 10:223–229 (1997).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cravener TL, Roush WB and Jordan H, Pareto assessment of quality control in poultry processing plants. J Appl Poultry Res 2:297–302 (1993).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karuppusami G and Gandhinathan R, Pareto analysis of critical success factors of total quality management: a literature review and analysis. TQM Mag 18:372–385 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fotopoulos C, Kafetzopoulos D and Gotzamani K, Critical factors for effective implementation of the HACCP system: a pareto analysis. Br Food J 113:578–597 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez MG, Fearne A, Caswell JA and Henson S, Co‐regulation as a possible model for food safety governance: opportunities for public–private partnerships. Food Policy 32:299–314 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen T, Wang L and Wang J, Transparent assessment of the supervision information in China's food safety: a fuzzy‐ANP comprehensive evaluation method. J Food Qual 2017:1–14 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shapiro S and Morrall JF III, The triumph of regulatory politics: benefit–cost analysis and political salience. Regul Governance 6:189–206 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massiani J, Cost‐benefit analysis of policies for the development of electric vehicles in Germany: methods and results. Transp Policy 38:19–26 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Traill WB and Koenig A, Economic assessment of food safety standards: costs and benefits of alternative approaches. Food Control 21:1611–1619 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arrow KJ, Cropper ML, Eads GC, Hahn RW, Lave LB, Noll RG et al., Is there a role for benefit‐cost analysis in environmental, health, and safety regulation? in Benefit‐Cost Analysis in Environmental, Health, and Safety Regulation, Vol. 272. American Enterprise Institute, Washington, DC, pp. 1–17 (1996).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Ravenswaay EO and Hoehn JP, The theoretical benefits of food safety policies: a total economic value framework. Am J Agric Econ 78:1291–1296 (1996).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antle JM, Efficient food safety regulation in the food manufacturing sector. Am J Agric Econ 78:1242–1247 (1996).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antle JM, Benefits and costs of food safety regulation. Food Policy 24:605–623 (1999).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Zhang J and Chen T, Retracted: an ANP‐fuzzy evaluation model of food quality safety supervision based on China's data. Food Sci Nutr 8:3157–3163 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H and Zhao S, The efficiency evaluation of food safety regulation in China‐ based on SBM‐DEA and Malmquist models with undesired outputs. Rev Econ Manage 36:46–57 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Wang S and Guo B, Research on the evaluation of performance of China's food safety regulations ‐a survey of 688 regulatory entities nationwide. Mod Econ Res 08:17–24 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Qi R and Liu H, Designing independent regulatory system of food safety in China. Agric Agric Sci Proc 1:288–295 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unnevehr L and Hoffmann V, Food safety management and regulation: international experiences and lessons for China. J Integr Agric 14:2218–2230 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connolly AJ, Luo LS, Woolsey M, Lyons M and Phillips‐Connoly K, A blueprint for food safety in China. China Agric Econ Rev 8:129–147 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laffont JJ and Tirole J, The politics of government decision‐making: a theory of regulatory capture. Q J Econ 106:1089–1127 (1991).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouvière E and Caswell JA, From punishment to prevention: a French case study of the introduction of co‐regulation in enforcing food safety. Food Policy 37:246–254 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmeiser S, Consumer inference and the regulation of consumer information. Int J Ind Org 37:192–200 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni G and Zheng F, The transaction costs of media supervision on food safety regulatory efficiency: a system model and its equilibrium analysis. China Econ Q 13:559–582 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong Q, Zhang Y and Yu J, Incentives, information and food safety regulation. Econ Res J 48:135–147 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie K, Liu Y and Zhao X, The condition and strategy of media participating in food safety social co‐governance. Manage Rev 29:192–204 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li T and Bo H, Quantitative evaluation of supervision sampling efficiency of food safety in China. Science and Technology of Food Industry 43:301–310 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao T, Li T, Liu D and Yun L, The impact of food safety regulatory information intervention on enterprises' production violations in China: a randomized intervention experiment. Front Sustainable Food Syst 7:1245773 (2024).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>