<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39230603</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-0460</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Dysphagia</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Dysphagia</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Effects of Adding Particles in Texture Modified Food on Tongue Strength and Swallowing Function in Patients with Oropharyngeal Dysphagia: A Proof of Concept Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00455-024-10752-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The use of texture modified food (TMF) is widely spread in the daily care of patients with oropharyngeal dysphagia (OD). However, TMF have been shown to have a negative impact on the patients' quality of life. Adherence rates are low, increasing the risk of malnutrition and aspiration in an already vulnerable patient population. The aim of this exploratory study was to gain insight in the feasibility of adding particles to pureed food on tongue strength, swallowing safety and efficiency in patients with OD. Ten adult participants with OD swallowed three different boluses. Bolus 1 consisted of no particles (IDDSI level 4), small and bigger particles were added in bolus 2 and 3. Tongue strength during swallowing (Pswal) was measured using the Iowa Oral Performance Instrument (IOPI). Swallow safety (penetration and aspiration) and swallow efficiency (residu) were quantified during fiberoptic endoscopic evaluation of swallowing by means of the PAS scale and Pooling score. RM Anova and Friedman tests were performed for analyzing the impact of bolus on the outcome parameters. No significant effect of bolus type on Pswal was measured. Neither the PAS nor the Pooling score differed significantly between the three different boluses. Aspiration was never observed during swallowing any bolus with particles. This preliminary study shows that the addition of particles to pureed food had no impact on Pswal, swallowing efficiency or safety in patients with OD. This innovative project is the first step in research to explore the characteristics of TMF beyond bolus volume, viscosity and temperature.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Van den Steen</LastName><ForeName>Leen</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8158-7629</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antwerp University Hospital, Wilrijkstraat 10, Antwerp, Edegem, 2650, Belgium. Leen.Van.den.Steen@uza.be.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Antwerp, Universiteitsplein 1, Antwerp, Wilrijk, 2610, Belgium. Leen.Van.den.Steen@uza.be.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goossens</LastName><ForeName>Edwig</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Research and Innovation in Gastrology &amp; Primary Food Care (CRIGA), Wallonie, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Gemst</LastName><ForeName>Martijn</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Research and Innovation in Gastrology &amp; Primary Food Care (CRIGA), Wallonie, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vlaemynck</LastName><ForeName>Geertrui</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Research and Innovation in Gastrology &amp; Primary Food Care (CRIGA), Wallonie, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Flanders Research Institute for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food (ILVO), Technology and Food Science Unit, Wallonie, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Geurden</LastName><ForeName>Bart</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antwerp University Hospital, Wilrijkstraat 10, Antwerp, Edegem, 2650, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Antwerp, Universiteitsplein 1, Antwerp, Wilrijk, 2610, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Research and Innovation in Gastrology &amp; Primary Food Care (CRIGA), Wallonie, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Van Nuffelen</LastName><ForeName>Gwen</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Antwerp University Hospital, Wilrijkstraat 10, Antwerp, Edegem, 2650, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Antwerp, Universiteitsplein 1, Antwerp, Wilrijk, 2610, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Department of Speech, Language, and Hearing Sciences, De Pintelaan 185, Ghent, 9000, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Dysphagia</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8610856</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0179-051X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dysphagia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Particles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Swallowing efficiency</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Swallowing safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Texture modified food</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tongue strength</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39230603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00455-024-10752-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00455-024-10752-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Streicher M, Wirth R, Schindler K, Sieber CC, Hiesmayr M, Volkert D. Dysphagia in nursing homes-results from the NutritionDay Project. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2018;19(2):141–e1472. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jamda.2017.08.015 . Epub 2017 Oct 10. PMID: 29030310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2017.08.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29030310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miles A, Liang V, Sekula J, Broadmore S, Owen P, Braakhuis AJ. Texture-modified diets in aged care facilities: Nutrition, swallow safety and mealtime experience. Australas J Ageing. 2020;39(1):31–9. https://doi.org/10.1111/ajag.12640 . Epub 2019 Mar 13. PMID: 30868723.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ajag.12640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30868723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cichero JA, Steele C, Duivestein J, Clavé P, Chen J, Kayashita J, Dantas R, Lecko C, Speyer R, Lam P, Murray J. The need for International Terminology and definitions for texture-modified foods and Thickened liquids used in Dysphagia Management: foundations of a Global Initiative. Curr Phys Med Rehabil Rep. 2013;1(4):280–91. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40141-013-0024-z . PMID: 24392282; PMCID: PMC3873065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40141-013-0024-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24392282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3873065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann G. Review of reports on relative prevalence of swallowing disorders after acute stroke (Dysphagia 16:141–142, 2001). Dysphagia. 2002 Winter;17(1):81 – 2. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-001-0105-5 . PMID: 11820390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://iddsi.org/IDDSI/media/images/Complete_IDDSI_Framework_Final_31July2019.pdf Accessed 7 December 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Keeffe ST. Use of modified diets to prevent aspiration in oropharyngeal dysphagia: is current practice justified? BMC Geriatr. 2018;18(1):167. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12877-018-0839-7 . PMID: 30029632; PMCID: PMC6053717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12877-018-0839-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30029632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6053717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beck AM, Kjaersgaard A, Hansen T, Poulsen I. Systematic review and evidence based recommendations on texture modified foods and thickened liquids for adults (above 17 years) with oropharyngeal dysphagia - An updated clinical guideline. Clin Nutr. 2018;37(6 Pt A):1980–1991. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2017.09.002. Epub 2017 Sep 9. PMID: 28939270.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu A, Yamaguchi K, Tohara H. Impact of pureed and liquidised diets on health-related quality of life scores in older patients during postacute rehabilitation: a pilot study. J Hum Nutr Diet. 2024;37:227–33. https://doi.org/10.1111/jhn.13250 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jhn.13250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37805824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu XS, Miles A, Braakhuis AJ, Texture-Modified, Diets. Nutritional status and mealtime satisfaction: a systematic review. Healthc (Basel). 2021;9(6):624. https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare9060624 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/healthcare9060624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swan K, Speyer R, Heijnen BJ, Wagg B, Cordier R. Living with oropharyngeal dysphagia: effects of bolus modification on health-related quality of life–a systematic review. Qual Life Res. 2015;24(10):2447–56. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11136-015-0990-y . Epub 2015 Apr 14. PMID: 25869989.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11136-015-0990-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25869989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu A, Momosaki R, Kayashita J, Fujishima I. Impact of multiple texture-modified diets on oral intake and nutritional status in older patients with pneumonia: a retrospective cohort study. Dysphagia. 2020;35(4):574–82. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-019-10063-4 . Epub 2019 Sep 18. PMID: 31535216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00455-019-10063-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31535216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu A, Yamaguchi K, Tohara H. Impact of pureed and liquidised diets on health-related quality of life scores in older patients during postacute rehabilitation: A pilot study. J Hum Nutr Diet. 2023 Oct 8. https://doi.org/10.1111/jhn.13250 . Epub ahead of print. PMID: 37805824.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eglseer D, Halfens RJG, Schols JMGA, Lohrmann C. Dysphagia in Hospitalized Older Patients: Associated Factors and Nutritional Interventions. J Nutr Health Aging. 2018;22(1):103–110. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12603-017-0928-x . PMID: 29300429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shim JS, Oh BM, Han TR. Factors associated with compliance with viscosity-modified diet among dysphagic patients. Ann Rehabil Med. 2013;37(5):628–32. https://doi.org/10.5535/arm.2013.37.5.628 . Epub 2013 Oct 29. PMID: 24231801; PMCID: PMC3825938.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5535/arm.2013.37.5.628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24231801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3825938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele CM, Miller AJ. Sensory input pathways and mechanisms in swallowing: a review. Dysphagia. 2010;25(4):323 – 33. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-010-9301-5 . Epub 2010 Sep 3. PMID: 20814803; PMCID: PMC2992653.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawagishi S, Kou F, Yoshino K, Tanaka T, Masumi S. Decrease in stereognostic ability of the tongue with age. J Oral Rehabil. 2009;36(12):872–9. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2842.2009.02005.x . Epub 2009 Oct 14. PMID: 19840359.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2842.2009.02005.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19840359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferris L, Doeltgen S, Cock C, Rommel N, Schar M, Carrión S, Scholten I, Omari T. Modulation of pharyngeal swallowing by bolus volume and viscosity. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2021;320(1):G43–53. https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpgi.00270.2020 . Epub 2020 Oct 28. PMID: 33112160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00270.2020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33112160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moon IY, Yi CH, Park IW, Yong JH. Effects of sitting posture and bolus volume on activation of swallowing-related muscles. J Oral Rehabil. 2020;47(5):577–83. https://doi.org/10.1111/joor.12934 . Epub 2020 Jan 23. PMID: 31926028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joor.12934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31926028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sia I, Crary MA, Kairalla J, Carnaby GD, Sheplak M, McCulloch T. Bolus volume and viscosity effects on pharyngeal swallowing power-how physiological bolus accommodation affects bolus dynamics. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2018;30(12):e13481. https://doi.org/10.1111/nmo.13481 . Epub 2018 Oct 15. PMID: 30324641.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nmo.13481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30324641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus CL, Logemann JA, Rademaker AW, Kahrilas PJ, Pajak T, Lazar R, Halper A. Effects of bolus volume, viscosity, and repeated swallows in nonstroke subjects and stroke patients. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1993;74(10):1066-70. https://doi.org/10.1016/0003-9993(93)90063-g . PMID: 8215858.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kahrilas PJ, Logemann JA. Volume accommodation during swallowing. Dysphagia. 1993;8(3):259 – 65. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01354548 . PMID: 8359048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele CM, Alsanei WA, Ayanikalath S, Barbon CE, Chen J, Cichero JA, Coutts K, Dantas RO, Duivestein J, Giosa L, Hanson B, Lam P, Lecko C, Leigh C, Nagy A, Namasivayam AM, Nascimento WV, Odendaal I, Smith CH, Wang H. The influence of food texture and liquid consistency modification on swallowing physiology and function: a systematic review. Dysphagia. 2015;30(1):2–26. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-014-9578-x . Epub 2014 Oct 25. Erratum in: Dysphagia. 2015;30(2):272-3. PMID: 25343878; PMCID: PMC4342510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dantas RO, Dodds WJ. Effect of bolus volume and consistency on swallow-induced submental and infrahyoid electromyographic activity. Braz J Med Biol Res. 1990;23(1):37–44. PMID: 2386847.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2386847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Youmans SR, Stierwalt JA. Measures of tongue function related to normal swallowing. Dysphagia. 2006;21(2):102 – 11. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-006-9013-z . PMID: 16685469.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selçuk B, Uysal H, Aydogdu I, Akyuz M, Ertekin C. Effect of temperature on electrophysiological parameters of swallowing. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2007;44(3):373 – 80. https://doi.org/10.1682/jrrd.2006.08.0089 . PMID: 18247234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gatto AR, Cola PC, Silva RG, Spadotto AA, Ribeiro PW, Schelp AO, Carvalho LR, Henry MA. Sour taste and cold temperature in the oral phase of swallowing in patients after stroke. Codas. 2013;25(2):164-8. https://doi.org/10.1590/s2317-17822013000200012 . PMID: 24408246.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben Tobin A, Mihnea M, Hildenbrand M, Miljkovic A, Garrido-Bañuelos G, Xanthakis E, Lopez-Sanchez P. Bolus rheology and ease of swallowing of particulated semi-solid foods as evaluated by an elderly panel. Food Funct. 2020;11(10):8648–8658. https://doi.org/10.1039/d0fo01728k . PMID: 32936178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engelen L, Fontijn-Tekamp A, van der Bilt A. The influence of product and oral characteristics on swallowing. Arch Oral Biol. 2005;50(8):739 – 46. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.archoralbio.2005.01.004 . Epub 2005 Feb 26. PMID: 15958205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann GMASA. The Mann Assessment of swallowing ability. Boston: Cengage Learning; 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanderwegen J, Van Nuffelen G, Elen R, De Bodt M. The influence of age, sex, visual feedback, bulb position, and the order of testing on maximum anterior and posterior tongue strength in healthy Belgian children. Dysphagia. 2019;34(6):834–51. Epub 2019 Jan 7. PMID: 30617844.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00455-019-09976-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30617844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Nuffelen G, Van den Steen L, Vanderveken O, Specenier P, Van Laer C, Van Rompaey D, Guns C, Mariën S, Peeters M, Van de Heyning P, Vanderwegen J, De Bodt M. Study protocol for a randomized controlled trial: tongue strengthening exercises in head and neck cancer patients, does exercise load matter? Trials. 2015;16:395. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13063-015-0889-5 . PMID: 26340887; PMCID: PMC4560920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13063-015-0889-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26340887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4560920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathlin J, Courtier N, Hopkinson J. Taste changes during radiotherapy for head and neck cancer. Radiography (Lond). 2023;29(4):746–51. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.radi.2023.05.004 . Epub ahead of print. PMID: 37224583.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.radi.2023.05.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37224583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambiado-Lillo MM, Presbyphagia. A Conceptual Analysis of Contemporary Proposals and Their Influences on Clinical Diagnosis. Dysphagia. 2024 Jan 18. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-023-10658-y . Epub ahead of print. PMID: 38238574.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crary MA, Mann GD, Groher ME. Initial psychometric assessment of a functional oral intake scale for dysphagia in stroke patients. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2005;86(8):1516-20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2004.11.049 . PMID: 16084801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van den Steen L, Van Gestel D, Vanderveken O, Vanderwegen J, Lazarus C, Daisne JF, Van Laer C, Specenier P, Van Rompaey D, Mariën S, Lawson G, Chantrain G, Desuter G, Van den Weyngaert D, Cvilic S, Beauvois S, Allouche J, Delacroix L, Vermorken JB, Peeters M, Dragan T, Van de Heyning P, De Bodt M, Van Nuffelen G. Evolution of self-perceived swallowing function, tongue strength and swallow-related quality of life during radiotherapy in head and neck cancer patients. Head Neck. 2019;41(7):2197–207. https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.25684 . Epub 2019 Feb 14. PMID: 30793811.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hed.25684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30793811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valenzano TJ, Guida BT, Peladeau-Pigeon M, Steele CM. Respiratory-swallow coordination in healthy adults during drinking of thin to extremely thick liquids: a Research note. J Speech Lang Hear Res. 2020;63(3):702–9. https://doi.org/10.1044/2019_JSLHR-19-00163 . Epub 2020 Feb 27. PMID: 32109178; PMCID: PMC7229706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1044/2019_JSLHR-19-00163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32109178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7229706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tariq B, Simon SR, Pilz W, Maxim A, Kremer B, Baijens LWJ. Evaluating the safety of oral methylene blue during swallowing assessment: a systematic review. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol. 2021;278(9):3155–69. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00405-020-06509-3 . Epub 2021 Jan 2. PMID: 33389001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00405-020-06509-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33389001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong MKL, Ku PKM, Tong MCF, Lee KYS, Fong R. Endoscopic and observational findings of swallowing of traditional and molded puree in healthy individuals. Dysphagia. 2023;38(5):1363–1370. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-023-10565-2 . Epub 2023 Mar 4. PMID: 36869928.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele CM, Bailey GL, Polacco RE, Hori SF, Molfenter SM, Oshalla M, Yeates EM. Outcomes of tongue-pressure strength and accuracy training for dysphagia following acquired brain injury. Int J Speech Lang Pathol. 2013;15(5):492–502. https://doi.org/10.3109/17549507.2012.752864 . Epub 2013 Jan 22. PMID: 23336825; PMCID: PMC3793268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/17549507.2012.752864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23336825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3793268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus C, Logemann JA, Huang CF, Rademaker AW. Effects of two types of tongue strengthening exercises in young normals. Folia Phoniatr Logop. 2003 Jul-Aug;55(4):199–205. https://doi.org/10.1159/000071019 . PMID: 12802092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbek JC, Robbins JA, Roecker EB, Coyle JL, Wood JL. A penetration-aspiration scale. Dysphagia. 1996 Spring;11(2):93 – 8. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00417897 . PMID: 8721066.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borders JC, Brates D. Use of the penetration-aspiration scale in Dysphagia Research: a systematic review. Dysphagia. 2020;35(4):583–97. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-019-10064-3 . Epub 2019 Sep 19. PMID: 31538220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00455-019-10064-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31538220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farneti D, Fattori B, Nacci A, Mancini V, Simonelli M, Ruoppolo G, Genovese E. The pooling-score (P-score): inter- and intra-rater reliability in endoscopic assessment of the severity of dysphagia. Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital. 2014;34(2):105–10. PMID: 24843220; PMCID: PMC4025184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24843220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4025184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faul F, Erdfelder E, Lang AG, Buchner A. G*Power 3: a flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences. Behav Res Methods. 2007;39(2):175 – 91. https://doi.org/10.3758/bf03193146 . PMID: 17695343.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Troche MS, Sapienza CM, Rosenbek JC. Effects of bolus consistency on timing and safety of swallow in patients with Parkinson’s disease. Dysphagia. 2008;23(1):26–32. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-007-9090-7 . Epub 2007 Jun 6. PMID: 17551793.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00455-007-9090-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17551793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stierwalt JA, Youmans SR. Tongue measures in individuals with normal and impaired swallowing. Am J Speech Lang Pathol. 2007;16(2):148 – 56. https://doi.org/10.1044/1058-0360(2007/019 ). PMID: 17456893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus CL, Logemann JA, Pauloski BR, Rademaker AW, Larson CR, Mittal BB, Pierce M. Swallowing and tongue function following treatment for oral and oropharyngeal cancer. J Speech Lang Hear Res. 2000;43(4):1011-23. https://doi.org/10.1044/jslhr.4304.1011 . PMID: 11386468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park JS, Oh DH, Chang M. Comparison of maximal tongue strength and tongue strength used during swallowing in relation to age in healthy adults. J Phys Ther Sci. 2016;28(2):442–5. https://doi.org/10.1589/jpts.28.442 . Epub 2016 Feb 29. PMID: 27064477; PMCID: PMC4792987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1589/jpts.28.442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27064477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4792987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Rong L, Shen M, Yu Q, Chen Y, Li J, Xie J, Rheology. Texture and swallowing characteristics of a texture-modified Dysphagia Food Prepared using common supplementary materials. Foods. 2023;12(12):2287. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12122287 . PMID: 37372499; PMCID: PMC10297091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12122287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37372499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10297091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman R, Vilardell N, Clavé P, Speyer R. Effect of Bolus Viscosity on the Safety and Efficacy of Swallowing and the Kinematics of the Swallow Response in Patients with Oropharyngeal Dysphagia: White Paper by the European Society for Swallowing Disorders (ESSD). Dysphagia. 2016;31(2):232 – 49. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00455-016-9696-8 . Epub 2016 Mar 25. Erratum in: Dysphagia. 2016;31(5):719. PMID: 27016216; PMCID: PMC4929168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espitalier F, Fanous A, Aviv J, Bassiouny S, Desuter G, Nerurkar N, Postma G, Crevier-Buchman L. International consensus (ICON) on assessment of oropharyngeal dysphagia. Eur Ann Otorhinolaryngol Head Neck Dis. 2018;135(1S):S17-S21. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anorl.2017.12.009 . Epub 2018 Feb 1. PMID: 29396225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brates D, Harel D, Molfenter SM. Perception of Swallowing-Related Fatigue Among Older Adults. J Speech Lang Hear Res. 2022;65(8):2801–2814. https://doi.org/10.1044/2022_JSLHR-22-00151 . Epub 2022 Aug 3. PMID: 35921661.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>