<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39237595</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2396-8370</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>8</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>NPJ science of food</Title><ISOAbbreviation>NPJ Sci Food</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Opportunities and challenges for global food safety in advancing circular policies and practices in agrifood systems.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>60</StartPage><MedlinePgn>60</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">60</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41538-024-00286-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Sustainable agrifood systems are needed to provide safe and nutritious food for the growing world's population. To improve sustainability, transforming linear policies and practices in agrifood systems into circularity will be critical, with food safety considerations key for the success of this shift. This review provides a synthesis of the current and emerging risks, data gaps, and opportunities for food safety in agrifood initiatives aiming to advance circular economy models.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pearson</LastName><ForeName>Andrew J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8984-6517</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agrifood Systems and Food Safety Division, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Rome, Italy. apearson@tonkintaylor.co.nz.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tonkin + Taylor Ltd, Wellington, New Zealand. apearson@tonkintaylor.co.nz.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mukherjee</LastName><ForeName>Keya</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agrifood Systems and Food Safety Division, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fattori</LastName><ForeName>Vittorio</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agrifood Systems and Food Safety Division, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lipp</LastName><ForeName>Markus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3432-5300</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agrifood Systems and Food Safety Division, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>NPJ Sci Food</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101739627</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2396-8370</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>the authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39237595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11377707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41538-024-00286-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41538-024-00286-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Strategic Framework 2022-31. Rome (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO estimates of the global burden of foodborne diseases: foodborne disease burden epidemiology reference group 2007-2015. Geneva (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaffee, S., Henson, S., Unnevehr, L., Grace, D. &amp; Cassou, E. The Safe Food Imperative: Accelerating Progress in Low and Middle-Income Countries. Agriculture and Food Series. Washington, DC: World Bank (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; World Health Organization. Codex Alimentarius – Understanding Codex. Rome, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; Geneva, World Health Organization (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Transforming Food and Agriculture to Achieve the SDGs: 20 interconnected actions to guide decision-makers. Rome (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. The state of the world’s land and water resources for food and agriculture – Systems at breaking point. Synthesis report 2021. Rome (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Assessment of agricultural plastics and their sustainability. A call for action. Rome (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rico Lugo, S. D., Kimita, K. &amp; Nishino, N. Characteristics of decision process towards circular food economy: A review. Clean. Logist. Supply Chain.7, 100104 (2023).10.1016/j.clscn.2023.100104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clscn.2023.100104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Focker, M. et al. Review of food safety hazards in circular food systems in Europe. Food Res. Int.158, 111505 (2022). 10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111505</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35840214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailone, R. L., Borra, R. C., Fukushima, H. C. S. &amp; Aguiar, L. K. Water reuse in the food industry. Discover Food2, 5 (2022).10.1007/s44187-021-00002-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44187-021-00002-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Favere, J. et al. Safeguarding the microbial water quality from source to tap. npj Clean. Water4, 28 (2021).10.1038/s41545-021-00118-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41545-021-00118-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paruch, A. M., Mæhlum, T. &amp; Robertson, L. Changes in microbial quality of irrigated water under different weather conditions in Southeast Norway. Environ. Process.2, 115 (2015).10.1007/s40710-014-0054-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40710-014-0054-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stine, S. W., Song, I., Choi, C. Y. &amp; Gerba, C. P. Application of microbial risk assessment to the development of standards for enteric pathogens in water used to irrigate fresh produce. J. Food Prot.68, 913–918 (2005). 10.4315/0362-028X-68.5.913</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X-68.5.913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15895721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; World Health Organization. Safety and quality of water used with fresh fruits and vegetables. Microbiological Risk Assessment Series No. 37. Rome, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; Geneva, World Health Organization (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tripathi, V. K., Rajput, T. B. S., Patel, N. &amp; Nain, L. Impact of municipal wastewater reuse through micro-irrigation system on the incidence of coliforms in selected vegetable crops. J. Environ. Manag.251, 109532 (2019).10.1016/j.jenvman.2019.109532</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2019.109532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31542620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y.-J., Deering, A. J. &amp; Kim, H.-J. The occurrence of Shiga toxin-producing E. coli in aquaponic and hydroponic systems. Horticulturae6, 1 (2020).10.3390/horticulturae6010001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/horticulturae6010001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bundesinstitut für Risikobewertung. Reclaimed wastewater: preventing viral pathogens on plant foods. BfR Opinion No 019/2022. 10.17590/20220708-132535 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes, L. S., Galvão, A., Santos, R. &amp; Monteiro, S. Impact of water reuse on agricultural practices and human health. Environ. Res.216, 11476 (2023).10.1016/j.envres.2022.114762</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2022.114762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36356670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, M. et al. Prevalence of Salmonella and Listeria monocytogenes in non-traditional irrigation waters in the Mid-Atlantic United States is affected by water type, season, and recovery method. PLoS One15, e0229365 (2020). 10.1371/journal.pone.0229365</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0229365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7077874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32182252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; World Health Organization. Safety and quality of water use and reuse in the production and processing of dairy products – Meeting report. Microbiological Risk Assessment Series, No. 40. Rome, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; Geneva, World Health Organization (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; World Health Organization. Safety and quality of water used with food production and processing. Microbiological Risk Assessment Series No. 33. Rome, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; Geneva, World Health Organization (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natural Resource Management Ministerial Council Environment Protection and Heritage Council Australian Health Ministers’ Conference. National Guidelines for Water Recycling: Managing Health and Environmental Risks. https://www.waterquality.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/water-recycling-guidelines-full-21.pdf (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poppenga, R. et al. Independent Advisory Panel Final Report: Using Disinfected Tertiary Recycled Water for Non-Dairy Livestock Watering: A Human and Animal Health Evaluation for the State of California. Prepared for the California State Water Resources Control Board by the National Water Research Institute, Fountain Valley, CA, USA (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Farsi, R., Ahmed, M., Al-Busaidi, A. &amp; Choudri, B. S. Assessing the presence of pharmaceuticals in soil and plants irrigated with treated wastewater in Oman. Int J. Recycl Org. Waste Agric.7, 165–172 (2018).10.1007/s40093-018-0202-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40093-018-0202-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunyer-Caldú, A. et al. Reclaimed water in agriculture: A plot-scale study assessing crop uptake of emerging contaminants and pathogens. J. Environ. Chem. Eng.10, 108831 (2022).10.1016/j.jece.2022.108831</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jece.2022.108831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manasfi, R. et al. Impact of long-term irrigation with municipal reclaimed wastewater on the uptake and degradation of organic contaminants in lettuce and leek. Sci. Total Environ.765, 142742 (2021). 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142742</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33097266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben Mordechay, E., Tarchitzky, J., Chen, Y., Shenker, M. &amp; Chefetz, B. Composted biosolids and treated wastewater as sources of pharmaceuticals and personal care products for plant uptake: A case study with carbamazepine. Environ. Pollut.232, 164–172 (2018). 10.1016/j.envpol.2017.09.029</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2017.09.029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28935405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costello, M. C. S. &amp; Lee, L. S. Sources, Fate, and Plant Uptake in Agricultural Systems of Per- and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances. Curr. Pollut. Rep. 10.1007/s40726-020-00168-y (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malayil, L. et al. Variations in Bacterial Communities and Antibiotic Resistance Genes Across Diverse Recycled and Surface Water Irrigation Sources in the Mid-Atlantic and Southwest United States: A CONSERVE Two-Year Field Study. Environ. Sci. Technol.56, 15019–15033 (2022). 10.1021/acs.est.2c02281</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c02281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9632240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36194536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; World Health Organization. Safety and quality of water used in the production and processing of fish and fishery products – Meeting report. Microbiological Risk Assessment Series, No. 41. Rome, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &amp; Geneva, World Health Organization (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. The State of Food and Agriculture 2019. Moving forward on food loss and waste reduction. Rome (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Environment Programme. Food Waste Index Report 2021. Nairobi (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Voluntary Code of Conduct for Food Loss and Waste Reduction. Rome (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goossens, Y., Wegner, A. &amp; Schmidt, T. Sustainability assessment of food waste prevention measures: review of existing evaluation practices. Front. Sustain. Food Syst.3, 90 (2019).10.3389/fsufs.2019.00090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2019.00090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakali, A., MacRae, J. D., Isenhour, C. &amp; Blackmer, T. Composition and contamination of source separated food waste from different sources and regulatory environments. J. Environ. Manag.314, 115043 (2022).10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.115043</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.115043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35429688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boumans, I. J. M. M. et al. Feeding food losses and waste to pigs and poultry: Implications for feed quality and production. J. Clean. Prod.378, 134623 (2022).10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.134623</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.134623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, W. F. Temporal variation of antibiotic resistome and pathogens in food waste during short-term storage. J. Hazard. Mater.436, 129261 (2022). 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.129261</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.129261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35739780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Periasamy, J. et al. Food wastes as a potential hotspot of antibiotic resistance: synergistic expression of multidrug resistance and ESBL genes confer antibiotic resistance to microbial communities. Environ. Monit. Assess.195, 783 (2023). 10.1007/s10661-023-11335-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-023-11335-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37261634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemunier, M. et al. Long-term survival of pathogenic and sanitation indicator bacteria in experimental biowaste composts. Appl. Environ. Microbiol.71(10), 5779–5786 (2005). 10.1128/AEM.71.10.5779-5786.2005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.10.5779-5786.2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1265932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16204488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hogg, D. et al. Comparison of compost standards within the EU, North America and Australasia. The Waste and Resources Action Programme, Banbury, UK (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, Z. Mobile genetic elements in potential host microorganisms are the key hindrance for the removal of antibiotic resistance genes in industrial-scale composting with municipal solid waste. Bioresour. Technol.301, 122723 (2020). 10.1016/j.biortech.2019.122723</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.122723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31962245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, T., Jin, Y. &amp; Shen, D. A safety analysis of food waste-derived animal feeds from three typical conversion techniques in China. Waste Manag.45, 42–50 (2015). 10.1016/j.wasman.2015.06.041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wasman.2015.06.041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26188613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huyben, D. et al. Screening of intact yeasts and cell extracts to reduce Scrapie prions during biotransformation of food waste. Acta Vet. Scand.60, 9 (2018). 10.1186/s13028-018-0363-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13028-018-0363-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5806280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29422098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopes, P. et al. Mycotoxins’ prevalence in food industry by-products: a systematic review. Toxins15, 249 (2023). 10.3390/toxins15040249</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins15040249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10142126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37104187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smeu, I. et al. Byproducts from the vegetable oil industry: the challenges of safety and sustainability. Sustainability14, 2039 (2022).10.3390/su14042039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su14042039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suominen, K., Verta, M. &amp; Marttinen, S. Hazardous organic compounds in biogas plant end products—Soil burden and risk to food safety. Sci. Total Environ.491–492, 192–199 (2014). 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2014.02.036</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2014.02.036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24593894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golovko, O. et al. Organic micropollutants, heavy metals and pathogens in anaerobic digestate based on food waste. J. Environ. Manag.313, 114997 (2022).10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.114997</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.114997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35395528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Růžičková, J. et al. The potential environmental risks of the utilization of composts from household food waste. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res28, 24663–24679 (2021).10.1007/s11356-020-09916-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09916-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32705551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakali, A. &amp; MacRae, J. D. A review of chemical and microbial contamination in food: What are the threats to a circular food system? Environ. Res.194, 110635 (2021). 10.1016/j.envres.2020.110635</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33347866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen, T. T., Rosello, C., Bélanger, R. &amp; Ratti, C. Fate of residual pesticides in Fruit and Vegetable Waste (FVW) processing. Foods9, 1468 (2020). 10.3390/foods9101468</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods9101468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7602544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33076324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sójka, M. et al. Pesticide residue levels in strawberry processing by-products that are rich in ellagitannins and an assessment of their dietary risk to consumers. NFS J.1, 31–37 (2015).10.1016/j.nfs.2015.09.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nfs.2015.09.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans, N. M. &amp; Shao, S. Mycotoxin metabolism by edible insects. Toxins14, 217 (2022). 10.3390/toxins14030217</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins14030217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8949902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35324714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camenzuli, L. et al. Tolerance and excretion of the Mycotoxins Aflatoxin B1, Zearalenone, Deoxynivalenol, and Ochratoxin A by Alphitobius diaperinus and Hermetia illucens from Contaminated Substrates. Toxins10, 91 (2018). 10.3390/toxins10020091</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins10020091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5848191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29495278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lievens, S. et al. Chemical safety of black soldier fly larvae (Hermetia illucens), knowledge gaps and recommendations for future research: a critical review. J. Insects Food Feed.7, 383–396 (2021).10.3920/JIFF2020.0081</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/JIFF2020.0081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wynants, E. et al. Assessing the Microbiota of Black Soldier Fly Larvae (Hermetia illucens) reared on organic waste streams on four different locations at laboratory and large scale. Micro. Ecol.77, 13–930 (2019).10.1007/s00248-018-1286-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00248-018-1286-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30430196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fazion, J. P. et al. A systematic review of experimental studies on Salmonella persistence in insects. npj Sci. Food7, 44 (2023). 10.1038/s41538-023-00223-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41538-023-00223-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10462725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37640696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Looking at edible insects from a food safety perspective. Challenges and opportunities for the sector. Rome (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandeweyer, D. et al. Real-time PCR detection and quantification of selected transferable antibiotic resistance genes in fresh edible insects from Belgium and the Netherlands. Int. J. Food Microbiol.290, 288–295 (2019). 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.10.027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.10.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30412800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scopetani, C. et al. Hazardous contaminants in plastics contained in compost and agricultural soil. Chemosphere293, 133645 (2022). 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.133645</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.133645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35051512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azeem, I. et al. Uptake and accumulation of nano/microplastics in plants: a critical review. Nanomaterials11, 2935 (2021). 10.3390/nano11112935</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nano11112935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8618759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34835700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Man, Y. B., Mo, W. Y., Zhang, F. &amp; Wong, M. H. Health risk assessments based on polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in freshwater fish cultured using food waste-based diets. Environ. Pollut.256, 113380 (2020). 10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113380</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31662266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, Z. et al. Replacing fish meal by food waste in feed pellets to culture lower trophic level fish containing acceptable levels of organochlorine pesticides: Health risk assessments. Environ. Int.73, 22–27 (2014). 10.1016/j.envint.2014.07.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2014.07.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25080070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Civero, G., Rusciano, V., Scarpato, D. &amp; Simeone, M. Food: Not only safety, but also sustainability. the emerging trend of new social consumers. Sustainability13, 12967 (2021).10.3390/su132312967</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su132312967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham-Rowe, E., Jessop, D. C. &amp; Sparks, P. Identifying motivations and barriers to minimising household food waste. Resour. Conserv Recycl84, 15–23 (2014).10.1016/j.resconrec.2013.12.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resconrec.2013.12.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Traynor, A. et al. An analysis of emerging food safety and fraud risks of novel insect proteins within complex supply chains. npj Sci. Food8, 7 (2024). 10.1038/s41538-023-00241-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41538-023-00241-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10799884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38245539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manning, L. &amp; Kowalska, A. Considering fraud vulnerability associated with credence-based products such as organic food. Foods10, 1879 (2021). 10.3390/foods10081879</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10081879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8393577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34441656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kavanaugh, M. &amp; Quinlan, J. J. Consumer knowledge and behaviors regarding food date labels and food waste. Food Control115, 107285 (2020).10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasza, G. et al. Conflicting issues of sustainable consumption and food safety: risky consumer behaviors in reducing food waste and plastic packaging. Foods11, 3520 (2022). 10.3390/foods11213520</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11213520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9655145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36360133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matumba, L. et al. Knowledge, attitude, and practices concerning presence of molds in foods among members of the general public in Malawi. Mycotoxin Res.32, 27–36 (2016). 10.1007/s12550-015-0237-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12550-015-0237-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26711441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsen, M., Gidlund, A. &amp; Sulyok, M. Experimental mould growth and mycotoxin diffusion in different food items. World Mycotoxin J.10, 153–161 (2017).10.3920/WMJ2016.2163</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/WMJ2016.2163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guillard, V. et al. The next generation of sustainable food packaging to preserve our environment in a circular economy context. Front. Nutr. 5, 121 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6288173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30564581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato, L. S. &amp; Conte-Junior, C. A. Safety of plastic food packaging: the challenges about non-intentionally added substances (NIAS) discovery, identification and risk assessment. Polymers13, 2077 (2021). 10.3390/polym13132077</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/polym13132077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8271870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34202594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eriksen, M. K., Christiansen, J. D., Daugaard, A. E. &amp; Astrup, T. F. Closing the loop for PET, PE and PP waste from households: Influence of material properties and product design for plastic recycling. Waste Manag.96, 75–85 (2019). 10.1016/j.wasman.2019.07.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wasman.2019.07.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31376972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>López-Gálvez, F. et al. Reusable Plastic Crates (RPCs) for fresh produce (case study on cauliflowers): sustainable packaging but potential Salmonella survival and risk of cross-contamination. Foods10, 1254 (2021). 10.3390/foods10061254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10061254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8228333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34205868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Widén, H., Leufvén, A. &amp; Nielsen, T. Identification of chemicals, possibly originating from misuse of refillable PET bottles, responsible for consumer complaints about off-odours in water and soft drinks. Food Addit. Contam22, 681–692 (2005). 10.1080/02652030500159987</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/02652030500159987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16019844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tisler, S. &amp; Christensen, J. H. Non-target screening for the identification of migrating compounds from reusable plastic bottles into drinking water. J. Hazard. Mater.429, 128331 (2022). 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.128331</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.128331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35091188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonwick, G., Bradley, E., Lock, I. &amp; Romero, R. Bio-Based Materials For Use In Food Contact Applications - Fera project number FR/001658. Report to the Food Standards Agency (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouma, K., Kalsbeek-van Wijk, D. K. &amp; Sijm, D. T. H. M. Migration of formaldehyde from ‘biobased’ bamboo/melamine cups: A Dutch retail survey. Chemosphere292, 133439 (2022). 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.133439</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.133439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34968515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares, C. T. M., Ek, M., Östmark, E., Gällstedt, M. &amp; Karlsson, S. Recycling of multi-material multilayer plastic packaging: Current trends and future scenarios. Resour. Conserv Recycl176, 105905 (2022).10.1016/j.resconrec.2021.105905</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resconrec.2021.105905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, H., Lindström, A., Trischler, J., Wikström, F. &amp; Rowe, Z. Avoiding food becoming waste in households – The role of packaging in consumers’ practices across different food categories. J. Clean. Prod.265, 121775 (2020).10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121775</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marsh, K. &amp; Bugusu, B. Food packaging—roles, materials, and environmental Issues. J. Food Sci.72, R39–R55 (2007). 10.1111/j.1750-3841.2007.00301.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2007.00301.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17995809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wikström, F., Williams, H., Verghese, K. &amp; Clune, S. The influence of packaging attributes on consumer behaviour in food-packaging life cycle assessment studies - a neglected topic. J. Clean. Prod.73, 100–108 (2014).10.1016/j.jclepro.2013.10.042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2013.10.042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savchenko, O. M., Li, T., Kecinski, M. &amp; Messer, K. D. Does food processing mitigate consumers’ concerns about crops grown with recycled water? Food Policy88, 101748 (2019).10.1016/j.foodpol.2019.101748</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodpol.2019.101748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aschemann-Witzel, J. &amp; Stangherlin, I. D. C. Upcycled by-product use in agri-food systems from a consumer perspective: A review of what we know, and what is missing. Technol. Forecast Soc. Change168, 120749 (2021).10.1016/j.techfore.2021.120749</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2021.120749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qamar, Z. et al. Appraisement, source apportionment and health risk of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in vehicle-wash wastewater, Pakistan. Sci. Total Environ.605–606, 106–113 (2017). 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.06.152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.06.152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28662424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Tohamy, R. et al. A critical review on the treatment of dye-containing wastewater: Ecotoxicological and health concerns of textile dyes and possible remediation approaches for environmental safety. Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.231, 113160 (2022). 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2021.113160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2021.113160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35026583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thurston-Enriquez, J. A., Gilley, J. E. &amp; Eghball, B. Microbial quality of runoff following land application of cattle manure and swine slurry. J. Water Health3, 157–171 (2005). 10.2166/wh.2005.0015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wh.2005.0015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16075941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, W., Ding, Y., Chiou, C. T. &amp; Li, H. Selected veterinary pharmaceuticals in agricultural water and soil from land application of animal manure. J. Environ. Qual.39, 1211–1217 (2010). 10.2134/jeq2009.0090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2134/jeq2009.0090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20830908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rad, S. M., Ray, A. K. &amp; Barghi, S. Water pollution and agriculture pesticide. Clean. Technol.4, 1088–1102 (2022).10.3390/cleantechnol4040066</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cleantechnol4040066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garnett, A. Microbial water quality of commercial and residential greywater sources. BRANZ Study Report SR40. Judgeford, New Zealand: BRANZ Ltd (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner, R. D. R., Warne, M. S. J., Dawes, L. A., Thompson, K. &amp; Will, G. D. Greywater irrigation as a source of organic micro-pollutants to shallow groundwater and nearby surface water. Sci. Total Environ.669, 570–578 (2019). 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.03.073</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.03.073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30889446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, S. C., Lim, K.-Y., Huang, X., McCarthy, D. &amp; Hamilton, A. J. Human and environmental health risks and benefits associated with use of urban stormwater. WIREs Water2, 683–699 (2015).10.1002/wat2.1107</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/wat2.1107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johannessen, C., Helm, P. &amp; Metcalfe, C. D. Detection of selected tire wear compounds in urban receiving waters. Environ. Pollut.287, 117659 (2021). 10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117659</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34426371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevens, D. P., Surapaneni, A., Thodupunuri, R., O’Connor, N. A. &amp; Smith, D. Helminth log reduction values for recycling water from sewage for the protection of human and stock health. Water Res.125, 501–511 (2017). 10.1016/j.watres.2017.08.069</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2017.08.069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28942117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Styszko, K., Proctor, K., Castrignanò, E. &amp; Kasprzyk-Hordern, B. Occurrence of pharmaceutical residues, personal care products, lifestyle chemicals, illicit drugs and metabolites in wastewater and receiving surface waters of Krakow agglomeration in South Poland. Sci. Total Environ.768, 144360 (2021). 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.144360</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.144360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33450690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasilachi, I. C., Asiminicesei, D. M., Fertu, D. I. &amp; Gavrilescu, M. Occurrence and fate of emerging pollutants in water environment and options for their removal. Water13, 181 (2021).10.3390/w13020181</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w13020181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenka, S. P., Kah, M. &amp; Padhye, L. P. A review of the occurrence, transformation, and removal of poly- and perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in wastewater treatment plants. Water Res.199, 117187 (2021). 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117187</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34010737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weidhaas, J. et al. Microbial and chemical risk from reclaimed water use for residential irrigation. Water Reuse12, 289 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horodytska, O., Cabanes, A. &amp; Fullana, A. Non-intentionally added substances (NIAS) in recycled plastics. Chemosphere251, 126373 (2020). 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.126373</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.126373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32163780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brosché, S., Strakova, J., Bell, L. &amp; Karlsson, T. Widespread chemical contamination of recycled plastic pellets globally. International Pollutants Elimination Network (IPEN), Sweden. (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chibwe, L. et al. Target and nontarget screening of organic chemicals and metals in recycled plastic materials. Environ. Sci. Technol.57, 3380–3390 (2023). 10.1021/acs.est.2c07254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c07254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9979653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36787488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franz, R. &amp; Welle, F. Contamination levels in recollected PET bottles from non-food applications and their impact on the safety of recycled PET for food contact. Molecules25, 4998 (2020). 10.3390/molecules25214998</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules25214998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7663040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33126687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland Food Standards Agency – Committee on Toxicity. Discussion paper on Ocean Bound Plastic TOX/2022/37. FSA, London (2022).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>