<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39239269</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2234-943X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in oncology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Oncol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Case report: Safety of Tumor Treating Fields therapy with an implantable cardiac pacemaker in a patient with glioblastoma.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1441146</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1441146</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1441146</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fonc.2024.1441146</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) therapy is an anti-cancer treatment modality that is delivered noninvasively to the tumor site via skin-placed arrays. The therapy is US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved and Conformité Européenne (CE) marked for adults with newly diagnosed and recurrent glioblastoma (GBM) (grade 4 glioma in the European Union). To date, there are limited data on the safety and efficacy of TTFields therapy in patients with implanted cardiac pacemakers. Herein, we report a case of a 79-year-old male patient with GBM receiving TTFields therapy with a prior medical history of cardiac events necessitating a cardiac pacemaker. The patient presented to the emergency department in May 2021 with newly onset left-sided weakness along with seizures. Based on an initial evaluation and results of the initial computed tomography (CT) scans (May 2021), the patient was clinically diagnosed with a high-grade glioma which was later confirmed as <i>IDH</i> wildtype following a biopsy. He was treated with radiotherapy (40 Gy in 15 fractions), followed by adjuvant temozolomide (TMZ) (75 mg/m<sup>2</sup>). TTFields therapy was initiated alongside maintenance TMZ (150 mg/m<sup>2</sup>). Average TTFields therapy usage was 67% throughout the duration of treatment. Follow-up CT scans (February and May of 2022) indicated stable disease. CT scans in August 2022 showed an increase in size of a mass with heterogeneous contrast enhancement and the patient subsequently passed away in October 2022. The patient's last cardiac tests demonstrated that the pacemaker was operational with adequate cardiac function. This report suggests that TTFields therapy concomitant with an implanted electronic device may be safe in patients with GBM.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Biedermann, Merrifield and Lustgarten.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Biedermann</LastName><ForeName>Gregory B</ForeName><Initials>GB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Merrifield</LastName><ForeName>Kathleen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Medical Safety, Novocure Inc., New York, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lustgarten</LastName><ForeName>Leonardo</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Affairs, Novocure Inc., New York, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Oncol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101568867</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2234-943X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Optune-Gio</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TTFields therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">active implantable medical device</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cardiac pacemaker</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">glioblastoma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">safety</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Authors KM and LL were employed by the company Novocure. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The authors declare that this study received funding from Novocure. The funder had the following involvement in the study: funding of medical writing support.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39239269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11374662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fonc.2024.1441146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bray F, Ferlay J, Soerjomataram I, Siegel RL, Torre LA, Jemal A. Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin. (2018) 68:394–424. doi: 10.3322/caac.21492</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3322/caac.21492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30207593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller KD, Ostrom QT, Kruchko C, Patil N, Tihan T, Cioffi G, et al. . Brain and other central nervous system tumor statistics, 2021. CA Cancer J Clin. (2021) 71:381–406. doi: 10.3322/caac.21693</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3322/caac.21693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34427324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikh S, Radivoyevitch T, Barnholtz-Sloan JS, Vogelbaum M. Long-term trends in glioblastoma survival: implications for historical control groups in clinical trials. Neurooncol Pract. (2020) 7:158–63. doi: 10.1093/nop/npz046</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nop/npz046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7318862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32626584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostrom QT, Patil N, Cioffi G, Waite K, Kruchko C, Barnholtz-Sloan JS. CBTRUS statistical report: primary brain and other central nervous system tumors diagnosed in the United States in 2013-2017. Neuro Oncol. (2020) 22:iv1–iv96. doi: 10.1093/neuonc/noaa200</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/neuonc/noaa200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7596247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33123732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Novocure . Optune®: instructions for use (2019). Available online at: https://cms-admin.optunegio.com/sites/patient/files/2023-11/Optune_IFU.pdf (Accessed March 1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Novocure . Novocure Receives CE Mark for NovoTTF-100L™ System (2020). Available online at: https://www.novocure.com/novocure-receives-ce-mark-for-novottf-100l-system/ (Accessed February 1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stupp R, Taillibert S, Kanner A, Read W, Steinberg D, Lhermitte B, et al. . Effect of Tumor-Treating Fields plus maintenance temozolomide vs maintenance temozolomide alone on survival in patients with glioblastoma: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. (2017) 318:2306–16. doi: 10.1001/jama.2017.18718</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2017.18718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5820703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29260225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stupp R, Wong ET, Kanner AA, Steinberg D, Engelhard H, Heidecke V, et al. . NovoTTF-100A versus physician's choice chemotherapy in recurrent glioblastoma: a randomised phase III trial of a novel treatment modality. Eur J Cancer. (2012) 48:2192–202. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2012.04.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2012.04.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22608262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
National Comprehensive Cancer Network . Referenced with permission from the NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology (NCCN Guidelines®) for Central Nervous System Cancers V.1.2023. © National Comprehensive Cancer Network, Inc. 2023 (2023). Available online at: https://www.nccn.org/guidelines/guidelines-detail?category=1&amp;id=1425 (Accessed April 8, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirson ED, Gurvich Z, Schneiderman R, Dekel E, Itzhaki A, Wasserman Y, et al. . Disruption of cancer cell replication by alternating electric fields. Cancer Res. (2004) 64:3288–95. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-0083</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-0083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15126372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voloshin T, Schneiderman RS, Volodin A, Shamir RR, Kaynan N, Zeevi E, et al. . Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) hinder cancer cell motility through regulation of microtubule and actin dynamics. Cancers (Basel). (2020) 12:3016. doi: 10.3390/cancers12103016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cancers12103016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7603026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33080774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karanam NK, Story MD. An overview of potential novel mechanisms of action underlying Tumor Treating Fields-induced cancer cell death and their clinical implications. Int J Radiat Biol. (2021) 97:1044–54. doi: 10.1080/09553002.2020.1837984</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09553002.2020.1837984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33086019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stupp R, Taillibert S, Kanner AA, Kesari S, Steinberg DM, Toms SA, et al. . Maintenance therapy with tumor-treating fields plus temozolomide vs temozolomide alone for glioblastoma: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. (2015) 314:2535–43. doi: 10.1001/jama.2015.16669</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.16669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26670971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toms SA, Kim CY, Nicholas G, Ram Z. Increased compliance with tumor treating fields therapy is prognostic for improved survival in the treatment of glioblastoma: a subgroup analysis of the EF-14 phase III trial. J Neurooncol. (2019) 141:467–73. doi: 10.1007/s11060-018-03057-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11060-018-03057-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6342854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30506499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballo MT, Conlon P, Lavy-Shahaf G, Kinzel A, Vymazal J, Rulseh AM. Association of Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) therapy with survival in newly diagnosed glioblastoma: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Neurooncol. (2023) 164:1–9. doi: 10.1007/s11060-023-04348-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11060-023-04348-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10462574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37493865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
US Food and Drug Administration . Optune™ (formerly NovoTTF-100A™ System) Summary of Safety and Effectiveness Data (SSED) (2015). Available online at: https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/cdrh_docs/pdf10/P100034S013b.pdf (Accessed October 11).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenger C, Giladi M, Bomzon Z, Salvador R, Basser PJ, Miranda PC. (2015). Modeling Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) application in single cells during metaphase and telophase, in: Conf Proc IEEE Eng Med Biol Soc, Vol. 2015. pp. 6892–5. doi: 10.1109/EMBC.2015.7319977</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/EMBC.2015.7319977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26737877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper GM. The development and causes of cancer. In: The Cell: A Molecular Approach, 2nd Edition. Sinauer Associates, Sunderland MA: (2000).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baba AI, Câtoi C. Tumor cell morphology. In: Comparative Oncology. The Publishing House of the Romanian Academy, Bucharest, RO: (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20806453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trainito CI, Sweeney DC, Cemazar J, Schmelz EM, Francais O, Le Pioufle B, et al. . Characterization of sequentially-staged cancer cells using electrorotation. PloS One. (2019) 14:e0222289. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0222289</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6752768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31536516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haemmerich D, Schutt DJ, Wright AW, Webster JG, Mahvi DM. Electrical conductivity measurement of excised human metastatic liver tumours before and after thermal ablation. Physiol measurement. (2009) 30:459–66. doi: 10.1088/0967-3334/30/5/003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/0967-3334/30/5/003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2730770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19349647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad MA, Natour ZA, Mustafa F, Rizvi TA. Electrical characterization of normal and cancer cells. IEEE Access. (2018) 6:25979–86. doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2018.2830883</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2018.2830883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirson ED, Dbalý V, Tovaryš F, Vymazal J, Soustiel JF, Itzhaki A, et al. . Alternating electric fields arrest cell proliferation in animal tumor models and human brain tumors. Proc Natl Acad Sci United States America. (2007) 104:10152–7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0702916104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0702916104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1886002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17551011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones TH, Song JW, Abushahin L. Tumor treating fields: An emerging treatment modality for thoracic and abdominal cavity cancers. Transl Oncol. (2022) 15:101296. doi: 10.1016/j.tranon.2021.101296</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tranon.2021.101296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8633677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34847422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puette JA, Malek R, Ellison MB. Pacemaker. Treasure Island (FL: StatPearls Publishing; (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostrom QT, Price M, Neff C, Cioffi G, Waite KA, Kruchko C, et al. . CBTRUS statistical report: primary brain and other central nervous system tumors diagnosed in the United States in 2015-2019. Neuro Oncol. (2022) 24:v1–v95. doi: 10.1093/neuonc/noac202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/neuonc/noac202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9533228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36196752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schaff LR, Mellinghoff IK. Glioblastoma and other primary brain malignancies in adults: A review. JAMA. (2023) 329:574–87. doi: 10.1001/jama.2023.0023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2023.0023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36809318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mrugala MM, Engelhard HH, Dinh Tran D, Kew Y, Cavaliere R, Villano JL, et al. . Clinical practice experience with NovoTTF-100A™ system for glioblastoma: the Patient Registry Dataset (PRiDe). Semin Oncol. (2014) 41:S4–S13. doi: 10.1053/j.seminoncol.2014.09.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.seminoncol.2014.09.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25213869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi W, Blumenthal DT, Oberheim Bush NA, Kebir S, Lukas RV, Muragaki Y, et al. . Global post-marketing safety surveillance of Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) in patients with high-grade glioma in clinical practice. J Neurooncol. (2020) 148:489–500. doi: 10.1007/s11060-020-03540-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11060-020-03540-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7438370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32535723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashby L, Hasselle M, Chowdhary S, Fathallah-Shaykh H, Zhu JJ. ATCT-04: Retrospective analysis of Tumor Treating fields (TTFields) in adults with glioblastoma: safety profile of the Optune™ medical device in patients with implanted non-programmable shunts, programmable shunts, and pacemakers/defibrillators. Neuro Oncol. (2015) 17:v1. doi: 10.1093/neuonc/nov206.04</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/neuonc/nov206.04</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kew Y, Demopoulos A, Oberheim-Bush NA, Zhu JJ. ACTR-65. Safety profile of Tumor Treating Fields in adult glioblastoma patients with implanted non-programmable shunts, programmable shunts, and pacemakers/defibrillators: 6-year updated retrospective analysis of Optune® therapy. Neuro Oncol. (2017) 19:vi14–vi5. doi: 10.1093/neuonc/nox168.053</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/neuonc/nox168.053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mrugala MM, Shi W, Iwomoto F, Lukas RV, Palmer JD, Suh JH, et al. . Global post−marketing safety surveillance of Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) therapy in over 25,000 patients with CNS Malignancies treated between 2011-2022. J Neurooncol. (2024) 169(1):25–38. doi: 10.1007/s11060-024-04682-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11060-024-04682-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11269345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38949692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberheim-Bush NA, Shi W, McDermott MW, Grote A, Stindl J, Lustgarten L. The safety profile of Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) therapy in glioblastoma patients with ventriculoperitoneal shunts. J Neurooncol. (2022) 158:453–61. doi: 10.1007/s11060-022-04033-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11060-022-04033-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9256561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35639236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoyanov GS, Lyutfi E, Georgieva R, Georgiev R, Dzhenkov DL, Petkova L, et al. . Reclassification of glioblastoma multiforme according to the 2021 World Health Organization classification of central nervous system tumors: a single institution report and practical significance. Cureus. (2022) 14:e21822. doi: 10.7759/cureus.21822</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.21822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8896839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35291535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>