<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39230390</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A meta-analysis of factors influencing the inactivation of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O157:H7 in leafy greens.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70012</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70012</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70012</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Recent advancements in modeling suggest that microbial inactivation in leafy greens follows a nonlinear pattern, rather than the simple first-order kinetics. In this study, we evaluated 17 inactivation models commonly used to describe microbial decline and established the conditions that govern microbial survival on leafy greens. Through a systematic review of 65 articles, we extracted 530 datasets to model the fate of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O157:H7 on leafy greens. Various factor analysis methods were employed to evaluate the impact of identified conditions on survival metrics. A two-parameter model (jm2) provided the best fit to most of both natural and antimicrobial-induced persistence datasets, whereas the one-parameter exponential model provided the best fit to less than 20% of the datasets. The jm2 model (adjusted R<sup>2</sup> = .89) also outperformed the exponential model (adjusted R<sup>2</sup> = .58) in fitting the pooled microbial survival data. In the context of survival metrics, the model averaging approach generated higher values than the exponential model for &gt;4 log reduction times (LRTs), suggesting that the exponential model may be overpredicting inactivation at later time points. The random forest technique revealed that temperature and inoculum size were common factors determining inactivation in both natural and antimicrobial-induced die-offs.. The findings show the limitations of relying on the first-order survival metric of 1 LRT and considering nonlinear inactivation in produce safety decision-making.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Owade</LastName><ForeName>Joshua Ombaka</ForeName><Initials>JO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Human Nutrition, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biosystems and Agricultural Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bergholz</LastName><ForeName>Teresa M</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Human Nutrition, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mitchell</LastName><ForeName>Jade</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2199-4190</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biosystems and Agricultural Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>AM21SCBPCA1002</GrantID><Agency>The Center for Produce Safety and the U.S. Department of Agriculture's (USDA) Agricultural Marketing Service</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019453" MajorTopicYN="Y">Escherichia coli O157</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014675" MajorTopicYN="N">Vegetables</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D050296" MajorTopicYN="N">Microbial Viability</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018515" MajorTopicYN="N">Plant Leaves</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">condition</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">die‐off</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">factor analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">first order</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nonlinear</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">survival metrics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39230390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abadias, M., Alegre, I., Oliveira, M., Altisent, R., &amp; Viñas, I. (2012). Growth potential of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on fresh‐cut fruits (melon and pineapple) and vegetables (carrot and escarole) stored under different conditions. Food Control, 27(1), 37–44. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.02.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abnavi, M. D., Kothapalli, C. R., Munther, D., &amp; Srinivasan, P. (2021). Chlorine inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in fresh produce wash process: Effectiveness and modeling. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 356, Article 109364. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2021.109364</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abraham, G., Debray, E., Candau, Y., &amp; Piar, G. (1990). Mathematical model of thermal destruction of Bacillus stearothermophilus spores. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 56(10), 3073–3080. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.56.10.3073‐3080.1990</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aragao, G. M. F., Corradini, M. G., Normand, M. D., &amp; Peleg, M. (2007). Evaluation of the Weibull and log normal distribution functions as survival models of Escherichia coli under isothermal and non isothermal conditions. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 119(3), 243–257. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2007.08.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Astill, G. (2019). Seasonality in Romaine outbreaks and regional shipments (VGS‐362‐SA). U.S. Department of Agriculture, Economic Research Service.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barton, K. (2023). Package ‘muMIn’: Multi‐model interface. CRAN.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belias, A. M., Sbodio, A., Truchado, P., Weller, D., Pinzon, J., Skots, M., Allende, A., Munther, D., Suslow, T., Wiedmann, M., &amp; Ivanek, R. (2020). Effect of weather on the die‐off of Escherichia coli and attenuated Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium on preharvest leafy greens following irrigation with contaminated water. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 86(17), Article e00899‐20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benaglia, T., Chauveau, D., Hunter, D. R., &amp; Young, D. S. (2009). Mixtools: An R package for analyzing finite mixture models. Journal of Statistical Software, 32(6), 1–29. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v032.i06</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bevilacqua, A., Speranza, B., Sinigaglia, M., &amp; Corbo, M. R. (2015). A focus on the death kinetics in predictive microbiology: Benefits and limits of the most important models and some tools dealing with their application in foods. Foods, 4(4), 565–580. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods4040565</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bezanson, G., Delaquis, P., Bach, S., McKellar, R., Topp, E., Gill, A., Blais, B., &amp; Gilmour, M. (2012). Comparative examination of Escherichia coli O157:H7 survival on romaine lettuce and in soil at two independent experimental sites. Journal of Food Protection, 75(3), 480–487. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐11‐306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyacioglu, O., Sharma, M., Sulakvelidze, A., &amp; Goktepe, I. (2013). Biocontrol of Escherichia coli O157. Bacteriophage, 3(1), Article e24620. https://doi.org/10.4161/bact.24620</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandl, M. T., Ivanek, R., Allende, A., &amp; Munther, D. S. (2023). Predictive population dynamics of Escherichia coli o157:H7 and Salmonella enterica on plants: A mechanistic mathematical model based on weather parameters and bacterial state. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 89(7), Article e0070023. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.00700‐23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavalli‐Sforza, L. T., Menozzi, P., &amp; Strata, A. (1983). A model and program for study of a tolerance curve: Application to lactose absorption tests. International Journal of Bio‐Medical Computing, 14(1), 31–41. https://doi.org/10.1016/0020‐7101(83)90084‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). (2024). List of multistate foodborne outbreak notices. https://www.cdc.gov/foodsafety/outbreaks/lists/outbreaks‐list.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang, J. M., &amp; Fang, T. J. (2007). Survival of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella enterica serovars Typhimurium in iceberg lettuce and the antimicrobial effect of rice vinegar against E. coli O157:H7. Food Microbiology, 24(7–8), 745–751. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2007.03.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chase, J. A., Atwill, E. R., Partyka, M. L., Bond, R. F., &amp; Oryang, D. (2017). Inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on romaine lettuce when inoculated in a fecal slurry matrix. Journal of Food Protection, 80(5), 792–798. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐16‐307</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chase, J. A., Partyka, M. L., Bond, R. F., &amp; Atwill, E. R. (2019). Environmental inactivation and irrigation‐mediated regrowth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on romaine lettuce when inoculated in a fecal slurry matrix. PeerJ, 7, Article e6591. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.6591</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J. C., Patel, K., Smith, P. A., Vidyaprakash, E., Snyder, C., Tagg, K. A., Webb, H. E., Schroeder, M. N., Katz, L. S., Rowe, L. A., Howard, D., Griswold, T., Lindsey, R. L., &amp; Carleton, H. A. (2023). Reoccurring Escherichia coli O157:H7 strain linked to leafy greens—Associated outbreaks, 2016–2019. Emerging Infectious Diseases, 29(9), 2016–2019. https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2909.230069</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chhetri, V. S., Han, Y., Janes, M. E., &amp; Adhikari, A. (2020). Evaluation of viability of E. coli O157:H7 on chlorine and lactic acid treated spinach leaves using combined propidium monoazide staining and real‐time PCR. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology, 125, Article 109259. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109259</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chick, H. (1908). An investigation of the laws of disinfection. Journal of Hygiene, 8(1), 92–158. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022172400006987</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, S., Bang, J., Kim, H., Beuchat, L. R., &amp; Ryu, J.‐H. (2011). Survival and colonization of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on spinach leaves as affected by inoculum level and carrier, temperature and relative humidity. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 111(6), 1465–1472. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2672.2011.05175.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coroller, L., Leguerinel, I., Mettler, E., Savy, N., &amp; Mafart, P. (2006). General model, based on two mixed Weibull distributions of bacterial resistance, for describing various shapes of inactivation curves. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 72(10), 6493–6502. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.00876‐06</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crane, S. R., &amp; Moore, J. A. (1986). Modeling enteric bacterial die‐off: A review. Water, Air, and Soil Pollution, 27(3–4), 411–439. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00649422</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, H., Bai, M., Yuan, L., Surendhiran, D., &amp; Lin, L. (2018). Sequential effect of phages and cold nitrogen plasma against Escherichia coli O157:H7 biofilms on different vegetables. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 268, 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.01.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson, G. R., Kaminski, C. N., &amp; Ryser, E. T. (2014). Impact of organic load on Escherichia coli O157:H7 survival during pilot‐scale processing of iceberg lettuce with acidified sodium hypochlorite. Journal of Food Protection, 77(10), 1669–1681. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐14‐067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson, G. R., Kaminski‐Davidson, C. N., &amp; Ryser, E. T. (2017). Persistence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 during pilot‐scale processing of iceberg lettuce using flume water containing peroxyacetic acid‐based sanitizers and various organic loads. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 248, 22–31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2017.02.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dean, K., &amp; Mitchell, J. (2022). Meta‐analysis addressing the implications of model uncertainty in understanding the persistence of indicators and pathogens in natural surface waters. Environmental Science and Technology, 56(17), 12106–12115. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.1c07552</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dean, K., Wissler, A., Hernandez‐Suarez, J. S., Nejadhashemi, A. P., &amp; Mitchell, J. (2020). Modeling the persistence of viruses in untreated groundwater. Science of the Total Environment, 717, Article 134599. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134599</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delaquis, P., Bach, S., &amp; Dinu, L. D. (2007). Behavior of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in leafy vegetables. Journal of Food Protection, 70(8), 1966–1974. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐70.8.1966</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, T., Jin, Y., Rahman, S. M. E., Kim, J., Choi, K., Choi, G., &amp; Oh, D. (2009). Prediction of growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in lettuce treated with alkaline electrolyzed water at different temperatures. Journal of Food Hygiene and Safety, 24(3), 232–237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinu, L. D., &amp; Bach, S. (2011). Induction of viable but nonculturable Escherichia coli O157:H7 in the phyllosphere of lettuce: A food safety risk factors. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 77(23), 8295–8302. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.05020‐11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dixit, A. R., Khodadad, C. L. M., Hummerick, M. E., Spern, C. J., Spencer, L. S. E., Fischer, J. A., Curry, A. B., Gooden, J. L., Maldonado Vazquez, G. J., Wheeler, R. M., Massa, G. D., &amp; Romeyn, M. W. (2021). Persistence of Escherichia coli in the microbiomes of red Romaine lettuce (Lactuca sativa cv. ‘Outredgeous’) and mizuna mustard (Brassica rapa var. japonica)—Does seed sanitization matter? BMC Microbiology, 21(1), Article 289. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866‐021‐02345‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doering, H. J., Harrison, M. A., Morrow, R. A., Hurst, W. C., &amp; Kerr, W. L. (2009). Use of the systems approach to determine the fate of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on fresh lettuce and spinach. Journal of Food Protection, 72(7), 1560–1568. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐72.7.1560</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elhadidy, M., &amp; Álvarez‐Ordóñez, A. (2016). Diversity of survival patterns among Escherichia coli O157:H7 genotypes subjected to food‐related stress conditions. Frontiers in Microbiology, 7, Article 322. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2016.00322</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enger, K. S., Mitchell, J., Murali, B., Birdsell, D. N., Keim, P., Gurian, P. L., &amp; Wagner, D. M. (2018). Evaluating the long‐term persistence of Bacillus spores on common surfaces. Microbial Biotechnology, 11(6), 1048–1059. https://doi.org/10.1111/1751‐7915.13267</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fabozzi, F. J., Focardi, S. M., Rachev, S. T., &amp; Arshanapalli, B. G. (2014). Appendix E: Model selection criterion: AIC and BIC. In F. J. Fabozzi, S. M. Focardi, S. T. Rachev, &amp; B. G. Arshanapalli (Eds.), The basics of financial econometrics: Tools, concepts, and asset management applications (pp. 399–403). John Wiley &amp; Sons. https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118856406.app5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franz, E., Tromp, S. O., Rijgersberg, H., &amp; van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J. (2010). Quantitative microbial risk assessment for Escherichia coli O157:H7, Salmonella enterica, and Listeria monocytogenes in leafy green vegetables consumed at salad bars, based on modeling supply chain logistics. Journal of Food Protection, 73(10), 1830–1840. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐73.10.1830</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, T. J., Li, Y., Awad, D., Zhou, T. Y., &amp; Liu, L. (2018). Factors affecting the performance and monitoring of a chlorine wash in preventing Escherichia coli O157:H7 cross‐contamination during postharvest washing of cut lettuce. Food Control, 94, 212–221. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.06.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gil, M. M., Miller, F. A., Brandão, T. R. S., &amp; Silva, C. L. M. (2011). On the use of the Gompertz model to predict microbial thermal inactivation under isothermal and non‐isothermal conditions. Food Engineering Reviews, 3(1), 17–25. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12393‐010‐9032‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gleeson, E., &amp; O'Beirne, D. (2005). Effects of process severity on survival and growth of Escherichia coli and Listeria innocua on minimally processed vegetables. Food Control, 16(8), 677–685. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2004.06.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González, J. M. (1995). Modelling enteric bacteria survival in aquatic systems. Hydrobiologia, 316(2), 109–116. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00016892</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibekwe, A. M., Grieve, C. M., Papiernik, S. K., &amp; Yang, C.‐H. (2009). Persistence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on the rhizosphere and phyllosphere of lettuce. Letters in Applied Microbiology, 49(6), 784–790. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1472‐765X.2009.02745.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jodrá, P. (2009). A closed‐form expression for the quantile function of the Gompertz‐Makeham distribution. Mathematics and Computers in Simulation, 79(10), 3069–3075. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matcom.2009.02.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juneja, V. K., Eblen, B. S., &amp; Marks, H. M. (2001). Modeling non‐linear survival curves to calculate thermal inactivation of Salmonella in poultry of different fat levels. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 70(1–2), 37–51. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0168‐1605(01)00518‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juneja, V. K., Huang, L., &amp; Thippareddi, H. H. (2006). Predictive model for growth of Clostridium perfringens in cooked cured pork. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 110(1), 85–92. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2006.01.038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J., Chung, H., Cho, J., &amp; Yoon, K. (2013). Evaluation of models describing the growth of nalidixic acid‐resistant E. coli O157:H7 in blanched spinach and iceberg lettuce as a function of temperature. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 10(7), 2857–2870. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph10072857</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, S. Y., &amp; Baek, S. Y. (2008). Effect of chemical sanitizer combined with modified atmosphere packaging on inhibiting Escherichia coli O157:H7 in commercial spinach. Food Microbiology, 25(4), 582–587. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2008.02.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Likotrafiti, E., Anagnou, M., Lampiri, P., &amp; Rhoades, J. (2014). Effect of storage temperature on the behaviour of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella enterica serotype Typhimurium on salad vegetables. Journal of Food Research, 3(2), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.5539/jfr.v3n2p1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, Y., Zhou, B., Van Haute, S., Nou, X., Zhang, B., Teng, Z., Turner, E. R., Wang, Q., &amp; Millner, P. D. (2018). Association between bacterial survival and free chlorine concentration during commercial fresh‐cut produce wash operation. Food Microbiology, 70, 120–128. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2017.09.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoud, B. S. M., &amp; Linton, R. H. (2008). Inactivation kinetics of inoculated Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella enterica on lettuce by chlorine dioxide gas. Food Microbiology, 25(2), 244–252. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2007.10.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markland, S. M., Shortlidge, K. L., Hoover, D. G., Yaron, S., Patel, J., Singh, A., Sharma, M., &amp; Kniel, K. E. (2013). Survival of pathogenic Escherichia coli on basil, lettuce, and spinach. Zoonoses and Public Health, 60(8), 563–571. https://doi.org/10.1111/zph.12033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Max, A., Wing, J., Weston, S., Williams, A., Keefer, C., Engelhardt, A., Cooper, T., Mayer, Z., Ziem, A., Scrucca, L., Hunt, T., &amp; Kuhn, M. M. (2021). Package ‘caret’: Classification and regression training (version 6.0‐88). CRAN.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKellar, R. C., LeBlanc, D. I., Rodríguez, F. P., &amp; Delaquis, P. (2014). Comparative simulation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 behaviour in packaged fresh‐cut lettuce distributed in a typical Canadian supply chain in the summer and winter. Food Control, 35(1), 192–199. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2013.06.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKellar, R. C., Peréz‐Rodríguez, F., Harris, L. J., Moyne, A.‐L., Blais, B., Topp, E., Bezanson, G., Bach, S., &amp; Delaquis, P. (2014). Evaluation of different approaches for modeling Escherichia coli O157:H7 survival on field lettuce. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 184, 74–85. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.04.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell, J., &amp; Akram, S. (2017). Pathogen specific persistence modeling data. In J. B. Rose &amp; B. Jiménez‐Cisneros (Eds.), Water and sanitation for the 21st century: Health and microbiological aspects of excreta and wastewater management (Global water pathogen project) (pp. 1–20). UNESCO. https://www.waterpathogens.org/book/waste‐stabilization‐ponds</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyne, A. L., Blessington, T., Williams, T. R., Koike, S. T., Cahn, M. D., Marco, M. L., &amp; Harris, L. J. (2020). Conditions at the time of inoculation influence survival of attenuated Escherichia coli O157:H7 on field‐inoculated lettuce. Food Microbiology, 85, Article 103274. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2019.103274</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyne, A. L., Harris, L. J., &amp; Marco, M. L. (2013). Assessments of total and viable Escherichia coli O157:H7 on field and laboratory grown lettuce. PLoS ONE, 8(7), Article e70643. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0070643</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyne, A. L., Sudarshana, M. R., Blessington, T., Koike, S. T., Cahn, M. D., &amp; Harris, L. J. (2011). Fate of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in field‐inoculated lettuce. Food Microbiology, 28(8), 1417–1425. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2011.02.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukhopadhyay, S., Sokorai, K., Ukuku, D. O., Jin, T., Fan, X., Olanya, O. M., Leng, J., &amp; Juneja, V. (2021). Effects of direct and in‐package pulsed light treatment on inactivation of E. coli O157:H7 and reduction of microbial loads in Romaine lettuce. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology, 139, Article 110710. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.110710</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munther, D. S., Carter, M. Q., Aldric, C. V., Ivanek, R., &amp; Brandl, M. T. (2020). Formation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 persister cells in the lettuce phyllosphere and application of differential equation models to predict their prevalence on lettuce plants in the field. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 86(2), Article e01602‐19. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01602‐19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nou, X., Luo, Y., Hollar, L., Yang, Y., Feng, H., Millner, P., &amp; Shelton, D. (2011). Chlorine stabilizer T‐128 enhances efficacy of chlorine against cross‐contamination by E. coli O157:H7 and Salmonella in fresh‐cut lettuce processing. Journal of Food Science, 76(3), 218–224. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1750‐3841.2011.02046.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira, M., Usall, J., Solsona, C., Alegre, I., Viñas, I., &amp; Abadias, M. (2010). Effects of packaging type and storage temperature on the growth of foodborne pathogens on shredded “Romaine” lettuce. Food Microbiology, 27(3), 375–380. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2009.11.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ottoson, J. R., Nyberg, K., Lindqvist, R., &amp; Albihn, A. (2011). Quantitative microbial risk assessment for Escherichia coli o157 on lettuce, based on survival data from controlled studies in a climate chamber. Journal of Food Protection, 74(12), 2000–2007. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐10‐563</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peleg, M. (1996). Evaluation of the Fermi equation as a model of dose‐response curves. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 46(3), 303–306. https://doi.org/10.1007/s002530050821</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peleg, M. (2003). Calculation of the non‐isothermal inactivation patterns of microbes having sigmoidal isothermal semi‐logarithmic survival curves. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 43(6), 645–658. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408690390251156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peleg, M. (2006). Advanced quantitative microbiology for foods and biosystems: Models for predicting growth and inactivation. CRC Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peleg, M. (2021). Microbial dose‐response curves and disinfection efficacy models revisited. Food Engineering Reviews, 13(2), 305–321. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12393‐020‐09249‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peleg, M., &amp; Normand, M. D. (2004). Calculating microbial survival parameters and predicting survival curves from non‐isothermal inactivation data. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 44(6), 409–418. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408690490489297</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peleg, M., Normand, M. D., &amp; Campanella, O. H. (2003). Estimating microbial inactivation parameters from survival curves obtained under varying conditions—The linear case. Bulletin of Mathematical Biology, 65(2), 219–234. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0092‐8240(02)00097‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. (2022). R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing. https://www.r‐project.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers, S. W., Donnelly, M., Peed, L., Kelty, C. A., Mondal, S., Zhong, Z., &amp; Shanks, O. C. (2011). Decay of bacterial pathogens, fecal indicators, and real‐time quantitative PCR genetic markers in manure‐amended soils. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 77(14), 4839–4848. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.02427‐10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seidu, R., Sjølander, I., Abubakari, A., Amoah, D., Larbi, J. A., &amp; Stenström, T. A. (2013). Modeling the die‐off of E. coli and Ascaris in wastewater‐irrigated vegetables: Implications for microbial health risk reduction associated with irrigation cessation. Water Science and Technology, 68(5), 1013–1021. https://doi.org/10.2166/wst.2013.335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, S. H., Kim, S. J., Kwak, S. J., &amp; Yoon, K. S. (2012). Efficacy of sodium hypochlorite and acidified sodium chlorite in preventing browning and microbial growth on fresh‐cut produce. Preventive Nutrition and Food Science, 17(3), 210–216. https://doi.org/10.3746/pnf.2012.17.3.210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyagi, D., Kraft, A. L., Smith, S. L., Roof, S. E., Sherwood, J. S., Wiedmann, M., &amp; Bergholz, T. M. (2019). Pre‐harvest survival and post‐harvest chlorine tolerance of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli on lettuce. Toxins, 11(11), Article 675. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins11110675</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Food and Drug Administration (USFDA). (2022). Potential for infiltration, survival, and growth of human pathogens within fruits and vegetables. Hazard Analysis Critical Control Point (HACCP). https://www.fda.gov/food/hazard‐analysis‐critical‐control‐point‐haccp/potential‐infiltration‐survival‐and‐growth‐human‐pathogens‐within‐fruits‐and‐vegetables</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uzeh, R. E., &amp; Adepoju, A. (2013). Incidence and survival of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Listeria monocytogenes on salad vegetables. International Food Research Journal, 20(4), 1921–1925. https://www.scopus.com/inward/record.uri?eid=2‐s2.0‐84884676693&amp;partnerID=40&amp;md5=4c0054d2106a5c9d72df45d8a829543e</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Elsas, J. D., Semenov, A. V., Costa, R., &amp; Trevors, J. T. (2011). Survival of Escherichia coli in the environment: Fundamental and public health aspects. ISME Journal, 5(2), 173–183. https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.80</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Gerwen, S. J. C., &amp; Zwietering, M. H. (1998). Growth and inactivation models to be used in quantitative risk assessments. Journal of Food Protection, 61(11), 1541–1549. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X‐61.11.1541</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watson, H. E. (1908). A note on the variation of the rate of disinfection with change in the concentration of the disinfectant. Epidemiology and Infection, 8(4), 536–542. https://doi.org/10.1017/s0022172400015928</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, J. W., Hung, W. L., &amp; Tsai, C. H. (2004). Estimation of parameters of the Gompertz distribution using the least squares method. Applied Mathematics and Computation, 158(1), 133–147. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amc.2003.08.086</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong, R., Xie, G., Edmondson, A. E., &amp; Sheard, M. A. (1999). A mathematical model for bacterial inactivation. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 46(1), 45–55. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0168‐1605(98)00172‐X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, W., Vorst, K., Brown, W., Marks, B. P., Jeong, S., Pérez‐Rodríguez, F., &amp; Ryser, E. T. (2014). Growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Listeria monocytogenes in packaged fresh‐cut romaine mix at fluctuating temperatures during commercial transport, retail storage, and display. Journal of Food Protection, 77(2), 197–206. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐13‐117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zwietering, M. H., De Wit, J. C., &amp; Notermans, S. (1996). Application‐of predictive microbiology to estimate the number of Bacillus cereus in pasteurised milk at the point of consumption. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 30(1–2), 55–70. https://doi.org/10.1016/0168‐1605(96)00991‐9</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>