<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39233147</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>279</Volume><Issue>Pt 3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>In situ modification of foaming bacterial cellulose with chitosan and its application to active food packaging.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>135114</StartPage><MedlinePgn>135114</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135114</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)05920-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Owing to a lack of specific biological functions, bacterial cellulose (BC) has been restricted in its application to the field of active packaging. In this study, we developed antimicrobial packaging materials using foaming BC (FBC) with chitosan (CS) and applied it to the preservation of chilled sea bass. The material property analysis demonstrated that 1.5 % CS/FBC maintained a high water content of 91 %, a swelling ratio of 75.6 %, great stress of 1.61 MPa, and great strain of 1.87 %. CS incorporation into FBC also decreased its crystallinity from 73.39 % to 69.3 %. Meanwhile, 1.5 % CS/FBC also provided great antimicrobial ability against Escherichia coli and Staphylococcus aureus by approximately 2 log colony-forming units/mL inhibition utilizing contact-killing. Results of the preservation assessment indicated that 1.5 % CS/FBC efficiently inhibited Shewanella putrefaciens growth, reduced total volatile basic nitrogen release, and slightly inhibited lipid oxidation. Based on the above results, CS/FBC is an ecofriendly biomaterial produced from a microorganism that possesses high absorbency and strong antibacterial properties, making it suitable for development as antibacterial active packaging.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Shin-Ping</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Safety, College of Nutrition, Taipei Medical University, 250 Wu-Hsing Street, Taipei 11031, Taiwan; Ph.D. Program in Drug Discovery and Development Industry, College of Pharmacy, Taipei Medical University, 250 Wu-Hsing Street, Taipei 11031, Taiwan; TMU Research Center for Digestive Medicine, Taipei Medical University, 250 Wu-Hsing Street, Taipei 11031, Taiwan; Research Center of Biomedical Device, Taipei Medical University, 250 Wu-Hsing Street, Taipei 11031, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hong</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food Science and Technology, National Taiwan University, 1 Roosevelt Rd., Sec. 4, Taipei 10617, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hsieh</LastName><ForeName>Chen-Che</ForeName><Initials>CC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biotechnology, National Taiwan University, 1 Roosevelt Rd., Sec. 4, Taipei 10617, Taiwan; Department of Seafood Science, College of Hydrosphere, National Kaohsiung University of Science and Technology, Kaohsiung 81157, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Yun-Hsin</ForeName><Initials>YH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biotechnology, National Taiwan University, 1 Roosevelt Rd., Sec. 4, Taipei 10617, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chou</LastName><ForeName>Yu-Chieh</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ph.D. Program in Drug Discovery and Development Industry, College of Pharmacy, Taipei Medical University, 250 Wu-Hsing Street, Taipei 11031, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Santoso</LastName><ForeName>Shella Permatasari</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical Engineering, Widya Mandala Surabaya Catholic University, 37 Kalijudan, Surabaya 60114, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hsieh</LastName><ForeName>Chang-Wei</ForeName><Initials>CW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Biotechnology, National Chung Hsing University, 145 Xingda Rd., South Dist., Taichung City 402, Taiwan; Department of Medical Research, China Medical University Hospital, China Medical University, 91 Hsueh-Shih Road, Taichung 40402, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsai</LastName><ForeName>Tsung-Yu</ForeName><Initials>TY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, Fu Jen Catholic University, 510 Zhongzheng Rd., Xinzhuang Dist., New Taipei City 242062, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Kuan-Chen</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food Science and Technology, National Taiwan University, 1 Roosevelt Rd., Sec. 4, Taipei 10617, Taiwan; Institute of Biotechnology, National Taiwan University, 1 Roosevelt Rd., Sec. 4, Taipei 10617, Taiwan; Department of Medical Research, China Medical University Hospital, China Medical University, 91 Hsueh-Shih Road, Taichung 40402, Taiwan; Department of Optometry, Asia University, 500 Lioufeng Rd., Wufeng, Taichung 41354, Taiwan. Electronic address: kccheng@ntu.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Active packaging</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antimicrobial property</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chitosan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Foaming bacterial cellulose</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">In situ</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sea bass</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39233147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)05920-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>