<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39248037</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>09</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Fermentation starters and bacteriocins as biocontrol strategies for table olives preservation: a mini-review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13874</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Biopreservation is a powerful strategy to prolong the shelf life of food products by applying naturally occurring microorganisms and/or their metabolites. Current food trends emphasise the need to develop alternatives for chemical or thermal preservation methods. In this line, different fermentation starters from table olives present the potential to control spoilage or pathogen-occurring microorganism in table olives storage. One of the most interesting family used as biopreservative culture is Lactobacillaceae and it has also been used in combination with yeasts as olive fermentation starter. Lactic acid bacteria, from Lactobacillaceae family, are characterised by the production of bacteriocins, proteins with the potential for preserving food by changing the organisation of the membrane of spoilage microorganisms. These bacteriocins-producing bacteria can be directly inoculated, although nanosystem technology is the most promising incorporation strategy. In table olives, the most commonly used starters are Lactiplantibacillus plantarum, Lactiplantibacillus pentosus, Saccharomyces cerevisiae, Wickerhamomyces anomalus, among others. These strains with biopreservation characteristics, inoculated alone or in mixed cultures, ensure food safety by conferring the product added value and prolonging product shelf life. © 2024 The Author(s). Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rus-Fernández</LastName><ForeName>Patricia</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8849-5292</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Ingeniería de Alimentos - FoodUPV, Universitat Politècnica de València, Valencia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fuentes</LastName><ForeName>Ana</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4144-2396</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Ingeniería de Alimentos - FoodUPV, Universitat Politècnica de València, Valencia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacteriocin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biopreservation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">starter</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">table olives</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39248037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Perpetuini G, Prete R, Garcia‐Gonzalez N, Alam MK and Corsetti A, Table olives more than a fermented food. Foods 9:1–16 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conte P, Fadda C, Del Caro A, Urgeghe PP and Piga A, Table olives: an overview on effects of processing on nutritional and sensory quality. Foods 9:514 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hurtado A, Reguant C, Bordons A and Rozès N, Evaluation of a single and combined inoculation of a lactobacillus pentosus starter for processing cv. Arbequina natural green olives. Food Microbiol 27:731–740 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Angelis M, Campanella D, Cosmai L, Summo C, Rizzello CG and Caponio F, Microbiota and metabolome of un‐started and started Greek‐type fermentation of Bella di Cerignola table olives. Food Microbiol 52:18–30 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campus M, Degirmencioglu N and Comunian R, Technologies and trends to improve table olive quality and safety. Front Microbiol 9:617 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Silva Sabo S, Vitolo M, González JMD and de Souza Oliveira RP, Overview of lactobacillus plantarum as a promising bacteriocin producer among lactic acid bacteria. Food Res Int 64:527–536 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hurtado A, Reguant C, Bordons A and Rozès N, Lactic acid bacteria from fermented table olives. Food Microbiol 31:1–8 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holzapfel WH, Appropriate starter culture technologies for small‐scale fermentation in developing countries. Int J Food Microbiol 75:197–212 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corsetti A, Perpetuini G, Schirone M, Tofalo R and Suzzi G, Application of starter cultures to table olive fermentation: an overview on the experimental studies. Front Microbiol 3:1–6 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romeo FV, Microbiological aspects of table olives, in Olive Germplasm ‐ The Olive Cultivation, Table Olive and Olive Oil Industry in Italy, ed. by Muzzalupo I. In Tech Open, London, p. 321 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng J, Wittouck S, Salvetti E, Franz CMAP, Harris HMB, Mattarelli P et al., A taxonomic note on the genus Lactobacillus: description of 23 novel genera, emended description of the genus Lactobacillus Beijerinck 1901, and union of Lactobacillaceae and Leuconostocaceae. Int J Syst Evol Microbiol 70:2782–2858 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barcenilla C, Ducic M, López M, Prieto M and Álvarez‐Ordóñez A, Application of lactic acid bacteria for the biopreservation of meat products: a systematic review. Meat Sci 183:108661 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakhmanova A, Khan ZA and Shah K, A mini review fermentation and preservation: role of lactic acid bacteria. Food Process Technol 6:414‐416 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bamforth CW and Cook DJ, The science underpinning food fermentations. Food Ferment Micro‐organisms:5–42 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Portilha‐Cunha MF, Macedo AC and Malcata FX, A review on adventitious lactic acid bacteria from table olives. Foods 9:948 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu Q, Application of bacteriocins in the food industry, in Bacteriocins. Springer Nature, Singapore (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Cuellar MR, Rodríguez‐Hernández AI and Chavarría‐Hernández N, LAB bacteriocin applications in the last dec. Biotechnology and Biotechnological Equipment 30:1039–1050 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juturu V and Wu JC, Microbial production of bacteriocins: latest research development and applications. Biotechnol Adv 36:2187–2200 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younes M, Aggett P, Aguilar F, Crebelli R, Dusemund B, Filipič M et al., Safety of nisin (E 234) as a food additive in the light of new toxicological data and the proposed extension of use. EFSA J 15:e05063 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zacharof MP and Lovitt RW, Bacteriocins produced by lactic acid bacteria a review article. APCBEE Proc 2:50–56 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soltani S, Hammami R, Cotter PD, Rebuffat S, Said LB, Gaudreau H et al., Bacteriocins as a new generation of antimicrobials: toxicity aspects and regulations. FEMS Microbiol Rev 45:fuaa039 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abriouel H, Benomar N, Gálvez A and Pérez Pulido R, Preservation of Manzanilla Aloreña cracked green table olives by high hydrostatic pressure treatments singly or in combination with natural antimicrobials. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology 56:427–431 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dicks LMT, Dreyer L, Smith C and Van Staden AD, A review: the fate of bacteriocins in the human gastro‐intestinal tract: do they cross the gut–blood barrier? Front Microbiol 9:1–14 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reviriego C, Lactococcus lactis “Productores de Pediocina PA‐1 Y Enterocoos aislados de leche materna como agentes bioconservantes en quesos (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma DK, Thakur M, Singh S, Tripathy S, Gupta AK, Baranwal D et al., Bacteriocins as antimicrobial and preservative agents in food: biosynthesis, separation and application. Food Biosci 46:101594 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumariya R, Garsa AK, Rajput YS, Sood SK, Akhtar N and Patel S, Bacteriocins: classification, synthesis, mechanism of action and resistance development in food spoilage causing bacteria. Microb Pathog 128:171–177 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preciado GM, Michel MM, Villarreal‐Morales SL, Flores‐Gallegos AC, Aguirre‐Joya J, Morlett‐Chávez J et al., Bacteriocins and its use for multidrug‐resistant bacteria control, in Antibiotic Resistance: Mechanisms and New Antimicrobial Approaches. Academic Press, United States, pp. 329–349 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radaic A, De Jesus MB and Kapila YL, Bacterial anti‐microbial peptides and nano‐sized drug delivery systems: the state of the art toward improved bacteriocins. J Control Release 321:100–118 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deegan LH, Cotter PD, Hill C and Ross P, Bacteriocins: biological tools for bio‐preservation and shelf‐life extension. Int Dairy J 16:1058–1071 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Punia Bangar S, Chaudhary V, Singh TP and Özogul F, Retrospecting the concept and industrial significance of LAB bacteriocins. Food Biosci 46:101607 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drider D, Fimland G, Héchard Y, McMullen LM and Prévost H, The continuing story of class IIa Bacteriocins. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 70:564–582 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negash AW and Tsehai BA, Current applications of Bacteriocin. Int J Microbiol 2020:1–7 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gálvez A, Abriouel H, López RL and Omar NB, Bacteriocin‐based strategies for food biopreservation. Int J Food Microbiol 120:51–70 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leal‐Sánchez MV, Ruiz‐Barba JL, Sánchez AH, Rejano L, Jiménez‐Díaz R and Garrido A, Fermentation profile and optimization of green olive fermentation using Lactobacillus plantarum LPCO10 as a starter culture. Food Microbiol 20:421–430 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐García E, Benítez‐Cabello A, Ramiro‐García J, Ladero V and Arroyo‐López FN, In silico evidence of the multifunctional features of Lactiplantibacillus pentosus LPG1, a natural fermenting agent isolated from table olive biofilms. Foods 12:938 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abriouel H, Caballero Gómez N, Manetsberger J and Benomar N, Dual effects of a bacteriocin‐producing Lactiplantibacillus pentosus CF‐6HA, isolated from fermented aloreña table olives, as potential probiotic and antimicrobial agent. Heliyon 10:e28408 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐García E, Benítez‐Cabello A, Tronchoni J and Arroyo‐López FN, Understanding the transcriptomic response of Lactiplantibacillus pentosus LPG1 during Spanish‐style green table olive fermentations. Front Microbiol 14:1264341 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Issaoui K, Khay EO, Abrini J, Zinebi S, Amajoud N, Senhaji NS et al., Molecular identification and antibiotic resistance of bacteriocinogenic lactic acid bacteria isolated from table olives. Arch Microbiol 203:597–607 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero‐Gil V, Medina E, Garrido‐Fernández A and Arroyo‐López FN, Foodborne pathogen survival in commercial Aloreña de Málaga table olive packaging. Front Microbiol 9:418310 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medina E, Brenes M, Romero C, Ramírez E and De Castro A, Survival of foodborne pathogenic bacteria in table olive brines. Food Control 34:719–724 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delgado A, Brito D, Peres C, Noé‐Arroyo F and Garrido‐Fernández A, Bacteriocin production by lactobacillus pentosus B96 can be expressed as a function of temperature and NaCl concentration. Food Microbiol 22:521–528 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H and Hoover D, Bacteriocins and their food applications. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 2:82–100 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Settanni L and Corsetti A, Application of bacteriocins in vegetable food biopreservation. Int J Food Microbiol 121:123–138 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ercolini D, La Storia A, Villani F and Mauriello G, Effect of a bacteriocin‐activated polythene film on Listeria monocytogenes as evaluated by viable staining and epifluorescence microscopy. J Appl Microbiol 100:765–772 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz‐Barba JL, Caballero‐Guerrero B, Maldonado‐Barragán A and Jiménez‐Díaz R, Coculture with specific bacteria enhances survival of Lactobacillus plantarum NC8, an autoinducer‐regulated bacteriocin producer, in olive fermentations. Food Microbiol 27:413–417 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahrami A, Delshadi R, Jafari SM and Williams L, Nanoencapsulated nisin: an engineered natural antimicrobial system for the food industry. Trends Food Sci Technol 94:20–31 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonatsou S, Tassou C, Panagou E and Nychas G‐J, Table olive fermentation using starter cultures with multifunctional potential. Microorganisms 5:30 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anagnostopoulos DA and Tsaltas D, Current status, recent advances, and main challenges on table olive fermentation: the present meets the future. Front Microbiol 12:797295 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Correa‐Galeote D, Ghomari I, Asehraou A and González‐López J, Revealing the bacterial abundance and diversity in brines from started Spanish‐style green table olives. LWT 160:113212 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Servili M, Settanni L, Veneziani G, Esposto S, Massitti O, Taticchi A et al., The use of Lactobacillus pentosus 1MO to shorten the debittering process time of black table olives (Cv. Itrana and Leccino): a pilot‐scale application. J Agric Food Chem 54:3869–3875 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez‐Gómez F, Romero‐Gil V, Arroyo‐López FN, Bautista Gallego J, García‐García P and Garrido‐Fernández A, Effect of packaging and storage conditions on microbial survival, physicochemical characteristics and colour of non‐thermally preserved green Spanish‐style Manzanilla olives. LWT‐Food Sci Technol 63:367–375 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadelli M, Zoumpopoulou G, Georgalaki M, Anastasiou R, Manolopoulou E, Lytra I et al., Evaluation of two lactic acid bacteria starter cultures for the fermentation of natural black table olives (Olea europaea L cv. Kalamon). Pol. J Microbiol 64:265–271 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blana VA, Grounta A, Tassou CC, Nychas G‐JE, &amp; Panagou EZ, Inoculated fermentation of green olives with potential probiotic Lactobacillus pentosus and Lactobacillus plantarum starter cultures isolated from industrially fermented olives. Food Microbiol, 38:208–218 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Argyri AA, Nisiotou AA, Pramateftaki P, Doulgeraki AI, Panagou EZ and Tassou CC, Preservation of green table olives fermented with lactic acid bacteria with probiotic potential under modified atmosphere packaging. LWT‐Food Sci Technol 62:783–790 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pino A, Vaccalluzzo A, Solieri L, Romeo FV, Todaro A, Caggia C et al., Effect of sequential inoculum of Beta‐glucosidase positive and probiotic strains on brine fermentation to obtain low salt Sicilian table olives. Front Microbiol 10:174 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cosmai L, Campanella D, De Angelis M, Summo C, Paradiso VM, Pasqualone A et al., Use of starter cultures for table olives fermentation as possibility to improve the quality of thermally stabilized olive‐based paste. LWT 90:381–388 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benítez‐Cabello A, Calero‐Delgado B, Rodríguez‐Gómez F, Bautista‐Gallego J, Garrido‐Fernández A, Jiménez‐Díaz R et al., The use of multifunctional yeast‐lactobacilli starter cultures improves fermentation performance of Spanish‐style green table olives. Food Microbiol 91:103497 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tufariello M, Anglana C, Crupi P, Virtuosi I, Fiume P, Di TB et al., Efficacy of yeast starters to drive and improve Picual, Manzanilla and Kalamàta table olive fermentation. J Sci Food Agric 99:2504–2512 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tufariello M, Durante M, Ramires FA, Grieco F, Tommasi L, Perbellini E et al., New process for production of fermented black table olives using selected autochthonous microbial resources. Front Microbiol 6:155674 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopes JLS, Nobre TM, Siano Á, Humpola V, Bossolan NRS, Zaniquelli MED et al., Disruption of Saccharomyces cerevisiae by Plantaricin 149 and investigation of its mechanism of action with biomembrane model systems. Biochim Biophys Acta 1788:2252–2258 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Reenen CA, Dicks LMT and Chikindas ML, Isolation, purification and partial characterization of plantaricin 423, a bacteriocin produced by Lactobacillus plantarum. J Appl Microbiol 84:1131–1137 (1998).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavermicocca P, Angiolillo L, Lonigro SL, Valerio F, Bevilacqua A, Perricone M et al., Lactobacillus plantarum 5BG survives during refrigerated storage bio‐preserving packaged Spanish‐style table olives (cv. Bella di Cerignola). Front Microbiol 9:889 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panagou EZ, Schillinger U, Franz CMAP and Nychas GJE, Microbiological and biochemical profile of cv. Conservolea naturally black olives during controlled fermentation with selected strains of lactic acid bacteria. Food Microbiol 25:348–358 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández A, Martín A, Córdoba MG, Benito MJ, Aranda E and Pérez‐Nevado F, Determination of killer activity in yeasts isolated from the elaboration of seasoned green table olives. Int J Food Microbiol 121:178–188 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parafati L, Palmeri R, Pitino I and Restuccia C, Killer yeasts isolated from olive brines: technological and probiotic aptitudes. Food Microbiol 103:103950 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Passoth V, Olstorpe M and Schnürer J, Past, present and future research directions with Pichia anomala. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek 99:121–125 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bevilacqua A, Corbo MR and Sinigaglia M, Selection of yeasts as starter cultures for table olives: a step‐by‐step procedure. Front Microbiol 3:27312 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bevilacqua A, De Stefano F, Augello S, Pignatiello S, Sinigaglia M and Corbo MR, Biotechnological innovations for table olives. Int J Food Sci Nutr 66:127–131 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doulgeraki AI, Hondrodimou O, Iliopoulos V and Panagou EZ, Lactic acid bacteria and yeast heterogeneity during aerobic and modified atmosphere packaging storage of natural black Conservolea olives in polyethylene pouches. Food Control 26:49–57 (2012).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>