<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39245918</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>AI-based R&amp;D for frozen and thawed meat: Research progress and future prospects.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70016</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70016</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70016</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Frozen and thawed meat plays an important role in stabilizing the meat supply chain and extending the shelf life of meat. However, traditional methods of research and development (R&amp;D) struggle to meet rising demands for quality, nutritional value, innovation, safety, production efficiency, and sustainability. Frozen and thawed meat faces specific challenges, including quality degradation during thawing. Artificial intelligence (AI) has emerged as a promising solution to tackle these challenges in R&amp;D of frozen and thawed meat. AI's capabilities in perception, judgment, and execution demonstrate significant potential in problem-solving and task execution. This review outlines the architecture of applying AI technology to the R&amp;D of frozen and thawed meat, aiming to make AI better implement and deliver solutions. In comparison to traditional R&amp;D methods, the current research progress and promising application prospects of AI in this field are comprehensively summarized, focusing on its role in addressing key challenges such as rapid optimization of thawing process. AI has already demonstrated success in areas such as product development, production optimization, risk management, and quality control for frozen and thawed meat. In the future, AI-based R&amp;D for frozen and thawed meat will also play an important role in promoting personalization, intelligent production, and sustainable development. However, challenges remain, including the need for high-quality data, complex implementation, volatile processes, and environmental considerations. To realize the full potential of AI that can be integrated into R&amp;D of frozen and thawed meat, further research is needed to develop more robust and reliable AI solutions, such as general AI, explainable AI, and green AI.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qiao</LastName><ForeName>Jiangshan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Province International Joint Laboratory on Fresh Food Smart Processing and Quality Monitoring, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Min</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8107-5212</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>China General Chamber of Commerce Key Laboratory on Fresh Food Processing &amp; Preservation, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Dayuan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Province International Joint Laboratory on Fresh Food Smart Processing and Quality Monitoring, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mujumdar</LastName><ForeName>Arun S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bioresource Engineering, Macdonald Campus, McGill University, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chu</LastName><ForeName>Chaoyang</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Golden Monkey Food Co., Ltd, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>JUFSTR20180205</GrantID><Agency>National First-Class Discipline Program of Food Science and Technology</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>FMZ202003</GrantID><Agency>Jiangsu Province Key Laboratory Project of Advanced Food Manufacturing Equipment and Technology</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>BE2018329</GrantID><Agency>Jiangsu Province (China) Agricultural Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001185" MajorTopicYN="Y">Artificial Intelligence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008460" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meat</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005615" MajorTopicYN="N">Freezing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005519" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Preservation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">applications</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">artificial intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">freezing and thawing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meat</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">research and development</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39245918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abie, S. M., Martinsen, Ø. G., Egelandsdal, B., Hou, J., Bjerke, F., Mason, A., &amp; Münch, D. (2021). Feasibility of using electrical impedance spectroscopy for assessing biological cell damage during freezing and thawing. Sensors, 21(12), 4129. https://doi.org/10.3390/s21124129</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrawal, R., Majumdar, A., Kumar, A., &amp; Luthra, S. (2023). Integration of artificial intelligence in sustainable manufacturing: Current status and future opportunities. Operations Management Research, 16(4), 1720–1741. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12063‐023‐00383‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Isyrofie, A. I. F., Kashif, M., Aji, A. K., Aidatuzzahro, N., Rahmatillah, A., Winarno, Susilo, Y., Syahrom, A., &amp; Astuti, S. D. (2022). Odor clustering using a gas sensor array system of chicken meat based on temperature variations and storage time. Sensing and Bio‐Sensing Research, 37, 100508. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbsr.2022.100508</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amani, M. A., &amp; Sarkodie, S. A. (2022). Mitigating spread of contamination in meat supply chain management using deep learning. Scientific Reports, 12(1), 5037. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐022‐08993‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>An, J., Zhang, M., &amp; Lu, Q. (2007). Changes in some quality indexes in fresh‐cut green asparagus pretreated with aqueous ozone and subsequent modified atmosphere packaging. Journal of Food Engineering, 78(1), 340–344. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2005.10.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora, M., &amp; Mangipudi, P. (2021). A computer vision‐based method for classification of red meat quality after nitrosamine appendage. International Journal of Computational Intelligence and Applications, 20(01), 2150005. https://doi.org/10.1142/s146902682150005x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bao, X., Leng, J., Mao, J., &amp; Chen, B. (2022). Cutting of sheep carcass using 3D point cloud with dual‐robot system. International Journal of Agricultural and Biological Engineering, 15(5), 163–171. https://doi.org/10.25165/j.ijabe.20221505.7161</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brahma, S., Kavasseri, R., Cao, H., Chaudhuri, N. R., Alexopoulos, T., &amp; Cui, Y. (2017). Real‐time identification of dynamic events in power systems using PMU data, and potential applications—Models, promises, and challenges. IEEE Transactions on Power Delivery, 32(1), 294–301. https://doi.org/10.1109/tpwrd.2016.2590961</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, D., Wu, P., Wang, K., Wang, S., Ji, X., Shen, Q., Yu, Y., Qiu, X., Xu, X., Liu, Y., &amp; Tang, G. (2022). Combining computer vision score and conventional meat quality traits to estimate the intramuscular fat content using machine learning in pigs. Meat Science, 185, 108727. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2021.108727</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, P.‐Y., &amp; Das, P. (2023). AI maintenance: A robustness perspective. Computer, 56(2), 48–56. https://doi.org/10.1109/mc.2022.3218005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, J., Sun, J., Yao, K., &amp; Dai, C. (2023a). Generalized and hetero two‐dimensional correlation analysis of hyperspectral imaging combined with three‐dimensional convolutional neural network for evaluating lipid oxidation in pork. Food Control, 153, 109940. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.109940</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, J., Sun, J., Yao, K., Xu, M., &amp; Dai, C. (2023b). Multi‐task convolutional neural network for simultaneous monitoring of lipid and protein oxidative damage in frozen‐thawed pork using hyperspectral imaging. Meat Science, 201, 109196. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2023.109196</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinu, &amp; Bansal, U. (2023). Explainable AI: To reveal the logic of black‐box models. New Generation Computing, 42(1), 53–87. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00354‐022‐00201‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chongwatpol, J. (2024). A technological, data‐driven design journey for artificial intelligence (AI) initiatives. Education and Information Technologies, 1, 24. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10639‐024‐12459‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corradini, M. G. (2018). Shelf life of food products: From open labeling to real‐time measurements. Annual Review of Food Science and Technology, 9, 251–269. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev‐food‐030117‐012433</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darma, P. N., &amp; Takei, M. (2021). High‐speed and accurate meat composition imaging by mechanically‐flexible electrical impedance tomography with k‐nearest neighbor and fuzzy k‐means machine learning approaches. IEEE Access, 9, 38792–38801. https://doi.org/10.1109/access.2021.3064315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Melo, M. J., Gonçalves, D. N., Gomes, M. D. N. B., Faria, G., Silva, J. D. A., Ramos, A. P. M., Osco, L. P., Furuya, M. T. G., Marcato Junior, J., &amp; Gonçalves, W. N. (2022). Automatic segmentation of cattle rib‐eye area in ultrasound images using the UNet++ deep neural network. Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, 195, 106818. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compag.2022.106818</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng, C., Fang, X., Wang, X., &amp; Law, K. (2022). Software orchestrated and hardware accelerated artificial intelligence: Toward low latency edge computing. IEEE Wireless Communications, 29(4), 110–117. https://doi.org/10.1109/mwc.005.2100531</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Derraz, B., Breda, G., Kaempf, C., Baenke, F., Cotte, F., Reiche, K., Köhl, U., Kather, J. N., Eskenazy, D., &amp; Gilbert, S. (2024). New regulatory thinking is needed for AI‐based personalised drug and cell therapies in precision oncology. NPJ Precision Oncology, 8(1), 23. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41698‐024‐00517‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, H., Tian, J., Yu, W., Wilson, D. I., Young, B. R., Cui, X., Xin, X., Wang, Z., &amp; Li, W. (2023). The application of artificial intelligence and big data in the food industry. Foods, 12(24), 4511. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12244511</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dini, P., Diana, L., Elhanashi, A., &amp; Saponara, S. (2024). Overview of AI‐models and tools in embedded IIoT applications. Electronics, 13(12), 2322. https://doi.org/10.3390/electronics13122322</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dourou, D., Grounta, A., Argyri, A. A., Froutis, G., Tsakanikas, P., Nychas, G.‐J. E., Doulgeraki, A. I., Chorianopoulos, N. G., &amp; Tassou, C. C. (2021). Rapid microbial quality assessment of chicken liver inoculated or not with salmonella using FTIR spectroscopy and machine learning. Frontiers in Microbiology, 11, 623788. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2020.623788</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan, X., Zhang, M., &amp; Mujumdar, A. S. (2007). Study on a combination drying technique of sea cucumber. Drying Technology, 25(12), 2011–2019. https://doi.org/10.1080/07373930701728497</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Karam, S. A., Ferrand, M., Astruc, T., &amp; Germond, A. (2023). Evaluation and prediction of salt effects on pig muscle by deep UV and machine learning. Meat Science, 199, 109136. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2023.109136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enériz, D., Medrano, N., &amp; Calvo, B. (2021). An FPGA‐based machine learning tool for in‐situ food quality tracking using sensor fusion. Biosensors, 11(10), 366. https://doi.org/10.3390/bios11100366</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fengou, L.‐C., Mporas, I., Spyrelli, E., Lianou, A., &amp; Nychas, G.‐J. (2020). Estimation of the microbiological quality of meat using rapid and non‐invasive spectroscopic sensors. IEEE Access, 8, 106614–106628. https://doi.org/10.1109/access.2020.3000690</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, Y., Cao, S., Yang, L., &amp; Li, Z. (2022). Flavor formation based on lipid in meat and meat products: A review. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 46(12), e14439. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.14439</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia‐Perez, A., Miñón, R., Torre‐Bastida, A. I., &amp; Zulueta‐Guerrero, E. (2023). Analysing edge computing devices for the deployment of embedded AI. Sensors (Basel), 23(23), 9495. https://doi.org/10.3390/s23239495</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghebrehiwet, I., Zaki, N., Damseh, R., &amp; Mohamad, M. S. (2024). Revolutionizing personalized medicine with generative AI: A systematic review. Artificial Intelligence Review, 57(5), 128. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10462‐024‐10768‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giannakourou, M., &amp; Taoukis, P. (2020). Holistic approach to the uncertainty in shelf life prediction of frozen foods at dynamic cold chain conditions. Foods, 9(6), 714. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods9060714</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gredell, D. A., Schroeder, A. R., Belk, K. E., Broeckling, C. D., Heuberger, A. L., Kim, S.‐Y., King, D. A., Shackelford, S. D., Sharp, J. L., Wheeler, T. L., Woerner, D. R., &amp; Prenni, J. E. (2019). Comparison of machine learning algorithms for predictive modeling of beef attributes using rapid evaporative ionization mass spectrometry (REIMS) data. Scientific Reports, 9(1), 5721. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐019‐40927‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenwood, P. L., Gardner, G. E., &amp; Ferguson, D. M. (2018). Current situation and future prospects for the Australian beef industry—A review. Journal of Animal Sciences, 31(7), 992–1006. https://doi.org/10.5713/ajas.18.0090</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagras, H. (2018). Toward human‐understandable, explainable AI. Computer, 51(9), 28–36. https://doi.org/10.1109/MC.2018.3620965</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He, H.‐J., Wang, Y., Ou, X., Ma, H., Liu, H., &amp; Yan, J. (2023). Rapid determination of chemical compositions in chicken flesh by mining hyperspectral data. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis, 116, 105069. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfca.2022.105069</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henchion, M. M., &amp; Shirsath, A. P. (2022). Developing and implementing a transdisciplinary framework for future pathways in the circular bioeconomy: The case of the red meat industry. Journal of Cleaner Production, 380, 134845. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.134845</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hicks, T. M., Knowles, S. O., &amp; Farouk, M. M. (2018). Global provisioning of red meat for flexitarian diets. Frontiers and Nutrition, 5, 50. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2018.00050</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosseinpour, S., Ilkhchi, A. H., &amp; Aghbashlo, M. (2019). An intelligent machine vision‐based smartphone app for beef quality evaluation. Journal of Food Engineering, 248, 9–22. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2018.12.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, R., Sun, D.‐W., &amp; Tian, Y. (2024). Green natural deep eutectic agents (GNDEAs) for biocryopreservation: syntheses, properties and advanced applications. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 151, 104590. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2024.104590</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, R., Zhang, M., Jiang, Q., &amp; Law, C. L. (2023). A novel infrared and microwave alternate thawing method for frozen pork: Effect on thawing rate and products quality. Meat Science, 198, 109084. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2022.109084</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, R., Zhang, M., Liu, W., Mujumdar, A. S., &amp; Bai, B. (2022c). Novel synergistic freezing methods and technologies for enhanced food product quality: A critical review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 21(2), 1979–2001. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12919</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, R., Zhang, M., &amp; Mujumdar, A. S. (2022a). Application of infrared and microwave heating prior to freezing of pork: Effect on frozen meat quality. Meat Science, 189, 108811. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2022.108811</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, R., Zhang, M., &amp; Mujumdar, A. S. (2022b). Novel assistive technologies for efficient freezing of pork based on high voltage electric field and static magnetic field: A comparative study. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 80, 103087. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2022.103087</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, L.‐L., Zhang, M., Mujumdar, A. S., Sun, D.‐F., Tan, G.‐W., &amp; Tang, S. (2009). Studies on decreasing energy consumption for a freeze‐drying process of apple slices. Drying Technology, 27(9), 938–946. https://doi.org/10.1080/07373930902901844</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Y., Zhang, X., Liu, S., Wang, R., Guo, J., Chen, Y., &amp; Ma, X. (2023). Wireless food‐freshness monitoring and storage‐time prediction based on ammonia‐sensitive MOF@SnS2 PN heterostructure and machine learning. Chemical Engineering Journal, 458, 141364. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cej.2023.141364</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janiesch, C., Zschech, P., &amp; Heinrich, K. (2021). Machine learning and deep learning. Electronic Markets, 31(3), 685–695. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12525‐021‐00475‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, Q., Zhang, M., &amp; Mujumdar, A. S. (2022). Application of physical field‐assisted freezing and thawing to mitigate damage to frozen food. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 103(5), 2223–2238. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.12260</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, Q., Zhang, M., Mujumdar, A. S., &amp; Gan, S. (2023). Effects of magnetic field‐assisted liquid carbon dioxide spray freezing on the quality of honeydew melon. Food Chemistry, 417, 135850. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.135850</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiménez, H., Aribisala, A., Cavalcante, C., Do, P., &amp; Lee, C. G. (2023). A deep reinforcement learning‐based maintenance optimization for vacuum packaging machines considering product quality degradation. Journal of Food Process Engineering, 46(11), e14429. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpe.14429</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson, K. B., Wei, W.‐Q., Weeraratne, D., Frisse, M. E., Misulis, K., Rhee, K., Zhao, J., &amp; Snowdon, J. L. (2021). Precision medicine, AI, and the future of personalized health care. Clinical and Translation Science, 14(1), 86–93. https://doi.org/10.1111/cts.12884</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamkar, M., Leonard, K. C., Ferrer, I., Loo, S. C. J., Biddinger, E. J., Brady, D., Carrier, D. J., Gathergood, N., Han, H., Hermans, I., Hii, K. K. M., Hwang, B. J., Loh, W., Meier, M. A. R., Marr, A. C., Newton, G. N., Srubar, W. V., Yan, N., Tam, M. K. C., … Serrano, J. F. (2024). Artificial intelligence (AI) for sustainable resource management and chemical processes. ACS Sustainable Chemistry &amp; Engineering, 12(8), 2924–2926. https://doi.org/10.1021/acssuschemeng.4c01004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapovskiy, B. R., Pchelkina, V. A., &amp; Dydykin, A. S. (2023). Application of fuzzy and clear mathematical models in hybrid control of the process of single‐stage mincing of frozen meat. Engineering Technologies and Systems, 4(33), 558–584. https://doi.org/10.15507/2658‐4123.033.202304.558‐584</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, D.‐E., Nando, Y. A., &amp; Chung, W.‐Y. (2023). Battery‐free pork freshness estimation based on colorimetric sensors and machine learning. Applied Sciences, 13(8), 4896. https://doi.org/10.3390/app13084896</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, Y. G., Lee, S., Son, J., Bae, H., &amp; Chung, B. D. (2020). Multi‐agent system and reinforcement learning approach for distributed intelligence in a flexible smart manufacturing system. Journal of Manufacturing Systems, 57, 440–450. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmsy.2020.11.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko, E., Jeong, K., Oh, H., Park, Y., Choi, J., &amp; Lee, E. (2023). A deep learning‐based framework for predicting pork preference. Current Research in Food Science, 6, 100495. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.crfs.2023.100495</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovalenko, I., Barton, K., Moyne, J., &amp; Tilbury, D. M. (2023). Opportunities and challenges to integrate artificial intelligence into manufacturing systems: Thoughts from a panel discussion [opinion]. IEEE Robotics &amp; Automation Magazine, 30(2), 109–112. https://doi.org/10.1109/mra.2023.3262464</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kucha, C. T., Liu, L., Ngadi, M., &amp; Gariépy, C. (2023). Hyperspectral imaging and chemometrics assessment of intramuscular fat in pork Longissimus thoracic et lumborum primal cut. Food Control, 145, 109379. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109379</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni, P., Mahadevappa, M., &amp; Chilakamarri, S. (2022). The emergence of artificial intelligence in cardiology: Current and future applications. Current Cardiology Reviews, 18(3), e191121198124. https://doi.org/10.2174/1573403x17666211119102220</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, P., Abubakar, A. A., Verma, A. K., Umaraw, P., Adewale Ahmed, M., Mehta, N., Nizam Hayat, M., Kaka, U., &amp; Sazili, A. Q. (2022). New insights in improving sustainability in meat production: Opportunities and challenges. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 63(33), 11830–11858. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2022.2096562</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, S., Datta, S., Singh, V., Singh, S. K., &amp; Sharma, R. (2024). Opportunities and challenges in data‐centric AI. IEEE Access, 12, 33173–33189. https://doi.org/10.1109/access.2024.3369417</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurrek, P., Zoghlami, F., Jocas, M., Stoelen, M., &amp; Salehi, V. (2020). Q‐model: An artificial intelligence based methodology for the development of autonomous robots. Journal of Computing and Information Science in Engineering, 20(6), 1–16. https://doi.org/10.1115/1.4046992</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lakehal, S., &amp; Lakehal, B. (2023). Storage time prediction of frozen meat using artificial neural network modeling with color values. Revista Científica De La Facultad De Ciencias Veterinarias, XXXIII(2), 1–6. https://doi.org/10.52973/rcfcv‐e33268</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lan, X., &amp; Chen, H. (2023). Simulation analysis of production scheduling algorithm for intelligent manufacturing cell based on artificial intelligence technology. Soft Computing, 27(9), 6007–6017. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00500‐023‐08074‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, D., Chen, M.‐H., &amp; Lai, G.‐W. (2022). Achieving energy savings through artificial‐intelligence‐assisted fault detection and diagnosis: Case study on refrigeration systems. Case Studies in Thermal Engineering, 40, 102499. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.csite.2022.102499</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, H.‐J., Koh, Y. J., Kim, Y.‐K., Lee, S. H., Lee, J. H., &amp; Seo, D. W. (2022). MSENet: Marbling score estimation network for automated assessment of Korean beef. Meat Science, 188, 108784. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2022.108784</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, A., Li, C., Gao, M., Yang, S., Liu, R., Chen, W., &amp; Xu, K. (2021). Beef cut classification using multispectral imaging and machine learning method. Frontiers in Nutrition, 8, 755007. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2021.755007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Ye, Z., &amp; Zhang, C. (2022). Study on the interaction between big data and artificial intelligence. Systems Research and Behavioral Science, 39(3), 641–648. https://doi.org/10.1002/sres.2878</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Liu, D., Pu, Y., &amp; Zhong, Y. (2023). Recent advance of intelligent packaging aided by artificial intelligence for monitoring food freshness. Foods, 12(15), 2976. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12152976</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, Y., Ma, J., Sun, D.‐W, Cheng, J.‐H., &amp; Wang, Q. (2023). A pH‐responsive colourimetric sensor array based on machine learning for real‐time monitoring of beef freshness. Food Control, 150, 109729. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.109729</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Guo, C., &amp; Er, M. J. (2022). Robotic 3‐D laser‐guided approach for efficient cutting of porcine belly. IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics, 27(5), 2963–2972. https://doi.org/10.1109/tmech.2021.3129911</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mason, A., Romanov, D., Cordova‐Lopez, L. E., Ross, S., &amp; Korostynska, O. (2022). Smart knife: Technological advances towards smart cutting tools in meat industry automation. Sensor Review, 42(1), 155–163. https://doi.org/10.1108/sr‐09‐2021‐0315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mavani, N. R., Ali, J. M., Othman, S., Hussain, M. A., Hashim, H., &amp; Rahman, N. A. (2021). Application of artificial intelligence in food industry—A guideline. Food Engineering Reviews, 14(1), 134–175. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12393‐021‐09290‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mungoli, N. (2023). Scalable, distributed AI frameworks: leveraging cloud computing for enhanced deep learning performance and efficiency. arXiv e‐prints, arXiv: 2304.13738. https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13738</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paraschos, P. D., Koulinas, G. K., &amp; Koulouriotis, D. E. (2023). A reinforcement learning/ad‐hoc planning and scheduling mechanism for flexible and sustainable manufacturing systems. Flexible Services and Manufacturing Journal. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10696‐023‐09496‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parastar, H., van Kollenburg, G., Weesepoel, Y., van den Doel, A., Buydens, L., &amp; Jansen, J. (2020). Integration of handheld NIR and machine learning to “measure &amp; monitor” chicken meat authenticity. Food Control, 112, 107149. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S., Hong, S.‐J., Kim, S., Ryu, J., Roh, S., &amp; Kim, G. (2023). Classification of fresh and frozen‐thawed beef using a hyperspectral imaging sensor and machine learning. Agriculture, 13(4), 918. https://doi.org/10.3390/agriculture13040918</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penning, B. W., Snelling, W. M., &amp; Woodward‐Greene, M. J. (2020). Machine learning in the assessment of meat quality. IT Professional, 22(3), 39–41. https://doi.org/10.1109/mitp.2020.2986123</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phuhongsung, P., Zhang, M., &amp; Devahastin, S. (2020). Investigation on 3D printing ability of soybean protein isolate gels and correlations with their rheological and textural properties via LF‐NMR spectroscopic characteristics. LWT, 122, 109019. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pounds, K., Bao, H., Luo, Y., De, J., Schneider, K., Correll, M., &amp; Tong, Z. (2022). Real‐time and rapid food quality monitoring using smart sensory films with image analysis and machine learning. ACS Food Science &amp; Technology, 2(7), 1123–1134. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsfoodscitech.2c00124</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, S., Berry, D. P., Roantree, M., Onibonoje, O., Gualano, L., Scriney, M., &amp; Mccarren, A. (2021). Using artificial intelligence to automate meat cut identification from the semimembranosus muscle on beef boning lines. Journal of Animal Science, 99(12), 1–13. https://doi.org/10.1093/jas/skab319</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian, C., Murphy, S. I., Orsi, R. H., &amp; Wiedmann, M. (2023). How can AI help improve food safety? Annual Review of Food Science and Technology, 14(1), 517–538. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev‐food‐060721‐013815</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmani, A. M., Yousefpoor, E., Yousefpoor, M. S., Mehmood, Z., Haider, A., Hosseinzadeh, M., &amp; Ali Naqvi, R. (2021). Machine learning (ML) in medicine: Review, applications, and challenges. Mathematics, 9(22), 2970. https://doi.org/10.3390/math9222970</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raman, R., Pattnaik, D., Lathabai, H. H., Kumar, C., Govindan, K., &amp; Nedungadi, P. (2024). Green and sustainable AI research: An integrated thematic and topic modeling analysis. Journal of Big Data, 11(1), 55. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40537‐024‐00920‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramirez‐Asis, E., Vilchez‐Carcamo, J., Thakar, C. M., Phasinam, K., Kassanuk, T., &amp; Naved, M. (2022). A review on role of artificial intelligence in food processing and manufacturing industry. Materials Today: Proceedings, 51, 2462–2465. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matpr.2021.11.616</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell, S., &amp; Norvig, P. (2004). Artificial intelligence‐ A modern approach. Tsinghua University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeghi, R. K., Ojha, D., Kaur, P., Mahto, R. V., &amp; Dhir, A. (2024). Explainable artificial intelligence and agile decision‐making in supply chain cyber resilience. Decision Support Systems, 180, 114194. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dss.2024.114194</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sak, J., &amp; Suchodolska, M. (2021). Artificial intelligence in nutrients science research: A review. Nutrients, 13(2), 322. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13020322</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez, C. N., Orvañanos‐Guerrero, M. T., Domínguez‐Soberanes, J., &amp; Álvarez‐Cisneros, Y. M. (2023). Analysis of beef quality according to color changes using computer vision and white‐box machine learning techniques. Heliyon, 9(7), e17976. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e17976</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarker, I. H. (2021a). Deep learning: A comprehensive overview on techniques, taxonomy, applications and research directions. SN Computer Science, 2(6), 420. https://doi.org/10.1007/s42979‐021‐00815‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarker, I. H. (2021b). Machine learning: Algorithms, real‐world applications and research directions. SN Computer Science, 2(3), 16000. https://doi.org/10.1007/s42979‐021‐00592‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sempionatto, J. R., Montiel, V. R.‐V., Vargas, E., Teymourian, H., &amp; Wang, J. (2021). Wearable and mobile sensors for personalized nutrition. ACS Sensors, 6(5), 1745–1760. https://doi.org/10.1021/acssensors.1c00553</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, S., Gahlawat, V. K., Rahul, K., Mor, R. S., &amp; Malik, M. (2021). Sustainable innovations in the food industry through artificial intelligence and big data analytics. Logistics, 5(4), 66. https://doi.org/10.3390/logistics5040066</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, Y., Wang, X., Borhan, M. S, Young, J., Newman, D., Berg, E., &amp; Sun, X. (2021). A review on meat quality evaluation methods based on non‐destructive computer vision and artificial intelligence technologies. Food Science of Animal Resources, 41(4), 563–588. https://doi.org/10.5851/kosfa.2021.e25</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silveira, R. M. F., Lima, D. F., Camelo, B. V., Mcmanus, C., Da Silva, V. J., Ferreira, J., Costa, H. H. A., Dos Santos Dias, C. T., Contreras‐Castillo, C. J., Paveloski, A., De Vecchi, L. B., Sales, A. P., Sarries, G. A., &amp; Landim, A. V. (2023). Machine learning applied to understand perceptions, habits and preferences of lamb meat consumers in the Brazilian semi‐arid region. Small Ruminant Research, 227, 107088. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smallrumres.2023.107088</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su, W., Xu, G., He, Z., Machica, I. K., Quimno, V., Du, Y., &amp; Kong, Y. (2023). Cloud‐edge computing‐based ICICOS framework for industrial automation and artificial intelligence: A survey. Journal of Circuits, Systems and Computers, 32(10), 2350168. https://doi.org/10.1142/S0218126623501682</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swanson, A., &amp; Gowen, A. (2022). Detection of previously frozen poultry through plastic lidding film using portable visible spectral imaging (443–726 NM). Poultry Science, 101(2), 101578. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psj.2021.101578</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tadini, C. C., &amp; Gut, J. A. W. (2022). The importance of heating unit operations in the food industry to obtain safe and high‐quality products. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, 853638. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.853638</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taneja, A., Nair, G., Joshi, M., Sharma, S., Sharma, S., Jambrak, A. R., Roselló‐Soto, E., Barba, F. J., Castagnini, J. M., Leksawasdi, N., &amp; Phimolsiripol, Y. (2023). Artificial intelligence: Implications for the agri‐food sector. Agronomy, 13(5), 1397. https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy13051397</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, F., Zhang, M., &amp; Yu, H.‐Q. (2007). Effect of vacuum cooling on physiological changes in the antioxidant system of mushroom under different storage conditions. Journal of Food Engineering, 79(4), 1302–1309. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2006.04.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tóth, Z., Caruana, R., Gruber, T., &amp; Loebbecke, C. (2022). The dawn of the AI robots: Towards a new framework of AI robot accountability. Journal of Business Ethics, 178(4), 895–916. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10551‐022‐05050‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verdecchia, R., Sallou, J., &amp; Cruz, L. (2023). A systematic review of Green AI. WIREs Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery, 13(4), e1507. https://doi.org/10.1002/widm.1507</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, H., Wang, X. D., Liu, D., Wang, Y., Li, X., &amp; Duan, J. (2019). Evaluation of beef flavor attribute based on sensor array in tandem with support vector machines. Journal of Food Measurement and Characterization, 13(4), 2663–2671. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11694‐019‐00187‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Xia, L., Liu, H., Zhao, C., Ming, S., &amp; Wu, J. (2024). Colorimetric microneedle sensor using deep learning algorithm for meat freshness monitoring. Chemical Engineering Journal, 481, 148474. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cej.2023.148474</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Ting, J. S. L., &amp; Ip, W. H. (2013). Design of supply‐chain pedigree interactive dynamic explore (SPIDER) for food safety and implementation of hazard analysis and critical control points (HACCPs). Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, 90, 14–23. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compag.2012.10.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M., &amp; Li, X. (2024). Application of artificial intelligence techniques in meat processing: A review. Journal of Food Process Engineering, 47(3), e14590. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpe.14590</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Zhang, M., &amp; Mujumdar, A S. (2010a). Effect of food ingredient on microwave freeze drying of instant vegetable soup. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 43(7), 1144–1150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2010.03.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Zhang, M., &amp; Mujumdar, A S. (2010b). Effect of osmotic dehydration on microwave freeze‐drying characteristics and quality of potato chips. Drying Technology, 28(6), 798–806. https://doi.org/10.1080/07373937.2010.482700</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, X., Zhang, M., &amp; Bhandari, B. (2019). A novel infrared freeze drying (IRFD) technology to lower the energy consumption and keep the quality of Cordyceps militaris. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 54, 34–42. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2019.03.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, X.‐F., Zhang, M., Adhikari, B., &amp; Sun, J. (2017). Recent developments in novel freezing and thawing technologies applied to foods. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 57(17), 3620–3631. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2015.1132670</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, A., Sun, D.‐W, Xu, Z., &amp; Zhu, Z. (2015). Rapid detection of frozen pork quality without thawing by vis–NIR hyperspectral imaging technique. Talanta, 139, 208–215. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2015.02.027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xin, X., Jiang, Q., Li, S., Gong, S., &amp; Chen, K. (2021). Energy‐efficient scheduling for a permutation flow shop with variable transportation time using an improved discrete whale swarm optimization. Journal of Cleaner Production, 293, 126121. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.126121</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong, Y., Li, Y., Wang, C., Shi, H., Wang, S., Yong, C., Gong, Y., Zhang, W., &amp; Zou, X. (2023). Non‐destructive detection of chicken freshness based on electronic nose technology and transfer learning. Agriculture, 13(2), 496. https://doi.org/10.3390/agriculture13020496</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, T., Zhao, W., Cai, L., Shi, X., &amp; Wang, X. (2023). Lightweight saliency detection method for real‐time localization of livestock meat bones. Scientific Reports, 13(1), 4510. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐023‐31551‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, W., Wang, J., Deng, Y., Li, J., Yan, T., Zhao, S., Yang, X., Xu, E., Wang, W., &amp; Liu, D. (2022). Advanced cutting techniques for solid food: Mechanisms, applications, modeling approaches, and future perspectives. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 21(2), 1568–1597. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12896</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, R., Wang, Z., &amp; Chen, J. (2021). An integrated approach of mechanistic‐modeling and machine‐learning for thickness optimization of frozen microwaveable foods. Foods, 10(4), 763. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10040763</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, Q., Zhang, M., Mujumdar, A. S., &amp; Li, J. (2024). AI‐based additive manufacturing for future food: Potential applications, challenges and possible solutions. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 92, 103599. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2024.103599</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Liu, G., Li, Y., Guo, M., Pu, F., &amp; Wang, H. (2022). Rapid identification of lamb freshness grades using visible and near‐infrared spectroscopy (vis‐NIR). Journal of Food Composition and Analysis, 111, 104590. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfca.2022.104590</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Zhang, M., Shan, L., &amp; Fang, Z. (2007). Microwave‐vacuum heating parameters for processing savory crisp bighead carp (Hypophthalmichthys nobilis) slices. Journal of Food Engineering, 79(3), 885–891. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2006.03.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., &amp; Zhang, L. (2022). Artificial intelligence for remote sensing data analysis: A review of challenges and opportunities. IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Magazine, 10(2), 270–294. https://doi.org/10.1109/mgrs.2022.3145854</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., Zhang, M., &amp; Mujumdar, A. S. (2021). Technological innovations or advancement in detecting frozen and thawed meat quality: A review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 63(11), 1483–1499. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2021.1964434</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M., Tang, J., Mujumdar, A. S., &amp; Wang, S. (2006). Trends in microwave‐related drying of fruits and vegetables. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 17(10), 524–534. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2006.04.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M., Zhan, Z. G., Wang, S. J., &amp; Tang, J. M. (2008). Extending the shelf‐life of asparagus spears with a compressed mix of argon and xenon gases. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 41(4), 686–691. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2007.04.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M., Zhang, C.‐J., &amp; Shrestha, S. (2005). Study on the preparation technology of superfine ground powder of Agrocybe chaxingu Huang. Journal of Food Engineering, 67(3), 333–337. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2004.04.036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, R., Realini, C. E., Kim, Y. H. B, &amp; Farouk, M. M. (2023). Challenges and processing strategies to produce high quality frozen meat. Meat Science, 205, 109311. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2023.109311</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, S., Chen, Y., Liu, W., Liu, B., &amp; Zhou, X. (2023). Marbling‐net: A novel intelligent framework for pork marbling segmentation using images from smartphones. Sensors, 23(11), 5135. https://doi.org/10.3390/s23115135</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, J., &amp; Gómez Fariñas, B. (2022). Artificial intelligence and sustainable decisions. European Business Organization Law Review, 24(1), 1–39. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40804‐022‐00262‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, X., Chai, C., Li, G., &amp; Sun, J. (2022). Database meets artificial intelligence: A survey. IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering, 34(3), 1096–1116. https://doi.org/10.1109/tkde.2020.2994641</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, J., Wang, L., &amp; Han, X. (2022). Safety and performance, why not both? Bi‐objective optimized model compression toward AI software deployment. In. Proceedings of the 37th IEEE/ACM international conference on automated software engineering, 50, 376–390.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>