<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39240488</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2161-3311</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current nutrition reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Nutr Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effects of Caloric Restriction and Intermittent Fasting and Their Combined Exercise on Cognitive Functioning: A Review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s13668-024-00570-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE OF REVIEW" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The impact of dietary habits on cognitive function is increasingly gaining attention. The review is to discuss how caloric restriction (CR) and intermittent fasting (IF) can enhance cognitive function in healthy states through multiple pathways that interact with one another. Secondly, to explore the effects of CR and IF on cognitive function in conditions of neurodegenerative diseases, obesity diabetes and aging, as well as potential synergistic effects in combination with exercise to prevent cognitively related neurodegenerative diseases.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RECENT FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">With age, the human brain ages and develops corresponding neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease, and epilepsy, which in turn trigger cognitive impairment. Recent research indicates that the impact of diet and exercise on cognitive function is increasingly gaining attention. The benefits of exercise for cognitive function and brain plasticity are numerous, and future research can examine the efficacy of particular dietary regimens during physical activity when combined with diet which can prevent cognitive decline.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Junming</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0002-4254-2089</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Key Laboratory of Food Quality and Safety of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, 510642, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rang</LastName><ForeName>Yifeng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1356-1563</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Key Laboratory of Food Quality and Safety of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, 510642, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Chunhong</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4354-9151</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China. liuch@scau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Key Laboratory of Food Quality and Safety of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, 510642, China. liuch@scau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Nutr Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101587480</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2161-3311</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Caloric restriction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cognitive</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Exercise</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intermittent fasting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neurodegenerative diseases</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39240488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13668-024-00570-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s13668-024-00570-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Salthouse TA. When does age-related cognitive decline begin? Neurobiol Aging. 2009;30:507–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19231028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2683339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2008.09.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gudden J, Arias Vasquez A, Bloemendaal M. The Effects of Intermittent Fasting on Brain and Cognitive Function. Nutrients. 2021;13:3166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34579042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8470960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13093166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin B, Mattson MP, Maudsley S. Caloric restriction and intermittent fasting: Two potential diets for successful brain aging. Ageing Res Rev. 2006;5:332–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16899414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2622429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2006.04.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spuch C, Navarro C. Liposomes for Targeted Delivery of Active Agents against Neurodegenerative Diseases (Alzheimer’s Disease and Parkinson’s Disease). J Drug Deliv. 2011;2011:1–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2011/469679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adlimoghaddam A, Neuendorff M, Roy B, Albensi BC. A review of clinical treatment considerations of donepezil in severe Alzheimer’s disease. CNS Neurosci Ther. 2018;24:876–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30058285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6489741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cns.13035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stansley B, Yamamoto B. L-Dopa and Brain Serotonin System Dysfunction. Toxics. 2015;3:75–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29056652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5634697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxics3010075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Q, Zou L, Kong Z, Yang L. Cognitive Impact of Calorie Restriction: A Narrative Review. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2020;21:1394–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32693996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2020.05.047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schafer MJ, Dolgalev I, Alldred MJ, Heguy A, Ginsberg SD. Calorie Restriction Suppresses Age-Dependent Hippocampal Transcriptional Signatures. Anderson RM, editor. PLoS ONE. 2015;10:e0133923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherif A, Roelands B, Meeusen R, Chamari K. Effects of Intermittent Fasting, Caloric Restriction, and Ramadan Intermittent Fasting on Cognitive Performance at Rest and During Exercise in Adults. Sports Med. 2016;46:35–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26438184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40279-015-0408-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masoro EJ. Overview of caloric restriction and ageing. Mech Ageing Dev. 2005;126:913–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15885745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mad.2005.03.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Lakhanpal D, Kumar S, Sharma S, Kataria H, Kaur M, et al. Late-onset intermittent fasting dietary restriction as a potential intervention to retard age-associated brain function impairments in male rats. Age. 2012;34:917–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21861096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11357-011-9289-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J, Duan W, Mattson MP. Evidence that brain-derived neurotrophic factor is required for basal neurogenesis and mediates, in part, the enhancement of neurogenesis by dietary restriction in the hippocampus of adult mice. J Neurochem. 2002;82:1367–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12354284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2002.01085.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu A, Sun X, Liu Y. Effects of caloric restriction on cognition and behavior in developing mice. Neurosci Lett. 2003;339(2):166–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12614920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(03)00008-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willcox DC, Willcox BJ, Todoriki H, Curb JD, Suzuki M. Caloric restriction and human longevity: what can we learn from the Okinawans? Biogerontology. 2006;7:173–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16810568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10522-006-9008-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leclerc E, Trevizol AP, Grigolon RB, Subramaniapillai M, McIntyre RS, Brietzke E, et al. The effect of caloric restriction on working memory in healthy non-obese adults. CNS Spectr. 2020;25:2–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30968820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1092852918001566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witte AV, Fobker M, Gellner R, Knecht S, Flöel A. Caloric restriction improves memory in elderly humans. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2009;106:1255–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19171901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2633586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0808587106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brocchi A, Rebelos E, Dardano A, Mantuano M, Daniele G. Effects of Intermittent Fasting on Brain Metabolism. Nutrients. 2022;14:1275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35334932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8954770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14061275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fenneni MA, Latiri I, Aloui A, Rouatbi S, Saafi MA, Bougmiza I, et al. Effects of Ramadan on physical capacities of North African boys fasting for the first time. Libyan J Med. 2014;9:25391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25261691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3402/ljm.v9.25391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michalsen A, Li C. Fasting Therapy for Treating and Preventing Disease - Current State of Evidence. Complement Med Res. 2013;20:444–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000357765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stockman M-C, Thomas D, Burke J, Apovian CM. Intermittent Fasting: Is the Wait Worth the Weight? Curr Obes Rep. 2018;7:172–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29700718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5959807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13679-018-0308-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Wang Z, Zuo Z. Chronic Intermittent Fasting Improves Cognitive Functions and Brain Structures in Mice. Xie Z, editor. PLoS ONE. 2013;8:e66069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng H, Ton H, Yang L, Liufu N, Dong Y, Zhang Y, et al. Acute Fasting Does Not Induce Cognitive Impairment in Mice. Front Neurosci. 2019;13:896.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31507368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6718131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnins.2019.00896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattson MP, Longo VD, Harvie M. Impact of intermittent fasting on health and disease processes. Ageing Res Rev. 2017;39:46–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27810402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2016.10.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Currenti W, Godos J, Castellano S, Mogavero MP, Ferri R, Caraci F, et al. Time restricted feeding and mental health: a review of possible mechanisms on affective and cognitive disorders. Int J Food Sci Nutr. 2021;72:723–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33356688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09637486.2020.1866504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray AJ, Knight NS, Cole MA, Cochlin LE, Carter E, Tchabanenko K, et al. Novel ketone diet enhances physical and cognitive performance. FASEB J. 2016;30:4021–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27528626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5102124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1096/fj.201600773R</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thelen M, Brown-Borg HM. Does Diet Have a Role in the Treatment of Alzheimer’s Disease? Front Aging Neurosci. 2020;12: 617071.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33424583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7785773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2020.617071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Francesco A, Di Germanio C, Bernier M, De Cabo R. A time to fast. Science. 2018;362:770–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30442801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8504313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.aau2095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller L, Power Guerra N, Stenzel J, Rühlmann C, Lindner T, Krause BJ, et al. Long-Term Caloric Restriction Attenuates β-Amyloid Neuropathology and Is Accompanied by Autophagy in APPswe/PS1delta9 Mice. Nutrients. 2021;13:985.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33803798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8003277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13030985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ntsapi CM, Loos B. Neurons die with heightened but functional macro- and chaperone mediated autophagy upon increased amyloid-ß induced toxicity with region-specific protection in prolonged intermittent fasting. Exp Cell Res. 2021;408: 112840.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34624324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2021.112840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alirezaei M, Kemball CC, Flynn CT, Wood MR, Whitton JL, Kiosses WB. Short-term fasting induces profound neuronal autophagy. Autophagy. 2010;6:702–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20534972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3106288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4161/auto.6.6.12376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava SC, Haigis M. Role of Sirtuins and Calorie Restriction in Neuroprotection: Implications in Alzheimers and Parkinsons Diseases. Curr Pharm Des. 2011;17:3418–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21902666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/138161211798072526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattson MP. Interventions that Improve Body and Brain Bioenergetics for Parkinson’s Disease Risk Reduction and Therapy. J Parkinson’s Dis. 2014;4:1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/JPD-130335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maswood N, Young J, Tilmont E, Zhang Z, Gash DM, Gerhardt GA, et al. Caloric restriction increases neurotrophic factor levels and attenuates neurochemical and behavioral deficits in a primate model of Parkinson’s disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2004;101:18171–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15604149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">539733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0405831102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coppens J, Bentea E, Bayliss J, Demuyser T, Walrave L, Albertini G, et al. Caloric Restriction Protects against Lactacystin-Induced Degeneration of Dopamine Neurons Independent of the Ghrelin Receptor. IJMS. 2017;18:558.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28273852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5372574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms18030558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojha U, Khanal S, Park P-H, Hong JT, Choi D-Y. Intermittent fasting protects the nigral dopaminergic neurons from MPTP-mediated dopaminergic neuronal injury in mice. J Nutr Biochem. 2023;112: 109212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36370926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2022.109212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman LR, Haley-Zitlin V, Rosenberger DS, Granholm A-C. Damaging effects of a high-fat diet to the brain and cognition: A review of proposed mechanisms. Nutr Neurosci. 2014;17:241–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24192577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1179/1476830513Y.0000000092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan NA, Raine LB, Donovan SM, Hillman CH IV. The Cognitive Implications Of Obesity And Nutrition In Childhood. Monographs Society Res Child. 2014;79:51–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/mono.12130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz N, Vural H, Yilmaz M, Sutcu R, Sirmali R, Hicyilmaz H, et al. Calorie restriction modulates hippocampal NMDA receptors in diet-induced obese rats. J Recept Signal Transduct Res. 2011;31:214–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21470075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/10799893.2011.569724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim H, Kang H, Heo RW, Jeon BT, Yi C, Shin HJ, et al. Caloric restriction improves diabetes-induced cognitive deficits by attenuating neurogranin-associated calcium signaling in high-fat diet-fed mice. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2016;36:1098–110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26661177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0271678X15606724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahim HA, El-Gamal R, Sherif RN. Intermittent Fasting Attenuates High-Fat Diet-Induced Cerebellar Changes in Rats: Involvement of TNF-α, Autophagy, and Oxidative Stress. Cells Tissues Organs. 2021;210:351–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34551416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000519088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solianik R, Sujeta A, Čekanauskaitė A. Effects of 2-day calorie restriction on cardiovascular autonomic response, mood, and cognitive and motor functions in obese young adult women. Exp Brain Res. 2018;236:2299–308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29860630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00221-018-5305-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solianik R, Sujeta A. Two-day fasting evokes stress, but does not affect mood, brain activity, cognitive, psychomotor, and motor performance in overweight women. Behav Brain Res. 2018;338:166–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29097329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2017.10.028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teong XT, Hutchison AT, Liu B, Wittert GA, Lange K, Banks S, et al. Eight weeks of intermittent fasting versus calorie restriction does not alter eating behaviors, mood, sleep quality, quality of life and cognitive performance in women with overweight. Nutr Res. 2021;92:32–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34274552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nutres.2021.06.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anton SD, Lee SA, Donahoo WT, McLaren C, Manini T, Leeuwenburgh C, et al. The Effects of Time Restricted Feeding on Overweight Older Adults: A Pilot Study. Nutrients. 2019;11:1500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31262054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6682944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu11071500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanek A, Brożyna-Tkaczyk K, Zolghadri S, Cholewka A, Myśliński W. The Role of Intermittent Energy Restriction Diet on Metabolic Profile and Weight Loss among Obese Adults. Nutrients. 2022;14:1509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35406122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9002823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14071509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coker LH, Shumaker SA. Type 2 diabetes mellitus and cognition An understudied issue in women’s health. J Psychosom Res. 2003;54(2):129–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12573734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(02)00523-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biessels GJ. Caffeine, Diabetes, Cognition, and Dementia. Cunha RA, De Mendonça A, editors. JAD. 2010;20:S143–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira LSS, Fernandes CS, Vieira MNN, De Felice FG. Insulin Resistance in Alzheimer’s Disease. Front Neurosci. 2018;12:830.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30542257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6277874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnins.2018.00830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milstein JL, Ferris HA. The brain as an insulin-sensitive metabolic organ. Mol Metab. 2021;52: 101234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33845179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8513144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.molmet.2021.101234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farzi A, Hassan AM, Zenz G, Holzer P. Diabesity and mood disorders: Multiple links through the microbiota-gut-brain axis. Mol Aspects Med. 2019;66:80–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30513310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mam.2018.11.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frank J, Gupta A, Osadchiy V, Mayer EA. Brain–Gut–Microbiome Interactions and Intermittent Fasting in Obesity. Nutrients. 2021;13:584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33578763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7916460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13020584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Dai X, Zhang H, Shi R, Hui Y, Jin X, et al. Gut microbiota mediates intermittent-fasting alleviation of diabetes-induced cognitive impairment. Nat Commun. 2020;11:855.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32071312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7029019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-14676-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elesawy BH, Raafat BM, Muqbali AA, Abbas AM, Sakr HF. The Impact of Intermittent Fasting on Brain-Derived Neurotrophic Factor, Neurotrophin 3, and Rat Behavior in a Rat Model of Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus. Brain Sci. 2021;11:242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33671898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7918995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/brainsci11020242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ugochukwu NH, Mukes JD, Figgers CL. Ameliorative effects of dietary caloric restriction on oxidative stress and inflammation in the brain of streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats. Clin Chim Acta. 2006;370:165–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16546151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2006.02.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parr EB, Devlin BL, Lim KHC, Moresi LNZ, Geils C, Brennan L, et al. Time-Restricted Eating as a Nutrition Strategy for Individuals with Type 2 Diabetes: A Feasibility Study. Nutrients. 2020;12:3228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33105701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7690416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12113228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutton EF, Beyl R, Early KS, Cefalu WT, Ravussin E, Peterson CM. Early Time-Restricted Feeding Improves Insulin Sensitivity, Blood Pressure, and Oxidative Stress Even without Weight Loss in Men with Prediabetes. Cell Metab. 2018;27:1212-1221.e3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29754952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5990470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2018.04.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearce KL, Noakes M, Wilson C, Clifton PM. Continuous Glucose Monitoring and Cognitive Performance in Type 2 Diabetes. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2012;14:1126–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23046398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/dia.2012.0143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seidler K. Intermittent fasting and cognitive performance – Targeting BDNF as potential strategy to optimise brain health. Front Neuroendocrinol. 2022;65:100971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34929259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yfrne.2021.100971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu R, Liu IY, Bi X, Thompson RF, Doctrow SR, Malfroy B, et al. Reversal of age-related learning deficits and brain oxidative stress in mice with superoxide dismutase/catalase mimetics. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2003;100:8526–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12815103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">166262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1332809100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Manchanda S, Kaur T, Kumar S, Lakhanpal D, Lakhman SS, et al. Middle age onset short-term intermittent fasting dietary restriction prevents brain function impairments in male Wistar rats. Biogerontology. 2015;16:775–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26318578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10522-015-9603-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Jia M, Chen W, Liu Z. The neuroprotective effects of intermittent fasting on brain aging and neurodegenerative diseases via regulating mitochondrial function. Free Radical Biol Med. 2022;182:206–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2022.02.021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang F, Chu X, Yin M, Liu X, Yuan H, Niu Y, et al. mTOR and autophagy in normal brain aging and caloric restriction ameliorating age-related cognition deficits. Behav Brain Res. 2014;264:82–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24525424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2014.02.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin A-L, Coman D, Jiang L, Rothman DL, Hyder F. Caloric Restriction Impedes Age-Related Decline of Mitochondrial Function and Neuronal Activity. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2014;34:1440–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24984898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4158670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/jcbfm.2014.114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pronk NP. Neuroplasticity and the role of exercise and diet on cognition. Am J Clin Nutr. 2021;113:1392–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33851206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ajcn/nqab083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komulainen P, Tuomilehto J, Savonen K, Männikkö R, Hassinen M, Lakka TA, et al. Exercise, diet, and cognition in a 4-year randomized controlled trial: Dose-Responses to Exercise Training (DR’s EXTRA). Am J Clin Nutr. 2021;113:1428–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33742194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8244125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ajcn/nqab018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marosi K, Mattson MP. BDNF mediates adaptive brain and body responses to energetic challenges. Trends Endocrinol Metab. 2014;25:89–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24361004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tem.2013.10.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibbons TD, Cotter JD, Ainslie PN, Abraham WC, Mockett BG, Campbell HA, et al. Fasting for 20 h does not affect exercise-induced increases in circulating BDNF in humans. J Physiol. 2023;601:2121–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36631068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1113/JP283582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khabour OF, Alzoubi KH, Alomari MA, Alzubi MA. Changes in spatial memory and BDNF expression to concurrent dietary restriction and voluntary exercise. Hippocampus. 2010;20:637–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19530223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hipo.20657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng A, Wan R, Yang J-L, Kamimura N, Son TG, Ouyang X, et al. Involvement of PGC-1α in the formation and maintenance of neuronal dendritic spines. Nat Commun. 2012;3:1250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23212379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ncomms2238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Praag H, Fleshner M, Schwartz MW, Mattson MP. Exercise, Energy Intake, Glucose Homeostasis, and the Brain. J Neurosci. 2014;34:15139–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25392482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4228123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2814-14.2014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pratchayasakul W, Arunsak B, Suparan K, Sriwichaiin S, Chunchai T, Chattipakorn N, et al. Combined caloric restriction and exercise provides greater metabolic and neurocognitive benefits than either as a monotherapy in obesity with or without estrogen deprivation. J Nutr Biochem. 2022;110: 109125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35977664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2022.109125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kishi T. Exercise training plus calorie restriction causes synergistic protection against cognitive decline via up-regulation of BDNF in hippocampus of stroke-prone hypertensive rats. Annu Int Conf IEEE Eng Med Biol Soc. 2012;2012:6764–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stranahan AM, Lee K, Martin B, Maudsley S, Golden E, Cutler RG, et al. Voluntary exercise and caloric restriction enhance hippocampal dendritic spine density and BDNF levels in diabetic mice. Hippocampus. 2009;19:951–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19280661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2755651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hipo.20577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tay J, Zajac IT, Thompson CH, Luscombe-Marsh ND, Danthiir V, Noakes M, et al. A randomised-controlled trial of the effects of very low-carbohydrate and high-carbohydrate diets on cognitive performance in patients with type 2 diabetes. Br J Nutr. 2016;116:1745–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0007114516004001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattson MP. Energy Intake and Exercise as Determinants of Brain Health and Vulnerability to Injury and Disease. Cell Metab. 2012;16(6):706–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23168220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3518570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2012.08.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelc MA. The effects of intermittent fasting and a low-carbohydrate diet on type 2 diabetes. JAAPA. 2023;36:26–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37368850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.JAA.0000923536.23229.d3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trepanowski JF, Kroeger CM, Barnosky A, Klempel MC, Bhutani S, Hoddy KK, et al. Effect of Alternate-Day Fasting on Weight Loss, Weight Maintenance, and Cardioprotection Among Metabolically Healthy Obese Adults: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Intern Med. 2017;177:930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28459931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5680777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2017.0936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattson MP, Moehl K, Ghena N, Schmaedick M, Cheng A. Intermittent metabolic switching, neuroplasticity and brain health. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2018;19:81–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrn.2017.156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang DS, Kwak HB, Ko IG, Kim SE, Jin JJ, Ji ES, et al. Treadmill Exercise Improves Memory Function Depending on Circadian Rhythm Changes in Mice. Int Neurourol J. 2016;20:S141-149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27915477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5169096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5213/inj.1632738.369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>George &amp; Anne Ryan Institute for Neuroscience, University of Rhode Island, 130 Flagg Road, Kingston, RI, 02881, US, Francis N, Department of Psychology, Stony Brook University, 100 Nicolls Rd, Stony Brook, NY, 11794, US. Intermittent Fasting and Brain Health: Efficacy and Potential Mechanisms of Action. OBM Geriatrics. 2020;4:1–19.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>