<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39241545</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-3460</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>426</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of food microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Food Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>LED induced non-thermal preservation of muscle foods: A systematic review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>110892</StartPage><MedlinePgn>110892</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2024.110892</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0168-1605(24)00336-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>LED technology has emerged as a promising non-thermal preservation method for highly perishable muscle foods like meat and fish. Muscle foods are most susceptible to spoilage due to their high moisture content and nutrient density, which create an ideal environment for microbial growth, chemical oxidation, and enzymatic activity, which negatively alter their quality. LED treatment offers an effective solution by significantly reducing microbial loads and extending shelf life without adversely affecting sensory and nutritional properties. Specific wavelengths of LED light induce microbial inactivation through mechanisms like DNA damage, lipid oxidation, and protein alteration. Studies have shown that LED treatment can preserve the fresh-like quality of muscle foods by mitigating common spoilage processes. The advantages of LED technology include its non-thermal nature, ability to integrate with other preservation methods, and controllability in terms of intensity and wavelength. This enables for tailored applications based on food type and spoilage risks. As consumer demand grows for safe, chemical-free food options, LED technology addresses this need while enhancing food safety and quality. Further research is encouraged to optimize LED applications in various muscle food preservation contexts. With its exceptional ability to produce DNA damage in bacteria, inactivate enzymes, and malfunction biological activities, LED could serve as an inexpensive processing intervention to safeguard the quality of meat and seafood products. This review underscores the potential of LED technology as a promising alternative to traditional preservation methods for decontamination of muscle food.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patil</LastName><ForeName>S A</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Technology, Shivaji University, Vidyanagar, Kolhapur 416004, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khandekar</LastName><ForeName>S P</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Shivaji University, Vidyanagar, Kolhapur 416004, Maharashtra, India. Electronic address: snehal.khandekar5@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Food Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8412849</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0168-1605</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biochemical spoilage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">LED technology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meat and fish</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Microbial spoilage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Non-thermal preservation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39241545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2024.110892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0168-1605(24)00336-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>