<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39245910</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Antimicrobial peptides derived from food byproducts: Sources, production, purification, applications, and challenges.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13422</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13422</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.13422</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Food wastes can be a valuable reservoir of bioactive substances that can serve as natural preservatives in foods or as functional ingredients with potential health benefits. The antimicrobial properties of protein hydrolysates, especially antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) derived from food byproducts (FBs), have been extensively explored. These protein fragments are defined by their short length, low molecular weight, substantial content of hydrophobic and basic amino acids, and positive net charge. The intricate mechanisms by which these peptides exert their antimicrobial effects on microorganisms and pathogens have been elaborately described. This review also focuses on techniques for producing and purifying AMPs from diverse FBs, including seafood, livestock, poultry, plants, and dairy wastes. According to investigations, incorporating AMPs as additives and alternatives to chemical preservatives in food formulations and packaging materials has been pursued to enhance both consumer health and the shelf life of foods and their products. However, challenges associated with the utilization of AMPs derived from food waste depend on their interaction with the food matrix, acceptability, and commercial viability. Overall, AMPs can serve as alternative safe additives, thereby ensuring the safety and prolonging the storage duration of food products based on specific regulatory approvals as recommended by the respective safety authorities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davoudi</LastName><ForeName>Mahshad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Faculty of Agriculture, Tarbiat Modares University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gavlighi</LastName><ForeName>Hassan Ahmadi</ForeName><Initials>HA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9103-2291</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Faculty of Agriculture, Tarbiat Modares University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Halal Research Center of IRI, Iran Food and Drug Administration, Ministry of Health and Medical Education, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Javanmardi</LastName><ForeName>Fardin</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, School of Nutritional Sciences and Dietetics, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Benjakul</LastName><ForeName>Soottawat</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9433-3671</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Center of Excellence in Seafood Science and Innovation, Faculty of Agro-Industry, Prince of Songkla University, Songkhla, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nikoo</LastName><ForeName>Mehdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathobiology and Quality Control, Artemia and Aquaculture Research Institute, Urmia University, Urmia, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Tarbiat Modares University</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000089882">Antimicrobial Peptides</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014866">Waste Products</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000089882" MajorTopicYN="Y">Antimicrobial Peptides</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014866" MajorTopicYN="N">Waste Products</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobial peptide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food waste</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">natural additives</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sustainability</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39245910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.13422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdelhamid, A. G., Campbell, E. P., Hawkins, Z., &amp; Yousef, A. E. (2022). Efficient production of broad‐spectrum antimicrobials by Paenibacillus polymyxa OSY‐EC using acid whey‐based medium and novel antimicrobial concentration approach. Frontiers in Bioengineering and Biotechnology, 10, 869778. https://doi.org/10.3389/fbioe.2022.869778</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel‐Hamid, M., Goda, H. A., De Gobba, C., Jenssen, H., &amp; Osman, A. (2016). Antibacterial activity of papain hydrolysed camel whey and its fractions. International Dairy Journal, 61, 91–98. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.idairyj.2016.04.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel‐Hamid, M., Romeih, E., Saporito, P., Osman, A., Mateiu, R. V., Mojsoska, B., &amp; Jenssen, H. (2020). Camel milk whey hydrolysate inhibits growth and biofilm formation of Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1 and methicillin‐resistant Staphylococcus aureus. Food Control, 111, 107056. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.107056</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelhedi, O., Jridi, M., Jemil, I., Mora, L., Toldrá, F., Aristoy, M.‐C., Boualga, A., Nasri, M., &amp; Nasri, R. (2016). Combined biocatalytic conversion of smooth hound viscera: Protein hydrolysates elaboration and assessment of their antioxidant, anti‐ACE and antibacterial activities. Food Research International, 86, 9–23. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2016.05.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd Rashid, N. Y., Manan, M. A., Pa'ee, K. F., Saari, N., &amp; Wong, F. W. F. (2022). Evaluation of antioxidant and antibacterial activities of fish protein hydrolysate produced from Malaysian fish sausage (Keropok lekor) by‐products by indigenous Lactobacillus casei fermentation. Journal of Cleaner Production, 347, 131303. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.131303</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abou‐Diab, M., Thibodeau, J., Fliss, I., Dhulster, P., Bazinet, L., &amp; Nedjar, N. (2022). Production of demineralized antibacterial, antifungal and antioxidant peptides from bovine hemoglobin using an optimized multiple‐step system: Electrodialysis with bipolar membrane. Membranes (Basel), 12(5), 512. https://doi.org/10.3390/membranes12050512</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aguilar‐Toalá, J., Santiago‐López, L., Peres, C., Peres, C., Garcia, H., Vallejo‐Cordoba, B., González‐Córdova, A., &amp; Hernández‐Mendoza, A. (2017). Assessment of multifunctional activity of bioactive peptides derived from fermented milk by specific Lactobacillus plantarum strains. Journal of Dairy Science, 100(1), 65–75. https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.2016‐11846</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed, R., &amp; Chun, B.‐S. (2018). Subcritical water hydrolysis for the production of bioactive peptides from tuna skin collagen. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 141, 88–96. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2018.03.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aissaoui, N., Chobert, J. M., Haertle, T., Marzouki, M. N., &amp; Abidi, F. (2017). Purification and biochemical characterization of a neutral serine protease from Trichoderma harzianum. Use in antibacterial peptide production from a fish by‐product hydrolysate. Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology, 182(2), 831–845. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12010‐016‐2365‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alavi, F., &amp; Ciftci, O. N. (2023). Purification and fractionation of bioactive peptides through membrane filtration: A critical and application review. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 131, 118–128. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2022.11.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alizadeh, O., &amp; Aliakbarlu, J. (2020). Effects of ultrasound and ohmic heating pretreatments on hydrolysis, antioxidant and antibacterial activities of whey protein concentrate and its fractions. LWT, 131, 109913. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109913</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almaas, H., Eriksen, E., Sekse, C., Comi, I., Flengsrud, R., Holm, H., Jensen, E., Jacobsen, M., Langsrud, T., &amp; Vegarud, G. E. (2011). Antibacterial peptides derived from caprine whey proteins, by digestion with human gastrointestinal juice. British Journal of Nutrition, 106(6), 896–905. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114511001085</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amiri, S., Mokarram, R. R., Khiabani, M. S., Bari, M. R., &amp; Khaledabad, M. A. (2022). Characterization of antimicrobial peptides produced by Lactobacillus acidophilus LA‐5 and Bifidobacterium lactis BB‐12 and their inhibitory effect against foodborne pathogens. LWT, 153, 112449. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112449</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreev, K., Martynowycz, M. W., Ivankin, A., Huang, M. L., Kuzmenko, I., Meron, M., Lin, B., Kirshenbaum, K., &amp; Gidalevitz, D. (2016). Cyclization improves membrane permeation by antimicrobial peptoids. Langmuir, 32(48), 12905–12913. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.langmuir.6b03477</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arntfield, S. (2018). Proteins from oil‐producing plants. In Proteins in food processing (pp. 187–221). Woodhead Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐08‐100722‐8.00008‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asri, N. M., Muhialdin, B. J., Zarei, M., &amp; Saari, N. (2020). Low molecular weight peptides generated from palm kernel cake via solid state lacto‐fermentation extend the shelf life of bread. LWT, 134, 110206. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.110206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atef, M., Chait, Y. A., Ojagh, S. M., Latifi, A. M., Esmaeili, M., Hammami, R., &amp; Udenigwe, C. C. (2021). Anti‐Salmonella activity and peptidomic profiling of peptide fractions produced from sturgeon fish skin collagen (Huso huso) using commercial enzymes. Nutrients, 13(8), 2657. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13082657</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baindara, P., &amp; Mandal, S. M. (2022). Plant‐derived antimicrobial peptides: Novel preservatives for the food industry. Foods, 11(16), 2415. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11162415</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balakrishnan, B., Prasad, B., Rai, A. K., Velappan, S. P., Subbanna, M. N., &amp; Narayan, B. (2011). In vitro antioxidant and antibacterial properties of hydrolysed proteins of delimed tannery fleshings: Comparison of acid hydrolysis and fermentation methods. Biodegradation, 22(2), 287–295. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10532‐010‐9398‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bargeman, G., Houwing, J., Recio, I., Koops, G. H., &amp; van der Horst, C. (2002). Electro‐membrane filtration for the selective isolation of bioactive peptides from an αs2‐casein hydrolysate. Biotechnology and Bioengineering, 80(6), 599–609. https://doi.org/10.1002/bit.10419</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaubier, S., Przybylski, R., Bodin, A., Nedjar, N., Dhulster, P., &amp; Kapel, R. (2021). Ultrafiltration fractionation of bovine hemoglobin hydrolysates: Prediction of separation performances for optimal enrichment in antimicrobial peptide. Membranes (Basel), 11(2), 73. https://doi.org/10.3390/membranes11020073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaulieu, L., Thibodeau, J., Bonnet, C., Bryl, P., &amp; Carbonneau, M.‐É. (2013). Detection of antibacterial activity in an enzymatic hydrolysate fraction obtained from processing of Atlantic rock crab (Cancer irroratus) by‐products. PharmaNutrition, 1(4), 149–157. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phanu.2013.05.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaulieu, L., Thibodeau, J., Desbiens, M., Saint‐Louis, R., Zatylny‐Gaudin, C., &amp; Thibault, S. (2010). Evidence of antibacterial activities in peptide fractions originating from snow crab (Chionoecetes opilio) by‐products. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins, 2(3), 197–209. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12602‐010‐9043‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellavita, R., Braccia, S., Galdiero, S., &amp; Falanga, A. (2023). Glycosylation and lipidation strategies: Approaches for improving antimicrobial peptide efficacy. Pharmaceuticals, 16(3), 439. https://doi.org/10.3390/ph16030439</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benavides, J., &amp; Rito‐Palomares, M. (2008). Practical experiences from the development of aqueous two‐phase processes for the recovery of high value biological products. Journal of Chemical Technology &amp; Biotechnology: International Research in Process, Environmental &amp; Clean Technology, 83(2), 133–142. https://doi.org/10.1002/jctb.1844</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borad, S. G., Kumar, A., &amp; Singh, A. K. (2017). Effect of processing on nutritive values of milk protein. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 57(17), 3690–3702. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2016.1160361</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borrajo, P., López‐Pedrouso, M., Franco, D., Pateiro, M., &amp; Lorenzo, J. M. (2020). Antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of porcine liver hydrolysates using flavourzyme. Applied Sciences, 10(11), 3950. https://doi.org/10.3390/app10113950</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borrajo, P., Pateiro, M., Barba, F. J., Mora, L., Franco, D., Toldrá, F., &amp; Lorenzo, J. M. (2019). Antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of peptides extracted from meat by‐products: A review. Food Analytical Methods, 12, 2401–2415. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12161‐019‐01595‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borrajo, P., Pateiro, M., Gagaoua, M., Franco, D., Zhang, W., &amp; Lorenzo, J. M. (2020). Evaluation of the antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of porcine liver protein hydrolysates obtained using Alcalase, bromelain, and papain. Applied Sciences, 10(7), 2290. https://doi.org/10.3390/app10072290</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bougatef, H., Krichen, F., Kobbi, S., Martinez‐Alvarez, O., Nedjar, N., Bougatef, A., &amp; Sila, A. (2020). Physicochemical and biological properties of eel by‐Products protein hydrolysates: Potential application to meat product preservation. Waste and Biomass Valorization, 11(3), 931–942. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649‐018‐0424‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabizza, R., Fancello, F., Petretto, G. L., Addis, R., Pisanu, S., Pagnozzi, D., Piga, A., &amp; Urgeghe, P. P. (2021). Exploring the DPP‐IV inhibitory, antioxidant and antibacterial potential of ovine “Scotta” hydrolysates. Foods, 10(12), 3137. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10123137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrera, M., Ezquerra‐Brauer, J. M., &amp; Aubourg, S. P. (2019). Characterization of the jumbo squid (Dosidicus gigas) skin by‐product by shotgun proteomics and protein‐based bioinformatics. Marine Drugs, 18(1), 31. https://doi.org/10.3390/md18010031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castañeda‐Valbuena, D., Berenguer‐Murcia, Á., Fernandez‐Lafuente, R., Morellon‐Sterling, R., &amp; Tacias‐Pascacio, V. G. (2022). Biological activities of peptides obtained by pepsin hydrolysis of fishery products. Process Biochemistry, 120, 53–63. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procbio.2022.05.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceruso, M., Liu, Y., Gunther, N. W., IV, Pepe, T., Anastasio, A., Qi, P. X., Tomasula, P. M., &amp; Renye, J. A., Jr. (2021). Anti‐listerial activity of thermophilin 110 and pediocin in fermented milk and whey. Food Control, 125, 107941. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.107941</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakka, A. K., Elias, M., Jini, R., Sakhare, P. Z., &amp; Bhaskar, N. (2015). In‐vitro antioxidant and antibacterial properties of fermentatively and enzymatically prepared chicken liver protein hydrolysates. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 52(12), 8059–8067. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐015‐1920‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakrabarti, S., Guha, S., &amp; Majumder, K. (2018). Food‐derived bioactive peptides in human health: Challenges and opportunities. Nutrients, 10(11), 1738. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu10111738</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandrudu, S., Simerska, P., &amp; Toth, I. (2013). Chemical methods for peptide and protein production. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 18(4), 4373–4388. doi.org/10.3390/molecules18044373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary, K., Kumar, R., Singh, S., Tuknait, A., Gautam, A., Mathur, D., Anand, P., Varshney, G. C., &amp; Raghava, G. P. (2016). A web server and mobile app for computing hemolytic potency of peptides. Scientific Reports, 6(1), 22843. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep22843</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaves de Lima, E. d. L., de Moura Fernandes, J., &amp; Cardarelli, H. R. (2017). Optimized fermentation of goat cheese whey with Lactococcus lactis for production of antilisterial bacteriocin‐like substances. LWT, 84, 710–716. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2017.06.040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Jiang, D., Xu, P., Geng, Z., Xiong, G., Zou, Y., Wang, D., &amp; Xu, W. (2021). Structural and antimicrobial properties of Maillard reaction products in chicken liver protein hydrolysate after sonication. Food Chemistry, 343, 128417. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.128417</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chi, C., Hu, F., Li, Z., Wang, B., &amp; Luo, H. (2016). Influence of different hydrolysis processes by trypsin on the physicochemical, antioxidant, and functional properties of collagen hydrolysates from Sphyrna lewini, Dasyatis akjei, and Raja porosa. Journal of Aquatic Food Product Technology, 25(5), 616–632. https://doi.org/10.1080/10498850.2014.898004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chwialkowska, J., Duber, A., Zagrodnik, R., Walkiewicz, F., Łężyk, M., &amp; Oleskowicz‐Popiel, P. (2019). Caproic acid production from acid whey via open culture fermentation – Evaluation of the role of electron donors and downstream processing. Bioresource Technology, 279, 74–83. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2019.01.086</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Claesson, M. J., Li, Y., Leahy, S., Canchaya, C., van Pijkeren, J. P., Cerdeño‐Tárraga, A. M., Parkhill, J., Flynn, S., O'Sullivan, G. C., &amp; Collins, J. K. (2006). Multireplicon genome architecture of Lactobacillus salivarius. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 103(17), 6718–6723. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0511060103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cournoyer, A., Thibodeau, J., Ben Said, L., Sanchez‐Reinoso, Z., Mikhaylin, S., Fliss, I., &amp; Bazinet, L. (2022). How discoloration of porcine cruor hydrolysate allowed the identification of new antifungal peptides. Foods, 11(24), 4035. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11244035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz‐Casas, D. E., Aguilar, C. N., Ascacio‐Valdés, J. A., Rodríguez‐Herrera, R., Chávez‐González, M. L., &amp; Flores‐Gallegos, A. C. (2021). Enzymatic hydrolysis and microbial fermentation: The most favorable biotechnological methods for the release of bioactive peptides. Food Chemistry: Molecular Sciences, 3, 100047. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fochms.2021.100047</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, Q., Sun, Y., Zhou, Z., Cheng, J., &amp; Guo, M. (2021). Effects of enzymatic hydrolysis on physicochemical properties and solubility and bitterness of milk protein hydrolysates. Foods, 10(10), 2462. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10102462</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalsgaard, T. K., Nielsen, J. H., &amp; Larsen, L. B. (2006). Characterization of reaction products formed in a model reaction between pentanal and lysine‐containing oligopeptides. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 54(17), 6367–6373. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf060003g</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Rocha, M., Alemán, A., Baccan, G. C., López‐Caballero, M. E., Gómez‐Guillén, C., Montero, P., &amp; Prentice, C. (2018). Anti‐Inflammatory, antioxidant, and antimicrobial effects of underutilized fish protein hydrolysate. Journal of Aquatic Food Product Technology, 27(5), 592–608. https://doi.org/10.1080/10498850.2018.1461160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Silva Dantas, C. C., de Souza, E. L., Cardoso, J. D., de Lima, L. A., de Sousa Oliveira, K., Migliolo, L., Dias, S. C., Franco, O. L., &amp; Magnani, M. (2014). Identification of a napin‐like peptide from Eugenia malaccensis L. seeds with inhibitory activity toward Staphylococcus aureus and Salmonella enteritidis. The Protein Journal, 33, 549–556. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10930‐014‐9587‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Silva Pereira, L., do Nascimento, V. V., de Fátima Ferreira Ribeiro, S., Rodrigues, R., Fernandes, K. V. S., de Oliveira Carvalho, A., Vasconcelos, I. M., dos Santos Bento, C., Sudré, C. P., &amp; Zottich, U. (2018). Characterization of Capsicum annuum L. leaf and root antimicrobial peptides: Antimicrobial activity against phytopathogenic microorganisms. Acta Physiologiae Plantarum, 40, 107. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11738‐018‐2685‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Benedetti, S., Girlando, V., Pasquali, M., &amp; Scarafoni, A. (2021). Valorization of okara by enzymatic production of anti‐fungal compounds for plant protection. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 26(16), 4858. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26164858</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Castro, R. J. S., &amp; Sato, H. H. (2015). Biologically active peptides: Processes for their generation, purification and identification and applications as natural additives in the food and pharmaceutical industries. Food Research International, 74, 185–198. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2015.05.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Lima, E. d. L. C., de Moura Fernandes, J., &amp; Cardarelli, H. R. (2017). Optimized fermentation of goat cheese whey with Lactococcus lactis for production of antilisterial bacteriocin‐like substances. LWT, 84, 710–716. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2017.06.040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demers‐Mathieu, V., Gauthier, S. F., Britten, M., Fliss, I., Robitaille, G., &amp; Jean, J. (2013). Antibacterial activity of peptides extracted from tryptic hydrolyzate of whey protein by nanofiltration. International Dairy Journal, 28(2), 94–101. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.idairyj.2012.09.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Oliveira Filho, J. G., Rodrigues, J. M., Valadares, A. C. F., de Almeida, A. B., Valencia‐Mejia, E., Fernandes, K. F., Lemes, A. C., Alves, C. C. F., Sousa, H. A. d. F., &amp; da Silva, E. R. (2021). Bioactive properties of protein hydrolysate of cottonseed byproduct: Antioxidant, antimicrobial, and angiotensin‐converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitory activities. Waste and Biomass Valorization, 12, 1395–1404. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649‐020‐01066‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djellouli, M., López‐Caballero, M. E., Arancibia, M. Y., Karam, N., &amp; Martínez‐Alvarez, O. (2020). Antioxidant and antimicrobial enhancement by reaction of protein hydrolysates derived from shrimp by‐products with glucosamine. Waste and Biomass Valorization, 11(6), 2491–2505. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649‐019‐00607‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyen, A., Saucier, L., Beaulieu, L., Pouliot, Y., &amp; Bazinet, L. (2012). Electroseparation of an antibacterial peptide fraction from snow crab by‐products hydrolysate by electrodialysis with ultrafiltration membranes. Food Chemistry, 132(3), 1177–1184. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.11.059</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durham, R., &amp; Hourigan, J. (2007). Waste management and co‐product recovery in dairy processing. In Handbook of waste management and co‐product recovery in food processing (pp. 332–387). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1533/9781845692520.4.332</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Menif, E., Offret, C., Labrie, S., &amp; Beaulieu, L. (2019). Identification of peptides implicated in antibacterial activity of snow crab hepatopancreas hydrolysates by a bioassay‐guided fractionation approach combined with mass spectrometry. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins, 11, 1023–1033. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12602‐018‐9484‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ennaas, N., Hammami, R., Beaulieu, L., &amp; Fliss, I. (2015a). Production of antibacterial fraction from Atlantic mackerel (Scomber scombrus) and its processing by‐products using commercial enzymes. Food and Bioproducts Processing, 96, 145–153. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbp.2015.07.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ennaas, N., Hammami, R., Beaulieu, L., &amp; Fliss, I. (2015b). Purification and characterization of four antibacterial peptides from protamex hydrolysate of Atlantic mackerel (Scomber scombrus) by‐products. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, 462(3), 195–200. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2015.04.091</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ennaas, N., Hammami, R., Gomaa, A., Bedard, F., Biron, E., Subirade, M., Beaulieu, L., &amp; Fliss, I. (2016). Collagencin, an antibacterial peptide from fish collagen: Activity, structure and interaction dynamics with membrane. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, 473(2), 642–647. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2016.03.121</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdem Büyükkiraz, M., &amp; Kesmen, Z. (2022). Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs): A promising class of antimicrobial compounds. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 132(3), 1573–1596. https://doi.org/10.1111/jam.15314</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Etemadian, Y., Ghaemi, V., Shaviklo, A. R., Pourashouri, P., Mahoonak, A. R. S., &amp; Rafipour, F. (2021). Development of animal/plant‐based protein hydrolysate and its application in food, feed and nutraceutical industries: State of the art. Journal of Cleaner Production, 278, 123219. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.123219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francis, F., &amp; Chaudhary, N. (2023). Antimicrobial peptides: Features and modes of action. In Antimicrobial peptides (pp. 33–65). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐323‐85682‐9.00016‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freitas, C. S., Vericimo, M. A., da Silva, M. L., da Costa, G. C. V., Pereira, P. R., Paschoalin, V. M. F., &amp; Del Aguila, E. M. (2019). Encrypted antimicrobial and antitumoral peptides recovered from a protein‐rich soybean (Glycine max) by‐product. Journal of Functional Foods, 54, 187–198. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2019.01.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frestedt, J. L. (2018). Foods, food additives, and generally regarded as safe (GRAS) food assessments. In Food control and biosecurity (pp. 543–565). Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐811445‐2.00016‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman, M. (2005). Biological effects of Maillard browning products that may affect acrylamide safety in food: Biological effects of Maillard products. In Chemistry and safety of acrylamide in food (pp. 135–156). Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/0‐387‐24980‐X_12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanakis, C. M. (2015). Food waste recovery: Processing technologies and industrial techniques. Academic Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia‐Garcia, G., Woolley, E., Rahimifard, S., Colwill, J., White, R., &amp; Needham, L. (2017). A methodology for sustainable management of food waste. Waste and Biomass Valorization, 8(6), 2209–2227. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649‐016‐9720‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghalamara, S., Coscueta, E. R., Silva, S., Brazinha, C., Pereira, C. D., &amp; Pintado, M. E. (2022). Integrated ultrafiltration, nanofiltration, and reverse osmosis pilot process to produce bioactive protein/peptide fractions from sardine cooking effluent. Journal of Environmental Management, 317, 115344. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.115344</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghalamara, S., Silva, S., Brazinha, C., &amp; Pintado, M. (2020). Valorization of fish by‐products: Purification of bioactive peptides from codfish blood and sardine cooking wastewaters by membrane processing. Membranes (Basel), 10(3), 44. https://doi.org/10.3390/membranes10030044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghanbari, M., Jami, M., Domig, K. J., &amp; Kneifel, W. (2013). Seafood biopreservation by lactic acid bacteria – A review. LWT, 54(2), 315–324. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2013.05.039</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilbert‐López, B., Plaza, M., Mendiola, J. A., Ibáñez, E., &amp; Herrero, M. (2017). Subcritical water extraction and neoformation of antioxidants. In Water extraction of bioactive compounds (pp. 109–130). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐809380‐1.00004‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Girotto, F., Alibardi, L., &amp; Cossu, R. (2015). Food waste generation and industrial uses: A review. Waste Management, 45, 32–41. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2015.06.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gottardi, D., Hong, P. K., Ndagijimana, M., &amp; Betti, M. (2014). Conjugation of gluten hydrolysates with glucosamine at mild temperatures enhances antioxidant and antimicrobial properties. LWT, 57(1), 181–187. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2014.01.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartmann, R., &amp; Meisel, H. (2007). Food‐derived peptides with biological activity: From research to food applications. Current Opinion in Biotechnology, 18(2), 163–169. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copbio.2007.01.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasani, K., Ariaii, P., &amp; Ahmadi, M. (2022). Antimicrobial, antioxidant and anti‐cancer properties of protein hydrolysates from Indian mackerel (Rastrelliger kanagurta) waste prepared using commercial enzyme. International Journal of Peptide Research and Therapeutics, 28(3), 86. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10989‐022‐10396‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatab, S., Chen, M. L., Miao, W., Lin, J., Wu, D., Wang, C., Yuan, P., &amp; Deng, S. (2017). Protease hydrolysates of filefish (Thamnaconus modestus) byproducts effectively inhibit foodborne pathogens. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease, 14(11), 656–666. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2017.2317</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedhili, K., Dimitrov, K., Vauchel, P., Sila, A., Chataigné, G., Dhulster, P., &amp; Nedjar, N. (2015). Valorization of cruor slaughterhouse by‐product by enzymatic hydrolysis for the production of antibacterial peptides: Focus on α 1–32 family peptides mechanism and kinetics modeling. Bioprocess and Biosystems Engineering, 38(10), 1867–1877. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00449‐015‐1427‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hidalgo, F. J., León, M. M., &amp; Zamora, R. (2016). Amino acid decarboxylations produced by lipid‐derived reactive carbonyls in amino acid mixtures. Food Chemistry, 209, 256–261. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.04.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hidalgo, F. J., &amp; Zamora, R. (2007). Conversion of phenylalanine into styrene by 2, 4‐decadienal in model systems. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 55(12), 4902–4906. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf070527w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horvat, Š., &amp; Roščić, M. (2010). Glycosylation of lysine‐containing pentapeptides by glucuronic acid: New insights into the Maillard reaction. Carbohydrate Research, 345(3), 377–384. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carres.2009.11.031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, F., Wu, Q., Song, S., She, R., Zhao, Y., Yang, Y., Zhang, M., Du, F., Soomro, M. H., &amp; Shi, R. (2016). Antimicrobial activity and safety evaluation of peptides isolated from the hemoglobin of chickens. BMC Microbiology, 16, 287. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866‐016‐0904‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huan, Y., Kong, Q., Mou, H., &amp; Yi, H. (2020). Antimicrobial peptides: Classification, design, application and research progress in multiple fields. Frontiers in Microbiology, 11, 582779. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2020.582779</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, E., Hussein, W. E., Campbell, E. P., &amp; Yousef, A. E. (2021). Applications in food technology: Antimicrobial peptides. In Biologically active peptides (pp. 745–770). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐821389‐6.00006‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain, Z., Rafiq, N., Niaz, S., Mohammed Khan, K., Perveen, Z., Mabood, F., Jabeen, F., &amp; Ara, H. (2017). Alkali hydrolyzed conversion of fish scales into protein hydrolysates and evaluation of their antimicrobial activity against different pathogenic bacteria. Journal of the Chemical Society of Pakistan, 39(5), 793–801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussein, N. N. A. (2022). Production of peptide antibiotic bacteriocin using banana peel media. Iranian Journal of Ichthyology, 9, 377–381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibarra‐Sánchez, L. A., El‐Haddad, N., Mahmoud, D., Miller, M. J., &amp; Karam, L. (2020). Invited review: Advances in nisin use for preservation of dairy products. Journal of Dairy Science, 103(3), 2041–2052. https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.2019‐17498</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakas, A., Katić, A., Bionda, N., &amp; Horvat, Š. (2008). Glycation of a lysine‐containing tetrapeptide by d‐glucose and d‐fructose—Influence of different reaction conditions on the formation of Amadori/Heyns products. Carbohydrate Research, 343(14), 2475–2480. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carres.2008.07.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jozala. (2011). Processing of byproducts to improve nisin production by Lactococcus lactis. African Journal of Biotechnology, 10(66), 14920–14925. https://doi.org/10.5897/ajb11.979</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadam, S. U., Tiwari, B. K., Álvarez, C., &amp; O'Donnell, C. P. (2015). Ultrasound applications for the extraction, identification and delivery of food proteins and bioactive peptides. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 46(1), 60–67. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2015.07.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamal, I., Ashfaq, U. A., Hayat, S., Aslam, B., Sarfraz, M. H., Yaseen, H., Rajoka, M. S. R., Shah, A. A., &amp; Khurshid, M. (2023). Prospects of antimicrobial peptides as an alternative to chemical preservatives for food safety. Biotechnology Letters, 45(2), 137–162. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10529‐022‐03328‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamdem, J. P., &amp; Tsopmo, A. (2019). Reactivity of peptides within the food matrix. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 43(1), e12489. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.12489</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotlar, C. E., Ponce, A. G., &amp; Roura, S. I. (2013). Improvement of functional and antimicrobial properties of brewery byproduct hydrolysed enzymatically. LWT, 50(2), 378–385. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2012.09.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kristinsson, H. G., &amp; Rasco, B. A. (2000). Fish protein hydrolysates: Production, biochemical, and functional properties. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 40(1), 43–81. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408690091189266</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kshetri, P., Singh, P. L., Chanu, S. B., Singh, T. S., Rajiv, C., Tamreihao, K., Singh, H. N., Chongtham, T., Devi, A. K., &amp; Sharma, S. K. (2022). Biological activity of peptides isolated from feather keratin waste through microbial and enzymatic hydrolysis. Electronic Journal of Biotechnology, 60, 11–18. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejbt.2022.08.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, K., Yadav, A. N., Kumar, V., Vyas, P., &amp; Dhaliwal, H. S. (2017). Food waste: A potential bioresource for extraction of nutraceuticals and bioactive compounds. Bioresources and Bioprocessing, 4, 18. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40643‐017‐0148‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larichev, T., Yustratov, V., Kurbanova, M., &amp; Voroshilin, R. (2022). Identifying bioactive peptides from poultry by‐products. Food Processing: Techniques and Technology, 52(3), 545–554. https://doi.org/10.21603/2074‐9414‐2022‐3‐2387</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, J.‐K., Gopal, R., Seo, C. H., Cheong, H., &amp; Park, Y. (2012). Isolation and purification of a novel deca‐antifungal peptide from potato (Solanum tuberosum L. cv. Jopung) against Candida albicans. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 13(4), 4021–4032. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms13044021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, T.‐H., Hall, K. N., &amp; Aguilar, M.‐I. (2016). Antimicrobial peptide structure and mechanism of action: A focus on the role of membrane structure. Current Topics in Medicinal Chemistry, 16(1), 25–39. https://doi.org/10.2174/1568026615666150703121700</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei, B., Majumder, K., Shen, S., &amp; Wu, J. (2011). Effect of sonication on thermolysin hydrolysis of ovotransferrin. Food Chemistry, 124(3), 808–815. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.06.100</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemes, A. C., Sala, L., Ores, J. d. C., Braga, A. R. C., Egea, M. B., &amp; Fernandes, K. F. (2016). A review of the latest advances in encrypted bioactive peptides from protein‐rich waste. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 17(6), 950. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms17060950</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leng, W., Wu, X., Xiong, Z., Shi, T., Sun, Q., Yuan, L., &amp; Gao, R. (2022). Study on antibacterial properties of mucus extract of snakehead (Channa argus) against Escherichia coli and its application in chilled fish fillets preservation. LWT, 167, 113840. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2022.113840</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leon Madrazo, A., &amp; Segura Campos, M. R. (2020). Review of antimicrobial peptides as promoters of food safety: Limitations and possibilities within the food industry. Journal of Food Safety, 40(6), e12854. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfs.12854</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, L., Zong, X. Y., Zhang, J., Wei, C. H., Huang, Z. G., &amp; Luo, H. B. (2013). Antibacterial activity of brewer's spent grains peptides to Staphylococcus aureus. Advanced Materials Research, 699, 320–325. https://doi.org/10.4028/www.scientific.net/AMR.699.320</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, S., Mao, Y., Zhang, L., Wang, M., Meng, J., Liu, X., Bai, Y., &amp; Guo, Y. (2022). Recent advances in microbial ε‐poly‐L‐lysine fermentation and its diverse applications. Biotechnology for Biofuels and Bioproducts, 15(1), 65. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13068‐022‐02166‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, T., Wang, X., Wang, Y., Fan, T., Xu, Y., &amp; Fan, Z. (2016). Characterization of antimicrobial peptides isolated from the processing by‐products of African catfish Clarias gariepinus. International Journal of Peptide Research and Therapeutics, 23(2), 227–233. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10989‐016‐9554‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Li, J., Lin, S.‐J., Yang, Z.‐S., &amp; Jin, H.‐X. (2019). Preparation of antioxidant peptide by microwave‐assisted hydrolysis of collagen and its protective effect against H2O2‐induced damage of RAW264.7 cells. Marine Drugs, 17(11), 642. https://doi.org/10.3390/md17110642</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, T., Lu, H., Ma, J., Sun, L., &amp; Wang, J. (2023). Progress on membrane technology for separating bioactive peptides. Journal of Food Engineering, 340, 111321. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2022.111321</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima, K. O., de Quadros, C. d. C., da Rocha, M., de Lacerda, J. T. J. G., Juliano, M. A., Dias, M., Mendes, M. A., &amp; Prentice, C. (2019). Bioactivity and bioaccessibility of protein hydrolyzates from industrial byproducts of stripped weakfish (Cynoscion guatucupa). LWT, 111, 408–413. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2019.05.043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, D., Liu, M., Meng, D., Mu, Y., Wang, T., &amp; Lv, Z. (2022). Harsh sensitivity and mechanism exploration of an antibacterial peptide extracted from walnut oil residue derived from agro‐industrial waste. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70(24), 7460–7470. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.2c02699</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, L., Li, S., Zheng, J., Bu, T., He, G., &amp; Wu, J. (2020). Safety considerations on food protein‐derived bioactive peptides. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 96, 199–207. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2019.12.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Sameen, D. E., Ahmed, S., Dai, J., &amp; Qin, W. (2021). Antimicrobial peptides and their application in food packaging. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 112, 471–483. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2021.04.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, D., Chen, Y., Xie, Q., Qiu, Z., Zhang, H., Sun, P., Pan, J., &amp; Wang, Y. (2022). Preparation of bioactive peptides from marine industrial waste for moon cake preservation by coating. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 46(12), e17221. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.17221</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luz, C., Izzo, L., Graziani, G., Gaspari, A., Ritieni, A., Mañes, J., &amp; Meca, G. (2018). Evaluation of biological and antimicrobial properties of freeze‐dried whey fermented by different strains of Lactobacillus plantarum. Food &amp; Function, 9(7), 3688–3697. https://doi.org/10.1039/C8FO00535D</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luz, C., Izzo, L., Ritieni, A., Manes, J., &amp; Meca, G. (2020). Antifungal and antimycotoxigenic activity of hydrolyzed goat whey on Penicillium spp.: An application as biopreservation agent in pita bread. LWT, 118, 108717. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2019.108717</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majura, J. J., Cao, W., Chen, Z., Htwe, K. K., Li, W., Du, R., Zhang, P., Zheng, H., &amp; Gao, J. (2022). The current research status and strategies employed to modify food‐derived bioactive peptides. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, 950823. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.950823</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marciniak, A., Suwal, S., Naderi, N., Pouliot, Y., &amp; Doyen, A. (2018). Enhancing enzymatic hydrolysis of food proteins and production of bioactive peptides using high hydrostatic pressure technology. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 80, 187–198. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2018.08.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcus, J. P., Goulter, K. C., Green, J. L., Harrison, S. J., &amp; Manners, J. M. (1997). Purification, characterisation and cDNA cloning of an antimicrobial peptide from Macadamia integrifolia. European Journal of Biochemistry, 244(3), 743–749. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1432‐1033.1997.00743.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mardani, M., Badakné, K., Farmani, J., &amp; Aluko, R. E. (2023). Antioxidant peptides: Overview of production, properties, and applications in food systems. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 22(1), 46–106. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.13061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mei, J., Ma, X., &amp; Xie, J. (2019). Review on natural preservatives for extending fish shelf life. Foods, 8(10), 490. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods8100490</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekonnen, T. H., Mussone, P. G., El‐Thaher, N., Choi, P., &amp; Bressler, D. C. (2015). Subcritical hydrolysis and characterization of waste proteinaceous biomass for value added applications. Journal of Chemical Technology &amp; Biotechnology, 90(3), 476–483. https://doi.org/10.1002/jctb.4333</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirzapour‐Kouhdasht, A., McClements, D. J., Taghizadeh, M. S., Niazi, A., &amp; Garcia‐Vaquero, M. (2023). Strategies for oral delivery of bioactive peptides with focus on debittering and masking. Npj Science of Food, 7(1), 22. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41538‐023‐00198‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirzapour‐Kouhdasht, A., Moosavi‐Nasab, M., Lee, C. W., Yun, H., &amp; Eun, J. B. (2021). Structure‐function engineering of novel fish gelatin‐derived multifunctional peptides using high‐resolution peptidomics and bioinformatics. Scientific Reports, 11(1), 7401. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐021‐86808‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moayedi, A., Hashemi, M., &amp; Safari, M. (2016). Valorization of tomato waste proteins through production of antioxidant and antibacterial hydrolysates by proteolytic Bacillus subtilis: Optimization of fermentation conditions. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 53, 391–400. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐015‐1965‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murtaza, M. A., Irfan, S., Hafiz, I., Ranjha, M. M. A., Rahaman, A., Murtaza, M. S., Ibrahim, S. A., &amp; Siddiqui, S. A. (2022). Conventional and novel technologies in the production of dairy bioactive peptides. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, 780151. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.780151</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naderi, N., House, J. D., Pouliot, Y., &amp; Doyen, A. (2017). Effects of high hydrostatic pressure processing on hen egg compounds and egg products. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 16(4), 707–720. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12273</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naghdi, S., Lorenzo, J. M., Mirnejad, R., Ahmadvand, M., &amp; Moosazadeh Moghaddam, M. (2023). Bioactivity evaluation of peptide fractions from bighead carp (Hypophthalmichthys nobilis) using Alcalase and hydrolytic enzymes extracted from Oncorhynchus mykiss and their potential to develop the edible coats. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 16(5), 1128–1148. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐022‐02986‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naghdi, S., Rezaei, M., Tabarsa, M., &amp; Abdollahi, M. (2023). Fish protein hydrolysate from sulfated polysaccharides extraction residue of tuna processing by‐products with bioactive and functional properties. Global Challenges, 7(4), 2200214. https://doi.org/10.1002/gch2.202200214</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ney, K. H. (1979). Bitterness of peptides: Amino acid composition and chain length (Vol. 115). ACS Publications. https://doi.org/10.1021/bk‐1979‐0115.ch006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ockerman, H., &amp; Hansen, C. (2000). Poultry by‐products. In Animal by‐product processing and utilization (pp. 439–455). CRC press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onyeaka, H. N., &amp; Nwabor, O. F. (2022). Food preservation and safety of natural products. Academic Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman, A., Goda, H. A., Abdel‐Hamid, M., Badran, S. M., &amp; Otte, J. (2016). Antibacterial peptides generated by Alcalase hydrolysis of goat whey. LWT, 65, 480–486. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2015.08.043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil, S. M., Sujay, S., Tejaswini, M., Sushma, P., Prithvi, S., &amp; Ramu, R. (2020). Bioactive peptides: Its production and potential role on health. Innovative Food Science and Emerging Technologies, 7, 167–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul, T., Mandal, A., Mandal, S. M., Ghosh, K., Mandal, A. K., Halder, S. K., Das, A., Maji, S. K., Kati, A., &amp; Mohapatra, P. K. D. (2015). Enzymatic hydrolyzed feather peptide, a welcoming drug for multiple‐antibiotic‐resistant Staphylococcus aureus: Structural analysis and characterization. Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology, 175, 3371–3386. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12010‐015‐1509‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pei, J., Jiang, H., Li, X., Jin, W., &amp; Tao, Y. (2017). Antimicrobial peptides sourced from post‐butter processing waste yak milk protein hydrolysates. AMB Express, 7(1), 217. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13568‐017‐0497‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira, N. d. L. Á., Fangio, M. F., Rodriguez, Y. E., Bonadero, M. C., Harán, N. S., &amp; Fernández‐Gimenez, A. V. (2021). Characterization of liquid protein hydrolysates shrimp industry waste: Analysis of antioxidant and microbiological activity, and shelf life of final product. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 46(8), e15526. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.15526</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez, O. E., &amp; Pilosof, A. M. (2004). Pulsed electric fields effects on the molecular structure and gelation of β‐lactoglobulin concentrate and egg white. Food Research International, 37(1), 102–110. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2003.09.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pezeshk, S., Ojagh, S. M., Rezaei, M., &amp; Shabanpour, B. (2019). Fractionation of protein hydrolysates of fish waste using membrane ultrafiltration: Investigation of antibacterial and antioxidant activities. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins, 11, 1015–1022. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12602‐018‐9483‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phoenix, D. A., Dennison, S. R., &amp; Harris, F. (2012). Antimicrobial peptides. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires, A. F., Marnotes, N. G., Rubio, O. D., Garcia, A. C., &amp; Pereira, C. D. (2021). Dairy by‐products: A review on the valorization of whey and second cheese whey. Foods, 10(5), 1067. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10051067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Przybylski, R., Bazinet, L., Firdaous, L., Kouach, M., Goossens, J. F., Dhulster, P., &amp; Nedjar, N. (2020a). Harnessing slaughterhouse by‐products: From wastes to high‐added value natural food preservative. Food Chemistry, 304, 125448. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2019.125448</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Przybylski, R., Bazinet, L., Firdaous, L., Kouach, M., Goossens, J.‐F., Dhulster, P., &amp; Nedjar‐Arroume, N. (2020b). Electroseparation of slaughterhouse by‐product: Antimicrobial peptide enrichment by pH modification. Membranes, 10(5), 90. https://doi.org/10.3390/membranes10050090</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Przybylski, R., Bazinet, L., Kouach, M., Goossens, J.‐F., Dhulster, P., Firdaous, L., &amp; Nedjar‐Arroume, N. (2021). Slaughterhouse by‐product valorization: Hydrolysis degree modification for higher antimicrobial recovery by electroseparation. Waste and Biomass Valorization, 12(4), 1977–1989. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649‐020‐01154‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Przybylski, R., Firdaous, L., Châtaigné, G., Dhulster, P., &amp; Nedjar, N. (2016). Production of an antimicrobial peptide derived from slaughterhouse by‐product and its potential application on meat as preservative. Food Chemistry, 211, 306–313. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.05.074</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qara, S., &amp; Habibi Najafi, M. B. (2018). Bioactive properties of Kilka (Clupeonella cultriventris caspi) fish protein hydrolysates. Journal of Food Measurement and Characterization, 12(4), 2263–2270. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11694‐018‐9843‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin, X., Xu, X., Guo, Y., Shen, Q., Liu, J., Yang, C., Scott, E., Bitter, H., &amp; Zhang, C. (2022). A sustainable and efficient recycling strategy of feather waste into keratin peptides with antimicrobial activity. Waste Management, 144, 421–430.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashidian, G., Abedian Kenari, A., &amp; Nikkhah, M. (2021). Evaluation of antioxidative and antibacterial activities of fractionated hydrolysate from shrimp Litopenaeus vannamei head wastes against aquatic pathogenic bacteria. Aquaculture Research, 52(8), 3696–3704. https://doi.org/10.1111/are.15214</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashidian, G., Moghaddam, M. M., Mirnejad, R., &amp; Azad, Z. M. (2021). Supplementation of zebrafish (Danio rerio) diet using a short antimicrobial peptide: Evaluation of growth performance, immunomodulatory function, antioxidant activity, and disease resistance. Fish &amp; Shellfish Immunology, 119, 42–50. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsi.2021.09.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren, X., Ma, L., Chu, J., Wang, Y., Zhuang, Y., Zhang, S., Yang, H., &amp; An, H. (2012). Optimization of enzymatic hydrolysis of channel catfish bones for preparing antimicrobial agents. Journal of Aquatic Food Product Technology, 21(2), 99–110. https://doi.org/10.1080/10498850.2011.586136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rito‐Palomares, M. (2004). Practical application of aqueous two‐phase partition to process development for the recovery of biological products. Journal of Chromatography B, 807(1), 3–11. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jchromb.2004.01.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert, M., Zatylny‐Gaudin, C., Fournier, V., Corre, E., Le Corguille, G., Bernay, B., &amp; Henry, J. (2014). Transcriptomic and peptidomic analysis of protein hydrolysates from the white shrimp (L. vannamei). Journal of Biotechnology, 186, 30–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbiotec.2014.06.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert, M., Zatylny‐Gaudin, C., Fournier, V., Corre, E., Le Corguillé, G., Bernay, B., &amp; Henry, J. (2015). Molecular characterization of peptide fractions of a Tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus) by‐product hydrolysate and in vitro evaluation of antibacterial activity. Process Biochemistry, 50(3), 487–492. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procbio.2014.12.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakr, M., &amp; Liu, S. (2014). A comprehensive review on applications of ohmic heating (OH). Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews, 39, 262–269. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rser.2014.07.061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salami, M., Moosavi‐Movahedi, A. A., Ehsani, M. R., Yousefi, R., Haertle, T., Chobert, J.‐M., Razavi, S. H., Henrich, R., Balalaie, S., &amp; Ebadi, S. A. (2010). Improvement of the antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of camel and bovine whey proteins by limited proteolysis. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 58(6), 3297–3302. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf9033283</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez‐Gomez, S., Lamata, M., Leiva, J., Blondelle, S. E., Jerala, R., Andra, J., Brandenburg, K., Lohner, K., Moriyon, I., &amp; Martinez‐de‐Tejada, G. (2008). Comparative analysis of selected methods for the assessment of antimicrobial and membrane‐permeabilizing activity: A case study for lactoferricin derived peptides. BMC Microbiology, 8, 196. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471‐2180‐8‐196</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez‐Reinoso, Z., Cournoyer, A., Thibodeau, J., Said, L. B., Fliss, I., Bazinet, L., &amp; Mikhaylin, S. (2021). Effect of pH on the antimicrobial activity and peptide population of pepsin hydrolysates derived from bovine and porcine hemoglobins. ACS Food Science &amp; Technology, 1(9), 1687–1701. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsfoodscitech.1c00141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, J. C. P., Sousa, R. C. S., Otoni, C. G., Moraes, A. R. F., Souza, V. G. L., Medeiros, E. A. A., Espitia, P. J. P., Pires, A. C. S., Coimbra, J. S. R., &amp; Soares, N. F. F. (2018). Nisin and other antimicrobial peptides: Production, mechanisms of action, and application in active food packaging. Innovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies, 48, 179–194. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2018.06.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasidharan, A., &amp; Venugopal, V. (2020). Proteins and co‐products from seafood processing discards: Their recovery, functional properties and applications. Waste and Biomass Valorization, 11, 5647–5663. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649‐019‐00812‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seo, Y., Sung, M., Hwang, J., &amp; Yoon, Y. (2023). Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of propionic acid, sorbic acid, and benzoic acid against food spoilage microorganisms in animal products to use MIC as threshold for natural preservative production. Food Science of Animal Resources, 43(2), 319–330. https://doi.org/10.5851/kosfa.2022.e79</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, P., Kaur, J., Sharma, G., &amp; Kashyap, P. (2022). Plant derived antimicrobial peptides: Mechanism of target, isolation techniques, sources and pharmaceutical applications. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 46(10), e14348. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.14348</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, R., Garg, P., Kumar, P., Bhatia, S. K., &amp; Kulshrestha, S. (2020). Microbial fermentation and its role in quality improvement of fermented foods. Fermentation, 6(4), 106. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation6040106</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, S. (2015). Food preservatives and their harmful effects. International Journal of Scientific and Research Publications, 5(4), 1–2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, X., Zhang, M., Bhandari, B., &amp; Gao, Z. (2019). Novel technologies in utilization of byproducts of animal food processing: A review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 59(21), 3420–3430. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2018.1493428</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shishir, M. R. I., Xie, L., Sun, C., Zheng, X., &amp; Chen, W. (2018). Advances in micro and nano‐encapsulation of bioactive compounds using biopolymer and lipid‐based transporters. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 78, 34–60. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2018.05.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shwaiki, L. N., Lynch, K. M., &amp; Arendt, E. K. (2021). Future of antimicrobial peptides derived from plants in food application – A focus on synthetic peptides. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 112, 312–324. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2021.04.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shwaiki, L. N., Sahin, A. W., &amp; Arendt, E. K. (2020). Study on the inhibitory activity of a synthetic defensin derived from barley endosperm against common food spoilage yeast. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 26(1), 165. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26010165</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, R., Langyan, S., Sangwan, S., Rohtagi, B., Khandelwal, A., &amp; Shrivastava, M. (2022). Protein for human consumption from oilseed cakes: A review. Frontiers in Sustainable Food Systems, 6, 856401. https://doi.org/10.3389/fsufs.2022.856401</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinkiewicz, I., Staroszczyk, H., &amp; Śliwińska, A. (2018). Solubilization of keratins and functional properties of their isolates and hydrolysates. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 42(2), e12494. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.12494</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sriariyanun, M., Muangrod, P., Charoenchokpanich, W., Roytrakul, S., Rungsardthong, V., Vatanyoopaisarn, S., Charoenlappanit, S., Wonganu, B., Thumthanaruk, B., Cheng, Y., Bhattacharyya, D., Rodiahwati, W., &amp; Jayex Panakkal, E. (2022). Effect of pepsin on antioxidant and antibacterial activity of protein hydrolysate from salted jellyfish (Lobonema smithii and Rhopilema hispidum) by‐products. E3S Web of Conferences, 355, 02013. https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202235502013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sridhar, K., Inbaraj, B. S., &amp; Chen, B.‐H. (2021). Recent developments on production, purification and biological activity of marine peptides. Food Research International, 147, 110468. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110468</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tacias‐Pascacio, V. G., Morellon‐Sterling, R., Siar, E.‐H., Tavano, O., Berenguer‐Murcia, A., &amp; Fernandez‐Lafuente, R. (2020). Use of Alcalase in the production of bioactive peptides: A review. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 165, 2143–2196. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.10.060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, Y. N., Ayob, M. K., &amp; Matthews, K. R. (2013). Comparative antibacterial activity of tryptic‐hydrolyzed palm kernel cake proteins of different degrees of hydrolysis. Journal of Food Quality, 36(6), 447–456. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfq.12061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, Y. N., Ayob, M. K., &amp; Wan Yaacob, W. A. (2013). Purification and characterisation of antibacterial peptide‐containing compound derived from palm kernel cake. Food Chemistry, 136(1), 279–284. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2012.08.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, Y. N., Matthews, K. R., Di, R., &amp; Ayob, M. K. (2012). Bacteriostatic mode of action of trypsin‐hydrolyzed palm kernel expeller peptide against Bacillus cereus. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins, 4(1), 59–65. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12602‐012‐9091‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, S.‐S., Prodhan, Z. H., Biswas, S. K., Le, C.‐F., &amp; Sekaran, S. D. (2018). Antimicrobial peptides from different plant sources: Isolation, characterisation, and purification. Phytochemistry, 154, 94–105. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.07.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, W., Zhang, H., Wang, L., Qian, H., &amp; Qi, X. (2015). Targeted separation of antibacterial peptide from protein hydrolysate of anchovy cooking wastewater by equilibrium dialysis. Food Chemistry, 168, 115–123. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.07.027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taniguchi, M., Aida, R., Saito, K., Oya, R., Ochiai, A., Saitoh, E., &amp; Tanaka, T. (2020). Identification of cationic peptides derived from low protein rice by‐products and evaluation of their multifunctional activities. Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering, 129(3), 307–314. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbiosc.2019.09.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Théolier, J., Hammami, R., Labelle, P., Fliss, I., &amp; Jean, J. (2013). Isolation and identification of antimicrobial peptides derived by peptic cleavage of whey protein isolate. Journal of Functional Foods, 5(2), 706–714. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2013.01.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thery, T., Lynch, K. M., &amp; Arendt, E. K. (2019). Natural antifungal peptides/proteins as model for novel food preservatives. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 18(5), 1327–1360. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12480</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thery, T., Lynch, K. M., Zannini, E., &amp; Arendt, E. K. (2020). Isolation, characterisation and application of a new antifungal protein from broccoli seeds–New food preservative with great potential. Food Control, 117, 107356. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107356</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toldrà, M., Lynch, S. A., Couture, R., &amp; Álvarez, C. (2019). Blood proteins as functional ingredients. In Sustainable meat production and processing (pp. 85–101). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐814874‐7.00005‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tovar‐Jiménez, X., Muro‐Urista, C. R., Tellez‐Jurado, A., Mercado‐Flores, Y., Abreu‐Corona, A., &amp; Arana‐Cuenca, A. (2017). Hydrolysate antimicrobial activity released from bovine whey protein concentrate by the aspartyl protease Eap1 of Sporisorium reilianum. Revista Mexicana De Ingeniería Química, 16(1), 11–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchida, K., &amp; Stadtman, E. (1992). Modification of histidine residues in proteins by reaction with 4‐hydroxynonenal. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 89(10), 4544–4548. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.89.10.4544</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulug, S. K., Jahandideh, F., &amp; Wu, J. (2021). Novel technologies for the production of bioactive peptides. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 108, 27–39. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2020.12.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma, A. K., Chatli, M. K., Mehta, N., &amp; Kumar, P. (2022). Antimicrobial and antioxidant potential of papain liver hydrolysate in meat emulsion model at chilling storage under aerobic packaging condition. Waste and Biomass Valorization, 13, 417–429. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649‐021‐01538‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidal, A. R., Cansian, R. L., Mello, R. d. O., Demiate, I. M., Kempka, A. P., Dornelles, R. C. P., Rodriguez, J. M. L., &amp; Campagnol, P. C. B. (2022). Production of collagens and protein hydrolysates with antimicrobial and antioxidant activity from sheep slaughter by‐products. Antioxidants, 11(6), 1173. https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox11061173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilas‐Boas, A. A., Pintado, M., &amp; Oliveira, A. L. (2021). Natural bioactive compounds from food waste: Toxicity and safety concerns. Foods, 10(7), 1564. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10071564</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voroshilin, R. A., Kurbanova, M. G., Yustratov, V. P., &amp; Larichev, T. A. (2022). Identifying bioactive peptides from poultry by‐products. Food Processing: Techniques &amp; Technology, 52(3), 545–554. https://doi.org/10.21603/2074‐9414‐2022‐3‐2387</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wafaa, N., Elbarbary, H., Ibrahim, E., Mohamed, H., &amp; Jenssen, H. (2022). Effect of enzyme type and hydrolysis time on antibacterial and antioxidant activity of whey protein hydrolysates. Iraqi Journal of Agricultural Sciences, 53(6), 1340–1357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wald, M., Schwarz, K., Rehbein, H., Bußmann, B., &amp; Beermann, C. (2016). Detection of antibacterial activity of an enzymatic hydrolysate generated by processing rainbow trout by‐products with trout pepsin. Food Chemistry, 205, 221–228. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.03.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, G. (2017). Antimicrobial peptides: Discovery, design, and novel therapeutic strategies. CABI.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Sun, J., Ding, S., &amp; Qi, B. (2018). Isolation and identification of novel antioxidant and antimicrobial oligopeptides from enzymatically hydrolyzed anchovy fish meal. Process Biochemistry, 74, 148–155. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procbio.2018.08.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, M., Zhou, J., Pallarés, N., Bäuerl, C., Collado, M. C., Dar, B. N., &amp; Barba, F. J. (2021). Role of extracts obtained from rainbow trout and sole side streams by accelerated solvent extraction and pulsed electric fields on modulating bacterial and anti‐inflammatory activities. Separations, 8(10), 187. https://doi.org/10.3390/separations8100187</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Han, Z., Ji, R., Xiao, Y., Si, R., Guo, F., He, J., Hai, L., Ming, L., &amp; Yi, L. (2020). Antibacterial activity of trypsin‐hydrolyzed camel and cow whey and their fractions. Animals (Basel), 10(2), 337. https://doi.org/10.3390/ani10020337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wójciak, K. M., Karwowska, M., &amp; Dolatowski, Z. J. (2014). Use of acid whey and mustard seed to replace nitrites during cooked sausage production. Meat Science, 96(2), 750–756. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2013.09.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, Y., Peng, X., Li, Z., Wang, J., Li, M., Xiao, S., &amp; Zhang, S. (2022). Production and fermentation characteristics of antifungal peptides by synergistic interactions with Lactobacillus paracasei and Propionibacterium freudenii in supplemented whey protein formulations. LWT, 164, 113632. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2022.113632</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yujia, X., Peng, X., Li, Z., Wang, J., Li, M., Xiao, S., &amp; Zhang, S. (2022). Production and fermentation characteristics of antifungal peptides by synergistic interactions with Lactobacillus paracasei and Propionibacterium freudenii in supplemented whey protein formulations. LWT, 164, 113632. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2022.113632</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaky, A. A., Simal‐Gandara, J., Eun, J.‐B., Shim, J.‐H., &amp; Abd El‐Aty, A. (2022). Bioactivities, applications, safety, and health benefits of bioactive peptides from food and by‐products: A review. Frontiers in Nutrition, 8, 815640. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2021.815640</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Q., Zhou, H., Zhai, S., &amp; Yan, B. (2010). Natural product‐inspired synthesis of thiazolidine and thiazolidinone compounds and their anticancer activities. Current Pharmaceutical Design, 16(16), 1826–1842. https://doi.org/10.2174/138161210791208983</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., &amp; Ho, C. T. (1989). Volatile compounds formed from thermal interaction of 2, 4‐decadienal with cysteine and glutathione. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 37(4), 1016–1020. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf00088a044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, J., Han, Q., Koyama, T., &amp; Ishizaki, S. (2023). Preparation, purification and characterization of antibacterial and ACE inhibitory peptides from head protein hydrolysate of kuruma shrimp, Marsupenaeus japonicus. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 28(2), 894. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules28020894</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinina, O., Merenkova, S., Rebezov, M., Galimov, D., Khayrullin, M., &amp; Burkov, P. (2022). Physicochemical, functional, and technological properties of protein hydrolysates obtained by microbial fermentation of broiler chicken gizzards. Fermentation, 8(7), 317. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation8070317</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>