<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">39244275</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1474-547X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>404</Volume><Issue>10456</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Lancet (London, England)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The global blood donation index: an imperfect measure of transfusion need.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>988</StartPage><EndPage>990</EndPage><MedlinePgn>988-990</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01550-2</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0140-6736(24)01550-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The optimum number of units of blood and the associated number of blood donors required to meet a given population's needs remain undetermined globally. Typically, a whole blood donation rate of ten donations per 1000 population, at a minimum, is necessary to meet a country's blood needs. This rate is attributed to a WHO recommendation that 1% of a given country's population should donate blood to ensure a blood supply that is sufficient to meet clinical needs. This often cited metric was first referenced in a 1971 WHO report, yet neither supporting data or references were provided, suggesting that it was flawed at its founding. Regardless, this metric does not provide an accurate or contemporary determination of blood needs, which has ramifications for health service provision and planning, particularly in low-income and lower-middle-income countries. Modelling studies that account for geographical variability in disease burden, health-care infrastructure, and transfusion practices are needed to accurately estimate blood needs. A paucity of data to inform modelling remains a major obstacle in this regard. We discuss the history of the global blood donation index and highlight some factors that should be considered to better understand contemporary blood needs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jacobs</LastName><ForeName>Jeremy W</ForeName><Initials>JW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Microbiology, and Immunology, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bates</LastName><ForeName>Imelda</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine, Liverpool, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cohn</LastName><ForeName>Claudia S</ForeName><Initials>CS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA; Association for the Advancement of Blood and Biotherapies, Bethesda, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choudhury</LastName><ForeName>Nabajyoti</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dibrugarh Cancer Center, ACCF, Dibrugarh, Assam, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Owusu-Ofori</LastName><ForeName>Shirley</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Blood Service Ghana, Kumasi, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vrielink</LastName><ForeName>Hans</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Unit of Transfusion Medicine of Sanquin Blood Supply, Sanquin Blood Supply Foundation, Amsterdam, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Eshan U</ForeName><Initials>EU</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wendel</LastName><ForeName>Silvano</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Sírio-Libanês Blood Bank, Săo Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tobian</LastName><ForeName>Aaron A R</ForeName><Initials>AAR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Transfusion Medicine, Department of Pathology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bloch</LastName><ForeName>Evan M</ForeName><Initials>EM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Transfusion Medicine, Department of Pathology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA. Electronic address: ebloch2@jhmi.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985213R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0140-6736</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000094345" MajorTopicYN="Y">Blood Donation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000600" MajorTopicYN="N">supply &amp; distribution</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001803" MajorTopicYN="Y">Blood Transfusion</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003906" MajorTopicYN="N">Developing Countries</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014943" MajorTopicYN="Y">Global Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006301" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Services Needs and Demand</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020380" MajorTopicYN="N">Needs Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014944" MajorTopicYN="N">World Health Organization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests AART has received financial support from Ortho Clinical Diagnostics, Ashland Global, and UptoDate; and is the principal investigator of a US Government funded clinical trial evaluating Mirasol Pathogen Reduction Technology. EMB has received financial support from Grifols, Abbott, UptoDate, Tegus, and Health Advances; is a co-investigator on a US Government funded clinical trial evaluating Mirasol Pathogen Reduction Technology; and is a member of the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Blood Products Advisory Committee. CSC reports personal fees from QuidelOrtho and Fresenius Kabi; is a co-investigator on a US Government funded translational research initiative to improve blood safety in sub-Saharan Africa; is the site principal investigator on a US Government funded clinical trial to evaluate cold stored platelets; is the chair of the US Advisory Committee for Blood and Tissue Safety and Availability (ACBTSA); and is the chief medical officer of the Association for the Advancement of Blood and Biotherapies (AABB). AART is the President of AABB. SO-O is a Regional Director and board member of the International Society of Blood Transfusion (ISBT) for Africa. All other authors declare no competing interests. Any views or opinions expressed in this manuscript are the authors’ own and do not necessarily represent the views of the Blood Products Advisory Committee, the FDA, the ACBTSA, the AABB, and the ISBT.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39244275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01550-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0140-6736(24)01550-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>