<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39243533</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-3460</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>426</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of food microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Food Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Formation and resuscitation of viable but non-culturable (VBNC) yeast in the food industry: A review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>110901</StartPage><MedlinePgn>110901</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2024.110901</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0168-1605(24)00345-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The viable but non-culturable (VBNC) state is a survival strategy adopted by microorganisms in response to unfavorable conditions in the environment. VBNC cells are unable to form colonies but still maintain a low level of activity, posing a potential threat to food safety and public health. Therefore, the development of effective strategies to prevent the formation and resuscitation of VBNC cells of microorganisms is a key challenge in food science and microbiology research. However, current research on VBNC cells has primarily focused on bacteria, with relatively limited reports on fungi. This paper provides a comprehensive and systematic review of yeast in the VBNC state, discussing various factors that induce and facilitate resuscitation, along with detection methods and formation and recovery mechanisms. A comprehensive understanding of the induction and resuscitation of yeast in the VBNC state and exploration of its molecular mechanism hold significant implications for food safety and public health. It is imperative to enhance our comprehension of the underlying mechanisms and contributory factors pertaining to VBNC yeast, thereby facilitating the efficient management of the food fermentation process and ensuring the integrity of food quality and safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiao</LastName><ForeName>Yang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; School of Food Engineering, Qingdao Institute of Technology, Qingdao 266300, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jiayang</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Key Laboratory of Special Food Processing (Co-construction by Ministry and Province), Ministry of Agriculture Rural Affairs, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Shandong Technology Innovation Center of Special Food, Qingdao 266109, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Pengdong</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Key Laboratory of Special Food Processing (Co-construction by Ministry and Province), Ministry of Agriculture Rural Affairs, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Shandong Technology Innovation Center of Special Food, Qingdao 266109, China; Qingdao Special Food Research Institute, Qingdao 266109, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ding</LastName><ForeName>Ting</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Key Laboratory of Special Food Processing (Co-construction by Ministry and Province), Ministry of Agriculture Rural Affairs, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Shandong Technology Innovation Center of Special Food, Qingdao 266109, China; Qingdao Special Food Research Institute, Qingdao 266109, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jingyuan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Key Laboratory of Special Food Processing (Co-construction by Ministry and Province), Ministry of Agriculture Rural Affairs, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Shandong Technology Innovation Center of Special Food, Qingdao 266109, China; Qingdao Special Food Research Institute, Qingdao 266109, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deng</LastName><ForeName>Yang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Key Laboratory of Special Food Processing (Co-construction by Ministry and Province), Ministry of Agriculture Rural Affairs, Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao 266109, China; Shandong Technology Innovation Center of Special Food, Qingdao 266109, China; Qingdao Special Food Research Institute, Qingdao 266109, China. Electronic address: dengyang719@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Food Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8412849</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0168-1605</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food processing and storage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Formation mechanism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Resuscitation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">VBNC state</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Yeast</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest We declare that we have no financial and personal relationships with other people or organizations that can inappropriately influence our work, there is no professional or other personal interest of any nature or kind in any product, service and/or company that could be construed as influencing the position presented in, or the review of, the manuscript entitled “Formation and Resuscitation of Viable but Non-culturable (VBNC) Yeast in the Food Industry: A Review”.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39243533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2024.110901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0168-1605(24)00345-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>