<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39257496</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2590-1575</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food chemistry: X</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem X</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of acrylamide concentration in commercial falafel available in Tehran City by different cooking methods: A health risk assessment study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>101750</StartPage><MedlinePgn>101750</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">101750</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.fochx.2024.101750</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The objective of current research was to measure the amount of acrylamide in falafel samples by GC-MS (Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry) technique. The results presented, the average amount of acrylamide in falafel samples was 1.23 ± 0.83 mg/kg (ranged from 0.12 to 3.75 mg/kg). Also, the results showed lower temperature and frying with electric oven and low oil, reduces the average formation of acrylamide (0.73 ± 0.42 mg/kg), while frying at high temperature and frying with gas and immersion in edible oil, increases the average amount of acrylamide formation (1.72 ± 0.86 mg/kg). The highest and lowest average amount of acrylamide was observed in falafel cooked with canola oil (1.57 ± 0.96 mg/kg) and cooked with soybean oil (0.92 ± 0.32 mg/kg), respectively. Based on the MCS (Monte Carlo Simulation) results, the THQ (Target Hazard Quotient) and ILCR (Incremental Lifetime Cancer Risk) related to exposure to acrylamide via commercial falafel for adults were 2.72E-2 and 2.77E-5; and for children were 9.69E-2 and 9.25E-5, respectively. Therefore, there doesn't a significant health risk from falafel consumption.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Faraji</LastName><ForeName>Fahimeh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Hygiene, Ayatollah Amoli Branch, Islamic Azad University, Amol, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shahidi</LastName><ForeName>Seyed-Ahmad</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, Ayatollah Amoli Branch, Islamic Azad University, Amol, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shariatifar</LastName><ForeName>Nabi</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmadi</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Hygiene, Ayatollah Amoli Branch, Islamic Azad University, Amol, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem X</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101751436</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2590-1575</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Edible oil</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Incremental lifetime Cancer risk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Monte Carlo simulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Target hazard quotient</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose. The authors declare that they have no competing interests. The study does not involve any human or animal testing, the authors declare, and they do not have any conflicts of interest. The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39257496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11386257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fochx.2024.101750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2590-1575(24)00638-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>(EU), C. R . 2017. Establishing mitigation measures and benchmark levels for the reduction of the presence of acrylamide in food, 2017/2158 of 20 November 2017. (Official Journal of the European Union)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aghvami M., Mohammadi A., Khaniki G.J., Ahmadi M., Moazzen M., Arabameri M., Shariatifar N. Investigation of cocoa and cinnamon effect on acrylamide formation in cakes production using GC/MS method: A risk assessment study. Food Chemistry: X. 2023;18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10023898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36941961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Başaran B., Çuvalcı B., Kaban G. Dietary acrylamide exposure and cancer risk: A systematic approach to human epidemiological studies. Foods. 2023;12(2):346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9858116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36673439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biedermann M., Grundböck F., Fiselier K., Biedermann S., Bürgi C., Grob K. Acrylamide monitoring in Switzerland, 2007–2009: Results and conclusions. Food Additives and Contaminants. 2010;27(10):1352–1362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20730646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çebi A. Elsevier; 2024. Acrylamide intake, its effects on tissues and cancer acrylamide in food; pp. 65–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission, E . 2011. Commission recommendation of 10.1. 2011 on investigations into the levels of acrylamide in food.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delgado-Andrade C., Mesías M., Morales F.J., Seiquer I., Navarro M.P. Assessment of acrylamide intake of Spanish boys aged 11–14 years consuming a traditional and balanced diet. LWT-Food Science and Technology. 2012;46(1):16–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eerola S., Hollebekkers K., Hallikainen A., Peltonen K. Acrylamide levels in Finnish foodstuffs analysed with liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry. Molecular Nutrition &amp; Food Research. 2007;51(2):239–247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17230586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Ziney M., Al-Turki A., Tawfik M. Acrylamide status in selected traditional saudi foods and infant milk and foods with estimation of daily exposure. American Journal of Food Technology. 2009;4(5):177–191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA . 2022. U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11645578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fikry M., Khalifa I., Sami R., Khojah E., Ismail K.A., Dabbour M. Optimization of the frying temperature and time for preparation of healthy falafel using air frying technology. Foods. 2021;10(11):2567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8625143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34828848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gazi S., Taş N.G., Görgülü A., Gökmen V. Effectiveness of asparaginase on reducing acrylamide formation in bakery products according to their dough type and properties. Food Chemistry. 2023;402</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36126579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karimi F., Rezaei M., Shariatifar N., Alikord M., Arabameri M., Moazzen M. Probabilistic health risk assessment and concentration of trace elements in meat, egg, and milk of Iran. International Journal of Environmental Analytical Chemistry. 2023;103(18):6940–6951.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur N., Halford N.G. Reducing the risk of acrylamide and other processing contaminant formation in wheat products. Foods. 2023;12(17):3264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10486470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37685197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalili F., Shariatifar N., Dehghani M.H., Yaghmaeian K., Nodehi R.N., Yaseri M., Arabameri M. The analysis and probabilistic health risk assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in cereal products. Environmental Science and Pollution Research. 2022;29:31099–31109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35000169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitson F.G., Larsen B.S., McEwen C.N. Academic Press; 1996. Gas chromatography and mass spectrometry: A practical guide.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knol J.J., Viklund G.Å., Linssen J.P., Sjöholm I.M., Skog K.I., van Boekel M.A. Kinetic modelling: A tool to predict the formation of acrylamide in potato crisps. Food Chemistry. 2009;113(1):103–109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18320572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konings E.J., Baars A., van Klaveren J.D., Spanjer M., Rensen P., Hiemstra M., Peters P. Acrylamide exposure from foods of the Dutch population and an assessment of the consequent risks. Food and Chemical Toxicology. 2003;41(11):1569–1579.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12963010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao C.-M., Chio C.-P., Chen W.-Y., Ju Y.-R., Li W.-H., Cheng Y.-H., Ling M.-P. Lung cancer risk in relation to traffic-related nano/ultrafine particle-bound PAHs exposure: A preliminary probabilistic assessment. Journal of Hazardous Materials. 2011;190(1–3):150–158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21458918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu R., Sobue T., Kitamura T., Kitamura Y., Ishihara J., Kotemori A., Iwasaki M. Dietary Acrylamide Intake and Risk of Esophageal, Gastric, and Colorectal Cancer: The Japan Public Health Center–Based Prospective Study. Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp; Prevention. 2019;28(9):1461–1468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31186264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthäus B., Haase N.U., Vosmann K. Factors affecting the concentration of acrylamide during deep-fat frying of potatoes. European Journal of Lipid Science and Technology. 2004;106(11):793–801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthys C., Bilau M., Govaert Y., Moons E., De Henauw S., Willems J. Risk assessment of dietary acrylamide intake in Flemish adolescents. Food and Chemical Toxicology. 2005;43(2):271–278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15621340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehraie A., Shariatifar N., Arabameri M., Moazzen M., Mortazavian A.M., Sheikh F., Sohrabvandi S. Determination of phthalate acid esters (PAEs) in bottled water distributed in Tehran: A health risk assessment study. International Journal of Environmental Analytical Chemistry. 2024;104(10):2417–2431.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mojska H., Gielecińska I., Szponar L., Ołtarzewski M. Estimation of the dietary acrylamide exposure of the polish population. Food and Chemical Toxicology. 2010;48(8–9):2090–2096.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20470853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mousavi Khaneghah A., Fakhri Y., Nematollahi A., Seilani F., Vasseghian Y. The concentration of acrylamide in different food products: A global systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression. Food Reviews International. 2022;38(6):1286–1304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Normandin L., Bouchard M., Ayotte P., Blanchet C., Becalski A., Bonvalot Y., Courteau M. Dietary exposure to acrylamide in adolescents from a Canadian urban center. Food and Chemical Toxicology. 2013;57:75–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23517909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nwoke S., Ekere N., Abugu H., Ihedioha J., Ezike C., Odum P., Eze S. Potential toxic elements (PTEs) and the health risk impact of some dairy products marketed in Nigeria. Eurasian Journal of Analytical Chemistry. 2021;16(2):01–09.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedreschi F., Kaack K., Granby K. Reduction of acrylamide formation in potato slices during frying. LWT-Food Science and Technology. 2004;37(6):679–685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pugajeva I., Zumbure L., Melngaile A., Bartkevics V. 2014. Determination of acrylamide levels in selected foods in Latvia and assessment of the population intake. 111-116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romani S., Bacchiocca M., Rocculi P., Dalla Rosa M. Effect of frying time on acrylamide content and quality aspects of French fries. European Food Research and Technology. 2008;226:555–560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roudbari A., Nazari R.R., Shariatifar N., Moazzen M., Abdolshahi A., Mirzamohammadi S., Arabameri M. Concentration and health risk assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in commercial tea and coffee samples marketed in Iran. Environmental Science and Pollution Research. 2021;28(4):4827–4839.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32949359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleh S.I., El-Okazy A.M. Assessment of the mean daily dietary intake of acrylamide in alexandria. The Journal of the Egyptian Public Health Association. 2007;82(3–4):331–345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18410716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seilani F., Shariatifar N., Nazmara S., Khaniki G.J., Sadighara P., Arabameri M. The analysis and probabilistic health risk assessment of acrylamide level in commercial nuggets samples marketed in Iran: Effect of two different cooking methods. Journal of Environmental Health Science and Engineering. 2021;19:465–473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8172649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34150250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahbazi R., Adergani B.A., Shariatifar N., Jafari K., Taheri E., Fathabad A.E., Khaneghah A.M. Assessment of food additives impact on acrylamide formation in popcorn supplied in Tehran, Iran: A risk assessment study. Carpathian Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology. 2022;14(4):216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahsavari S., Shariatifar N., Arabameri M., Mahmoudi R., Moazzen M., Ghajarbeygi P. Analysis of polychlorinated biphenyls in cream and ice cream using modified QuEChERS extraction and GC-QqQ-MS/MS method: A risk assessment study. International Journal of Dairy Technology. 2022;75(2):448–459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams J. Influence of variety and processing conditions on acrylamide levels in fried potato crisps. Food Chemistry. 2005;90(4):875–881.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaminifar S., Aeenehvand S., Ghelichkhani G., Ahmadloo M., Arabameri M., Moazzen M., Shariatifar N. The measurement and health risk assessment of polychlorinated biphenyls in butter samples using the QuEChERS/GC-MS method. International Journal of Dairy Technology. 2021;74(4):737–746.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu W.Z., Shen P., Lim I., Shi R.R.S., Cai M., Chin Y.S., Lim G.S. Occurrence and dietary exposure to acrylamide from foods consumed within and outside main meals in Singapore. Foods. 2023;12(16):3022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10453405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37628020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y., Duan X., Qin N., Lv J., Wu G., Wei F. Health risk from dietary exposure to polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in a typical high cancer incidence area in Southwest China. Science of the Total Environment. 2019;649:731–738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30176483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>