<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39258362</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1524-4539</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>150</Volume><Issue>15</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Circulation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Circulation</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Pulsed Field Ablation to Treat Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation: Safety and Effectiveness in the AdmIRE Pivotal Trial.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1174</StartPage><EndPage>1186</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1174-1186</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.124.070333</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Evidence from clinical trials of early pulsed field ablation (PFA) systems in treating atrial fibrillation has demonstrated their promising potential to reduce complications associated with conventional thermal modalities while maintaining efficacy. However, the lack of a fully integrated mapping system, a staple technology of most modern electrophysiology procedures, poses limitations in lesion creation and workflow options. A novel variable-loop PFA catheter integrated with an electroanatomic mapping system has been developed that allows for real-time nonfluoroscopic procedural guidance and lesion indexing as well as feedback of tissue-to-catheter proximity. AdmIRE (Assessment of Safety and Effectiveness in Treatment Management of Atrial Fibrillation With the Bosense-Webster Irreversible Electroporation Ablation System), a multicenter, single-arm, Food and Drug Administration investigational device exemption study, evaluated the long-term safety and effectiveness of this integrated PFA system in a large United States-based drug-refractory symptomatic paroxysmal atrial fibrillation patient population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Using the PFA catheter with a compatible electroanatomic mapping system, patients with drug-refractory symptomatic paroxysmal atrial fibrillation underwent pulmonary vein isolation. The primary safety end point was primary adverse event within 7 days of ablation. The primary effectiveness end point was a composite end point that included 12-month freedom from documented atrial tachyarrhythmia (ie, atrial fibrillation, atrial tachycardia, atrial flutter) episodes, failure to achieve pulmonary vein isolation, use of a nonstudy catheter for pulmonary vein isolation, repeat procedure (except for one redo during blanking), taking a new or previously failed class I or III antiarrhythmic drug at higher dose after blanking, or direct current cardioversion after blanking.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">At 30 centers, 277 patients with paroxysmal atrial fibrillation (61.5±10.3 years of age; 64.3% male) in the pivotal cohort underwent PFA. More than 25% of the procedures were performed without fluoroscopy. Median (Q1, Q3) pulmonary vein isolation procedure, fluoroscopy, and transpired PFA application times were 81.0 (61.0, 112.0), 7.1 (0.00, 14.3), and 31.0 (24.8, 40.9) minutes, respectively. The primary adverse event rate was 2.9% (8 of 272), with the most common complication being pericardial tamponade. The 12-month primary effectiveness end point was 74.6%. The 1-year freedom from atrial fibrillation, atrial tachycardia, or atrial flutter recurrence rate after blanking was 75.4%. Substantial improvements in quality of life were observed as early as 3 months after the procedure, concurrent with a reduction in multiple health care use measures.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">AdmIRE confirmed the safety and effectiveness of the variable-loop PFA catheter, with short procedure and PFA application times and low fluoroscopy exposure.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">URL: https://www.clinicaltrials.gov; Unique identifier: NCT05293639.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reddy</LastName><ForeName>Vivek Y</ForeName><Initials>VY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Helmsley Electrophysiology Center, Mount Sinai Fuster Heart Hospital, New York, NY (V.Y.R.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Calkins</LastName><ForeName>Hugh</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9262-9433</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions, Baltimore, MD (H.C.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mansour</LastName><ForeName>Moussa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston (M.M.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wazni</LastName><ForeName>Oussama</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7115-7716</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cleveland Clinic Foundation, OH (O.W., A.H.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Di Biase</LastName><ForeName>Luigi</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6508-4047</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Montefiore Health System at Albert Einstein College of Medicine, New York, NY (L.D.B.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bahu</LastName><ForeName>Marwan</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Phoenix Cardiovascular Research Group, AZ (M.B.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Newton</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Memorial Health University Medical Center, Savannah, GA (D. Newton).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Christopher F</ForeName><Initials>CF</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8852-4551</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New York Presbyterian-Weill Cornell Medicine, NY (C.F.L.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sauer</LastName><ForeName>William H</ForeName><Initials>WH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-8556-3612</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brigham &amp; Women's Hospital, Boston, MA (W.H.S.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goyal</LastName><ForeName>Sandeep</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6915-9835</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Piedmont Heart Institute, Atlanta, GA (S.G.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iyer</LastName><ForeName>Vivek</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Marin Health Medical Center, Larkspur, CA (V.I.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nair</LastName><ForeName>Devi</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8253-947X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>St. Bernard's Medical Center &amp; Arrhythmia Research Group, Jonesboro, AR (D. Nair).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Athill</LastName><ForeName>Charles</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0001-9423-2261</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>San Diego Cardiac Center, CA (C.A.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hussein</LastName><ForeName>Ayman</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8359-1525</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cleveland Clinic Foundation, OH (O.W., A.H.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Whalen</LastName><ForeName>Patrick</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wake Forest Baptist Health, Winston-Salem, NC (P.W.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Melby</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Minneapolis Heart Institute, MN (D.M.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Natale</LastName><ForeName>Andrea</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5487-0728</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Texas Cardiac Arrhythmia Research Foundation, Austin (A.N.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedicine and Prevention, Division of Cardiology, University of Tor Vergata, Rome, Italy (A.N.).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>AdmIRE Trial Investigators</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT05293639</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016448">Multicenter Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016430">Clinical Trial</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Circulation</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0147763</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0009-7322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001281" MajorTopicYN="Y">Atrial Fibrillation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000601" MajorTopicYN="N">surgery</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017115" MajorTopicYN="Y">Catheter Ablation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000295" MajorTopicYN="N">instrumentation</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016896" MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011667" MajorTopicYN="N">Pulmonary Veins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000601" MajorTopicYN="N">surgery</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">atrial fibrillation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">catheters</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pulmonary veins</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Dr Reddy reports receiving consulting fees and grant support from Biosense-Webster; unrelated to this article, serves as a consultant for and has equity in Ablacon, Acutus Medical, Affera-Medtronic, Anumana, Apama Medical-Boston Scientific, APN Health, Aquaheart, Atacor, Autonomix, Axon Therapies, Backbeat, BioSig, CardiaCare, Cardiofocus, CardioNXT/AFTx, Circa Scientific, CoRISMA, Corvia Medical, Dinova-Hangzhou DiNovA EP Technology, East End Medical, EPD-Philips, EP Frontiers, Epix Therapeutics-Medtronic, EpiEP, Eximo, Farapulse-Boston Scientific, Field Medical, Focused Therapeutics, HRT, Intershunt, Javelin, Kardium, Keystone Heart, Laminar Medical, LuxMed, Medlumics, Middlepeak, Neutrace, Nuvera-Biosense Webster, Oracle Health, Restore Medical, Sirona Medical, SoundCath, and Valcare; unrelated to this work, has served as a consultant for Abbott, Adagio Medical, Append Medical, AtriAN, BioTel Heart, Biotronik, Boston Scientific, Cairdac, Cardionomic, CoreMap, Fire1, Gore &amp; Associates, Impulse Dynamics, Medtronic, Novartis, Novo Nordisk, Philips, and Pulse Biosciences; and unrelated to this work, has equity in Atraverse, DRS Vascular, Manual Surgical Sciences, Newpace, Nyra Medical, Soundcath, Surecor, and Vizaramed. Dr Calkins receives consulting fees from Biosense Webster and Boston Scientific and payment for honoraria from Boston Scientific and Medtronic. Dr Mansour reports grants from Biosense Webster, Inc, and Boston Scientific; consulting fees from Biosense Webster, Inc, Boston Scientific, Philips, and Medtronic; support for attending meetings/travel from Biosense Webster, Inc, and Boston Scientific; and stock/stock options from NewPace Limited and EPD Solutions. Dr Wazni serves as a consultant for Biosense Webster. Dr Di Biase is a consultant for Biosense Webster, Stereoataxis, and Rhythm Management, and has received speaker honoraria/travel from Biosense Webster, St. Jude Medical (now Abbott), Boston Scientific, Medtronic, Biotronik, Atricure, Baylis, and Zoll. Drs Bahu and Liu have nothing to disclose. Dr Newton serves as a consultant for Biosense Webster. Dr Sauer receives grants from Biosense Webster and Medtronic and consulting fees from Boston Scientific, Biosense Webster, and Abbott. Dr Goyal receives consulting fees from Biosense Webster and Medtronic. Dr Iyer receives consulting fees from Biosense Webster. Dr Nair serves as a consultant for and receives research grants from Abbott, Boston Scientific, Medtronic, Biosense Webster, and Adagio, and receives research grants from Laminar. Dr Athill receives consulting fees from Boston Scientific, Abbott, and Biosense Webster, and payment/honoraria from Zoll and Janssen. Dr Hussein receives research grants from Boston Scientific and serves on steering committees for Biosense Webster. Dr Whalen serves on the advisory board for Biosense Webster. Dr Melby serves as a consultant for and receives research grants from Biosense Webster. Dr Natale serves as a consultant for Abbott, Biosense Webster, Biotronik, Boston Scientific, and iRhythm.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39258362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.124.070333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11458102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Anic A, Koruth J, Petru J, Funasako M, Minami K, Breskovic T, Sikiric I, Dukkipati SR, Kawamura I, et al. . Pulsed field ablation in patients with persistent atrial fibrillation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2020;76:1068–1080. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2020.07.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32854842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Anter E, Rackauskas G, Peichl P, Koruth JS, Petru J, Funasako M, Minami K, Natale A, Jais P, et al. . Lattice-tip focal ablation catheter that toggles between radiofrequency and pulsed field energy to treat atrial fibrillation: a first-in-human trial. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2020;13:e008718. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.120.008718</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32383391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Dukkipati SR, Neuzil P, Anic A, Petru J, Funasako M, Cochet H, Minami K, Breskovic T, Sikiric I, et al. . Pulsed field ablation of paroxysmal atrial fibrillation: 1-year outcomes of IMPULSE, PEFCAT, and PEFCAT II. JACC Clin Electrophysiol. 2021;7:614–627. doi: 10.1016/j.jacep.2021.02.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33933412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Neuzil P, Koruth JS, Petru J, Funosako M, Cochet H, Sediva L, Chovanec M, Dukkipati SR, Jais P. Pulsed field ablation for pulmonary vein isolation in atrial fibrillation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2019;74:315–326. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2019.04.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31085321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt B, Bordignon S, Neven K, Reichlin T, Blaauw Y, Hansen J, Adelino R, Ouss A, Futing A, Roten L, et al. . European Real-World Outcomes With Pulsed Field Ablation in Patients With Symptomatic Atrial Fibrillation: lessons from the multi-centre EU-PORIA registry. Europace. 2023;25:euad185. doi: 10.1093/europace/euad185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10320231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37379528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turagam MK, Neuzil P, Schmidt B, Reichlin T, Neven K, Metzner A, Hansen J, Blaauw Y, Maury P, Arentz T, et al. . Safety and effectiveness of pulsed field ablation to treat atrial fibrillation: one-year outcomes from the MANIFEST-PF registry. Circulation. 2023;148:35–46. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.123.064959</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37199171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma A, Haines DE, Boersma LV, Sood N, Natale A, Marchlinski FE, Calkins H, Sanders P, Packer DL, Kuck KH, et al. ; PULSED AF Investigators. Pulsed field ablation for the treatment of atrial fibrillation: PULSED AF pivotal trial. Circulation. 2023;147:1422–1432. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.123.063988</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10158608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36877118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cochet H, Nakatani Y, Sridi-Cheniti S, Cheniti G, Ramirez FD, Nakashima T, Eggert C, Schneider C, Viswanathan R, Derval N, et al. . Pulsed field ablation selectively spares the oesophagus during pulmonary vein isolation for atrial fibrillation. Europace. 2021;23:1391–1399. doi: 10.1093/europace/euab090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8427383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33961027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koruth J, Kuroki K, Iwasawa J, Enomoto Y, Viswanathan R, Brose R, Buck ED, Speltz M, Dukkipati SR, Reddy VY. Preclinical evaluation of pulsed field ablation: electrophysiological and histological assessment of thoracic vein isolation. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2019;12:e007781. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.119.007781</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6924932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31826647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koruth JS, Kuroki K, Kawamura I, Brose R, Viswanathan R, Buck ED, Donskoy E, Neuzil P, Dukkipati SR, Reddy VY. Pulsed field ablation versus radiofrequency ablation: esophageal injury in a novel porcine model. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2020;13:e008303. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.119.008303</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7069397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31977250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansour M, Gerstenfeld EP, Patel C, Natale A, Whang W, Cuoco FA, Mountantonakis SE, Gibson DN, Harding JD, Holland SK, et al. . Pulmonary vein narrowing after pulsed field versus thermal ablation. Europace. 2024;26:euae038. doi: 10.1093/europace/euae038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10875916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38305503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neven K, van Es R, van Driel V, van Wessel H, Fidder H, Vink A, Doevendans P, Wittkampf F. Acute and long-term effects of full-power electroporation ablation directly on the porcine esophagus. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2017;10:e004672. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.116.004672</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28487347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Koruth J, Jais P, Petru J, Timko F, Skalsky I, Hebeler R, Labrousse L, Barandon L, Kralovec S, et al. . Ablation of atrial fibrillation with pulsed electric fields: an ultra-rapid, tissue-selective modality for cardiac ablation. JACC Clin Electrophysiol. 2018;4:987–995. doi: 10.1016/j.jacep.2018.04.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30139499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yavin H, Brem E, Zilberman I, Shapira-Daniels A, Datta K, Govari A, Anic A, Wazni O, Anter E. A circular multielectrode pulsed-field ablation catheter “Lasso PFA”: lesion characteristics, durability and effect on neighboring structures. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2021;14:e009229. 10.1161/circep.120.009229</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7909749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33417475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Gerstenfeld EP, Natale A, Whang W, Cuoco FA, Patel C, Mountantonakis SE, Gibson DN, Harding JD, Ellis CR, et al. ; ADVENT Investigators. Pulsed field or conventional thermal ablation for paroxysmal atrial fibrillation. N Engl J Med. 2023;389:1660–1671. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2307291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37634148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard B, Verma A, Tzou WS, Mattison L, Kos B, Miklavcic D, Onal B, Stewart MT, Sigg DC. Effects of electrode-tissue proximity on cardiac lesion formation using pulsed field ablation. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2022;15:e011110. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.122.011110</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9584049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36166690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu JC, Banker RS, Gibson DN, Gomez T, Berman D, Datta K, Chen Q, Doshi SK. Comprehensive dose-response study of pulsed field ablation using a circular catheter compared with radiofrequency ablation for pulmonary vein isolation: a preclinical study. Heart Rhythm O2. 2023;4:662–667. doi: 10.1016/j.hroo.2023.09.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10626186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37936668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu JC, Gibson D, Banker R, Doshi SK, Gidney B, Gomez T, Berman D, Datta K, Govari A, Natale A. In vivo porcine characterization of atrial lesion safety and efficacy utilizing a circular pulsed-field ablation catheter including assessment of collateral damage to adjacent tissue in supratherapeutic ablation applications. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2022;33:1480–1488. doi: 10.1111/jce.15522</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9545022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35510408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Potter T, Grimaldi M, Duytschaever M, Anic A, Vijgen J, Neuzil P, Van Herendael H, Verma A, Skanes A, Scherr D, et al. ; INSPIRE Trial Investigators. Predictors of success for pulmonary vein isolation with pulsed field ablation using a variable loop catheter with 3D mapping integration: complete 12-month outcomes from INSPIRE. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2024;17:e012667. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.123.012667</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11111320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38655693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duytschaever M, De Potter T, Grimaldi M, Anic A, Vijgen J, Neuzil P, Van Herendael H, Verma A, Skanes A, Scherr D, et al. ; INSPIRE Trial Investigators. Paroxysmal atrial fibrillation ablation using a novel variable-loop biphasic pulsed field ablation catheter integrated with a 3-dimensional mapping system: 1-year outcomes of the multicenter INSPIRE study. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2023;16:e011780. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.122.011780</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10026968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36735937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newton D, Natale A, Mansour M, Nair D, Senn T, Reddy VY, on behalf of the ADMIRE Trial Investigators. Pulsed field ablation using a variable loop circular catheter with 3D mapping integration: early outcomes of the ADMIRE study. Presented at the AF Symposium, Boston, MA, February 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calkins H, Hindricks G, Cappato R, Kim YH, Saad EB, Aguinaga L, Akar JG, Badhwar V, Brugada J, Camm J, et al. . 2017 HRS/EHRA/ECAS/APHRS/SOLAECE expert consensus statement on catheter and surgical ablation of atrial fibrillation. Europace. 2018;20:e1–e160. doi: 10.1093/europace/eux274</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5834122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29016840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Peichl P, Anter E, Rackauskas G, Petru J, Funasako M, Minami K, Koruth JS, Natale A, Jais P, et al. . A focal ablation catheter toggling between radiofrequency and pulsed field energy to treat atrial fibrillation. JACC Clin Electrophysiol. 2023;9:1786–1801. doi: 10.1016/j.jacep.2023.04.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37227340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Anter E, Peichl P, Rackauskas G, Petru J, Funasako M, Koruth JS, Marinskis G, Turagam M, Aidietis A, et al. . First-in-human clinical series of a novel conformable large-lattice pulsed field ablation catheter for pulmonary vein isolation. Europace. 2024;26:euae090. doi: 10.1093/europace/euae090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11057205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38584468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekanem E, Reddy VY, Schmidt B, Reichlin T, Neven K, Metzner A, Hansen J, Blaauw Y, Maury P, Arentz T, et al. ; MANIFEST-PF Cooperative. Multi-national survey on the methods, efficacy, and safety on the post-approval clinical use of pulsed field ablation (MANIFEST-PF). Europace. 2022;24:1256–1266. doi: 10.1093/europace/euac050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9435639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35647644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY, Ekanem E. Multi-national survey on the safety of the post-approval use of pulsed field ablation in 17000+ patients (MANIFEST-17K). Presented at the American Heart Association (AHA) Late Breaking &amp; Featured Science Scientific Sessions; Philadelphia, PA; November 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaita F, Guerra PG, Battaglia A, Anselmino M. The dream of near-zero x-rays ablation comes true. Eur Heart J. 2016;37:2749–2755. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehw223</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27354053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orme NM, Rihal CS, Gulati R, Holmes DR, Jr, Lennon RJ, Lewis BR, McPhail IR, Thielen KR, Pislaru SV, Sandhu GS, et al. . Occupational health hazards of working in the interventional laboratory: a multisite case control study of physicians and allied staff. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2015;65:820–826. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2014.11.056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25720626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorian P, Burk C, Mullin CM, Bubien R, Godejohn D, Reynolds MR, Lakkireddy DR, Wimmer AP, Bhandari A, Spertus J. Interpreting changes in quality of life in atrial fibrillation: how much change is meaningful? Am Heart J. 2013;166:381–387.e8. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2013.04.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23895823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massachusetts General Hospital. Safety and Effectiveness of Pulmonary Vein Isolation and Posterior Wall Ablation With Pulsed Field Energy in Patients With Paroxysmal and Persistent AF (POLARIS).
ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT06099730. Updated January 16, 2024. https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT06099730</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy VY. Versatility of a Circular Multielectrode Catheter in the Individualized Recognition &amp; Treatment of Atrial Fibrillation and Related Arrhythmias Using Pulsed Field Energy (VIRTUE).
ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT06056557. Updated October 18, 2023. https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT06056557</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osorio J, Miranda-Arboleda AF, Velasco A, Varley AL, Rajendra A, Morales GX, Hoyos C, Matos C, Thorne C, D’Souza B, et al. . Real-world data of radiofrequency catheter ablation in paroxysmal atrial fibrillation: short- and long-term clinical outcomes from the prospective multicenter REAL-AF Registry. Heart Rhythm. 2024;S1547-5271:02524-4. doi: 10.1016/j.hrthm.2024.04.090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38768839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemoine MD, Fink T, Mencke C, Schleberger R, My I, Obergassel J, Bergau L, Sciacca V, Rottner L, Moser J, et al. . Pulsed-field ablation-based pulmonary vein isolation: acute safety, efficacy and short-term follow-up in a multi-center real world scenario. Clin Res Cardiol. 2023;112:795–806. doi: 10.1007/s00392-022-02091-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10241704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36131138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metzl MD, Hunter TD, Thatcher WH, Nazari J. Real-world experience comparing zero versus conventional fluoroscopy catheter ablation for the treatment of symptomatic persistent atrial fibrillation. JAFIB-EP. 2023;16:68–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osorio J, Hunter TD, Rajendra A, Zei P, Silverstein J, Morales G. Predictors of clinical success after paroxysmal atrial fibrillation catheter ablation. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2021;32:1814–1821. doi: 10.1111/jce.15028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33825242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>