<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39257643</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2451-943X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>25</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Veterinary and animal science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vet Anim Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle><i>Artemisia afra</i> essential oils inclusion in diets induces desirable effects on meat quality and fatty acid profiles of broilers chickens.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100390</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100390</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100390</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.vas.2024.100390</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The effects of A<i>rtemisia afra</i> (African wormwood) essential oil incorporation in diets on meat quality and fatty acid profilers of broilers was assessed. Four hundred Cobb500 day-old chicks were obtained and placed randomly into the following 4 diets replicated 10 times: NC-Negative control (broiler diet without antibiotics), PC-positive control (broiler diet with zinc bacitracin), AA1-broiler diet + 0.1 % <i>A. afra</i> essential oil and AA2 - broiler diet + 0.3% <i>A. afra</i> essential oil. A pen having 10 chicks was regarded as the experimental unit. From the results, all carcass traits were influenced (P &lt; 0.01) by diet apart from the dressing out percentage. The highest slaughter weights (1846g) and hot carcass weight (1427.36g) were obtained in birds fed the AA1 diet. Highest ultimate pH value (6.24) was obtained from the birds fed the AA1 while the highest values for meat lightness (L*) were obtained in birds offered the AA1 and NC diets (55.73 and 55.82). Cooking loss was highest in birds fed the NC (31.01%) diet. Birds fed the AA2 diet (23.7mg/g)) had the highest intramuscular fat followed by the AA1 fed birds. Inclusion of <i>A. afra</i> essential oils in diets also increased the proportion of PUFAs, n-6 and n-3 fatty acids and the PUFA/SFA ratios. In conclusion, the incorporation of <i>A. afra</i> essential oil in diets improved meat quality and fatty acid composition of broiler meat for the benefit of consumers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marume</LastName><ForeName>U</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Agricultural Sciences, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, North-West University, P Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Security and Safety Niche area, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, North-West University, P Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zvarivadza</LastName><ForeName>W</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Agricultural Sciences, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, North-West University, P Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Security and Safety Niche area, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, North-West University, P Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hugo</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Science Division: Microbial Biochemical and Food Biotechnology, Faculty of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, PO Box 339, Bloemfontein, 9300, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Vet Anim Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101694897</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2451-943X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Drip loss</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Omega-3</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Omega-6</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Slaughter weight</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Water holding capacity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors hereby confirm that there are no conflict of interest in the submission of this manuscript</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39257643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11386498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vas.2024.100390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2451-943X(24)00057-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Afolayan A.J., Sunmonu T.O. Protective role of Artemisia afra aqueous extract on tissue antioxidant defense systems in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats. African Journal of Traditional, Complementary and Alternative Medicines. 2013;10(1):15–20. doi: 10.4314/ajtcam.v10i1.3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4314/ajtcam.v10i1.3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3746352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24082320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afsharmanesh M., Lotfi M., Mehdipour Z. Effects of wet feeding and early feed restriction on blood parameters and growth performance of broiler chickens. Animal Nutrition. 2016;2:168–172. doi: 10.1016/j.aninu.2016.04.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2016.04.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5940997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29767053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad A., Khan A., Akhtar F., Yousuf S., Xess I., Khan L., Manzoor N. Fungicidal activity of thymol and carvacrol by disrupting ergosterol biosynthesis and membrane integrity against Candida. European Journal of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases. 2011;30:41–50. doi: 10.1007/s10096-010-1050-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10096-010-1050-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20835742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed S.T., Islam M.M., Bostami A.B.M.R., Mun H.S., Kim Y.J., Yang C.J. Meat composition, fatty acid profile and oxidative stability of meat from broilers supplemented with pomegranate (Punica granatum L.) by-products. Food Chemistry. 2015;188:481–488. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.04.140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.04.140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26041221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ao T., Cantor A.H., Pescatore A.J., Pierce J.L. In vitro evaluation of feed grade enzymes activity at pH levels stimulating various parts of the avian digestive tract. Animal Feed Science and Technology. 2008;140:462–468. doi: 10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2007.04.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2007.04.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ari M.M., Ayanwale B.A., Ogah D.M. Effects of alkali treatment of Soya bean on carcass traits, intestinal morphology and cooking yield of broilers. Trakia Journal of Sciences. 2013;2:189–196. http://www.uni-sz.bg</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attia Y.A., Zeweil H.S., Alsaffar A.A., El-Shafy A.S. Effect of non-antibiotic feed additives as an alternative flavomycin on productivity, meat quality and blood parameters in broilers. Arch Fur Geflugelkunde. 2011;75:40–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attia Y.A., Al-Harthi M., El-Kelawy M. Utilization of essential oils as a natural growth promoter for broiler chickens. Italian Journal of Animal Science. 2019;18:1005–1012. doi: 10.1080/1828051X.2019.1607574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1828051X.2019.1607574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai H.X., Chang Q.F., Shi B.M., Shan A.S. Effects of fulvic acid on growth performance and meat quality in growing-finishing pigs. Livestock Science. 2013;158:118–123. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2013.10.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2013.10.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çabuk M., Bozkurt M., Alçiçek A., Çatl A.U., Başer K.H.C. The effect of a mixture of herbal essential oils, a mannan oligosaccharide or an antibiotic on performance of laying hens under hot climatic conditions. South African Journal of Animal Science. 2006;36:135–141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cázares-Gallegos R., Silva-Vázquez R., Hernández-Martínez C.A., Gutiérrez-Soto J.G., Kawas-Garza J.R., Hume M.E., Méndez-Zamora Performance, Carcass Variables, and Meat Quality of Broilers Supplemented with Dietary Mexican Oregano Oil. Brazilian Journal of Poultry Science. 2019;21:1–10. doi: 10.1590/1806-9061-2018-0801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1806-9061-2018-0801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho J.H., Kim I.H., Kim I. Effects of phytogenic feed additive on growth performance, digestibility, blood metabolites, intestinal microbiota, meat color and relative organ weight after oral challenge with clostridium perfringens in broilers. Livestock Science. 2014;160:82–88. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2013.11.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2013.11.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury S., Mandal G.P., Patra K.A. Different essential oils in diets of chickens: 1. Growth performance, nutrient utilisation, nitrogen excretion, carcass traits and chemical composition of meat. Animal Feed Science and Technology. 2018;236:86–97. doi: 10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2017.12.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2017.12.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui X., Gou Z., Fan Q., Li L., Lin X., Wang Y., Jiang S., Jiang Z. Effects of dietary perilla seed oil supplementation on lipid metabolism, meat quality, and fatty acid profiles in Yellow-feathered chickens. Poultry Science. 2019;98(11):5714–5723. doi: 10.3382/ps/pez358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pez358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31376347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demir E., Kilinc K., Yildirim Y., Dincer F., Eseceli H. Comparative effects of mint, sage, thyme and flavomycin in wheat-based broiler diets. Arch Zootechnica. 2008;11:54–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disetlhe A.R.P., Marume U., Mlambo V., Hugo A. Effects of dietary humic acid and enzymes on meat quality and fatty acid profiles of broiler chickens fed canola-based diets. Asian-Australas Journal of Animal Science. 2019;32(5):711–720. doi: 10.5713/ajas.18.0408.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5713/ajas.18.0408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6502717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30208685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disetlhe A.R.P., Marume U., Mlambo V. Humic acid and enzymes inclusion in canola-based diets generate different responses in growth performance, protein utilization dynamics, and hemato-biochemical parameters in broiler chickens. Poultry Science. 2018;97(8):2745–2753. doi: 10.3382/ps/pey047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pey047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29757447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dotas V., Bampidis V.A., Sinapis E., Hatzipanagiotou A., Papanikolaou K. Effect of dietary field pea (Pisum sativum L.) supplementation on growth performance, and carcass and meat quality of broiler chickens. Livestock Science. 2014;164:135–143. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2014.03.024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2014.03.024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engberg R.M., Hedemann M.S., Leser T.D., Jensen B.B. Effect of zinc bacitracin and salimomycin on intestinal microflora and performance of broilers. Poultry Science. 2000;79:1311–1319. doi: 10.1093/ps/79.9.1311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/79.9.1311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11020077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO/WHO Fats and fatty acids in human nutrition. Proceedings of the Joint FAO/WHO Expert Consultation; Geneva, Switzerland; Annals of Nutritional Metabolism; 2008. pp. 5–300. November 10–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Folch J., Lees M., Sloane Stanley G.H. A simple method for the isolation and purification of total lipids from animal tissues. Journal of Biological Chemistry. 1957;226:497–509. doi: 10.1016/S0021-9258(18)64849-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(18)64849-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13428781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong J., Yin F., Hou R., Yin Y.L. Chinese herbs as alternatives to antibiotics in feed for swine and poultry production: potential and challenges in application. Canadian Journal of Animal Science. 2014;94:223–241. doi: 10.1139/CJAS2013-144. Review.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/CJAS2013-144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grau R., Hamm R. Vol. 105. Zur Lebensmittel Untersuchungen Forschung; 1957. pp. 446–460. (Measurement of water-holding capacity and juiciness in Meat, Poultry and Fish Products).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofmann K. What is quality? Definition, measurement and evaluation of meat quality. Meat Focus International. 1996;3:73–82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong J.C., Steiner T., Aufy A., Lien T.F. Effects of supplemental essential oil on growth performance, lipid metabolites and immunity, intestinal characteristics, microbiota and carcass traits in broilers. Livestock Science. 2012;144:253–262. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2011.12.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2011.12.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huff-Lonergan E., Baas T.J., Malek M., Dekkers J.C.M., Prusa K., Rothschild M.F. Correlations among selected pork quality traits. Journal of Animal Science. 2002;80:617–627. doi: 10.2527/2002.803617x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2527/2002.803617x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11892678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenkins T.C. Technical note: Common analytical errors yielding inaccurate results during analysis of fatty acids in feed and digesta samples. Journal of Dairy Science. 2010;93(3):1170–1174. doi: 10.3168/jds.2009-2509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2009-2509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20172237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirkpinar F., Ünlü H.B., Özdemir G. Effects of oregano and garlic essential oils on performance, carcase, organ and blood characteristics and intestinal microflora of broilers. Livestock Science. 2011;137:219–225. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2010.11.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2010.11.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirkpinar F., Ünlü H.B., Serdaroğlu M., Turp G.Y. Effects of dietary oregano and garlic essential oils on carcass characteristics, meat composition, colour, pH and sensory quality of broiler meat. British Poultry Science. 2014;55(2):157–166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24404997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knight M.I., Linden N., Ponnampalam E.N., Kerr M.G., Brown W.G., Hopkins D.L., Wesley I. Development of VISNIR predictive regression models for ultimate pH, meat tenderness (shear force) and intramuscular fat content of Australian lamb. Meat Science. 2019;155:102–108. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2019.05.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2019.05.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31102991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X.K., Wang J.Z., Wang C.Q., Zhang C.H., Li X., Tang C.H., Wei X.L. Effect of dietary phosphorus levels on meat quality and lipid metabolism in broiler chickens. Food chemistry. 2016;205:289–296. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.02.133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.02.133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27006242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim Ah Tock M.J., Viljoen A.M. Investigating the quality of commercially available indigenous southern African plant oils and the need for quality regulation. South African Journal of Botany. 2024;168:595–609. doi: 10.1016/j.sajb.2024.03.046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2024.03.046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu N.Q., Van der Kooy F., Verboort R. Artemisia afra: A potential flagship for African medicinal plants. South African Journal of Botany. 2009;75:185–195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macit M., Aksakal V., Emsen E., Aksu M.I., Karaoglu M., Esenbuga N. Effects of vitamin E supplementation on performance and meat quality traits of Morkaraman male lambs. Meat Science. 2003;6:51–55. doi: 10.1016/s0309-1740(02)00052-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0309-1740(02)00052-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22061985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mangwiro T.N., Dhliwayo M., Nyamushamba G.B. Towards sustainable broiler production – Does use of processed velvet bean (Mucuna pruiens) as an adjunct protein substitute for soyabean affect broiler performance. Scientific Journal of Animal Science. 2013;2(11):296–303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mapiye C., Chimonyo M., Dzama K., Hugo A., Strydom P.E., Muchenje V. Fatty acid composition of beef from Nguni steers supplemented with Acacia karroo leaf-meal. Journal of Food Compositional Analysis. 2011;24:523–528. doi: 10.1016/j.jfca.2011.01.018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2011.01.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moschini M., Masoero F., Prandini A., Fusconi G., Morlacchini M., Piva G. Raw pea (Pisum sativum), raw faba bean (Vicia faba var. minor) and raw lupin (Lupinus albus var. multitalia) as alternative protein sources in broiler diets. Italian Journal of Animal Science. 2005;4:59–69. doi: 10.4081/ijas.2005.59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/ijas.2005.59</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mpofu D.A., Marume U., Mlambo V. The effects of Lippia javanica dietary inclusion on growth performance, carcass characteristics and fatty acid profiles of broiler chickens. Animal Nutrition. 2016;2(3):160–167. doi: 10.1016/j.aninu.2016.05.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2016.05.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5941030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29767096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muyima N.Y.O., Zulu G., Bhengu T., Popplewell D. The potential application of some novel essential oils as natural cosmetic preservatives in an aqueous cream formulation. Flavour and Fragrance Journal. 2002;17:258–266. doi: 10.1002/ffj.1093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ffj.1093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozbey O., Esen F. The effects of breeding systems and stocking density on some blood parameters of rock partridges (Alectoris graeca) Poultry Science. 2007;86:420–422. doi: 10.1093/ps/86.2.420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ps/86.2.420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17234860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panaite T.D., Criste R.D., Vlaicu P.A., Saracila M., Tabuc C., Olteanu M., Turcu R.P., Buleandră M. Influence of Artemisia Annua on broiler performance and intestinal microflora. Brazilian Journal of Poultry Science. 2019;21:4. doi: 10.1590/1806-9061-2019-1092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1806-9061-2019-1092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park J.H., Kang S.N., Chu G.M., Jin S.K. Growth performance, blood cell profiles, and meat quality properties of broilers fed with Saposhnikovia divaricata, Lonicera japonica, and Chelidonium majus extracts. Livestock Science. 2014;165:87–94. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2014.04.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2014.04.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil G.V., Dass S.K., Chandra R. Artemisia afra and modern diseases. Journal of Pharmacogenomics and Pharmacoproteomics. 2011;2:105. doi: 10.4172/2153-0645.1000105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4172/2153-0645.1000105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qwele K., Muchenje V., Oyedemi S.O., Moyo B., Masika P.J. Chemical composition, fatty acid contents and antioxidant potential of meat from goats supplemented with Moringa (Moringa oleifera) leaves, sunflower cake and grass hay. Meat Science. 2013;93:455–462. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.11.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.11.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23273450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SAS, 2010. Statistical Analysis System Institute Inc. Users Guide, Carry, NC, USA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schaefer D.M., Liu Q., Faustman C., Yin M.C. Supranutritional administration of vitamins E and C improves oxidative stability of beef. Journal of Nutrition. 1995;125:1792–1798.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7782948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sukhija P.S., Palmquist D.L. Rapid method for determination of total fatty acid content and composition of feedstuffs and feces. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry. 1988;36(6):1202–1206. doi: 10.1021/jf00084a019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf00084a019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trifan A., Zengin G., Sinan K.I., Sieniawska E., Sawicki R., Maciejewska-Turska M., Skalikca-Woźniak K., Luca S.V. Unveiling the phytochemical profile and biological potential of five Artemisia species. Antioxidants. 2022;11:1017. doi: 10.3390/antiox11051017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox11051017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9137812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35624882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vahmani P., Rolland D.C., McAllister T.A., Block H.C., Proctor S.D., Guan L.L., Prieto N., López-Campos Ó., Aalhus J.L., Dugan M.E.R. Effects of feeding steers extruded flaxseed on its own before hay or mixed with hay on animal performance, carcass quality, and meat and hamburger fatty acid composition. Meat Science. 2017;131:9–17. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2017.04.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2017.04.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28448838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viljoen A.M., Van Vuuren S.F., Gwebu T., Demirci B., Baser K., Husnu C. The geographical variation and antimicrobial activity of African wormwood (Artemisia afra Jacq.) essential oil. Journal of Essential Oil Research. 2006;18:19–25. doi: 10.1080/10412905.2006.12067114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10412905.2006.12067114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H., Wang L.S., Shi B.M., Shan A.S. Effects of dietary corn dried distillers grains with solubles and vitamin E on growth performance, meat quality, fatty acid profiles, and pork shelf life of finishing pigs. Livestock Science. 2012;149:155–166. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2012.07.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2012.07.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenk C. Herbs and botanicals as feed additives in monogastric animals. Asian-Australas Journal of Animal Science. 2003;16:282–289. doi: 10.5713/ajas.2003.282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5713/ajas.2003.282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witkowska D., Sowińska J., Murawska D., Matusevičius P., Kwiatkowska-Stenzel A., Mituniewicz T., Wójcik A. Effect of peppermint and thyme essential oil mist on performance and physiological parameters in broiler chickens. South African Journal of Animal Science. 2019;49:1. doi: 10.4314/sajas.v49i1.4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4314/sajas.v49i1.4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai H., Liu H., Wang S., Wu J., Kluenter A.M. Potential of essential oils for poultry and pigs. Animal Nutrition Journal. 2018;4(2):179–186. doi: 10.1016/j.aninu.2018.01.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2018.01.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6103468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30140757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zvarivadza W., Marume U. Growth performance and heamatobiochemical parameters of broilers fed diets containing Artemisia afra essential oil. Canadian Journal of Animal Science. 2022;102(2):382–391. doi: 10.1139/cjas-2020-0113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/cjas-2020-0113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>