<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39251035</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-6351</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>193</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food and chemical toxicology : an international journal published for the British Industrial Biological Research Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem Toxicol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comprehensive risk assessment of lead concentrations in chicken, quail, and duck egg albumen and yolk using Monte Carlo simulations.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>114987</StartPage><MedlinePgn>114987</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.fct.2024.114987</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0278-6915(24)00553-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study conducted a comparative analysis of the concentration of the lead (Pb) in the albumen and yolk of eggs from domesticated chicken, quail, and duck, with a concurrent assessment of the potential carcinogenic and non-carcinogenic risks associated with the consumption of eggs sourced from Türkiye. A total of 78 poultry egg samples were gathered from breeding farms and farmers' markets situated in Şanlıurfa province. Lead concentrations were assessed through inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometry (ICP-OES). Human health risk assessment adheres to the guidelines set forth by the United States Environmental Protection Agency (US EPA), which primarily emphasizes estimated daily intake (EDI), international lifetime cancer risk (ILCR), target hazard quotient (THQ), and Monte Carlo simulation (MCS) as a probabilistic approach. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was employed to compare Pb concentrations within egg yolks and albumens, as well as among various types of eggs. The levels of Pb found in the albumen of chicken, quail, and duck eggs were measured to be 0.31 ± 0.11, 0.43 ± 0.11, and 0.47 ± 0.16 μg kg<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. The concentrations of Pb in the yolks of chicken, quail, and duck eggs were found to be 0.54 ± 0.19, 0.28 ± 0.11, and 0.69 ± 0.21 μg kg<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. These concentrations were below the maximum permitted levels set by the FAO/WHO. The results indicated that Pb content in all tested eggs was safe for consumption, with exposure levels significantly below Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives (JECFA) risk thresholds. The THQ values were less than one, indicating no non-carcinogenic risk. In addition, this study provides accurate and reliable data for policy makers to improve food safety measures and reduce potential public health risks.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kılıç Altun</LastName><ForeName>Serap</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Hygiene and Technology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Harran, 63200, Şanlıurfa, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paksoy</LastName><ForeName>Nilgün</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Harran, 63200, Şanlıurfa, Turkey. Electronic address: nilgunpaksoy@harran.edu.tr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aydemir</LastName><ForeName>Mehmet Emin</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Hygiene and Technology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Harran, 63200, Şanlıurfa, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem Toxicol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8207483</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0278-6915</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Egg albumen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Egg yolk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lead</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poultry egg</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Risk assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Simulations</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39251035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2024.114987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0278-6915(24)00553-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>