<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39251465</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1993-0402</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Chinese journal of integrative medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Chin J Integr Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficacy of Wuda Granule on Recovery of Gastrointestinal Function after Laparoscopic Bowel Resection: A Randomized Double-Blind Controlled Trial.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11655-024-3813-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To evaluate the efficacy and safety of Wuda Granule (WDG) on recovery of gastrointestinal function after laparoscopic bowel resection in the setting of enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS)-based perioperative care.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 108 patients aged 18 years or older undergoing laparoscopic bowel resection with a surgical duration of 2 to 4.5 h were randomly assigned (1:1) to receive either WDG or placebo (10 g/bag) twice a day from postoperative days 1-3, combining with ERAS-based perioperative care. The primary outcome was time to first defecation. Secondary outcomes were time to first flatus, time to first tolerance of liquid or semi-liquid food, gastrointestinal-related symptoms and length of stay. Subgroup analysis of the primary outcome according to sex, age, tumor site, surgical time, histories of underlying disease or history of abdominal surgery was undertaken. Adverse events were observed and recorded.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 107 patients [53 in the WDG group and 54 in the placebo group; 61.7 ± 12.1 years; 50 males (46.7%)] were included in the intention-to-treat analysis. The patients in the WDG group had a significantly shorter time to first defecation and flatus [between-group difference -11.01 h (95% CI -20.75 to -1.28 h), P=0.012 for defecation; -5.41 h (-11.10 to 0.27 h), P=0.040 for flatus] than the placebo group. Moreover, the extent of improvement in postoperative gastrointestinal-related symptoms in the WDG group was significantly better than that in the placebo group (P&lt;0.05). Subgroup analyses revealed that the benefits of WDG were significantly superior in patients who were male, or under 60 years old, or surgical time less than 3 h, or having no history of basic disease or no history of abdominal surgery. There were no serious adverse events.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The addition of WDG to an ERAS postoperative care may be a viable strategy to enhance gastrointestinal function recovery after laparoscopic bowel resection surgery. (Registry No. ChiCTR2100046242).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Chinese Journal of Integrated Traditional and Western Medicine Press and Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Hai-Ping</ForeName><Initials>HP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cao</LastName><ForeName>Li-Xing</ForeName><Initials>LX</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Traditional Chinese Medicine Applications Perioperative, Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diao</LastName><ForeName>De-Chang</ForeName><Initials>DC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Colorectal Surgery, Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wen</LastName><ForeName>Ze-Huai</ForeName><Initials>ZH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Unit of Methodology in Clinical Research, the Second Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Clinical Research on Traditional Chinese Medicine Syndrome, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ouyang</LastName><ForeName>Wen-Wei</ForeName><Initials>WW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Unit of Methodology in Clinical Research, the Second Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Public Health, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, 17176, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ou</LastName><ForeName>Ai-Hua</ForeName><Initials>AH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Big Data Research of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wan</LastName><ForeName>Jin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gastrointestinal Cancer Center, Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peng</LastName><ForeName>Zhi-Jun</ForeName><Initials>ZJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Second School of Clinical Medicine, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510405, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Zhi-Qiang</ForeName><Initials>ZQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Traditional Chinese Medicine Applications Perioperative, Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, 510120, China. profchen7233@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>China</Country><MedlineTA>Chin J Integr Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101181180</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1672-0415</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chinese medicine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wuda Granule</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enhanced recovery after surgery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gastrointestinal function</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">laparoscopic bowel resection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">postoperative ileus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">randomized double-blind controlled trial</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39251465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11655-024-3813-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11655-024-3813-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Venara A, Neunlist M, Slim K, Barbieux J, Colas PA, Hamy A, et al. Postoperative ileus: pathophysiology, incidence, and prevention. J Visc Surg 2016;153:439–446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviscsurg.2016.08.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27666979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedrick TL, McEvoy MD, Mythen MMG, Bergamaschi R, Gupta R, Holubar SD, et al. American Society for Enhanced Recovery and Perioperative Quality Initiative Joint consensus statement on postoperative gastrointestinal dysfunction within an enhanced recovery pathway for elective colorectal surgery. Anesth Analg 2018;126:1896–1907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1213/ANE.0000000000002742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29293183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tevis SE, Carchman EH, Foley EF, Harms BA, Heise CP, Kennedy GD. Postoperative Ileus—more than just prolonged length of stay? J Gastrointest Surg 2015;19:1684–1690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11605-015-2877-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26105552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asgeirsson T, El-Badawi KI, Mahmood A, Barletta J, Luchtefeld M, Senagore AJ. Postoperative ileus: it costs more than you expect. J Am Coll Surg 2010;210:228–231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2009.09.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20113944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li LT, Mills WL, White DL, Li A, Gutierrez AM, Berger DH, et al. Causes and prevalence of unplanned readmissions after colorectal surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Am Geriatr Soc 2013;61:1175–1181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jgs.12307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23730901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng H, Wang W, Cao L, Wu Y, Ouyang W, Diao D, et al. Effect of Wuda Granule on gastrointestinal function recovery after laparoscopic intestinal resection: a randomized-controlled trial. Gastroenterol Rep (Oxf) 2022;10:goac004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/gastro/goac004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35186297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen QC, Jiang Z, Cao LL, Chen ZQ. Establishment of diagnostic criteria of the syndrome of spleen-stomach qi deficiency and qi stagnation for postoperative by Delphi-method. Chin J Surg Integr Tradit West Med (Chin) 2023;29:463–468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng HP, Cao LX, Chen QC, Jiang Z, Chen ZQ. Research progress of traditional Chinese medicine in promoting postoperative gastrointestinal function recovery. Chin J Integr Med 2022;42:117–122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng HP, Wang T, Cao LX, Chen ZQ. Effects of Xiangbin Formula on gastrointestinal function recovery after laparoscopic surgery for colorectal cancer. China J Tradit Chin Med Pharm (Chin) 2021;36:3747–3750.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen ZQ, Cao LX, Shang WP, Yang RX, Ye F, Chen QC, et al. Effect of Xiangbin prescription on gastrointestinal motility after abdominal surgery in dogs. J Tradit Chin Med 2015;56:1953–1957.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen QC, Jiang Z, Zhang JH, Cao LX, Chen ZQ. Xiangbinfang Granules enhance gastric antrum motility via intramuscular interstitial cells of Cajal in mice. World J Gastroenterol 2021;27:576–591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3748/wjg.v27.i7.576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33642830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7901053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen SL, Feng X, Chen ZQ, Xiao J, Zhang WX. Effect of XiangBin Granules on post-operative gastrointestinal function and brain-gut peptides after transabdominal gynecological surgery. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol 2016;205:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2016.07.496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27552171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irani JL, Hedrick TL, Miller TE, Lee L, Steinhagen E, Shogan BD, et al. Clinical practice guidelines for enhanced recovery after colon and rectal surgery from the American Society of Colon and Rectal Surgeons and the Society of American Gastrointestinal and Endoscopic Surgeons. Surg Endosc 2023;37:5–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00464-022-09758-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36515747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinese Society of Surgery, Chinese Society of Anesthesiology. Chinese consensus and clinical guidelines for enhanced recovery after surgery (2018 edition): part of colorectal surgery. Chin J Anesthesiol (Chin) 2018;38:29–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan L, Zhao Q, Chen J, Fan BF, Gao CR, Hu L, et al. Expert Consensus on the application of pain evaluation questionnaires in China (2020 edition). Chin J Painol (Chin) 2020;16:177–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clavien PA, Barkun J, de Oliveira ML, Vauthey JN, Dindo D, Schulick RD, et al. The Clavien-Dindo classification of surgical complications: five-year experience. Ann Surg 2009;250:187–196.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181b13ca2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19638912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang JW, Shao JK, Wang Y, Liu Q, Liang JW, Yan SY, et al. Effect of acupuncture on postoperative ileus after laparoscopic elective colorectal surgery: a prospective, randomised, controlled trial. EClinicalMedicine 2022;49:101472.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35747183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9156985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vlug MS, Wind J, Hollmann MW, Ubbink DT, Cense HA, Engel AF, et al. Laparoscopy in combination with fast track multimodal management is the best perioperative strategy in patients undergoing colonic surgery: a randomized clinical trial (LAFA-study). Ann Surg 2011;254:868–875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SLA.0b013e31821fd1ce</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21597360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee TG, Kang SB, Kim DW, Hong S, Heo SC, Park KJ. Comparison of early mobilization and diet rehabilitation program with conventional care after laparoscopic colon surgery: a prospective randomized controlled trial. Dis Colon Rectum 2011;54:21–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/DCR.0b013e3181fcdb3e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21160309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Yang JW, Yan SY, Lu Y, Han JG, Pei W, et al. Electroacupuncture vs sham electroacupuncture in the treatment of postoperative Ileus after laparoscopic surgery for colorectal cancer: a multicenter, randomized clinical trial. JAMA Surg 2023;158:20–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2022.5674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36322060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vather R, Trivedi S, Bissett I. Defining postoperative ileus: results of a systematic review and global survey. J Gastrointest Surg 2013;17:962–972.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11605-013-2148-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23377782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Bree SH, Bemelman WA, Hollmann MW, Zwinderman AH, Matteoli G, El Temna S, et al. Identification of clinical outcome measures for recovery of gastrointestinal motility in postoperative ileus. Ann Surg 2014;259:708–714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SLA.0b013e318293ee55</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23657087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang H, Zhou P, Li J, Luo H, Yu L. Enhanced recovery after surgery in primary liver cancer patients undergoing hepatectomy: experience from a large tertiary hospital in China. BMC Surg 2023;23:185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12893-023-02040-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37386393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10311806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo J, Xu A, Sun X, Zhao X, Xia Y, Rao H, et al. Combined surgery and extensive intraoperative peritoneal lavage vs surgery alone for treatment of locally advanced gastric cancer: the SEIPLUS randomized clinical trial. JAMA Surg 2019;154:610–616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2019.0153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30916742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6583840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arfa S, Turco C, Lakkis Z, Bourgeois S, Fouet I, Evrard P, et al. Delayed return of gastrointestinal function after hepatectomy in an ERAS program: incidence and risk factors. HPB (Oxford) 2022;24:1560–1568.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hpb.2022.03.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35484074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namba Y, Hirata Y, Mukai S, Okimoto S, Fujisaki S, Takahashi M, et al. Clinical indicators for the incidence of postoperative ileus after elective surgery for colorectal cancer. BMC Surg 2021;21:80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12893-021-01093-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33573636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7879517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Zhang HQ, Ma XW, Tang SN, Chen SF, Huo R, et al. Influencing factors of postoperative gastrointestinal dysfunction in patients with gastrointestinal tumors: a meta-analysis. Chin J Surg Oncol (Chin) 2023;15:396–403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiranyakas A, Bashankaev B, Seo CJ, Khaikin M, Wexner SD. Epidemiology, pathophysiology and medical management of postoperative ileus in the elderly. Drugs Aging 2011;28:107–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2165/11586170-000000000-00000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21275436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Z, Li Y, Wu J, Zheng H, Yang C. Nomogram for prediction of prolonged postoperative ileus after colorectal resection. BMC Cancer 2022;22:1273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12885-022-10377-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36474177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9724353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quiroga-Centeno AC, Jerez-Torra KA, Martin-Mojica PA, Castañeda-Alfonso SA, Castillo-Sánchez ME, Calvo-Corredor OF, et al. Risk factors for prolonged postoperative Ileus in colorectal surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis. World J Surg 2020;44:1612–1626.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00268-019-05366-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31912254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchida F, Tominaga T, Nonaka T, To K, Hisanaga M, Takeshita H, et al. Incidence of and risk factors for postoperative ileus between right and left laparoscopic colectomy using propensity-score-matched analysis: a retrospective multicenter study. Asian J Endosc Surg 2023;16:706–714.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ases.13227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37409677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Z, Yang C, Wang Y, Yan M, Zheng H. Comparison of prolonged postoperative ileus between laparoscopic right and left colectomy under enhanced recovery after surgery: a propensity score matching analysis. World J Surg Oncol 2022;20:68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12957-022-02504-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35246150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8895612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Z, Chen Q, Zhang J, Cao L, Chen Z. Wuda Granule, a traditional Chinese herbal medicine, ameliorates postoperative ileus by anti-inflammatory action. Pathol Res Pract 2020;216:152605.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.prp.2019.152605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31974003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng HP, Cao LX, Chen ZQ. Study on molecular mechanism of Wuda Granules for gastrointestinal motility disorder based on network pharmacology and molecular docking technology. J New Chin Med (Chin) 2022;54:7–14.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>