<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39253908</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>High internal phase emulsions stabilized by fluorescent phycocyanin for improved stability and bioaccessibility of β-carotene.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13868</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">High internal phase emulsions (HIPE) are distinguished from ordinary emulsions by higher oil-phase percentage and better storage stability. Recently, HIPE stabilized with protein-based particles has received more attention. However, organic precipitation, chemical cross-linking and thermal denaturation are often needed to stabilize emulsions with natural proteins, and there is an urgent need to reduce the pollution of organic reagents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">HIPE loaded with β-carotene stabilized by phycocyanin was prepared under mild conditions. It demonstrated strong stability in terms of temperature and storage, as evidenced by its 94.17% retention rate and 81.06% bioavailability. This stability was ascribed to the efficient defense against heat and UV rays, which was probably associated with the oil-droplet environment and interfacial protection of phycocyanin. It is speculated that the possible main interaction site between phycocyanin and sorbitol exists near amino acids 110 to 120 of the B chain. The hydrogen bond and hydrophobic interaction between them make the phycocyanin fully adsorbed on the oil-water interface when sorbitol is stable, forming a strong oil-water structure, which increases the stability of the emulsion.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The outstanding fluorescence characteristics provide a feasible alternative for fluorescent emulsions to distribute and trace active compounds in vitro. HIPE loaded with β-carotene might have potential as a 3D printing material for edible functional foods. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Engineering Laboratory for Food Green Processing and Safety Control, Shaanxi Key Laboratory for Hazard Factors Assessment in Processing and Storage of Agricultural Products, Engineering Research Center of High Value Utilization of Western Fruit Resources, College of Food Engineering and Nutritional Science, Shaanxi Normal University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Xiaolin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Engineering Laboratory for Food Green Processing and Safety Control, Shaanxi Key Laboratory for Hazard Factors Assessment in Processing and Storage of Agricultural Products, Engineering Research Center of High Value Utilization of Western Fruit Resources, College of Food Engineering and Nutritional Science, Shaanxi Normal University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Zhong</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2409-5820</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Engineering Laboratory for Food Green Processing and Safety Control, Shaanxi Key Laboratory for Hazard Factors Assessment in Processing and Storage of Agricultural Products, Engineering Research Center of High Value Utilization of Western Fruit Resources, College of Food Engineering and Nutritional Science, Shaanxi Normal University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Wenjun</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4017-2520</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yantai Institute of Coastal Zone Research, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Yantai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7895-2525</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Engineering Laboratory for Food Green Processing and Safety Control, Shaanxi Key Laboratory for Hazard Factors Assessment in Processing and Storage of Agricultural Products, Engineering Research Center of High Value Utilization of Western Fruit Resources, College of Food Engineering and Nutritional Science, Shaanxi Normal University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Xingbin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8039-0525</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Engineering Laboratory for Food Green Processing and Safety Control, Shaanxi Key Laboratory for Hazard Factors Assessment in Processing and Storage of Agricultural Products, Engineering Research Center of High Value Utilization of Western Fruit Resources, College of Food Engineering and Nutritional Science, Shaanxi Normal University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2022YFF1102200</GrantID><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021YFC2103900</GrantID><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>31972183</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">3D printing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">high internal phase emulsions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phycocyanin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">β‐carotene</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39253908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Liu Z, Jiang H and Mao X, Biotechnology advances in β‐carotene production by microorganisms. Trends Food Sci Technol 111:322–332 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zong C, Xiao Y, Shao T, Amber Chiou J, Wu A, Huang Z et al., Alfalfa as a vegetable source of β‐carotene: the change mechanism of β‐carotene during fermentation. Food Res Int 172:113104 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Lin J, Shen B, Zheng C, Huang B, Zou J et al., Chlorogenic acid‐chitosan copolymers: synthesis, characterization and application in O/W emulsions for enhanced β‐carotene stability. Int J Biol Macromol 254:127839 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao W, Ye X and Cao Y, Isomerization and degradation of all‐trans‐β‐carotene during in‐vitro digestion. Food Sci Human Wellness 10:370–374 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemmens L, Colle I, Buggenhout SV, Palmero P, Loey AV and Hendrickx M, Carotenoid bioaccessibility in fruit and vegetable‐based food products as affected by product (micro)structural characteristics and the presence of lipids: a review. Trends Food Sci Technol 38:125–135 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salvia‐Trujillo L, Verkempinck SHE, Zhang X, Van Loey AM, Grauwet T and Hendrickx ME, Comparative study on lipid digestion and carotenoid bioaccessibility of emulsions, nanoemulsions and vegetable‐based in situ emulsions. Food Hydrocoll 87:119–128 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitri IA, Mitbumrung W, Akanitkul P, Rungraung N, Kemsawasd V, Jain S et al., Encapsulation of β‐carotene in oil‐in‐water emulsions containing nanocellulose: impact on emulsion properties, in vitro digestion, and bioaccessibility. Polymers 14:1414 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gasa‐Falcon A, Acevedo‐Fani A, Oms‐Oliu G, Odriozola‐Serrano I and Martín‐Belloso O, Development, physical stability and bioaccessibility of β‐carotene‐enriched tertiary emulsions. J Funct Foods 64:103615 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu B, Li Y, Chen Q, Zhang Z, Shi C and Li W, Facile preparation of biocompatible polymer microgels with tunable properties and unique functions to solely stabilize high internal phase emulsions. Chem Eng J 315:500–508 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun X, Zhang Z, Li W, Tian H, Li Y and Yang X, stabilization mechanism and stability investigation of high internal phase emulsions prepared from phycocyanin‐small molecule sugar. J Sci Food Agric 104:2917–2927 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Z, Zhao W, Sun H, Mou H, Liu J, Yu H et al., Phycocyanin from microalgae: a comprehensive review covering microalgal culture, phycocyanin sources and stability. Food Res Int 186:114362 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong Y, Sun S, Dai T, Zhang H, Wu J and Gong E, Phycocyanin‐chitosan complex stabilized emulsion: preparation, characteristics, digestibility, and stability. Int J Biol Macromol 260:129253 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Ouyang Z, Hu L, Cheng Y, Zhu J, Ma L et al., Self‐assembly of gelatin and phycocyanin for stabilizing thixotropic emulsions and its effect on 3D printing. Food Chem 397:133725 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai Y, Sun Y, Li X, Ren J, Sun C, Chen X et al., Phycocyanin/lysozyme nanocomplexes to stabilize Pickering emulsions for fucoxanthin encapsulation. Food Res Int 173:113386 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu D, Zhang Z, Yuan L, Li W, Guo Y, Zhang R et al., Load phycocyanin to achieve in vivo imaging of casein‐porous starch microgels induced by ultra‐high‐pressure homogenization. Int J Biol Macromol 193:127–136 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Li J, Wang X, Shen D and Chen L, Quantum dots based mesoporous structured imprinting microspheres for the sensitive fluorescent detection of phycocyanin. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces 7:9118–9127 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu RZ, Li WJ, Zhang J, Liu ZY, Li Y, Liu C et al., The inhibitory effect of phycocyanin peptide on pulmonary fibrosis in vitro. Mar Drugs 20:696 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Wang Y, Chen F and Tang C, Whether ovalbumin performs as a particulate or polymeric emulsifier is largely determined by pH. Food Hydrocoll 103:105694 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris GM, Huey R, Lindstrom W, Sanner MF, Belew RK, Goodsell DS et al., AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: automated docking with selective receptor flexibility. J Comput Chem 30:2785–2791 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laskowski RA and Swindells MB, LigPlot+: multiple ligand–protein interaction diagrams for drug discovery. J Chem Inf Model 51:2778–2786 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan M, Wang Y, Shen X, Dong S, Diao M, Zhao Y et al., Enhanced foaming properties of lactoferrin by forming functional complexes with ginsenoside Re and Rb1. Food Hydrocoll 123:107159 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park J and Choi SJ, Influence of interfacial characteristics and antioxidant polarity on the chemical stability of β‐carotene in emulsions prepared using non‐ionic surfactant blends. Food Chem 369:130945 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Nian Y, Huang Y, Zeng X, Chen Q and Hu B, High loading contents, distribution and stability of β‐carotene encapsulated in high internal phase emulsions. Food Hydrocoll 96:300–309 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H, Li S, Chen S, Wang C, Liu D and Li X, Antibacterial and antioxidant activities of sodium starch octenylsuccinate‐based Pickering emulsion films incorporated with cinnamon essential oil. Int J Biol Macromol 159:696–703 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng D, Huang C, Li B, Zhu X, Liu R and Zhao H, Effect of a novel shell material—starch‐protein‐fatty acid ternary nanoparticles on loading levels and in vitro release of curcumin. Int J Biol Macromol 192:471–478 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y, Zhou L, Zhang D, Wei Y, Jiang S, Chen Y et al., Stability and release of peach polyphenols encapsulated by Pickering high internal phase emulsions in vitro and in vivo. Food Hydrocoll 139:108593 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao R, Qiu Z, Bai X, Xiang L, Qiao Y and Lu X, Digestive properties and prebiotic activity of garlic saccharides with different‐molecular‐weight obtained by acidolysis. Curr Res Food Sci 5:2033–2044 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu W, Gao H, McClements DJ, Zhou L, Wu J and Zou L, Stability, rheology, and β‐carotene bioaccessibility of high internal phase emulsion gels. Food Hydrocoll 88:210–217 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karyappa R and Hashimoto M, Chocolate‐based ink three‐dimensional printing (Ci3DP). Sci Rep 9:14178 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu C and Zhang W, Micro/nano emulsion delivery systems: effects of potato protein/chitosan complex on the stability, oxidizability, digestibility and β‐carotene release characteristics of the emulsion. Innov Food Sci Emerg Technol 77:102980 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai H, Li Y, Ma L, Yu Y, Zhu H, Wang H et al., Fabrication of cross‐linked β‐lactoglobulin nanoparticles as effective stabilizers for Pickering high internal phase emulsions. Food Hydrocoll 109:106151 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Lv N, Ren G, Wu R, Wang B, Cao Z et al., Explore the interaction mechanism between zein and EGCG using multi‐spectroscopy and molecular dynamics simulation methods. Food Hydrocoll 102:106906 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang F, Shi Y, Shi J and Cao W, Exploring the binding mechanism of pumpkin seed protein and apigenin: spectroscopic analysis, molecular docking and molecular dynamics simulation. Food Hydrocoll 137:108318 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Liu M, Guo P, Zhang H, Jiang L, Xia N et al., Understanding the structure, interfacial properties, and digestion fate of high internal phase Pickering emulsions stabilized by food‐grade coacervates: tracing the dynamic transition from coacervates to complexes. Food Chem 414:135718 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao X, Liu F, Kong Z, Yang Z, Dai L, Wang Y et al., Pickering emulsion gel stabilized by pea protein nanoparticle induced by heat‐assisted pH‐shifting for curcumin delivery. J Food Eng 350:111504 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang T, Liu T, Li X and Tang CH, Novel nanoparticles from insoluble soybean polysaccharides of okara as unique pickering stabilizers for oil‐in‐water emulsions. Food Hydrocoll 94:255–267 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binks BP, Particles as surfactants‐similarities and differences. Curr Opin Colloid Interface Sci 21‐42:1359 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zare D, Allison JR and McGrath KM, Molecular dynamics simulation of β‐lactoglobulin at different oil/water interfaces. Biomacromolecules 17:1572–1581 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grasberger K, Sunds AV, Sanggaard KW, Hammershøj M and Corredig M, Behavior of mixed pea‐whey protein at interfaces and in bulk oil‐in‐water emulsions. Innov Food Sci Emerg Technol 81:103136 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Xie F, Zhou J, He J, Din Z, Cheng S et al., High internal phase pickering emulsion stabilized by zein‐tannic acid‐sodium alginate complexes: β‐carotene loading and 3D printing. Food Hydrocoll 142:108762 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Wang J, Su Y, Chang C, Gu L, Yang Y et al., Utilization of high internal phase emulsion stabilized by egg yolk‐modified starch complex for the delivery of lutein. LWT – Food Sci Technol 142:111024 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Zhang R, McClements D, Li F, Liu H, Cao Y et al., Nanoemulsion‐based delivery systems for nutraceuticals: influence of long‐chain triglyceride (lct) type on in vitro digestion and astaxanthin bioaccessibility. Food Biophys 13:412–421 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bao C, Jiang P, Chai J, Jiang Y, Li D, Bao W et al., The delivery of sensitive food bioactive ingredients: absorption mechanisms, influencing factors, encapsulation techniques and evaluation models. Food Res Int 120:130–140 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu X, Zheng J, Liu F, Qiu C, Lin W and Tang C, Freeze‐thaw stability of Pickering emulsions stabilized by soy protein nanoparticles: influence of ionic strength before or after emulsification. Food Hydrocoll 74:37–45 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin D, Kelly AL and Miao S, Preparation, structure‐property relationships and applications of different emulsion gels: bulk emulsion gels, emulsion gel particles, and fluid emulsion gels. Trends Food Sci Technol 102:123–137 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Zhou C, Xing S, Chen Y, Su W, Wang H et al., Sea bass protein‐polyphenol complex stabilized high internal phase of algal oil Pickering emulsions to stabilize astaxanthin for 3D food printing. Food Chem 417:135824 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Zaky A, Zhou C, Chen Y, Su W, Wang H et al., High internal phase Pickering emulsion stabilized by sea bass protein microgel particles: food 3D printing application. Food Hydrocoll 131:107744 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng T, Fan C, Wang X, Wang X, Xia S and Huang Q, Food‐grade Pickering emulsions and high internal phase Pickering emulsions encapsulating cinnamaldehyde based on pea protein‐pectin‐EGCG complexes for extrusion 3D printing. Food Hydrocoll 124:107265 (2022).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>