<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39269526</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1614-7499</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>31</Volume><Issue>45</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science and pollution research international</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Methylmercury in commercial fish species from the Erhai Lake Basin, Southwest China: concentrations, health risk assessment, and implications for future monitoring.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>56473</StartPage><EndPage>56481</EndPage><MedlinePgn>56473-56481</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11356-024-34947-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Erhai Lake, a highland lake situated in Southwest China, provides critical aquatic protein sources for the local community, and its preservation is vital due to the sensitivity of alpine freshwater ecosystems to disturbance. However, there is a lack of research on the contamination status of methylmercury (MeHg) in aquatic organisms of the Erhai Lake Basin. MeHg concentrations in important commercial fish species from the Erhai Lake were examined, and the potential health risks associated with human consumption were assessed. Our results showed significant inter-species differences in fish muscle MeHg: the carnivorous S. asotus exhibited the highest level (303 ng/g; ww), while that of the detritivorous R. ocellatus was the lowest (3.86 ng/g). Moreover, MeHg concentrations in P. fulvidraco and C. auratus collected from the Luoshi River (a major tributary of Erhai Lake) were significantly higher compared to those from the Erhai Lake, indicating possible river-based input of MeHg into the Erhai Lake. Additionally, our study revealed a significant positive correlation between the MeHg levels and the length as well as weight of the examined fish species. All the fish species analyzed in our study had MeHg concentrations within the limits of China's food safety standard. Nevertheless, a relatively low consumption quantity of 16 g per day of certain species (i.e., S. asotus) may still pose potential health risks especially for children. The present study provides baseline data for MeHg monitoring and risk assessment in the Erhai Lake Basin, and warrants continued monitoring and source investigation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Wenxian</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Erhai Watershed Ecological Environment Quality Testing Engineering Research Center of Yunnan Provincial Universities, Erhai Research Institute, West Yunnan University of Applied Sciences, Dali, CN-671006, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Jingrui</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Marine Life Sciences, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, CN-266003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chao</LastName><ForeName>Le</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Marine Life Sciences, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, CN-266003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kang</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Mariculture (Ocean University of China), Ministry of Education, Qingdao, CN-266003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Jiachen</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0191-3085</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Marine Life Sciences, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, CN-266003, China. sunjiachen@ouc.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>DXDGCZX01</GrantID><Agency>Erhai Watershed Ecological Environment Quality Testing Engineering Research Center of Yunnan Provincial Universities</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>202341007</GrantID><Agency>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9441769</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0944-1344</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D008767">Methylmercury Compounds</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014874">Water Pollutants, Chemical</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008767" MajorTopicYN="Y">Methylmercury Compounds</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060106" MajorTopicYN="Y">Lakes</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005399" MajorTopicYN="Y">Fishes</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018570" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="Y">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014874" MajorTopicYN="Y">Water Pollutants, Chemical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aquatic ecosystem</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioaccumulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Legacy contaminants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pollution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Toxic elements</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39269526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-34947-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11356-024-34947-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Andersen JL, Depledge MH (1997) A survey of total mercury and methylmercury in edible fish and invertebrates from Azorean waters. Mar Environ Res 44:331–350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0141-1136(97)00011-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ATSDR (1999) Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry (ATSDR), Toxicological profile for mercury (draft for public comment). Atlanta, GA: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baptista-Salazar C, Liem-Nguyen V, Jonsson S (2022) Experiments revealing the formation of refractory methylmercury pools in natural sediments and soils. Geochim Cosmochim Acta 328:76–84</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gca.2022.04.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basaran B (2022) Assessment of aluminum via baby foods consumption in Turkey: estimated early-life dietary exposure and target hazard quotient. Biol Trace Elem Res 200:3892–3901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12011-021-02961-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanchfield PJ, Rudd JWM, Hrenchuk LE, Amyot M, Babiarz CL, Beaty KG, Bodaly RAD, Branfireun BA, Gilmour CC, Graydon JA, Hall BD, Harris RC, Heyes A, Hintelmann H, Hurley JP, Kelly CA, Krabbenhoft DP, Lindberg SE, Mason RP, Paterson MJ, Podemski CL, Sandilands KA, Southworth GR, St Louis VL, Tate LS, Tate MT (2022) Experimental evidence for recovery of mercury-contaminated fish populations. Nature 601:74–78</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-04222-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boening DW (2000) Ecological effects, transport, and fate of mercury: a general review. Chemosphere 40:1335–1351</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0045-6535(99)00283-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosch AC, O’Neill B, Sigge GO, Kerwath SE, Hoffman LC (2016) Mercury accumulation in Yellowfin tuna (Thunnus albacares) with regards to muscle type, muscle position and fish size. Food Chem 190:351–356</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.05.109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell LM, Osano O, Hecky RE, Dixon DG (2003) Mercury in fish from three rift valley lakes (Turkana, Naivasha and Baringo), Kenya, East Africa. Environ Pollut 125:281–286</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0269-7491(03)00053-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carwile JL, Butler LJ, Janulewicz PA, Winter MR, Aschengrau A (2016) Childhood fish consumption and learning and behavioral disorders. Int J Environ Res Public Health 13:1069</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph13111069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chao L, Ni G, Ge Y, Zhang C, Chen J, Sun J (2024) Occurrence, dietary influence and risks of selected trace metals in different coastal predatory species. Environ Res 245:117985</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2023.117985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarkson TW (1997) The toxicology of mercury. Crit Rev Clin Lab Sci 34:369–403</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/10408369708998098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CNA (2022) Dietary guidelines for Chinese residents 2022. Chinese Nutrition Association. People’s Medical Publishing House, Beijing</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Copat C, Rizzo M, Zuccaro A, Grasso A, Zuccarello P, Fiore M, Mancini G, Ferrante M (2019) Metals/metalloids and oxidative status markers in saltwater fish from the ionic coast of Sicily, Mediterranean Sea. Int J Environ Res 14:15–27</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41742-019-00237-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dang F, Wang WX (2012) Why mercury concentration increases with fish size? Biokinetic explanation. Environ Pollut 163:192–198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2011.12.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Castro Paiva T, Dary EP, Pestana IA, Amadio SA, Malm O, Kasper D (2022) Flood-pulse and trophic position modulate mercury concentrations in fishes from an Amazon floodplain lake. Environ Res 215:114307</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2022.114307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira Ribeiro CA, Belger L, Pelletier E, Rouleau C (2002) Histopathological evidence of inorganic mercury and methyl mercury toxicity in the arctic charr (Salvelinus alpinus). Environ Res 90:217–225</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0013-9351(02)00025-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Depew DC, Basu N, Burgess NM, Campbell LM, Devlin EW, Drevnick PE, Hammerschmidt CR, Murphy CA, Sandheinrich MB, Wiener JG (2012) Toxicity of dietary methylmercury to fish: derivation of ecologically meaningful threshold concentrations. Environ Toxicol Chem 31:1536–1547</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/etc.1859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO (2022) Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. The State of World Fisheries and Aquaculture 2022. Towards Blue Transformation. https://doi.org/10.4060/cc0461en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner D (1978) Mercury in fish and waters of the Irish Sea and other United Kingdom fishing grounds. Nature 272:49–51</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/272049a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gentes S, Lohrer B, Legeay A, Mazel AF, Anschutz P, Charbonnier C, Tessier E, Maury-Brachet R (2021) Drivers of variability in mercury and methylmercury bioaccumulation and biomagnification in temperate freshwater lakes. Chemosphere 267:128890</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grandjean P, Landrigan PJ (2014) Neurobehavioural effects of developmental toxicity. Lancet Neurol 13:330–338</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(13)70278-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagoe CH, Shaw-Allen PL, Brundage S (1996) Gill Na+, K+-ATPase activity in largemouth bass (Micropterus salmoides) from three reservoirs with different levels of mercury contamination. Aquat Toxicol 36:161–176</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0166-445X(96)00814-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin L, Liang L, Jiang G, Xu Y (2006) Methylmercury, total mercury and total selenium in four common freshwater fish species from Ya-Er Lake, China. Environ Geochem Health 28:401–407</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-005-9038-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kehrig HA, Costa M, Moreira I, Malm O (2002) Total and methylmercury in a Brazilian estuary, Rio de Janeiro. Mar Poll Bull 44:1018–1023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0025-326X(02)00140-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kehrig HA, Seixas TG, Baeta AP, Malm O, Moreira I (2010) Inorganic and methylmercury: do they transfer along a tropical coastal food web? Mar Poll Bull 60:2350–2356</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2010.08.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalili Tilami S, Sampels S (2018) Nutritional value of fish: lipids, proteins, vitamins, and minerals. Rev Fish Sci Aquac 26:243–253</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/23308249.2017.1399104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavoie RA, Jardine TD, Chumchal MM, Kidd KA, Campbell LM (2013) Biomagnification of mercury in aquatic food webs: a worldwide meta-analysis. Environ Sci Technol 47:13385–13394</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es403103t</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Wang WX (2019) Inter-species differences of total mercury and methylmercury in farmed fish in Southern China: does feed matter? Sci Total Environ 651:1857–1866</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.10.095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li GZ, Lu MQ, Yan DW, Zhao GY, Li ML (2009) Analysis of biochemical components in muscle and nutritional evaluation of Schizothorax yunnanensis. S China Fish Sci 5:56–62</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang Q, Chen T, Wang Y, Gao L, Hou L (2022) Seasonal variation in release characteristics and mechanisms of sediment phosphorus to the overlying water in a free water surface wetland, southwest China. Environ Pollut 308:119612</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Q, Liu E, Zhang E, Li K, Shen J (2016) Spatial distribution, contamination and ecological risk assessment of heavy metals in surface sediments of Erhai Lake, a large eutrophic plateau lake in southwest China. CATENA 145:193–203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.catena.2016.06.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lino AS, Kasper D, Guida YS, Thomaz JR, Malm O (2019) Total and methyl mercury distribution in water, sediment, plankton and fish along the Tapajos River basin in the Brazilian Amazon. Chemosphere 235:690–700</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.06.212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H, Liu E, Yu Z, Lin Q, Zhang E, Shen J (2022) Spatio-temporal accumulation patterns of trace metals in sediments of a large plateau lake (Erhai) in Southwest China and their relationship with human activities over the past century. J Geochem Explor 234:106943</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gexplo.2022.106943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu SY, Zhang WT, Xing Y, Qu JT, Li K, Zhang Q, Xue W (2015) Spatial distribution of water quality parameters of rivers around Erhai Lake during the dry and rainy seasons. Environ Earth Sci 74:7423–7430</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12665-015-4725-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makaure J, Dube T, Stewart D, Razavi NR (2023) Mercury exposure in two fish trophic guilds from protected and ASGM-impacted reservoirs in Zimbabwe and possible risks to human health. Arch Environ Contam Toxicol 84:199–213</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00244-023-00977-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mason RP, Laporte J, Andres S (2000) Factors controlling the bioaccumulation of mercury, methylmercury, arsenic, selenium, and cadmium by freshwater invertebrates and fish. Arch Environ Contam Toxicol 38:283–297</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s002449910038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moriarity RJ, Liberda EN, Tsuji LJS (2020) Subsistence fishing in the Eeyou Istchee (James Bay, Quebec, Canada): a regional investigation of fish consumption as a route of exposure to methylmercury. Chemosphere 258:127413</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myers GJ, Davidson PW, Cox C, Shamlaye C, Cernichiari E, Clarkson TW (2000) Twenty-seven years studying the human neurotoxicity of methylmercury exposure. Environ Res 83:275–285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1006/enrs.2000.4065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NRC (2000) National Research Council (NRC), Committee on the toxicological effects of methylmercury. Toxicological effects of methylmercury. Washington (D.C.): National Academies Press (U.S.)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacyna EG, Pacyna J, Sundseth K, Munthe J, Kindbom K, Wilson S, Steenhuisen F, Maxson P (2010) Global emission of mercury to the atmosphere from anthropogenic sources in 2005 and projections to 2020. Atmos Environ 44:2487–2499</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2009.06.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pirrone N, Cinnirella S, Feng X, Finkelman RB, Friedli HR, Leaner J, Mason R, Mukherjee AB, Stracher GB, Streets DG, Telmer K (2010) Global mercury emissions to the atmosphere from anthropogenic and natural sources. Atmos Chem Phys 10:5951–5964</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5194/acp-10-5951-2010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu P, Pang M, Wang P, Ma X, Zhang Z, Wang Z, Gong Y (2022) Bioaccumulation of mercury along continuous fauna trophic levels in the Yellow River Estuary and adjacent sea indicated by nitrogen stable isotopes. J Hazard Mater 432:128631</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.128631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salazar-Camacho C, Salas-Moreno M, Paternina-Uribe R, Marrugo-Negrete J, Diez S (2021) Mercury species in fish from a tropical river highly impacted by gold mining at the Colombian Pacific region. Chemosphere 264:128478</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selin H, Keane SE, Wang S, Selin NE, Davis K, Bally D (2018) Linking science and policy to support the implementation of the Minamata Convention on Mercury. Ambio 47:198–215</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13280-017-1003-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Storelli MM, Giacominelli-Stuffler R, Marcotrigiano GO (2002) Total and methylmercury residues in cartilaginous fish from Mediterranean Sea. Mar Poll Bull 44:1354–1358</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0025-326X(02)00223-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang J, Ye S, Li W, Liu J, Zhang T, Guo Z, Zhu F, Li Z (2013) Status and historical changes in the fish community in Erhai Lake. Chin J Oceanol Limnol 31:712–723</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00343-013-2324-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thera JC, Kidd KA, Stewart AR, Bertolo RF, O’Driscoll NJ (2022) Using tissue cysteine to predict the trophic transfer of methylmercury and selenium in lake food webs. Environ Pollut 311:119936</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tjerngren I, Karlsson T, Björn E, Skyllberg U (2012) Potential Hg methylation and MeHg demethylation rates related to the nutrient status of different boreal wetlands. Biogeochemistry 108:335–350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10533-011-9603-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>US EPA (1989) United States. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Water Regulations. Assessing human health risks from chemically contaminated fish and shellfish: A Guidance Manual. Washington (D.C.)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasistha P, Ganguly R (2020) Water quality assessment of natural lakes and its importance: an overview. Mater Today: Proc 32:544–552</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang WX (2012) Biodynamics understanding of mercury accumulation in marine and freshwater fish. Adv Environ Res 1:15–35</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12989/aer.2012.1.1.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber JH (1993) Review of possible paths for abiotic methylation of mercury (II) in the aquatic environment. Chemosphere 26:2063–2077</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0045-6535(93)90032-Z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woolway RI, Kraemer BM, Lenters JD, Merchant CJ, O’Reilly CM, Sharma S (2020) Global lake responses to climate change. Nat Rev Earth Environ 1:388–403</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43017-020-0067-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Wang WX, Zheng N, Cao Y, Xiao H, Zhu R, Guan H, Xiao H (2021) Methylmercury biomagnification in aquatic food webs of Poyang Lake, China: insights from amino acid signatures. J Hazard Mater 404:123700</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.123700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Wang W, Lin C, Feng X, Shi J, Jiang G, Larssen T (2022) Decreasing mercury levels in consumer fish over the three decades of increasing mercury emissions in China. Eco-Environ Health 1:46–52</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eehl.2022.04.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong S, Geng Y, Huang B, Zhu Q, Cui X, Wu F (2020) Quantitative assessment of eco-compensation standard from the perspective of ecosystem services: a case study of Erhai in China. J Clean Prod 263:121530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou XA, Qiao YM, Wang S, Yang Y, Liu XX (2016) Characteristics of fish assemblages associated with environmental factors in the Lake Erhai. Chin J Ecol 35:1569–1577</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>