<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39263981</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1520-6882</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>38</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Analytical chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Anal Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Label-Free Detection of Waterborne Pathogens Using an All-Solid-State Laser-Induced Graphene Potentiometric Ion Flux Immunosensor.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>15476</StartPage><EndPage>15483</EndPage><MedlinePgn>15476-83</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acs.analchem.4c03607</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Waterborne pathogens are harmful microorganisms transmitted through water sources. Early and rapid pathogen detection is important for preventing illnesses and implementing stringent water safety measures to minimize the risk of contamination. This work introduces a miniaturized all-solid-state potentiometric ion flux immunosensor for the rapid and label-free detection of waterborne pathogens. A screen-printed silver/silver chloride electrode coated with a reference electrode membrane and polyurethane as an all-solid-state reference electrode was combined with a solid-state contact ion-selective electrode (ISE). An all-solid-state ISE was constructed on laser-induced graphene by coating it with a cationic marker and a carboxylated poly(vinyl chloride)-based membrane for immobilizing antibodies and controlling ion fluxes through the membrane. Proof-of-concept was achieved by detecting <i>Escherichia coli</i> and <i>Salmonella enterica</i> serovar Typhimurium using the assembled immunosensors within 10 min. The potentiometric response shift attributed to the blocking effect in the ion flux caused by pathogen-antibody interaction corresponded to pathogen concentration, indicating detection limits of 0.1 CFU/mL and working ranges of 0.1-10<sup>5</sup> CFU/mL. Furthermore, the developed sensors revealed high selectivity and were directly applied in groundwater and tap water without any sample preparation, demonstrating high recovery percentages. The simple operation and elimination of sample preparation are key benefits to further usability of the developed immunosensors for efficient pathogen detection.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Preechakasedkit</LastName><ForeName>Pattarachaya</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metallurgy and Materials Science Research Institute, Chulalongkorn University, Soi Chula 12, Phayathai Rd, Pathumwan, Bangkok 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pulsrikarn</LastName><ForeName>Chaiwat</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Health, Department of Medical Science, Ministry of Public Health, Nonthaburi 11000, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nuanualsuwan</LastName><ForeName>Suphachai</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Public Health, Faculty of Veterinary Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence for Food and Water Risk Analysis (FAWRA), Department of Veterinary Public Health, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rattanadilok Na Phuket</LastName><ForeName>Nawarat</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Regional Medical Science Center 4, Muak Lek, Saraburi 18180, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Citterio</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7420-045X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Applied Chemistry, Faculty of Science and Technology, Keio University, Yokohama, Kanagawa 223-8522, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruecha</LastName><ForeName>Nipapan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3330-9771</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metallurgy and Materials Science Research Institute, Chulalongkorn University, Soi Chula 12, Phayathai Rd, Pathumwan, Bangkok 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence for Food and Water Risk Analysis (FAWRA), Department of Veterinary Public Health, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Anal Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370536</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0003-2700</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors
declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39263981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11428094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.4c03607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wittler R. R. Foodborne and Waterborne Illness. Pediatr. Rev. 2023, 44 (2), 81–91. 10.1542/pir.2022-005621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/pir.2022-005621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36720680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S.; Nehra M.; Mehta J.; Dilbaghi N.; Marrazza G.; Kaushik A. Point-of-Care Strategies for Detection of Waterborne Pathogens. Sensors 2019, 19 (20), 4476.10.3390/s19204476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s19204476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6833035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31623064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin J.; Duan L.; Fu J.; Chai F.; Zhou Q.; Wang Y.; Shao X.; Wang L.; Yan M.; Su X.; et al. A real-time LAMP-based dual-sample microfluidic chip for rapid and simultaneous detection of multiple waterborne pathogenic bacteria from coastal waters. Anal. Methods 2021, 13 (24), 2710–2721. 10.1039/D1AY00492A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1AY00492A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34041513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Q.; Natarajan B.; Kannan P. Nanostructured biosensing platforms for the detection of food- and water-borne pathogenic Escherichia coli. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2023, 415 (16), 3111–3129. 10.1007/s00216-023-04731-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-023-04731-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37169938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avila-Huerta M. D.; Ortiz-Riaño E. J.; Mancera-Zapata D. L.; Morales-Narváez E. Real-Time Photoluminescent Biosensing Based on Graphene Oxide-Coated Microplates: A Rapid Pathogen Detection Platform. Anal. Chem. 2020, 92 (17), 11511–11515. 10.1021/acs.analchem.0c02200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.0c02200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32603091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhsin S. A.; Al-Amidie M.; Shen Z.; Mlaji Z.; Liu J.; Abdullah A.; El-Dweik M.; Zhang S.; Almasri M. A microfluidic biosensor for rapid simultaneous detection of waterborne pathogens. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2022, 203, 113993.10.1016/j.bios.2022.113993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2022.113993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35114471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu J.; Chiang E. L. C.; Medriano C. A. D.; Li L.; Bae S. Rapid quantification of fecal indicator bacteria in water using the most probable number - loop-mediated isothermal amplification (MPN-LAMP) approach on a polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) microchip. Water Res. 2021, 199, 117172.10.1016/j.watres.2021.117172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33991777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pebdeni A. B.; Roshani A.; Mirsadoughi E.; Behzadifar S.; Hosseini M. Recent advances in optical biosensors for specific detection of E. coli bacteria in food and water. Food Control 2022, 135, 108822.10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.108822.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.108822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lomae A.; Preechakasedkit P.; Teekayupak K.; Panraksa Y.; Yukird J.; Chailapakul O.; Ruecha N. Microfluidic Paper-Based Device for Medicinal Diagnosis. Curr. Top. Med. Chem. 2022, 22, 2282.10.2174/1568026623666221103103211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1568026623666221103103211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36330618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidic J.; Manzano M. Electrochemical biosensors for rapid pathogen detection. Curr. Opini. Electrochem. 2021, 29, 100750.10.1016/j.coelec.2021.100750.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coelec.2021.100750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding J.; Qin W. Recent advances in potentiometric biosensors. TrAC, Trends Anal. Chem. 2020, 124, 115803.10.1016/j.trac.2019.115803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trac.2019.115803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magar H. S.; Hassan R. Y. A.; Mulchandani A. Electrochemical Impedance Spectroscopy (EIS): Principles, Construction, and Biosensing Applications. Sensors 2021, 21 (19), 6578.10.3390/s21196578.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s21196578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8512860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34640898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen T.; Fojan P.; Pedersen A. K. N.; Magnusson N. E.; Gurevich L. Amperometric Biosensor for Quantitative Measurement Using Sandwich Immunoassays. Biosensors 2023, 13 (5), 519.10.3390/bios13050519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bios13050519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10216821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37232880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cesewski E.; Johnson B. N. Electrochemical biosensors for pathogen detection. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2020, 159, 112214.10.1016/j.bios.2020.112214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2020.112214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7152911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32364936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karimi-Maleh H.; Orooji Y.; Karimi F.; Alizadeh M.; Baghayeri M.; Rouhi J.; Tajik S.; Beitollahi H.; Agarwal S.; Gupta V. K.; et al. A critical review on the use of potentiometric based biosensors for biomarkers detection. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2021, 184, 113252.10.1016/j.bios.2021.113252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2021.113252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33895688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruecha N.; Chailapakul O.; Suzuki K.; Citterio D. Fully Inkjet-Printed Paper-Based Potentiometric Ion-Sensing Devices. Anal. Chem. 2017, 89 (19), 10608–10616. 10.1021/acs.analchem.7b03177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.7b03177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28849646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zdrachek E.; Bakker E. Potentiometric Sensing. Anal. Chem. 2019, 91 (1), 2–26. 10.1021/acs.analchem.8b04681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.8b04681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30335354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee C.-W.; Jeong S.-Y.; Kwon Y.-W.; Lee J.-U.; Cho S.-C.; Shin B.-S. Fabrication of laser-induced graphene-based multifunctional sensing platform for sweat ion and human motion monitoring. Sens Actuators A Phys. 2022, 334, 113320.10.1016/j.sna.2021.113320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sna.2021.113320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M.; Zhao G.; Yang C.; Wang H.; Cheng J. An Enzymatic Electrochemical Biosensing Interface Developed by The Laser-Induced Graphene Electrode. Adv. Mater. Interfaces 2023, 10 (35), 2300235.10.1002/admi.202300235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/admi.202300235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teekayupak K.; Lomae A.; Agir I.; Chuaypen N.; Dissayabutra T.; Henry C. S.; Chailapakul O.; Ozer T.; Ruecha N. Large-scale fabrication of ion-selective electrodes for simultaneous detection of Na+, K+, and Ca2+ in biofluids using a smartphone-based potentiometric sensing platform. Microchim. Acta. 2023, 190 (6), 237.10.1007/s00604-023-05818-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00604-023-05818-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37222781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janik-Karpinska E.; Ceremuga M.; Niemcewicz M.; Podogrocki M.; Stela M.; Cichon N.; Bijak M. Immunosensors—The Future of Pathogen Real-Time Detection. Sensors 2022, 22 (24), 9757.10.3390/s22249757.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s22249757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9785510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozdemir M. S.; Marczak M.; Bohets H.; Bonroy K.; Roymans D.; Stuyver L.; Vanhoutte K.; Pawlak M.; Bakker E. A Label-Free Potentiometric Sensor Principle for the Detection of Antibody–Antigen Interactions. Anal. Chem. 2013, 85 (9), 4770–4776. 10.1021/ac400514u.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac400514u</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23534536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Ghobashy M. A.; Nadim A. H.; El-Sayed G. M.; Nebsen M. Label-Free Potentiometric Ion Flux Immunosensor for Determination of Recombinant Human Myelin Basic Protein: Application to Downstream Purification from Transgenic Milk. ACS Sens. 2019, 4 (2), 413–420. 10.1021/acssensors.8b01315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssensors.8b01315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30608656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva N. F. D.; Magalhães J. M. C. S.; Barroso M. F.; Oliva-Teles T.; Freire C.; Delerue-Matos C. In situ formation of gold nanoparticles in polymer inclusion membrane: Application as platform in a label-free potentiometric immunosensor for Salmonella typhimurium detection. Talanta 2019, 194, 134–142. 10.1016/j.talanta.2018.10.024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2018.10.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30609512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva N. F. D.; Almeida C. M. R.; Magalhães J. M. C. S.; Gonçalves M. P.; Freire C.; Delerue-Matos C. Development of a disposable paper-based potentiometric immunosensor for real-time detection of a foodborne pathogen. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2019, 141, 111317.10.1016/j.bios.2019.111317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2019.111317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31226602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandhu S. S.; Kotagiri Y. G.; Fernando P. U. A. I. I; Kalaj M.; Tostado N.; Teymourian H.; Alberts E. M.; Thornell T. L.; Jenness G. R.; Harvey S. P.; et al. Green MIP-202(Zr) Catalyst: Degradation and Thermally Robust Biomimetic Sensing of Nerve Agents. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2021, 143 (43), 18261–18271. 10.1021/jacs.1c08356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jacs.1c08356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34677965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yakoh A.; Pimpitak U.; Rengpipat S.; Hirankarn N.; Chailapakul O.; Chaiyo S. Paper-based electrochemical biosensor for diagnosing COVID-19: Detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies and antigen. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2021, 176, 112912.10.1016/j.bios.2020.112912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2020.112912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7746088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33358057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preechakasedkit P.; Panphut W.; Lomae A.; Wonsawat W.; Citterio D.; Ruecha N. Dual Colorimetric/Electrochemical Detection of Salmonella typhimurium Using a Laser-Induced Graphene Integrated Lateral Flow Immunoassay Strip. Anal. Chem. 2023, 95 (37), 13904–13912. 10.1021/acs.analchem.3c02252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.3c02252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37638540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghavipanjeh A.; Sadeghzadeh S. Simulation and experimental evaluation of laser-induced graphene on the cellulose and lignin substrates. Sci. Rep. 2024, 14 (1), 4475.10.1038/s41598-024-54982-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-54982-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10891141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38395956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najafi M.; Abbasi A.; Masteri-Farahani M.; Janczak J. Two novel octamolybdate nanoclusters as catalysts for dye degradation by air under room conditions. Dalton Trans. 2015, 44 (13), 6089–6097. 10.1039/C4DT03377A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C4DT03377A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25727722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaballah S. T.; Khalil A. M.; Rabie S. T. Thiazole derivatives-functionalized polyvinyl chloride nanocomposites with photostability and antimicrobial properties. J. Vinyl Addit. Techn. 2019, 25 (S1), E137–E14610.1002/vnl.21670.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/vnl.21670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y.; Li C.; Wang L.; Wang H. Application of froth flotation in the separation of polyvinyl chloride and polycarbonate for recycling of waste plastic based on a novel surface modification. Waste Manage. 2020, 110, 43–52. 10.1016/j.wasman.2020.05.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wasman.2020.05.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32470902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang T.; Yin B.; Liu X.; Yang L.; Pang H.; Song J.; Wu S. Porous carbon-based robust, durable, and flexible electrochemical device for K+ detection in sweat. Analyst 2022, 147 (6), 1144–1151. 10.1039/D1AN02322E.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1AN02322E</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35180282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee M. S.; Paul A.; Xu Y.; Hairston W. D.; Cauwenberghs G. Characterization of Ag/AgCl Dry Electrodes for Wearable Electrophysiological Sensing. Fron. Electron. 2022, 2, 700363.10.3389/felec.2021.700363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/felec.2021.700363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Guzmán J. J.; Pérez-Ràfols C.; Cuartero M.; Crespo G. A. Toward In Vivo Transdermal pH Sensing with a Validated Microneedle Membrane Electrode. ACS Sens. 2021, 6 (3), 1129–1137. 10.1021/acssensors.0c02397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssensors.0c02397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8023800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33566575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Police Patil A. V.; Chuang Y.-S.; Li C.; Wu C.-C. Recent Advances in Electrochemical Immunosensors with Nanomaterial Assistance for Signal Amplification. Biosensors 2023, 13 (1), 125.10.3390/bios13010125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bios13010125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9855954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36671960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong M.; Yang L.; Yang H.; Cheng C.; Deng W.; Tan Y.; Xie Q.; Yao S. An electrochemical immunobiosensor for ultrasensitive detection of Escherichia coli O157: H7 using CdS quantum dots-encapsulated metal-organic frameworks as signal-amplifying tags. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2019, 126, 493–500. 10.1016/j.bios.2018.11.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2018.11.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30476880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares R. R. A.; Hjort R. G.; Pola C. C.; Parate K.; Reis E. L.; Soares N. F. F.; McLamore E. S.; Claussen J. C.; Gomes C. L. Laser-Induced Graphene Electrochemical Immunosensors for Rapid and Label-Free Monitoring of Salmonella enterica in Chicken Broth. ACS Sens. 2020, 5 (7), 1900–1911. 10.1021/acssensors.9b02345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssensors.9b02345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32348124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao S.; Yang X.; Wu J.; Liu Q.; Li D.; Huang S.; Xie H.; Yu Z.; Gan N. Reusable electrochemical biosensing platform based on egg yolk antibody-labeled magnetic covalent organic framework for on-site detection of Escherichia coli in foods. Sensors Actuat. B Chem. 2022, 369, 132320.10.1016/j.snb.2022.132320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2022.132320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández I.; Carinelli S.; González-Mora J. L.; Villalonga R.; Lecuona M.; Salazar-Carballo P. A. Electrochemical bioassay based on l-lysine-modified magnetic nanoparticles for Escherichia coli detection: Descriptive results and comparison with other commercial magnetic beads. Food Control 2023, 145, 109492.10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu C.; Wei G.; Zhu F.; Wu A.; Luo L.; Shen S.; Jia N.; Zhang J. Label-Free Electrochemical Biosensing Architecture Based on a Protein-Decorated Pt@BSA Nanocomposite for Sensitive Immunoassay of Pathogenic Escherichia coli O157: H7. ACS Sustainable Chem. Eng. 2023, 11 (20), 7894–7907. 10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c01241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c01241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dębosz M.; Wieczorek M.; Paluch J.; Migdalski J.; Baś B.; Kościelniak P. 3D-printed flow manifold based on potentiometric measurements with solid-state ion-selective electrodes and dedicated to multicomponent water analysis. Talanta 2020, 217, 121092.10.1016/j.talanta.2020.121092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2020.121092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32498863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu D.; Ryu K.; Otto S. J. G.; Stothard P.; Banting G.; Ruecker N.; Neumann N. F.; Zhi S. Differential survival of potentially pathogenic, septicemia- and meningitis-causing E. coli across the wastewater treatment train. Npj Clean Water 2022, 5 (1), 33.10.1038/s41545-022-00177-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41545-022-00177-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dobrzyński J.; Kulkova I.; Wierzchowski P. S.; Wróbel B. Response of Physicochemical and Microbiological Properties to the Application of Effective Microorganisms in the Water of the Turawa Reservoir. Water 2022, 14 (1), 12.10.3390/w14010012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w14010012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>