<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39267188</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Cannabis-infused foods: Phytonutrients, health, and safe product innovations.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70021</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70021</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70021</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Cannabis-infused foods are currently on the rise in markets all around the world. Meanwhile, there are concerns over the health implications for consumers. Studies have explored the therapeutic potential and nutritional and economic benefits of cannabis usage. Yet, the phytonutrients, processing methods, and health implications of cannabis-infused foods have not been well explored. This review evaluates existing evidence on the nutritional, processing, safety, and phytonutrient composition of cannabis-infused food products and their medicinal and functional prospects. Cannabis seeds contain the highest amount of dietary nutrients, while flowers contain the highest amount of bioactive constituents. Oils, butter, seeds, flowers, and leaf extracts are the plant forms currently incorporated into food products such as beverages, baked products, cooking ingredients, functional foods, nutraceuticals, and nootropics. Cannabis-infused foods have been found to offer therapeutic benefits for pain management, brain function, gut health, and certain cancers. Findings also show significant constraints associated with cannabis-infused foods regarding dosage guidelines, limited research, efficacy, and long-term health effects on consumers. This is further worsened by the lack of policies that regulate the industry. To realize the full potential of cannabis use in the food and health industries and in research, regulatory guidelines are needed to control dosages and improve its efficient use in these industries. This will go a long way to ensure the safety of cannabis users and enhance responsible production, marketing, and distribution.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fordjour</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-7542-8190</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biotron Experimental Climate Change Research Centre/Department of Biology, University of Western Ontario, London, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manful</LastName><ForeName>Charles F</ForeName><Initials>CF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science and the Environment, Grenfell Campus, Memorial University of Newfoundland, Corner Brook, Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khalsamehta</LastName><ForeName>Tarsaim S K</ForeName><Initials>TSK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biotron Experimental Climate Change Research Centre/Department of Biology, University of Western Ontario, London, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Armah</LastName><ForeName>Abraham</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science and the Environment, Grenfell Campus, Memorial University of Newfoundland, Corner Brook, Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheema</LastName><ForeName>Mumtaz</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science and the Environment, Grenfell Campus, Memorial University of Newfoundland, Corner Brook, Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thomas</LastName><ForeName>Raymond</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biotron Experimental Climate Change Research Centre/Department of Biology, University of Western Ontario, London, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D064209">Phytochemicals</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010936">Plant Extracts</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002188" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cannabis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D064209" MajorTopicYN="Y">Phytochemicals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019587" MajorTopicYN="N">Dietary Supplements</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055951" MajorTopicYN="N">Functional Food</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010936" MajorTopicYN="N">Plant Extracts</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cannabis‐infused foods</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medicinal benefits</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutritional benefits</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phytonutrients</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">safety risks</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39267188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdel‐Salam, O. M., Salem, N. A., El‐Shamarka, M. E.‐S., Ahmed, N. A.‐S., Hussein, J. S., &amp; El‐Khyat, Z. A. (2013). Cannabis‐induced impairment of learning and memory: Effect of different nootropic drugs. EXCLI Journal, 12, Article 193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abu‐Amna, M., Salti, T., Khoury, M., Cohen, I., &amp; Bar‐Sela, G. (2021). Medical cannabis in oncology: A valuable unappreciated remedy or an undesirable risk? Current Treatment Options in Oncology, 22, Article 16. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11864‐020‐00811‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Addison, E. J. (2022). Review Cannabis: A new strategy against methicillin‐resistant Staphylococcus aureus. Vietnam Journal of Science, Technology and Engineering, 64(4), 70–78. https://doi.org/10.31276/VJSTE.64(4).70‐78</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alamgir, A. N. M. (2017). Pharmacognostical Botany: Classification of medicinal and aromatic plants (MAPs), botanical taxonomy, morphology, and anatomy of drug plants. In A. N. M. Alamgir (Ed.), Therapeutic use of medicinal plants and their extracts: Volume 1: Pharmacognosy (pp. 177–293). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alamgir, A. N. M. (2018a). Phytoconstituents—Active and inert constituents, metabolic pathways, chemistry and application of phytoconstituents, primary metabolic products, and bioactive compounds of primary metabolic origin. In A. N. M. Alamgir (Ed.), Therapeutic use of medicinal plants and their extracts: Volume 2: Phytochemistry and bioactive compounds (pp. 25–164). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alamgir, A. N. M. (2018b). Secondary metabolites: Secondary metabolic products consisting of C and H; C, H, and O; N, S, and P elements; and O/N heterocycles. In A. N. M. Alamgir (Ed.), Therapeutic use of medicinal plants and their extracts: Volume 2: Phytochemistry and bioactive compounds (pp. 165–309). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aliferis, K. A., &amp; Bernard‐Perron, D. (2020). Cannabinomics: Application of metabolomics in cannabis (Cannabis sativa L.) research and development. Frontiers in Plant Science, 11, Article 554. https://doi.org/10.4140/TCP.n.2017.341</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aloo, S. O., Kwame, F. O., &amp; Oh, D.‐H. (2023). Identification of possible bioactive compounds and a comparative study on in vitro biological properties of whole hemp seed and stem. Food Bioscience, 51, Article 102329.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aloo, S. O., Mwiti, G., Ngugi, L. W., &amp; Oh, D.‐H. (2024). Uncovering the secrets of industrial hemp in food and nutrition: The trends, challenges, and new‐age perspectives. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 64(15), 5093–5112. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2022.2149468</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso‐Esteban, J. I., Pinela, J., Ćirić, A., Calhelha, R. C., Soković, M., Ferreira, I. C. F. R., Barros, L., Torija‐Isasa, E., Sánchez‐Mata, M., &amp; de, C. (2022). Chemical composition and biological activities of whole and dehulled hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) seeds. Food Chemistry, 374, 131754. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.131754</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Ubeed, Brennan, C. S., Schanknecht, E., Alsherbiny, M. A., Saifullah, M., Nguyen, K., &amp; Vuong, Q. V. (2022). Potential applications of hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) extracts and their phytochemicals as functional ingredients in food and medicinal supplements: A narrative review. International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology, 57(12), 7542–7555. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.16116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin, M. R., &amp; Ali, D. W. (2019). Pharmacology of medical cannabis. Springer Cham.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andre, C. M., Hausman, J.‐F., &amp; Guerriero, G. (2016). Cannabis sativa: The plant of the thousand and one molecules. Frontiers in Plant Science, 7, Article 19. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2016.00019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews, S. (2022). How to make THC‐infused drinks? https://softsecrets.com/en‐US/article/how‐make‐thc‐infused‐drinks</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angarita, G. A., Emadi, N., Hodges, S., &amp; Morgan, P. T. (2016). Sleep abnormalities associated with alcohol, cannabis, cocaine, and opiate use: A comprehensive review. Addiction Science &amp; Clinical Practice, 11, Article 9. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13722‐016‐0056‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ascrizzi, R., Iannone, M., Cinque, G., Marianelli, A., Pistelli, L., &amp; Flamini, G. (2020). “Hemping” the drinks: Aromatizing alcoholic beverages with a blend of Cannabis sativa L. flowers. Food Chemistry, 325, Article 126909.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atakan, Z. (2012). Cannabis, a complex plant: Different compounds and different effects on individuals. Therapeutic Advances in Psychopharmacology, 2(6), 241–254. https://doi.org/10.1177/2045125312457586</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aychman, M. M., Goldman, D. L., &amp; Kaplan, J. S. (2023). Cannabidiol's neuroprotective properties and potential treatment of traumatic brain injuries. Frontiers in Neurology, 14, Article 1087011. https://doi.org/10.3389/fneur.2023.1087011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babson, K. A., Sottile, J., &amp; Morabito, D. (2017). Cannabis, cannabinoids, and sleep: A review of the literature. Current Psychiatry Reports, 19, Article 23. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11920‐017‐0775‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakowska‐Barczak, A., de Larminat, M.‐A., &amp; Kolodziejczyk, P. P. (2020). The application of flax and hempseed in food, nutraceutical and personal care products. In R. M. Kozłowski &amp; M. Mackiewicz‐Talarczyk (Eds.), Handbook of natural fibres (2nd ed., pp. 557–590). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldino, L., Scognamiglio, M., &amp; Reverchon, E. (2020). Supercritical fluid technologies applied to the extraction of compounds of industrial interest from Cannabis sativa L. and to their pharmaceutical formulations: A review. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 165, Article 104960. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2020.104960</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baron, E. P. (2015). Comprehensive review of medicinal marijuana, cannabinoids, and therapeutic implications in medicine and headache: What a long strange trip it's been…. Headache: The Journal of Head and Face Pain, 55(6), 885–916. https://doi.org/10.1111/head.12570</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baron, E. P. (2018). Medicinal properties of cannabinoids, terpenes, and flavonoids in cannabis, and benefits in migraine, headache, and pain: An update on current evidence and cannabis science. Headache: The Journal of Head and Face Pain, 58(7), 1139–1186. https://doi.org/10.1111/head.13345</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrus, D. G., Capogrossi, K. L., Cates, S. C., Gourdet, C. K., Peiper, N. C., Novak, S. P., Lefever, T. W., &amp; Wiley, J. L. (2016). Tasty THC: Promises and challenges of cannabis edibles (Publication No. OP‐0035‐1611). RTI Press. https://doi.org/10.3768/2Frtipress.2016.op.0035.1611</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beal, K. (2019). Considerations in the addition of cannabis to chocolate. Current Opinion in Food Science, 28, 14–17. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2019.02.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beitzke, B., &amp; Pate, D. W. (2021). A broader view on deriving a reference dose for THC traces in foods. Critical Reviews in Toxicology, 51(8), 695–722. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408444.2021.2008867</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belščak‐Cvitanović, A., Vojvodić, A., Bušić, A., Keppler, J., Steffen‐Heins, A., &amp; Komes, D. (2018). Encapsulation templated approach to valorization of cocoa husk, poppy and hemp macrostructural and bioactive constituents. Industrial Crops and Products, 112, 402–411. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2017.12.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett, C. (2010). Cannabis and the soma solution. Trine Day.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bent, S. (2008). Herbal medicine in the United States: Review of efficacy, safety, and regulation: Grand rounds at University of California, San Francisco medical center. Journal of General Internal Medicine, 23, 854–859. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606‐008‐0632‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berghofer, E., Pollmann, K., Traby, M., &amp; Frenkenberger, C. (2003). Method for producing hemp milk (Canada Patent No. https://patents.google.com/patent/CA2505350C/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bidwell, L., Sznitman, S., Martin‐Willett, R., &amp; Hitchcock, L. (2024). Daily associations with cannabis use and sleep quality in anxious cannabis users. Behavioral Sleep Medicine, 22(2), 150–167.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisterfeld Von, M. (2012). Method of obtaining hemp plant juice and use of same for the production of beverages (United States Patent No. https://patents.google.com/patent/US8778418B2/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonn‐Miller, M. O., Loflin, M. J., Thomas, B. F., Marcu, J. P., Hyke, T., &amp; Vandrey, R. (2017). Labeling accuracy of cannabidiol extracts sold online. JAMA, 318(17), 1708–1709. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2017.11909</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonn‐Miller, M. O., Pollack, C. V., Jr., Casarett, D., Dart, R., ElSohly, M., Good, L., Guzmán, M., Hanuš, L., Hill, K. P., &amp; Huestis, M. A (2019). Priority considerations for medicinal cannabis‐related research. Cannabis and Cannabinoid Research, 4(3), 139–157. https://doi.org/10.1089/can.2019.0045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Booth, J. K., Page, J. E., &amp; Bohlmann, J. (2017). Terpene synthases from Cannabis sativa. PLoS ONE, 12(3), Article e0173911. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0173911</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borgelt, L. M., Franson, K. L., Nussbaum, A. M., &amp; Wang, G. S. (2013). The pharmacologic and clinical effects of medical cannabis. Pharmacotherapy: The Journal of Human Pharmacology and Drug Therapy, 33(2), 195–209. https://doi.org/10.1002/phar.1187</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouarfa, M., Lebtar, S., Boukhira, S., &amp; Bousta, D. (2020). An ethnobotanical and ethnopharmacological survey of Cannabis sativa of Taounate Region in Northern Morocco. International Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences Review and Research, 64(2), 116–122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouloc, P., Allegret, S., &amp; Arnaud, L. (2013). Hemp: Industrial production and uses. CABI.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouquié, R., Deslandes, G., Mazaré, H., Cogné, M., Mahé, J., Grégoire, M., &amp; Jolliet, P. (2018). Cannabis and anticancer drugs: Societal usage and expected pharmacological interactions—A review. Fundamental &amp; Clinical Pharmacology, 32(5), 462–484. https://doi.org/10.1111/fcp.12373</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breijyeh, Z., Jubeh, B., Bufo, S. A., Karaman, R., &amp; Scrano, L. (2021). Cannabis: A toxin‐producing plant with potential therapeutic uses. Toxins, 13(2), Article 117. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins13020117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruci, Z., Papoutsis, I., Athanaselis, S., Nikolaou, P., Pazari, E., Spiliopoulou, C., &amp; Vyshka, G. (2012). First systematic evaluation of the potency of Cannabis sativa plants grown in Albania. Forensic Science International, 222(1–3), 40–46. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2012.04.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burstein, S. (2015). Cannabidiol (CBD) and its analogs: A review of their effects on inflammation. Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry, 23(7), 1377–1385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carhart‐Harris, R. L., &amp; Goodwin, G. M. (2017). The therapeutic potential of psychedelic drugs: Past, present, and future. Neuropsychopharmacology, 42(11), 2105–2113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho, V. M., de Almeida, F. G., de Macêdo Vieira, A. C., Rocha, E. D., Cabral, L. M., &amp; Strongin, R. M. (2022). Chemical profiling of Cannabis varieties cultivated for medical purposes in southeastern Brazil. Forensic Science International, 335, Article 111309. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2022.111309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casey, K. R., &amp; Kraynak, J. (2019). Cannabis for dummies. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassano, T., Villani, R., Pace, L., Carbone, A., Bukke, V. N., &amp; Orkisz, S. (2020). From Cannabis sativa to cannabidiol: Promising therapeutic candidate for the treatment of neurodegenerative diseases. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 11, Article 515092. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2020.00124</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celińska‐Janowicz, K., Zaręba, I., Lazarek, U., Teul, J., Tomczyk, M., Pałka, J., &amp; Miltyk, W. (2018). Constituents of propolis: Chrysin, caffeic acid, p‐coumaric acid, and ferulic acid induce PRODH/POX‐dependent apoptosis in human tongue squamous cell carcinoma cell (CAL‐27). Frontiers in Pharmacology, 9, Article 336. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2018.00336</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerino, P., Buonerba, C., Cannazza, G., D'Auria, J., Ottoni, E., Fulgione, A., Di Stasio, A., Pierri, B., &amp; Gallo, A. (2021). A Review of Hemp as Food and Nutritional Supplement. Cannabis and Cannabinoid Research, 6(1), 19–;27. https://doi.org/10.1089/can.2020.0001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerrato, A., Citti, C., Cannazza, G., Capriotti, A. L., Cavaliere, C., Grassi, G., Marini, F., Montone, C. M., Paris, R., &amp; Piovesana, S. (2021). Phytocannabinomics: Untargeted metabolomics as a tool for cannabis chemovar differentiation. Talanta, 230, Article 122313. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2021.122313</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandra, S., Lata, H., ElSohly, M. A., Walker, L. A., &amp; Potter, D. (2017). Cannabis cultivation: Methodological issues for obtaining medical‐grade product. Epilepsy &amp; Behavior, 70, 302–312. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yebeh.2016.11.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlebois, S., Somogyi, S., &amp; Sterling, B. (2018). Cannabis‐infused food and Canadian consumers' willingness to consider “recreational” cannabis as a food ingredient. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 74, 112–118. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2018.02.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chasiotis, V., Tsakirakis, A., Termentzi, A., Machera, K., &amp; Filios, A. (2022). Drying and quality characteristics of Cannabis sativa L. inflorescences under constant and time‐varying convective drying temperature schemes. Thermal Science and Engineering Progress, 28, Article 101076. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tsep.2021.101076</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Z., &amp; Wong, R. (2023). Association Between Cannabis Use and Subjective Cognitive Decline: Findings from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS). Current Alzheimer Research, 20(11), 802–810. https://doi.org/10.2174/0115672050301726240219050051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chopra, A. S., Lordan, R., Horbańczuk, O. K., Atanasov, A. G., Chopra, I., Horbańczuk, J. O., Jóźwik, A., Huang, L., Pirgozliev, V., &amp; Banach, M. (2022). The current use and evolving landscape of nutraceuticals. Pharmacological Research, 175, Article 106001. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2021.106001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cital, S., Kramer, K., Hughston, L., &amp; Gaynor, J. S. (2021). Cannabis therapy in veterinary medicine. Springer International Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐030‐68317‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Citti, C., Russo, F., Linciano, P., Strallhofer, S. S., Tolomeo, F., Forni, F., Vandelli, M. A., Gigli, G., &amp; Cannazza, G. (2021). Origin of Δ9‐tetrahydrocannabinol impurity in synthetic cannabidiol. Cannabis and Cannabinoid Research, 6(1), 28–39. https://doi.org/10.1089/can.2020.0021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colatruglio, S., &amp; Slater, J. (2014). Food literacy: Bridging the gap between food, nutrition and well‐being. https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Joyce‐Slater/publication/269394694_Food_Literacy_Bridging_the_Gap_between_Food_Nutrition_and_Well‐Being/links/54889f910cf289302e30b685/Food‐Literacy‐Bridging‐the‐Gap‐between‐Food‐Nutrition‐and‐Well‐Being.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connor, J. P., Stjepanović, D., Le Foll, B., Hoch, E., Budney, A. J., &amp; Hall, W. D. (2021). Cannabis use and cannabis use disorder. Nature Reviews Disease Primers, 7(1), Article 16. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41572‐021‐00247‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crean, R. D., Crane, N. A., &amp; Mason, B. J. (2011). An evidence‐based review of acute and long‐term effects of cannabis use on executive cognitive functions. Journal of Addiction Medicine, 5(1), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1097/ADM.0b013e31820c23fa</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crescente, G., Piccolella, S., Esposito, A., Scognamiglio, M., Fiorentino, A., &amp; Pacifico, S. (2018). Chemical composition and nutraceutical properties of hempseed: An ancient food with actual functional value. Phytochemistry Reviews, 17, 733–749. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11101‐018‐9556‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crini, G., Lichtfouse, E., Chanet, G., &amp; Morin‐Crini, N. (2020). Applications of hemp in textiles, paper industry, insulation and building materials, horticulture, animal nutrition, food and beverages, nutraceuticals, cosmetics and hygiene, medicine, agrochemistry, energy production and environment: A review. Environmental Chemistry Letters, 18(5), 1451–1476. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10311‐020‐01029‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crippa, J. A., Guimarães, F. S., Campos, A. C., &amp; Zuardi, A. W. (2018). Translational investigation of the therapeutic potential of cannabidiol (CBD): Toward a new age. Frontiers in Immunology, 9, Article 2009. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2018.02009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Porto, C., Decorti, D., &amp; Tubaro, F. (2012). Fatty acid composition and oxidation stability of hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) seed oil extracted by supercritical carbon dioxide. Industrial Crops and Products, 36(1), 401–404. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2011.09.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davenport, S., &amp; Pardo, B. (2016). The Dangerous Drugs Act amendment in Jamaica: Reviewing goals, implementation, and challenges. International Journal of Drug Policy, 37, 60–69. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugpo.2016.08.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Degenhardt, F., Stehle, F., &amp; Kayser, O. (2017). The biosynthesis of cannabinoids. In V. R. Preedy (Ed.), Handbook of Cannabis and related pathologies (pp. 13–23). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>del Bo, C., Deon, V., Abello, F., Massini, G., Porrini, M., Riso, P., &amp; Guardamagna, O. (2019). Eight‐week hempseed oil intervention improves the fatty acid composition of erythrocyte phospholipids and the omega‐3 index, but does not affect the lipid profile in children and adolescents with primary hyperlipidemia. Food Research International, 119, 469–476. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2018.12.045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Della Rocca, G., &amp; Di Salvo, A. (2020). Hemp in veterinary medicine: From feed to drug. Frontiers in Veterinary Science, 7, Article 387. https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00387</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devi, V., &amp; Khanam, S. (2019). Comparative study of different extraction processes for hemp (Cannabis sativa) seed oil considering physical, chemical and industrial‐scale economic aspects. Journal of Cleaner Production, 207, 645–657. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2018.10.036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deville, M., Dubois, N., Denooz, R., &amp; Charlier, C. (2020). Validation of an UHPLC/DAD method for the determination of cannabinoids in seized materials: Analysis of 213 samples sold in Belgian CBD shops. Forensic Science International, 310, 110234. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2020.110234</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devinsky, O., Cilio, M. R., Cross, H., Fernandez‐Ruiz, J., French, J., Hill, C., Katz, R., Di Marzo, V., Jutras‐Aswad, D., &amp; Notcutt, W. G. (2014). Cannabidiol: Pharmacology and potential therapeutic role in epilepsy and other neuropsychiatric disorders. Epilepsia, 55(6), 791–802. https://doi.org/10.1111/epi.12631</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dimić, E., Romanić, R., &amp; Vujasinović, V. (2009). Essential fatty acids, nutritive value and oxidative stability of cold pressed hempseed (Cannabis sativa L.) oil from different varieties. Acta Alimentaria, 38(2), 229–236. https://doi.org/10.1556/aalim.2008.0035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donvito, G., Nass, S. R., Wilkerson, J. L., Curry, Z. A., Schurman, L. D., Kinsey, S. G., &amp; Lichtman, A. H. (2018). The endogenous cannabinoid system: A budding source of targets for treating inflammatory and neuropathic pain. Neuropsychopharmacology, 43(1), 52–79. https://www.nature.com/articles/npp2017204</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drennan, M., Karoly, H., Bryan, A., Hutchison, K., &amp; Bidwell, L. (2021). Acute objective and subjective intoxication effects of legal‐market high potency THC‐dominant versus CBD‐dominant cannabis concentrates. Scientific Reports, 11(1), Article 21744. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐021‐01128‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duke, S., Canel, C., Rimando, A., Telle, M., Duke, M., &amp; Paul, R. (2000). Current and potential exploitation of plant glandular trichome productivity. Advances in Botanical Research, 31, 121–151. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0065‐2296(00)31008‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunford, N. (2015). Hemp and flaxseed oil: Properties and applications for use in food. In G. Talbot (Ed.), Specialty oils and fats in food and nutrition (pp. 39–63). Woodhead Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐1‐78242‐376‐8.00002‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egashira, N., Manome, N., Mishima, K., Iwasaki, K., Oishi, R., &amp; Fujiwara, M. (2012). Involvement of opioid system in cognitive deficits induced by ∆9‐tetrahydrocannabinol in rats. Psychopharmacology, 219, 1111–1118. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00213‐011‐2442‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Feraly, F. S., &amp; Turner, C. E. (1975). Alkaloids of Cannabis sativa leaves. Phytochemistry, 14(10), Article 2304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elsohly, M., &amp; Turner, C. (1977). Screening of Cannabis grown from seed of various geographical origins for the alkaloids hordenine, cannabisativine and anhydrocannabisativine (Scientific Research on Cannabis 54). UN Secretariat ST/SOA/SER.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elsohly, M. A., Turner, C. E., Phoebe, C. H., Jr., Knapp, J. E., Schiff, P. L., Jr., &amp; Slatkin, D. J. (1978). Anhydrocannabisativine, a new alkaloid from Cannabis sativa L. Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences, 67(1), 124–124. https://doi.org/10.1002/jps.2600670135</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ely, K., &amp; Fike, J. (2022). Industrial hemp and hemp byproducts as sustainable feedstuffs in livestock diets. In D. C. Agrawal, R. Kumar, &amp; M. Dhanasekaran (Eds.), Cannabis/hemp for sustainable agriculture and materials (pp. 145–162). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans, J. (2020). The ultimate guide to CBD: Explore the world of cannabidiol. Fair Winds Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans, J. (2021). Cannabis drinks: Secrets to crafting CBD and THC beverages at home. Fair Winds Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fadda, P., Robinson, L., Fratta, W., Pertwee, R. G., &amp; Riedel, G. (2006). Scopolamine and MK801‐induced working memory deficits in rats are not reversed by CBD‐rich cannabis extracts. Behavioural Brain Research, 168(2), 307–311. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbr.2005.11.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farag, M. A., Elimam, D. M., &amp; Afifi, S. M. (2021). Outgoing and potential trends of the omega‐3 rich linseed oil quality characteristics and rancidity management: A comprehensive review for maximizing its food and nutraceutical applications. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 114, 292–309. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2021.05.041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fathordoobady, F., Singh, A., Kitts, D. D., &amp; Pratap Singh, A. (2019). Hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) extract: Anti‐microbial properties, methods of extraction, and potential oral delivery. Food Reviews International, 35(7), 664–684. https://doi.org/10.1080/87559129.2019.1600539</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, B., Khyatti, M., Ben‐Ayoub, W., Dahmoul, S., Ayad, M., Maachi, F., Bedadra, W., Abdoun, M., Mesli, S., &amp; Bakkali, H. (2009). Cannabis, tobacco and domestic fumes intake are associated with nasopharyngeal carcinoma in North Africa. British Journal of Cancer, 101(7), 1207–1212. https://www.nature.com/articles/6605281</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fike, J. (2016). Industrial hemp: Renewed opportunities for an ancient crop. Critical Reviews in Plant Sciences, 35(5‐6), 406–424. https://doi.org/10.1080/07352689.2016.1257842</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frassinetti, S., Moccia, E., Caltavuturo, L., Gabriele, M., Longo, V., Bellani, L., Giorgi, G., &amp; Giorgetti, L. (2018). Nutraceutical potential of hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) seeds and sprouts. Food Chemistry, 262, 56–66. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.04.078</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giese, M. W., Lewis, M. A., Giese, L., &amp; Smith, K. M. (2015). Method for the analysis of cannabinoids and terpenes in Cannabis. Journal of AOAC International, 98(6), 1503–1522. https://doi.org/10.5740/jaoacint.15‐116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giordano, G., Martin‐Willett, R., Gibson, L. P., Camidge, D. R., Bowles, D. W., Hutchison, K. E., &amp; Bryan, A. D. (2023). Cannabis use in cancer patients: Acute and sustained associations with pain, cognition, and quality of life. Exploration of Medicine, 4(2), 254–271. https://doi.org/10.37349/emed.2023.00138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Girgih, A., He, R., Malomo, S., Offengenden, M., Wu, J., &amp; Aluko, R. E. (2014). Structural and functional characterization of hemp seed (Cannabis sativa L.) protein‐derived antioxidant and antihypertensive peptides. Journal of Functional Foods, 6, 384–394. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2013.11.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon, D. (1996). From rituals of rapture to dependence: The political economy of khoikhoi narcotic consumption, c. 1487–1870. South African Historical Journal, 35(1), 62–88. https://doi.org/10.1080/02582479608671247</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant, I., Gonzalez, R., Carey, C. L., Natarajan, L., &amp; Wolfson, T. (2003). Non‐acute (residual) neurocognitive effects of cannabis use: A meta‐analytic study. Journal of the International Neuropsychological Society, 9(5), 679–689. https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal‐of‐the‐international‐neuropsychological‐society/article/abs/nonacute‐residual‐neurocognitive‐effects‐of‐cannabis‐use‐a‐metaanalytic‐study/234197F31748C9BDCAABC49C4A892DB3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greineisen, W. E., &amp; Turner, H. (2010). Immunoactive effects of cannabinoids: Considerations for the therapeutic use of cannabinoid receptor agonists and antagonists. International Immunopharmacology, 10(5), 547–555. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.intimp.2010.02.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grotenhermen, F., Leson, G., &amp; Pless, P. (2001). Assessment of exposure to and human health risk from THC and other cannabinoids in hemp foods. Leson Environmental Consulting.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall, W., &amp; Lynskey, M. (2020). Assessing the public health impacts of legalizing recreational cannabis use: The US experience. World Psychiatry, 19(2), 179–186. https://doi.org/10.1002/wps.20735</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haroutounian, S., Gilron, I., Belton, J., Degenhardt, L., Di Forti, M., Finn, D. P., Fogarty, A., Kalso, E., Krane, E., &amp; Moore, R. A. (2021). Societal issues and policy implications related to the use of cannabinoids, cannabis, and cannabis‐based medicines for pain management. Pain, 162, S110–S116. https://file/C/Users/hp/Downloads/societal_issues_and_policy_implications_related_to.10.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartsel, J. A., Eades, J., Hickory, B., &amp; Makriyannis, A. (2016). Cannabis sativa and hemp. In R. C. Gupta (Ed.), Nutraceuticals (pp. 735–754). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassoun, A., Cropotova, J., Trif, M., Rusu, A. V., Bobiş, O., Nayik, G. A., Jagdale, Y. D., Saeed, F., Afzaal, M., &amp; Mostashari, P. (2022). Consumer acceptance of new food trends resulting from the fourth industrial revolution technologies: A narrative review of literature and future perspectives. Frontiers in Nutrition, 9, Article 972154. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.972154</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawes, M. D., &amp; Cohen, M. R. (2015). Method of drying cannabis materials (U.S. Patent No. 20150096189A1). U.S. Patent and Trademark Office.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hazekamp, A. (2018). The Trouble with CBD Oil. Medical Cannabis and Cannabinoids, 1(1), 65–72. Portico. https://doi.org/10.1159/000489287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>House, J. D., Neufeld, J., &amp; Leson, G. (2010). Evaluating the quality of protein from hemp seed (Cannabis sativa L.) products through the use of the protein digestibility‐corrected amino acid score method. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 58(22), 11801–11807. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf102636b</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Guang Yuan, H. (2004). Hemp seed protein powder and its preparing method and use (China Patent No. https://patents.google.com/patent/CN1294833C/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Z., Wu, Y., Lin, B., Maskaoui, K., Zhuang, D., &amp; Zheng, T. (2006). Isolation and characterization of two phenol‐degrading yeast strains from marine sediment. Bulletin of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, 76, 899–906. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00128‐006‐1003‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iftikhar, A., Zafar, U., Ahmed, W., Shabbir, M. A., Sameen, A., Sahar, A., Bhat, Z. F., Kowalczewski, P. Ł., Jarzębski, M., &amp; Aadil, R. M. (2021). Applications of Cannabis sativa L. in food and its therapeutic potential: From a prohibited drug to a nutritional supplement. Molecules, 26(24), Article 7699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irakli, M., Tsaliki, E., Kalivas, A., Kleisiaris, F., Sarrou, E., &amp; Cook, C. M. (2019). Effect οf Genotype and Growing Year on the Nutritional, Phytochemical, and Antioxidant Properties of Industrial Hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) Seeds. Antioxidants, 8(10), 491. https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox8100491</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iversen, L. L. (2001). The science of marijuana. Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jha, P. K., Le‐Bail, A., Rawson, A., Parua, S., Mohapatra, P. K. D., &amp; Mondal, K. C. (2019). Indigenous fermented beverages of the Indian subcontinent: Processing methods, nutritional, and nutraceutical potential. In S. C. Deka, D. Seth, &amp; N. R. S. Hulle (Eds.), Food bioactives (pp. 323–358). Apple Academic Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>John, M., Black, M., Semprini, A., Oldfield, K., Glass, M., Braithwaite, I., &amp; Van Den Berg, M. (2020). Cannabis‐based medicinal products in arthritis, a painful conundrum. The New Zealand Medical Journal, 133(1515), 35–35. https://www.proquest.com/openview/2c495a65c2518afc8e0d5d6a41506eff/1?pq‐origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=1056335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson, R. (2019). Defining hemp: A fact sheet (Report No. R44742). Congressional Research Service.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaufmann, C. N., Malhotra, A., Yang, K. H., Han, B. H., Nafsu, R., Lifset, E. T., Nguyen, K., Sexton, M., &amp; Moore, A. A. (2023). Cannabis use for sleep disturbance among older patients in a geriatrics clinic. The International Journal of Aging and Human Development, 97(1), 3–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaul, M., Zee, P. C., &amp; Sahni, A. S. (2021). Effects of cannabinoids on sleep and their therapeutic potential for sleep disorders. Neurotherapeutics, 18, 217–227. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13311‐021‐01013‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khaleghi, M. (2020). New arthritis foundation guidelines on CBD use could be first of many more to come. Alternative Therapies in Health and Medicine, 26, 8–11. https://athmjournal.com/beyondcbd/wp‐content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Khaleghi.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kicman, A., &amp; Toczek, M. (2020). The effects of cannabidiol, a non‐intoxicating compound of cannabis, on the cardiovascular system in health and disease. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 21(18), Article 6740. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21186740</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein, R. F. (2017). Analysis of “marijuana edibles”—Food products containing marijuana or marijuana extracts—An overview, review, and literature survey. Microgram Journal, 14(1–4), 9–32. https://www.dea.gov/sites/default/files/pr/microgram‐journals/2017/mj14‐1_9‐32.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klumpers, L. E., &amp; Thacker, D. L. (2019). A brief background on cannabis: From plant to medical indications. Journal of AOAC International, 102(2), 412–420. https://doi.org/10.5740/jaoacint.18‐0208</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koenigs, R. (2022). Brewing with hemp: The essential guide. Brewers Association.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kolodziejczyk, P., Ozimek, L., &amp; Kozłowska, J. (2012). The application of flax and hemp seeds in food, animal feed and cosmetics production. In R. M. Kozłowski (Ed.), Handbook of natural fibres (pp. 329–366). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kontogianni, M. D., Vlassopoulos, A., Gatzieva, A., Farmaki, A.‐E., Katsiougiannis, S., Panagiotakos, D. B., Kalogeropoulos, N., &amp; Skopouli, F. N. (2013). Flaxseed oil does not affect inflammatory markers and lipid profile compared to olive oil, in young, healthy, normal weight adults. Metabolism, 62(5), 686–693. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.metabol.2012.11.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kornpointner, C., Martinez, A. S., Marinovic, S., Haselmair‐Gosch, C., Jamnik, P., Schröder, K., Löfke, C., &amp; Halbwirth, H. (2021). Chemical composition and antioxidant potential of Cannabis sativa L. roots. Industrial Crops and Products, 165, Article 113422. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2021.113422</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korus, J., Witczak, M., Ziobro, R., &amp; Juszczak, L. (2017). Hemp (Cannabis sativa subsp. sativa) flour and protein preparation as natural nutrients and structure forming agents in starch based gluten‐free bread. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology, 84, 143–150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2017.05.046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kosa, K. M., Giombi, K. C., Rains, C. B., &amp; Cates, S. C. (2017). Consumer use and understanding of labelling information on edible marijuana products sold for recreational use in the states of Colorado and Washington. International Journal of Drug Policy, 43, 57–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraszkiewicz, A., Kachel, M., Parafiniuk, S., Zając, G., Niedziółka, I., &amp; Sprawka, M. (2019). Assessment of the possibility of using hemp biomass (Cannabis sativa L.) for energy purposes: A case study. Applied Sciences, 9(20), Article 4437. https://doi.org/10.3390/app9204437</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krüger, M., van Eeden, T., &amp; Beswa, D. (2022). Cannabis sativa cannabinoids as functional ingredients in snack foods—Historical and developmental aspects. Plants, 11(23), Article 3330. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11233330</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kukula‐Koch, W., &amp; Widelski, J. (2017). Alkaloids. In R. McCreath (Ed.), Pharmacognosy: Fundamentals, applications and strategies (pp. 163–198). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuzdzal, S., Clifford, R., Winkler, P., &amp; Bankert, W. (2018). Cannabis testing: Taking a closer look. In B. Wedman‐St. Louis (Ed.), Cannabis (pp. 233–246). CRC Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lachenmeier, D. W., &amp; Walch, S. G. (2005). Analysis and toxicological evaluation of cannabinoids in hemp food products—A review. Electronic Journal of Environmental, Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 4, 812–826. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.438133</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamy, F. R., Daniulaityte, R., Sheth, A., Nahhas, R. W., Martins, S. S., Boyer, E. W., &amp; Carlson, R. G. (2016). “Those edibles hit hard”: Exploration of Twitter data on cannabis edibles in the US. Drug and Alcohol Dependence, 164, 64–70. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2016.04.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanni, C., Lenzken, S. C., Pascale, A., Del Vecchio, I., Racchi, M., Pistoia, F., &amp; Govoni, S. (2008). Cognition enhancers between treating and doping the mind. Pharmacological Research, 57(3), 196–213. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2008.02.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanzoni, D., Skřivanová, E., Rebucci, R., Crotti, A., Baldi, A., Marchetti, L., &amp; Giromini, C. (2023). Total phenolic content and antioxidant activity of in vitro digested hemp‐based products. Foods, 12(3), Article 601.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larkin, P. J., Jr. (2018). Marijuana edibles and “gummy bears”. Buffalo Law Review, 66(2), 313–383.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latter, H. L., Abraham, D. J., Turner, C. E., Knapp, J. E., Schiff, P. L., Jr., &amp; Slatkin, D. J. (1975). Cannabisativine, a new alkaloid from Cannabis sativa L. root. Tetrahedron Letters, 16(33), 2815–2818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavorato, V. (2021). Double chocolate weed brownies. https://food52.com/recipes/85328‐best‐weed‐brownies‐recipe</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawrence, R. G. (2019). Pot in pans: A history of eating cannabis. Rowman &amp; Littlefield.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarjani, M. P., Young, O., Kebede, L., &amp; Seyfoddin, A. (2021). Processing and extraction methods of medicinal cannabis: A narrative review. Journal of Cannabis Research, 3, Article 32. https://doi.org/10.1186/s42238‐021‐00087‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leonard, W., Zhang, P., Ying, D., &amp; Fang, Z. (2020). Hempseed in food industry: Nutritional value, health benefits, and industrial applications. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 19(1), 282–308. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12517</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Carvajal, R., Bruner, L., &amp; Kaminski, N. E. (2021). The current understanding of the benefits, safety, and regulation of cannabidiol in consumer products. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 157, Article 112600. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2021.112600</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Light, K., &amp; Karboune, S. (2022). Emulsion, hydrogel and emulgel systems and novel applications in cannabinoid delivery: A review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 62(29), 8199–8229. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2021.1926903</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindholst, C. (2010). Long term stability of cannabis resin and cannabis extracts. Australian Journal of Forensic Sciences, 42(3), 181–190. https://doi.org/10.1080/00450610903258144</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindsay, C. C. (2022). Form and content of Jamaican cannabis edibles. Toxicologie Analytique et Clinique, 34(3), S133–S134. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxac.2022.06.221</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindsay, C. M., Abel, W. D., Jones‐Edwards, E. E., Brown, P. D., Bernard, K. K., &amp; Taylor, T. T. (2021). Form and content of Jamaican cannabis edibles. Journal of Cannabis Research, 3, Article 29. https://doi.org/10.1186/s42238‐021‐00079‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo, M. (2022). The weed gummies cookbook: Recipes for cannabis candies, THC and CBD edibles, and more. Simon and Schuster.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Łopusiewicz, Ł., Waszkowiak, K., Polanowska, K., Mikołajczak, B., Śmietana, N., Hrebień‐Filisińska, A., Sadowska, J., Mazurkiewicz‐Zapałowicz, K., &amp; Drozłowska, E. (2022). The effect of yogurt and kefir starter cultures on bioactivity of fermented industrial by‐product from Cannabis sativa production—Hemp press cake. Fermentation, 8(10), Article 490. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation8100490</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorca, C., Mulet, M., Arévalo‐Caro, C., Sanchez, M. Á., Perez, A., Perrino, M., Bach‐Faig, A., Aguilar‐Martínez, A., Vilella, E., &amp; Gallart‐Palau, X. (2023). Plant‐derived nootropics and human cognition: A systematic review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 63(22), 5521–5545. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2021.2021137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Louis, B. W.‐S. (2018). Cannabis nutrition. In B. Wedman‐St. Louis (Ed.), Cannabis (pp. 159–180). CRC Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maddison, K. J., Kosky, C., &amp; Walsh, J. H. (2022). Is there a place for medicinal cannabis in treating patients with sleep disorders? What we know so far. Nature and Science of Sleep, 14, 957–968. https://doi.org/10.2147/NSS.S340949</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maguire, W. J., Call, C. W., Cerbu, C., Jambor, K. L., &amp; Benavides‐Montes, V. E. (2019). Comprehensive determination of unregulated pesticide residues in Oregon cannabis flower by liquid chromatography paired with triple quadrupole mass spectrometry and gas chromatography paired with triple quadrupole mass spectrometry. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 67(46), 12670–12674. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.9b01559</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahvan, T. D., Hilaire, M. L., Mann, A., Brown, A., Linn, B., Gardner, T., &amp; Lai, B. (2017). Marijuana use in the elderly: Implications and considerations. The Consultant Pharmacist, 32(6), 341–351. https://doi.org/10.4140/TCP.n.2017.341</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malabadi, R. B., Kolkar, K. P., &amp; Chalannavar, R. K. (2023). Cannabis sativa: Industrial hemp (fiber‐type)—An emerging opportunity for India. International Journal of Research and Scientific Innovation (IJRSI), 10(3), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.51244/IJRS</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malone, T., &amp; Gomez, K. (2019). Hemp in the United States: A case study of regulatory path dependence. Applied Economic Perspectives and Policy, 41(2), 199–214. https://doi.org/10.1093/aepp/ppz001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marangoni, I. P., &amp; Marangoni, A. G. (2019). Cannabis edibles: Dosing, encapsulation, and stability considerations. Current Opinion in Food Science, 28, 1–6. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2019.01.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez, V., Iriondo de‐Hond, A., Borrelli, F., Capasso, R., del Castillo, M. D., &amp; Abalo, R. (2020). Cannabidiol and other non‐psychoactive cannabinoids for prevention and treatment of gastrointestinal disorders: Useful nutraceuticals? International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 21(9), Article 3067. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21093067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matheson, J., &amp; Le Foll, B. (2020). Cannabis legalization and acute harm from high potency cannabis products: A narrative review and recommendations for public health. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 11, Article 591979. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2020.591979</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metz, M., &amp; Selg‐Mann, K. (2000). Production of a food seasoning, e.g. useful as a substitute for soy sauce, by two‐stage fermentation of hemp seeds (Germany Patent No. https://patents.google.com/patent/DE10002389A1/en Available online: https://patents.google.com/patent/DE10002389A1/en (accessed on 25 December 2023)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGregor, I. S., Cairns, E. A., Abelev, S., Cohen, R., Henderson, M., Couch, D., Arnold, J. C., &amp; Gauld, N. (2020). Access to cannabidiol without a prescription: A cross‐country comparison and analysis. International Journal of Drug Policy, 85, 102935. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugpo.2020.102935</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McPartland, J. M., &amp; McKernan, K. J. (2017). Contaminants of concern in cannabis: Microbes, heavy metals and pesticides. In S. Chandra, H. Lata, &amp; M. ElSohly (Eds.), Cannabis sativa L.—Botany and biotechnology (pp. 457–474). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mead, A. (2019). Legal and regulatory issues governing cannabis and cannabis‐derived products in the United States. Frontiers in Plant Science, 10, Article 697. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2019.00697</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mechoulam, R., Devane, W., &amp; Glaser, R. (2019). Cannabinoid geometry and biological activity. In G. G. Nahas, K. M. Sutin, D. Harvey, S. Agurell, N. Pace, &amp; R. Cancro (Eds.), Marihuana and medicine (pp. 65–90). Taylor and Francis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meija, J., McRae, G., Miles, C. O., &amp; Melanson, J. E. (2022). Thermal stability of cannabinoids in dried cannabis: A kinetic study. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 414, 377–384. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216‐020‐03098‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mezher, J. (2023). Sweet treats: How to make a weed cake. https://apotforpot.com/blogs/recipes/weed‐cake/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mihoc, M., Pop, G., Alexa, E., &amp; Radulov, I. (2012). Nutritive quality of romanian hemp varieties (Cannabis sativa L.) with special focus on oil and metal contents of seeds. Chemistry Central Journal, 6(1), Article 122. https://doi.org/10.1186/1752‐153X‐6‐122</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra, G., Singh, P., Molla, M., Yimer, Y. S., Ewunetie, A., Tadesse, T. Y., Ayele, T. M., &amp; Kefale, B. (2022). Nutraceuticals: A source of benefaction for neuropathic pain and fibromyalgia. Journal of Functional Foods, 97, Article 105260. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2022.105260</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moltke, J., &amp; Hindocha, C. (2021). Reasons for cannabidiol use: A cross‐sectional study of CBD users, focusing on self‐perceived stress, anxiety, and sleep problems. Journal of Cannabis Research, 3, Article 5. https://doi.org/10.1186/s42238‐021‐00061‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mostafaei Dehnavi, M., Ebadi, A., Peirovi, A., Taylor, G., &amp; Salami, S. A. (2022). THC and CBD fingerprinting of an elite cannabis collection from Iran: Quantifying diversity to underpin future cannabis breeding. Plants, 11(1), Article 129. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11010129</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naeem, M. Y., Corbo, F., Crupi, P., &amp; Clodoveo, M. L. (2023). Hemp: An alternative source for various industries and an emerging tool for functional food and pharmaceutical sectors. Processes, 11(3), Article 718. https://doi.org/10.3390/pr11030718</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagarkatti, P., Pandey, R., Rieder, S. A., Hegde, V. L., &amp; Nagarkatti, M. (2009). Cannabinoids as novel anti‐inflammatory drugs. Future Medicinal Chemistry, 1(7), 1333–1349. https://doi.org/10.4155/fmc.09.93</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namdar, D., Charuvi, D., Ajjampura, V., Mazuz, M., Ion, A., Kamara, I., &amp; Koltai, H. (2019). LED lighting affects the composition and biological activity of Cannabis sativa secondary metabolites. Industrial Crops and Products, 132, 177–185. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.02.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niloy, N., Hediyal, T. A., Vichitra, C., Sonali, S., Chidambaram, S. B., Gorantla, V. R., &amp; Mahalakshmi, A. M. (2023). Effect of cannabis on memory consolidation, learning and retrieval and its current legal status in India: A review. Biomolecules, 13(1), Article 162. https://doi.org/10.3390/biom13010162</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nissen, L., Casciano, F., Babini, E., &amp; Gianotti, A. (2022). Industrial hemp foods and beverages and product properties. In M. Pojić &amp; B. K. Tiwari (Eds.), Industrial hemp (pp. 219–246). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nissen, L., di Carlo, E., &amp; Gianotti, A. (2020). Prebiotic potential of hemp blended drinks fermented by probiotics. Food Research International, 131, Article 109029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norajit, K., Gu, B.‐J., &amp; Ryu, G.‐H. (2011). Effects of the addition of hemp powder on the physicochemical properties and energy bar qualities of extruded rice. Food Chemistry, 129(4), 1919–1925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuutinen, T. (2018). Medicinal properties of terpenes found in Cannabis sativa and Humulus lupulus. European Journal of Medicinal Chemistry, 157, 198–228. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2018.07.076</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyland, C. R., &amp; Moyer, D. C. (2022). Regulating for safety: Cannabidiol dose in food: A review. Journal of Food Protection, 85(9), 1355–1369. https://doi.org/10.4315/JFP‐21‐374</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Brien, K., &amp; Blair, P. (2021). Overview of medicinal cannabis. In K. O'Brien &amp; P. Blair (Eds.), Medicinal cannabis and CBD in mental healthcare (pp. 89–129). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orsolini, L., Chiappini, S., Volpe, U., De Berardis, D., Latini, R., Papanti, G. D., &amp; Corkery, J. M. (2019). Use of medicinal cannabis and synthetic cannabinoids in post‐traumatic stress disorder (PTSD): A systematic review. Medicina, 55(9), Article 525. https://doi.org/10.3390/medicina55090525</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parnes, J. E., Smith, J. K., &amp; Conner, B. T. (2018). Reefer madness or much ado about nothing? Cannabis legalization outcomes among young adults in the United States. International Journal of Drug Policy, 56, 116–120. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugpo.2018.03.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Passie, T., Emrich, H. M., Karst, M., Brandt, S. D., &amp; Halpern, J. H. (2012). Mitigation of post‐traumatic stress symptoms by Cannabis resin: A review of the clinical and neurobiological evidence. Drug Testing and Analysis, 4(7–8), 649–659. https://doi.org/10.1002/dta.1377</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathak, S., Nadar, R., Deruiter, J., Ramesh, S., Ramapuram, J. B., Govidarajulu, M., Moore, T., Agrawal, D. C., &amp; Dhanasekaran, M. (2022). Cannabis as a unique and valuable nutraceutical formulation for the current and future global wellbeing. In D. C. Agrawal, R. Kumar, &amp; M. Dhanasekaran (Eds.), Cannabis/marijuana for healthcare (pp. 271–299). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavlovic, R., Nenna, G., Calvi, L., Panseri, S., Borgonovo, G., Giupponi, L., Cannazza, G., &amp; Giorgi, A. (2018). Quality traits of “cannabidiol oils”: Cannabinoids content, terpene fingerprint and oxidation stability of European commercially available preparations. Molecules, 23(5), Article 1230. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules23051230</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, H., &amp; Shahidi, F. (2021). Cannabis and cannabis edibles: A review. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 69(6), 1751–1774. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.0c07472</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peralt, A., Ke, P., &amp; Castaneto, M. S. (2022). Impact of cannabis‐infused edibles on public safety and regulation. Journal of Forensic Sciences, 67(6), 2387–2393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perlmutter, S. B. (2019). High times ahead: Products liability in medical marijuana. Health Matrix: The Journal of Law‐Medicine, 29, 225–291. https://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/hmax29&amp;div=8&amp;id=&amp;page=</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisanti, S., &amp; Bifulco, M. (2019). Medical Cannabis: A plurimillennial history of an evergreen. Journal of Cellular Physiology, 234(6), 8342–8351. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcp.27725</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisciottano, I. D. M. (2023). Cannabis‐related compounds in beverages and food. In C. R. Martin, V. B. Patel, &amp; V. R. Preedy (Eds.), Cannabis use, neurobiology, psychology, and treatment (pp. 33–54). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollastro, F., Minassi, A., &amp; Fresu, L. G. (2018). Cannabis phenolics and their bioactivities. Current Medicinal Chemistry, 25(10), 1160–1185. https://doi.org/10.2174/0929867324666170810164636</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pretorius, S. P. (2006). The significance of the use of ganja as a religious ritual in the Rastafari movement. Verbum et Ecclesia, 27(3), 1012–1030. https://doi.org/10.4102/ve.v27i3.199</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qamar, S., Torres, Y. J., Parekh, H. S., &amp; Falconer, J. R. (2021). Extraction of medicinal cannabinoids through supercritical carbon dioxide technologies: A review. Journal of Chromatography B, 1167, Article 122581. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jchromb.2021.122581</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radočaj, O., Dimić, E., &amp; Tsao, R. (2014). Effects of hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) seed oil press‐cake and decaffeinated green tea leaves (Camellia sinensis) on functional characteristics of gluten‐free crackers. Journal of Food Science, 79(3), C318–C325. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.12370</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasera, G. B., Ohara, A., &amp; de Castro, R. J. S. (2021). Innovative and emerging applications of cannabis in food and beverage products: From an illicit drug to a potential ingredient for health promotion. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 115, 31–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashid, A., Ali, V., Khajuria, M., Faiz, S., Gairola, S., &amp; Vyas, D. (2021). GC–MS based metabolomic approach to understand nutraceutical potential of Cannabis seeds from two different environments. Food Chemistry, 339, 128076. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.128076</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman, M., Fahad, S., Du, G., Cheng, X., Yang, Y., Tang, K., Liu, L., Liu, F.‐H., &amp; Deng, G. (2021). Evaluation of hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) as an industrial crop: A review. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 28(38), 52832–52843. https://doi.org/10.3390/app9204437</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez‐Martin, N. M., Toscano, R., Villanueva, A., Pedroche, J., Millan, F., Montserrat‐de la Paz, S., &amp; Millan‐Linares, M. C. (2019). Neuroprotective protein hydrolysates from hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) seeds. Food &amp; Function, 10(10), 6732–6739. https://doi.org/10.1039/c9fo01904a</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romano, L. L., &amp; Hazekamp, A. (2013). Cannabis oil: Chemical evaluation of an upcoming cannabis‐based medicine. Cannabinoids, 1(1), 1–11. https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Arno‐Hazekamp/publication/297707359_Cannabis_oil_Chemical_evaluation_of_an_upcoming_cannabis‐_based_medicine/links/57c923a808ae9d6404818918/Cannabis‐oil‐Chemical‐evaluation‐of‐an‐upcoming‐cannabis‐based‐medicine.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rong, C., Lee, Y., Carmona, N. E., Cha, D. S., Ragguett, R.‐M., Rosenblat, J. D., Mansur, R. B., Ho, R. C., &amp; McIntyre, R. S. (2017). Cannabidiol in medical marijuana: Research vistas and potential opportunities. Pharmacological Research, 121, 213–218. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2017.05.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rupasinghe, H. V., Davis, A., Kumar, S. K., Murray, B., &amp; Zheljazkov, V. D. (2020). Industrial hemp (Cannabis sativa subsp. sativa) as an emerging source for value‐added functional food ingredients and nutraceuticals. Molecules, 25(18), Article 4078. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules25184078</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo, E. B. (2016). Current therapeutic cannabis controversies and clinical trial design issues. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 7, Article 309. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2016.00309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryz, N. R., Remillard, D. J., &amp; Russo, E. B. (2017). Cannabis roots: A traditional therapy with future potential for treating inflammation and pain. Cannabis and Cannabinoid Research, 2(1), 210–216. https://doi.org/10.1089/can.2017.0028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samsamikor, M., Mackay, D., Mollard, R. C., &amp; Aluko, R. E. (2020). A double‐blind, randomized, crossover trial protocol of whole hemp seed protein and hemp seed protein hydrolysate consumption for hypertension. Trials, 21, Article 354. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13063‐020‐4164‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarma, N. D., Waye, A., ElSohly, M. A., Brown, P. N., Elzinga, S., Johnson, H. E., Marles, R. J., Melanson, J. E., Russo, E., &amp; Deyton, L. (2020). Cannabis inflorescence for medical purposes: USP considerations for quality attributes. Journal of Natural Products, 83(4), 1334–1351. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b01200</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheuer, L. (2020). The green rush: The public marijuana securities market. Widener Law Review, 26(1), 53–100. https://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/wlsj26&amp;div=8&amp;id=&amp;page=</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuster, R. M., Gilman, J., Schoenfeld, D., Evenden, J., Hareli, M., Ulysse, C., Nip, E., Hanly, A., Zhang, H., &amp; Evins, A. E. (2018). One month of cannabis abstinence in adolescents and young adults is associated with improved memory. The Journal of Clinical Psychiatry, 79(6), Article 17m11977.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwab, U. S., Callaway, J. C., Erkkilä, A. T., Gynther, J., Uusitupa, M. I., &amp; Järvinen, T. (2006). Effects of hempseed and flaxseed oils on the profile of serum lipids, serum total and lipoprotein lipid concentrations and haemostatic factors. European Journal of Nutrition, 45, 470–477. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00394‐006‐0621‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sen, C. T. (2004). Food culture in India. Greenwood Publishing Group.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sethi, V., Jain, M., &amp; Thakur, R. (1977). Chemical investigation of wild Cannabis sativa L. roots. Planta Medica, 32(08), 378–379. https://doi.org/10.1055/s‐0028‐1097617</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shim, J.‐Y. (2009). Transmembrane Helical Domain of the Cannabinoid CB1 Receptor. Biophysical Journal, 96(8), 3251–3262. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2008.12.3934</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silver, R., Wakshalg, J., Wynn, S., &amp; Kramer, K. (2021). Nutritional analysis of Cannabis. In S. Cital, K. Kramer, L. Hughston, &amp; J. S. Gaynor (Eds.), Cannabis therapy in veterinary medicine: A complete guide (pp. 271–293). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, S., Singh, T. G., Mahajan, K., &amp; Dhiman, S. (2020). Medicinal plants used against various inflammatory biomarkers for the management of rheumatoid arthritis. Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmacology, 72(10), 1306–1327. https://doi.org/10.1111/jphp.13326</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skelley, J. W., Deas, C. M., Curren, Z., &amp; Ennis, J. (2020). Use of cannabidiol in anxiety and anxiety‐related disorders. Journal of the American Pharmacists Association, 60(1), 253–261. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.japh.2019.11.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Small, E. (2015). Evolution and classification of Cannabis sativa (marijuana, hemp) in relation to human utilization. The Botanical Review, 81, 189–294. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12229‐015‐9157‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, J. W., Evans, A. T., Costall, B., &amp; Smythe, J. W. (2002). Thyroid hormones, brain function and cognition: A brief review. Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews, 26(1), 45–60. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0149‐7634(01)00037‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sommano, S. R., Chittasupho, C., Ruksiriwanich, W., &amp; Jantrawut, P. (2020). The cannabis terpenes. Molecules, 25(24), Article 5792. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules25245792</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sommano, S. R., Sunanta, P., Leksawasdi, N., Jantanasakulwong, K., Rachtanapun, P., Seesuriyachan, P., Phimolsiripol, Y., Sringarm, K., Ruksiriwanich, W., &amp; Jantrawut, P. (2022). Mass spectrometry‐based metabolomics of phytocannabinoids from non‐cannabis plant origins. Molecules, 27(10), Article 3301. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27103301</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinbach, W. (1997). Hemp pralines (Germany Patent No. https://patents.google.com/patent/DE19746830C1/en. Available online: https://patents.google.com/patent/DE19746830C1/en (accessed on 20 December, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steigerwald, S., Wong, P. O., Khorasani, A., &amp; Keyhani, S. (2018). The Form and Content of Cannabis Products in the United States. Journal of General Internal Medicine, 33(9), 1426–1428. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606‐018‐4480‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stith, S. S., Li, X., Diviant, J. P., Brockelman, F. C., Keeling, K. S., Hall, B., &amp; Vigil, J. M. (2020). The effectiveness of inhaled Cannabis flower for the treatment of agitation/irritability, anxiety, and common stress. Journal of Cannabis Research, 2, Article 47. https://doi.org/10.1186/s42238‐020‐00051‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subritzky, T., Pettigrew, S., &amp; Lenton, S. (2017). Into the void: Regulating pesticide use in Colorado's commercial cannabis markets. International Journal of Drug Policy, 42, 86–96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunda, F., &amp; Arowolo, A. (2020). A molecular basis for the anti‐inflammatory and anti‐fibrosis properties of cannabidiol. The FASEB Journal, 34(11), 14083–14092. https://doi.org/10.1096/fj.202000975R</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swift, W., Wong, A., Li, K. M., Arnold, J. C., &amp; McGregor, I. S. (2013). Analysis of cannabis seizures in NSW, Australia: Cannabis potency and cannabinoid profile. PLoS ONE, 8(7), Article e70052. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0070052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taura, F., Sirikantaramas, S., Shoyama, Y., Shoyama, Y., &amp; Morimoto, S. (2007). Phytocannabinoids in Cannabis sativa: Recent studies on biosynthetic enzymes. Chemistry &amp; Biodiversity, 4(8), 1649–1663. https://www.icmag.com/attachments/taura‐phytocannabinoids‐in‐cannabis‐and‐biosynthetic‐enzymes‐pdf.12693157/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tireki, S. (2021). A review on packed non‐alcoholic beverages: Ingredients, production, trends and future opportunities for functional product development. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 112, 442–454. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2021.03.058</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tonoyan, L., Babu, D., Reiz, B., Le, T., &amp; Siraki, A. G. (2022). Heating of consumer cannabis oils can lead to free radical initiated degradation, causing CBD and THC depletion. Free Radical Biology and Medicine, 192, 77–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsaliki, E., Kalivas, A., Jankauskiene, Z., Irakli, M., Cook, C., Grigoriadis, I., Panoras, I., Vasilakoglou, I., &amp; Dhima, K. (2021). Fibre and seed productivity of industrial hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) varieties under mediterranean conditions. Agronomy, 11(1), Article 171. https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy11010171</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turgeman, I., &amp; Bar‐Sela, G. (2019). Cannabis for cancer – Illusion or the tip of an iceberg: A review of the evidence for the use of Cannabis and synthetic cannabinoids in oncology. Expert Opinion on Investigational Drugs, 28(3), 285–296. https://doi.org/10.1080/13543784.2019.1561859</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ujváry, I. (2023). Hexahydrocannabinol and closely related semi‐synthetic cannabinoids: A comprehensive review. Drug Testing and Analysis, 16(2), 127–161. https://doi.org/10.1002/dta.3519</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urits, I., Gress, K., Charipova, K., Habib, K., Lee, D., Lee, C., Jung, J. W., Kassem, H., Cornett, E., &amp; Paladini, A. (2020). Use of cannabidiol (CBD) for the treatment of chronic pain. Best Practice &amp; Research Clinical Anaesthesiology, 34(3), 463–477. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpa.2020.06.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valizadehderakhshan, M. (2022). Extraction and purification of cannabinoids from hemp – Experimentation and process modeling. North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Solinge, T. B. (1996). Ganja in Jamaica. Amsterdams Drug Tijdschrift, 2, 11–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Tran, K., Twohig, M., &amp; Hudalla, C. J. (2021). Analysis of cannabinoids in Cannabis plant materials and edible products using ultraperformance liquid chromatography (UPLC) with PDA and mass detection. Waters Corporation, ProVerde Laboratories. https://www.waters.com/webassets/cms/library/docs/720007199en.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Von Meer, G. U. B. (2014). Method of obtaining hemp plant juice and use of same for the production of beverages (U.S. Patent No 20140044807A1). U.S. Patent and Trademark Office.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagoner, K. G., Lazard, A. J., Romero‐Sandoval, E. A., &amp; Reboussin, B. A. (2021). Health claims about cannabidiol products: A retrospective analysis of US Food and Drug Administration warning letters from 2015 to 2019. Cannabis and Cannabinoid Research, 6(6), 559–563. https://doi.org/10.1089/can.2020.0166</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waheed, M., Haq, S. M., Arshad, F., Bussmann, R. W., Pieroni, A., Mahmoud, E. A., Casini, R., Yessoufou, K., &amp; Elansary, H. O. (2023). Traditional wild food plants gathered by ethnic groups living in semi‐arid region of Punjab, Pakistan. Biology, 12(2), Article 269. https://doi.org/10.3390/biology12020269</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werz, O., Seegers, J., Schaible, A. M., Weinigel, C., Barz, D., Koeberle, A., Allegrone, G., Pollastro, F., Zampieri, L., Grassi, G., &amp; Appendino, G. (2014). Cannflavins from hemp sprouts, a novel cannabinoid‐free hemp food product, target microsomal prostaglandin E2 synthase‐1 and 5‐lipoxygenase. PharmaNutrition, 2(3), 53–60. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phanu.2014.05.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White, C. M., Browne, T., &amp; Nafziger, A. N. (2021). Inherent dangers of using non–US Food and Drug Administration–approved substances of abuse. The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology, 61, S129–S141. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcph.1860</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witkop, M., Lambing, A., &amp; Fritz, R. (2012). Prevalence of pain. National Hemophilia Foundation. Nursing Working Group. Nurses’ Guide to Bleeding Disorders, 1–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolf, C. E., Poklis, J. L., &amp; Poklis, A. (2017). Stability of tetrahydrocannabinol and cannabidiol in prepared quality control medible brownies. Journal of Analytical Toxicology, 41(2), 153–157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, J., Bai, M., Song, H., Yang, L., Zhu, D., &amp; Liu, H. (2022). Hemp (Cannabis sativa subsp. sativa) Chemical composition and the application of hempseeds in food formulations. Plant Foods for Human Nutrition, 77(4), 504–513. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11130‐022‐01013‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, Y., Li, J., Zhao, J., Wang, W., Griffin, J., Li, Y., Bean, S., Tilley, M., &amp; Wang, D. (2021). Hempseed as a nutritious and healthy human food or animal feed source: A review. International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology, 56(2), 530–543. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.14755</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yalcin, H., Konca, Y., &amp; Durmuscelebi, F. (2018). Effect of dietary supplementation of hemp seed (Cannabis sativa L.) on meat quality and egg fatty acid composition of Japanese quail (Coturnix coturnix japonica). Journal of Animal Physiology and Animal Nutrition, 102(1), 131–141. https://doi.org/10.1111/jpn.12670</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Y., Lewis, M. M., Bello, A. M., Wasilewski, E., Clarke, H. A., &amp; Kotra, L. P. (2017). Cannabis sativa (hemp) seeds, Δ9‐tetrahydrocannabinol, and potential overdose. Cannabis and Cannabinoid Research, 2(1), 274–281. https://doi.org/10.1089/can.2017.0040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M., Li, T., Guo, G., Liu, Z., &amp; Hao, N. (2023). Production of nattokinase from hemp seed meal by solid‐state fermentation and improvement of its nutritional quality. Fermentation, 9(5), Article 469. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation9050469</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, H., Chen, B., &amp; Rao, J. (2022). Nutraceutical potential of industrial hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) extracts: physicochemical stability and bioaccessibility of cannabidiol (CBD) nanoemulsions. Food &amp; Function, 13(8), 4502–4512. https://doi.org/10.1039/d1fo04433h</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhornitsky, S., &amp; Potvin, S. (2012). Cannabidiol in humans—The quest for therapeutic targets. Pharmaceuticals, 5(5), 529–552. https://doi.org/10.3390/ph5050529</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, Y., Wang, S., Ji, J., Lou, H., &amp; Fan, P. (2018). Hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) seed phenylpropionamides composition and effects on memory dysfunction and biomarkers of neuroinflammation induced by lipopolysaccharide in mice. ACS Omega, 3(11), 15988–15995. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.8b02250</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimniewska, M. (2022). Hemp fibre properties and processing target textile: A review. Materials, 15(5), Article 1901. https://doi.org/10.3390/ma15051901</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuurman, L., Ippel, A. E., Moin, E., &amp; Van Gerven, J. M. (2009). Biomarkers for the effects of cannabis and THC in healthy volunteers. British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology, 67(1), 5–21. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2125.2008.03329.x</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>