<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39267987</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2662-4044</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>5</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>CABI agriculture and bioscience</Title><ISOAbbreviation>CABI Agric Biosci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of storage conditions on the shelf life of aflatoxin biocontrol products containing atoxigenic isolates of <i>Aspergillus flavus</i> as active ingredient applied in various countries in Africa.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>78</StartPage><MedlinePgn>78</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">78</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s43170-024-00283-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Aflatoxin contamination significantly threatens food safety and security, particularly in tropical and sub-tropical regions where staple crops such as maize, groundnut, and sorghum become frequently affected. This contamination is primarily caused by the fungus <i>Aspergillus flavus</i>. The contamination causes adverse health effects, reduced income, and trade restrictions. In response to this challenge, various technologies have been developed to mitigate the impacts of aflatoxin. Among these, biocontrol products containing atoxigenic isolates of <i>A. flavus</i> as the active ingredient can effectively reduce aflatoxin levels both at pre- and post-harvest. A notable example of such products is Aflasafe, which contains four atoxigenic isolates native to specific target regions. These products have undergone rigorous testing, have received regulatory approval, and are commercially available in multiple African countries. However, their manufacturing processes have evolved, and comprehensive shelf life studies for current formulations are lacking. Evaluations of the spore production ability of atoxigenic <i>A. flavus</i> isolates in Aflasafe products over 4 years, under various storage conditions, revealed a significant linear decrease in sporulation with storage months (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001; <i>R</i> <sup><i>2</i></sup>  = 0.203), with no significant differences observed between treatments. However, this marginal decline (<i>P</i> = 0.398) is unlikely to be sufficient to prevent the effectiveness in limiting aflatoxin. In addition, storing the products for 2 weeks at 54 °C did not affect (<i>P</i> &gt; 0.05) the ability of the coated fungi to produce spores compared to when the products were stored at 24 °C. The findings contribute valuable insights for manufacturers and users of atoxigenic-based aflatoxin biocontrol products, informing best practices for product storage and utilization to ensure prolonged effectivenes in aflatoxin mitigation efforts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ortega-Beltran</LastName><ForeName>Alejandro</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3747-8094</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02smred28</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.512912.c</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aikore</LastName><ForeName>M O Samuel</ForeName><Initials>MOS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02smred28</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.512912.c</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaptoge</LastName><ForeName>Lawrence</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02smred28</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.512912.c</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agbetiameh</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02smred28</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.512912.c</Identifier></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Crop and Soil Sciences, Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology, Kumasi, Ghana.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/00cb23x68</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.9829.a</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0946 6120</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moral</LastName><ForeName>Juan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departamento de Agronomía, Universidad de Córdoba, Maria de Maeztu Unit of Excelente, Córdoba, Spain.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/05yc77b46</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411901.c</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2183 9102</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bandyopadhyay</LastName><ForeName>Ranajit</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02smred28</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.512912.c</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>CABI Agric Biosci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101777285</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2662-4044</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aflatoxin control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Aspergillus flavus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Atoxigenic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioprotectant</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Long-term stability</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Competing interestsThe authors received no direct financial benefit from the manufacturing and marketing of any of the aflatoxin biocontrol products mentioned in this article. The Aflasafe name is the Trademark of the International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA). IITA used to manufacture and commercialize Aflasafe for use in Nigeria, Senegal, Burkina Faso, The Gambia, and Ghana. Manufacturing and distribution responsibilities have been licensed to the private or public sector. IITA charges a small licensing fee to manufacturers for the use of the Aflasafe name and the cost associated with technology transfer and technical backstopping. A. Ortega-Beltran, M.O.S. Aikore, and L. Kaptoge are IITA employees. D. Agbetiameh was a Graduate Student at IITA when the studies were conducted. R. Bandyopadhyay was an IITA employee at the time of the study; after retirement, he continued with IITA as an Emeritus Scientist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39267987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11387433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s43170-024-00283-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adhikari BN, Bandyopadhyay R, Cotty PJ. Degeneration of aflatoxin gene clusters in Aspergillus flavus from Africa and North America. AMB Express. 2016;6:62. 10.1186/s13568-016-0228-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13568-016-0228-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5005231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27576895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agbetiameh D, Ortega-Beltran A, Awuah RT, Callicott KA, Cotty PJ, Bandyopadhyay R. Potential of atoxigenic Aspergillus flavus vegetative compatibility groups associated with maize and groundnut in Ghana as biocontrol agents for aflatoxin management. Front Microbiol. 2019;10:2069. 10.3389/fmicb.2019.02069</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6743268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31555251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agbetiameh D, Ortega-Beltran A, Awuah RT, Atehnkeng J, Elzein A, Cotty PJ, et al. Field efficacy of two atoxigenic biocontrol products for mitigation of aflatoxin contamination in maize and groundnut in Ghana. Biol Control. 2020;150:104351. 10.1016/j.biocontrol.2020.104351</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2020.104351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7457722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33144821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amaike S, Keller NP. Aspergillus flavus. Annu Rev Phytopathol. 2011;49:107–33. 10.1146/annurev-phyto-072910-095221</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-phyto-072910-095221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21513456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atehnkeng J, Ojiambo PS, Cotty PJ, Bandyopadhyay R. Field efficacy of a mixture of atoxigenic Aspergillus flavus Link: FR vegetative compatibility groups in preventing aflatoxin contamination in maize (Zea mays L.). Biol Control. 2014;72:62–70.10.1016/j.biocontrol.2014.02.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2014.02.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atehnkeng J, Donner M, Ojiambo PS, Ikotun B, Augusto J, Cotty PJ, et al. Environmental distribution and genetic diversity of vegetative compatibility groups determine biocontrol strategies to mitigate aflatoxin contamination of maize by Aspergillus flavus. Microb Biotechnol. 2016;9:75–88. 10.1111/1751-7915.12324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.12324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4720411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26503309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayalew A, Kimanya M, Matumba L, Bandyopadhyay R, Menkir A, Cotty PJ. Controlling aflatoxins in maize in Africa: strategies, challenges and opportunities for improvement. In: Watson D, editor. Achieving sustainable cultivation of maize: Cultivation techniques, pest and disease control, vol. 2. Cambridge: Burleigh Dodds Science Publishing Limited; 2017. p. 371–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay R, Ortega-Beltran A, Akande A, Mutegi C, Atehnkeng J, Kaptoge L, et al. Biological control of aflatoxins in Africa: current status and potential challenges in the face of climate change. World Mycotoxin J. 2016;9:771–89.10.3920/WMJ2016.2130</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/WMJ2016.2130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay R, Atehnkeng J, Ortega-Beltran A, Akande A, Falade T, Cotty PJ. “Ground-truthing” efficacy of biological control for aflatoxin mitigation in farmers’ fields in Nigeria: from field trials to commercial usage, a 10-year study. Front Microbiol. 2019;10:2528. 10.3389/fmicb.2019.02528</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6882503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31824438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay R, Ortega-Beltran A, Konlambigue M, Kaptoge L, Falade T, Cotty PJ. Development and scale-up of bioprotectants to keep staple foods safe from aflatoxin contamination in Africa. In: Köhl J, Ravensberg W, editors. Microbial Bioprotectants for Plant Disease Management. Cambridge: Burleigh Dodds Science Publishing; 2022. p. 1–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bateman R. Constraints and enabling technologies for mycopesticide development. Outlooks Pest Manag. 2004;15:64.10.1564/15apl07</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1564/15apl07</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell BC, Molyneux RJ, Schatzki TF. Current research on reducing pre- and post-harvest aflatoxin contamination of U.S. almond, pistachio, and walnut. J Toxicol Toxin Rev. 2003;22:225–66.10.1081/TXR-120024093</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1081/TXR-120024093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang PK, Horn BW, Dorner JW. Sequence breakpoints in the aflatoxin biosynthesis gene cluster and flanking regions in nonaflatoxigenic Aspergillus flavus isolates. Fungal Genet Biol. 2005;42:914–23. 10.1016/j.fgb.2005.07.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2005.07.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16154781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J. Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences. 2nd ed. New Jersey: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc.; 1988.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cotty PJ, Bayman P, Egel DS, Elias KS. Agriculture, aflatoxins and Aspergillus. In: Powell K, editor. The Genus Aspergillus. New York: Plenum Press; 1994. p. 1–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cotty PJ, Antilla L, Wakelyn PJ. Competitive exclusion of aflatoxin producers: farmer-driven research and development. In: Vincent C, Goettel MS, Lazarovits G, editors. Biological control: a global perspective. Oxfordshire: CABI; 2007. p. 241–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cotty PJ, Probst C, Jaime-Garcia R. Etiology and management of aflatoxin contamination. In: Leslie JF, Bandyopadhyay R, Visconti A, editors. Mycotoxins: detection methods, management, public health and agricultural trade. Oxfordshire: CAB International; 2008. p. 287–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai Y, Huang K, Zhang B, Zhu L, Xu W. Aflatoxin B1-induced epigenetic alterations: an overview. Food Chem Toxicol. 2017;109:683–9. 10.1016/j.fct.2017.06.034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2017.06.034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28645871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de la Cruz-Quiroz R, Cruz Maldonado JJ, de Rostro Alanis MJ, Torres JA, Parra Saldívar R. Fungi-based biopesticides: shelf-life preservation technologies used in commercial products. J Pest Sci. 2019;92:1003–15.10.1007/s10340-019-01117-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10340-019-01117-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demšar J. Statistical comparisons of classifiers over multiple data sets. J Mach Learn Res. 2006;7:1–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorner JW. Biological control of aflatoxin contamination of crops. J Toxicol Toxin Rev. 2004;23:425–50.10.1081/TXR-200027877</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1081/TXR-200027877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorner JW. Development of biocontrol technology to manage aflatoxin contamination in peanuts. Peanut Sci. 2009;36:60–7.10.3146/AT07-002.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3146/AT07-002.1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doster MA, Cotty PJ, Michailides TJ. Evaluation of the atoxigenic Aspergillus flavus strain AF36 in pistachio orchards. Plant Dis. 2014;98:948–56. 10.1094/PDIS-10-13-1053-RE</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PDIS-10-13-1053-RE</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30708840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eskola M, Kos G, Elliott CT, Hajšlová J, Mayar S, Krska R. Worldwide contamination of food-crops with mycotoxins: validity of the widely cited ‘FAO estimate’ of 25%. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2020;60:2773–89. 10.1080/10408398.2019.1658570</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2019.1658570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31478403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezekiel CN, Warth B, Ogara IM, Abia WA, Ezekiel VC, Atehnkeng J, et al. Mycotoxin exposure in rural residents in northern Nigeria: a pilot study using multi-urinary biomarkers. Environ Int. 2014;66:138–45. 10.1016/j.envint.2014.02.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2014.02.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24583186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezekiel CN, Ortega-Beltran A, Oyedeji EO, Atehnkeng J, Kössler P, Tairu F, et al. Aflatoxin in chili peppers in Nigeria: extent of contamination and control using atoxigenic Aspergillus flavus genotypes as biocontrol agents. Toxins. 2019;11:429. 10.3390/toxins11070429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins11070429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6669588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31336571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). Food safety and quality. 2020; accessed 14 July 2024. https://www.fao.org/food-safety/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hell K, Fandohan P, Bandyopadhyay R, Kiewnick S, Sikora R, Cotty PJ. Pre- and post-harvest management of aflatoxin in maize: an African perspective. In: Leslie JF, Bandyopadhyay R, Visconti A, editors. Mycotoxins: detection methods, management, public health and agricultural trade. Oxfordshire: CAB International; 2008. p. 219–219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismail A, Naeem I, Gong YY, Routledge MN, Akhtar S, Riaz M, et al. Early life exposure to dietary aflatoxins, health impact and control perspectives: a review. Trends Food Sci Technol. 2021;112:212–24.10.1016/j.tifs.2021.04.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.04.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaronski ST, Mascarin GM. Mass production of entomopathogenic fungi: state of the art. In: Morales-Ramos JA, Rojas MG, Shapiro-Ilan DI, editors. Mass production of beneficial organisms: invertebrates and entomopathogens. Academic Press; 2013. p. 357–413.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>JECFA. Safety evaluation of certain contaminants in food: prepared by the eighty-third meeting of the Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives (JECFA), WHO Food A. World Health Organization and Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Geneva; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamala A, Shirima C, Jani B, Bakari M, Sillo H, Rusibamayila N, et al. Outbreak of an acute aflatoxicosis in Tanzania during 2016. World Mycotoxin J. 2018;11:311–20.10.3920/WMJ2018.2344</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/WMJ2018.2344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klich MA. Aspergillus flavus: the major producer of aflatoxin. Mol Plant Pathol. 2007;8:713–22. 10.1111/j.1364-3703.2007.00436.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2007.00436.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20507532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logrieco AF, Miller JD, Eskola M, Krska R, Ayalew A, Bandyopadhyay R, et al. The mycotox charter: increasing awareness of, and concerted action for, minimizing mycotoxin exposure worldwide. Toxins. 2018;10:149. 10.3390/toxins10040149</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins10040149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5923315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29617309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahuku G, Mauro A, Pallangyo B, Nsami E, Boni SB, Koyano E, et al. Atoxigenic-based technology for biocontrol of aflatoxin in maize and groundnuts for Tanzania. World Mycotoxin J. 2023;16:59–73.10.3920/WMJ2021.2758</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/WMJ2021.2758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matumba L, Namaumbo S, Ngoma T, Meleke N, De Boevre M, Logrieco AF, et al. Five keys to prevention and control of mycotoxins in grains: a proposal. Glob Food Sec. 2021;30:100562.10.1016/j.gfs.2021.100562</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gfs.2021.100562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mauro A, Garcia-Cela E, Pietri A, Cotty PJ, Battilani P. Biological control products for aflatoxin prevention in Italy: commercial field evaluation of atoxigenic Aspergillus flavus active ingredients. Toxins. 2018;10:30. 10.3390/toxins10010030</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins10010030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5793117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29304008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehl HL, Jaime R, Callicott KA, Probst C, Garber NP, Ortega-Beltran A, et al. Aspergillus flavus diversity on crops and in the environment can be exploited to reduce aflatoxin exposure and improve health. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2012;1273:7–17. 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06800.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06800.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23230832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moral J, Garcia-Lopez MT, Camiletti BX, Jaime R, Michailides TJ, Bandyopadhyay R, et al. Present status and perspective on the future use of aflatoxin biocontrol products. Agronomy. 2020;10:491.10.3390/agronomy10040491</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agronomy10040491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojiambo PS, Battilani P, Cary JW, Blum BH, Carbone I. Cultural and genetic approaches to manage aflatoxin contamination: recent insights provide opportunities for improved control. Phytopathology. 2018;108:1024–37. 10.1094/PHYTO-04-18-0134-RVW</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-04-18-0134-RVW</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29869954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ola OT, Ogedengbe OO, Raji TM, Eze B, Chama M, Ilori ON, et al. Aflatoxin biocontrol effectiveness in the real world—private sector-led efforts to manage aflatoxins in Nigeria through biocontrol-centered strategies. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:977789. 10.3389/fmicb.2022.977789</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.977789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9478371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36118233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega-Beltran A, Moral J, Picot A, Puckett RD, Cotty PJ, Michailides TJ. Atoxigenic Aspergillus flavus isolates endemic to almond, fig, and pistachio orchards in California with potential to reduce aflatoxin contamination in these crops. Plant Dis. 2019;103:905–12. 10.1094/PDIS-08-18-1333-RE</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PDIS-08-18-1333-RE</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30807246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega-Beltran A, Kaptoge L, Senghor AL, Aikore MOS, Jarju P, Momanyi H, et al. Can it be all more simple? Manufacturing aflatoxin biocontrol products using dry spores of atoxigenic isolates of Aspergillus flavus as active ingredients. Microb Biotechnol. 2022;15:901–14. 10.1111/1751-7915.13802</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8913866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33755307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Probst C, Njapau H, Cotty PJ. Outbreak of an acute aflatoxicosis in Kenya in 2004: identification of the causal agent. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2007;73:2762–4. 10.1128/AEM.02370-06</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02370-06</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1855601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17308181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha-Turna N, Wu F. Effects of aflatoxin on the immune system: evidence from human and mammalian animal research. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2023. 10.1080/10408398.2023.2219336. 10.1080/10408398.2023.2219336</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2023.2219336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37283041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarrocco S, Mauro A, Battilani P. Use of competitive filamentous fungi as an alternative approach for mycotoxin risk reduction in staple cereals: state of art and future perspectives. Toxins. 2019;11:701. 10.3390/toxins11120701</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins11120701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6950288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31810316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seetha A, Munthali W, Msere HW, Swai E, Muzanila Y, Sichone E, et al. Occurrence of aflatoxins and its management in diverse cropping systems of central Tanzania. Mycotoxin Res. 2017;33:323–31. 10.1007/s12550-017-0286-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12550-017-0286-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5644708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28785910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senghor LA, Ortega-Beltran A, Atehnkeng J, Callicott KA, Cotty PJ, Bandyopadhyay R. The atoxigenic biocontrol product Aflasafe SN01 is a valuable tool to mitigate aflatoxin contamination of both maize and groundnut cultivated in Senegal. Plant Dis. 2020;104:510–20. 10.1094/PDIS-03-19-0575-RE</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PDIS-03-19-0575-RE</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31790640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senghor AL, Ortega-Beltran A, Atehnkeng J, Jarju P, Cotty PJ, Bandyopadhyay R. Aflasafe SN01 is the first biocontrol product approved for aflatoxin mitigation in two nations Senegal and the Gambia. Plant Dis. 2021;105:1461–73. 10.1094/PDIS-09-20-1899-RE</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1094/PDIS-09-20-1899-RE</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33332161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udomkun P, Wiredu AN, Nagle M, Bandyopadhyay R, Müller J, Vanlauwe B. Mycotoxins in sub-Saharan Africa: present situation, socio-economic impact, awareness, and outlook. Food Control. 2017;72:110–22.10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.07.039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.07.039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA. Amendments, Extensions, and/or Issuances of Experimental Use Permits - A Notice by the Environmental Protection Agency on 10/05/2016. https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2016/10/05/2016-24101/amendments-extensions-andor-issuances-of-experimental-use-permits; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waliyar F, Kumar PL, Traoré A, Ntare BR, Diarra B, Kodio O. Pre- and postharvest management of aflatoxin contamination in peanuts. In: Leslie JF, Bandyopadhyay R, Visconti A, editors. Mycotoxins: detection methods, management, public health and agricultural trade. Oxfordshire: CAB International; 2008. p. 209–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weaver M, Abbas HK. Field displacement of aflatoxigenic Aspergillus flavus strains through repeated biological control applications. Front Microbiol. 2019;10:1788. 10.3389/fmicb.2019.01788</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6692475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31447810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weaver MA, Abbas HK, Falconer LL, Allen TW, Pringle HL III, Sciumbato GL. Biological control of aflatoxin is effective and economical in Mississippi field trials. Crop Prot. 2015;69:52–5.10.1016/j.cropro.2014.12.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cropro.2014.12.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F. Global impacts of aflatoxin in maize: trade and human health. World Mycotoxin J. 2015;8:137–42.10.3920/WMJ2014.1737</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/WMJ2014.1737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>