<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39269488</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-1912</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Naunyn-Schmiedeberg's archives of pharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch Pharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the benefits of astaxanthin as a functional food ingredient: Its effects on oxidative stress and reproductive outcomes in women with PCOS - A systematic review and single-arm meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00210-024-03432-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS) is a prevalent gynecological-endocrinological disorder characterized by hyperandrogenism, menstrual irregularities, and metabolic disturbances. Recent research has highlighted the role of oxidative stress and chronic inflammation in exacerbating PCOS symptoms and impeding reproductive outcomes. Astaxanthin, a potent antioxidant found in marine organisms, has been suggested as a potential therapeutic intervention due to its ability to reduce oxidative stress and inflammation. This meta-analysis systematically reviews randomized controlled trials assessing the impact of astaxanthin supplementation on oxidative stress and reproductive outcomes in women with PCOS. Data from four trials were analyzed, focusing on markers of oxidative stress and reproductive health metrics. The meta-analysis utilized fixed and random-effects models to synthesize results, with heterogeneity assessed using Chi-square and I<sup>2</sup> statistics. The findings indicate that while astaxanthin significantly improves markers of total antioxidant capacity (TAC) in follicular fluid, it does not show a consistent effect on other oxidative stress biomarkers such as malondialdehyde (MDA), catalase (CAT), or superoxide dismutase (SOD). Reproductive outcomes, including oocyte quality and the number of high-quality embryos, showed moderate improvements, although effects on fertilization rates and pregnancy outcomes were insignificant. The analysis highlights variability in study designs and dosing, suggesting a need for further research with standardized protocols and larger sample sizes. Future studies should focus on determining optimal dosing, exploring mechanistic pathways, and investigating the combined effects of astaxanthin with other interventions. Longitudinal studies are needed to assess long-term benefits and safety, and personalized approaches could enhance treatment efficacy for individuals with PCOS.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Rodrigues</LastName><ForeName>Victória Dogani</ForeName><Initials>VD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Faculdade de Medicina de Marília (FAMEMA), Marília, São Paulo, 17519-030, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Boaro</LastName><ForeName>Beatriz Leme</ForeName><Initials>BL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Faculdade de Medicina de Marília (FAMEMA), Marília, São Paulo, 17519-030, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laurindo</LastName><ForeName>Lívia Fornari</ForeName><Initials>LF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Faculdade de Medicina de São José Do Rio Preto (FAMERP), São José Do Rio Preto, São Paulo, 15090-000, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chagas</LastName><ForeName>Eduardo Federighi Baisi</ForeName><Initials>EFB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Postgraduate Program in Structural and Functional Interactions in Rehabilitation, School of Medicine, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Lima</LastName><ForeName>Enzo Pereira</ForeName><Initials>EP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laurindo</LastName><ForeName>Lucas Fornari</ForeName><Initials>LF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Faculdade de Medicina de Marília (FAMEMA), Marília, São Paulo, 17519-030, Brazil. lucasffffor@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil. lucasffffor@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Administration, Associate Degree in Hospital Management, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil. lucasffffor@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barbalho</LastName><ForeName>Sandra Maria</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Postgraduate Program in Structural and Functional Interactions in Rehabilitation, School of Medicine, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition, School of Food and Technology of Marília (FATEC), Marília, São Paulo, 17500-000, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UNIMAR Charity Hospital, Universidade de Marília (UNIMAR), Marília, São Paulo, 17525-902, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch Pharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0326264</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0028-1298</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Assisted reproductive technology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Astaxanthin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Carotenoid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meta-analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Oxidative stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Polycystic ovary syndrome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Systematic review</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Women's health</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39269488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00210-024-03432-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00210-024-03432-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abdelazim K, Ghit A, Assal D, Dorra N, Noby N, Khattab SN, El Feky SE, Hussein A (2023) Production and therapeutic use of astaxanthin in the nanotechnology era. Pharmacol Rep 75:771–790</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37179259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10182848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43440-023-00488-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AbdolWahab NR, MeorMohdAffandi MMR, Fakurazi S, Alias E, Hassan H (2022) Nanocarrier system: State-of-the-art in oral delivery of astaxanthin. Antioxidants (Basel) 11:1676</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox11091676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambati RR, Phang SM, Ravi S, Aswathanarayana RG (2014) Astaxanthin: sources, extraction, stability, biological activities and its commercial applications–a review. Mar Drugs 12:128–152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24402174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3917265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md12010128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahbah EI, Ghozy S, Attia MS, Negida A, Emran TB, Mitra S, Albadrani GM, Abdel-Daim MM, Uddin MS, Simal-Gandara J (2021) Molecular mechanisms of astaxanthin as a potential neurotherapeutic agent. Mar Drugs 19:201</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33916730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8065559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md19040201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai F, Gusbeth C, Frey W, Nick P (2020) Nanosecond pulsed electric fields modulate the expression of the astaxanthin biosynthesis genes psy, crtR-b and bkt 1 in Haematococcus pluvialis. Sci Rep 10:15508</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32968095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7511312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-72479-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basiony M, Ouyang L, Wang D, Yu J, Zhou L, Zhu M, Wang X, Feng J, Dai J, Shen Y, Zhang C, Hua Q, Yang X, Zhang L (2022) Optimization of microbial cell factories for astaxanthin production: Biosynthesis and regulations, engineering strategies and fermentation optimization strategies. Synth Syst Biotechnol 7:689–704</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35261927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8866108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.synbio.2022.01.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brotosudarmo THP, Limantara L, Setiyono E, Heriyanto (2020) Structures of astaxanthin and their consequences for therapeutic application. Int J Food Sci 2020:2156582</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32775406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7391096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2020/2156582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao Y, Yang L, Qiao X, Xue C, Xu J (2023) Dietary astaxanthin: an excellent carotenoid with multiple health benefits. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 63:3019–3045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34581210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.1983766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dang Y, Li Z, Yu F (2024) Recent advances in astaxanthin as an antioxidant in food applications. Antioxidants (Basel) 13:879</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39061947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox13070879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Lorenzo M, Cacciapuoti N, Lonardo MS, Nasti G, Gautiero C, Belfiore A, Guida B, Chiurazzi M (2023) Pathophysiology and nutritional approaches in Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS): A comprehensive review. Curr Nutr Rep 12:527–544</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37213054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10444658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13668-023-00479-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding YW, Lu CZ, Zheng Y, Ma HZ, Jin J, Jia B, Yuan YJ (2023) Directed evolution of the fusion enzyme for improving astaxanthin biosynthesis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Synth Syst Biotechnol 8:46–53</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36408203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.synbio.2022.10.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donoso A, González-Durán J, Muñoz AA, González PA, Agurto-Muñoz C (2021) Therapeutic uses of natural astaxanthin: An evidence-based review focused on human clinical trials. Pharmacol Res 166:105479</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33549728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2021.105479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fakhri S, Aneva IY, Farzaei MH, Sobarzo-Sánchez E (2019) The neuroprotective effects of astaxanthin: Therapeutic targets and clinical perspective. Molecules 24:2640</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31330843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6680436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules24142640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fereidouni F, Kashani L, Amidi F, Khodarahmian M, Zhaeentan S, Ardehjani NA, Rastegar T (2024) Astaxanthin treatment decreases pro-inflammatory cytokines and improves reproductive outcomes in patients with polycystic ovary syndrome undergoing assisted reproductive technology: A randomized clinical trial. Inflammopharmacology 32:2337–2347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38916710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10787-024-01504-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharaei R, Alyasin A, Mahdavinezhad F, Samadian E, Ashrafnezhad Z, Amidi F (2022) Randomized controlled trial of astaxanthin impacts on antioxidant status and assisted reproductive technology outcomes in women with polycystic ovarian syndrome. J Assist Reprod Genet 39:995–1008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35237893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9050983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10815-022-02432-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosh A, Banik S, Yamada K, Misaka S, Prud’homme RK, Sato H, Onoue S (2023) Stabilized astaxanthin nanoparticles developed using flash nanoprecipitation to improve oral bioavailability and hepatoprotective effects. Pharmaceutics 15:2562</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38004541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10675309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics15112562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Göttl VL, Meyer F, Schmitt I, Persicke M, Peters-Wendisch P, Wendisch VF, Henke NA (2024) Enhancing astaxanthin biosynthesis and pathway expansion towards glycosylated C40 carotenoids by Corynebacterium glutamicum. Sci Rep 14:8081</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38582923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10998873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-58700-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta AK, Seth K, Maheshwari K, Baroliya PK, Meena M, Kumar A, Vinayak V, Harish (2021) Biosynthesis and extraction of high-value carotenoid from algae. FBL 26:171–190</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34162044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins JP (2008) Cochrane handbook for systematic reviews of interventions version 5.0. 1. The Cochrane Collaboration. http://www.cochrane-handbook.org . Accessed date 13 Aug 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Zhong Y, Sandmann G, Liu J, Chen F (2012) Cloning and selection of carotenoid ketolase genes for the engineering of high-yield astaxanthin in plants. Planta 236:691–699</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22526507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00425-012-1654-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang D, Liu W, Li A, Wang C, Hu Z (2019) Discovery of Geranylgeranyl Pyrophosphate Synthase (GGPPS) paralogs from haematococcus pluvialis based on iso-seq analysis and their function on astaxanthin biosynthesis. Mar Drugs 17:696</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31842293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6950171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md17120696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabarpour M, Aleyasin A, Nashtaei MS, Lotfi S, Amidi F (2023) Astaxanthin treatment ameliorates ER stress in polycystic ovary syndrome patients: a randomized clinical trial. Sci Rep 13:3376</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36854788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9974957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-28956-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabarpour M, Aleyasin A, Shabani Nashtaei M, Amidi F (2024a) Astaxanthin supplementation impact on insulin resistance, lipid profile, blood pressure, and oxidative stress in polycystic ovary syndrome patients: A triple-blind randomized clinical trial. Phytother Res 38:321–330</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37874168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.8037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabarpour M, Amidi F, Aleyasin A, Nashtaei MS, Marghmaleki MS (2024b) Randomized clinical trial of astaxanthin supplement on serum inflammatory markers and ER stress-apoptosis gene expression in PBMCs of women with PCOS. J Cell Mol Med 28:e18464</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39036884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">11261353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcmm.18464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Y-J, Lin J-Y, Wang D-S, Chen C-H, Chiou M-H (2017) Safety assessment of astaxanthin derived from engineered Escherichia coli K-12 using a 13-week repeated dose oral toxicity study and a prenatal developmental toxicity study in rats. Regul Toxicol Pharmacol 87:95–105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28483713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yrtph.2017.05.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T, Zhang L, Joo D, Sun SC (2017) NF-κB signaling in inflammation. Signal Transduct Target Ther 2:17023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29158945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5661633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sigtrans.2017.23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maleki-Hajiagha A, Shafie A, Maajani K, Amidi F (2024) Effect of astaxanthin supplementation on female fertility and reproductive outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis of clinical and animal studies. J Ovarian Res 17:163</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39127677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">11316280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13048-024-01472-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez-Álvarez Ó, Calvo MM, Gómez-Estaca J (2020) Recent advances in astaxanthin micro/nanoencapsulation to improve its stability and functionality as a food ingredient. Mar Drugs 18:406</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32752203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7459837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md18080406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medoro A, Davinelli S, Milella L, Willcox BJ, Allsopp RC, Scapagnini G, Willcox DC (2023) Dietary astaxanthin: a promising antioxidant and anti-inflammatory agent for brain aging and adult neurogenesis. Mar Drugs 21:643</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38132964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10744637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md21120643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair A, Ahirwar A, Singh S, Lodhi R, Lodhi A, Rai A, Jadhav DA, Harish A, Varjani S, Singh G, Marchand J, Schoefs B, Vinayak V (2023) Astaxanthin as a king of ketocarotenoids: structure, synthesis, accumulation bioavailability and antioxidant properties. Mar Drugs 21:176</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36976225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10056084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md21030176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishida Y, Berg PC, Shakersain B, Hecht K, Takikawa A, Tao R, Kakuta Y, Uragami C, Hashimoto H, Misawa N, Maoka T (2023) Astaxanthin: Past, Present, and Future. Mar Drugs 21:514</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37888449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10608541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md21100514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu T, Zhou J, Wang F, Xuan R, Chen J, Wu W, Chen H (2020) Safety assessment of astaxanthin from Haematococcus pluvialis: Acute toxicity, genotoxicity, distribution and repeat-dose toxicity studies in gestation mice. Regul Toxicol Pharmacol 115:104695</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32512118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.yrtph.2020.104695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norman RJ, Dewailly D, Legro RS, Hickey TE (2007) Polycystic ovary syndrome. Lancet 370:685–697</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17720020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)61345-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orisaka M, Mizutani T, Miyazaki Y, Shirafuji A, Tamamura C, Fujita M, Tsuyoshi H, Yoshida Y (2023) Chronic low-grade inflammation and ovarian dysfunction in women with polycystic ovarian syndrome, endometriosis, and aging. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 14:1324429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38192421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1324429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, Shamseer L, Tetzlaff JM, Akl EA, Brennan SE, Chou R, Glanville J, Grimshaw JM, Hróbjartsson A, Lalu MM, Li T, Loder EW, Mayo-Wilson E, McDonald S, McGuinness LA, Stewart LA, Thomas J, Tricco AC, Welch VA, Whiting P, Moher D (2021) The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ 372:n71–n71</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8005924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palomba S (2021) Is fertility reduced in ovulatory women with polycystic ovary syndrome? An opinion paper. Hum Reprod 36:2421–2428</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34333641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/humrep/deab181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palomba S, de Wilde MA, Falbo A, Koster MP, La Sala GB, Fauser BC (2015) Pregnancy complications in women with polycystic ovary syndrome. Hum Reprod Update 21:575–592</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26117684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/humupd/dmv029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palomba S, Daolio J, La Sala GB (2017) Oocyte Competence in Women with Polycystic Ovary Syndrome. Trends Endocrinol Metab 28:186–198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27988256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tem.2016.11.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palomba S, Piltonen TT, Giudice LC (2021) Endometrial function in women with polycystic ovary syndrome: a comprehensive review. Hum Reprod Update 27:584–618</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33302299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/humupd/dmaa051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao X, Yang L, Zhang T, Zhou Q, Wang Y, Xu J, Xue C (2018) Synthesis, stability and bioavailability of astaxanthin succinate diester. J Sci Food Agric 98:3182–3189</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29230828</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.8824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raza SHA, Naqvi SRZ, Abdelnour SA, Schreurs N, Mohammedsaleh ZM, Khan I, Shater AF, Abd El-Hack ME, Khafaga AF, Quan G, Khan R, Wang S, Cheng G, Zan L (2021) Beneficial effects and health benefits of Astaxanthin molecules on animal production: A review. Res Vet Sci 138:69–78</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34111716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2021.05.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizzardi N, Pezzolesi L, Samorì C, Senese F, Zalambani C, Pitacco W, Calonghi N, Bergamini C, Prata C, Fato R (2022) Natural astaxanthin is a green antioxidant able to counteract lipid peroxidation and ferroptotic cell death. Int J Mol Sci 23:15137</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36499464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9737268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms232315137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satoh T, Gupta RC (2021) Chapter 51 - Astaxanthin: health benefits and toxicity. In: Gupta RC, Lall R, Srivastava A (eds) Nutraceuticals (Second Edition). Academic Press, pp 881–889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snell TW, Carberry J (2022) Astaxanthin bioactivity is determined by stereoisomer composition and extraction method. Nutrients 14:1522</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35406135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9002770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14071522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachowiak B, Szulc P (2021) Astaxanthin for the food industry. Molecules 26:2666</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34063189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8125449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26092666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taniguchi K, Karin M (2018) NF-κB, inflammation, immunity and cancer: coming of age. Nat Rev Immunol 18:309–324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29379212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nri.2017.142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visioli F, Artaria C (2017) Astaxanthin in cardiovascular health and disease: mechanisms of action, therapeutic merits, and knowledge gaps. Food Funct 8:39–63</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27924978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C6FO01721E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang HQ, Sun XB, Xu YX, Zhao H, Zhu QY, Zhu CQ (2010) Astaxanthin upregulates heme oxygenase-1 expression through ERK1/2 pathway and its protective effect against beta-amyloid-induced cytotoxicity in SH-SY5Y cells. Brain Res 1360:159–167</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20828541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2010.08.100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wardyn JD, Ponsford AH, Sanderson CM (2015) Dissecting molecular cross-talk between Nrf2 and NF-κB response pathways. Biochem Soc Trans 43:621–626</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26551702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4613495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/BST20150014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Q, Zhang XS, Wang HD, Zhang X, Yu Q, Li W, Zhou ML, Wang XL (2014) Astaxanthin activates nuclear factor erythroid-related factor 2 and the antioxidant responsive element (Nrf2-ARE) pathway in the brain after subarachnoid hemorrhage in rats and attenuates early brain injury. Mar Drugs 12:6125–6141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25528957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4278222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md12126125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu H, Niu H, Shao A, Wu C, Dixon BJ, Zhang J, Yang S, Wang Y (2015) Astaxanthin as a potential neuroprotective agent for neurological diseases. Mar Drugs 13:5750–5766</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26378548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4584352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md13095750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang C, Hassan YI, Liu R, Zhang H, Chen Y, Zhang L, Tsao R (2019) Anti-inflammatory effects of different astaxanthin isomers and the roles of lipid transporters in the cellular transport of astaxanthin isomers in caco-2 cell monolayers. J Agric Food Chem 67:6222–6231</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31117505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.9b02102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Qiao X, Gu J, Li X, Cao Y, Xu J, Xue C (2021) Influence of molecular structure of astaxanthin esters on their stability and bioavailability. Food Chem 343:128497</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33160771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.128497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarneshan SN, Fakhri S, Farzaei MH, Khan H, Saso L (2020) Astaxanthin targets PI3K/Akt signaling pathway toward potential therapeutic applications. Food Chem Toxicol 145:111714</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32871194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2020.111714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Chen X, Too HP (2020) Microbial astaxanthin biosynthesis: recent achievements, challenges, and commercialization outlook. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 104:5725–5737</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32399589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-020-10648-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao X, Zhang X, Liu H, Zhu H, Zhu Y (2019) Enzyme-assisted extraction of astaxanthin from Haematococcus pluvialis and its stability and antioxidant activity. Food Sci Biotechnol 28:1637–1647</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31807336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6859130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10068-019-00608-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Q, Zeng D, Yu S, Cui C, Li J, Li H, Chen J, Zhang R, Zhao X, Chen L, Liu YG (2018) From golden rice to aSTARice: Bioengineering astaxanthin biosynthesis in rice endosperm. Mol Plant 11:1440–1448</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30296601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2018.09.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>