<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39269525</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1614-7499</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>31</Volume><Issue>45</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science and pollution research international</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Critical review on toxic contaminants in surface water ecosystem: sources, monitoring, and its impact on human health.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>56428</StartPage><EndPage>56462</EndPage><MedlinePgn>56428-56462</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11356-024-34932-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Surface water pollution is a critical and urgent global issue that demands immediate attention. Surface water plays a crucial role in supporting and sustaining life on the earth, but unfortunately, till now, we have less understanding of its spatial and temporal dynamics of discharge and storage variations at a global level. The contamination of surface water arises from various sources, classified into point and non-point sources. Point sources are specific, identifiable origins of pollution that release pollutants directly into water bodies through pipes or channels, allowing for easier identification and management, e.g., industrial discharges, sewage treatment plants, and landfills. However, non-point sources originate from widespread activities across expansive areas and present challenges due to its diffuse nature and multiple pathways of contamination, e.g., agricultural runoff, urban storm water runoff, and atmospheric deposition. Excessive accumulation of heavy metals, persistent organic pollutants, pesticides, chlorination by-products, pharmaceutical products in surface water through different pathways threatens food quality and safety. As a result, there is an urgent need for developing and designing new tools for identifying and quantifying various environmental contaminants. In this context, chemical and biological sensors emerge as fascinating devices well-suited for various environmental applications. Numerous chemical and biological sensors, encompassing electrochemical, magnetic, microfluidic, and biosensors, have recently been invented by hydrological scientists for the detection of water pollutants. Furthermore, surface water contaminants are monitored through different sensors, proving their harmful effects on human health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Prince Kumar</ForeName><Initials>PK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Ecotoxicology, Department of Botany, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, 221005, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Umesh</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Ecotoxicology, Department of Botany, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, 221005, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Indrajeet</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Ecotoxicology, Department of Botany, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, 221005, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dwivedi</LastName><ForeName>Akanksha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Ecotoxicology, Department of Botany, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, 221005, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Priyanka</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Ecotoxicology, Department of Botany, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, 221005, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mishra</LastName><ForeName>Saumya</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Ecotoxicology, Department of Botany, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, 221005, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seth</LastName><ForeName>Chandra Shekhar</ForeName><Initials>CS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Botany, University of Delhi, New Delhi, 110007, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Rajesh Kumar</ForeName><Initials>RK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Ecotoxicology, Department of Botany, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, 221005, India. rajeshbot78@bhu.ac.in.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9441769</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0944-1344</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014874">Water Pollutants, Chemical</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="Y">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014874" MajorTopicYN="Y">Water Pollutants, Chemical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017753" MajorTopicYN="Y">Ecosystem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014876" MajorTopicYN="N">Water Pollution</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Climate change</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pollutants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Surface water</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39269525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-34932-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11356-024-34932-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abdeldayem R (2022) Domestic water and accumulating Hg toxicity in the kidney. Appl Water Sci 12(6):114</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13201-021-01551-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Satar AM, Ali MH, Goher ME (2017) Indices of water quality and metal pollution of Nile River, Egypt. Egyp J Aqua Res 43(1):21–29</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejar.2016.12.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acuna V, Bregoli F, Font C, Barceló D, Corominas LL, Ginebreda A, Petrovic M, Rodríguez-Roda I, Sabater S, Marcé R (2020) Management actions to mitigate the occurrence of pharmaceuticals in river networks in a global change context. Environ Int 143:105993</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adekanmi AT (2021) Health hazards of toxic and essential heavy metals from the poultry waste on human and aquatic organisms. Animal Feed Science and Nutrition-Production, Health and Environment</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adeola AO, Forbes PB (2022) Antiretroviral drugs in African surface waters: prevalence, analysis, and potential remediation. Environ Toxicol Chem 41(2):247–262</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/etc.5127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aghaie A, Khanmohammadi A, Hajian A, Schmid U, Bagheri H (2019) Nonenzymatic electrochemical determination of paraoxon ethyl in water and fruits by graphene-based NiFe bimetallic phosphosulfide nanocomposite as a superior sensing layer. Food Anal Methods 12:1545–1555</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-019-01486-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed MK, Shaheen N, Islam MS, Habibullah-al-Mamun M, Islam S, Mohiduzzaman M, Bhattacharjee L (2015) Dietary intake of trace elements from highly consumed cultured fish (Labeo rohita, Pangasius pangasius and Oreochromis mossambicus) and human health risk implications in Bangladesh. Chemosphere 128:284–292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2015.02.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhtar N, Syakir Ishak MI, Bhawani SA, Umar K (2021) Various natural and anthropogenic factors responsible for water quality degradation: a review. Water 13(19):2660</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w13192660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Álvarez-Salgado XA, Nieto-Cid M, Rossel PE (2022) Dissolved organic matter. Marine Analytical Chemistry. Springer International Publishing, Cham, pp 39–102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antoine JM, Fung LAH, Grant CN, Dennis HT, Lalor GC (2012) Dietary intake of minerals and trace elements in rice on the Jamaican market. J Food Comp Anal 26(1–2):111–121</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2012.01.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Argos M, Kalra T, Rathouz PJ, Chen Y, Pierce B, Parvez F, Islam T, Ahmed A, Rakibuz-Zaman M, Hasan R, Ahsan H (2010) As exposure from drinking water, and all-cause and chronic-disease mortalities in Bangladesh (HEALS): a prospective cohort study. Lancet 376(9737):252–258</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60481-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashraf S, AghaKouchak A, Nazemi A, Mirchi A, Sadegh M, Moftakhari HR, Hassanzadeh E, Miao CY, Madani K, Mousavi Baygi M, Mallakpour I (2019) Compounding effects of human activities and climatic changes on surface water availability in Iran. Clim Change 152:379–391</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10584-018-2336-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atar N, Eren T, Yola ML, Wang S (2015) A sensitive molecular imprinted surface plasmon resonance nanosensor for selective determination of trace triclosan in wastewater. Sens Act B Chem 216:638–644</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2015.04.076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aylaz G, Kuhn J, Lau EC, Yeung CC, Roy VA, Duman M, Yiu HH (2021) Recent developments on magnetic molecular imprinted polymers (MMIPs) for sensing, capturing, and monitoring pharmaceutical and agricultural pollutants. J Chem Technol Biotechnol 96(5):1151–1160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jctb.6681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagheri H, Afkhami A, Khoshsafar H, Rezaei M, Sabounchei SJ, Sarlakifar M (2015) Simultaneous electrochemical sensing of thallium, lead and Hg using a novel ionic liquid/graphene modified electrode. Anal Chim Acta 870:56–66</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2015.03.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagheri H, Hajian A, Rezaei M, Shirzadmehr A (2017) Composite of Cu metal nanoparticles-multiwall carbon nanotubes-reduced graphene oxide as a novel and high performance platform of the electrochemical sensor for simultaneous determination of nitrite and nitrate. J Hazard Mater 324:762–772</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2016.11.055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakytkarim Y, Tursynbolat S, Zeng Q, Huang J, Wang L (2019) Nanomaterial ink for on-site painted sensor on studies of the electrochemical detection of organoP pesticide residuals of supermarket vegetables. J Electroanalytic Chem 841:45–50</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jelechem.2019.03.063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balana BB, Vinten A, Slee B (2011) A review on cost-effectiveness analysis of agri-environmental measures related to the EU WFD: key issues, methods, and applications. Ecologic Econ 70(6):1021–1031</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2010.12.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baqar M, Sadef Y, Ahmad SR, Mahmood A, Qadir A, Aslam I, Li J, Zhang G (2017) Occurrence, ecological risk assessment, and spatio-temporal variation of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) in water and sediments along River Ravi and its northern tributaries, Pakistan. Environ Sci Poll Res 24:27913–27930</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-017-0182-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barguilla I, Peremartí J, Bach J, Marcos R, Hernández A (2020) Role of As3mt and Mth1 in the genotoxic and carcinogenic effects induced by long-term exposures to As in MEF cells. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol 409:115303</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2020.115303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barral-Fraga L, Barral MT, MacNeill KL, Martiñá-Prieto D, Morin S, Rodríguez-Castro MC, Tuulaikhuu BA, Guasch H (2020) Biotic and abiotic factors influencing As biogeochemistry and toxicity in fluvial ecosystems: a review. Int J Environ Res Public Health 17(7):2331</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17072331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bates B, Kundzewicz Z, Wu S (2008) Climate change and water. Technical Paper of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, IPCC Secretariat, Geneva, p 210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baudart J, Grabulos J, Barusseau JP, Lebaron P (2000) Salmonella spp. and fecal coliform loads in coastal waters from a point vs. nonpoint source of pollution. Am Soc Agron Crop Sci Soc Am Soil Sci Soc Am 29(1):241–250</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bej AK, Steffan RJ, DiCesare J, Haff L, Atlas RM (1990) Detection of coliform bacteria in water by polymerase chain reaction and gene probes. Appl Environ Microbiol 56(2):307–314</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.56.2.307-314.1990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell J, Climent E, Hecht M, Buurman M, Rurack K (2016) Combining a droplet-based microfluidic tubing system with gated indicator releasing nanoparticles for Hg trace detection. ACS Sensors 1(4):334–338</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acssensors.5b00303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennetzen EH, Smith P, Porter JR (2016) Agricultural production and greenhouse gas emissions from world regions—the major trends over 40 years. Global Environ Change 37:43–55</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.12.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhanjana G, Dilbaghi N, Kumar R, Kumar S (2015) Zn oxide quantum dots as efficient electron mediator for ultrasensitive and selective electrochemical sensing of Hg. Electrochimica Acta 178:361–367</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2015.07.113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhateria R, Jain D (2016) Water quality assessment of lake water: a review. Sustain Wat Res Manag 2:161–173</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40899-015-0014-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhuiyan MAH, Suruvi NI, Dampare SB, Islam MA, Quraishi SB, Ganyaglo S, Suzuki S (2011) Investigation of the possible sources of heavy metal contamination in lagoon and canal water in the tannery industrial area in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Environ Monitor Assess 175:633–649</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-010-1557-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhuyan MS, Bakar MA, Rashed-Un-Nabi M, Senapathi V, Chung SY, Islam MS (2019) Monitoring and assessment of heavy metal contamination in surface water and sediment of the Old Brahmaputra River, Bangladesh. Appl Wat Sci 9(5):1–13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, (2020) Water, sanitation &amp; hygiene strategy overview. Available from https://www.epa.gov/national-aquatic-resource-surveys/national -lakes-assessment-2012-key-findings. Accessed on 9 June 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BIS (2012) Indian standard drinking water–specification (second revision). Bureau of Indian Standards (BIS), New Delhi, pp 1–11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas P, Karn AK, Balasubramanian P, Kale PG (2017) Biosensor for detection of dissolved Cr in potable water: a review. Biosens Bioelectr 94:589–604</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2017.03.043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biyani M, Biyani R, Tsuchihashi T, Takamura Y, Ushijima H, Tamiya E, Biyani M (2016) DEP-On-Go for simultaneous sensing of multiple heavy metals pollutants in environmental samples. Sensors 17(1):45</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s17010045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyd AS, Seger D, Vannucci S, Langley M, Abraham JL, King LE Jr (2000) Hg exposure and cutaneous disease. J Am Acad Dermatol 43(1):81–90</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1067/mjd.2000.106360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Branca JJV, Morucci G, Pacini A (2018) Cd-induced neurotoxicity: still much ado. Neural Regen Res 13(11):1879</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/1673-5374.239434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown AR, Owen SF, Peters J, Zhang Y, Soffker M, Paull GC, Hosken DJ, Wahab MA, Tyler CR (2015) Climate change and pollution speed declines in zebrafish populations. Proc Nat Acad Sci 112(11):E1237–E1246</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1416269112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bujes-Garrido J, Arcos-Martínez MJ (2017) Development of a wearable electrochemical sensor for voltammetric determination of chloride ions. Sens Actuators B Chem 240:224–228</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2016.08.119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byappanahalli MN, Nevers MB, Korajkic A, Staley ZR, Harwood VJ (2012) Enterococci in the environment. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 76(4):685–706</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00023-12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bytyçi P, Fetoshi O, Durmishi BH, Etemi FZ, Çadraku H, Ismaili M, Abazi AS (2018) Status assessment of heavy metals in water of the Lepenci River Basin, Kosova. J Ecol Eng 19(5):19–32</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao T, Meng J, Liang H, Yang X, Chen W (2017) Can biochar provide ammonium and nitrate to poor soils?: Soil column incubation. J Soil Sci Plant Nutr 17(2):253–265</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carmichael WW, Boyer GL (2016) Health impacts from cyanobacteria harmful algae blooms: Implications for the North American Great Lakes. Harmful Algae 54:194–212</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hal.2016.02.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cepal, N. (2017). The outlook for agriculture and rural development in the Americas: a perspective on Latin America and the Caribbean</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cetinkaya T, Ayseli MT, Yilmaz D (2024) Sustainable water management in food and agriculture industries: preventive practices, sensory aspects, emerging concerns, and nonthermal strategies. In: Water, the Environment and the Sustainable Development Goals. Elsevier. pp 127-156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty P, Khuman SN, Selvaraj S, Sampath S, Devi NL, Bang JJ, Katsoyiannis A (2016) Polychlorinated biphenyls and organochlorine pesticides in River Brahmaputra from the outer Himalayan Range and River Hooghly emptying into the Bay of Bengal: Occurrence, sources and ecotoxicological risk assessment. Environ Poll 219:998–1006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2016.06.067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty P, Mukhopadhyay M, Sampath S, Ramaswamy BR, Katsoyiannis A, Cincinelli A, Snow D (2019) Organic micropollutants in the surface riverine sediment along the lower stretch of the transboundary river Ganga: occurrences, sources and ecological risk assessment. Environ Poll 249:1071–1080</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2018.10.115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamani S, Mobasheri L, Rostami Z, Zare I, Naghizadeh A, Mostafavi E (2023) Heavy metals in contact dermatitis: a review. J Trace Elem Med Biol 79:127240</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtemb.2023.127240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang J, Zhang J, Tan B, Wang Q, Liu N, Xue Q (2020) New insight into the removal of Cd (II) from aqueous solution by diatomite. Environ Sci Poll Res 27:9882–9890</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-07620-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauhan S, Yadav A, Kurup PM, Li X, Swarnakar P, Gupta RK (2023) Devising a people-friendly test kit for overcoming challenges in the assessment of water quality and analysis of water pollution in the river Ganga. RSC Sustainability 1(3):418–43</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D2SU00071G</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Huang R, Guan Y, Zhuang T, Wang Y, Tan R, Wang J, Zhou R, Wang B, Xu J, Chen M (2021) The profiling of elements and pesticides in surface water in Nanjing, China with global comparisons. Sci Total Environ 774:145749</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.145749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiang TY, Lin CH (2014) A microfluidic chip for ammonium sensing incorporating ion-selective membranes formed by surface tension forces. Rsc Adv 4(1):379–385</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C3RA45809A</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chin LK, Liu AQ, Zhang JB, Lim CS, Soh YC (2008) An on-chip liquid tunable grating using multiphase droplet microfluidics. Appl Phys Lett 93(16):164107</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1063/1.3009560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhary P, Bharagava RN, Mishra S, Khan N (2020) Role of industries in water scarcity and its adverse effects on environment and human health. Environmental Concerns and Sustainable Development: Volume 1: Air, Water and Energy Resources, 235-256</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cinti S, Talarico D, Palleschi G, Moscone D, Arduini F (2016) Novel reagentless paper-based screen-printed electrochemical sensor to detect phosphate. Anal Chim Acta 919:78–84</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2016.03.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cleary J, Maher D, Slater C, Diamond D (2010) In situ monitoring of environmental water quality using an autonomous microfluidic sensor. In: 2010 IEEE Sensors Applications Symposium (SAS). IEEE. pp 36-40</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Custodio M, Cuadrado W, Peñaloza R, Montalvo R, Ochoa S, Quispe J (2020) Human risk from exposure to heavy metals and As in water from rivers with mining influence in the Central Andes of Peru. Water 12(7):1946</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w12071946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das S, Dash HR (2014) Microbial bioremediation: a potential tool for restoration of contaminated areas. In: Microbial biodegradation and bioremediation. Elsevier, pp 1-21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Datta AR, Kang Q, Chen B, Ye X (2018) Fate and transport modelling of emerging pollutants from watersheds to oceans: a review. Adv Mar Biol 81:97–128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/bs.amb.2018.09.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies H, Delistraty D (2016) Evaluation of PCB sources and releases for identifying priorities to reduce PCBs in Washington state (USA). Environ Sci Poll Res 23:2033–2041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-015-4828-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis LE, Standefer JC, Kornfeld M, Abercrombie DM, Butler C (1981) Acute thallium poisoning: toxicological and morphological studies of the nervous system. Annals Neurol Off J Am Neurol Assoc Child Neurol Soc 10(1):38–44</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De A, Bose R, Kumar A, Mozumdar S (2014) Targeted delivery of pesticides using biodegradable polymeric nanoparticles (Vol. 10, pp. 978-81). New Delhi: Springer India</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Souza RM, Seibert D, Quesada HB, de Jesus Bassetti F, Fagundes-Klen MR, Bergamasco R (2020) Occurrence, impacts and general aspects of pesticides in surface water: a review. Process Safe Environ Protect 135:22–37</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psep.2019.12.035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng H, Wei R, Luo W, Hu L, Li B, Shi H (2020) Microplastic pollution in water and sediment in a textile industrial area. Environ Poll 258:113658</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey S, Bano F, Malik A (2019) Pharmaceuticals and personal care product (PPCP) contamination—a global discharge inventory. In: Pharmaceuticals and personal care products: waste management and treatment technology. Butterworth-Heinemann. pp 1-26</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di M, Liu X, Wang W, Wang J (2019) Manuscript prepared for submission to environmental toxicology and pharmacology pollution in drinking water source areas: microplastics in the Danjiangkou Reservoir, China. Environ Toxicol Pharmacol 65:82–89</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.etap.2018.12.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dipp VR, Valles S, Ortiz-Kerbertt H, Suarez JV, Bardullas U (2018) Neurobehavioral alterations in zebrafish due to long-term exposure to low doses of inorganic As. Zebrafish 15(6):575–585</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/zeb.2018.1627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodds L, King WD (2001) Relation between trihalomethane compounds and birth defects. Occup Environ Med 58(7):443–446</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/oem.58.7.443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong J, Hou J, Jiang J, Ai S (2015) Innovative approach for the electrochemical detection of non-electroactive organoP pesticides using oxime as electroactive probe. Anal Chim Acta 885:92–97</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2015.05.033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong S, Feng H, Xia M, Li Y, Wang C, Wang L (2020) Spatial–temporal evolutions of groundwater environment in prairie opencast coal mine area: a case study of Yimin Coal Mine, China. Environ Geochem Health 42:3101–3118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00544-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong M, He L, Jiang M, Zhu Y, Wang J, Gustave W, Wang S, Deng Y, Zhang X, Wang Z (2023) Biochar for the removal of emerging pollutants from aquatic systems: a review. Int J Environ Res Public Health 20(3):1679</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20031679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dórea JG (2021) Exposure to environmental neurotoxic substances and neurodevelopment in children from Latin America and the Caribbean. Environ Res 192:110199</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drury B, Rosi-Marshall E, Kelly JJ (2013) Wastewater treatment effluent reduces the abundance and diversity of benthic bacterial communities in urban and suburban rivers. Appl Environ Microbiol 79(6):1897–1905</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.03527-12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutta M, Islam N, Rabha S, Narzary B, Bordoloi M, Saikia D, Silva LF, Saikia BK (2020) Acid mine drainage in an Indian high-sulfur coal mining area: cytotoxicity assay and remediation study. J Hazard Mater 389:121851</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.121851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efthimiou I, Vlastos D, Triantafyllidis V, Antonopoulou M (2022) Kastoria and Mikri Prespa Lakes: The impact of anthropogenic activities on the differentiation in the genotoxic and toxic profile of the surface water. Land 12(1):119</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/land12010119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ensafi AA, Rezaloo F, Rezaei B (2017) Electrochemical determination of fenitrothion organoP pesticide using polyZnon modified-glassy carbon electrode. Electroanalysis 29(12):2839–2846</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/elan.201700406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erogul S, Bas SZ, Ozmen M, Yildiz S (2015) A new electrochemical sensor based on Fe3O4 functionalized graphene oxide-gold nanoparticle composite film for simultaneous determination of catechol and hydroquinone. Electrochimica Acta 186:302–313</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2015.10.174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans CD, Monteith DT, Reynolds B, Clark JM (2008) Buffering of recovery from acidification by organic acids. Sci Total Environ 404(2–3):316–325</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2007.11.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO (2017) Pesticide residues in food. Joint FAO/WHO Meeting on Pesticide Residues, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fekadu S, Alemayehu E, Dewil R, Van der Bruggen B (2019) Pharmaceuticals in freshwater aquatic environments: a comparison of the African and European challenge. Sci Total Environ 654:324–337</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.11.072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng L, Zhang J, Fan J, Wei L, He S, Wu H (2022) Tracing dissolved organic matter in inflowing rivers of Nansi Lake as a storage reservoir: Implications for water-quality control. Chemosphere 286:131624</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.131624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feretti D, Acito M, Dettori M, Ceretti E, Fatigoni C, Posadino S, Zerbini I, Villarini M, Moretti M, Castiglia P, Azara A (2020) Genotoxicity of source, treated and distributed water from four drinking water treatment plants supplied by surface water in Sardinia, Italy. Environ Res 185:109385</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.109385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Font C, Bregoli F, Acuña V, Sabater S, Marcé R (2019) GLOBAL-FATE (version 1.0.0): A geographical information system (GIS)-based model for assessing contaminants fate in the global river network. Geosci Model Dev 12(12):5213–5228</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5194/gmd-12-5213-2019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>François B, Schlef KE, Wi S, Brown CM (2019) Design considerations for riverine floods in a changing climate–a review. J Hydrol 574:557–573</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2019.04.068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freitas JS, Kupsco A, Diamante G, Felicio AA, Almeida EA, Schlenk D (2016) Influence of temperature on the thyroidogenic effects of Diuron and its metabolite 3, 4-DCA in tadpoles of the American bullfrog (Lithobates catesbeianus). Environ Sci Technol 50(23):13095–13104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.6b04076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friberg LT, Elinder GG, Kjellstrom T, Nordberg GF (Eds.). (2019) Cd and health: a toxicological and epidemiological appraisal: Volume 2: Effects and response 1 CRC press</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fridrich B, Krčmar D, Dalmacija B, Molnar J, Pešić V, Kragulj M, Varga N (2014) Impact of wastewater from pig farm lagoons on the quality of local groundwater. Agric Water Manag 135:40–53</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.agwat.2013.12.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García J, Ortiz A, Álvarez E, Belohlav V, García-Galán MJ, Díez-Montero RR, Álvarez JA, Uggetti E (2018) Nutrient removal from agricultural run-off in demonstrative full scale tubular photobioreactors for microalgae growth. Ecologic Eng 120:513–521</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoleng.2018.07.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Esquinas E, Pollán M, Umans JG, Francesconi KA, Goessler W, Guallar E, Howard B, Farley J, Best LG, Navas-Acien A (2013) As exposure and cancer mortality in a US-based prospective cohort: the strong heart study. Cancer Epidemiol Biomark Prevent 22(11):1944–1953</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-13-0234-T</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garza-Lombó C, Pappa A, Panayiotidis MI, Gonsebatt ME, Franco R (2019) As-induced neurotoxicity: a mechanistic appraisal. JBIC J Biol Inorg Chem 24:1305–1316</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00775-019-01740-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geissen V, Mol H, Klumpp E, Umlauf G, Nadal M, van der Ploeg M, van de Zee SE, Ritsema CJ (2015) Emerging pollutants in the environment: a challenge for water resource management. Int Soil Water Cons Res 3(1):57–65</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geyer R, Jambeck JR, Law KL (2017) Production, use, and fate of all plastics ever made. Sci Adv 3(7):e1700782</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1700782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giddings JC, Karaiskakis G, Caldwell KD (1981) Concentration and analysis of dilute colloidal samples by sedimentation field-flow fractionation. Sep Sci Technol 16(6):725–744</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01496398108058124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glaser U, Hochrainer D, Klöppel H, Kuhnen H (1985) Low-level Cr (VI) inhalation effects on alveolar macrophages and immune functions in Wistar rats. Arch Toxicol 57:250–256</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF00324787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glöckner FO, Babenzien HD, Amann R (1998) Phylogeny and identification in situ of Nevskia ramosa. Appl Environ Microbiol 64(5):1895–1901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.64.5.1895-1901.1998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldhaber SB (2003) Trace element risk assessment: essentiality vs toxicity. Reg Toxicol Pharmacol 38(2):232–242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0273-2300(02)00020-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonsioroski A, Mourikes VE, Flaws JA (2020) Endocrine disruptors in water and their effects on the reproductive system. Int J Mol Sci 21(6):1929</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms21061929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzales-Siles L, Sjöling Å (2016) The different ecological niches of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli. Environ Microbiol 18(3):741–751</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.13106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govindhan M, Lafleur T, Adhikari BR, Chen A (2015) Electrochemical sensor based on carbon nanotubes for the simultaneous detection of phenolic pollutants. Electroanalysis 27(4):902–909</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/elan.201400608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goyer RA (1989) Mechanisms of lead and Cd nephrotoxicity. Toxicol Lett 46(1–3):153–162</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0378-4274(89)90124-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graciaa DS, Cope JR, Roberts VA, Cikesh BL, Kahler AM, Vigar M, Hilborn ED, Wade TJ, Backer LC, Montgomery SP (2018) Outbreaks associated with untreated recreational water—United States. Am J Transplant 18:2083–2087</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ajt.15002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gregoire C, Elsaesser D, Huguenot D, Lange J, Lebeau T, Merli A, Mose R, Passeport E, Payraudeau S, Schütz T, Schulz R, Wanko A (2009) Mitigation of agricultural nonpoint-source pesticide pollution in artificial wetland ecosystems. Environ Chem Lett 7:205–231</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10311-008-0167-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guimberteau M, Ciais P, Ducharne A, Boisier JP, Dutra Aguiar AP, Biemans H, De Deurwaerder H, Galbraith D, Kruijt B, Langerwisch F, Poveda G, Verbeeck H (2017) Impacts of future deforestation and climate change on the hydrology of the Amazon Basin: a multi-model analysis with a new set of land-cover change scenarios. Hydrol Earth Syst Sci 21(3):1455–1475</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5194/hess-21-1455-2017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guissouma W, Hakami O, Al-Rajab AJ, Tarhouni J (2017) Risk assessment of fluoride exposure in drinking water of Tunisia. Chemosphere 177:102–108</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.03.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo L, Qiu Y, Zhang G, Zheng GJ, Lam PKS, Li X (2008) Levels and bioaccumulation of organochlorine pesticides (OCPs) and polybrominated diphenyl ethers (PBDEs) in fishes from the PearlbRiver estuary and Daya Bay, South China. Environ Poll 152:604–611</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2007.06.067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo B, Wen B, Cheng W, Zhou X, Duan X, Zhao M, Xia Q, Ding S (2018) An enzyme-free and label-free surface plasmon resonance biosensor for ultrasensitive detection of fusion gene based on DNA self-assembly hydrogel with streptavidin encapsulation. Biosens Bioelectr 112:120–126</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2018.04.027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta T, Paul M (2013) The seasonal variation in ionic composition of pond water of Lumding, Assam, Inda. Curr World Environ 8(1):127–131</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12944/CWE.8.1.12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta V, Kumar D, Dwivedi A, Vishwakarma U, Malik DS, Paroha S, Mohan N, Gupta N (2023) Heavy metal contamination in river water, sediment, groundwater and human blood, from Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh, India. Environ Geochem Health 45(5):1807–1818</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-022-01290-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzman-Herrador B, Carlander A, Ethelberg S, Freiesleben de Blasio B, Kuusi M, Lund V, Löfdahl M, MacDonald E, Nichols G, Schönning C, Sudre B, Nygård K (2015) Waterborne outbreaks in the Nordic countries, 1998 to 2012. Eurosurveillance 20(24):21160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES2015.20.24.21160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib MA, Islam ARMT, Bodrud-Doza M, Mukta FA, Khan R, Siddique MAB, Phoungthong K, Techato K (2020) Simultaneous appraisals of pathway and probable health risk associated with trace metals contamination in groundwater from Barapukuria coal basin, Bangladesh. Chemosphere 242:125183</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habibullah-Al-Mamun M, Ahmed MK, Islam MS, Tokumura M, Masunaga S (2019) Occurrence, distribution and possible sources of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) in the surface water from the Bay of Bengal coast of Bangladesh. Ecotoxicol Environ Safe 167:450–458</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.10.052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadzi GY, Essumang DK, Ayoko GA (2018) Assessment of contamination and health risk of heavy metals in selected water bodies around gold mining areas in Ghana. Environ Monitor Assess 190:1–17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-018-6750-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao Z, Chen L, Wang C, Zou X, Zheng F, Feng W, Zhang D, Peng L (2019) Heavy metal distribution and bioaccumulation ability in marine organisms from coastal regions of Hainan and Zhoushan, China. Chemosphere 226:340–350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.03.132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasanein P, Emamjomeh A (2019) Beneficial effects of natural compounds on heavy metal–induced hepatotoxicity. In: Dietary interventions in liver disease. Acad Press. 345-355</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashmi TA, Qureshi R, Tipre D, Menon S (2020) Investigation of pesticide residues in water, sediments and fish samples from Tapi River, India as a case study and its forensic significance. Environ Forens 21(1):1–10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15275922.2019.1693441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He X, Li P, Wu J, Wei M, Ren X, Wang D (2021) Poor groundwater quality and high potential health risks in the Datong Basin, northern China: research from published data. Environ Geochem Health 43:791–812</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00520-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Q, Wang B, Liang J, Liu J, Liang B, Li G, Long Y, Zhang G, Liu H (2023) Research on the construction of portable electrochemical sensors for environmental compounds quality monitoring. Mater Today Adv 17:100340</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mtadv.2022.100340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hegazy AM, Fouad UA (2014) Evaluation of lead hepatotoxicity; histological, histochemical and ultrastructural study. Forens Med Anatom Res 2(03):70</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4236/fmar.2014.23013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hejzlar J, Dubrovský M, Buchtele J, Růžička M (2003) The apparent and potential effects of climate change on the inferred concentration of dissolved organic matter in a temperate stream (the Malše River, South Bohemia). Sci Total Environ 310(1–3):143–152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0048-9697(02)00634-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellström L, Elinder CG, Dahlberg B, Lundberg M, Järup L, Persson B, Axelson O (2001) Cd exposure and end-stage renal disease. Am J Kidney Dis 38(5):1001–1008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/ajkd.2001.28589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera-Domínguez M, Morales-Luna G, Mahlknecht J, Cheng Q, Aguilar-Hernández I, Ornelas-Soto N (2023) Optical biosensors and their applications for the detection of water pollutants. Biosensors 13(3):370</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bios13030370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hertz-Picciotto I, Croft J (1993) Review of the relation between blood lead and blood pressure. Epidemiol Rev 15(2):352–373</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.epirev.a036125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hester ET, Doyle MW (2011) Human impacts to river temperature and their effects on biological processes: a quantitative synthesis 1. JAWRA J Am Water Res Assoc 47(3):571–587</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1752-1688.2011.00525.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hlavsa MC, Roberts VA, Kahler AM, Hilborn ED, Wade TJ, Backer LC, Yoder JS (2014) Recreational water–associated disease outbreaks—United States, 2009–2010. Morbid Mortal Week Rep 63(1):6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hlavsa MC, Roberts VA, Kahler AM, Hilborn ED, Mecher TR, Beach MJ, Wade TJ, Yoder JS (2015) Outbreaks of illness associated with recreational water—United States, 2011–2012. Morbid Mortal Week Rep 64(24):668</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horowitz Y, Greenberg D, Ling G, Lifshitz M (2002) Acrodynia: a case report of two siblings. Arch Dis Childhood 86(6):453–453</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/adc.86.6.453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horton AA, Walton A, Spurgeon DJ, Lahive E, Svendsen C (2017) Microplastics in freshwater and terrestrial environments: evaluating the current understanding to identify the knowledge gaps and future research priorities. Sci Total Environ 586:127–141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.01.190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoskins JK (1934) Most probable numbers for evaluation of coliaerogenes tests by fermentation tube method. Public Health Rep 1896–1970:393–405</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/4581120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsiao EY, Patterson PH (2011) Activation of the maternal immune system induces endocrine changes in the placenta via IL-6. Brain Behav Immun 25(4):604–615</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2010.12.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Qi S, Wu C, Ke Y, Chen J, Chen W, Gong X (2012) Preliminary assessment of heavy metal contamination in surface water and sediments from Honghu Lake, East Central China. Front Earth Sci 6:39–47</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11707-012-0309-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu L, Fong CC, Zhang X, Chan LL, Lam PK, Chu PK, Wong KY, Yang M (2016) Au nanoparticles decorated TiO2 nanotube arrays as a recyclable sensor for photoenhanced electrochemical detection of bisphenol A. Environ Sci Technol 50(8):4430–4438</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.5b05857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang HW, Lee CH, Yu HS (2019) As-induced carcinogenesis and immune dysregulation. Int J Environ Res Public Health 16(15):2746</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph16152746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hung YT, Eldridge J, Taricska JR, Li KH, Shuster WW (2021) Cooling and reuse of thermal discharges. Environ Nat Res Eng, 195-228</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huntley BJ (2023) Soil, water and nutrients. Ecology of Angola: Terrestrial biomes and ecoregions. Springer International Publishing, Cham, pp 127–147</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-18923-4_6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyder O, Chung M, Cosgrove D, Herman JM, Li Z, Firoozmand A, Gurakar A, Koteish A, Pawlik TM (2013) Cd exposure and liver disease among US adults. J Gastrointest Surg 17:1265–1273</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11605-013-2210-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ighalo JO, Adeniyi AG, Adeniran JA, Ogunniyi S (2021) A systematic literature analysis of the nature and regional distribution of water pollution sources in Nigeria. J Clean Prod 283:124566</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.124566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Igwe PU, Chukwudi CC, Ifenatuorah FC, Fagbeja IF, Okeke CA (2017) A review of environmental effects of surface water pollution. Int J Adv Eng Res Sci 4(12):237340</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikeagwuani CC, Akanno CC (2023) Assessment of river degradation by industrial waste material using pollution measures and multivariate statistical analysis. Arab J Geosci 16(5):294</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12517-023-11367-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imran U, Ullah A, Shaikh K, Mehmood R, Saeed M (2019) Health risk assessment of the exposure of heavy metal contamination in surface water of lower Sindh, Pakistan. SN Appl Sci 1:1–10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42452-019-0594-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam MMM (2019) Present and future river microbial water quality in Bangladesh. SUB J Sustain Environ Dev, 77–86</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Issa HM, Alshatteri AH (2021) Impacts of wastewater discharge from Kalar city on Diyala-Sirwan river water quality, Iraq: pollution evaluation, health risks of heavy metals contamination. Appl Water Sci 11(4):73</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13201-021-01397-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivars-Barceló F, Zuliani A, Fallah M, Mashkour M, Rahimnejad M, Luque R (2018) Novel applications of microbial fuel cells in sensors and biosensors. Appl Sci 8(7):1184</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app8071184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyiola AO, Asiedu B, Oyewole EO, Akinrinade AJ (2022) Impacts of climate change on aquatic biodiversity in Africa. In Biodiversity in Africa: Potentials, Threats and Conservation. Singapore: Springer Nature Singapore, pp 369-394</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacobs J, Rhodes M, Sturgis B, Wood B (2009) Influence of environmental gradients on the abundance and distribution of Mycobacterium spp. in a coastal lagoon estuary. Appl Environ Microbiol 75(23):7378–7384</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01900-09</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadeja NB, Banerji T, Kapley A, Kumar R (2022) Water pollution in India–current scenario. Water Security 16:100119</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wasec.2022.100119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang J, Wang X, Chao R, Ren Y, Hu C, Xu Z, Liu GL (2014) Smartphone based portable bacteria pre-concentrating microfluidic sensor and impedance sensing system. Sensors Actuators B Chem 193:653–659</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2013.11.103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jofre CF, Regiart M, Fernández-Baldo MA, Bertotti M, Raba J, Messina GA (2020) Electrochemical microfluidic immunosensor based on TES-AuNPs@ Fe3O4 and CMK-8 for IgG anti-Toxocara canis determination. Analytica Chimica Acta 1096:120–129</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2019.10.040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joyce RJ, Dhillon HS (1994) Trace level determination of bromate in ozonated drinking water using ion chromatography. J Chromatograph A 671(1–2):165–171</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0021-9673(94)80235-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kahlon SK, Sharma G, Julka JM, Kumar A, Sharma S, Stadler FJ (2018) Impact of heavy metals and nanoparticles on aquatic biota. Environ Chem Lett 16:919–946</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10311-018-0737-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaler KV, Prakash R (2014) Droplet microfluidics for chip-based diagnostics. Sensors 14(12):23283–23306</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s141223283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kandjou V, Nkwe DO (2023) Analysing the quality of Botswana’s surface waters in terms of microbial contamination and postulating feasible treatment and removal means. Ecohydrol Hydrobiol 24:217–225</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecohyd.2023.09.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karimi-Maleh H, Fakude CT, Mabuba N, Peleyeju GM, Arotiba OA (2019) The determination of 2-phenylphenol in the presence of 4-chlorophenol using nano-Fe3O4/ionic liquid paste electrode as an electrochemical sensor. J Colloid Interf Sci 554:603–610</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcis.2019.07.047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karimi-Maleh H, Ayati A, Davoodi R, Tanhaei B, Karimi F, Malekmohammadi S, Orooji Y, Fu L, Sillanpää M (2021) Recent advances in using of chitosan-based adsorbents for removal of pharmaceutical contaminants: a review. J Clean Prod 291:125880</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.125880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karri RR, Ravindran G, Dehghani MH (2021) Wastewater—sources, toxicity, and their consequences to human health. In: Soft computing techniques in solid waste and wastewater management. Elsevier, pp 3-33</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassal P, Steinberg MD, Steinberg IM (2018) Wireless chemical sensors and biosensors: a review. Sensors Actuators B Chem 266:228–245</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2018.03.074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasten-Jolly J, Heo Y, Lawrence DA (2010) Impact of developmental lead exposure on splenic factors. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol 247(2):105–115</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2010.06.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaushal SS, Likens GE, Jaworski NA, Pace ML, Sides AM, Seekell D, Belt KT, Secor DH, Wingate RL (2010) Rising stream and river temperatures in the United States. Front Ecol Environ 8(9):461–466</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1890/090037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaya D, Imamoglu I, Sanin FD, Sowers KR (2018) A comparative evaluation of anaerobic dechlorination of PCB-118 and Aroclor 1254 in sediment microcosms from three PCB-impacted environments. J Hazard Mater 341:328–335</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2017.08.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khairy M, Ayoub HA, Banks CE (2018) Non-enzymatic electrochemical platform for parathion pesticide sensing based on nanometer-sized Ni oxide modified screen-printed electrodes. Food Chem 255:104–111</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.02.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan R, Saxena A, Shukla S, Sekar S, Senapathi V, Wu J (2021) Environmental contamination by heavy metals and associated human health risk assessment: a case study of surface water in Gomti River Basin, India. Environ Sci Poll Res 28(40):56105–56116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-14592-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim YJ, Kim JM (2015) As toxicity in male reproduction and development. Dev Reprod 19(4):167</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12717/DR.2015.19.4.167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiulia NM, Hofstra N, Vermeulen LC, Obara MA, Medema G, Rose JB (2015) Global occurrence and emission of rotaviruses to surface waters. Pathogens 4(2):229–255</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens4020229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleinow KM, Goodrich MS, Cockerham L, Shane B (1994) Environmental aquatic toxicology. Basic Environ Toxicol, 353-384</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kodavanti PRS (2017) Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs). Reference Mod Neurosci Biobehav Psychol</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kolpin DW, Furlong ET, Meyer MT, Thurman EM, Zaugg SD, Barber LB, Buxton HT (2002) Pharmaceuticals, hormones, and other organic wastewater contaminants in US streams, 1999–2000: a national reconnaissance. Environ Sci Technol 36(6):1202–1211</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es011055j</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korostynska O, Mason A, Al-Shamma’a AI (2013) Monitoring pollutants in wastewater: traditional lab based versus modern real-time approaches. Smart Sensors Real-time Water Quality Monitoring, 1-24</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuester RK, Waalkes MP, Goering PL, Fisher BL, McCuskey RS, Sipes IG (2002) Differential hepatotoxicity induced by Cd in Fischer 344 and Sprague-Dawley rats. Toxicol Sci 65(1):151–159</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/toxsci/65.1.151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V, Thakur RK, Kumar P (2019) Assessment of heavy metals uptake by cauliflower (Brassica oleracea var. botrytis) grown in integrated industrial effluent irrigated soils: a prediction modeling study. Sci Hort 257:108682</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2019.108682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V, Sharma A, Bhardwaj R, Thukral AK (2020) Water quality of River Beas, India, and its correlation with reflectance data. J Water Chem Technol 42(2):134–141</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3103/S1063455X2002006X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A, Saxena P, Kisku GC (2023) Heavy metal contamination of surface water and bed-sediment quality for ecological risk assessment of Gomti River, India. Stochast Environ Res Risk Assess, 1-18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar R, Goyal MK, Surampalli RY, Zhang TC (2024) River pollution in India: exploring regulatory and remedial paths. Clean Technol Environ Policy, 1-23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumwimba MN, Meng F, Iseyemi O, Moore MT, Zhu B, Tao W, Liang TJ, Ilunga L (2018) Removal of non-point source pollutants from domestic sewage and agricultural runoff by vegetated drainage ditches (VDDs): design, mechanism, management strategies, and future directions. Sci Total Environ 639:742–759</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.05.184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kvakić M, Pellerin S, Ciais P, Achat DL, Augusto L, Denoroy P, Denoroy P, Gerber JS, Goll D, Mollier A, Mueller ND, Ringeval B (2018) Quantifying the limitation to world cereal production due to soil P status. Global Biogeochem Cycles 32(1):143–157</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/2017GB005754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee S, Bong S, Ha J, Kwak M, Park SK, Piao Y (2015) Electrochemical deposition of bismuth on activated graphene-nafion composite for anodic stripping voltammetric determination of trace heavy metals. Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical 215:62–69</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2015.03.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee S, Oh J, Kim D, Piao Y (2016) A sensitive electrochemical sensor using an iron oxide/graphene composite for the simultaneous detection of heavy metal ions. Talanta 160:528–536</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2016.07.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J, Schlichting R, König M, Scholz S, Krauss M, Escher BI (2022) Monitoring mixture effects of neurotoxicants in surface water and wastewater treatment plant effluents with neurite outgrowth inhibition in SH-SY5Y cells. ACS Environmental Au 2(6):523–535</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsenvironau.2c00026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lentini P, Zanoli L, Granata A, Signorelli SS, Castellino P, Dell’Aquila R (2017) Kidney and heavy metals-the role of environmental exposure. Mol Med Rep 15(5):3413–3419</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3892/mmr.2017.6389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levallois P, Gingras S, Marcoux S, Legay C, Catto C, Rodriguez M, Tardif R (2012) Maternal exposure to drinking-water chlorination by-products and small-for-gestational-age neonates. Epidemiology 23(2):267–276</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e3182468569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Gou H, Al-Ogaidi I, Wu N (2013) Nanostructured sensors for detection of heavy metals: a review. Sustain Chem Eng 1:713–723</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/sc400019a</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Ren H, Yin E, Tang S, Li Y, Cao J (2015) Pilot-scale study on N and aromatic compounds removal in printing and dyeing wastewater by reinforced hydrolysis-denitrification coupling process and its microbial community analysis. Environ Sci Poll Res 22:9483–9493</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-015-4124-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li E, Saleem F, Edge TA, Schellhorn HE (2021) Biological indicators for fecal pollution detection and source tracking: a review. Processes 9(11):2058</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pr9112058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Xue Q, Chen T, Liu F, Wang Q, Chang C, Lu X, Zhou T, Niwa O (2021) The influence mechanism of the molecular structure on the peak current and peak potential in electrochemical detection of typical quinolone antibiotics. Phys Chem Chem Phys 23(25):13873–13877</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1CP01358K</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao K, Hu H, Ma S, Ren H (2019) Effect of microbial activity and microbial community structure on the formation of dissolved organic nitrogen (DON) and bioavailable DON driven by low temperatures. Water Res 159:397–405</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2019.04.049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling F, Foody GM, Du H, Ban X, Li X, Zhang Y, Du Y (2017) Monitoring thermal pollution in rivers downstream of dams with Landsat ETM+ thermal infrared images. Remote Sensing 9(11):1175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/rs9111175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisowski P, Zarzycki PK (2013) Microfluidic paper-based analytical devices (μPADs) and micro total analysis systems (μTAS): Development, applications and future trends. Chromatographia 76(19–20):1201–1214</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10337-013-2413-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T, Wang F, Michalski G, Xia X, Liu S (2013) Using 15N, 17O, and 18O to determine nitrate sources in the Yellow River, China. Environ Sci Technol 47(23):13412–13421</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es403357m</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Fiedler H, Gong W, Wang B, Yu G (2018) Potential sources of unintentionally produced PCB, HCB, and PeCBz in China: a preliminary overview. Front Environ Sci Eng 12:1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11783-018-1036-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Liu G, Yuan Z, Liu H, Lam PK (2018) Heavy metals (As, Hg and V) and stable isotope ratios (δ13C and δ15N) in fish from Yellow River Estuary, China. Sci Total Environ 613:462–471</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu K, Wang X, Song Z, Wei N, Ye H, Cong X, Zhao L, Li Y, Qu L, Zhu L, Zhang F (2020) Global inventory of atmospheric fibrous microplastics input into the ocean: an implication from the indoor origin. J Hazard Mater 400:123223</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.123223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Xue Q, Chang C, Wang R, Liu Z, He L (2022) Recent progress regarding electrochemical sensors for the detection of typical pollutants in water environments. Anal Sci 38(1):55–70</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2116/analsci.21SAR12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu W Q, Xie SH, Zhou WS, Zhang SH, Liu AL (2008) Water pollution and health impact in China: a mini review. Open Environ Sci J, 2(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyubimova T, Lepikhin A, Parshakova Y, Lyakhin Y, Tiunov A (2018) The modeling of the formation of technogenic thermal pollution zones in large reservoirs. Int J Heat Mass Trans 126:342–352</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijheatmasstransfer.2018.05.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma X, Wang L, Yang H, Li N, Gong C (2020) Spatiotemporal analysis of water quality using multivariate statistical techniques and the water quality identification index for the Qinhuai River Basin, East China. Water 12(10):2764</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w12102764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maansi Jindal R, Wats M (2022) Evaluation of surface water quality using water quality indices (WQIs) in Lake Sukhna, Chandigarh, India. Appl Water Sci, 12, 1-14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madden N, Lewis A, Davis M (2013) Thermal effluent from the power sector: an analysis of once-through cooling system impacts on surface water temperature. Env Res Lett 8(3):035006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/8/3/035006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madheshiya P, Gupta GS, Sahoo A, Tiwari S (2022) Biomonitoring tools and bioprogramming: an overview. New Paradigms Environ Biomonitor Using Plants, 341-366</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmood I, Imadi SR, Shazadi K, Gul A, Hakeem KR (2016) Effects of pesticides on environment. Plant, soil and microbes: volume 1: implications in crop science, 253-269</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mai L, Sun XF, Xia LL, Bao LJ, Liu LY, Zeng EY (2020) Global riverine plastic outflows. Environ Sci Technol 54(16):10049–10056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.0c02273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mairhofer J, Roppert K, Ertl P (2009) Microfluidic systems for pathogen sensing: a review. Sensors 9(6):4804–4823</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s90604804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maity JP, Vithanage M, Kumar M, Ghosh A, Mohan D, Ahmad A, Bhattacharya P (2021) Seven 21st century challenges of As-fluoride contamination and remediation. Groundwater Sustain Dev 12:100538</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gsd.2020.100538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manoj S, RamyaPriya R, Elango L (2021) Long-term exposure to Cr contaminated waters and the associated human health risk in a highly contaminated industrialised region. Environ Sci Pollut Res 28:4276–4288</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-10762-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao G, Zhao Y, Zhang F, Liu J, Huang X (2019) Spatiotemporal variability of heavy metals and identification of potential source tracers in the surface water of the Lhasa River basin. Environ Sci Pollut Res 26:7442–7452</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-019-04188-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchetti C (2014) Interaction of metal ions with neurotransmitter receptors and potential role in neurodiseases. Biometals 27:1097–1113</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10534-014-9791-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mateos-Cárdenas A, Scott DT, Seitmaganbetova G, van Pelt Frank NAM, AK JM (2019) Polyethylene microplastics adhere to Lemna minor (L.), yet have no effects on plant growth or feeding by Gammarus duebeni (Lillj.). Sci Total Environ, 689:413-421</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthews NH, Fitch K, Li WQ, Morris JS, Christiani DC, Qureshi AA, Cho E (2019) Exposure to trace elements and risk of skin cancer: a systematic review of epidemiologic studies. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prevent 28(1):3–21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-18-0286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayanglambam B, Neelam SS (2022) Physicochemistry and water quality of Loktak Lake water, Manipur, India. Int J Environ Anal Chem 102(7):1638–1661</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03067319.2020.1742888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meador JP, Yeh A, Young G, Gallagher EP (2016) Contaminants of emerging concern in a large temperate estuary. Environ Poll 213:254–267</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2016.01.088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medina-Sánchez M, Mayorga-Martinez CC, Watanabe T, Ivandini TA, Honda Y, Pino F, Nakata K, Fujishima A, Einaga Y, Merkoçi A (2016) Microfluidic platform for environmental contaminants sensing and degradation based on boron-doped diamond electrodes. Biosens Bioelectr 75:365–374</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2015.08.058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehmeti E, Stanković DM, Hajrizi A, Kalcher K (2016) The use of graphene nanoribbons as an efficient electrochemical sensing material for nitrite determination. Talanta 159:34–39</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2016.05.079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mejia, A. (2014). Water scarcity in Latin America and the Caribbean: myths and reality. In: Water for the Americas (pp. 40-60). Routledge</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menart E, Jovanovski V, Hocevar SB (2015) Silver particle-decorated carbon paste electrode based on ionic liquid for improved determination of nitrite. Electrochem Commun 52:45–48</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.elecom.2015.01.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller RZ, Watts AJ, Winslow BO, Galloway TS, Barrows AP (2017) Mountains to the sea: river study of plastic and non-plastic microfiber pollution in the northeast USA. Mar Poll Bullet 124(1):245–251</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2017.07.028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milton AH, Hussain S, Akter S, Rahman M, Mouly TA, Mitchell K (2017) A review of the effects of chronic As exposure on adverse pregnancy outcomes. Int J Environ Res Public Health 14(6):556</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph14060556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra KP (2009) Lead exposure and its impact on immune system: a review. Toxicol In Vitro 23(6):969–972</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tiv.2009.06.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra S, Dwivedi SP, Singh RB (2010) A review on epigenetic effect of heavy metal carcinogens on human health. Open Nutraceutic J 3(1):188–193</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miura S, Takahashi K, Imagawa T, Uchida K, Saito S, Tominaga M, Ohta T (2013) Involvement of TRPA1 activation in acute pain induced by Cd in mice. Mol Pain 9:1744–8069</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1744-8069-9-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moorman MC, Augspurger T, Stanton JD, Smith A (2017) Where’s the grass? disappearing submerged aquatic vegetation and declining water quality in lake mattamuskeet. J Fish Wildlife Manag 8(2):401–417</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3996/082016-JFWM-068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morkunas I, Woźniak A, Mai VC, Rucińska-Sobkowiak R, Jeandet P (2018) The role of heavy metals in plant response to biotic stress. Molecules 23(9):2320</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules23092320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mustafa G, Khan MS, Asif MI, Ullah A, Khan I, Ullah I (2021) Water pollutants and nanosensors. In: Aquananotechnology pp 105-133. Elsevier</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naddeo V, Secondes MFN, Borea L, Hasan SW, Ballesteros F Jr, Belgiorno V (2020) Removal of contaminants of emerging concern from real wastewater by an innovative hybrid membrane process–UltraSound, Adsorption, and Membrane ultrafiltration (USAMe®). Ultrason Sonochem 68:105237</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Napiórkowska-Krzebietke A, Skrzypczak AR, Kicińska A (2023) Abiotic–biotic interrelations in the context of stabilized ecological potential of post-mining waters. Water 15(19):3328</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w15193328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navas-Acien A, Selvin E, Sharrett AR, Calderon-Aranda E, Silbergeld E, Guallar E (2004) Lead, Cd, smoking, and increased risk of peripheral arterial disease. Circulation 109(25):3196–3201</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000130848.18636.B2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newton RJ, Bootsma MJ, Morrison HG, Sogin ML, McLellan SL (2013) A microbial signature approach to identify fecal pollution in the waters off an urbanized coast of Lake Michigan. Microb Ecol 65:1011–1023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00248-013-0200-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nithin A, Sundaramanickam A, Sathish M (2022) Seasonal distribution of microplastics in the surface water and sediments of the Vellar estuary, Parangipettai, southeast coast of India. Mar Poll Bullet 174:113248</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2021.113248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu L, Wang Y, Li Y, Lin L, Chen Y, Shen J (2023) Occurrence, degradation pathways, and potential synergistic degradation mechanism of microplastics in surface water: a review. Curr Poll Rep 9:1–15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nogales B, Lanfranconi MP, Piña-Villalonga JM, Bosch R (2011) Anthropogenic perturbations in marine microbial communities. FEMS Microbiol Rev 35(2):275–298</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2010.00248.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nomngongo PN, Ngila JC, Msagati TA, Gumbi BP, Iwuoha EI (2012) Determination of selected persistent organic pollutants in wastewater from landfill leachates, using an amperometric biosensor. Phys Chem Earth, Parts A/B/C 50:252–261</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pce.2012.08.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowak DJ, Greenfield EJ (2020) The increase of impervious cover and decrease of tree cover within urban areas globally (2012–2017). Urban Forest Urban Green 49:126638</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ufug.2020.126638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okereafor U, Makhatha M, Mekuto L, Uche-Okereafor N, Sebola T, Mavumengwana V (2020) Toxic metal implications on agricultural soils, plants, animals, aquatic life and human health. Int J Environ Res Public Health 17(7):2204</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17072204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olisah C, Adeniji AO, Okoh OO, Okoh AI (2019) Occurrence and risk evaluation of organochlorine contaminants in surface water along the course of Swartkops and Sundays River Estuaries, Eastern Cape Province, South Africa. Environ Geochem Health 41:2777–2801</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10653-019-00336-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortiz-Hernández ML, Sánchez-Salinas E, Dantán-González E, Castrejón-Godínez ML (2013) Pesticide biodegradation: mechanisms, genetics and strategies to enhance the process. Biodegrad-life Sci 10:251–287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyedotun TDT, Ally N (2021) Environmental issues and challenges confronting surface waters in South America: a review. Environ Chall 3:100049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envc.2021.100049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Packer M (2016) Co cardiomyopathy: a critical reappraisal in light of a recent resurgence. Circulat Heart Fail 9(12):e003604</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCHEARTFAILURE.116.003604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pajooheshpour N, Rezaei M, Hajian A, Afkhami A, Sillanpää M, Araduini F, Bagheri H (2018) Protein templated Au-Pt nanoclusters-graphene nanoribbons as a high performance sensing layer for the electrochemical determination of diazinon. Sens Actuat B Chem 275:180–189</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2018.08.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan Z, Sun Y, Liu Q, Lin C, Sun X, He Q, Zhou K, Lin H (2020) Riverine microplastic pollution matters: a case study in the Zhangjiang River of Southeastern China. Marine Poll Bullet 159:111516</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2020.111516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey S, Kumari N (2023) Impact assessment of heavy metal pollution in surface water bodies. Metals Water 2023:129–154</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-323-95919-3.00004-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey A, Agrawal M, Agrawal SB (2023) Ultraviolet-B and heavy metal-induced regulation of secondary metabolites in medicinal plants: a review. Metabolites 13(3):341</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/metabo13030341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park M, Choi YS, Shin HJ, Song I, Yoon CG, Choi JD, Yu SJ (2019) A comparison study of runoff characteristics of non-point source pollution from three watersheds in South Korea. Water 11(5):966</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w11050966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paruch L, Paruch AM, Eiken HG, Sørheim R (2019) Faecal pollution affects abundance and diversity of aquatic microbial community in anthropo-zoogenically influenced lotic ecosystems. Sci Rep 9(1):19469</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-56058-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasquini AI, Formica SM, Sacchi GA (2012) Hydrochemistry and nutrients dynamic in the Suquía River urban catchment’s, Córdoba, Argentina. Environ Earth Sci 65:453–467</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12665-011-0978-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel M, Kumar R, Kishor K, Mlsna T, Pittman CU Jr, Mohan D (2019) Pharmaceuticals of emerging concern in aquatic systems: chemistry, occurrence, effects, and removal methods. Chem Rev 119(6):3510–3673</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.8b00299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul MB, Stock V, Cara-Carmona J, Lisicki E, Shopova S, Fessard V, Braeuning A, Sieg H, Böhmert L (2020) Micro-and nanoplastics–current state of knowledge with the focus on oral uptake and toxicity. Nanoscale Adv 2(10):4350–4367</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0NA00539H</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pednekar AM, Grant SB, Jeong Y, Poon Y, Oancea C (2005) Influence of climate change, tidal mixing, and watershed urbanization on historical water quality in Newport Bay, a saltwater wetland and tidal embayment in southern California. Environ Sci Technol 39(23):9071–9082</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es0504789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peña-Guzmán C, Ulloa-Sánchez S, Mora K, Helena-Bustos R, Lopez-Barrera E, Alvarez J, Rodriguez-Pinzón M (2019) Emerging pollutants in the urban water cycle in Latin America: a review of the current literature. J Environ Manag 237:408–423</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2019.02.100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Percival SL, McCarty S, Hunt JA, Woods EJ (2014) The effects of pH on wound healing, biofilms, and antimicrobial efficacy. Wound Repair Regen 22(2):174–186</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/wrr.12125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perera WPRT, Dayananda MDNR, Liyanage JA (2020) Exploring the root cause for chronic kidney disease of unknown etiology (CKDU) via analysis of metal ion and counterion contaminants in drinking water: a study in Sri Lanka. J Chem 2020(1):8670974</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierce BL, Kibriya MG, Tong L, Jasmine F, Argos M, Roy S, Paul-Brutus R, Rahaman R, Rakibuz-Zaman M, Parvez F, Ahsan H (2012) Genome-wide association study identifies chromosome 10q24.32 variants associated with As metabolism and toxicity phenotypes in Bangladesh. PLoS Genetics 8(2):e1002522</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pobi KK, Satpati S, Dutta S, Nayek S, Saha RN, Gupta S (2019) Sources evaluation and ecological risk assessment of heavy metals accumulated within a natural stream of Durgapur industrial zone, India, by using multivariate analysis and pollution indices. Appl Water Sci 9(3):1–16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13201-019-0946-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prathumratana L, Sthiannopkao S, Kim KW (2008) The relationship of climatic and hydrological parameters to surface water quality in the lower Mekong River. Environ Int 34(6):860–866</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2007.10.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO/UNICEF Joint Water Supply, &amp; Sanitation Monitoring Programme (2015) Progress on sanitation and drinking water: 2015 update and MDG assessment. World Health Organization</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prohaska JR (2000) Long-term functional consequences of malnutrition during brain development: Cu. Nutrition 7(16):502–504</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0899-9007(00)00308-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proshad R, Islam S, Tusher TR, Zhang D, Khadka S, Gao J, Kundu S (2021) Appraisal of heavy metal toxicity in surface water with human health risk by a novel approach: a study on an urban river in vicinity to industrial areas of Bangladesh. Toxin Rev 40(4):803–819</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15569543.2020.1780615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi N, Li B, You H, Zhang W, Fu L, Wang Y, Chen L (2014) Surface-enhanced Raman scattering on a zigzag microfluidic chip: towards high-sensitivity detection of As (III) ions. Analytic Methods 6(12):4077–4082</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C3AY42283F</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi P, Wang J, Wang X, Wang X, Wang Z, Xu H, Di S, Wang Q, Wang X (2018) Sensitive determination of fenitrothion in water samples based on an electrochemical sensor layered reduced graphene oxide, molybdenum sulfide (MoS2)-Au and zirconia films. Electrochimica Acta 292:667–675</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2018.09.187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao J, Tang J, Xue Q (2020) Study on Pb release by several new lixiviants in weathered crust elution-deposited rare earth ore leaching process: behavior and mechanism. Ecotoxicol Environ Safe 190:110138</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.110138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quan B, Li X, Zhang H, Zhang C, Ming Y, Huang Y, Xi Y, Weihua X, Yunguo L, Tang Y (2019) Technology and principle of removing triclosan from aqueous media: a review. Chem Eng J 378:122185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2019.122185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman MM, Khan A, Asiri AM (2015) Chemical sensor development based on poly (o-anisidine) silverized–MWCNT nanocomposites deposited on glassy carbon electrodes for environmental remediation. RSC Adv 5(87):71370–71378</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C5RA10793H</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmani T, Bagheri H, Behbahani M, Hajian A, Afkhami A (2018) Modified 3D graphene-Au as a novel sensing layer for direct and sensitive electrochemical determination of carbaryl pesticide in fruit, vegetable, and water samples. Food Anal Methods 11:3005–3014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12161-018-1280-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rango T, Jeuland M, Manthrithilake H, McCornick P (2015) Nephrotoxic contaminants in drinking water and urine, and chronic kidney disease in rural Sri Lanka. Sci Total Environ 518:574–585</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2015.02.097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasheed T, Bilal M, Nabeel F, Adeel M, Iqbal HM (2019) Environmentally-related contaminants of high concern: potential sources and analytical modalities for detection, quantification, and treatment. Environ Int 122:52–66</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.11.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawal A, Chakraborty S, Li B, Lewis K, Godoy M, Paulette L, Weindorf DC (2019) Determination of base saturation percentage in agricultural soils via portable X-ray fluorescence spectrometer. Geoderma 338:375–382</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2018.12.032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raymundo-Pereira PA, Campos AM, Mendonça CD, Calegaro ML, Machado SA, Oliveira ON Jr (2017) Printex 6L carbon nanoballs used in electrochemical sensors for simultaneous detection of emerging pollutants hydroquinone and paracetamol. Sens Actuat B Chem 252:165–174</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2017.05.121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy AVB, Moniruzzaman M, Aminabhavi TM (2019) Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) in the environment: recent updates on sampling, pretreatment, cleanup technologies and their analysis. Chem Eng J 358:1186–1207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2018.09.205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed ML, Pinckney JL, Keppler CJ, Brock LM, Hogan SB, Greenfield DI (2016) The influence of N and P on phytoplankton growth and assemblage composition in four coastal, southeastern USA systems. Estuarine, Coast Shelf Sci 177:71–82</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecss.2016.05.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren H, Wang G, Ding W, Li H, Shen X, Shen D, Jiang X, Qadeer A (2023) Response of dissolved organic matter (DOM) and microbial community to submerged macrophytes restoration in lakes: a review. Environ Res 231:116185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2023.116185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes JL, Molina-Jijón E, Rodríguez-Muñoz R, Bautista-García P, Debray-García Y, Namorado MDC (2013) Tight junction proteins and oxidative stress in heavy metals-induced nephrotoxicity. BioMed Res Int 2013:730789</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2013/730789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhouati A, Berkani M, Vasseghian Y, Golzadeh N (2022) MXene-based electrochemical sensors for detection of environmental pollutants: a comprehensive review. Chemosphere 291:132921</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.132921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizk R, Juzsakova T, Ali MB, Rawash MA, Domokos E, Hedfi A, Almalki M, Boufahja F, Shafik HM, Rédey Á (2022) Comprehensive environmental assessment of heavy metal contamination of surface water, sediments and Nile Tilapia in Lake Nasser, Egypt. J King Saud Univ-Sci 34(1):101748</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jksus.2021.101748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Mozaz S, Lopez de Alda MJ, Barceló D (2006) Biosensors as useful tools for environmental analysis and monitoring. Anal Bioanalytic Chem 386:1025–1041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-006-0574-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenfeld PE, Feng LGH (2011) Emerging contaminants. Risks Hazard Wastes 215–222</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rousseau MC, Parent ME, Nadon L, Latreille B, Siemiatycki J (2007) Occupational exposure to lead compounds and risk of cancer among men: a population-based case-control study. Am J Epidemiol 166(9):1005–1014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kwm183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Routti H, Atwood TC, Bechshoft T, Boltunov A, Ciesielski TM, Desforges JP, Dietz R, Gabrielsen GW, Jenssen BM, Letcher RJ, Tartu S (2019) State of knowledge on current exposure, fate and potential health effects of contaminants in polar bears from the circumpolar Arctic. Sci Total Environ 664:1063–1083</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.02.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy JS, Chatterjee D, Das N, Giri AK (2018) Substantial evidences indicate that inorganic As is a genotoxic carcinogen: a review. Toxicol Res 34:311–324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5487/TR.2018.34.4.311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha P, Paul B (2019) Assessment of heavy metal toxicity related with human health risk in the surface water of an industrialized area by a novel technique. Human Ecol Risk Assess Int J 25(4):966–987</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10807039.2018.1458595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha N, Mollah MZI, Alam MF, Rahman MS (2016) Seasonal investigation of heavy metals in marine fishes captured from the Bay of Bengal and the implications for human health risk assessment. Food Contr 70:110–118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.05.040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahoo S, Goswami S (2023) Theoretical framework for assessing the economic and environmental impact of water pollution: a detailed study on sustainable development of India. J Fut Sustain 4(1):23–34</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sajid M, Nazal MK, Baig N, Osman AM (2018) Removal of heavy metals and organic pollutants from water using dendritic polymers based adsorbents: a critical review. Separat Purif Technol 191:400–423</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.seppur.2017.09.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salles FJ, de Toledo MCB, César ACG, Ferreira GM, Barbério A (2016) Cytotoxic and genotoxic assessment of surface water from São Paulo State, Brazil, during the rainy and dry seasons. Ecotoxicology 25:633–645</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10646-016-1622-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salman SA, Asmoay AA, El-Gohary A, Sabet H (2019) Evaluation of human risks of surface water and groundwater contaminated with Cd and Pb in the southern El-Minya Governorate, Egypt. Drinking Water Eng Sci 12(1):23–30</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5194/dwes-12-23-2019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salnikow K, Zhitkovich A (2008) Genetic and epigenetic mechanisms in metal carcinogenesis and cocarcinogenesis: Ni, As, and Cr. Chem Res Toxicol 21(1):28–44</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/tx700198a</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salonen JT, Seppänen K, Lakka TA, Salonen R, Kaplan GA (2000) Hg accumulation and accelerated progression of carotid atherosclerosis: a population-based prospective 4-year follow-up study in men in eastern Finland. Atherosclerosis 148(2):265–273</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0021-9150(99)00272-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samia K, Dhouha A, Anis C, Ammar M, Rim A, Abdelkrim C (2018) Assessment of organic pollutants (PAH and PCB) in surface water: sediments and shallow groundwater of Grombalia watershed in northeast of Tunisia. Arab J Geosci 11(2):34</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12517-017-3362-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarker KK, Bristy MS, Alam N, Baki MA, Shojib FH, Quraishi SB, Khan MF (2020) Ecological risk and source apportionment of heavy metals in surface water and sediments on Saint Martin’s Island in the Bay of Bengal. Environ Sci Pollut Res 27:31827–31840</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09384-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasakova N, Gregova G, Takacova D, Mojzisova J, Papajova I, Venglovsky J, Szaboova T, Kovacova S (2018) Pollution of surface and ground water by sources related to agricultural activities. Front Sustain Food Syst 2:42</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2018.00042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheurer M, Bigalke M (2018) Microplastics in Swiss floodplain soils. Environ Sci Technol 52(6):3591–3598</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.7b06003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segrave AJ (2009) Scenes: Briefing paper river water temperature for industrial cooling. KWR Watercyc Res Ins 93:100901</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sehgal S, Aggarwal S, Banik SP, Kaushik P (2024) Impact of water contamination on food safety and related health risks. Microbial Biotechnology in the Food Industry: Advances, Challenges, and Potential Solutions. Springer International Publishing, Cham, pp 337–363</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-51417-3_14</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shan K, Wang X, Yang H, Zhou B, Song L, Shang M (2020) Use statistical machine learning to detect nutrient thresholds in Microcystis blooms and microcystin management. Harmful Algae 94:101807</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hal.2020.101807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma RK, Agrawal M, Marshall F (2007) Heavy metal contamination of soil and vegetables in suburban areas of Varanasi, India. Ecotoxicol Envir Safe 66(2):258–266</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2005.11.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma A, Kumar V, Shahzad B, Tanveer M, Sidhu GPS, Handa N, Kohli SK, Yadav P, Bali AS, Parihar RD, Thukral AK (2019) Worldwide pesticide usage and its impacts on ecosystem. SN Appl Sci 1:1–16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42452-019-1485-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma BM, Bečanová J, Scheringer M, Sharma A, Bharat GK, Whitehead PG, Klánová J, Nizzetto L (2019) Health and ecological risk assessment of emerging contaminants (pharmaceuticals, personal care products, and artificial sweeteners) in surface and groundwater (drinking water) in the Ganges River Basin, India. Sci Total Environ 646:1459–1467</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.07.235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma S, Nagpal AK, Kaur I (2022) Potentially toxic elements in river water and associated health risks in Ropar Wetland, India and its vicinity. Int J Environ Sci Technol 19:475–498</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13762-020-03101-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siddique MAM, Rahman M, Rahman SMA, Hassan MR, Fardous Z, Chowdhury MAZ, Hossain MB (2021) Assessment of heavy metal contamination in the surficial sediments from the lower Meghna River estuary, Noakhali coast, Bangladesh. Int J Sed Res 36(3):384–391</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijsrc.2020.10.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva LF, Crissien TJ, Sampaio CH, Hower JC, Dai S (2020) Occurrence of carbon nanotubes and implication for the siting of elements in selected anthracites. Fuel 263:116740</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fuel.2019.116740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinclair RG, Jones EL, Gerba CP (2009) Viruses in recreational water-borne disease outbreaks: a review. J Appl Microbiol 107(6):1769–1780</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2009.04367.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh PK, Yadav JS, Kumar I, Kumar U, Sharma RK (2022) Carpet industry irrigational sources risk assessment: heavy metal contaminated vegetables and cereal crops in northern India. Toxicol Rep 9:1906–1919</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2022.10.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh PK, Kumar I, Kumar U, Sharma RK (2024) Soil-mustard revitalization via rice husk ash, a promising soil amendment material for sustainable management of heavy metal contamination in tropical ecosystem. J Environ Manag 355:120538</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.120538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh PK, Sharma RK (2021) Wastewater reuse in peri-urban agriculture ecosystem: current scenario, consequences, and control measures. Water Poll Manag Pract, 121-146</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slanetz LW, Bent DF, Bartley CH (1955) Use of the membrane filter technique to enumerate enterococci in water. Public Health Rep 70(1):67</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/4589009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sonbhadra S, Pandey LM (2023) Assessment of microplastics from surface water bodies: challenges and future scopes. Wat Air Soil Poll 234(2):80</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11270-023-06094-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y, Zhang H, Chon CH, Pan X, Li D (2011) Nanoparticle detection by microfluidic resistive pulse sensor with a submicron sensing gate and dual detecting channels-two stage differential amplifier. Sens Actuators B Chem 155(2):930–936</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2011.01.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soni R, Soni M, Shukla DP (2020) Emerging techniques and materials for water pollutants detection. Sens Water Poll Monitor Role Mater, 277-297</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soto DX, Koehler G, Wassenaar LI, Hobson KA (2019) Spatio-temporal variation of nitrate sources to Lake Winnipeg using N and O isotope (δ15N, δ18O) analyses. Sci Total Environ 647:486–493</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.07.346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spellman FR (2017) The drinking water handbook. CRC Press</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1201/9781315159126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Starling MCV, Amorim CC, Leão MMD (2019) Occurrence, control and fate of contaminants of emerging concern in environmental compartments in Brazil. J Hazard Mater 372:17–36</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2018.04.043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sudha V, Kumar SMS, Thangamuthu R (2018) Simultaneous electrochemical sensing of sulphite and nitrite on acid-functionalized multi-walled carbon nanotubes modified electrodes. J Alloys Compounds 749:990–999</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jallcom.2018.03.287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sukanya S, Joseph S (2023) Climate change impacts on water resources: an overview. Visual Techniq Clim Change Mach Learn Artif Intell, 55-76</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun YF, Li PH, Yang M, Huang XJ (2019) Highly sensitive electrochemical detection of Pb (II) based on excellent adsorption and surface Ni (II)/Ni (III) cycle of porous flower-like NiO/rGO nanocomposite. Sens Actuators B Chem 292:136–147</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2019.04.131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutherland KP, Shaban S, Joyner JL, Porter JW, Lipp EK (2011) Human pathogen shown to cause disease in the threatened eklhorn coral Acropora palmata. PloS One 6(8):e23468</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syeed MM, Hossain MS, Karim MR, Uddin MF, Hasan M, Khan RH (2023) Surface water quality profiling using the water quality index, pollution index and statistical methods: A critical review. Environ Sustain Indicat 18:100247</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indic.2023.100247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang S, Lin L, Wang X, Feng A, Yu A (2020) Pb (II) uptake onto nylon microplastics: interaction mechanism and adsorption performance. J Hazard Mater 386:121960</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.121960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tellez-Plaza M, Navas-Acien A, Crainiceanu CM, Guallar E (2008) Cd exposure and hypertension in the 1999–2004 National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES). Environ Health Perspect 116(1):51–56</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.10764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tellez-Plaza M, Jones MR, Dominguez-Lucas A, Guallar E, Navas-Acien A (2013) Cd exposure and clinical cardiovascular disease: a systematic review. Curr Atheroscleros Rep 15:1–15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11883-013-0356-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian X, Liu L, Li Y, Yang C, Zhou Z, Nie Y, Wang Y (2018) Nonenzymatic electrochemical sensor based on CuO-TiO2 for sensitive and selective detection of methyl parathion pesticide in groundwater. Sens Actuators B Chem 256:135–142</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2017.10.066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ting SL, Ee SJ, Ananthanarayanan A, Leong KC, Chen P (2015) Graphene quantum dots functionalized gold nanoparticles for sensitive electrochemical detection of heavy metal ions. Electrochimica Acta 172:7–11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2015.01.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomar S, Shahadat M, Ali SW, Joshi M, Butola BS (2023) Treatment of textile‐wastewater using green technologies. Green Chem Sustain Water Purif, 129-156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tunesi MM, Kalwar N, Abbas MW, Karakus S, Soomro RA, Kilislioglu A, Abro MI, Hallam KR (2018) Functionalised CuO nanostructures for the detection of organoP pesticides: a non-enzymatic inhibition approach coupled with nano-scale electrode engineering to improve electrode sensitivity. Sens Actuators B Chem 260:480–489</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2018.01.084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner AP (2000) Biosensors–sense and sensitivity. Sci 290(5495):1315–1317</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.290.5495.1315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uddin MG, Nash S, Olbert AI (2021) A review of water quality index models and their use for assessing surface water quality. Ecologic Indicat 122:107218</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2020.107218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umapathi R, Park B, Sonwal S, Rani GM, Cho Y, Huh YS (2022) Advances in optical-sensing strategies for the on-site detection of pesticides in agricultural foods. Trends Food Sci Technol 119:69–89</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.11.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umeh CT, Nduka JK, Omokpariola DO, Morah JE, Mmaduakor EC, Okoye NH, Lilian EEI, Kalu IF (2023) Ecological pollution and health risk monitoring assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and heavy metals in surface water, southeastern Nigeria. Environ Anal Health Toxicol 38:e2023007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5620/eaht.2023007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urresti-Estala B, Vadillo-Pérez I, Jiménez-Gavilán P, Soler A, Sánchez-García D, Carrasco-Cantos F (2015) Application of stable isotopes (δ34S-SO4, δ18O-SO4, δ15N-NO3, δ18O-NO3) to determine natural background and contamination sources in the Guadalhorce River Basin (southern Spain). Sci Total Environ 506:46–57</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2014.10.090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA (1992) Guidelines for exposure assessment:125. 57:22888–22938</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA (2002). Development document for the final revisions to the national pollutant discharge elimination system regulation and the effluent guidelines for concentrated animal feeding operations. EPA-821-R-03-001. Washington, DC: USEPA, Office of Water. Available online at: http://cfpub.epa.gov/npdes/afo/aforule.cfm (Accessed December, 2011)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA (2012) Recreational water quality criteria. Health and Ecological Criteria Division OoSaT, 42</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vastila K, Kummu M, Sangmanee C, Chinvanno S (2010) Modelling climate change impacts on the flood pulse in the Lower Mekong floodplains. J Water Clim Change 1(1):67–86</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wcc.2010.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma N, Sharma R, Kumar S (2016) Advancement towards microfluidic approach to develop economical disposable optical biosensor for lead detection. Austin J Biosens Bioelectron 2(2):1021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vikesland PJ (2018) Nanosensors for water quality monitoring. Nat Nanotechnol 13(8):651–660</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41565-018-0209-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vital Siqueira Resck D, Eurípedes Da Silva J, Lopes AS, Marciano Da Costa L (2006) Management systems in northern South America. Dryland Agric, 23:427-525</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vorkamp K (2016) An overlooked environmental issue? A review of the inadvertent formation of PCB-11 and other PCB congeners and their occurrence in consumer products and in the environment. Sci Total Environ 541:1463–1476</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2015.10.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker CLF, Rudan I, Liu L, Nair H, Theodoratou E, Bhutta ZA, O’Brien KL, Campbell H, Black RE (2013) Global burden of childhood pneumonia and diarrhoea. The Lancet 381(9875):1405–1416</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60222-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waller CL et al (2017) Microplastics in the Antarctic marine system: an emerging area of research. Sci Total Environ 598:220e227</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.03.283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walli HA (2015) Determination of PAHs in Surface Water of Al-Dalmaj Marsh, Al-Diwaniya Province, Iraq. J Environ Earth Sci 5(12):67–72</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang JN (2011) A microfluidic long-period fiber grating sensor platform for chloride ion concentration measurement. Sensors 11(9):8550–8568</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s110908550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang A, Holladay SD, Wolf DC, Ahmed SA, Robertson JL (2006) Reproductive and developmental toxicity of As in rodents: a review. Int J Toxicol 25(5):319–331</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10915810600840776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Han T, Jeon TJ, Park S, Kim SM (2013) Rapid detection and quantification of bacteria using an integrated micro/nanofluidic device. Sens Actuators B Chem 178:683–688</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2013.01.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Su Y, Kim H, Yong D, Wang L, Han X (2015) A highly efficient ZrO2 nanoparticle based electrochemical sensor for the detection of organoP pesticides. Chin J Chem 33(10):1135–1139</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cjoc.201500460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Han J, Bi C, Huang X, Jia J, Chen Z (2017) Distribution, sources, and risk assessment of polychlorinated biphenyls in surface waters and sediments of rivers in Shanghai, China. Front Earth Sci 11:283–296</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11707-016-0590-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Li W, Chen S, Li D, Wang D, Liu J (2018) The spatial and temporal variation of total suspended solid concentration in Pearl River Estuary during 1987–2015 based on remote sensing. Sci Total Environ 618:1125–1138</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.09.196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang G, Lu J, Tong Y, Liu Z, Zhou H, Xiayihazi N (2020) Occurrence and pollution characteristics of microplastics in surface water of the Manas River Basin, China. Sci Total Environ 710:136099</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.136099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Shao Z, Yu H, Bah H (2020) Distribution of fluoride in surface water and a health risk assessment in the upper reaches of the Yongding River. J Geographic Sci 30:908–920</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11442-020-1761-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang B, Du Y (2013) Cd and its neurotoxic effects. Oxidative medicine and cellular longevity, 2013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wear SL, Thurber RV (2015) Sewage pollution: mitigation is key for coral reef stewardship. Annals of the New York Acad Sci 1355(1):15–30</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nyas.12785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei M, Wu J, Li W, Zhang Q, Su F, Wang Y (2021) Groundwater geochemistry and its impacts on groundwater As enrichment, variation, and health risks in Yongning County, Yinchuan Plain of northwest China. Expos Health 14:1–20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wetzel RG (2001) Limnology: lake and river ecosystems. gulf professional publishing</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiesner-Sękala M, Kończak B (2023) Assessment of the Impact of Industrial and Municipal Discharges on the Surface Water Body Status (Poland). Sustainability 15(2):997</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su15020997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wijethunga PA, Nanayakkara YS, Kunchala P, Armstrong DW, Moon H (2011) On-chip drop-to-drop liquid microextraction coupled with real-time concentration monitoring technique. Anal Chem 83(5):1658–1664</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac102716s</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams M, Kookana RS, Mehta A, Yadav SK, Tailor BL, Maheshwari B (2019) Emerging contaminants in a river receiving untreated wastewater from an Indian urban centre. Sci Total Environ 647:1256–1265</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.08.084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (2019) Progress on household drinking water, sanitation and hygiene 2000-2017: special focus on inequalities. World Health Organization</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright IA, Paciuszkiewicz K, Belmer N (2018) Increased water pollution after closure of Australia’s longest operating underground coal mine: a 13-month study of mine drainage, water chemistry and river ecology. Water Air Soil Poll 229:1–20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11270-018-3718-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F, Wang Y, Leung JY, Huang W, Zeng J, Tang Y, Chen J, Shi A, Yu X, Xu X, Cao L (2020) Accumulation of microplastics in typical commercial aquatic species: a case study at a productive aquaculture site in China. Sci Total Environ 708:135432</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.135432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Zhou T, Su Y, Fang L, Naidoo AR, Lv P, Lv S, Meng XZ (2023) How anthropogenic factors influence the dissolved oxygen in surface water over three decades in eastern China? J Environ Manag 326:116828</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.116828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue Q, Qi Y, Liu F (2015) Ultra-high performance liquid chromatography-electrospray tandem mass spectrometry for the analysis of antibiotic residues in environmental waters. Environ Sci Poll Res 22:16857–16867</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-015-4900-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav S, Jadeja NB, Dafale NA, Purohit HJ, Kapley A (2019) Pharmaceuticals and personal care products mediated antimicrobial resistance: future challenges. In: Pharmaceuticals and personal care products: waste management and treatment technology. Butterworth-Heinemann, pp 409-428</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamashita T, Ookawa N, Ishida M, Kanamori H, Sasaki H, Katayose Y, Yokoyama H (2016) A novel open-type biosensor for the in-situ monitoring of biochemical oxygen demand in an aerobic environment. Sci Rep 6(1):38552</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep38552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang H (2016) China’s soil plan needs strong support. Nature 536(7617):375–375</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/536375a</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang H, Huang X, Thompson JR, Flower RJ (2015) Enforcement key to China’s environment. Science 347(6224):834–835</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.347.6224.834-d</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang DH, Lee CS, Jeon BH, Choi SM, Kim YD, Shin JS, Kim H (2017) An electrochemical nanofilm sensor for determination of 1-hydroxypyrene using molecularly imprinted receptors. J Ind Eng Chem 51:106–112</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiec.2017.02.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang H, Shen X, Lai L, Huang X, Zhou Y (2017) Spatio-temporal variations of health costs caused by chemical fertilizer utilization in China from 1990 to 2012. Sustainability 9(9):1505</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su9091505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang K, Yu Z, Luo Y, Zhou X, Shang C (2019) Spatial-temporal variation of lake surface water temperature and its driving factors in Yunnan-Guizhou Plateau. Water Res Res 55(6):4688–4703</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1029/2019WR025316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yildirim N, Long F, Gu AZ (2014) Aptamer based E-coli detection in waste waters by portable optical biosensor system. In: 2014 40th Annual Northeast Bioengineering Conference (NEBEC) (pp. 1-3). IEEE</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin Y, Meng F, Sui C, Jiang Y, Zhang L (2019) As enhances cell death and DNA damage induced by ultraviolet B exposure in mouse epidermal cells through the production of reactive oxygen species. Clin Exp Dermatol 44(5):512–519</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ced.13834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yona C, Makange M, Moshiro E, Chengula A, Misinzo G (2023) Water pollution at Lake Natron Ramsar site in Tanzania: a threat to aquatic life. Ecohydrol Hydrobiol 23(1):98–108</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecohyd.2022.11.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshizawa K, Rimm EB, Morris JS, Spate VL, Hsieh CC, Spiegelman D, Stampfer MJ, Willett WC (2002) Hg and the risk of coronary heart disease in men. New England J Med 347(22):1755–1760</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa021437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Y, Yu C, Gao R, Chen J, Zhong H, Wen Y, Ji X, Wu J, He J (2019) Dandelion-like CuO microspheres decorated with Au nanoparticle modified biosensor for Hg2+ detection using a T-Hg2+-T triggered hybridization chain reaction amplification strategy. Biosens Bioelectr 131:207–213</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2019.01.063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan W, Liu X, Wang W, Di M, Wang J (2019) Microplastic abundance, distribution and composition in water, sediments, and wild fish from Poyang Lake, China. Ecotoxicol Environ Safe 170:180–187</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.11.126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue FJ, Liu CQ, Li SL, Zhao ZQ, Liu XL, Ding H, Liu BJ, Zhong J (2014) Analysis of δ15N and δ18O to identify nitrate sources and transformations in Songhua River, Northeast China. J Hydrol 519:329–339</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2014.07.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue Y, Jiang L, Li Z, Yuan J, Shi H, Feng S (2019) A glassy carbon electrode modified with a monolayer of zirconium (IV) phosphonate for sensing of methyl-parathion by square wave voltammetry. Microchimica Acta 186:1–10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00604-019-3493-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yumoto T, Tsukahara K, Naito H, Iida A, Nakao A (2017) A successfully treated case of criminal thallium poisoning. J Clin Diagn Res JCDR 11(4):OD01</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zalups RK (2000) Evidence for basolateral uptake of Cd in the kidneys of rats. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol 164(1):15–23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1006/taap.1999.8854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zefferino R, Piccoli C, Ricciardi N, Scrima R, Capitanio N (2017) Possible mechanisms of Hg toxicity and cancer promotion: involvement of gap junction intercellular communications and inflammatory cytokines. Oxid Med Cell Long 2017:7028583</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2017/7028583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang K, Shi H, Peng J, Wang Y, Xiong X, Wu C, Lam PK (2018) Microplastic pollution in China’s inland water systems: a review of findings, methods, characteristics, effects, and management. Sci Total Environ 630:1641–1653</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.02.300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Shi P, Li F, Wei A, Song J, Ma J (2018) Quantification of nitrate sources and fates in rivers in an irrigated agricultural area using environmental isotopes and a Bayesian isotope mixing model. Chemosphere 208:493–501</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.05.164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Liu S, Tan X, Liu Y, Zeng G, Yin Z, Ye S, Zeng Z (2019) Microwave-assisted chemical modification method for surface regulation of biochar and its application for estrogen removal. Process Safe Environ Protect 128:329–341</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psep.2019.06.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Kang S, Allen S, Allen D, Gao T, Sillanpää M (2020) Atmospheric microplastics: a review on current status and perspectives. Earth-Sci Rev 203:103118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.earscirev.2020.103118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang ZM, Zhang F, Du JL, Chen DC (2022) Surface water quality assessment and contamination source identification using multivariate statistical techniques: a case study of the Nanxi River in the Taihu Watershed, China. Water 14(5):778</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/w14050778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Guo Y, Wu J, Su F (2022) Surface water quality and health risk assessment in Taizhou City Zhejiang Province (China). Expos Health 14:1–16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12403-021-00408-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhaoyong Z, Abuduwaili J, Fengqing J (2015) Heavy metal contamination, sources, and pollution assessment of surface water in the Tianshan Mountains of China. Environ Monitor Assess 187:1–13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-014-4191-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng X, Li H, Xia F, Tian D, Hua X, Qiao X, Zhou C (2016) An electrochemical sensor for ultrasensitive determination the polychlorinated biphenyls. Electrochimica Acta 194:413–421</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.electacta.2016.02.115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou T, Wang Q, Umar A, Xu F, Gao Y, Wu J, Guo Z (2015) Electrochemical sensors based on semiconductor nanostructures modified electrodes. Sci Adv Mater 7(10):2069–2083</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1166/sam.2015.2437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>