<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39269951</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessing the cost barrier for small and medium food processing businesses to meet Preventive Controls for Human Foods standards.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0306618</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0306618</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0306618</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0306618</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The Preventive Controls for Human Food Rule regulation under the Food Safety Modernization Act sets new food safety standards. Both food safety educators and small and medium sized food processing businesses that manufacture certain value-added or processed foods lack knowledge regarding costs to prepare, implement, and manage ongoing food safety practices under the new standards. Current food safety training materials do not acknowledge costs or provide content addressing potential costs, and food safety educators do not have information needed to guide development of relevant materials that address costs. We combine economics and food science principles and use mixed methods to identify and estimate cost barriers for food processing businesses through an interdisciplinary research and extension project in the Northeast U.S. We first modify Preventive Controls extension programming to acknowledge costs and test how modified programming improves self-reported knowledge about costs. Materials that acknowledge that costs are associated with meeting standards significantly increases participants' self-reported perceived knowledge of costs by 1.3 points on a 1-to-5-point Likert scale. Compared with programming areas in which detailed content is provided, however, improvements in knowledge of costs lags behind overall knowledge gains (3.2 for costs versus 4.1 for food safety content). To fill this content gap, we next conduct semi-structured group interviews with a subset of participants (N = 10), develop a costs analysis framework, and measure actual costs associated with Preventive Controls. We find that initial costs average $20,000 per business to plan, implement, and manage standards, and almost $8,000 in every subsequent year to manage. We demonstrate that even modest interventions can reduce cost barriers for businesses seeking to meet compliance standards. We provide food safety educators with concrete cost information to support businesses to pursue Preventive Controls standards. Study results imply that low-cost methods could improve food safety in mid-scale supply chains.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Fitzsimmons et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fitzsimmons</LastName><ForeName>Jill Ann</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1193-8814</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Resource Economics, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kinchla</LastName><ForeName>Amanda J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6500-3689</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Allingham</LastName><ForeName>Christina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7786-6705</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059022" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Safety</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005511" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Handling</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000191" MajorTopicYN="N">economics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000592" MajorTopicYN="N">standards</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003365" MajorTopicYN="N">Costs and Cost Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39269951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11398691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0306618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-23-18148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Oldfield MT. Enactment of the Food Safety Modernization Act: The US FDA within the Context of Interacting Public-Private Governance Processes. European Journal of Risk Regulation. 2015;6(4):488–501. doi: 10.1017/S1867299X00005055</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1867299X00005055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Food and Drug Administration. FSMA Final Rule for Preventive Controls for Human Food | US Food and Drug Administration; 2022. Available from: https://www.fda.gov/food/food-safety-modernization-act-fsma/fsma-final-rule-preventive-controls-human-food.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Food and Drug Administration. FSMA Compliance Dates | US Food and Drug Administration; 2020. Available from: https://www.fda.gov/food/food-safety-modernization-act-fsma/fsma-compliance-dates.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Food and Drug Administration. Qualified Facility Attestation | US Food and Drug Administration; 2022. Available from: https://www.fda.gov/food/registration-food-facilities-and-other-submissions/qualified-facility-attestation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Food and Drug Administration. CFR—Code of Federal Regulations Title 21 | US Food and Drug Administration; Updated 2023. Available from: https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cdrh/cfdocs/cfCFR/CFRSearch.cfm?CFRPart=1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Food and Drug Administration. Webpage. [2022] Available from: https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/small-entity-compliance-guide-what-you-need-know-about-current-good-manufacturing-practice-hazard.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baron P, Baron BR. A Regulatory Compliance Model. In: Bellur VV, editor. Marketing Horizons: A 1980’s Perspective. Developments in Marketing Science: Proceedings of the Academy of Marketing Science. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2015. p. 288–292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henson S, Heasman M. Food safety regulation and the firm: understanding the compliance process1Financial support from the Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food (MAFF) is acknowledged. However, the views expressed in this paper reflect those of the author and not necessarily those of MAFF.1. Food Policy. 1998;23(1):9–23. doi: 10.1016/S0306-9192(98)00015-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0306-9192(98)00015-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mensah LD, Julien D. Implementation of food safety management systems in the UK. Food Control. 2011;22(8):1216–1225. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2011.01.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2011.01.021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yapp C, Fairman R. Factors affecting food safety compliance within small and medium-sized enterprises: implications for regulatory and enforcement strategies. Food Control. 2006;17(1):42–51. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2004.08.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2004.08.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grover AK, Chopra S, Mosher GA. Food safety modernization act: A quality management approach to identify and prioritize factors affecting adoption of preventive controls among small food facilities. Food Control. 2016;66:241–249. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.02.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.02.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barone NA, DiCaprio E, Snyder AB. A preliminary assessment of food safety training needs and preferences among Ohio food processors of various sizes. Food Control. 2020;114:107220. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107220</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzgerald A, Gilbert-Eckman A, Demmings E, Fitzsimmons JA, LaBorde L, Kinchla A, et al.. Understanding the Food Safety Needs of Small and Very Small Processors in the Northeast United States: Food Safety Communicator and Regulator Perspectives Food Protection Trends. Food Protection Trends. 2024; Forthcoming. doi: 10.4315/FPT-23-028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/FPT-23-028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bass G. Keynote presentation. [2021] Available from: https://www.ifsh.iit.edu/sites/ifsh/files/departments/fspca/pdfs/2021-FSPCA-Virtual-AC-Information-Packet-and-Agenda_2021-10-19.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henson S, Caswell J. Food safety regulation: an overview of contemporary issues. Food Policy. 1999;24(6):589–603. doi: 10.1016/S0306-9192(99)00072-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0306-9192(99)00072-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FSPCA Preventive Controls for Human Food | Food Safety Preventive Controls Alliance (FSPCA) | Institute for Food Safety and Health (IFSH) | Illinois Institute of Technology;. Available from: https://www.ifsh.iit.edu/fspca/fspca-preventive-controls-human-food.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adalja A, Lichtenberg E. Implementation challenges of the food safety modernization act: Evidence from a national survey of produce growers. Food Control. 2018;89:62–71. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.01.024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.01.024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmit TM, Wall GL, Newbold EJ, Bihn EA. Assessing the costs and returns of on-farm food safety improvements: A survey of Good Agricultural Practices (GAPs) training participants. PLOS ONE. 2020;15(7):e0235507. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0235507</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0235507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7332080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32614870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baron P, Frattaroli S. Awareness and Perceptions of Food Safety Risks and Risk Management in Poultry Production and Slaughter: A Qualitative Study of Direct-Market Poultry Producers in Maryland. PLOS ONE. 2016;11(6):e0158412. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0158412</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4920352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27341034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A, Sainsbury P, Craig J. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): a 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. International Journal for Quality in Health Care. 2007;19(6):349–357. doi: 10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanin LM, Stedefeldt E, Luning PA. The evolvement of food safety culture assessment: A mixed-methods systematic review. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology. 2021;118:125–142. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2021.08.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.08.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jespersen L, Griffiths M, Maclaurin T, Chapman B, Wallace CA. Measurement of food safety culture using survey and maturity profiling tools. Food Control. 2016;66:174–182. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.01.030</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.01.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanin LM, Luning PA, da Cunha DT, Stedefeldt E. Influence of educational actions on transitioning of food safety culture in a food service context: Part 1—Triangulation and data interpretation of food safety culture elements. Food Control. 2021;119:107447. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107447</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison JA, Critzer FJ, Harrison MA. Regulatory and Food Safety Knowledge Gaps Associated with Small and Very Small Food Businesses as Identified by Regulators and Food Safety Educators — Implications for Food Safety Training; 2016. Available from: https://www.foodprotection.org/files/food-protection-trends/nov-dec-16-harrison.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKean RN. Enforcement Costs in Environmental and Safety Regulation. Policy Analysis. 1980;6(3):269–289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapelko M, Lansink AO, Stefanou SE. Effect of Food Regulation on the Spanish Food Processing Industry: A Dynamic Productivity Analysis. PLOS ONE. 2015;10(6):e0128217. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0128217</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4461303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26057878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann S, Ashton L, Ahn J. Food safety: A policy history and introduction to avenues for economic research. Applied Economic Perspectives and Policy. 2021;43(2):680–700. doi: 10.1002/aepp.13158</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/aepp.13158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzsimmons JA, Lass D, Minifie K, Kinchla AJ. Financial feasibility of selling frozen produce in local and regional markets. Renewable Agriculture and Food Systems. 2023;38:e29. doi: 10.1017/S1742170523000236</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1742170523000236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Marketing Services. USDA Regional Food Business Centers Program. [2023] Available from: https://www.ams.usda.gov/services/local-regional/rfbcp.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henney J, Diez-Gonzalez F, Jones J, Kowalcyk B, Kumanyika S, Taylor J. Human foods program independent expert panel final report. Reagan Udall Foundation; 2022. Available from: https://reaganudall.org/sites/default/files/2022-12/Human%20Foods%20Program%20Independent%20Expert%20Panel%20Final%20Report%20120622.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahn JW, Rhodes MT. Examining Pathogen-Based Import Refusals: Trends and Analysis From 2002 to 2019. United States Department of Agriculture, Economic Research Service; 2021. EIB-232. Available from: https://ers.usda.gov/webdocs/publications/102878/eib-232.pdf?v=9998.6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceballos LA, Vercellino D, D’Errico V, Barzanti P, Decastelli L, Nicolandi L, et al.. Hazard perception and possibility of simplifying food safety management systems in small businesses in Piedmont region, Italy. Italian Journal of Food Safety. 2020;9(1):8273. doi: 10.4081/ijfs.2020.8273</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/ijfs.2020.8273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7154610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32300560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Njage PMK, Opiyo B, Wangoh J, Wambui J. Scale of production and implementation of food safety programs influence the performance of current food safety management systems: Case of dairy processors. Food Control. 2018;85:85–97. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.09.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.09.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzsimmons J, Fitzgerald A, Newbold E, Kinchla A. Identifying a Strategic Path to Engage Qualified Exempt Processors to Comply with Preventive Controls. Available upon request.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>