<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39267152</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Electrospinning-based sensing technologies: Opportunities for food applications.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13415</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13415</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.13415</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The article explores the science and practice of electrospinning, tracing its history and examining the factors that influence fiber morphology, including the solution composition, processing conditions, and environmental conditions. It offers a thorough examination of electrospinning fundamentals geared toward generating an appropriate platform for creating tailored nanofibers for sensing applications in the food industry. These nanofibers play a critical role in food analysis, sensing, and traceability, and we highlight their effectiveness in identifying pesticide residues, food components, antibiotics, heavy metals, and foodborne pathogens as well as in monitoring the freshness and spoilage of food. The use of electrospinning technology is poised to make sensing platforms more accessible, affordable, and widespread, thereby significantly contributing to the improvement of food quality and safety monitoring practices.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Matinfar</LastName><ForeName>Golshan</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food, Nutrition, and Health, Faculty of Land &amp; Food Systems, The University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ye</LastName><ForeName>Haoxin</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5964-3762</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food, Nutrition, and Health, Faculty of Land &amp; Food Systems, The University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bashiry</LastName><ForeName>Moein</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, School of Nutrition Sciences and Food Technology, Research Center for Environmental Determinants of Health (RCEDH), Health Institute, Kermanshah University of Medical Sciences, Kermanshah, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hashami</LastName><ForeName>Zahra</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, National Nutrition and Food Technology Research Institute, Faculty of Nutrition Science and Food Technology, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Tianxi</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4197-9262</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food, Nutrition, and Health, Faculty of Land &amp; Food Systems, The University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>The University of British Columbia</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057139" MajorTopicYN="Y">Nanofibers</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005504" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Analysis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">electrospinning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">electrospun nanofibers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sensing technologies</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39267152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.13415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abedalwafa, M. A., Tang, Z., Qiao, Y., Mei, Q., Yang, G., Li, Y., &amp; Wang, L. (2020). An aptasensor strip‐based colorimetric determination method for kanamycin using cellulose acetate nanofibers decorated DNA–gold nanoparticle bioconjugates. Microchimica Acta, 187(6), Article 360. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00604‐020‐04348‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelgawad, A. M., Hudson, S. M., &amp; Rojas, O. J. (2014). Antimicrobial wound dressing nanofiber mats from multicomponent (chitosan/silver‐NPs/polyvinyl alcohol) systems. Carbohydrate Polymers, 100, 166–178. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.12.043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal, S., Burgard, M., Greiner, A., &amp; Wendorff, J. (2016). Electrospinning: A practical guide to nanofibers. Walter de Gruyter GmbH &amp; Co KG.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal, S., Greiner, A., &amp; Wendorff, J. H. (2013). Functional materials by electrospinning of polymers. Progress in Polymer Science, 38(6), 963–991. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.progpolymsci.2013.02.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi, F., Shahsavari, A. A., &amp; Rahimi‐Nasrabadi, M. (2008). Automated extraction and preconcentration of multiresidue of pesticides on a micro‐solid‐phase extraction system based on polypyrrole as sorbent and off‐line monitoring by gas chromatography–flame ionization detection. Journal of Chromatography A, 1193(1), 26–31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2008.04.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altman, G. H., Diaz, F., Jakuba, C., Calabro, T., Horan, R. L., Chen, J., Lu, H., Richmond, J., &amp; Kaplan, D. L. (2003). Silk‐based biomaterials. Biomaterials, 24(3), 401–416. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0142‐9612(02)00353‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aman Mohammadi, M., Hosseini, S. M., &amp; Yousefi, M. (2020). Application of electrospinning technique in development of intelligent food packaging: A short review of recent trends. Food Science &amp; Nutrition, 8(9), 4656–4665.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amini, S., Kandeh, S. H., Ebrahimzadeh, H., &amp; Khodayari, P. (2023). Electrospun composite nanofibers modified with silver nanoparticles for extraction of trace heavy metals from water and rice samples: An highly efficient and reproducible sorbent. Food Chemistry, 420, Article 136122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amna, T., Hassan, M. S., Yousef, A., Mishra, A., Barakat, N. A. M., Khil, M.‐S., &amp; Kim, H. Y. (2013). Inactivation of foodborne pathogens by NiO/TiO2 composite nanofibers: A novel biomaterial system. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 6(4), 988–996. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐011‐0741‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayi, A. A., Ashishie, P. B., Khansi, E. E., Ogar, J. O., Anyama, C. A., &amp; Inah, B. E. (2020). Nano/micro‐structured materials: Synthesis, morphology and applications. In M. S. A. Sadia Ameen &amp; S. Hyung‐Shik (Eds.), Nanostructures. IntechOpen. https://doi.org/10.5772/intechopen.85698</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battilani, P., Toscano, P., Van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., Moretti, A., Camardo Leggieri, M., Brera, C., Rortais, A., Goumperis, T., &amp; Robinson, T. (2016). Aflatoxin B1 contamination in maize in Europe increases due to climate change. Scientific Reports, 6(1), Article 24328. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep24328</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumgarten, P. K. (1971). Electrostatic spinning of acrylic microfibers. Journal of Colloid and Interface Science, 36(1), 71–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhardwaj, N., &amp; Kundu, S. C. (2010). Electrospinning: A fascinating fiber fabrication technique. Biotechnology Advances, 28(3), 325–347.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauhan, R., Singh, J., Sachdev, T., Basu, T., &amp; Malhotra, B. D. (2016). Recent advances in mycotoxins detection. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 81, 532–545. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bios.2016.03.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, S. Y., Harrison, M., Ng, E. K., Sauvageau, D., &amp; Elias, A. (2021). Immobilized reporter phage on electrospun polymer fibers for improved capture and detection of Escherichia coli O157:H7. ACS Food Science &amp; Technology, 1(6), 1085–1094. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsfoodscitech.1c00101</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunha, S. C., Fernandes, J. O., Beatriz, M., &amp; Oliveira, P. P. (2007). Determination of phosmet and its metabolites in olives by matrix solid‐phase dispersion and gas chromatography–mass spectrometry. Talanta, 73(3), 514–522. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2007.04.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira Filho, J. G., Braga, A. R. C., Oliveira, B. R. d., Gomes, F. P., Moreira, V. L., Pereira, V. A. C., &amp; Egea, M. B. (2021). The potential of anthocyanins in smart, active, and bioactive eco‐friendly polymer‐based films: A review. Food Research International, 142, Article 110202. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110202</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doshi, J., &amp; Reneker, D. H. (1995). Electrospinning process and applications of electrospun fibers. Journal of Electrostatics, 35(2–3), 151–160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>dos Santos, D. M., Migliorini, F. L., Soares, A. C., Mattoso, L. H. C., Oliveira, O. N., Jr., &amp; Correa, D. S. (2023). Electrochemical immunosensor made with zein‐based nanofibers for on‐site detection of aflatoxin B1. Electroanalysis, 35(1), Article e202100672. https://doi.org/10.1002/elan.202100672</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan, M., Yu, S., Sun, J., Jiang, H., Zhao, J., Tong, C., Hu, Y., Pang, J., &amp; Wu, C. (2021). Development and characterization of electrospun nanofibers based on pullulan/chitin nanofibers containing curcumin and anthocyanins for active‐intelligent food packaging. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 187, 332–340. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.07.140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El‐Aassar, M. R., Hashem, F. S., Elzain, A. A., Ali, A. S. M., &amp; Mohamed, F. M. (2021). Reduction of non‐point source pollution by poly(styrene‐co‐acrylonitrile) composites nanofibers inoculated with sorbent materials. International Journal of Environmental Science and Technology, 18, 3071–3082.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El‐Moghazy, A. Y., Soliman, E. A., Ibrahim, H. Z., Marty, J.‐L., Istamboulie, G., &amp; Noguer, T. (2016). Biosensor based on electrospun blended chitosan‐poly (vinyl alcohol) nanofibrous enzymatically sensitized membranes for pirimiphos‐methyl detection in olive oil. Talanta, 155, 258–264. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2016.04.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, K., Zhai, M.‐Y., Wei, Y.‐S., Zong, M.‐H., Wu, H., &amp; Han, S.‐Y. (2021). Fabrication of nano/micro‐structured electrospun detection card for the detection of pesticide residues. Foods, 10(4), Article 889. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10040889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frenot, A., &amp; Chronakis, I. S. (2003). Polymer nanofibers assembled by electrospinning. Current Opinion in Colloid &amp; Interface Science, 8(1), 64–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, R., Hu, H., Shi, T., Bao, Y., Sun, Q., Wang, L., Ren, Y., Jin, W., &amp; Yuan, L. (2022). Incorporation of gelatin and Fe2+ increases the pH‐sensitivity of zein‐anthocyanin complex films used for milk spoilage detection. Current Research in Food Science, 5, 677–686. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.crfs.2022.03.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghorani, B., &amp; Tucker, N. (2015). Fundamentals of electrospinning as a novel delivery vehicle for bioactive compounds in food nanotechnology. Food Hydrocolloids, 51, 227–240. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2015.05.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golichenari, B., Nosrati, R., Farokhi‐Fard, A., Abnous, K., Vaziri, F., &amp; Behravan, J. (2018). Nano‐biosensing approaches on tuberculosis: Defy of aptamers. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 117, 319–331. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bios.2018.06.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ha, C. T., Lien, N. T. H., Anh, N. D., &amp; Lam, N. L. (2017). Development of natural anthocyanin dye‐doped silica nanoparticles for pH and borate‐sensing applications. Journal of Electronic Materials, 46(12), 6843–6847. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11664‐017‐5743‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haider, A., Haider, S., &amp; Kang, I.‐K. (2018). A comprehensive review summarizing the effect of electrospinning parameters and potential applications of nanofibers in biomedical and biotechnology. Arabian Journal of Chemistry, 11(8), 1165–1188. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.arabjc.2015.11.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hajikhani, M., Emam‐Djomeh, Z., &amp; Askari, G. (2021). Fabrication and characterization of mucoadhesive bioplastic patch via coaxial polylactic acid (PLA) based electrospun nanofibers with antimicrobial and wound healing application. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 172, 143–153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hajikhani, M., &amp; Lin, M. (2022). A review on designing nanofibers with high porous and rough surface via electrospinning technology for rapid detection of food quality and safety attributes. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 128, 118–128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong, J., Su, M., Zhao, K., Zhou, Y., Wang, J., Zhou, S.‐F., &amp; Lin, X. (2023). A minireview for recent development of nanomaterial‐based detection of antibiotics. Biosensors, 13(3), Article 327.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, X., Liu, S., Zhou, G., Huang, Y., Xie, Z., &amp; Jing, X. (2014). Electrospinning of polymeric nanofibers for drug delivery applications. Journal of Controlled Release, 185, 12–21. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jconrel.2014.04.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Z.‐M., Zhang, Y.‐Z., Kotaki, M., &amp; Ramakrishna, S. (2003). A review on polymer nanofibers by electrospinning and their applications in nanocomposites. Composites Science and Technology, 63(15), 2223–2253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson, S. L., Spence, J., Janssen, D. J., Ross, A. R. S., &amp; Cullen, J. T. (2018). Determination of Mn, Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn, Cd and Pb in seawater using offline extraction and triple quadrupole ICP‐MS/MS. Journal of Analytical Atomic Spectrometry, 33(2), 304–313. https://doi.org/10.1039/C7JA00237H</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jovanska, L., Chiu, C.‐H., Yeh, Y.‐C., Chiang, W.‐D., Hsieh, C.‐C., &amp; Wang, R. R. W. (2022). Development of a PCL‐PEO double network colorimetric pH sensor using electrospun fibers containing Hibiscus rosa sinensis extract and silver nanoparticles for food monitoring. Food Chemistry, 368, Article 130813.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kachwal, V., &amp; Tan, J. (2023). Stimuli‐responsive electrospun fluorescent fibers augmented with aggregation‐induced emission (AIE) for smart applications. Advanced Science, 10(1), Article 2204848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerry, J. P., O'Grady, M. N., &amp; Hogan, S. A. (2006). Past, current and potential utilisation of active and intelligent packaging systems for meat and muscle‐based products: A review. Meat Science, 74(1), 113–130. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2006.04.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, W. S., Asmatulu, R., Ceylan, M., &amp; Jabbarnia, A. (2013). Recent progress on conventional and non‐conventional electrospinning processes. Fibers and Polymers, 14, 1235–1247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, K. S., Dahms, H.‐U., Won, E.‐J., Lee, J.‐S., &amp; Shin, K.‐H. (2015). Microalgae—A promising tool for heavy metal remediation. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 113, 329–352. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2014.12.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, T. S. M., Kumar, K. S., Rajini, N., Siengchin, S., Ayrilmis, N., &amp; Rajulu, A. V. (2019). A comprehensive review of electrospun nanofibers: Food and packaging perspective. Composites Part B: Engineering, 175, Article 107074.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, J. K. Y., Chen, N., Peng, S., Li, L., Tian, L., Thakor, N., &amp; Ramakrishna, S. (2018). Polymer‐based composites by electrospinning: Preparation &amp; functionalization with nanocarbons. Progress in Polymer Science, 86, 40–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, T., Wang, D., Ren, L., Mei, J., Xu, Y., &amp; Li, J. (2021). Preparation of pH‐sensitive polylactic acid‐naringin coaxial electrospun fiber membranes for maintaining and monitoring salmon freshness. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 188, 708–718. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.08.087</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, W., Jiang, H.‐X., Geng, Y., Wang, X.‐H., Gao, R.‐Z., Tang, A.‐N., &amp; Kong, D.‐M. (2020). Facile removal of phytochromes and efficient recovery of pesticides using heteropore covalent organic framework‐based magnetic nanospheres and electrospun films. ACS Applied Materials &amp; Interfaces, 12(18), 20922–20932. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsami.0c01608</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Wen, Y., Wang, L., He, J., Al‐Deyab, S. S., El‐Newehy, M., Yu, J., &amp; Ding, B. (2015). Simultaneous visual detection and removal of lead (II) ions with pyromellitic dianhydride‐grafted cellulose nanofibrous membranes. Journal of Materials Chemistry A, 3(35), 18180–18189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, C., Loh, S., Stride, E., &amp; Edirisinghe, M. (2012). Electrospraying and electrospinning of chocolate suspensions. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 5, 2285–2300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, X., Guo, Z., He, P., Chen, T., Li, L., Ding, S., &amp; Li, H. (2018). Study on structure, mechanical property and cell cytocompatibility of electrospun collagen nanofibers crosslinked by common agents. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 113, 476–486.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, X., &amp; Lim, L.‐T. (2020). Curcumin‐loaded electrospun nonwoven as a colorimetric indicator for volatile amines. LWT ‐ Food Science and Technology, 128, Article 109493. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109493</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, Y., Nartker, S., Wiederoder, M., Miller, H., Hochhalter, D., Drzal, L. T., &amp; Alocilja, E. C. (2012). Novel biosensor based on electrospun nanofiber and magnetic nanoparticles for the detection of E. coli O157:H7. IEEE Transactions on Nanotechnology, 11(4), 676–681. https://doi.org/10.1109/TNANO.2011.2174801</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchese, S., Polo, A., Ariano, A., Velotto, S., Costantini, S., &amp; Severino, L. (2018). Aflatoxin B1 and M1: Biological properties and their involvement in cancer development. Toxins, 10(6), Article 214. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins10060214</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrani, Z., Ebrahimzadeh, H., Asgharinezhad, A. A., &amp; Moradi, E. (2019). Determination of copper in food and water sources using poly m‐phenylenediamine/CNT electrospun nanofiber. Microchemical Journal, 149, Article 103975. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.microc.2019.103975</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercante, L. A., Scagion, V. P., Migliorini, F. L., Mattoso, L. H., &amp; Correa, D. S. (2017). Electrospinning‐based (bio) sensors for food and agricultural applications: A review. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 91, 91–103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mo, W. Y., Chen, Z., Leung, H. M., &amp; Leung, A. O. W. (2017). Application of veterinary antibiotics in China's aquaculture industry and their potential human health risks. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 24(10), 8978–8989. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356‐015‐5607‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadi, S., Pooshang Bagheri, K., Mousavi Nadushan, R., &amp; Adabi, M. (2023). Nanoarchitectonics of electrochemical aptasensor based on electrospun carbon nanofibers and gold nanoparticles for tetracycline detection in chicken ham. Applied Physics A, 129(3), Article 176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadi, Z., &amp; Jafari, S. M. (2020). Detection of food spoilage and adulteration by novel nanomaterial‐based sensors. Advances in Colloid and Interface Science, 286, Article 102297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moradi, M., Tajik, H., Almasi, H., Forough, M., &amp; Ezati, P. (2019). A novel pH‐sensing indicator based on bacterial cellulose nanofibers and black carrot anthocyanins for monitoring fish freshness. Carbohydrate Polymers, 222, Article 115030. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2019.115030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moradi, S., Azizi‐Lalabadi, M., Bagheri, V., &amp; Sadeghi, E. (2020). Fabrication of electrospun sensor based on a synthesized component doped into PAN (polyacrylonitrile) nanofibers for electrochemical detection of zearalenone mycotoxin in foods simulant. Sensing and Bio‐Sensing Research, 28, Article 100321. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbsr.2020.100321</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myndrul, V., Coy, E., Bechelany, M., &amp; Iatsunskyi, I. (2021). Photoluminescence label‐free immunosensor for the detection of aflatoxin B1 using polyacrylonitrile/zinc oxide nanofibers. Materials Science and Engineering: C, 118, Article 111401. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.msec.2020.111401</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nath, V. A., Raja, V., Leena, M. M., Moses, J. A., &amp; Anandharamakrishnan, C. (2022). Co‐electrospun‐electrosprayed ethyl cellulose‐gelatin nanocomposite pH‐sensitive membrane for food quality applications. Food Chemistry, 394, Article 133420. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.133420</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicolini, A. M., Fronczek, C. F., &amp; Yoon, J.‐Y. (2015). Droplet‐based immunoassay on a ‘sticky’ nanofibrous surface for multiplexed and dual detection of bacteria using smartphones. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 67, 560–569. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bios.2014.09.040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Rourke, R. (2005). European Food Law. Sweet &amp; Maxwell. https://books.google.ca/books?id=fhJtDSVwMBQC</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey, V. K., Upadhyay, S. N., Niranjan, K., &amp; Mishra, P. K. (2020). Antimicrobial biodegradable chitosan‐based composite nano‐layers for food packaging. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 157, 212–219. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.04.149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popovtzer, R., Neufeld, T., Rishpon, J., &amp; Shacham‐Diamand, Y. (2006). Electrochemical detection of biological reactions using a novel nano‐bio‐chip array. Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical, 119(2), 664–672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy, K. E., Lee, W., Jeong, J. y., Lee, Y., Lee, H.‐J., Kim, M. S., Kim, D.‐W., Yu, D., Cho, A., Oh, Y. K., &amp; Lee, S. D. (2017). Effects of deoxynivalenol‐ and zearalenone‐contaminated feed on the gene expression profiles in the kidneys of piglets. Asian‐Australasian Journal of Animal Sciences, 31(1), 138–148. https://doi.org/10.5713/ajas.17.0454</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reneker, D. H., Yarin, A. L., Fong, H., &amp; Koombhongse, S. (2000). Bending instability of electrically charged liquid jets of polymer solutions in electrospinning. Journal of Applied Physics, 87(9), 4531–4547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaei, A., Nasirpour, A., &amp; Fathi, M. (2015). Application of cellulosic nanofibers in food science using electrospinning and its potential risk. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 14(3), 269–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, D. M. dos, Migliorini, F. L., Soares, A. C., Mattoso, L. H. C., Oliveira, O. N., &amp; Correa, D. (2022). Electrochemical immunosensor made with zein‐based nanofibers for on‐site detection of Aflatoxin B1. Electroanalysis. https://doi.org/10.1002/elan.202100672</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sannino, F., Ruocco, S., Marocco, A., Esposito, S., &amp; Pansini, M. (2013). Simazine removal from waters by adsorption on porous silicas tailored by sol–gel technique. Microporous and Mesoporous Materials, 180, 178–186. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micromeso.2013.06.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schek, R. M., Taboas, J. M., Segvich, S. J., Hollister, S. J., &amp; Krebsbach, P. H. (2004). Engineered osteochondral grafts using biphasic composite solid free‐form fabricated scaffolds. Tissue Engineering, 10(9–10), 1376–1385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaibani, P. M., Jiang, K., Haghighat, G., Hassanpourfard, M., Etayash, H., Naicker, S., &amp; Thundat, T. (2016). The detection of Escherichia coli (E. coli) with the pH sensitive hydrogel nanofiber‐light addressable potentiometric sensor (NF‐LAPS). Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical, 226, 176–183. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.snb.2015.11.135</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, M., Singh, J., Hazra, S., &amp; Basu, S. (2019). Adsorption of heavy metal ions by mesoporous ZnO and TiO2@ZnO monoliths: Adsorption and kinetic studies. Microchemical Journal, 145, 105–112. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.microc.2018.10.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, P. C., Goyal, R., Sharma, A., Sharma, D., Saini, N., Rajak, H., Sharma, S., &amp; Thakur, V. K. (2020). Insights on fluoroquinolones in cancer therapy: Chemistry and recent developments. Materials Today Chemistry, 17, Article 100296. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mtchem.2020.100296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sill, T. J., &amp; Von Recum, H. A. (2008). Electrospinning: Applications in drug delivery and tissue engineering. Biomaterials, 29(13), 1989–2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spasova, M., Mincheva, R., Paneva, D., Manolova, N., &amp; Rashkov, I. (2006). Perspectives on: Criteria for complex evaluation of the morphology and alignment of electrospun polymer nanofibers. Journal of Bioactive and Compatible Polymers, 21(5), 465–479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanić, Z. (2017). Curcumin, a compound from natural sources, a true scientific challenge—A review. Plant Foods for Human Nutrition, 72(1), 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11130‐016‐0590‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subrahmanya, T., Arshad, A. B., Lin, P. T., Widakdo, J., Makari, H., Austria, H. F. M., Hu, C.‐C., Lai, J.‐Y., &amp; Hung, W.‐S. (2021). A review of recent progress in polymeric electrospun nanofiber membranes in addressing safe water global issues. RSC Advances, 11(16), 9638–9663.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Z., Lu, J., Zhang, X., Shan, X., Wu, Q., Li, C., Li, H., Yang, S., &amp; Tian, L. (2023). Electrospun nanofibres containing Zn‐MOF for electrochemiluminescent determination of fenpropathrin residues in fruit juices. Food Chemistry, 405, Article 134950. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.134950</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szewczyk, P. K., &amp; Stachewicz, U. (2020). The impact of relative humidity on electrospun polymer fibers: From structural changes to fiber morphology. Advances in Colloid and Interface Science, 286, Article 102315. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cis.2020.102315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teodoro, K. B. R., Shimizu, F. M., Scagion, V. P., &amp; Correa, D. S. (2019). Ternary nanocomposites based on cellulose nanowhiskers, silver nanoparticles and electrospun nanofibers: Use in an electronic tongue for heavy metal detection. Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical, 290, 387–395. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.snb.2019.03.125</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thenmozhi, S., Dharmaraj, N., Kadirvelu, K., &amp; Kim, H. Y. (2017). Electrospun nanofibers: New generation materials for advanced applications. Materials Science and Engineering: B, 217, 36–48. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mseb.2017.01.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thenrajan, T., Selvasundarasekar, S. S., Kundu, S., &amp; Wilson, J. (2022). Novel electrochemical sensing of catechins in raw green tea extract via a trimetallic zeolitic imidazolate fibrous framework. ACS Omega, 7(23), 19754–19763. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.2c01536</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres‐Giner, S., Ocio, M. J., &amp; Lagaron, J. M. (2009). Novel antimicrobial ultrathin structures of zein/chitosan blends obtained by electrospinning. Carbohydrate Polymers, 77(2), 261–266. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2008.12.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tripathy, S., &amp; Singh, S. G. (2020). Label‐free electrochemical detection of DNA hybridization: A method for COVID‐19 diagnosis. Transactions of the Indian National Academy of Engineering, 5(2), 205–209. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41403‐020‐00103‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tucker, N., Stanger, J. J., Staiger, M. P., Razzaq, H., &amp; Hofman, K. (2012). The history of the science and technology of electrospinning from 1600 to 1995. Journal of Engineered Fibers and Fabrics, 7(2_suppl), 63–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unal, B., Yalcinkaya, E. E., Demirkol, D. O., &amp; Timur, S. (2018). An electrospun nanofiber matrix based on organo‐clay for biosensors: PVA/PAMAM‐Montmorillonite. Applied Surface Science, 444, 542–551. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apsusc.2018.03.109</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valizadeh, A., &amp; Mussa Farkhani, S. (2014). Electrospinning and electrospun nanofibres. IET Nanobiotechnology, 8(2), 83–92. https://doi.org/10.1049/iet‐nbt.2012.0040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Li, C., Li, Q., Zhang, S., lv, F., &amp; Yan, Z. (2020). Electrospinning fabrication of covalent organic framework composite nanofibers for pipette tip solid phase extraction of tetracycline antibiotics in grass carp and duck. Journal of Chromatography A, 1622, Article 461098. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2020.461098</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weng, R., Sun, L., Jiang, L., Li, N., Ruan, G., Li, J., &amp; Du, F. (2019). Electrospun graphene oxide–doped nanofiber‐based solid phase extraction followed by high‐performance liquid chromatography for the determination of tetracycline antibiotic residues in food samples. Food Analytical Methods, 12(7), 1594–1603. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12161‐019‐01495‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiang, G., Zhang, Y., Jiang, X., He, L., Fan, L., &amp; Zhao, W. (2010). Determination of trace copper in food samples by flame atomic absorption spectrometry after solid phase extraction on modified soybean hull. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 179(1), 521–525. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2010.03.034</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, M., Zhao, F., Zhang, Y., Xiong, Y., &amp; Han, S. (2022). Recent advances in aptamer‐based optical and electrochemical biosensors for detection of pesticides and veterinary drugs. Food Control, 131, Article 108399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, Q., Shi, W., Lv, P., Meng, W., Mao, G., Gong, C., Chen, Y., Wei, Y., He, X., Zhao, J., Han, H., Sun, M., &amp; Xiao, K. (2020). Critical role of caveolin‐1 in aflatoxin B1‐induced hepatotoxicity via the regulation of oxidation and autophagy. Cell Death &amp; Disease, 11, Article 6. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41419‐019‐2197‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi, J., Wu, P., Li, G., Xiao, W., Li, L., He, Y., He, Y., Ding, P., &amp; Chen, C. (2019). A composite prepared from carboxymethyl chitosan and aptamer‐modified gold nanoparticles for the colorimetric determination of Salmonella typhimurium. Microchimica Acta, 186(11), 711. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00604‐019‐3827‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yildiz, E., Sumnu, G., &amp; Kahyaoglu, L. N. (2021). Monitoring freshness of chicken breast by using natural halochromic curcumin loaded chitosan/PEO nanofibers as an intelligent package. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 170, 437–446. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.12.160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yurova, N. S., Danchuk, A., Mobarez, S. N., Wongkaew, N., Rusanova, T., Baeumner, A. J., &amp; Duerkop, A. (2018). Functional electrospun nanofibers for multimodal sensitive detection of biogenic amines in food via a simple dipstick assay. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 410(3), 1111–1121. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216‐017‐0696‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarkoob, S., Eby, R. K., Reneker, D. H., Hudson, S. D., Ertley, D., &amp; Adams, W. W. (2004). Structure and morphology of electrospun silk nanofibers. Polymer, 45(11), 3973–3977. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.polymer.2003.10.102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaarour, B., Zhu, L., Huang, C., &amp; Jin, X. (2020). A mini review on the generation of crimped ultrathin fibers via electrospinning: Materials, strategies, and applications. Polymers for Advanced Technologies, 31(7), 1449–1462. https://doi.org/10.1002/pat.4876</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaitoon, A., &amp; Lim, L.‐T. (2020). Effect of poly(ethylene oxide) on the electrospinning behavior and characteristics of ethyl cellulose composite fibers. Materialia, 10, Article 100649. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mtla.2020.100649</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai, M.‐Y., Feng, K., Hu, T.‐G., Zong, M.‐H., &amp; Wu, H. (2020). Development of a novel nano‐based detection card by electrospinning for rapid and sensitive analysis of pesticide residues. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 100(12), 4400–4408. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.10477</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, C., Li, Y., Wang, P., &amp; Zhang, H. (2020). Electrospinning of nanofibers: Potentials and perspectives for active food packaging. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 19(2), 479–502. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12536</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, R., Hong, Y., Reinhard, B. M., Liu, P., Wang, R., &amp; Dal Negro, L. (2018). Plasmonic nanotrough networks for scalable bacterial Raman biosensing. ACS Applied Materials &amp; Interfaces, 10(33), 27928–27935. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsami.8b07640</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X., Wang, J., Wu, Q., Li, L., Wang, Y., &amp; Yang, H. (2019). Determination of kanamycin by high performance liquid chromatography. Molecules, 24(10), Article 1902. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules24101902</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, J., Chen, A., Guo, H., Li, Y., He, X., Chen, L., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2022). Covalent organic framework/polyacrylonitrile electrospun nanofiber for dispersive solid‐phase extraction of trace quinolones in food samples. Nanomaterials, 12(14), Article 2482. https://doi.org/10.3390/nano12142482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zulkifli, M. Z. A., Kamarudin, N. H. N., &amp; Nordin, D. (2019). Polycaprolactone/chlorophyllin sodium copper salt nanofibrous mats prepared by electrospinning for soft tissue engineering. Jurnal Kejuruteraan, 2, 68–76.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>