<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39263900</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1552-4604</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of clinical pharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Clin Pharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of Food on the Pharmacokinetics, Safety, and Tolerability of Budesonide Oral Suspension in Healthy Adult Participants: A Randomized Phase 1 Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jcph.6131</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Budesonide oral suspension (BOS) is a swallowed corticosteroid indicated for 12-week therapy in eosinophilic esophagitis with minimal systemic exposure following administration. We aimed to assess the relative bioavailability of a single dose of BOS administered under fasting and fed (high-fat/high-calorie meal) conditions. Healthy adult volunteers (N = 20) were enrolled in an open-label, single-center, crossover study and were randomized (1:1) to receive a single oral dose of BOS 2.0 mg under fasting or fed conditions, with a 48-h washout period before crossover to the alternative conditions. Serial plasma samples were collected before and up to 24 h after dosing. Pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters were calculated from plasma budesonide concentration-time profiles by noncompartmental analysis. The mean peak budesonide concentration (C<sub>max</sub>) was ∼13% lower under fed than under fasting conditions (604.1 vs 692.9 pg/mL). Areas under the concentration-time curves from dosing to the last measurable budesonide concentration and from dosing to infinity were ∼26% higher and ∼27% higher under fed than fasting conditions (3529 vs 2811 pg h/mL and 3892 vs 3075 pg h/mL, respectively). The median time to peak plasma budesonide concentration was significantly longer (∼1 h) under fed than fasting conditions (2.516 vs 1.286 h, P &lt; .001). Safety and tolerability were also assessed throughout the study; all adverse events were mild or moderate in severity. Despite slight differences in budesonide PK parameters between fed and fasting conditions, the effect of food on systemic exposure to budesonide (BOS formulation) is not expected to be clinically meaningful.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Takeda Pharmaceuticals USA, Inc. The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American College of Clinical Pharmacology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prokopienko</LastName><ForeName>Alexander J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Takeda Development Center Americas, Inc., Cambridge, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Junyao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Takeda Development Center Americas, Inc., Cambridge, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yajnik</LastName><ForeName>Vijay</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Takeda Pharmaceuticals USA, Inc., Lexington, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baratta</LastName><ForeName>Mike</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Takeda Development Center Americas, Inc., Cambridge, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Desai</LastName><ForeName>Nirav K</ForeName><Initials>NK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Takeda Development Center Americas, Inc., Cambridge, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Richmond</LastName><ForeName>Camilla A</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Takeda Development Center Americas, Inc., Cambridge, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suri</LastName><ForeName>Ajit</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Takeda Development Center Americas, Inc., Cambridge, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Takeda Development Center Americas, Inc.</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Clin Pharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0366372</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0091-2700</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">budesonide oral suspension</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">eosinophilic esophagitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food‐effect study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacokinetics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">swallowed corticosteroids</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39263900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcph.6131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Dellon ES, Liacouras CA, Molina‐Infante J, et al. Updated international consensus diagnostic criteria for eosinophilic esophagitis: proceedings of the AGREE conference. Gastroenterology. 2018;155(4):1022‐1033.e1010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collins MH, Dellon ES, Katzka DA, Hirano I, Williams J, Lan L. Budesonide oral suspension significantly improves eosinophilic esophagitis histology scoring system results: analyses from a 12‐week, phase 2, randomized, placebo‐controlled trial. Am J Surg Pathol. 2019;43(11):1501‐1509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hahn JW, Lee K, Shin JI, et al. Global incidence and prevalence of eosinophilic esophagitis, 1976–2022: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2023;21(13):3270‐3284.e3277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Rhijn BD, Smout AJ, Bredenoord AJ. Disease duration determines health‐related quality of life in adult eosinophilic esophagitis patients. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2014;26(6):772‐778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safroneeva E, Coslovsky M, Kuehni CE, et al. Eosinophilic oesophagitis: relationship of quality of life with clinical, endoscopic and histological activity. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2015;42(8):1000‐1010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukkada V, Falk GW, Eichinger CS, King D, Todorova L, Shaheen NJ. Health‐related quality of life and costs associated with eosinophilic esophagitis: a systematic review. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2018;16(4):495‐503.e498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furuta GT, Katzka DA. Eosinophilic esophagitis. N Engl J Med. 2015;373(17):1640‐1648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossetti D, Isoldi S, Oliva S. Eosinophilic esophagitis: update on diagnosis and treatment in pediatric patients. Paediatr Drugs. 2020;22(4):343‐356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirano I, Chan ES, Rank MA, et al. AGA institute and the joint task force on allergy‐immunology practice parameters clinical guidelines for the management of eosinophilic esophagitis. Gastroenterology. 2020;158(6):1776‐1786.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dougherty T, Jr., Stephen S, Borum ML, Doman DB. Emerging therapeutic options for eosinophilic esophagitis. Gastroenterol Hepatol (N Y). 2014;10(2):106‐116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takeda Pharmaceuticals America Inc. Highlights of prescribing information, EOHILIA 2024. US FDA. Accessed May 31, 2024. https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2024/213976s000lbl.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dellon ES, Katzka DA, Collins MH, et al. Budesonide oral suspension improves symptomatic, endoscopic, and histologic parameters compared with placebo in patients with eosinophilic esophagitis. Gastroenterology. 2017;152(4):776‐786.e775.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirano I, Dellon ES, Gupta SK, et al. Safety of an investigational formulation of budesonide (budesonide oral suspension) for eosinophilic oesophagitis: an integrated safety analysis of six phase 1–3 clinical trials. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2023;57(10):1117‐1130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed CC, Fan C, Koutlas N, et al. Compounded oral viscous budesonide is effective and provides a durable response in eosinophilic esophagitis. HSOA J Gastroenterol Hepatol Res. 2018;7(1):2509‐2515.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta SK, Hill M, Vitanza JM, et al. Pharmacokinetics of budesonide oral suspension in children and adolescents with eosinophilic esophagitis. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2022;75(2):186‐191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song IH, Finkelman RD, Lan L. A pharmacokinetic bridging study to compare systemic exposure to budesonide between budesonide oral suspension and ENTOCORT EC in healthy individuals. Drugs R D. 2020;20(4):359‐367.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song IH, Rodgers T, Hayes S, Farrell C. A population pharmacokinetic analysis of budesonide oral suspension in children and adults with eosinophilic esophagitis and healthy adult volunteers. Am J Gastroenterol. 2020;115:S220.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundin P, Naber T, Nilsson M, Edsbacker S. Effect of food on the pharmacokinetics of budesonide controlled ileal release capsules in patients with active Crohn's disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2001;15(1):45‐51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edsbacker S, Bengtsson B, Larsson P, et al. A pharmacoscintigraphic evaluation of oral budesonide given as controlled‐release (Entocort) capsules. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2003;17(4):525‐536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salix Pharmaceuticals, Inc., a division of Bausch Health US, LLC. Uceris® (budesonide) extended‐release tablets. Prescribing information. 2020. Accessed May 31, 2024. https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2020/203634s007lbl.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AstraZeneca. Entocort EC (budesonide) delayed‐release capsules. Prescribing information. 2020. Accessed May 31, 2024. https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2020/021324s023lbl.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Assessing the effects of food on drugs in INDs and NDAs — clinical pharmacology considerations. Guidance for industry. 2022. Accessed May 31, 2024. https://www.fda.gov/downloads/drugs/guidancecomplianceregulatoryinformation/guidances/ucm070241.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ClinicalTrials.gov. An extension study to evaluate maintenance of efficacy and long‐term treatment effect of oral budesonide suspension (OBS) in adults and adolescents with eosinophilic esophagitis (EoE) (ORBIT2). Accessed May 31, 2024. https://www.clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT02736409</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ClinicalTrials.gov. Continuation study with budesonide oral suspension (BOS) for adolescent and adult subjects with eosinophilic esophagitis (EoE). Accessed May 31, 2024. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/study/NCT03245840</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glowczewski A, Krogulska A. Formulations of topical steroids in eosinophilic esophagitis ‐ current treatment and emerging possibilities. J Clin Med. 2022;11(5):1454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirano I, Collins MH, Katzka DA, et al. Budesonide oral suspension improves outcomes in patients with eosinophilic esophagitis: results from a phase 3 trial. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2022;20(3):525‐534.e510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vinther S, Christensen M, Christensen HR. The importance of convenience for patient adherence to drug treatments ‐ an overview of secondary literature. Clin Ther. 2015;37(8):E95‐E96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haasnoot ML, Safi S, Bredenoord AJ. Poor adherence to medical and dietary treatments in adult patients with eosinophilic esophagitis. Am J Gastroenterol. 2022;117(9):1412‐1418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander R, Alexander JA, Ravi K, et al. Measurement of observed eating behaviors in patients with active and inactive eosinophilic esophagitis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2019;17(11):2371‐2373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ClinicalTrials.gov. A study in adolescents and adults with eosinophilic esophagitis (EoE) measuring histologic response and determine if reduction in dysphagia is achieved (NCT02605867). Accessed May 31, 2024. https://classic.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT02605837</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comer GM, Bush MA, Dellon ES, Marino MT. Effect of food intake and body position on the pharmacokinetics of swallowed APT‐1011, a fluticasone orally disintegrating tablet, in healthy adult volunteers. J Clin Pharmacol. 2020;60(6):734‐743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dellon ES, Collins MH, Katzka DA, et al. Long‐term treatment of eosinophilic esophagitis with budesonide oral suspension. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2022;20(7):1488‐1498.e1411.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dellon ES, Katzka DA, Collins MH, et al. Safety and efficacy of budesonide oral suspension maintenance therapy in patients with eosinophilic esophagitis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2019;17(4):666‐673.e668.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta SK, Vitanza JM, Collins MH. Efficacy and safety of oral budesonide suspension in pediatric patients with eosinophilic esophagitis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2015;13(1):66‐76.e63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim AW, Talley NJ, Walker MM, Storm G, Hua S. Current status and advances in esophageal drug delivery technology: influence of physiological, pathophysiological and pharmaceutical factors. Drug Deliv. 2023;30(1):2219423.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>