<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39261391</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1867-1314</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Probiotics and antimicrobial proteins</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Intermittent Fasting and Probiotics: Synergistic Modulation of Gut Health for Therapeutic Advantages.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12602-024-10358-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Intermittent fasting (IF) is an increasingly popular dietary approach involving alternating fasting and eating periods. This review aims to summarize the growing body of literature demonstrating that IF is a potential nutritional practice that involves alternating periods of fasting and eating and the numerous benefits of IF, especially in the modulation of healthy gut microbiota. The positive impact of intermittent fasting on gut microbiota not only promotes gastrointestinal health but also has far-reaching effects on critical systems throughout the body. Additionally, the evidence presented in this review highlights the significant preventive and therapeutic effects of intermittent fasting on a wide range of disorders. This includes reducing the risk of diabetes, and neurological disorders, alleviating obesity, and enhancing the functioning of the liver, ultimately contributing to the maintenance of metabolic equilibrium. Perhaps most notably, these effects play a substantial role in preventing diabetes, a global health concern of increasing significance. This comprehensive investigation delves into the scientific foundations of intermittent fasting's impact on gut microbiota and its implications for averting chronic diseases, providing valuable insights for future research and therapeutic applications.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shehbaz</LastName><ForeName>Amna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Afzaal</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, Pakistan. muhammadafzaal@gcuf.edu.pk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akram</LastName><ForeName>Noor</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety &amp; Biotechnology Lab, Department of Food Science, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saeed</LastName><ForeName>Farhan</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, Pakistan. f.saeed@gcuf.edu.pk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Warda</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutritional Sciences, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Faiyaz</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Basic Health Sciences, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Qassim University, P.O. Box 6666, 51452, Buraydah, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Aftab</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutritional Sciences, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asghar</LastName><ForeName>Aasma</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutritional Sciences, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Faisal</LastName><ForeName>Zargham</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Human Nutrition and Dietetics, Iqra University Karachi, Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101484100</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1867-1306</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fasting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Glucose metabolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gut health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intermittent</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Obesity</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39261391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-024-10358-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12602-024-10358-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aljutaily T, Rehan M, Moustafa MM, Barakat H (2022) Effect of intermittent fasting, probiotic-fermented camel milk, and probiotic-fermented camel milk incorporating Sukkari date on diet-induced obesity in rats. Fermentation 8(11):619</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/fermentation8110619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antoni R, Johnston KL, Collins AL, Robertson MD (2017) Effects of intermittent fasting on glucose and lipid metabolism. Proc Nutri Soc 76(3):361–368</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0029665116002986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnason TG, Bowen MW, Mansell KD (2017) Effects of intermittent fasting on health markers in those with type 2 diabetes: a pilot study. World J Diabetes 8(4):154</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4239/wjd.v8.i4.154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28465792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5394735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atlas D, Federation ID (2017) IDF. Brussels, Belgium: International Diabetes Federation, 2013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beli E, Yan Y, Moldovan L, Vieira CP, Gao R, Duan Y ... Grant MB (2018) Restructuring of the gut microbiome by intermittent fasting prevents retinopathy and prolongs survival in db/db mice. Diabetes, 67(9), 1867–1879.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandhorst S, Levine ME, Wei M, Shelehchi M, Morgan TE, Nayak KS ... Longo VD (2024) Fasting-mimicking diet causes hepatic and blood markers changes indicating reduced biological age and disease risk. Nature Commun 15(1), 1309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braniste V, Al-Asmakh M, Kowal C, Anuar F, Abbaspour A, Tóth M ... Pettersson S (2014) The gut microbiota influences blood-brain barrier permeability in mice. Science translational medicine 6(263):263ra158–263ra158</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabral LQT, Ximenez JA, Moreno KGT, Fernandes R (2021) Probiotics have minimal effects on appetite-related hormones in overweight or obese individuals: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Clin Nutr 40(4):1776–1787</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clnu.2020.10.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33143930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaari A, Bendriss G, Zakaria D, McVeigh C (2020) Importance of dietary changes during the coronavirus pandemic: how to upgrade your immune response. Front Public Health 8:476</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.00476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32984253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7481450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Xiao Y, Li D, Zhang S, Wu Y, Zhang Q, Bai W (2023) New insights into the mechanisms of high-fat diet mediated gut microbiota in chronic diseases. iMeta 2(1):e69</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/imt2.69</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38868334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10989969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng CW, Villani V, Buono R, Wei M, Kumar S, Yilmaz OH ... Longo VD (2017) Fasting-mimicking diet promotes Ngn3-driven β-cell regeneration to reverse diabetes. Cell 168(5):775–788</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cignarella F, Cantoni C, Ghezzi L, Salter A, Dorsett Y, Chen L ... Piccio L (2018) Intermittent fasting confers protection in CNS autoimmunity by altering the gut microbiota. Cell metabolism 27(6):1222–1235</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daas MC, De Roos NM (2021) Intermittent fasting contributes to aligned circadian rhythms through interactions with the gut microbiome. Beneficial Microbes 12(2):147–161</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3920/BM2020.0149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33530881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalile B, Van Oudenhove L, Vervliet B, Verbeke K (2019) The role of short-chain fatty acids in microbiota–gut–brain communication. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 16(8):461–478</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41575-019-0157-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31123355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Felice FG, Ferreira ST (2014) Inflammation, defective insulin signaling, and mitochondrial dysfunction as common molecular denominators connecting type 2 diabetes to Alzheimer disease. Diabetes 63(7):2262–2272</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/db13-1954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24931033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elia AE, Lalli S, Monsurrò MR, Sagnelli A, Taiello AC, Reggiori B ... Albanese A (2016) Tauroursodeoxycholic acid in the treatment of patients with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Eur J Neurol 23(1):45–52</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frank J, Gupta A, Osadchiy V, Mayer EA (2021) Brain–gut–microbiome interactions and intermittent fasting in obesity. Nutrients 13(2):584</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13020584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33578763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7916460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstein I, Baek S, Presman DM, Paakinaho V, Swinstead EE, Hager GL (2017) Transcription factor assisted loading and enhancer dynamics dictate the hepatic fasting response. Genome Res 27(3):427–439</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/gr.212175.116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28031249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5340970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guldris SC, Parra EG, Amenós AC (2017) Gut microbiota in chronic kidney disease. Nefrología (English Edition) 37(1):9–19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nefroe.2017.01.017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y, Luo S, Ye Y, Yin S, Fan J, Xia M (2021) Intermittent fasting improves cardiometabolic risk factors and alters gut microbiota in metabolic syndrome patients. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 106(1):64–79</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/clinem/dgaa644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33017844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris L, Hamilton S, Azevedo LB, Olajide J, De Brún C, Waller G ... Ells L (2018) Intermittent fasting interventions for treatment of overweight and obesity in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JBI Evidence Synthesis 16(2):507–547</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartstra AV, Bouter KE, Bäckhed F, Nieuwdorp M (2015) Insights into the role of the microbiome in obesity and type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care 38(1):159–165</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc14-0769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25538312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan M (2022) A review on boosting immune system by healthy lifestyle (Doctoral dissertation, Brac University)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamshed H, Beyl RA, Della Manna DL, Yang ES, Ravussin E, Peterson CM (2019) Early time-restricted feeding improves 24-hour glucose levels and affects markers of the circadian clock, aging, and autophagy in humans. Nutrients 11(6):1234</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu11061234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31151228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6627766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan S, Tung N, Casanova-Acebes M, Chang C, Cantoni C, Zhang D ... Merad M (2019) Dietary intake regulates the circulating inflammatory monocyte pool. Cell 178(5):1102–1114</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kacimi S, Ref’at A, Fararjeh MA, Bustanji YK, Mohammad MK, Salem ML (2012) Intermittent fasting during Ramadan attenuates proinflammatory cytokines and immune cells in healthy subjects. Nutr Res 32(12):947–955</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nutres.2012.06.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23244540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klempel MC, Kroeger CM, Bhutani S, Trepanowski JF, Varady KA (2012) Intermittent fasting combined with calorie restriction is effective for weight loss and cardio-protection in obese women. Nutr J 11:1–9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1475-2891-11-98</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lessan N, Ali T (2019) Energy metabolism and intermittent fasting: the Ramadan perspective. Nutrients 11(5):1192</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu11051192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31137899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6566767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Patil IY, Jiang T, Sancheti H, Walsh JP, Stiles BL ... Cadenas E (2015) High-fat diet induces hepatic insulin resistance and impairment of synaptic plasticity. PloS one 10(5):e0128274</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malinowski B, Zalewska K, Węsierska A, Sokołowska MM, Socha M, Liczner G ... Wiciński M (2019) Intermittent fasting in cardiovascular disorders—an overview. Nutrients 11(3):673</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattson MP, Longo VD, Harvie M (2017) Impact of intermittent fasting on health and disease processes. Ageing Res Rev 39:46–58</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2016.10.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27810402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattson MP, Moehl K, Ghena N, Schmaedick M, Cheng A (2018) Intermittent metabolic switching, neuroplasticity and brain health. Nat Rev Neurosci 19(2):81–94</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrn.2017.156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mousavi SN, Rayyani E, Heshmati J, Tavasolian R, Rahimlou M (2022) Effects of Ramadan and non-Ramadan intermittent fasting on gut microbiome. Front Nutr 9:860575</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.860575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35392284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8980861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rong B, Wu Q, Saeed M, Sun C (2021) Gut microbiota—a positive contributor in the process of intermittent fasting-mediated obesity control. Animal Nutrition 7(4):1283–1295</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2021.09.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34786501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8567329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowan S, Jiang S, Korem T, Szymanski J, Chang ML, Szelog J ... Taylor A (2017) Involvement of a gut–retina axis in protection against dietary glycemia-induced age-related macular degeneration. Proc Natl Acad Sci 114(22):E4472-E4481</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saglam D, Gozde A, Sahin E, Ekren BY, Sezerman U, Bas M (2023) Effects of Ramadan intermittent fasting on gut microbiome: is the diet key? Front Microbiol 14:1203205</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1203205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37705730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10495574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez B, Delgado S, Blanco-Míguez A, Lourenço A, Gueimonde M, Margolles A (2017) Probiotics, gut microbiota, and their influence on host health and disease. Mol Nutr Food Res 61(1):1600240</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201600240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song WJ, Mondal P, Wolfe A, Alonso LC, Stamateris R, Ong BW ... Hussain MA (2014) Glucagon regulates hepatic kisspeptin to impair insulin secretion. Cell metabolism 19(4):667–681</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tay A, Pringle H, Penning E, Plank LD, Murphy R (2020) PROFAST: a randomized trial assessing the effects of intermittent fasting and Lacticaseibacillus rhamnosus probiotic among people with prediabetes. Nutrients 12(11):3530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12113530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33212907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7698325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teker HT, Ceylani T, Keskin S, Samgane G, Allahverdi H, Acikgoz E, Gurbanov R (2024) Supplementing probiotics during intermittent fasting proves more effective in restoring ileum and colon tissues in aged rats. J Cell Mol Med 28(6):e18203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcmm.18203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38445809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10915827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teker HT, Ceylani T, Keskin S, Samgane G, Baba B, Acıkgoz E, Gurbanov R (2024) Reduced liver damage and fibrosis with combined SCD Probiotics and intermittent fasting in aged rat. J Cell Mol Med 28(1):e18014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcmm.18014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37897241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tinsley GM, La Bounty PM (2015) Effects of intermittent fasting on body composition and clinical health markers in humans. Nutr Rev 73(10):661–674</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nutrit/nuv041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26374764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trepanowski JF, Kroeger CM, Barnosky A, Klempel MC, Bhutani S, Hoddy KK ... Varady KA (2017) Effect of alternate-day fasting on weight loss, weight maintenance, and cardioprotection among metabolically healthy obese adults: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Internal Med 177(7):930–938.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsitsou S, Zacharodimos N, Poulia KA, Karatzi K, Dimitriadis G, Papakonstantinou E (2022) Effects of time-restricted feeding and Ramadan fasting on body weight, body composition, glucose responses, and insulin resistance: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Nutrients 14(22):4778</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14224778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36432465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9696013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasim I, Majeed CN, DeBoer MD (2022) Intermittent fasting and metabolic health. Nutrients 14(3):631</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14030631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35276989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8839325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav S, Jha R (2019) Strategies to modulate the intestinal microbiota and their effects on nutrient utilization, performance, and health of poultry. J Animal Sci Biotechnol 10(1):1–11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40104-018-0310-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zang BY, He LX, Xue L (2022) Intermittent fasting: potential bridge of obesity and diabetes to health? Nutrients 14(5):981</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14050981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35267959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8912812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Li S, Yang L, Huang P, Li W, Wang S ... Zhao L (2013) Structural modulation of gut microbiota in life-long calorie-restricted mice. Nature Commun 4(1), 2163</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng D, Liwinski T, Elinav E (2020) Interaction between microbiota and immunity in health and disease. Cell Res 30(6):492–506</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-0332-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32433595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7264227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zmora N, Suez J, Elinav E (2019) You are what you eat: diet, health and the gut microbiota. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 16(1):35–56</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41575-018-0061-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30262901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zouhal H, Bagheri R, Triki R, Saeidi A, Wong A, Hackney AC ... Ben Abderrahman A (2020) Effects of Ramadan intermittent fasting on gut hormones and body composition in males with obesity. Intl J Environ Res Public Health 17(15):5600</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnosky AR, Hoddy KK, Unterman TG, Varady KA (2014) Intermittent fasting vs daily calorie restriction for type 2 diabetes prevention: a review of human findings. Transl Res 164(4):302–311</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trsl.2014.05.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24993615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>