<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39270816</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-8600</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>161</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Metabolism: clinical and experimental</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Metabolism</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The role of dietary modification in the prevention and management of metabolic dysfunction-associated fatty liver disease: An international multidisciplinary expert consensus.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>156028</StartPage><MedlinePgn>156028</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.metabol.2024.156028</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0026-0495(24)00255-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Metabolic dysfunction-associated fatty liver disease (MAFLD) or metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease (MASLD), has become the leading cause of chronic liver disease worldwide. Optimal dietary intervention strategies for MAFLD are not standardized. This study aimed to achieve consensus on prevention of MAFLD through dietary modification. A multidisciplinary panel of 55 international experts, including specialists in hepatology, gastroenterology, dietetics, endocrinology and other medical specialties from six continents collaborated in a Delphi-based consensus development process. The consensus statements covered aspects ranging from epidemiology to mechanisms, management, and dietary recommendations for MAFLD. The recommended dietary strategies emphasize adherence to a balanced diet with controlled energy intake and personalized nutritional interventions, such as calorie restriction, high-protein, or low-carbohydrate diets. Specific dietary advice encouraged increasing the consumption of whole grains, plant-based proteins, fish, seafood, low-fat or fat-free dairy products, liquid plant oils, and deeply colored fruits and vegetables. Concurrently, it advised reducing the intake of red and processed meats, saturated and trans fats, ultra-processed foods, added sugars, and alcohol. Additionally, maintaining the Mediterranean or DASH diet, minimizing sedentary behavior, and engaging in regular physical activity are recommended. These consensus statements lay the foundation for customized dietary guidelines and proposing avenues for further research on nutrition and MAFLD.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Xu-Fen</ForeName><Initials>XF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Nutrition, The First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Wenzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Varady</LastName><ForeName>Krista A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Kinesiology and Nutrition, University of Illinois Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xiang-Dong</ForeName><Initials>XD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jean Mayer USDA Human Nutrition Research Center on Aging at Tufts University, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Targher</LastName><ForeName>Giovanni</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Verona, Verona, Italy; Metabolic Diseases Research Unit, IRCCS Sacro Cuore-Don Calabria Hospital, Negrar di Valpolicella, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Byrne</LastName><ForeName>Christopher D</ForeName><Initials>CD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Southampton National Institute for Health and Care Research Biomedical Research Centre, University Hospital Southampton, and University of Southampton, Southampton General Hospital, Southampton, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tayyem</LastName><ForeName>Reema</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Human Nutrition, College of Health Science, Qatar University, Doha, Qatar.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Latella</LastName><ForeName>Giovanni</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition Division, Department of Life, Health and Environmental Sciences, University of L'Aquila, L'Aquila, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bergheim</LastName><ForeName>Ina</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutritional Sciences, Molecular Nutritional Science, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Valenzuela</LastName><ForeName>Rodrigo</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, Faculty of Medicine, University of Chile, Santiago, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>George</LastName><ForeName>Jacob</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Storr Liver Centre, The Westmead Institute for Medical Research, Westmead Hospital and University of Sydney, Sydney, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Newberry</LastName><ForeName>Carolyn</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Gastroenterology, Weill Cornell Medical Center, New York, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Ju-Sheng</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Westlake Center for Intelligent Proteomics, Westlake Laboratory of Life Sciences and Biomedicine, Hangzhou, China; School of Medicine, School of Life Sciences, Westlake University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>George</LastName><ForeName>Elena S</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition, School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University, Geelong, VIC, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Spearman</LastName><ForeName>C Wendy</ForeName><Initials>CW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Hepatology, Department of Medicine, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kontogianni</LastName><ForeName>Meropi D</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, School of Health Sciences &amp; Education, Harokopio University of Athens, Athens, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ristic-Medic</LastName><ForeName>Danijela</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Group for Nutritional Biochemistry and Dietology, Centre of Research Excellence in Nutrition and Metabolism, Institute for Medical Research, National Institute of the Republic of Serbia, University of Belgrade, Belgrade, Serbia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peres</LastName><ForeName>Wilza Arantes Ferreira</ForeName><Initials>WAF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, Josué de Castro Institute of Nutrition, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Depboylu</LastName><ForeName>Gamze Yurtdaş</ForeName><Initials>GY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Izmir Katip Celebi University, Faculty of Health Sciences, Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, İzmir, Türkiye.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Wanshui</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, School of Public Health, Anhui Medical University, Hefei, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Xu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, School of Public Health, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rosqvist</LastName><ForeName>Fredrik</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health and Caring Sciences, Clinical Nutrition and Metabolism, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden, and Department of Food Studies, Nutrition and Dietetics, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mantzoros</LastName><ForeName>Christos S</ForeName><Initials>CS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Valenti</LastName><ForeName>Luca</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Precision Medicine-Biological Resource Center, Transfusion Medicine, Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico Milano, Milan, Italy; Department of Pathophysiology and Transplantation, University of Milan, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yki-Järvinen</LastName><ForeName>Hannele</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Helsinki and Helsinki University Hospital, Helsinki, Finland; Minerva Foundation Institute for Medical Research, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mosca</LastName><ForeName>Antonella</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hepatology and Liver Transplant Unit, Bambino Gesù Children's Hospital, IRCCS, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sookoian</LastName><ForeName>Silvia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical and Molecular Hepatology, Translational Health Research Center (CENITRES), Maimónides University, Buenos Aires, Argentina; Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas (CONICET), Buenos Aires, Argentina; Faculty of Health Science, Maimónides University, Buenos Aires, Argentina.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Misra</LastName><ForeName>Anoop</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fortis-C-DOC Centre of Excellence for Diabetes, Metabolic Diseases and Endocrinology, New Delhi, India; National Diabetes, Obesity and Cholesterol Foundation (N-DOC), Diabetes Foundation (India) (DFI), New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yilmaz</LastName><ForeName>Yusuf</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, School of Medicine, Recep Tayyip Erdogan University, Rize, Türkiye.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Won</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Republic of Korea; Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Department of Internal Medicine, Seoul Metropolitan Government Boramae Medical Center, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fouad</LastName><ForeName>Yasser</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Endemic Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Minia University, Minia, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sebastiani</LastName><ForeName>Giada</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology and Chronic Viral Illness Service, McGill University Health Centre, Montreal, Canada; Division of Experimental Medicine, McGill University, Montreal, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wong</LastName><ForeName>Vincent Wai-Sun</ForeName><Initials>VW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine and Therapeutics, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Åberg</LastName><ForeName>Fredrik</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplantation and Liver Surgery, Helsinki University Hospital and University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wong</LastName><ForeName>Yu Jun</ForeName><Initials>YJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Changi General Hospital, Singapore; Duke-NUS Medical School, SingHealth, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Pianhong</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Nutrition, Second Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bermúdez-Silva</LastName><ForeName>Francisco-Javier</ForeName><Initials>FJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Investigación Biomédica de Málaga y Plataforma en Nanomedicina-IBIMA Plataforma BIONAND, Málaga, Spain; Clinical Unit of Endocrinology and Nutrition, University Regional Hospital of Málaga, Málaga, Spain; The Spanish Biomedical Research Centre in Diabetes and Associated Metabolic Disorders (CIBERDEM), Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ni</LastName><ForeName>Yan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lupsor-Platon</LastName><ForeName>Monica</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Imaging, Prof. Dr. Octavian Fodor Regional Institute of Gastroenterology and Hepathology, Iuliu Hațieganu University of Medicine and Pharmacy, Cluj-Napoca, Romania.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chan</LastName><ForeName>Wah Kheong</ForeName><Initials>WK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gastroenterology and Hepatology Unit, Department of Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Méndez-Sánchez</LastName><ForeName>Nahum</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, National Autonomous University of Mexico, Mexico City, Mexico; Liver Research Unit, Medica Sur Clinic &amp; Foundation, Mexico City, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Knegt</LastName><ForeName>Robert J</ForeName><Initials>RJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Erasmus MC University Medical Centre, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alam</LastName><ForeName>Shahinul</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hepatology, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Treeprasertsuk</LastName><ForeName>Sombat</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Gastroenterology, Department of Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Basic Medical Sciences, Beijing Key Laboratory of Neural Regeneration and Repair, Advanced Innovation Center for Human Brain Protection, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Mulong</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, Center for Global Health, School of Public Health, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Tiejun</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, the Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety of Ministry of Education, Fudan University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Ming-Lung</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hepatobiliary Division, Department of Internal Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung, Taiwan; College of Medicine and Center for Liquid Biopsy and Cohort Research, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung, Taiwan; School of Medicine and Doctoral Program of Clinical and Experimental Medicine, College of Medicine and Center of Excellence for Metabolic Associated Fatty Liver, National Sun Yat-sen University, Kaohsiung, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Huijie</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qi</LastName><ForeName>Xingshun</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, General Hospital of Northern Theater Command, Shenyang, Liaoning, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Xin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Public Health, Global Health Institute, Xi'an Jiaotong University Health Science Center, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pinyopornpanish</LastName><ForeName>Kanokwan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fan</LastName><ForeName>Yu-Chen</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hepatology, Qilu Hospital, Shandong University, Jinan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Niu</LastName><ForeName>Kaijun</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health of Tianjin University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Tianjin, China; Nutritional Epidemiology Institute and School of Public Health, Tianjin Medical University, Tianjin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jimenez-Chillaron</LastName><ForeName>Josep C</ForeName><Initials>JC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut de Recerca Sant Joan de Déu, SJD-Barcelona Children's Hospital, Endocrine Division, Esplugues, Barcelona, Spain; Department of Physiological Sciences, School of Medicine, University of Barcelona, L'Hospitalet, Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Ming-Hua</ForeName><Initials>MH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MAFLD Research Center, Department of Hepatology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Wenzhou, China; Key Laboratory of Diagnosis and Treatment for the Development of Chronic Liver Disease in Zhejiang Province, Wenzhou, China. Electronic address: zhengmh@wmu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Metabolism</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0375267</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0026-0495</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Consensus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dietary</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metabolic dysfunction-associated fatty liver disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest Christos S. Mantzoros has recused himself as EIC from handling this manuscript, reports grants through his institution from Merck, Massachusetts Life Sciences Center and Boehringer Ingelheim, has received grants through his Institution and personal consulting fees from Coherus Inc. and AltrixBio, he reports personal consulting fees and support with research reagents from Ansh Inc., collaborative research support from LabCorp Inc., reports personal consulting fees from Olympus, Genfit, Lumos, Novo Nordisk, Amgen, Biodexa, Laekna, Corcept, Intercept, 89 Bio, Madrigal, Aligos, Esperion and Regeneron, travel support and fees from UptoDate, TMIOA, Elsevier, and the Cardio Metabolic Health Conference. Ming-Hua Zheng has received honoraria for lectures from AstraZeneca, Hisky Medical Technologies, and Novo Nordisk and consulting fees from Boehringer Ingelheim and serves as a consultant for Eieling Technology. Christopher D Byrne has received an independent research grant from Echosens. France. W. Kim received honoraria for lectures from GSK, Hanmi, KOBIOLABS, and Novo Nordisk; consulting fees from Boehringer-Ingelheim, GSK, Novo Nordisk, Ildong, YUHAN, Hanmi, HK Inoen, Standigm, PharmaKing, Olix Pharma, TSD Life Sciences, Daewoong, QUEST, Therasid Bioscience, and Korea United Pharm; grants from GSK, Gilead, Novartis, Pfizer, Roche, Springbank, Ildong, BMS, DaeWoong, Hanmi, Novo Nordisk, Galmed, Enyo, and KOBIOLABS; stock options from KOBIOLABS and Lepidyne; and founded Remedygen outside the submitted work. Anoop Misra has received honorarium for lectures from Astra Zendeca, Boehringer Ingelgheim, Janssen, Lupin, Novo Nordisk and US Vitamins. Yusuf Yilmaz has served as a consultant or advisory board member for Zydus and Novo Nordisk. Boehringer Ingelheim. Wah Kheong Chan has served as a consultant or advisory board member for Abbott, Roche, Abbvie, Boehringer Ingelheim and Novo Nordisk; and a speaker for Abbott, Novo Nordisk, Echosens, Viatris and Hisky Medical. Ming-Lung Yu has received research support (grant) from Abbvie, BMS, Gilead, Merck and Roche diagnostics, served as a consultant of Abbott, Abbvie, BMS, Gilead, Roche and Roche diagnostics, and speaker of Abbvie, BMS, Eisai, Gilead, Roche and Roche diagnostics. Vincent Wong has served as a consultant or advisory board member for AbbVie, Boehringer Ingelheim, Echosens, Gilead Sciences, Intercept, Inventiva, Novo Nordisk, Pfizer, Sagimet Biosciences, TARGET PharmaSolutions, and Visirna; and a speaker for Abbott, AbbVie, Echosens, Gilead Sciences, Novo Nordisk, and Unilab. He has received a research grant from Gilead Sciences, and is a co-founder of Illuminatio Medical Technology. Giada Sebastiani has acted as speaker for Merck, Gilead, Abbvie, Novo Nordisk, Pfizer, served as an advisory board member for Pfizer, Merck, Novo Nordisk, Gilead, and has received unrestricted research funding from Theratecnologies Inc. Jacob George has served on advisory Boards and receives honoraria for talks from Novo Nordisk, Astra Zeneca, Roche, BMS, Pfizer, Cincera, Pharmaxis, Boehringer Mannheim, CSL, Gilead, Eisai. Carolyn Newberry serves as a consultant for Nestle Nutrition Sciences. The other authors declare no conflict of interest related to the preparation of this manuscript.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39270816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2024.156028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0026-0495(24)00255-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>