<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39272427</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2304-8158</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Foods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Foods of the Future: Challenges, Opportunities, Trends, and Expectations.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2663</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/foods13172663</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Creating propositions for the near and distant future requires a design to catch the tide of the times and move with or against trends. In addition, appropriate, adaptable, flexible, and transformational projects are needed in light of changes in science, technology, social, economic, political, and demographic fields over time. Humanity is facing a period in which science and developing technologies will be even more important in solving food safety, health, and environmental problems. Adapting to and mitigating climate change; reducing pollution, waste, and biodiversity loss; and feeding a growing global population with safe food are key challenges facing the agri-food industry and the food supply chain, requiring systemic transformation in agricultural systems and sustainable future agri-food. The aim of this review is to compile scientific evidence and data, define, and create strategies for the future in terms of food security, safety, and sufficiency; future sustainable foods and alternative protein sources; factors affecting food and nutrition security and agriculture; and promising food systems such as functional foods, novel foods, synthetic biology, and 3D food printing. In this review, the safety, conservation, nutritional, sensory, welfare, and potential challenges and limitations of food systems and the opportunities to overcome them on the basis of new approaches, innovative interpretations, future possibilities, and technologies are discussed. Additionally, this review also offers suggestions for future research and food trends in light of future perspectives. This article focuses on future sustainable foods, alternative protein sources, and novel efficient food systems, highlights scientific and technological advances and new research directions, and provides a significant perspective on sustainability.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Çakmakçı</LastName><ForeName>Songül</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0334-5621</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering, Faculty of Agriculture, Atatürk University, 25240 Erzurum, Türkiye.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Polatoğlu</LastName><ForeName>Bilgehan</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2554-6272</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology, Technical Sciences Vocational School, Atatürk University, 25240 Erzurum, Türkiye.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nanoscience and Nanoengineering, Graduate School of Natural and Applied Sciences, Atatürk University, 25240 Erzurum, Türkiye.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Çakmakçı</LastName><ForeName>Ramazan</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1354-1995</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Field Crops, Faculty of Agriculture, Çanakkale Onsekiz Mart University, 17100 Çanakkale, Türkiye.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Foods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101670569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2304-8158</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">3D food printing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">alternative proteins</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food security</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">functional foods</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">future foods</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nanotechnology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">new food sources</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">novel food</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sustainability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">synthetic biology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39272427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11393958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13172663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">foods13172663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Xiong Y., Guo H., Nor D.D.M.M., Song A., Dai L. Mineral resources depletion, environmental degradation, and exploitation of natural resources: COVID-19 aftereffects. Resour. Policy. 2023;85:103907. doi: 10.1016/j.resourpol.2023.103907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resourpol.2023.103907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nobanee H., Shanti H.Z. Assessing risk management trends in food security research. Environ. Dev. Sustain. 2024 doi: 10.1007/s10668-024-04462-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10668-024-04462-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çakmakçı R., Salık M.A., Çakmakçı S. Assessment and principles of environmentally sustainable food and agriculture systems. Agriculture. 2023;13:1073. doi: 10.3390/agriculture13051073.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agriculture13051073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie H., Wen Y., Choi Y., Zhang X. Global trends on food security research: A bibliometric analysis. Land. 2021;10:119. doi: 10.3390/land10020119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/land10020119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crippa M., Solazzo E., Guizzardi D., Monforti-Ferrario F., Tubiello F.N., Leip A. Food systems are responsible for a third of global anthropogenic GHG emissions. Nat. Food. 2021;2:198–209. doi: 10.1038/s43016-021-00225-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-021-00225-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Springmann M., Clark M., Mason-D’Croz D., Wiebe K., Bodirsky B.L., Lassaletta L., Vries W.d., Vermeulen S.J., Herrero M., Carlson K.M., et al. Options for keeping the food system within environmental limits. Nature. 2018;562:519–525. doi: 10.1038/s41586-018-0594-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0594-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30305731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Landesz T. Future of Food. In: Landesz T., Varghese S., Sargsyan K., editors. Future Intelligence. Future of Business and Finance. Springer; Cham, Switzerland: 2023. pp. 133–145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO . The Future of Food and Agriculture: Trends and Challenges. FAO; Rome, Italy: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lesk C., Coffel E., Winter J., Ray D., Zscheischler J., Seneviratne S.I., Horton R. Stronger temperature–moisture couplings exacerbate the impact of climate warming on global crop yields. Nat. Food. 2021;2:683–691. doi: 10.1038/s43016-021-00341-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-021-00341-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao W., Chou J., Li J., Xu Y., Li Y., Hao Y. Impacts of extreme climate events on future rice yields in global major rice-producing regions. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2022;19:4437. doi: 10.3390/ijerph19084437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19084437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9031651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35457305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu C., Qi Y., Guo A., Chang J. Grain yield and food security evaluation in the yellow river basin under climate change and water resources constraints. Front. Water. 2022;4:908945. doi: 10.3389/frwa.2022.908945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/frwa.2022.908945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonelli M., Basile L., Gagliardi F., Isernia P. The future of the Mediterranean agri-food systems: Trends and perspectives from a Delphi survey. Land Use Policy. 2022;120:106263. doi: 10.1016/j.landusepol.2022.106263.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.landusepol.2022.106263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harmanny K.S., Malek Ž. Adaptations in irrigated agriculture in the Mediterranean region: An overview and spatial analysis of implemented strategies. Reg. Environ. Chang. 2019;19:1401–1416. doi: 10.1007/s10113-019-01494-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10113-019-01494-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6531414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31178659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webb P., Benton T.G., Beddington J., Flynn D., Kelly N.M., Thomas S.M. The urgency of food system transformation is now irrefutable. Nat. Food. 2020;1:584–585. doi: 10.1038/s43016-020-00161-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-020-00161-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37128102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peixoto R.S., Voolstra C.R., Sweet M., Duarte C.M., Carvalho S., Villela H., Lunshof J.E., Gram L., Woodhams D.C., Walter J., et al. Harnessing the microbiome to prevent global biodiversity loss. Nat. Microbiol. 2022;7:1726–1735. doi: 10.1038/s41564-022-01173-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41564-022-01173-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35864220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horton P. A sustainable food future. R. Soc. Open Sci. 2023;10:230702. doi: 10.1098/rsos.230702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsos.230702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10445026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37621658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zurek M., Hebinck A., Selomane O. Climate change and the urgency to transform food systems. Science. 2022;376:1416–1421. doi: 10.1126/science.abo2364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abo2364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35737771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rockström J., Mazzucato M., Andersen L.S., Fahrländer S.F., Gerten D. Why we need a new economics of water as a common good. Nature. 2023;615:794–797. doi: 10.1038/d41586-023-00800-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/d41586-023-00800-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36949135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J., Oita A., Hayashi K., Matsubae K. Sustainability of vertical farming in comparison with conventional farming: A case study in Miyagi Prefecture, Japan, on nitrogen and phosphorus footprint. Sustainability. 2022;14:1042. doi: 10.3390/su14021042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su14021042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Zhang X. The potential of future foods for a sustainable future. eFood. 2024;5:e133. doi: 10.1002/efd2.133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/efd2.133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soria-Lopez A., Garcia-Perez P., Carpena M., Garcia-Oliveira P., Otero P., Fraga-Corral M., Cao H., Prieto M.A., Simal-Gandara J. Challenges for future food systems: From the Green Revolution to food supply chainswith a special focus on sustainability. Food Front. 2023;4:9–20. doi: 10.1002/fft2.173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fft2.173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeClerck F.A.J., Koziell I., Benton T., Garibaldi L.A., Kremen C., Maron M., Del Rio C.R., Sidhu A., Wirths J., Clark M., et al. A whole earth approach to nature positive food: Biodiversity and agriculture. In: von Braun J., Afsana K., Fresco L.O., Hassan M.H.A., editors. Science and Innovations for Food Systems Transformation. Springer; Cham, Switzerland: 2023. pp. 469–496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38285873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rockström J., Edenhofer O., Gaertner J., DeClerck F. Planet-proofing the global food system. Nat. Food. 2020;1:3–5. doi: 10.1038/s43016-019-0010-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-019-0010-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta A.K., Pratiksha, Das T., Kumar H., Rastogi S., Espinosa E., Rincón E., Morcillo-Martín R., Rather M.A., Kumar V., et al. Novel food materials: Fundamentals and applications in sustainable food systems for food processing and safety. Food Biosci. 2023;55:103013. doi: 10.1016/j.fbio.2023.103013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2023.103013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarbà C., Chinnici G., D’Amico M. Novel food: The impact of innovation on the paths of the traditional food chain. Sustainability. 2020;12:555. doi: 10.3390/su12020555.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su12020555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çakmakçı S., Çakmakçı R. Quality and nutritional parameters of food in agri-food production systems. Foods. 2023;12:351. doi: 10.3390/foods12020351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12020351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9857782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36673443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Augusto P.E.D. Challenges, trends and opportunities in food processing. Curr. Opin. Food Sci. 2020;35:72–78. doi: 10.1016/j.cofs.2020.03.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2020.03.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celi M., Rudkin J. Drawing food trends: Design potential in shaping food future. Futures. 2016;83:112–121. doi: 10.1016/j.futures.2016.05.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.futures.2016.05.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva V.L., Sereno A.M., Sobral P.J.A. Food industry and processing technology: On time to harmonize technology and social drivers. Food Eng. Rev. 2018;10:1–13. doi: 10.1007/s12393-017-9164-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12393-017-9164-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen C., Wei M., Sheng Y. A bibliometric analysis of food safety governance research from 1999 to 2019. Food Sci. Nutr. 2021;9:2316–2334. doi: 10.1002/fsn3.2220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fsn3.2220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8020926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33841848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qasrawi R., Hoteit M., Tayyem R., Bookari K., Al Sabbah H., Kamel I., Al-Halawa D.A. Machine learning techniques for the identification of risk factors associated with food insecurity among adults in Arab countries during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMC Public Health. 2023;23:1805. doi: 10.1186/s12889-023-16694-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-16694-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10505318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37716999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyelami L.O., Edewor S.E., Folorunso J.O., Abasilim U.D. Climate change, institutional quality and food security: Sub-Saharan African experiences. Sci. Afr. 2023;20:e01727. doi: 10.1016/j.sciaf.2023.e01727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sciaf.2023.e01727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calicioglu O., Flammini A., Bracco S., Bellù L., Sims R. The future challenges of food and agriculture: An integrated analysis of trends and solutions. Sustainability. 2019;11:222. doi: 10.3390/su11010222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su11010222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamam M., D’Amico M., Zarbà C., Chinnici G., Tóth J. Eco-innovations transition of agri-food enterprises into a circular economy. Front. Sustain. Food Syst. 2022;6:845420. doi: 10.3389/fsufs.2022.845420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2022.845420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fassio F., Minotti B. Circular economy for food policy: The case of the RePoPP project in the city of Turin (Italy) Sustainability. 2019;11:6078. doi: 10.3390/su11216078.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su11216078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djekić I., Velebit B., Pavlić B., Putnik P., Merkulov D.Š., Markovinović A.B., Kovačević D.B. Food quality 4.0: Sustainable food manufacturing for the twenty-first century. Food Eng. Rev. 2023;15:577–608. doi: 10.1007/s12393-023-09354-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12393-023-09354-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francisco C., Samyuktha K., Berber K. Impacts of a national lock down on small holder farmers 2019 income and food security: Empirical evidence from two states in India. World Dev. 2020;136:105069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penuelas J., Coello F., Sardans J. A better use of fertilizers is needed for global food security and environmental sustainability. Agric. Food Secur. 2023;12:5. doi: 10.1186/s40066-023-00409-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40066-023-00409-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarıkaya M.F., Tatar M. Global climate change and crop production. Int. J. Sivas Univ. Sci. Technol. 2023;2:65–78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Tang J., Tang M., Su M., Guo L. Scale of operation, financial support, and agricultural green total factor productivity: Evidence from China. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2022;19:9043. doi: 10.3390/ijerph19159043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19159043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9331884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35897410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heitala R., Liu P., Qi S. Does Small-Scale Organic Farming Contribute to the Local Environment—A Case Study in Suburban Shanghai, China. Agronomy. 2021;11:1601. doi: 10.3390/agronomy11081601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agronomy11081601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pawlak K., Kołodziejczak M. The role of agriculture in ensuring food security in developing countries: Considerations in the context of the problem of sustainable food production. Sustainability. 2020;12:5488. doi: 10.3390/su12135488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su12135488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parodi A., Leip A., De Boer I.J.M., Slegers P.M., Ziegler F., Temme E.H.M., Herrero M., Tuomisto H., Valin H., van Middelaar C.E., et al. The potential of future foods for sustainable and healthy diets. Nat. Sustain. 2018;1:782–789. doi: 10.1038/s41893-018-0189-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41893-018-0189-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y.S. The challenges and strategies of food security under rapid urbanization in China. Sustainability. 2019;11:542. doi: 10.3390/su11020542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su11020542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X., Shi L.J., Bernie A.E., Sun S.K., Zhao X.N., Wu P.T., Wang Y.B. New challenges of food security in Northwest China: Water footprint and virtual water perspective. J. Clean. Prod. 2020;245:118939. doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.118939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.118939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmerer K.S., Bell M.G., Chirisa I., Duvall C.S., Egerer M., Hung P.Y., Lerner A.M., Shackleton C., Ward J.D., Yacamán Ochoa C. Grand challenges in urban agriculture: Ecological and social approaches to transformative sustainability. Front. Sustain. Food Syst. 2021;5:668561. doi: 10.3389/fsufs.2021.668561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2021.668561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santeramo F.G., Carlucci D., De Devitiis B., Seccia A., Stasi A., Viscecchia R., Nardone G. Emerging trends in European food, diets and food industry. Food Res. Int. 2018;104:39–47. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2017.10.039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2017.10.039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29433781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mylona K., Maragkoudakis P., Miko L., Bock A.-K., Wollgast J., Caldeira S., Ulbertha F. Viewpoint: Future of food safety and nutrition—Seeking win-wins, coping with trade-offs. Food Policy. 2018;74:143–146. doi: 10.1016/j.foodpol.2017.12.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodpol.2017.12.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lonnie M., Hooker E., Brunstrom J.M., Corfe B.M., Green M.A., Watson A.W., Williams E.A., Stevenson E.J., Penson S., Johnstone A.M. Protein for life: Review of optimal protein intake, sustainable dietary sources and the effect on appetite in ageing adults. Nutrients. 2018;10:360. doi: 10.3390/nu10030360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu10030360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5872778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29547523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aschemann-Witzel J., Gantriis R.F., Fraga P., Perez-Cueto F.J.A. Plant-based food and protein trend from a business perspective: Markets, consumers, and the challenges and opportunities in the future. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2021;61:3119–3128. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2020.1793730.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2020.1793730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32654499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banach J.L., van der Berg J.P., Kleter G., van Bokhorst-van de Veen H., Bastiaan-Net S., Pouvreau L., van Asselt E.D. Alternative proteins for meat and dairy replacers: Food safety and future trends. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;63:11063–11080. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2022.2089625.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2022.2089625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35757863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotebagilu N.P., Bhatia S., Piramanayagam S. A qualitative investigation on Indian vegan food service providers’ perspective of trends, challenges and the future of vegan consumption. Int. J. Gastron. Food Sci. 2023;34:100824. doi: 10.1016/j.ijgfs.2023.100824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijgfs.2023.100824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams E., Vardavoulia A., Lally P., Gardner B. Experiences of initiating and maintaining a vegan diet among young adults: A qualitative study. Appetite. 2023;180:106357. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2022.106357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.appet.2022.106357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36341862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sim S.Y.J., Srv A., Chiang J.H., Henry C.J. Plant proteins for future foods: A roadmap. Foods. 2021;10:1967. doi: 10.3390/foods10081967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10081967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8391319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34441744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dernini S., Berry E.M., Serra-Majem L., La Vecchia C., Capone R., Medina F.X., Aranceta-Bartrina J., Belahsen R., Burlingame B., Calabrese G., et al. Med Diet 4.0: The Mediterranean diet with four sustainable benefits. Public Health Nutr. 2017;20:1322–1330. doi: 10.1017/S1368980016003177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1368980016003177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10261651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28003037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanakis C.M. Functionality of food components and emerging technologies. Foods. 2021;10:128. doi: 10.3390/foods10010128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10010128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7826514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33435589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palmieri N., Nervo C., Torri L. Consumers’ attitudes towards sustainable alternative protein sources: Comparing seaweed, insects and jellyfish in Italy. Food Qual. Prefer. 2023;104:104735. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassoun A., Cropotova J., Trif M., Rusu A.V., Bobiş O., Nayik G.A., Jagdale Y.D., Saeed F., Afzaal M., Mostashari P., et al. Consumer acceptance of new food trends resulting from the fourth industrial revolution technologies: A narrative review of literature and future perspectives. Front. Nutr. 2022;9:972154. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2022.972154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.972154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9399420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36034919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henn K., Olsen S.B., Goddyn H., Bredie W.L.P. Willingness to replace animal-based products with pulses among consumers in different European countries. Food Res. Int. 2022;157:111403. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35761657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trasca T.I., Ocnean M., Gherman R., Lile R.A., Balan I.M., Brad I., Tulcan C., Firu Negoescu G.A. Synergy between the waste of natural resources and food waste related to meat consumption in Romania. Agriculture. 2024;14:644. doi: 10.3390/agriculture14040644.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agriculture14040644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryant C., Szejda K., Parekh N., Deshpande V., Tse B. A survey of consumer perceptions of plant-based and clean meat in the USA, India, and China. Front. Sustain. Food Syst. 2019;3:432863. doi: 10.3389/fsufs.2019.00011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2019.00011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fehér A., Gazdecki M., Véha M., Szakály M., Szakály Z. A Comprehensive review of the benefits of and the barriers to the switch to a plant-based diet. Sustainability. 2020;12:4136. doi: 10.3390/su12104136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su12104136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raptou E., Tsiami A., Negro G., Ghuriani V., Baweja P., Smaoui S., Varzakas T. Gen Z’s willingness to adopt plant-based diets: Empirical evidence from Greece, India, and the UK. Foods. 2024;13:2076. doi: 10.3390/foods13132076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13132076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11241807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38998582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheah I., Shimul A.S., Liang J., Phau I. Drivers and barriers toward reducing meat consumption. Appetite. 2020;149:104636. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2020.104636.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.appet.2020.104636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32097692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alcorta A., Porta A., Tárrega A., Alvarez M.D., Vaquero M.P. Foods for Plant-Based Diets: Challenges and Innovations. Foods. 2021;10:293. doi: 10.3390/foods10020293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10020293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7912826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33535684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Z., Scherer L., Zhang Q., Behrens R. Adoption of plant-based diets across Europe can improve food resilience against the Russia-Ukraine conflict. Nat. Food. 2022;3:905–910. doi: 10.1038/s43016-022-00634-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-022-00634-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37118215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Springmann M., Van Dingenen R., Vandyck T., Latka C., Witzke P., Leip A. The global and regional air quality impacts of dietary change. Nat. Commun. 2023;14:6227. doi: 10.1038/s41467-023-41789-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-41789-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10558460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37802979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bunge A.C., Mazac R., Clark M., Wood A., Gordon L. Sustainability benefits of transitioning from current diets to plant-based alternatives or whole-food diets in Sweden. Nat. Commun. 2024;15:951. doi: 10.1038/s41467-024-45328-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-45328-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10831109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38296977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandran A.S., Suri S., Choudhary P. Sustainable plant protein: An up-to-date overview of sources, extraction techniques and utilization. Sustain. Food Technol. 2023;4:466–483. doi: 10.1039/D3FB00003F.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D3FB00003F</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu F., Li M., Wang Q., Yan J., Han S., Ma C., Ma P., Liu X., McClements D.J. Future foods: Alternative proteins, food architecture, sustainable packaging, and precision nutrition. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;63:6423–6444. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2022.2033683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2022.2033683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35213241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sá A.G.A., Moreno Y.M.F., Carciofi B.A.M. Plant proteins as high-quality nutritional source for human diet. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2020;97:170–180. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2020.01.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2020.01.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoury C.K., Amarilesa D., Sotoa J.S., Diaza M.V., Soteloa S., Sosaa C.C., Ramírez-Villegasa J., Achicanoya H.A., Velásquez-Tibatáe J., Guarinog L., et al. Comprehensiveness of conservation of useful wild plants: An operational indicator for biodiversity and sustainable development targets. Ecol. Indic. 2019;98:420–429. doi: 10.1016/j.ecolind.2018.11.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2018.11.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernhardt J.R., O’Connor M.I. Aquatic biodiversity enhances multiple nutritional benefits to humans. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2021;118:e1917487118. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1917487118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1917487118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8053940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33876740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhary B., Chauhan O.P., Mishra A. Edible seaweeds: A potential novel source of bioactive metabolites and nutraceuticals with human health benefits. Front. Mar. Sci. 2021;8:740054. doi: 10.3389/fmars.2021.740054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmars.2021.740054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duarte I.M., Marques S.C., Leandro S.M., Calado R. An overview of jellyfish aquaculture: For food, feed, pharma and fun. Rev. Aquac. 2022;14:265–287. doi: 10.1111/raq.12597.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/raq.12597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranasinghe R.A.S.N., Wijesekara W.L.I., Perera P.R.D., Senanayake S.A., Pathmalal M.M., Marapana R.A.U.J. Nutritional value and potential applications of jellyfish. J. Aquat. Food Prod. Technol. 2022;31:445–482. doi: 10.1080/10498850.2022.2060717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10498850.2022.2060717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarangapany A.K., Murugesan A., Annamalai A.S., Balasubramanian A., Shanmugam A. An overview on ultrasonically treated plant-based milk and its properties—A review. Appl. Food Res. 2022;2:100130. doi: 10.1016/j.afres.2022.100130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.afres.2022.100130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alae-Carew C., Green R., Stewart S., Cook B., Dangour A.D., Scheelbeek P.F.D. The role of plant-based alternative foods in sustainable and healthy food systems: Consumption trends in the UK. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;807:151041. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8724617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34673070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio N.R., Xiang N., Kaplan D.L. Plant-based and cell-based approaches to meat production. Nat. Commun. 2020;11:6276. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-20061-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-20061-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7722853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33293564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang G., Zhao X., Li X., Du G., Zhou J., Chen J. Challenges and possibilities for bio-manufacturing cultured meat. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2020;97:443–450. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2020.01.026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2020.01.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reiss J., Robertson S., Suzuki M. Cell sources for cultivated meat: Applications and considerations throughout the production workflow. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2021;22:7513. doi: 10.3390/ijms22147513.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms22147513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8307620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34299132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolgin E. Cell-based meat with a side of science. Nature. 2020;588:S64–S67. doi: 10.1038/d41586-020-03448-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/d41586-020-03448-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33299210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassoun A., Bekhit A.E.-D.A., Jambrak A.R., Regenstein J.M., Chemat F., Morton J.D., Gudjónsdóttir M., Carpena M., Prieto M.A., Varela P., et al. The fourth industrial revolution in the food industry-part II: Emerging food trends. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2024;64:407–437. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2022.2106472.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2022.2106472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35930319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stephens N., Di Silvio L., Dunsford I., Ellis M., Glencross A., Sexton A. Bringing cultured meat to market: Technical, socio-political, and regulatory challenges in cellular agriculture. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2018;78:155–166. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2018.04.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2018.04.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6078906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30100674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benny A., Pandi K., Upadhyay R. Techniques, challenges and future prospects for cell-based meat. Food Sci. Biotechnol. 2022;31:1225–1242. doi: 10.1007/s10068-022-01136-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10068-022-01136-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9385919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35992324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S., Yap W.S., Ge X.Y., Min V.L.X., Choudhury D. Cultured meat production fuelled by fermentation. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2022;120:48–58. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2021.12.028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.12.028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Zou L., Liu W., Chen X. An overview of recent progress in engineering three-dimensional scaffolds for cultured meat production. Foods. 2023;12:2614. doi: 10.3390/foods12132614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12132614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10340413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37444351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Post M.J., Levenberg S., Kaplan D.L., Genovese N., Fu J., Bryant C.J., Negowetti N., Verzijden K., Moutsatsou P. Scientific, sustainability and regulatory challenges of cultured meat. Nat. Food. 2020;1:403–415. doi: 10.1038/s43016-020-0112-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-020-0112-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Oliveira Padilha L.G., Malek L., Umberger W.J. Consumers’ attitudes towards lab-grown meat, conventionally raised meat and plant-based protein alternatives. Food Qual. Prefer. 2022;99:104573. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104573.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parlasca M.C., Qaim M. Meat consumption and sustainability. Annu. Rev. Resour. Econ. 2022;14:17–41. doi: 10.1146/annurev-resource-111820-032340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-resource-111820-032340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tzachor A., Richards C.E., Holt L. Future foods for risk-resilient diets. Nat. Food. 2021;326:326–329. doi: 10.1038/s43016-021-00269-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-021-00269-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wells M.L., Potin P., Craigie J.S., Raven J.A., Merchant S.S., Helliwell K.E., Smith A.G., Camire M.E., Brawley S.H. Algae as nutritional and functional food sources: Revisiting our understanding. J. Appl. Phycol. 2017;29:949–982. doi: 10.1007/s10811-016-0974-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10811-016-0974-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5387034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28458464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caporgno M.P., Mathys A. Trends in microalgae incorporation into innovative food products with potential health benefits. Front. Nutr. 2018;5:58. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2018.00058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2018.00058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6080594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30109233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M., Zhou J., Tavares J., Pinto C.A., Saraiva J.A., Prieto M.A., Cao H., Xiao J., Simal-Gandara J., Barba F.J. Applications of algae to obtain healthier meat products: A critical review on nutrients, acceptability and quality. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;63:8357–8374. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2022.2054939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2022.2054939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35357258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kusmayadi A., Leong Y.K., Yen H.-W., Huang C.-Y., Chang J.-S. Microalgae as sustainable food and feed sources for animals and humans-Biotechnological and environmental aspects. Chemosphere. 2021;271:129800. doi: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33736224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nwoba E.G., Parlevliet D.A., Laird D.W., Alameh K., Moheimani N.R. Light management technologies for increasing algal photobioreactor efficiency. Algal Res. 2019;39:101433. doi: 10.1016/j.algal.2019.101433.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.algal.2019.101433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guiné R.P.F., Correia P., Coelho C., Costa C.A. The role of edible insects to mitigate challenges for sustainability. Open Agric. 2021;6:24–36. doi: 10.1515/opag-2020-0206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/opag-2020-0206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ordoñez-Araque R., Quishpillo-Miranda N., Ramos-Guerrero L. Edible insects for humans and animals: Nutritional composition and an option for mitigating environmental damage. Insects. 2022;13:944. doi: 10.3390/insects13100944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/insects13100944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9604210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36292894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma B., Yadav D.K., Malakar S., Singh S., Sharma M., Suri S., Sridhar K. Insect proteins—Production technologies, bio-functional, and food applications: A perspective. Food Biosci. 2024;61:104560. doi: 10.1016/j.fbio.2024.104560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2024.104560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu M., Zhu C., Smetana S., Zhao M., Zhang H., Zhang F., Du Y. Minerals in edible insects: A review of content and potential for sustainable sourcing. Food Sci. Hum. Wellness. 2024;13:65–74. doi: 10.26599/FSHW.2022.9250005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26599/FSHW.2022.9250005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vinci G., Prencipe S.A., Masiello L., Zaki M.G. The application of life cycle assessment to evaluate the environmental impacts of edible insects as a protein source. Earth. 2022;3:925–938. doi: 10.3390/earth3030054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/earth3030054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuso A., Leni G., Prandi P., Lolli V., Caligiani A. Novel foods/feeds and novel frauds: The case of edible insects. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2024;147:104457. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2024.104457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2024.104457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernardo Y.A.A., Conte-Junior C.A. Oxidative stability in edible insects: Where is the knowledge frontier? Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2024;148:104518. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2024.104518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2024.104518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z.-Q., Chen S.-C., Xiao J.-H., Huang D.-W. State-of-the-art review of edible insect: From bioactives, pretreatment to enrichment. Food Biosci. 2024;59:103879. doi: 10.1016/j.fbio.2024.103879.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2024.103879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karaca A.C., Nickerson M., Caggia C., Randazzo C.L., Balange A.K., Carrillo C., Gallego M., Sharifi-Rad J., Kamiloglu S., Capanoglu E. nutritional and functional properties of novel protein sources. Food Rev. Int. 2023;39:6045–6077. doi: 10.1080/87559129.2022.2067174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/87559129.2022.2067174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raposo A., Coimbra A., Amaral L., Gonçalves A., Morais Z. Eating jellyfish: Safety, chemical and sensory properties. J. Sci. Food Agric. 2018;98:3973–3981. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.8921.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.8921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29384596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torri L., Tuccillo F., Puente-Tapia F.A., Morandini A.C., Segovia J., Nevarez-López C.A., Leoni V., Failla-Siquier G., Canepa-Oneto A., Quiñones J., et al. Jellyfish as sustainable food source: A cross-cultural study among Latin American countries. Food Qual. Prefer. 2024;117:105166. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2024.105166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2024.105166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vlaicu P.A., Untea A.E., Varzaru I., Saracila M., Oancea A.G. Designing nutrition for health-incorporating dietary by products into poultry feeds to create functional foods with ınsights into health benefits, risks, bioactive compounds, food component functionality and safety regulations. Foods. 2023;12:4001. doi: 10.3390/foods12214001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12214001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10650119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37959120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balthazar C.F., Guimarães J.F., Coutinho N.M., Pimentel T.C., Ranadheera C.S., Santillo A., Albenzio M., Cruz A.G., Sant’Ana A.S. The future of functional food: Emerging technolo¬gies application on prebiotics, probiotics and postbiotics. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2022;21:2560–2586. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35470949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çakmakçı S., Gülçin İ., Gündoğdu E., Öztekin H.E., Taslimi P. The comparison with commercial antioxidants, effects on colour, and sensory properties of green tea powder in butter. Antioxidants. 2023;12:1522. doi: 10.3390/antiox12081522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox12081522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10451864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37627517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Champagne C.P., Gomes da Cruz A., Daga M. Strategies to improve the functionality of probiotics in supplements and foods. Curr. Opin. Food Sci. 2018;22:160–166. doi: 10.1016/j.cofs.2018.04.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cofs.2018.04.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beltran-Peña A., D’Odorico P. Future food security in Africa under climate change. Earth’s Future. 2022;10:e2022EF002651. doi: 10.1029/2022EF002651.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1029/2022EF002651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Picciotti U., Massaro A., Galiano A., Garganese F. Cheese fortification: Review and possible improvements. Food Rev. Int. 2022;38:474–500. doi: 10.1080/87559129.2021.1874411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/87559129.2021.1874411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çakmakçı S., Öz E., Çakıroğlu K., Polat A., Gülçin İ., Ilgaz S., Seyyedcheraghi K., Ozhamamci I. Probiotic shelf life, antioxidant, sensory, physical and chemical properties of yogurts produced with Lactobacillus acidophilus and green tea powder. Kafkas Univ. Vet. Fak. Derg. 2019;25:673–682.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilango S., Antony U. Probiotic microorganisms from non-dairy traditional fermented foods. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2021;118:617–638. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2021.05.034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.05.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reque P.M., Brandelli A. Encapsulation of probiotics and nutraceuticals: Applications in functional food industry. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2021;114:1–10. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2021.05.022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.05.022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albayrak Ç.B., Duran M. Worldwide research tendencies on probiotics in food science: 1993 to 2021. Br. Food J. 2022;124:679–700. doi: 10.1108/BFJ-03-2021-0225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/BFJ-03-2021-0225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassoun A., Prieto M.A., Carpena M., Bouzembrak Y., Marvin H.J.P., Pallarés N., Barba F.J., Bangar S.P., Chaudhary V., Ibrahim S., et al. Exploring the role of green and Industry 4.0 technologies in achieving sustainable development goals in food sectors. Food Res. Int. 2022;162:112068. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2022.112068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.112068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36461323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sui M., Feng S., Yu J., Chen B., Li Z., Shao P. Removal and recovery of deep eutectic solvent with membrane-based methodology: A promising strategy to enhance extraction and purification of Dendrobium officinale flavonoids. Ind. Crop. Prod. 2023;206:117638. doi: 10.1016/j.indcrop.2023.117638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2023.117638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu S., Wang L., Zhao Y., Chen B., Qiu D., Sun P., Shao P., Feng S. Fabrication of high strength cold-set sodium alginate/whey protein nanofiber double network hydrogels and their interaction with curcumin. Food Res. Int. 2023;165:112490. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2023.112490.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2023.112490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36869501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leger D., Matassa S., Noor E., Shepon A., Milo R., Bar-Even A. Photovoltaic-driven microbial protein production can use land and sunlight more efficiently than conventional crops. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2021;118:e2015025. doi: 10.1073/pnas.2015025118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2015025118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8255800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34155098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker D.W., van Loon A.F. Droughts are coming on faster. Science. 2023;380:130–132. doi: 10.1126/science.adh3097.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.adh3097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37053333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takefuji Y. Sustainable protein alternatives. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2021;107:429–431. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2020.11.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2020.11.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim B.F., Santo R.E., Scatterday A.P., Fry J.P., Synk C.M., Cebron S.R., Mekonnen M.M., Hoekstra A.Y., de Pee S., Bloem M.W., et al. Country-specific dietary shifts to mitigate climate and water crises. Glob. Environ. Chang. 2020;62:101926. doi: 10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2019.05.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2019.05.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H., Zhu B., Cao Q. Future dietary transformation and its impacts on the environment in China. Sustainability. 2023;15:13021. doi: 10.3390/su151713021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su151713021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Giovannucci E.L. Ultra-processed foods and health: A comprehensive review. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;63:10836–10848. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2022.2084359.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2022.2084359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35658669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nile S.H., Baskar V., Selvaraj D., Nile A., Xiao J., Kai G. Nanotechnologies in food science: Applications, recent trends, and future perspectives. Nano-Micro Lett. 2020;12:45. doi: 10.1007/s40820-020-0383-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40820-020-0383-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7770847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34138283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins V.F.R., Pintado M.E., Morais R.M.S.C., Morais A.M.M.B. Valorisation of micro/nanoencapsulated bioactive compounds from plant sources for food applications towards sustainability. Foods. 2023;12:32. doi: 10.3390/foods12010032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12010032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9818261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36613248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghasemi-Varnamkhasti M., Apetrei C., Lozano J., Anyogu A. Potential use of electronic noses, electronic tongues and biosensors as multisensor systems for spoilage examination in foods. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2018;80:71–92. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2018.07.018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2018.07.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He X., Deng H., Hwang H. The current application of nanotechnology in food and agriculture. J. Food Drug Anal. 2019;27:1–21. doi: 10.1016/j.jfda.2018.12.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfda.2018.12.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9298627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30648562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang W.E., Nikel P.I. The synthetic microbiology caucus: From abstract ideas to turning microbes into cellular machines and back. Microb. Biotechnol. 2019;12:5–7. doi: 10.1111/1751-7915.13337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6302714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30461208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi S., Wang Z., Shen L., Xiao H. Synthetic biology: A new frontier in food production. Trends Biotechnol. 2022;40:781–803. doi: 10.1016/j.tibtech.2022.01.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2022.01.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35120749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Fonseca-Pereira P., Siqueira J.A., Monteiro-Batista R.C., Vaz M.G.M.V., Nunes-Nesi A., Araújo W.L. Using synthetic biology to improve photosynthesis for sustainable food production. J. Biotech. 2022;359:1–14. doi: 10.1016/j.jbiotec.2022.09.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2022.09.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36126804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Augustin M.A., Hartley C.J., Maloney G., Tyndall S. Innovation in precision fermentation for food ingredients. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;14:1–21. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2023.2166014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2023.2166014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36640107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asseng S., Palm C.A., Anderson J.L., Fresco L., Sanchez P.A., Asche F., Garlock T.M., Fanzo J., Smith M.D., Knapp G., et al. Implications of new technologies for future food supply systems. J. Agric. Sci. 2021;159:315–319. doi: 10.1017/S0021859621000836.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0021859621000836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tubb C., Seba T. Rethinking food and agriculture 2020–2030. The second domestication of plants and animals, the disruption of the cow, and the collapse of industrial livestock farming. Ind. Biotechnol. 2021;17:57–72. doi: 10.1089/ind.2021.29240.ctu.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/ind.2021.29240.ctu</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falcone P.M., González García S., Imbert E., Lijó L., Moreira M.T., Tani A., Tartiu V.E., Morone P. Transitioning towards the bio-economy: Assessing the social dimension through a stakeholder lens. Corp. Soc. Responsib. Environ. Manag. 2019;26:1135–1153. doi: 10.1002/csr.1791.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/csr.1791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicolas C., Geldres-Weiss V.V. Business and management research trends of sustainability assessment in the food sector. Br. Food J. 2023;125:220–236. doi: 10.1108/BFJ-06-2022-0528.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/BFJ-06-2022-0528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He C., Zhang M., Fang Z. 3D printing of food: Pretreatment and post-treatment of materials. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2020;60:2379–2392. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2019.1641065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2019.1641065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31313590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Q., Zhang M., Mujumdar A.S. Novel evaluation technology for the demand characteristics of 3D food printing materials: A review. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022;62:4669–4683. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2021.1878099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.1878099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33523706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorenz T., Iskandar M.M., Baeghbali V., Ngadi M.O., Kubow S. 3D food printing applications related to dysphagia: A narrative review. Foods. 2022;11:1789. doi: 10.3390/foods11121789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11121789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9222244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35741992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Handral H.K., Tay S.H., Chan W.W., Choudhury D. 3D printing of cultured meat products. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022;62:272–281. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2020.1815172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2020.1815172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32951433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindner N., Blaeser A. Scalable biofabrication: A perspective on the current state and future potentials of process automation in 3D-bioprinting applications. Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol. 2022;10:855042. doi: 10.3389/fbioe.2022.855042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fbioe.2022.855042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9165583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35669061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J.Y., Pandya J.K., McClements D.J., Lu J., Kinchla A.J. Advancements in 3D food printing: A comprehensive overview of properties and opportunities. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022;62:4752–4768. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2021.1878103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.1878103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33533641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bulut E.G., Candoğan K. Development and characterization of a 3D printed functional chicken meat-based snack: Optimization of process parameters and gelatin level. LWT. 2022;154:112768. doi: 10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112768.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu S., Vazquez Ramos P., Heckert O.R., Stieger M., van der Goot A.J., Schutyser M. Creating protein-rich snack foods using binder jet 3D printing. J. Food Eng. 2022;332:111124. doi: 10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2022.111124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2022.111124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoha K.S., Moses J.A. 3D printing approach to valorization of agri-food processing waste streams. Foods. 2023;12:212. doi: 10.3390/foods12010212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12010212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9818343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36613427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira T., Barroso S., Gil M.M. Food texture design by 3D printing: A review. Foods. 2021;10:320. doi: 10.3390/foods10020320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10020320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7913566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33546337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M., Li D., Zang Z., Sun X., Tan H., Si X., Tian J., Teng W., Wang J., Liang Q., et al. 3D food printing: Applications of plant-based materials in extrusion-based food printing. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022;62:7184–7198. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2021.1911929.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.1911929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33856247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diañez I., Martínez I., Franco J.M., Brito-de la Fuente E., Gallegos C. Advances in 3D printing of food and nutritional products. Adv. Food Nutr. Res. 2022;100:173–210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35659352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demei K., Zhang M., Phuhongsung P., Mujumdar A.S. 3D food printing: Controlling characteristics and improving tech¬nological effect during food processing. Food Res. Int. 2022;156:111120. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35651001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varvara R.-A., Szabo K., Vodnar D.C. 3D food printing: Principles of obtaining digitally-designed nourishment. Nutrients. 2021;13:3617. doi: 10.3390/nu13103617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13103617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8541666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34684618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T., Kaur L., Furuhata Y., Aoyama H., Singh J. 3D Printing of textured soft hybrid meat analogues. Foods. 2022;11:478. doi: 10.3390/foods11030478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11030478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8834039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35159628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghazal A.F., Zhang M., Mujumdar A.S., Ghamry M. Progress in 4D/5D/6D printing of foods: Applications and R&amp;D opportunities. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023;63:7399–7422.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35225117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Zhang X. The big food view and human health from the prospect of bio-manufacturing and future food. Front. Nutr. 2023;10:1160743. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2023.1160743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2023.1160743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10286865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37360295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pethick D.W., Bryden W.L., Mann N.J., Masters D.G., Lean I.J. The societal role of meat: The Dublin Declaration with an Australian perspective. Anim. Prod. Sci. 2023;63:1805–1826. doi: 10.1071/AN23061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1071/AN23061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munialo C.D., Stewart D., Campbell L., Euston S.R. Extraction, characterisation and functional applications of sustainable alternative protein sources for future foods: A review. Future Foods. 2022;6:100152. doi: 10.1016/j.fufo.2022.100152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fufo.2022.100152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehikoinen E., Salonen A.O. Food preferences in Finland: Sustainable diets and their differences between groups. Sustainability. 2019;11:1259. doi: 10.3390/su11051259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su11051259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlebois S., Juhasz M., Music J., Vézeau J. A review of Canadian and international food safety systems: Issues and recommendations for the future. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2021;20:5043–5066. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34390310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çakmakçı M.F., Çakmakçı R. Remote sensing, artificial intelligence and smart agriculture technology trends of the future. EJOSAT. 2023;52:234–246.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanakis C.M. The Future of Food. Foods. 2024;13:506. doi: 10.3390/foods13040506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13040506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10887894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38397483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu W., Nishinari K., Matsukawa S., Fang Y. The future trends of food hydrocolloids. Food Hydrocoll. 2020;103:105713. doi: 10.1016/j.foodhyd.2020.105713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2020.105713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryant C., Barnett J. Consumer acceptance of cultured meat: A systematic review. Meat Sci. 2018;143:8–17. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2018.04.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2018.04.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29684844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egea I., Fortes Y.E., Faura C., Egea-Fernández J., Bolarín M.C., Flores F.B. Salt-tolerant alternative crops as sources of quality food to mitigate the negative impact of salinity on agricultural production. Front. Plant Sci. 2023;14:1092585. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2023.1092885.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpls.2023.1092885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9935836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36818835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borelli T., Hunter D., Padulosi S., Amaya N., Meldrum G., de Oliveira Beltrame D.M., Samarasinghe G., Wasike V.W., Güner B., Tan A., et al. Local solutions for sustainable food systems: The contribution of orphan crops and wild edible species. Agronomy. 2020;10:231. doi: 10.3390/agronomy10020231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/agronomy10020231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerten D., Heck V., Jägermeyr J., Bodirsky B.L., Fetzer I., Jalava M., Kummu M., Lucht W., Rockström J., Schaphoff S., et al. Feeding ten billion people is possible within four terrestrial planetary boundaries. Nat. Sustain. 2020;3:200–208. doi: 10.1038/s41893-019-0465-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41893-019-0465-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hann E.C., Overa S., Harland-Dunaway M., Narvaez A.F., Le D.N., Orozco-Cárdenas M.L., Jiao F., Jinkerson R.E. A hybrid inorganic-biological artificial photosynthesis system for energy-efficient food production. Nat. Food. 2022;3:461–471. doi: 10.1038/s43016-022-00530-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-022-00530-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37118051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benke K., Tomkins B. Future foodproduction systems: Vertical farming and controlled-environment agriculture. Sustain. Sci. Pract. Policy. 2017;13:13–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knorr D., Sevenich R. Processed foods: From their emergence to resilient technologies. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2023;22:3765–3789. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.13205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.13205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37421325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Upadhyay S.K., Singh G., Rani N., Rajput V.D., Seth C.S., Dwivedi P., Minkina T., Wong M.H., Show P.L., Khoo K.S. Transforming aste into value-added products mediated microbes for enhancing soil health and crop production: Perspective views on circular economy. Environ. Technol. Innov. 2024;34:103573. doi: 10.1016/j.eti.2024.103573.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2024.103573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen T.H., Grote U., Neubacher F., Rahut D.B., Do M.H., Paudel G.P. Security risks from climate change and environmental degradation: Implications for sustainable land use transformation in the Global South. Curr. Opin. Environ. Sustain. 2023;63:101322. doi: 10.1016/j.cosust.2023.101322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cosust.2023.101322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knorr D., Augustin M.A. The future of foods. Sustain. Food Technol. 2024;2:253. doi: 10.1039/D3FB00199G.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D3FB00199G</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pörtner H.-O., Scholes R.J., Arneth A., Barnes D.K.A., Burrows M.T., Diamond S.E., Duarte C.M., Kiessling W., Leadley P., Managi S., et al. Overcoming the coupled climate and biodiversity crises and their societal impacts. Science. 2023;380:eabl4881. doi: 10.1126/science.abl4881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abl4881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37079687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyama E. Regional agriculture and social capital after massive natural disasters: The case of Miyagi Prefecture after the Great East Japan Earthquake. Sustainability. 2023;15:11725. doi: 10.3390/su151511725.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su151511725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Follmann A., Willkomm M., Dannenberg P. As the city grows, what do farmers do? A systematic review of urban and peri-urban agriculture under rapid urban growth across the Global South. Landscape Urban Plann. 2021;215:104186. doi: 10.1016/j.landurbplan.2021.104186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.landurbplan.2021.104186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuusaana E.D., Ayurienga I., Eledi Kuusaana J.A., Kidido J.K., Abdulai I.A. Challenges and sustainability dynamics of urban agriculture in the savannah ecological zone of Ghana: A study of bolgatanga municipality. Front. Sustain. Food Syst. 2022;6:797383. doi: 10.3389/fsufs.2022.797383.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2022.797383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azadi H., Barati A.A., Nooghabi S.N., Scheffran J. Climate-related disasters and agricultural land conversion: Towards prevention policies. Clim. Dev. 2022;14:814–828. doi: 10.1080/17565529.2021.2008291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/17565529.2021.2008291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambros P., Granvik M. Trends in agricultural land in EU countries of the Baltic Sea Region from the perspective of Resilience and Food Security. Sustainability. 2020;12:5851. doi: 10.3390/su12145851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su12145851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng Y., Zeng Z., Searchinger T.D., Ziegler A.D., Wu J., Wang D., He X., Elsen P.R., Ciais P., Xu R., et al. Doubling of annual forest carbon loss over the tropics during the early twenty-first century. Nat. Sustain. 2022;5:444–451. doi: 10.1038/s41893-022-00854-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41893-022-00854-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu P., Burney J., Chang J., Jin Z., Mueller N.D., Xin Q., Xu J., Yu L., Makowski D., Ciais P. Warming reduces global agricultural production by decreasing cropping frequency and yields. Nat. Clim. Chang. 2022;12:1016–1023. doi: 10.1038/s41558-022-01492-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41558-022-01492-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cos J., Doblas-Reyes F., Jury M., Marcos R., Bretonnière P.-A., Samsó M. The Mediterranean climate change hotspot in the CMIP5 and CMIP6 projections. Earth Syst. Dynam. 2022;13:321–340. doi: 10.5194/esd-13-321-2022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5194/esd-13-321-2022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Essa Y.H., Hirschi M., Thiery W., El-Kenawy A.M., Yang C. Drought characteristics in Mediterranean under future climate change. NPJ. Clim. Atmos. Sci. 2023;6:133. doi: 10.1038/s41612-023-00458-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41612-023-00458-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis K.F., Downs S., Gephart J.A. Towards food supply chain resilience to environmental shocks. Nat. Food. 2021;2:54–65. doi: 10.1038/s43016-020-00196-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-020-00196-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sardar A., Kiani A.K., Kuşlu Y., Bilgic A. Examining the role of livelihood diversification as a part of climate-smart agriculture (CSA) strategy. Atatürk Üniversitesi Ziraat Fakültesi Derg. 2020;51:79–87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarker U., Oba S., Ullah R., Bari A., Ercisli S., Skrovankova S., Adamkova A., Zvonkova M., Mlcek J. Nutritional and bioactive properties and antioxidant potential of Amaranthus tricolor, A. lividus, A. viridis, and A. spinosus leafy vegetables. Heliyon. 2024;10:e30453. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e30453.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e30453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11077029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38720726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasegawa T., Sakurai G., Fujimori S., Takahashi K., Hijioka Y., Masui T. Extreme climate events increase risk of global food insecurity and adaptation needs. Nat. Food. 2021;2:587–595. doi: 10.1038/s43016-021-00335-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43016-021-00335-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37118168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu B., Zhan P., Lei M., Zhou F., Wang P. Food quality monitoring system based on smart contracts and evaluation models. IEEE Access. 2020;8:12479–12490. doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2020.2966020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2020.2966020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mir S.A., Dar B.N., Shah M.A., Sofi S.A., Hamdani A.M., Oliveira C.A.F., Moosavi M.H., Khaneghah A.M., Sant’Ana A.S. Application of new technologies in decontamination of mycotoxins in cereal grains: Challenges, and perspectives. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2021;148:111976. doi: 10.1016/j.fct.2021.111976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2021.111976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33422602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash S.D., Siliveru K., Zheng Y. Emerging applications of cold plasma technology in cereal grains and products. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2023;141:104177. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2023.104177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2023.104177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grgić I., Ačkar Đ., Barišić V., Vlainić M., Knežević N., Knežević Z.M. Nonthermal methods for starch modification—A review. J. Food Process. Preserv. 2019;43:e14242. doi: 10.1111/jfpp.14242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfpp.14242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Y., Francis K., Zhang X. Review on formation of cold plasma activated water (PAW) and the applications in food and agriculture. Food Res. Int. 2022;157:111246. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35761559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oner M.E., Subasi B.G., Ozkan G., Esatbeyoglu T., Capanoglu E. Efficacy of cold plasma technology on the constituents of plant-based food products: Principles, current applications, and future potential. Food Res. Int. 2023;172:113079. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2023.113079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2023.113079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37689859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Li B., Shang H., Ma R., Zhu Y., Yang X., Ju S., Zhao W., Sun H., Zhuang J., et al. Effective inhibition of fungal growth, deoxynivalenol biosynthesis and pathogenicity in cereal pathogen Fusarium spp. by cold atmospheric plasma. Chem. Eng. J. 2022;437:135307. doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2022.135307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2022.135307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desai M., Chandel A., Chauhan O.P., Semwal A.D. Uses and future prospects of cold plasma in agriculture. Food Humanit. 2024;2:100262. doi: 10.1016/j.foohum.2024.100262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foohum.2024.100262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valdez-Narváez M.I., Fernández-Felipe M.T., Martinez A., Rodrigo D. Inactivation of Bacillus cereus spores and vegetative cells in inert matrix and rice grains using low-pressure cold plasma. Foods. 2024;13:2223. doi: 10.3390/foods13142223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13142223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11276126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39063307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjan R., Gupta A.K., Pandiselvam R., Chauhan A.K., Akhtar S., Jha A.K., Pratiksha, Ghosh T., Purohit S.R., Rather M.A., et al. Plasma treatment: An alternative and sustainable green approach for decontamination of mycotoxin in dried food products. J. Agric. Food Res. 2023;14:100867. doi: 10.1016/j.jafr.2023.100867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jafr.2023.100867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasenay S., Ačkar Đ. Bibliometric analysis of the scientific research of food industry by-products in the period 1976–2021. Sustainability. 2022;14:16910. doi: 10.3390/su142416910.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su142416910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chigwedere C.M., Njoroge D.M., Van Loey A.M., Hendrickx M.E. Understanding the relations among the storage, soaking, and cooking behavior of pulses: A scientific basis for innovations in sustainable foods for the future. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2019;18:1135–1165. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33337000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atalar M.N., Köktürk M., Altındağ F., Ozhan G., Özen T., Demirtas İ., Gülçin İ. LC-ESI-MS/MS analysis of secondary metabolites of different St. John’s wort (Hypericum perforatum) extracts used as food supplements and evaluation of developmental toxicity on zebrafish (Danio rerio) embryos and larvae. S. Afr. J. Bot. 2023;159:580–587. doi: 10.1016/j.sajb.2023.06.031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2023.06.031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Can H., Güven L., Demirkaya Miloğlu F., Abd El-Aty A.M. Development and validation of a UHPLC-ESI-MS/MS method for the simultaneous determination of organic acids and phenolic compounds in Filipendula vulgaris, Polygonum divaricatum, Hypericum linarioides, and Rheum ribes. Microchem. J. 2024;201:110683. doi: 10.1016/j.microc.2024.110683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2024.110683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur R., Kaur L., Gupta T.B., Singh J., Bronlund J. Multitarget preservation technologies for chemical-free sustainable meat processing. J. Food Sci. 2022;87:4312–4328. doi: 10.1111/1750-3841.16329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.16329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9825855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36120824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>