<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39270756</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-1208</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>196</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbial pathogenesis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microb Pathog</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Genomic insights into prevalence of virulence and multi drug resistance genes in milk borne Klebsiella pnuemoniae: Face of emerging resistance to last resort antibiotics.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>106936</StartPage><MedlinePgn>106936</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.106936</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0882-4010(24)00403-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Spread of hypervirulent and multi-drug resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae in raw milk is public health concern due to its potential impact on food safety and public health. Therefore, this study investigated antibiotic susceptibility test (AST), antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs), mutations conferring ARGs, virulence factor and plasmid replicons to check prevalence of fosfomycin resistant MDR K. pneumoniae isolated from raw milk samples collected from Saurashtra region of Gujarat, India. K. pneumoniae isolated from raw milk and subjected to disk diffusion assay. From that, MDR along with fosfomycin resistant isolates were analysed for multi locus sequence typing, presence of ARGs, mutations conferring resistance, virulence factors and plasmid replicon types by using its whole genome sequence. Results shows that, among 32 K. pneumoniae, 8 were phenotypically resistant to fosfomycin. As per WGS analysis, 8 MDR isolates were assigned into different sequence types such as ST3321, ST37, ST2715, ST1087, ST3157, ST299 and ST29. Among that, ST37 is well recognized MDR high risk clone reported worldwide and first time reported from raw milk of Saurashtra region of Gujarat, India. ARGs responsible for resistance to fosfomycin (fosA) were found in all 8 isolates. Other ARGs such as blaSHV, kdeA, OqxA, OqxB, dfrA1, sul1, qnrB4, aadA2 and ere(A) were also detected. High diversity of virulence factors was also identified by detection of genes encoding virulence factors related to iron uptake such as entE, fepD, entA, entB, Irp2, fepG, ybtU, ybtP, fepC, ybtA, ybtE, fepB, ybtS, fyuA, ybtQ, ybtT, ybtX, Irp1, adherence such as yagZ/ecpA, yagV/ecpE, yagX/ecpC, yagV/ecpE, ykgK/ecpR and invasion such as fimA, pla, fimC, fimH, fimB, fimE were detected in eight genomes. Mutations in murA, uhpT and glpT conferring a fosfomycin resistance were also present in genomes of 8 K. pneumoniae. IncF was the most common plasmid replicon type detected in all 8 genomes. The study reports high diversity of virulent and multidrug resistant K. pneumoniae in raw milk. Hence, genomic surveillance plans are urgently required for food borne pathogens.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adhyaru</LastName><ForeName>Hetvi J</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dairy Microbiology, College of Dairy Science, Kamdhenu University, Amreli, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mangroliya</LastName><ForeName>Devangi B</ForeName><Initials>DB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dairy Microbiology, College of Dairy Science, Kamdhenu University, Amreli, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhalu</LastName><ForeName>Arti B</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dairy Microbiology, College of Dairy Science, Kamdhenu University, Amreli, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kabariya</LastName><ForeName>Jayesh H</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dairy Microbiology, College of Dairy Science, Kamdhenu University, Amreli, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramani</LastName><ForeName>Vimal M</ForeName><Initials>VM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dairy Microbiology, College of Dairy Science, Kamdhenu University, Amreli, Gujarat, India. Electronic address: vmr@kamdhenuuni.edu.in.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Microb Pathog</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8606191</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0882-4010</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antimicrobial resistance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fosfomycin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Klebsiella pneumoniae</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Last resort antibiotics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Raw milk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virulence factors</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39270756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.106936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0882-4010(24)00403-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>