<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39276998</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-1026</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>954</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Science of the total environment</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Total Environ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Benzo[a]pyrene exposure induces anxiety-like behaviors in the mice through brain metabolic alterations.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>176215</StartPage><MedlinePgn>176215</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176215</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0048-9697(24)06371-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The deleterious health impacts of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) on the population have been extensively substantiated and acknowledged. Mounting evidence underscores that PAH exposure is closely linked to an elevated risk of mental disorders, particularly in populations experiencing occupational and high-level exposure. In this study, we aimed to investigate the mechanisms underlying anxiety-like behaviors induced by different dosages of PAHs, with a concentrated focus on brain region-specific metabolic alterations in mice using various metabolomics approaches. Male C57BL/6 mice were exposed to benzo[a]pyrene (B[a]P), a typical PAH, through gavage at occupational exposure and EPA toxicologically relevant dosages (2.0 and 20.0 mg/kg/day) for 21 days, respectively. Behavioral assessments revealed that occupational exposure to B[a]P induced anxiety-like behaviors in C57BL/6 mice. Meanwhile, elevated serum norepinephrine and corticotropin-releasing hormone further confirmed the anxiety-inducing effects of B[a]P exposure. Metabolomics analysis uncovered dysregulation across various metabolic pathways following B[a]P exposure, encompassing brain neurotransmitter, organic acid, amino acid, lipid, fatty acid, and cholesterol. Anxiety levels and lipid metabolic abnormalities were notably exacerbated at the higher dosage, despite being only a 10-fold increase. Of particular significance, a decrease in lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) and lysophosphatidylserine (LPS) emerged as pivotal indicators of B[a]P neurotoxicity. Spatial-resolved metabolomics further demonstrated distinctive lipid and metabolite profiles across different brain subregions after exposure to B[a]P. Remarkably, alterations were specifically observed in the anxiety-related brain regions, such as the hippocampus, cortex, white matter, and thalamus, varying with exposure dosages. These findings underscore the significance of brain metabolic abnormalities in the development of mental disorders triggered by B[a]P exposure and highlight the need for establishing precise exposure limits of B[a]P to safeguard public mental health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Fang</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Neuroimmunomodulation for Neurological Diseases, Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen-Hong Kong Institute of Brain Science, Shenzhen 518055, China; Institute of Neurological and Psychiatric Disorders, Shenzhen Bay Laboratory, Shenzhen 518067, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiao</LastName><ForeName>Qian</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Neuroimmunomodulation for Neurological Diseases, Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen-Hong Kong Institute of Brain Science, Shenzhen 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jingguang</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Key Laboratory of Food Safety Risk Assessment, Ministry of Health, China National Center of Food Safety and Risk Assessment, Beijing 100021, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhong</LastName><ForeName>Huifang</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Xirong</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Neuroimmunomodulation for Neurological Diseases, Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen-Hong Kong Institute of Brain Science, Shenzhen 518055, China; University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tu</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Neuroimmunomodulation for Neurological Diseases, Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen-Hong Kong Institute of Brain Science, Shenzhen 518055, China; University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China; CAS Key Laboratory of Brain Connectome and Manipulation, Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen 518055, China; Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Brain Connectome and Behavior, Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen 518055, China. Electronic address: jie.tu@siat.ac.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Qian</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen 518055, China; University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China. Electronic address: qian.luo@siat.ac.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Total Environ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0330500</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0048-9697</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety-like behaviors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Benzo[a]pyrene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Brain metabolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental disorders</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spatial-resolved metabolomics</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39276998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0048-9697(24)06371-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>