<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39272463</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2304-8158</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Foods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A New Design for Reference Values Assignment in Proficiency Testing for Fat and Crude Protein in Raw Milk for a Limited Number of Participants.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2693</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/foods13172693</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Proficiency testing (PT) allows food laboratories to endorse their competency to provide food safety guarantees to producers and consumers. One of the recommended methods for assigning reference values in PT with a small number of participants consists in considering the results that a laboratory obtains by means of a calibration test based on certified reference material (CRM). The present study delves into the results from eight PT rounds on the determination of fat and crude protein from raw milk, with modifications in the number of samples and the analysis sessions from that required by the ISO 13528:2022. The uncertainty criterion of the assigned value established by the ISO 13528:2022 standard was met by 93% of the participating laboratories, which allowed most participants to be evaluated through z-score. The assigned values were generally compatible with the results obtained by the participants. Thus, it can be concluded that the design for the assignment of the reference value is appropriate for PT with a limited number of participants. It is recommended for future PT to limit the uncertainty of the CRM according to their availability and to update the standard deviation of the proficiency assessment for the Mid-Infrared Spectroscopy method (MIR).</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Poo</LastName><ForeName>Susan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory for Measurement Quality Assurance (LACM), Institute of Food Sciences and Technology, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences, Universidad Austral de Chile, Valdivia 5090000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Analytical Chemistry, Center of Agri-Food and Wine Research (IVAGRO), Faculty of Science, University of Cadiz, 11510 Puerto Real, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Palma</LastName><ForeName>Miguel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8509-4226</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Analytical Chemistry, Center of Agri-Food and Wine Research (IVAGRO), Faculty of Science, University of Cadiz, 11510 Puerto Real, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Muñoz</LastName><ForeName>Ociel</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food Sciences and Technology, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences, Universidad Austral de Chile, Valdivia 5090000, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Foods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101670569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2304-8158</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">assigned value</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">crude protein</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fat</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">proficiency testing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">raw milk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">reduced number of laboratories</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">reference value</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39272463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11394484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13172693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">foods13172693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>General Requirements for the Competence of Testing and Calibration Laboratories. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olivares I.R.B., de Souza G.B., de Araujo Nogueira A.R., Pacces V.H.P., Grizotto P.A., da Silva Gomes Lima P.S., Bontempi R.M. Trends in the Development of Proficiency Testing for Chemical Analysis: Focus on Food and Environmental Matrices. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2022;27:55–83. doi: 10.1007/s00769-021-01487-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-021-01487-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conformity Assessment—General Requirements for the Competence of Proficiency Testing Providers. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breidbach A., Nørgaard J.V., Cubero-Leon E., Martinez Esteso M.J. Assignment of a Reference Value of Total Cow’s Milk Protein Content in Baked Cookies Used in an Interlaboratory Comparison. Foods. 2022;11:869. doi: 10.3390/foods11060869.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11060869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8956096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35327290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Łuszczyńska M., Gołaś-Prądzyńska M., Rola J.G. Control of Residues of Antimicrobial Substances by Screening Methods in Raw Milk Based on Participation in Proficiency Tests in Poland, 2017–2021. Foods. 2022;11:2635. doi: 10.3390/foods11172635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11172635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9455837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36076820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong S.-k. Performance Evaluation for Proficiency Testing with a Limited Number of Participants. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2011;16:539–544. doi: 10.1007/s00769-011-0816-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-011-0816-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistical Methods for Use in Proficiency Testing by Interlaboratory Comparison. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson M., Ellison S.L.R., Wood R. The International Harmonized Protocol for the Proficiency Testing of Analytical Chemistry Laboratories: (IUPAC Technical Report) Pure Appl. Chem. 2006;78:145–196. doi: 10.1351/pac200678010145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1351/pac200678010145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerrero A., Opitz R. Evolución Del Comercio Exterior Del Sector Lácteo y Su Situación Arancelaria 2019. Odepa, Ministerio de Agricultura de Chile; Santiago, Chile: 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peralta G. Situación Internacional y Nacional Del Sector Lácteo Bovino. Odepa, Ministerio de Agricultura de Chile; Santiago, Chile: 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spisso B.F., Monteiro M.A., Pereira M.U., Ferreira R.G., da Costa R.P., Carlos B.S., Negris S.T.C., de la Cruz M.H.C., da Nóbrega A.W. Preparation of In-House Reference Material of Benzylpenicillin in Milk and Results of a Brazilian Proficiency Testing Scheme. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2013;18:323–331. doi: 10.1007/s00769-013-0982-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-013-0982-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dajay L.C., Portugal T.R., Climaco J.C., Parcon M.R.V., Udarbe M.A., Placio R.E.E., Adona P.E. Establishment of Proficiency Testing Programs in the Philippines. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2019;24:65–71. doi: 10.1007/s00769-018-1363-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-018-1363-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuselman I., Fajgelj A. IUPAC/CITAC Guide: Selection and Use of Proficiency Testing Schemes for a Limited Number of Participants—Chemical Analytical Laboratories (IUPAC Technical Report) Pure Appl. Chem. 2010;82:1099–1135. doi: 10.1351/PAC-REP-09-08-15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1351/PAC-REP-09-08-15</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotyczka-Moranska M., Mastalerz M., Plis A., Sciazko M. Inter-Laboratory Proficiency Testing of the Measurement of Gypsum Parameters with Small Numbers of Participants. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2020;25:373–381. doi: 10.1007/s00769-020-01451-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-020-01451-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milde D., Klokočníková E., Nižnanská A. Practical Guidance for Organizing Small Interlaboratory Comparisons. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2021;26:17–22. doi: 10.1007/s00769-021-01458-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-021-01458-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armishaw P., King B., Millar R.G. Achieving Traceability in Chemical Measurement—A Metrological Approach to Proficiency Testing. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2003;8:184–190. doi: 10.1007/s00769-003-0625-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-003-0625-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng S., Mesquida C., Gui E.M., Cheow P.S., Lee T.K., Teo T.L. Providing a Traceable Assigned Value in a Proficiency Testing Programme on the Determination of Benzoic Acid in Orange Juice. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2014;19:439–443. doi: 10.1007/s00769-014-1087-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-014-1087-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheow P.S., Teo T.L., Lu T., Gui E.M., Lee T.K. An Accuracy-Based Proficiency Testing Programme with Metrological Reference Values for the Mass Fraction of Acesulfame Potassium and Sucralose in Cake Mix Flour. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2020;25:355–366. doi: 10.1007/s00769-020-01449-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-020-01449-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aryana N., Ramadhaningtyas D.P., Styarini D., Aristiawan Y. First Indonesian Proficiency Testing Using Reference Value from Isotope Dilution Mass Spectrometry Method for Benzoic Acid, Methyl Paraben, and n-Butyl Paraben in Sweet Soy Sauce. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2019;24:427–435. doi: 10.1007/s00769-019-01398-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-019-01398-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yarita T., Otake T., Aoyagi Y., Takasaka N., Suzuki T., Watanabe T. Comparison of Assigned Values from Participants’ Results, Spiked Concentrations of Test Samples, and Isotope Dilution Mass Spectrometric Results in Proficiency Testing for Pesticide Residue Analysis. J. AOAC Int. 2018;101:1199–1204. doi: 10.5740/jaoacint.17-0218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5740/jaoacint.17-0218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28978367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim H., Hwang E., Park J., Heo S.W., Yim Y.-H., Lim Y., Lim M.C., Lee J.W., Lee K.-S. Proficiency Testing for Total Mercury in Oyster with a Metrologically Traceable Reference Value from Isotope Dilution Mass Spectrometry: Implications on Laboratory Practices Using Mercury Analyzers. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2019;24:253–261. doi: 10.1007/s00769-019-01379-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-019-01379-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldan A., Van Der Veen A.M.H., Prauß D., Recknagel A., Boley N., Evans S., Woods D. Economy of Proficiency Testing: Reference versus Consensus Values. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2001;6:164–167. doi: 10.1007/PL00013515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/PL00013515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aryana N. Proficiency Testing for Determination of Pesticides Residues in Black Tea: Comparison of Three Robust Statistical Approaches Based on ISO 13528 to Estimate the Consensus Values for Small Number of Participants. IOP Conf. Ser. Mater. Sci. Eng. 2021;1011:012029. doi: 10.1088/1757-899X/1011/1/012029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1757-899X/1011/1/012029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maroto A. Ph.D. Thesis. Universitat Rovira I Virgili; Tarragona, Spain: 2002. Incertidumbre En Métodos Analíticos de Rutina.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schiller S.B. Statistical Aspects of the Certification of Chemical Batch SRMs. NIST Spec. Publ. 1996;48:60–125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conformity Assessment—General Requirements for the Competence of Proficiency Testing Providers. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LACM®/División de Metrología Manual de Procedimientos DM_MP_EA_06. Ensayos de Aptitud. Métodos Analíticos Para Materia Grasa y Proteína Bruta En Leche Cruda. LACM; Valdivia, Chile: 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk—Determination of Fat Content—Gravimetric Method (Reference Method) International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk and Milk Products—Determination of Nitrogen Content—Part 1: Kjeldahl Principle and Crude Protein Calculation. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk—Determination of Nitrogen Content—Part 3: Block-Digestion Method (Semi-Micro Rapid Routine Method) International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maroto A., Boqué R., Riu J., Rius F.X. Evaluating Uncertainty in Routine Analysis. Trends Anal. Chem. 1999;18:577–584. doi: 10.1016/S0165-9936(99)00151-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0165-9936(99)00151-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maronna R.A., Yohai V.J., Salibián-Barrera M. Robust Statistics: Theory and Methods (with R) John Wiley &amp; Sons; Hoboken, NJ, USA: 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidance for the Use of Repeatability, Reproducibility and Trueness Estimates in Measurement Uncertainty Evaluation. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellison S., Williams A., editors. Quantifying Uncertainty in Analytical Measurement. 3rd ed. Eurachem/CITAC; Teddington, UK: 2012. p. 141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LACM®/División de Metrología Obtención Del Valor Asignado Para Un Ítem de Ensayo de Aptitud Vía Ensayo de Calibración (Trazabilidad) Ejecutado Por El Laboratorio: Fundamentos. LACM; Valdivia, Chile: 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 19662:2018(E)/IDF 238:2018(E) Milk—Determination of Fat Content—Acido-Butyrometric (Gerber Method); International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk and Liquid Milk Products—Guidelines for the Application of Mid-Infrared Spectrometry. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk—Definition and Evaluation of the Overall Accuraccy of Alternative Methods of Milk Analysis—Part 1: Analytical Attributes of Alternative Methods. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk—Definition and Evaluation of the Overall Accuracy of Alternative Methods of Milk Analysis—Part 2: Calibration and Quality Control in the Dairy Laboratory. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AOAC Official Method . Fat Content of Raw and Pasteurized Whole Milk—Gerber Method by Weight. AOAC; Gaithersburg, MD, USA: 2004. 2000.18-2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pankratov I., Elhanany S., Henig S., Zaritsky S., Ostapenko I., Kuselman I. Development of a Proficiency Testing Scheme for a Limited Number of Participants in the Field of Natural Water Analysis. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2010;15:459–466. doi: 10.1007/s00769-010-0673-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-010-0673-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sin D.W.M., Wong Y.C. Use of Assigned Reference Values: Revisiting a Small-Scale Inter-Laboratory Comparison for Residual Pesticides in Tea. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2015;20:495–500. doi: 10.1007/s00769-015-1157-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-015-1157-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kardash E., Kuselman I., Pankratov I., Elhanan S. Proficiency Testing of pH and Electrolytic Conductivity Measurements of Groundwater: A Case Study of the Difference between Consensus and Metrologically Traceable Values. Accredit. Qual. Assur. 2013;18:373–381. doi: 10.1007/s00769-013-1006-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00769-013-1006-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk—Definition and Evaluation of the Overall Accuracy of Alternative Methods of Milk Analysis—Part 3. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milk, Dried Products and Cream—Determination of Fat Content—Gravimetric Method. International Organization for Standardization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leche—Determinación Del Contenido de Materia Grasa—Método de Gerber—Parte 1: Procedimiento. Instituto Nacional de Normalización (Chile); Santiago, Chile: 1998.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>