<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39278585</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0953</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>263</Volume><Issue>Pt 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exposure to bisphenol compounds accelerates the conjugative transfer of antibiotic resistance plasmid.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>120002</StartPage><MedlinePgn>120002</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.envres.2024.120002</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0013-9351(24)01909-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Antimicrobial resistance poses the most formidable challenge to public health, with plasmid-mediated horizontal gene transfer playing a pivotal role in its global spread. Bisphenol compounds (BPs), a group of environmental contaminants with endocrine-disrupting properties, are extensively used in various plastic products and can be transmitted to food. However, the impact of BPs on the plasmid-mediated horizontal transfer of antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) has not yet been elucidated. Herein, we demonstrate that BPs could promote the conjugative transfer frequency of RP4-7 and clinically multidrug-resistant plasmids. Furthermore, the promoting effect of BPs on the plasmid transfer was also confirmed in a murine model. Microbial diversity analysis of transconjugants indicated an increase in α diversity in the BPAF-treated group, along with the declined richness of some beneficial bacteria and elevated richness of Faecalibaculum rodentium, which might serve as an intermediate repository for resistance plasmids. The underlying mechanisms driving the enhanced conjugative transfer upon BPAF treatment include exacerbated oxidative stress, disrupted membrane homeostasis, augmented energy metabolism, and the increased expression of conjugation-related genes. Collectively, our findings highlight the potential risk associated with the exacerbated dissemination of AMR both in vitro and in vivo caused by BPs exposure.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Bingqing</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Co-innovation Center for Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, College of Veterinary Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Jingyi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Co-innovation Center for Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, College of Veterinary Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Shuyao</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Co-innovation Center for Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, College of Veterinary Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Zhiqiang</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Co-innovation Center for Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, College of Veterinary Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China; Joint International Research Laboratory of Agriculture and Agri-Product Safety, The Ministry of Education of China, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China. Electronic address: zqwang@yzu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yuan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Co-innovation Center for Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, College of Veterinary Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China; Joint International Research Laboratory of Agriculture and Agri-Product Safety, The Ministry of Education of China, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China; Institute of Comparative Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, China. Electronic address: liuyuan2018@yzu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0147621</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0013-9351</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">BPs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Conjugative transfer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gut microbiota</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multidrug-resistant plasmids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PMF</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39278585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2024.120002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0013-9351(24)01909-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>