<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39272524</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2304-8158</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Foods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Certified Food Safety Management Systems Assessed through the Lenses of Food Safety Culture and <i>Locus</i> of Control: A Pilot Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2759</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/foods13172759</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The approach to ensure food safety (FS) has evolved, including the concept of FS culture, which has been shaped by both the legislation and the scientific literature. In this study, two companies that produce foods associated with potential risks of cross-contamination (gluten-free foods and frozen pastry, respectively) and are certified according to international voluntary FS standards, such as the British Retail Council Global Standard (BRC) and the International Featured Standards Food Version (IFS), were investigated to assess: (a) if the assessment of FS culture's pillars can uncover unexpected critical areas; (b) if the scores of the FS culture's pillars are related to personal traits, namely, age, seniority in the company and <i>locus</i> of control orientation, i.e., the beliefs that an event is the result of external factors (luck, destiny or superior beings), or the result of internal factors (human behavior). Questionnaires for the survey and the scoring system applied were selected from the literature. Results showed that all food handlers had an optimistic bias, which paradoxically could be the consequence of the rigorous application of hygienic procedures. The younger food handlers had significantly (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05) lower commitment than the older ones. Moreover, the segment of food handlers having an external <i>locus</i> orientation demonstrated weaker normative beliefs than those having an internal <i>locus</i> of control orientation. Results showed that the FS culture survey, which is related to the shared FS culture, could disclose unknown weakness in third-party certified companies, even if the well implemented principles of voluntary FS standards are aligned with the FS-culture pillars. Moreover, the segmentation of food handlers according to their age and the <i>locus</i> of control assessment could provide additional information on the individual orientation toward FS behavior. Hence these tools could assist the leaders in the management of the dynamic nature of human capital.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Forte</LastName><ForeName>Giada</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food, Environmental and Nutritional Sciences, Università degli Studi di Milano, Via Celoria, 2, 20133 Milano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tornielli</LastName><ForeName>Simona</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Eurofin Food Assurance Italia, Via Bruno Buozzi, Milano 2, 20055 Vimodrone, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parini</LastName><ForeName>Daniela</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Eurofin Food Assurance Italia, Via Bruno Buozzi, Milano 2, 20055 Vimodrone, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lavelli</LastName><ForeName>Vera</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8606-757X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food, Environmental and Nutritional Sciences, Università degli Studi di Milano, Via Celoria, 2, 20133 Milano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Foods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101670569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2304-8158</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">certified company</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety culture</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">locus of control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">management system</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39272524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11394592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13172759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">foods13172759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Codex Alimentarius. General Principles of Food Hygiene CXC 1-1969. Adopted in 1969. Amended in 1999. Revised in 1997, 2003, 2020, 2023 Editorial Corrections in 2011.  [(accessed on 3 June 2024)]. 3b5c pp. Available online:  https://openknowledge.fao.org/server/api/core/bitstreams/f6f228d7-3b5c-42d1-8f47-1164c2a43ec7/content.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadhav H.B., Choudhary P. Emerging techniques for the processing of food to ensure higher food safety with enhanced food quality: A review. Discov. Food. 2024;4:20. doi: 10.1007/s44187-024-00089-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44187-024-00089-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerin T.F. Roles of company directors and the implications for governing for the emerging impacts of climate risks in the fresh food sector: A review. Food Control. 2022;133:108600. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondoc I. Treatise. 1st ed. Volume 1 “Ion Ionescu de la Brad” Publishing House; Iași, Romania: 2015. Foundations of veterinary sanitary and food safety legislation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondoc I. Treatise. 1st ed. Volume 2 “Ion Ionescu de la Brad” Publishing House; Iași, Romania: 2015. Foundations of veterinary sanitary and food safety legislation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondoc I. European regulation in the veterinary sanitary and food safety area, a component of the European policies on the safety of food products and the protection of consumer interests: A 2007 retrospective. Part two: Regulations.  [(accessed on 3 June 2024)];Universul Jurid. Suplim. 2016 :16–19. Available online:  https://www.cabidigitallibrary.org/doi/full/10.5555/20173244251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5555/20173244251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondoc I. European regulation in the veterinary sanitary and food safety area, a component of the European policies on the safety of food products and the protection of consumer interests: A 2007 retrospective. Part four: Decisions. Universul Jurid. Suppl. 2016:24–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luning P.A., Marcelis W.J. A techno-managerial approach in food quality management research. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2006;17:378–385. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2006.01.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2006.01.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GFSI  A Culture of Food Safety—A Position Paper from the Global Food Safety Initiative (GFSI) 2018.  [(accessed on 3 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://mygfsi.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/GFSI-Food-Safety-Culture-Full.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manning L., Luning P.A., Wallace C.A. The evolution and cultural framing of food safety management systems—Where from and where next? Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2019;18:1770–1792. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33336962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak R., Waterso P. Global food safety as a complex adaptive system: Key concepts and future prospects. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2019;91:409–425. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2019.07.040.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2019.07.040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>British Retail Council  British Retail Council Global Standard (BRCGS) for Food Safety, 2018, Issue 8.  [(accessed on 3 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://cdn.scsglobalservices.com/files/program_documents/brc_food_standard_8_0.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Featured Standards  International Featured Standards (IFS) Food Version 8. Standard for Auditing Product and Process Compliance in Relation to Food Safety and Quality. 2023.  [(accessed on 3 June 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.ifs-certification.com/images/ifs_documents/IFS_Food_v8_standard_EN.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) Regulation (EU) 2021/382 of 3 March 2021 amending the Annexes to Regulation (EC) No 852/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the hygiene of foodstuffs as regards food allergen management, redistribution of food and food safety culture.  [(accessed on 3 June 2024)];Off. J. Eur. Union. 2021 64:3–6. Available online:  https://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2021/382/oj.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J.C., Daraba A., Voidarou C., Rozos G., Enshasy H.A.E., Varzakas T. Implementation of food safety management systems along with other management tools (HAZOP, FMEA, Ishikawa, Pareto). The case study of Listeria monocytogenes and correlation with microbiological criteria. Foods. 2021;10:2169. doi: 10.3390/foods10092169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10092169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8468768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34574279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spagnoli P., Defalchidu L., Vlerick P., Jacxsens L. The Relationship between Food Safety Culture Maturity and Cost of Quality: An Empirical Pilot Study in the Food Industry. Foods. 2024;13:571. doi: 10.3390/foods13040571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13040571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10887550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38397548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanin L.M., Stedefeldt E., Luning P.A. The evolvement of food safety culture assessment: A mixed-methods systematic review. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2021;118:125–142. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2021.08.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.08.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanin L.M., Luning P.A., da Cunha D.T., Stedefeldt E. Influence of educational actions on transitioning of food safety culture in a food service context: Part 1-triangulation and data interpretation of food safety culture elements. Food Control. 2021;119:107447. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyarugwe S.P., Linnemann A., Nyanga L.K., Fogliano V., Luning P.A. Food safety culture assessment using a comprehensive mixed-methods approach: A comparative study in dairy processing organizations in an emerging economy. Food Control. 2018;84:186–196. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.07.038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.07.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanin L.M., Stedefeldt E., da Silva S.M., da Cunha D.T., Luning P.A. Influence of educational actions on transitioning of food safety culture in a food service context: Part 2-effectiveness of educational actions in a longitudinal study. Food Control. 2021;120:107542. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Escanciano C., Leticia Santos-Vijande M. Implementation of ISO-22000 in Spain: Obstacles and key benefits. Br. Food J. 2014;116:1581–1599. doi: 10.1108/BFJ-02-2013-0034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/BFJ-02-2013-0034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotsanopoulos K.V., Arvanitoyannis I.S. The Role of auditing, food safety, and food quality standards in the food industry: A review. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2017;16:760–775. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33371608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J.C., Neonaki M., Alexopoulos A., Varzakas T. Case studies of small-medium food enterprises around the world: Major constraints and benefits from the implementation of food safety management systems. Foods. 2023;12:3218. doi: 10.3390/foods12173218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12173218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10486654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37685151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng T.W.H., Sorensen K.L., Eby L.T. Locus of control at work: A meta-analysis. Int. J. Ind. Occup. Organ. Psychol. Behav. 2006;27:1057–1087. doi: 10.1002/job.416.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/job.416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Boeck E., Mortier A.V., Jacxsens L., Dequidt L., Vlerick P. Towards an extended food safety culture model: Studying the moderating role of burnout and jobstress, the mediating role of food safety knowledge and motivation in the relation between food safety climate and food safety behavior. Trend Food Sci. Technol. 2017;62:202–214. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2017.01.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2017.01.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones J., Wuebker L. Safety locus of control and employees accidents. J. Bus. Psychol. 1993;7:449–457. doi: 10.1007/BF01013758.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF01013758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christian M.S., Bradley J.C., Wallace J.C., Burke M.J. Workplace safety: A meta-analysis of the roles of person and situation factors. J. Appl. Psychol. 2009;94:1103–1127. doi: 10.1037/a0016172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/a0016172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19702360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahdinia M., Mohammadfam I., Soltanzadeh A., Aliabadi M.M., Aghaei H. A fuzzy Bayesian network DEMATEL model for predicting safety behavior. Int. J. Occup. Saf. Ergon. 2024;29:36–43. doi: 10.1080/10803548.2021.2015741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10803548.2021.2015741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34898390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto K., Gonçalves G., Sousa C., Sousa A. Individual factors as predictors of risk perception: Mediation of the physical safety climate, in a sample of Portuguese workers. In: Arezes P.M., Melo R.B., Carneiro P., Castelo Branco J., Colim A., Costa N., Costa S., Duarte J., Guedes J.C., Perestrelo G., et al., editors. Occupational and Environmental Safety and Health V. Volume 492. Springer; Cham, Switzerland: 2024. pp. 547–555. Studies in Systems, Decision and Control.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-38277-2_44</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haasa E.J., Yorio P.L. The role of risk avoidance and locus of control in workers’ near miss experiences: Implications for improving safety management systems. J. Loss Prev. Process Ind. 2019;59:91–99. doi: 10.1016/j.jlp.2019.03.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jlp.2019.03.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7479994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32913382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Cunha D.T., Braga A.R.C., Passos E.D.C., Stedefeldt E., de Rosso V.V. The existence of optimistic bias about foodborne disease by food handlers and its association with training participation and food safety performance. Food Res. Int. 2015;75:27–33. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2015.05.035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2015.05.035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28454956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Freitas G.R.S., da Cunha D.T., Stedefeldt E. Food safety knowledge as gateway to cognitive illusions of food handlers and the different degrees of risk perception. Food Res. Int. 2019;116:126–134. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2018.12.058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2018.12.058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30716914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cronbach L.J. Coefficient alpha and the internal structure of tests. Psychometrika. 1951;16:297–334. doi: 10.1007/BF02310555.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF02310555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Cunha D.T., Stedefeldt E., de Rosso V.V. He is worse than I am: The positive outlook of food handlers about foodborne disease. Food Qual. Prefer. 2014;35:95–97. doi: 10.1016/j.foodqual.2014.02.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2014.02.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomasevica I., Bursać Kovačević D., Režek Jambrak A., Szendrő K., Dalle Zotte A., Prodanov M., Sołowiej B., Sirbu A., Subić J., Roljević S., et al. Validation of novel food safety climate components and assessment of their indicators in Central and Eastern European food industry. Food Control. 2020;117:107357. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinstein N.D. Optimistic biases about personal risks. Science. 1989;246:1232–1233. doi: 10.1126/science.2686031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.2686031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2686031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miles S., Scaife V. Optimistic bias and food. Nutr. Res. Rev. 2003;16:3–19. doi: 10.1079/NRR200249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1079/NRR200249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19079933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parry S.M., Miles S., Tridente A., Palmer S.R., Gardner D. Differences in perception of risk between people who have and have not experienced Salmonella food poisoning. Risk Anal. 2004;24:289–299. doi: 10.1111/j.0272-4332.2004.00429.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.0272-4332.2004.00429.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15028018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu K., Park K.-H., Yang J.-Y., Bahk G.-J. Simple approach in HACCP for evaluating the risk level of hazards using probability distributions. Food Control. 2013;30:459–462. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.07.042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.07.042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer J.P., Allen N.J. A three-component conceptualization of organizational commitment. Hum. Resour. Manag. Rev. 1991;1:61–89. doi: 10.1016/1053-4822(91)90011-Z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/1053-4822(91)90011-Z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma J., Dhar R.L. Factors influencing job performance of nursing staff. Pers. Rev. 2016;45:161–182. doi: 10.1108/PR-01-2014-0007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/PR-01-2014-0007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taha S., Osaili T.M., Vij A., Albloush A., Nassoura A. Structural modelling of relationships between food safety knowledge, attitude, commitment and behavior of food handlers in restaurants in Jebel Ali Free Zone, Dubai, UAE. Food Control. 2020;118:107431. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taha S., Zanin L.M., Osaili T.M. Studying the perception of leadership styles and food handlers’ hygienic practices in food businesses: The role of commitment and job satisfaction as mediators. Food Control. 2024;157:110148. doi: 10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jevšnik M., Kirbiš A., Vadnjal S., Jamnikar-Ciglenecki U., Ovca A., Kavcic M. Food safety knowledge among professional food handlers in Slovenia: The results of a nation-wide survey. Foods. 2023;12:2735. doi: 10.3390/foods12142735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12142735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10379724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37509827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berglund Z., Simsek S., Feng Y. Effectiveness of online food-safety educational programs: A systematic review, random-effects meta-analysis, and thematic synthesis. Foods. 2024;13:794. doi: 10.3390/foods13050794.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13050794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10931379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38472907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kollmuss A., Agyeman J. Mind the Gap: Why do people act environmentally and what are the barriers to pro-environmental behavior? Environ. Educ. Res. 2002;8:239–260. doi: 10.1080/13504620220145401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13504620220145401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burke M.J., Scheuer M.L., Meredith R.J. A dialogical approach to skill development: The case of safety skills. Hum. Res. Dev. J. 2007;17:235–250. doi: 10.1016/j.hrmr.2007.04.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hrmr.2007.04.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nykänen M., Salmela-Aro K., Tolvanen A., Vuori J. Safety self-efficacy and internal locus of control as mediators of safety motivation–Randomized controlled trial (RCT) study. Saf. Sci. 2019;117:330–338. doi: 10.1016/j.ssci.2019.04.037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2019.04.037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marconi F., Sartoni M., Nuvoloni R., Torracca B., Gagliardi M., Zappalà G., Guidi A., Pedonese F. Food safety culture in food companies: Evaluation of the perception of food safety culture in three Tuscan food companies. Ital. J. Food Saf. 2023;12:11012. doi: 10.4081/ijfs.2023.11012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/ijfs.2023.11012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10102961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37064518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>