<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39271561</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1867-1314</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Probiotics and antimicrobial proteins</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Functional Effects of Probiotic Lactiplantibacillus plantarum in Alleviation Multidrug-Resistant Escherichia coli-Associated Colitis in BALB/c Mice Model.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12602-024-10356-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Multidrug-resistant Escherichia coli (MDR-E. coli) is a global health concern. Lactic acid bacteria (LAB) are important probiotics that have beneficial effects on health, and in recent years, their influences in preventing foodborne pathogens-induced colitis have attracted much attention. Therefore, this study aimed to investigate the oral administration of Lactiplantibacillus plantarum NWAFU-BIO-BS29 as an emerging approach to alleviate MDR-E. coli-induced colitis in BALB/c mice model. To illustrate the mode of action of NWAFU-BIO-BS29 interventions with the gut microbiota and immune responses, the changes on the colonic mucosal barrier, regulatory of the gene expressions of inflammatory cytokines, re-modulating the intestinal microflora, and changes in physiological parameters were studied. The results indicated that daily supplementation of 200 µL fresh bacteria for 7 days had ameliorated the associated colitis and partially prevented the infection. The modes of action by ameliorating the inflammatory response, which destructed villous and then affected the intestinal barrier integrity, reducing the secretion of interleukins (6 and β) and tumor necrosis factor (TNF-α) in serum by 87.88-89.93%, 30.73-35.98%, and 19.14-22.32%, respectively, enhancing the expressions of some epithelial integrity-related proteins in the mouse mucous layer of mucins 2 and 3, Claudin-1, and Occludin by 130.00-661.85%, 27.64-57.35%, 75.52-162.51%, and 139.36-177.73%, respectively, and 56.09-73.58% for toll-like receptor (TLR4) in colon tissues. Notably, the mouse gut microbiota analysis showed an increase in the relative abundance of beneficial bacteria, including Lactobacillus, Bacteriodales bacterium, Candidatus Saccharimonas, Enterorhabdus, and Bacilli. Furthermore, the probiotic promoted the proliferation of epithelia and goblet cells by increasing short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) levels by 19.23-31.39%. In conclusion, L. plantarum NWAFU-BIO-BS29 has potential applications and can be considered a safe dietary supplement to ameliorate the colitis inflammation symptoms of MDR-E. coli infection.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ismael</LastName><ForeName>Mohamedelfatieh</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Food Quality and Safety, College of Food Science, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab of Bioresource, College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, 712100, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sudanese Standards and Metrology Organization, Khartoum, 13573, Sudan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qayyum</LastName><ForeName>Nageena</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab of Bioresource, College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, 712100, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gu</LastName><ForeName>Yaxin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, China Agricultural University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Na</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab of Bioresource, College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, 712100, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haoyue</LastName><ForeName>Han</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab of Bioresource, College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, 712100, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farooq</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab of Bioresource, College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, 712100, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Panpan</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab of Bioresource, College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, 712100, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhong</LastName><ForeName>Qingping</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Food Quality and Safety, College of Food Science, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China. zhongqp@scau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lü</LastName><ForeName>Xin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab of Bioresource, College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, 712100, China. xinlu@nwsuaf.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101484100</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1867-1306</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lactiplantibacillus plantarum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gut microbiota</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immune system</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Inflammatory cytokine expression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multidrug-resistant Escherichia coli</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Probiotics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39271561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-024-10356-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12602-024-10356-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Dall LB, Lausch KR, Gedebjerg A, Fuursted K, Storgaard M, Larsen CS (2019) Do probiotics prevent colonization with multi-resistant Enterobacteriaceae during travel? A randomized controlled trial. Travel Med Infect Dis 27:81–86</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30508633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2018.11.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Kumar A (2022) Microbial pathogenesis in inflammatory bowel diseases. Microb Pathog 163:105383</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34974120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2021.105383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubinsky V, Reshef L, Rabinowitz K, Wasserberg N, Dotan I, Gophna U (2022) Escherichia coli strains from patients with inflammatory bowel diseases have disease-specific genomic adaptations. J Crohns Colitis 16(10):1584–1597</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35560165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjac071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu GW, Pang B, Li N, Jin H, Li JJ, Wu WQ, Ai CY, Jiang CM, Shi JL (2020) Therapeutic effect of Lactobacillus rhamnosusSHA113 on intestinal infection by multi-drug-resistant Staphylococcus aureus and its underlying mechanisms. Food Funct 11(7):6226–6239</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32589178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0FO00969E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilliland A, Chan JJ, De Wolfe TJ, Yang H, Vallance BA (2024) Pathobionts in inflammatory bowel disease: origins, underlying mechanisms, and implications for clinical care. Gastroenterology 166(1):44–58</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37734419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2023.09.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai YF, Wang GH, Qi H, Wang YP, Xu C, Yue L, Hou XL, Yu LY (2020) Immunogenicity of 987P fimbriae of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli surface-displayed on Lactobacillus casei. Res Vet Sci 128:308–314</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31901569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2019.12.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain A, Shaik S, Ranjan A, Nandanwar N, Tiwari SK, Majid M, Baddam R, Qureshi IA, Semmler T, Wieler LH et al (2017) Risk of transmission of antimicrobial resistant Escherichia coli from commercial broiler and free-range retail chicken in India. Front Microbiol 8:2120</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29180984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5694193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.02120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atumanya P, Sendagire C, Wabule A, Mukisa J, Ssemogerere L, Kwizera A, Agaba PK (2020) Assessment of the current capacity of intensive care units in Uganda; a descriptive study. J Crit Care 55:95–99</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31715537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcrc.2019.10.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Shi C, Wang S, Zhang Y, Wang S, Ismael M, Zhang J, Wang X, Lü X (2022) Protective effects of Companilactobacillus crustorum MN047 against dextran sulfate sodium-induced ulcerative colitis: a fecal microbiota transplantation study. J Agric Food Chem 70(5):1547–1561</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35077172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.1c07316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Hu D, Tian Y, Song Y, Hou Y, Sun L, Zhang Y, Man C, Zhang W, Jiang Y (2020) Protective effects of a novel Lactobacillus rhamnosus strain with probiotic characteristics against lipopolysaccharide-induced intestinal inflammation in vitro and in vivo. Food Funct 11(7):5799–5814</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32568317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0FO00308E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun SW, Kim JK, Lee KE, Oh YJ, Choi HJ, Han MJ, Kim DH (2020) A Probiotic Lactobacillus gasseri alleviates Escherichia coli-induced cognitive impairment and depression in mice by regulating il-1 beta expression and gut microbiota. Nutrients 12(11):3441</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33182607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7697804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu12113441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Wang S, Dong S, Zhang Y, Ismael M, Wang S, Shi C, Yang J, Wang X, Lü X (2022) Interaction of Companilactobacillus crustorum MN047-derived bacteriocins with gut microbiota. Food Chem 396:133730</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35878442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.133730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tu A, Wang XC, Chen H, Jia X, Wang T, Yi Y, Liu B, Xin W, Lü X, Shan Y (2021) Ovomucin ameliorates intestinal barrier and intestinal bacteria to attenuate DSS-induced colitis in mice. J Agric Food Chem 69(21):5887–5896</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34013725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.1c00865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li N, Pang B, Li JJ, Liu GW, Xu XG, Shao DY, Jiang CM, Yang BW, Shi JL (2020) Mechanisms for Lactobacillus rhamnosus treatment of intestinal infection by drug-resistant Escherichia coli. Food Funct 11(5):4428–4445</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32374342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0FO00128G</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Zheng J, Dong S, Ismael M, Shan Y, Wang X, Lü X (2022) Lacticaseibacillus rhamnosus LS8 ameliorates azoxymethane/dextran sulfate sodium-induced colitis-associated tumorigenesis in mice via regulating gut microbiota and inhibiting inflammation. Probiotics Antimicro Prot 14:947</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-022-09967-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aditya A, Peng MF, Young A, Biswas D (2020) Antagonistic mechanism of metabolites produced by Lactobacillus casei on lysis of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli. Front Microbiol 11:574422</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33329433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7719638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.574422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M, Dhaka P, Vijay D, Vergis J, Mohan V, Kumar A, Kurkure NV, Barbuddhe SB, Malik SVS, Rawool DB (2016) Antimicrobial effects of Lactobacillus plantarum and Lactobacillus acidophilus against multidrug-resistant enteroaggregative Escherichia coli. Int J Antimicrob Agents 48(3):265–270</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27451088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2016.05.014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat MI, Kapila S, Kapila R (2020) Lactobacillus fermentum (MTCC-5898) supplementation renders prophylactic action against Escherichia coli impaired intestinal barrier function through tight junction modulation. Lwt-Food Sci Technol 123:109118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang KMM, Zhu C, Wang L, Cao STT, Yang XFF, Gao KGG, Jiang ZYY (2021) Early supplementation with Lactobacillus plantarum in liquid diet modulates intestinal innate immunity through toll-like receptor 4-mediated mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling pathways in young piglets challenged with Escherichia coli K88. J Animal Sci 99(6):skab128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skab128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho SW, El-Nezami H, Shah NP (2020) The protective effects of enriched citrulline fermented milk with Lactobacillus helveticus on the intestinal epithelium integrity against Escherichia coli infection. Sci Rep 10(1):499</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31949265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6965087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-57478-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kathayat D, Closs G, Helmy YA, Deblais L, Srivastava V, Rajashekara G (2022) In vitro and in vivo evaluation of Lacticaseibacillus rhamnosus GG and Bifidobacterium lactis Bb12 against avian pathogenic Escherichia coli and identification of novel probiotic-derived bioactive peptides. Probiotics &amp; Antimicro Prot 14:1012–1028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu CL, Yan SQ, Guo Y, Qiao L, Ma L, Dou X, Zhang BH (2020) Lactobacillus casei ATCC 393 alleviates enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli K88-induced intestinal barrier dysfunction via TLRs/mast cells pathway. Life Sciences 244:117281</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31926249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2020.117281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fayyaz I, Zahoor MA, Shahid M, Rasool MH, Nawaz Z (2018) Effect of Lactobacillus casei on serum interleukins following enteropathogenic E. coli infection in experimental rabbits. Pak J Pharmaceut Sci 31(5):2131–2136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y, Ni XQ, Duan L, Niu LL, Liu Q, Zeng Y, Wang Q, Wang J, Khalique A, Pan KC et al (2021) Lactobacillus plantarum BSGP201683 improves the intestinal barrier of giant panda microbiota-associated mouse infected by enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli K88. Probiotics Antimicro Prot 13(3):664–676</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-020-09722-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismael M, Gu Y, Cui Y, Wang T, Yue F, Yantin Q, Lü X (2022) Lactic acid bacteria isolated from Chinese traditional fermented milk as novel probiotic strains and their potential therapeutic applications. 3 Biotech 12(12):337</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36340806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9626708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13205-022-03403-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismael M, Wang T, Yue F, Cui Y, Yantin Q, Qayyum N, Lü X (2023) A comparison of mining methods to extract novel bacteriocins from Lactiplantibacillus plantarum NWAFU-BIO-BS29. Anal Biochem 661:114938</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36379249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2022.114938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo X, Chen J, Sun H, Luo L, Gu Y, Yi Y, Wang X, Shan Y, Liu B, Zhou Y et al (2020) Mining, heterologous expression, purification and characterization of 14 novel bacteriocins from Lactobacillus rhamnosus LS-8. Int J Biol Macromol 164:2162–2176</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32791267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.08.067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Wang P, Ge W, Shi C, Xiao G, Wang X, Lü X (2021) Protective effect of a multi-strain probiotics mixture on azoxymethane/dextran sulfate sodium-induced colon carcinogenesis. Food Biosci 44:101346</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2021.101346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li N, Pang B, Liu G, Zhao X, Xu X, Jiang C, Yang B, Liu Y, Shi J (2020) Lactobacillus rhamnosus from human breast milk shows therapeutic function against foodborne infection by multi-drug resistant Escherichia coli in mice. Food Funct 11(1):435–447</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31829373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C9FO01698H</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu ZK, Yang KX, Zhang AR, Chang WH, Zheng AJ, Chen ZM, Cai H, Liu GH (2021) Effects of Lactobacillus acidophilus on the growth performance, immune response, and intestinal barrier function of broiler chickens challenged with Escherichia coli O157. Poultry Science 100(9):101323</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34280647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8319008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Zhang L, Wang P, Liu Y, Wang G, Shan Y, Yi Y, Zhou Y, Liu B, Wang X et al (2022) Lactobacillus coryniformis MXJ32 administration ameliorates azoxymethane/dextran sulfate sodium-induced colitis-associated colorectal cancer via reshaping intestinal microenvironment and alleviating inflammatory response. Eur J Nutr 61(1):85–99</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34185157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00394-021-02627-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang WF, Li HT, Zhou HY, Wang M, Zhao X, Sun XH, Li CT, Zhang XM (2021) Effects of Taraxacum and Astragalus extracts combined with probiotic Bacillus subtilis and Lactobacillus on Escherichia coli-infected broiler chickens. Poultry Science 100(4):101007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33647724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7921871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.01.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Yan H, Lu Y, Li X, Wang X, Shan Y, Yi Y, Liu B, Zhou Y, Lü X (2020) Anti-obesity effect of Lactobacillus rhamnosus LS-8 and Lactobacillus crustorum MN047 on high-fat and high-fructose diet mice base on inflammatory response alleviation and gut microbiota regulation. Eur J Nutr 59(6):2709–2728</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31659451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00394-019-02117-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu T, Shi YT, Zhang YY, Zhang M, Zhang LJ, Ma ZP, Zhao D, Wang L, Yu H, Hou YQ et al (2021) Lactobacillus rhamnosus LB1 alleviates enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli-Induced adverse effects in piglets by improving host immune response and anti-oxidation stress and restoring intestinal integrity. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 11:724401</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34796123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8594739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.724401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Sun H, Chen J, Luo L, Gu Y, Wang X, Shan Y, Yi Y, Liu B, Zhou Y et al (2021) Anti-adhesion effects of Lactobacillus strains on caco-2 cells against Escherichia coli and their application in ameliorating the symptoms of dextran sulfate sodium-induced colitis in mice. Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins 13(6):1632–1643</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33851347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-021-09774-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu C, Lv YT, Yang J, Bai YS, Ye JL, Wang ZL, Chen Z, Jiang ZY (2020) Proteomic alteration of porcine intestinal epithelial cells after pretreatment with Lactobacillus plantarum followed by infection with enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli F4. Vet Immunol Immunopathol 222:109943</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32146421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2019.109943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nieto-Veloza A, Wang Z, Zhong Q, D’Souza D, Krishnan HB, Dia VP (2022) Lunasin protease inhibitor concentrate decreases pro-inflammatory cytokines and improves histopathological markers in dextran sodium sulfate-induced ulcerative colitis. Food Sci Human Wellness 11(6):1508–1514</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fshw.2022.06.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Wang P, Ge W, Shi C, Xiao G, Wang X, Lü X (2021) The probiotic Companilactobacillus crustorum MN047 alleviates colitis-associated tumorigenesis via modulating the intestinal microenvironment. Food Funct 12(22):11331–11342</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34668003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1FO01531A</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao CJ, Hu XY, Bao LJ, Wu KY, Feng LJ, Qiu M, Hao HY, Fu YH, Zhang NS (2021) Aryl hydrocarbon receptor activation by Lactobacillus reuteri tryptophan metabolism alleviates Escherichia coli-induced mastitis in mice. Plos Pathogens 17(7):e1009774</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34297785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8336809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1009774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yue Y, He ZJ, Zhou YH, Ross RP, Stanton C, Zhao JX, Zhang H, Yang B, Chen W (2020) Lactobacillus plantarum relieves diarrhea caused by enterotoxin-producing Escherichia coli through inflammation modulation and gut microbiota regulation. Food Funct 11(12):10362–10374</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33220669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0FO02670K</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismael M, Gu Y, Cui Y, Wang T, Yue F, Qin Y, Lü X (2022) Probiotic of Lactiplantibacillus plantarum NWAFU-BIO-BS29 isolated from Chinese traditional fermented milk and its potential therapeutic applications based on gut microbiota regulation. Foods 11(23):3766</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36496574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9738876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11233766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q, Zhang LJ, Lyu Y, Shi YT, Zhu LY, Zhang M, Zhao YY, Zhao D, Wang L, Yi D et al (2022) p Dietary supplementation of Lactobacillus zeae regulated the gut microbiome in piglets infected with enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli. Czeh J Anim Sci 67(1):27–38</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17221/136/2021-CJAS</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Zhang Y, Wei K, He J, Ding N, Hua J, Zhou T, Niu F, Zhou G, Shi T et al (2021) Review: effect of gut microbiota and its metabolite SCFAs on radiation-induced intestinal injury. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 11:577236</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34307184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8300561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.577236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li YS, San Andres JV, Trenhaile-Grannemann MD, van Sambeek DM, Moore KC, Winkel SM, Fernando SC, Burkey TE, Miller PS (2021) Effects of mannan oligosaccharides and Lactobacillus mucosae on growth performance, immune response, and gut health of weanling pigs challenged with Escherichia coli lipopolysaccharides. J Animal Sci 99(12):skab286</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skab286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koo B, Bustamante-Garcia D, Kim JW, Nyachoti CM (2020) Health-promoting effects of Lactobacillus-fermented barley in weaned pigs challenged with Escherichia coli K88 (+). Animal 14(1):39–49</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31426877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1751731119001939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaewchomphunuch T, Charoenpichitnunt T, Thongbaiyai V, Ngamwongsatit N, Kaeoket K (2022) Cell-free culture supernatants of Lactobacillus spp. and Pediococcus spp. inhibit growth of pathogenic Escherichia coli isolated from pigs in Thailand. Bmc Vet Res 18(1):60</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35093088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8800250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12917-022-03140-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawrence GW, McCarthy N, Walsh CJ, Kunyoshi TM, Lawton EM, O’Connor PM, Begley M, Cotter PD, Guinane CM (2022) Effect of a bacteriocin-producing Streptococcus salivarius on the pathogen Fusobacterium nucleatum in a model of the human distal colon. Gut Microbes 14(1):2100203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35877697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9318236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/19490976.2022.2100203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang G, Tang H, Zhang Y, Xiao X, Xia Y, Ai L (2020) The intervention effects of Lactobacillus casei LC2W on Escherichia coli O157:H7 -induced mouse colitis. Food Sci Human Wellness 9(3):289–294</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fshw.2020.04.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie J, Yu Q, Nie S, Fan S, Xiong T, Xie M (2015) Effects of Lactobacillus plantarum NCU116 on intestine mucosal immunity in immunosuppressed mice. J Agric Food Chem 63(51):10914–10920</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26651209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.5b04757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JK, Lee KE, Lee SA, Jang HM, Kim DH (2020) Interplay between human gut bacteria Escherichia coli and Lactobacillus mucosae in the occurrence of neuropsychiatric disorders in mice. Front Immunol 11:273</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32158447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7051986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell JG, Kogure K (2006) Bacterial motility: links to the environment and a driving force for microbial physics. FEMS Microbiol Ecol 55(1):3–16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16420610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2005.00003.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng S, Li B, Ding Y, Hou B, Hung W, He J, Jiang Y, Zhang Y, Man C (2024) The probiotic fermented milk of Lacticaseibacillus paracasei JY062 and Lactobacillus gasseri JM1 alleviates constipation via improving gastrointestinal motility and gut microbiota. J Dairy Sci 107(4):1857–1876</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37923200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2023-24154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valvaikar S, Vaidya B, Sharma S, Bishnoi M, Kondepudi KK, Sharma SS (2024) Supplementation of probiotic Bifidobacterium breve Bif11 reverses neurobehavioural deficits, inflammatory changes and oxidative stress in Parkinson’s disease model. Neurochem Int 174:105691</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38311217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2024.105691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Wang J, Wu C (2022) Modulation of gut microbiota and immune system by probiotics, pre-biotics, and post-biotics. Front Nutr 8:634897</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35047537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8761849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2021.634897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azad MAK, Sarker M, Li T, Yin J (2018) Probiotic species in the modulation of gut microbiota: an overview. Biomed Res Int 2018:9478630</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29854813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5964481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/9478630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Y, Liu G, Wang W, Wang Y, Cao Z, Yang H, Li S (2021) Lactobacillus casei Zhang counteracts blood-milk barrier disruption and moderates the inflammatory response in Escherichia coli-induced mastitis. Front Microbiol 12:675492</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34248887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8264260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.675492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang KM, Zhu C, Wang L, Cao ST, Yang XF, Gao KG, Jiang ZY (2021) Early supplementation with Lactobacillus plantarum in liquid diet modulates intestinal innate immunity through toll-like receptor 4-mediated mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling pathways in young piglets challenged with Escherichia coli K88. J Anim Sci 99(6):skab128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33928383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8212570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jas/skab128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhi S, Szelewicki J, Ziebell K, Parsons B, Chui L (2019) General detection of Shiga toxin 2 and subtyping of Shiga toxin 1 and 2 in Escherichia coli using qPCR. J Microbiol Methods 159:51–55</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30772308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2019.02.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>