<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39282191</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0046-8991</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>64</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Indian journal of microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Indian J Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Role of Food Safety Regulations in Protecting Public Health.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1376</StartPage><EndPage>1378</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1376-1378</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12088-024-01240-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Food safety is a critical public health issue worldwide as the consumption of unhygienic food causes millions of illnesses annually. The contaminated food is primarily unsafe due to the presence of microorganisms (i.e. bacteria and viruses), chemicals (i.e. pesticides and heavy metals), and physical hazards (i.e. glass, metal and plastic). Foodborne illnesses such as salmonellosis, campylobacteriosis, listeriosis, <i>E. coli</i> infection, botulism, cholera, norovirus infection, and others are commonly caused by the problems associated with food hygiene. From the modest beginnings rooted in basic hygiene practices to the sophisticated frameworks of the modern era, the journey of food regulatory bodies has been marked by a commitment to protect consumers from the hazards associated with foodborne illnesses. In India, the 'Food Safety and Standards Authority of India sets standards, inspects food businesses, and acts against food safety violators. However, there is still more work to be done, including the effective enforcement of regulations, and thoroughly educating the consumers about food safety. The need of the hour is a multi-dimensional collaboration among different stakeholders to ensure that everyone has access to safe and nutritious food. In developing countries, the hurdles in preventing food adulteration include poor consumer awareness and insufficient resources for the enforcement of food regulations. Despite complications, the 'Food Safety and Standards Authority of India' is committed to improving food safety for consumers through cooperation with other agencies, increased enforcement, and public awareness initiatives. Developing countries face lots of challenges in regulating the safety of loose milk and street foods; including the problems of traceability, resource limitations, variety of techniques, cultural acceptance, and financial concerns. A multifaceted strategy that includes infrastructural development, consumer education, regulatory strengthening, and technological acceptance is needed to overcome all these problems linked to the safety of street foods and loose milk. Food regulators must set strict guidelines, conduct regular inspections, and licenses and training for various stakeholders involved. Proper education for customers should increase awareness and provide them with the latest information related to food safety. Access to clean water, sanitary facilities, waste management, and technological adoption should be the main priorities of infrastructure development. Challenges of traceability and labelling in loose milk and street foods include the threats of adulteration, inability to determine the origin, and improper labelling. Vendor registration, uniform labelling, stringent enforcement of food safety regulations, improved supply chain monitoring, consumer education, and technological adoption are all necessary to fully address these problems of food safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Association of Microbiologists of India 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Rameshwar</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bihar Animal Sciences University, Patna, Bihar India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Puniya</LastName><ForeName>Anil Kumar</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0043-5330</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-National Dairy Research Institute, Karnal, Haryana India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/03ap5bg83</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.419332.e</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2114 9718</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Indian J Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0374703</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0046-8991</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food regulations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food standards</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39282191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11399481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12088-024-01240-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>