<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39280834</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2297-1769</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in veterinary science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Vet Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The role of syndromic knowledge in Ethiopian veterinarians' treatment of cattle.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1364963</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1364963</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1364963</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fvets.2024.1364963</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Veterinarians play a significant role in the treatment and prevention of livestock diseases at the farm level, safeguarding public health and ensuring food safety. In sub-Saharan Africa, access to quality veterinary services is a major challenge for livestock farmers due to the low number of publicly employed veterinarians, underfunding and privatisation of veterinary services. Low investment in veterinary services and infrastructure, including a lack of laboratories for diagnosis, has made veterinarians rely on their experience and knowledge of cattle disease symptoms developed over years of practice to diagnose and treat cattle diseases. A cross-sectional survey using a role-play approach was used to collect data on knowledge regarding cattle diseases among veterinarians in veterinary clinics and private practices in Addis Ababa, Oromia and Adama regions in Ethiopia. Veterinarians were given a number of disease scenarios based on "fictive disease symptoms" that are commonly manifested in a sick cow and asked to identify the disease what personal biosecurity they would use, diagnostic tests they would perform, treatments they would prescribe, treatment costs, and additional services and inputs they would recommend to the farmer. The results show that veterinarians could identify endemic cattle diseases through symptoms. The majority of veterinarians did not find it important to report notifiable diseases, a behaviour which could hamper disease surveillance and outbreak response. The advice and services the veterinarians said they would offer and recommend to farmers included improvement in feeding, vaccination, use of artificial insemination, and adoption of farm biosecurity measures that can reduce disease prevalence, and improve food safety, animal health and welfare. Low use of personal protective equipment and other protective biosecurity measures among veterinarians could expose them to zoonotic diseases. The study concludes that there is a need for increased funding for continuous training, improved access to animal health-related information, and investment in infrastructure such as laboratories to enable veterinarians to deliver quality animal health services.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Nyokabi, Wood, Gemechu, Berg, Mihret, Lindahl and Moore.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nyokabi</LastName><ForeName>Ndungu S</ForeName><Initials>NS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Prosperity, University College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Edinburgh Business School, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wood</LastName><ForeName>James L N</ForeName><Initials>JLN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gemechu</LastName><ForeName>Gizachew</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Armauer Hansen Research Institute, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berg</LastName><ForeName>Stefan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bernhard Nocht Institute for Tropical Medicine, Hamburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mihret</LastName><ForeName>Adane</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Armauer Hansen Research Institute, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lindahl</LastName><ForeName>Johanna F</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI), Nairobi, Kenya.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biochemistry and Microbiology, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Sciences, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Uppsala, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moore</LastName><ForeName>Henrietta L</ForeName><Initials>HL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Prosperity, University College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Vet Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101666658</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2297-1769</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">animal health services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biosecurity practices</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cattle diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dairy cattle</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disease surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">herd health management</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">one health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">zoonoses</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39280834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11392921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1364963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kerwick CM, Meers J, Phillips CJC. Training veterinary personnel for effective identification and diagnosis of exotic animal diseases. J Vet Med Educ. (2008) 35:255–61. doi: 10.3138/jvme.35.2.255, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3138/jvme.35.2.255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18723812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright JG, Jung S, Holman RC, Marano NN, McQuiston JH. Infection control practices and zoonotic disease risks among veterinarians in the United States. J Am Vet Med Assoc. (2008) 232:1863–72. doi: 10.2460/javma.232.12.1863</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2460/javma.232.12.1863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18598158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molyneux D, Hallaj Z, Keusch GT, McManus DP, Ngowi H, Cleaveland S, et al. . Zoonoses and marginalised infectious diseases of poverty: where do we stand? Parasites Vectors. (2011) 4:2–7. doi: 10.1186/1756-3305-4-106, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-4-106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3128850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21672216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavalerie L, Wardeh M, Lebrasseur O, Nanyingi M, McIntyre KM, Kaba M, et al. . One hundred years of zoonoses research in the horn of Africa: a scoping review. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. (2021) 15:e0009607. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0009607, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0009607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8318308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34270551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayen F. A status report of veterinary education in Ethiopia: perceived needs, past history, recent changes, and current and future concerns. J Vet Med Educ. (2006) 33:244–7. doi: 10.3138/jvme.33.2.244, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3138/jvme.33.2.244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16849305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alafiatayo R, Galipo E, Ekiri AB, Dineva M, Endacott I, Tesfaye T, et al. . Training needs assessment of veterinary practitioners in Ethiopia. Trop Anim Health Prod. (2022) 54:72–11. doi: 10.1007/s11250-022-03075-0, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11250-022-03075-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8783848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35064854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon G, Hiwot D, Dagim B, Barbara W. A narrative review of animal health interventions for designing herd health interventions for Ethiopia. Joint ILRI and EVA Project Report. Addis Ababa, Ethiopia: (2019). 33</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellemain V. The role of veterinary services in animal health and food safety surveillance, and coordination with other services. OIE Rev Sci Tech. (2013) 32:371–81. doi: 10.20506/rst.32.2.2231, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20506/rst.32.2.2231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24547643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swan GE, Kriek NPJ. Veterinary education in Africa: current and future perspectives. Onderstepoort J Vet Res. (2009) 76:105–14. doi: 10.4102/ojvr.v76i1.73, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4102/ojvr.v76i1.73</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19967935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kebede H, Melaku A, Kebede E. Constraints in animal health service delivery and sustainable improvement alternatives in North Gondar. Ethiopia Onderstepoort J Vet Res. (2014) 81:1–10. doi: 10.4102/ojvr.v81i1.713, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4102/ojvr.v81i1.713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25685946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gummow B. A survey of zoonotic diseases contracted by south African veterinarians. J S Afr Vet Assoc. (2003) 74:72–6. doi: 10.4102/jsava.v74i3.514, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4102/jsava.v74i3.514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15029950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moya S, Tirado F, Espluga J, Ciaravino G, Armengol R, Diéguez J, et al. . Dairy farmers’ decision-making to implement biosecurity measures: a study of psychosocial factors. Transbound Emerg Dis. (2020) 67:698–710. doi: 10.1111/tbed.13387, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/tbed.13387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7079090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31600857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyokabi NS, Phelan L, Lindahl JF, Berg S, Muunda E, Mihret A, et al. . Exploring veterinary students’ awareness and perception of zoonoses risks, infection control practices, and biosecurity measures in Ethiopia. Front Vet Sci. (2024) 11:1–10. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2024.1385849, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1385849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11263103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39044741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fasina FO, Fasanmi OG, Makonnen YJ, Bebay C, Bett B, Roesel K. The one health landscape in sub-Saharan African countries. One Heal. (2021) 13:100325. doi: 10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100325, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8455361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34584927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Garine-Wichatitsky M, Caron A, Kock R, Tschopp R, Munyeme M, Hofmeyr M, et al. . A review of bovine tuberculosis at the wildlife-livestock-human interface in sub-Saharan Africa. Epidemiol Infect. (2013) 141:1342–56. doi: 10.1017/S0950268813000708</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268813000708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9151583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23587372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ducrotoy M, Bertu WJ, Matope G, Cadmus S, Conde-Álvarez R, Gusi AM, et al. . Brucellosis in sub-Saharan Africa: current challenges for management, diagnosis and control. Acta Trop. (2017) 165:179–93. doi: 10.1016/j.actatropica.2015.10.023, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2015.10.023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26551794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>K’Oloo TO, Ilukor J, Mockshell J, Ilatsia ED, Birner R. Are government veterinary paraprofessionals serving the poor? The perceptions of smallholder livestock farmers in Western Kenya. Trop Anim Health Prod. (2015) 47:243–5. doi: 10.1007/s11250-014-0697-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11250-014-0697-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25307762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman Y, Ali SM, Schelling E, Tschopp R, Hattendorf J, Muhumed A, et al. . Integrated community based human and animal syndromic surveillance in Adadle district of the Somali region of Ethiopia. One Heal. (2021) 13:100334. doi: 10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100334, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8515289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34692971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berhanu A., Primary animal health Care in Ethiopia: the experience so far. Primary animal healthcare in the 21st century: Shaping the rules, policies and institutions. Mombasa: African Union; (2003). 1–13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teklu A, Asseged B, Yimer E, Gebeyehu M, Woldesenbet Z. Tuberculous lesions not detected by routine abattoir inspection: the experience of the Hossana municipal abattoir, southern Ethiopia. OIE Rev Sci Tech. (2004) 23:957–64. doi: 10.20506/rst.23.3.1534</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20506/rst.23.3.1534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15861892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okello AL, Bardosh K, Smith J, Welburn SC. One health: past successes and future challenges in three African contexts. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. (2014) 8:1–7. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0002884</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4031173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24851901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gemeda BA, Amenu K, Magnusson U, Dohoo I, Hallenberg GS, Alemayehu G, et al. . Antimicrobial use in extensive smallholder livestock farming Systems in Ethiopia: knowledge, attitudes, and practices of livestock keepers. Front Vet Sci. (2020) 7:1–15. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2020.00055, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.00055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7055293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32175334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leta S, Mesele F. Spatial analysis of cattle and shoat population in Ethiopia: growth trend, distribution and market access. Springerplus. (2014) 3:310. doi: 10.1186/2193-1801-3-310, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/2193-1801-3-310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4078045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25019048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tschopp R, Gemechu G, Wood JLN. A longitudinal study of cattle productivity in intensive dairy farms in Central Ethiopia. Front Vet Sci. (2021) 8:1–11. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2021.698760, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.698760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8387621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34458355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gizaw S, Woldehanna M, Anteneh H, Ayledo G, Awol F, Gebreyohannes G, et al. . Animal health service delivery in crop-livestock and pastoral Systems in Ethiopia. Front Vet Sci. (2021) 8:1–14. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2021.601878, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.601878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8215337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34164445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habitu T, Areda D, Muwonge A, Tessema GT, Skjerve E, Gebrehiwot T. Prevalence and risk factors analysis of bovine tuberculosis in cattle raised in mixed crop-livestock farming system in Tigray region. Ethiopia Transbound Emerg Dis. (2019) 66:488–96. doi: 10.1111/tbed.13050, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/tbed.13050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30372585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekonnen GA, Conlan AJK, Berg S, Ayele BT, Alemu A, Guta S, et al. . Prevalence of bovine tuberculosis and its associated risk factors in the emerging dairy belts of regional cities in Ethiopia. Prev Vet Med. (2019) 168:81–9. doi: 10.1016/j.prevetmed.2019.04.010, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2019.04.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10364076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31097127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amenu K, Wieland B, Szonyi B, Grace D. Milk handling practices and consumption behaviour among Borana pastoralists in southern Ethiopia. J Health Popul Nutr. (2019) 38:6. doi: 10.1186/s41043-019-0163-7, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s41043-019-0163-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6367795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30732649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tegegne A, Hiko A, Elemo KK. Bovine Cysticercosis Human Taenias Animal-Human Health Econ Appr Treatment Trends Kombolcha Town. (2018) 4:15–21. doi: 10.14202/IJOH.2018.15-21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14202/IJOH.2018.15-21</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekonnen GA, Ameni G, Wood JLN, Berg S, Conlan AJK. Network analysis of dairy cattle movement and associations with bovine tuberculosis spread and control in emerging dairy belts of Ethiopia. BMC Vet Res. (2019) 15:262–14. doi: 10.1186/s12917-019-1962-1, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12917-019-1962-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6660945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31349832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deneke TT, Bekele A, Moore HL, Mamo T, Almaw G, Mekonnen GA, et al. . Milk and meat consumption patterns and the potential risk of zoonotic disease transmission among urban and peri-urban dairy farmers in Ethiopia. BMC Public Health. (2022) 22:222. doi: 10.1186/s12889-022-12665-4, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-12665-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8815239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35114957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemma HD, Mengistu A, Kuma T, Kuma B. Improving milk safety at farm-level in an intensive dairy production system: relevance to smallholder dairy producers. Food Qual Saf. (2018) 2:135–43. doi: 10.1093/fqsafe/fyy009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/fqsafe/fyy009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Organisation for Animal Health (WOAH) . Animal Diseases. (2023), Available at: https://www.woah.org/en/what-we-do/animal-health-and-welfare/animal-diseases/ [Accessed June 15, 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duguma B. A survey of management practices and major diseases of dairy cattle in smallholdings in selected towns of Jimma zone, South-Western Ethiopia. Anim Prod Sci. (2020) 60:1838. doi: 10.1071/AN19079</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1071/AN19079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tulu D. Bovine brucellosis: epidemiology, public health implications, and status of brucellosis in Ethiopia. Vet Med Res Reports. (2022) 13:21–30. doi: 10.2147/VMRR.S347337</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/VMRR.S347337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8752066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35028300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Firdessa R, Tschopp R, Wubete A, Sombo M, Hailu E, Erenso G, et al. . High prevalence of bovine tuberculosis in dairy cattle in Central Ethiopia: implications for the dairy industry and public health. PLoS One. (2012) 7:e52851. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0052851, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3532161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23285202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Megersa B, Biffa D, Niguse F, Rufael T, Asmare K, Skjerve E. Cattle brucellosis in traditional livestock husbandry practice in southern and eastern Ethiopia, and its zoonotic implication. Acta Vet Scand. (2011) 53:24. doi: 10.1186/1751-0147-53-24, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1751-0147-53-24</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3083371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21473760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duamor CT, Hampson K, Lankester F, Sambo M, Kreppel K, Wyke S, et al. . Use of lay vaccinators in animal vaccination programmes: a scoping review. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. (2021) 15:e0009691–20. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0009691, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0009691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8378730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34375325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alemayehu G, Mamo G, Desta H, Alemu B, Wieland B. Knowledge, attitude, and practices to zoonotic disease risks from livestock birth products among smallholder communities in Ethiopia. One Heal. (2021) 12:100223. doi: 10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100223, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2021.100223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7879039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33614884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tebug SF, Mouiche MMM, Abia WA, Teno G, Tiambo CK, Moffo F, et al. . Antimicrobial use and practices by animal health professionals in 20 sub-Saharan African countries. Prev Vet Med. (2021) 186:105212. doi: 10.1016/j.prevetmed.2020.105212, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2020.105212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33271469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mutua F, Sharma G, Grace D, Bandyopadhyay S, Shome B, Lindahl J. A review of animal health and drug use practices in India, and their possible link to antimicrobial resistance. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control. (2020) 9:103. doi: 10.1186/s13756-020-00760-3, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13756-020-00760-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7346624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32641109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemma M, Alemu B, Mekonnen M, Wieland B. Community conversations on antimicrobial use and resistance. Nairobi, Kenya: ILRI Editorial and Publishing Services, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia; (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaime G, Hobeika A, Figuié M. Access to veterinary drugs in sub-Saharan Africa: roadblocks and current solutions. Front Vet Sci. (2022) 8:1–13. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2021.558973, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.558973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8959935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35356415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Svensson C, Emanuelson U, Bard AM, Forsberg L, Wickström H, Reyher KK. Communication styles of Swedish veterinarians involved in dairy herd health management: a motivational interviewing perspective. J Dairy Sci. (2019) 102:10173–85. doi: 10.3168/jds.2018-15731, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2018-15731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31521349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ritter C, Jansen J, Roche S, Kelton DF, Adams CL, Orsel K, et al. . Invited review: determinants of farmers’ adoption of management-based strategies for infectious disease prevention and control. J Dairy Sci. (2017) 100:3329–47. doi: 10.3168/jds.2016-11977, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2016-11977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28237585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klous G, Huss A, Heederik DJJ, Coutinho RA. Human–livestock contacts and their relationship to transmission of zoonotic pathogens, a systematic review of literature. One Heal. (2016) 2:65–76. doi: 10.1016/j.onehlt.2016.03.001, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2016.03.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5462650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28616478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fasina FO, LeRoux-Pullen L, Smith P, Debusho LK, Shittu A, Jajere SM, et al. . Knowledge, attitudes, and perceptions associated with antimicrobial stewardship among veterinary students: A multi-country survey from Nigeria, South Africa, and Sudan. Front Public Heal. (2020) 8:517964. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2020.517964, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.517964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7609782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33194938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muca E, Cavallini D, Odore R, Baratta M, Bergero D, Valle E. Are veterinary students using technologies and online learning resources for didactic training? A Mini-Meta analysis. Educ Sci. (2022) 12:80573. doi: 10.3390/educsci12080573</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/educsci12080573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muca E, Cavallini D, Raspa F, Bordin C, Bergero D, Valle E. Integrating new learning methods into equine nutrition classrooms: the importance of students’ perceptions. J Equine Vet. (2023) 126:104537. doi: 10.1016/j.jevs.2023.104537, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jevs.2023.104537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37150232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomlinson M, Rotheram-Borus MJ, Swartz L, Tsai AC. Scaling up mHealth: where is the evidence? PLoS Med. (2013) 10:e1001382. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1001382, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3570540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23424286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nadal D, Beeching S, Cleaveland S, Cronin K, Hampson K, Steenson R, et al. . Rabies and the pandemic: lessons for one health. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. (2022) 116:197–200. doi: 10.1093/trstmh/trab123, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/trstmh/trab123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8890778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34392375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alessia V. Enhance the health status of the nomadic pastoralists in Filtu Woreda, Liben zone, Somali region, Ethiopia: One health operational research report. Ethiopia: Addis Ababa; (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hooper P., Review of animal health service delivery in the mixed crop-livestock system in Ethiopia. (2016). Available at: https://cgspace.cgiar.org/bitstream/handle/10568/73337/LIVES_wp_18.pdf?sequence=1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muca E, Buonaiuto G, Lamanna M, Silvestrelli S, Ghiaccio F, Federiconi A, et al. . Reaching a wider audience: Instagram’s role in dairy cow nutrition education and engagement. Animals. (2023) 13:1–9. doi: 10.3390/ani13223503, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ani13223503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10668764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38003121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan EG, Beatty SH, Gray E, Field N, Liston R, Rhodes V, et al. . Factors affecting retention of veterinary practitioners in Ireland: a cross-sectional study with a focus on clinical practice. Ir Vet J. (2022) 75:1–15. doi: 10.1186/s13620-022-00222-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13620-022-00222-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9172024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35668510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora N, Hanson K, Spicer N, Estifanos AS, Keraga DW, Welearegay AT, et al. . Understanding the importance of non-material factors in retaining community health workers in low-income settings: a qualitative case-study in Ethiopia. BMJ Open. (2020) 10:1–9. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2020-037989, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-037989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7545659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33033092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samuel TA, Ero D, Mor SM. One health insights into pastoralists’ perceptions on zoonotic diseases in Ethiopia: perspectives from south OMO zone of SNNP region. Pastoralism. (2023) 13:274. doi: 10.1186/s13570-023-00274-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13570-023-00274-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Africa one health university network (AFROHUN) . Welcome to Africa one health university network (AFROHUN). Kampala (2020). Available at: https://afrohun.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/WELCOME-TO-AFROHUN.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Münstermann S., Overview of capacity building opportunities in “one health”, internationally and with focus on Africa-a desk top study. (2022). Available at: https://www.giz.de/en/downloads/giz2022-en-overview-of-capacity-building-opportunities-in-one-health.pdf</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>