<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39289806</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Advances and challenges in the fractionation of edible oils and fats through supercritical fluid processing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70017</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70017</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70017</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Petrochemical solvents are widely used for the extraction and fractionation of biomolecules from edible oils and fats at an industrial scale. However, owing to its safety concerns, toxicity, price fluctuations, and sustainability, alternative solvents and technologies have been actively explored in recent years. Technologies, such as ultrasound and microwave-assisted extraction, supercritical carbon dioxide extraction, supercritical fluid fractionation, and sub-critical water extraction, and solvents, like ionic liquids and deep eutectic solvents, are reported for extraction and fractionation of biomolecules. Among them, supercritical carbon dioxide extraction and fractionation are some of the most promising green technologies with the potential to replace petrochemical-based conventional techniques. The addition of cosolvents, such as water, ethanol, and acetone, improves the extraction of amphiphilic and polar compounds from edible oils and fats. Supercritical fluid processing has diverse applications, including concentration of solutes, selective separation of desired molecules, and separation of undesirable compounds from the feed material. Temperature, pressure, particle size, porosity, flow rate, solvent-to-feed ratio, density, viscosity, diffusivity, solubility, partition coefficient, and separation factor are the fundamental factors governing the extraction and fractionation of desired biomolecules from lipids. Supercritical fluids stand alone compared to conventional fluids, because of their tunable solvent properties. Overall, it is to be noted that supercritical fluid-based methods have lots of scope to replace conventional solvent-based methods and progress toward the creation of sustainable food-processing techniques. This review critically evaluates the parameters responsible for the extraction and fractionation of biomolecules from edible oils and fats under supercritical conditions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gigi</LastName><ForeName>A A</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agro-Processing and Technology Division, CSIR-National Institute for Interdisciplinary Science and Technology, Thiruvananthapuram, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), Ghaziabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Praveena</LastName><ForeName>Ug</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agro-Processing and Technology Division, CSIR-National Institute for Interdisciplinary Science and Technology, Thiruvananthapuram, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pillai</LastName><ForeName>Prasanth S</ForeName><Initials>PS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Nutrition, University of Minnesota, Saint Paul, Minnesota, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ragavan</LastName><ForeName>K V</ForeName><Initials>KV</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0359-6172</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agro-Processing and Technology Division, CSIR-National Institute for Interdisciplinary Science and Technology, Thiruvananthapuram, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), Ghaziabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anandharamakrishnan</LastName><ForeName>C</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agro-Processing and Technology Division, CSIR-National Institute for Interdisciplinary Science and Technology, Thiruvananthapuram, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), Ghaziabad, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Coconut Development Board, Ministry of Agriculture and Farmers Welfare, Government of India</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010938">Plant Oils</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012997">Solvents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D005223">Fats</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D025924" MajorTopicYN="Y">Chromatography, Supercritical Fluid</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010938" MajorTopicYN="Y">Plant Oils</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012997" MajorTopicYN="N">Solvents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005223" MajorTopicYN="N">Fats</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">edible lipids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">partition coefficient</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">separation factor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">supercritical fluid extraction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">supercritical fluid fractionation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39289806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abeyrathne, E. D. N. S., Nam, K., &amp; Ahn, D. U. (2021). Analytical methods for lipid oxidation and antioxidant capacity in food systems. Antioxidants, 10(10), 1587. https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox10101587</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad, T., Masoodi, F. A., Rather, S. A., Wani, S. M., &amp; Gull, A. (2019). Supercritical fluid extraction: A review. Journal of Biological and chemical Chronicles, 5(1), 114–122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akanda, M. J. H., Sarker, M. Z. I., Ferdosh, S., Manap, M. Y. A., Ab Rahman, N. N., &amp; Ab Kadir, M. O. (2012). Applications of supercritical fluid extraction (SFE) of palm oil and oil from natural sources. Molecules, 17(2), 1764–1794. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules17021764</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amaral, G. V., Silva, E. K., Cavalcanti, R. N., Cappato, L. P., Guimaraes, J. T., Alvarenga, V. O., Esmerino, E. A., Portela, J. B., Sant'Ana, A. S., Freitas, M. Q., Silva, M. C., Raices, R. S. L., Meireles, M. A. A., &amp; Cruz, A. G. (2017). Dairy processing using supercritical carbon dioxide technology: Theoretical fundamentals, quality and safety aspects. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 64, 94–101. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2017.04.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amaro, H. M., Fernandes, F., Valentão, P., Andrade, P. B., Sousa‐Pinto, I., Malcata, F. X., &amp; Guedes, A. C. (2015). Effect of solvent system on extractability of lipidic components of Scenedesmus obliquus (M2‐1) and Gloeothece sp. on antioxidant scavenging capacity thereof. Marine Drugs, 13(10), 6453–6471. https://doi.org/10.3390/md13106453</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ameer, K., Shahbaz, H. M., &amp; Kwon, J.‐H. (2017). Green extraction methods for polyphenols from plant matrices and their byproducts: A review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 16(2), 295–315. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12253</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anandharamakrishnan, C., Moses, J. A., &amp; Priyanka, S. (2023). Food structure and the complexity of food matrices. In Food digestion and absorption (pp. 290–313). Royal Society of Chemistry. https://doi.org/10.1039/BK9781839162428‐00290</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnáiz, E., Bernal, J., Martín, M. T., García‐Viguera, C., Bernal, J. L., &amp; Toribio, L. (2011). Supercritical fluid extraction of lipids from broccoli leaves. European Journal of Lipid Science and Technology, 113(4), 479–486. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejlt.201000407</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barth, M. M., Zhou, C., Kute, K. M., &amp; Rosenthal, G. A. (1995). Determination of optimum conditions for supercritical fluid extraction of carotenoids from carrot (Daucus carota L.) tissue. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 43(11), 2876–2878. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf00059a019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bozan, B., &amp; Temelli, F. (2002). Supercritical CO2 extraction of flaxseed. Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society, 79(3), 231–235. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11746‐002‐0466‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budich, M., Heilig, S., Wesse, T., Leibküchler, V., &amp; Brunner, G. (1999). Countercurrent deterpenation of citrus oils with supercritical CO2. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 14(2), 105–114. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0896‐8446(98)00112‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budisa, N., &amp; Schulze‐Makuch, D. (2014). Supercritical carbon dioxide and its potential as a life‐sustaining solvent in a planetary environment. Life : Open Access Journal, 4(3), 331–340. https://doi.org/10.3390/life4030331</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergazin, T. D., Tielker, N., Zhang, Y., Mao, J., Gunner, M. R., Francisco, K., … &amp; Mobley, D. L. (2021). Evaluation of log P, p K a, and log D predictions from the SAMPL7 blind challenge. Journal of computer‐aided molecular design, 35(7), 771–802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calcara, M., &amp; Caricaterra, M. (2023). CO2 dipole moment: A simple model and its implications for CO2‐rock interactions. Minerals, 13(1), 87. https://doi.org/10.3390/min13010087</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calliauw, G., Fredrick, E., Gibon, V., Greyt, W. D., Wouters, J., Foubert, I., &amp; Dewettinck, K. (2010). On the fractional crystallization of palm olein: Solid solutions and eutectic solidification. Food Research International, 43(4), 972–981. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2010.01.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Canada. (2006). List of permitted carrier or extraction solvents (lists of permitted food additives) [Transparency—other; notices]. Government of Canada. https://www.canada.ca/en/health‐canada/services/food‐nutrition/food‐safety/food‐additives/lists‐permitted/15‐carrier‐extraction‐solvents.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capuzzo, A., Maffei, M., &amp; Occhipinti, A. (2013). Supercritical fluid extraction of plant flavors and fragrances. Molecules, 18(6), 7194–7238. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules18067194</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho, V. S., Barrales, F. M., Fasolin, L. H., Viganó, J., &amp; Martínez, J. (2024). Concentration of the oxyterpenes linalool and α‐terpineol in orange peel oil by supercritical fluid adsorption. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 213, 106354. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2024.106354</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casas‐Cardoso, L., Mantell, C., Obregón, S., Cejudo‐Bastante, C., Alonso‐Moraga, Á., de la Ossa, E. J. M., &amp; de Haro‐Bailón, A. (2021). Health‐promoting properties of borage seed oil fractionated by supercritical carbon dioxide extraction. Foods, 10(10), 2471. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10102471</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro‐Muñoz, R., Ahmad, M. Z., &amp; Cassano, A. (2023). Pervaporation‐aided processes for the selective separation of aromas, fragrances and essential (AFE) solutes from agro‐food products and wastes. Food Reviews International, 39(3), 1499–1525. https://doi.org/10.1080/87559129.2021.1934008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro‐Muñoz, R., Correa‐Delgado, M., Córdova‐Almeida, R., Lara‐Nava, D., Chávez‐Muñoz, M., Velásquez‐Chávez, V. F., Hernández‐Torres, C. E., Gontarek‐Castro, E., &amp; Ahmad, M. Z. (2022). Natural sweeteners: Sources, extraction and current uses in foods and food industries. Food Chemistry, 370, 130991. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130991</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro‐Muñoz, R., Díaz‐Montes, E., Cassano, A., &amp; Gontarek, E. (2021). Membrane separation processes for the extraction and purification of steviol glycosides: An overview. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 61(13), 2152–2174. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2020.1772717</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro‐Muñoz, R., Gontarek‐Castro, E., &amp; Jafari, S. M. (2022). Up‐to‐date strategies and future trends towards the extraction and purification of capsaicin: A comprehensive review. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 123, 161–171. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2022.03.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catchpole, O., Moreno, T., Montañes, F., &amp; Tallon, S. (2018). Perspectives on processing of high value lipids using supercritical fluids. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 134, 260–268. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2017.12.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, K., &amp; Yin, W. (2009). Effects of entrainers on the purity of andrographolide extracted from andrographolide raw material by SC‐CO2. Separation and Purification Technology, 70(2), 207–211. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seppur.2009.09.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choe, E., &amp; Min, D. B. (2006). Mechanisms and factors for edible oil oxidation. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 5(4), 169–186. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1541‐4337.2006.00009.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang, M.‐H., &amp; Brunner, G. (2006). Concentration of minor components in crude palm oil. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 37(2), 151–156. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2005.09.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cocero, M. J., &amp; Calvo, L. (1996). Supercritical fluid extraction of sunflower seed oil with CO2 ‐ethanol mixtures. Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society, 73(11), 1573–1578. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02523527</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coelho, J. A. P., &amp; Palavra, A. M. F. (2015). Supercritical fluid extraction of compounds from spices and herbs. In T. Fornari &amp; R. P. Stateva (Eds.), High pressure fluid technology for green food processing (pp. 357–396). Springer International Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐319‐10611‐3_10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connolly, S., &amp; Cusco, L. (2007). Hazards from high pressure carbon dioxide releases during carbon dioxide sequestration processes. In IChemE Symposium Series 153, 1‐5. .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cravotto, C., Fabiano‐Tixier, A.‐S., Claux, O., Abert‐Vian, M., Tabasso, S., Cravotto, G., &amp; Chemat, F. (2022). Towards substitution of hexane as extraction solvent of food products and ingredients with no regrets. Foods, 11(21), 3412. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11213412</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Da Porto, C., Decorti, D., &amp; Natolino, A. (2014). Water and ethanol as co‐solvent in supercritical fluid extraction of proanthocyanidins from grape marc: A comparison and a proposal. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 87, 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2013.12.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danlami, J. M., Arsad, A., Zaini, M. A. A., &amp; Sulaiman, H. (2014). A comparative study of various oil extraction techniques from plants. Reviews in Chemical Engineering, 30(6), 605–626. https://doi.org/10.1515/revce‐2013‐0038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Azevedo, A. B. A., Kieckbush, T. G., Tashima, A. K., Mohamed, R. S., Mazzafera, P., &amp; de Melo, S. A. B. V. (2008). Extraction of green coffee oil using supercritical carbon dioxide. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 44(2), 186–192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2007.11.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de De Lucas, A., De La Ossa, E. M., Rincón, J., Blanco, M. A., &amp; Gracia, I. (2002). Supercritical fluid extraction of tocopherol concentrates from olive tree leaves. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 22(3), 221–228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Valle, J. M., &amp; Uquiche, E. L. (2002). Particle size effects on supercritical CO2 extraction of oil‐containing seeds. Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society, 79(12), 1261–1266. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11746‐002‐0637‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dikshit, S., Bubna, S., Gupta, A., &amp; Kumar, P. (2020). Advances in various techniques for isolation and purification of sterols. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 57(7), 2393–2403. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐019‐04209‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Döker, O., Salgin, U., Yildiz, N., Aydoğmuş, M., &amp; Çalimli, A. (2010). Extraction of sesame seed oil using supercritical CO2 and mathematical modeling. Journal of Food Engineering, 97(3), 360–366. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2009.10.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan, M., Zhou, X., Fang, T., Zhou, D., Shi, Q., Ge, F., &amp; Wang, W. (2024). Efficient supercritical carbon dioxide extraction of astaxanthin from Hematococcus pluvialis at high pressure. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 205, 106145. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2023.106145</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duba, K. S., &amp; Fiori, L. (2015). Supercritical CO2 extraction of grape seed oil: Effect of process parameters on the extraction kinetics. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 98, 33–43. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2014.12.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunford, N. T., &amp; Temelli, F. (1995). Extraction of phospholipids from canola with supercritical carbon dioxide and ethanol. Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society, 72(9), 1009–1015. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02660713</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutta, S., Priyadarshini, S. R., Moses, J. A., &amp; Anandharamakrishnan, C. (2021). Supercritical fluid and ultrasound‐assisted green extraction technologies for catechin recovery. ChemBioEng Reviews, 8(6), 654–664. https://doi.org/10.1002/cben.202100001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambré, C., Barat Baviera, J. M., Bolognesi, C., Chesson, A., Cocconcelli, P. S., Crebelli, R., Gott, D. M., Grob, K., Lampi, E., Mengelers, M., Mortensen, A., Rivière, G., Steffensen, I.‐L., Tlustos, C., Van Loveren, H., Vernis, L., Zorn, H., Bignami, M., … Van Haver, E., EFSA Panel on Food Contact Materials, Enzymes and Processing Aids (CEP). (2022). Safety assessment of 2‐methyloxolane as a food extraction solvent. EFSA Journal, 20(3), e07138. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2022.7138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eller, F. J., &amp; Teel, J. A. (2019). Determination of crossover pressure for cedarwood oil in carbon dioxide. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 145, 201–204. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2018.12.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fahmy, T. M., Paulaitis, M. E., Johnson, D. M., &amp; McNally, M. E. P. (1993). Modifier effects in the supercritical fluid extraction of solutes from clay, soil, and plant materials. Analytical Chemistry, 65(10), 1462–1469.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fattori, M., Bulley, N. R., &amp; Meisen, A. (1988). Carbon dioxide extraction of canola seed: Oil solubility and effect of seed treatment. Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society, 65(6), 968–974. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02544522</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferdosh, S., Sarker, M. Z. I., Norulaini Nik Ab Rahman, N., Haque Akanda, M. J., Ghafoor, K., &amp; Kadir, M. O. A. (2016). Simultaneous extraction and fractionation of fish oil from tuna by‐product using supercritical carbon dioxide (SC‐CO2). Journal of Aquatic Food Product Technology, 25(2), 230–239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández‐Ronco, M. P., Gracia, I., Zetzl, C., De Lucas, A., García, M. T., &amp; Rodríguez, J. F. (2011). Equilibrium data for the separation of oleoresin capsicum using supercritical CO2: A theoretical design of a countercurrent gas extraction column. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 57(1), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2011.02.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreyra‐Suarez, D., Paredes‐Vargas, L., Jafari, S. M., García‐Depraect, O., &amp; Castro‐Muñoz, R. (2024). Extraction pathways and purification strategies towards carminic acid as natural‐based food colorant: A comprehensive review. Advances in Colloid and Interface Science, 323, 103052. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cis.2023.103052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foster, N. R., Gurdial, G. S., Yun, J. S. L., Liong, K. K., Tilly, K. D., Ting, S. S. T., Singh, H., &amp; Lee, J. H. (1991). Significance of the crossover pressure in solid‐supercritical fluid phase equilibria. Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research, 30(8), 1955–1964. https://doi.org/10.1021/ie00056a044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garza‐Cadena, C., Ortega‐Rivera, D. M., Machorro‐García, G., Gonzalez‐Zermeño, E. M., Homma‐Dueñas, D., Plata‐Gryl, M., &amp; Castro‐Muñoz, R. (2023). A comprehensive review on ginger (Zingiber officinale) as a potential source of nutraceuticals for food formulations: Towards the polishing of gingerol and other present biomolecules. Food Chemistry, 413, 135629. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.135629</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gast, K., Jungfer, M., Saure, C., &amp; Brunner, G. (2005). Purification of tocochromanols from edible oil. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 34, 17–25. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2004.09.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grosso, C., Figueiredo, A. C., Burillo, J., Mainar, A. M., Urieta, J. S., Barroso, J. G., Coelho, J. A., &amp; Palavra, A. M. F. (2010). Composition and antioxidant activity of Thymus vulgaris volatiles: Comparison between supercritical fluid extraction and hydrodistillation. Journal of Separation Science, 33(14), 2211–2218. https://doi.org/10.1002/jssc.201000192</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasanov, J., Salikhov, S., &amp; Oshchepkova, Y. (2023). Techno‐economic evaluation of supercritical fluid extraction of flaxseed oil. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 194, 105839. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2023.105839</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassim, N., Markom, M., Rosli, M. I., &amp; Harun, S. (2019). Scale‐up criteria and economic analysis for supercritical fluid extraction of Phyllanthus niruri. Chemical Engineering and Processing—Process Intensification, 139, 14–22. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cep.2019.03.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He, H.‐P., Corke, H., &amp; Cai, J.‐G. (2003). Supercritical carbon dioxide extraction of oil and squalene from Amaranthus grain. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 51(27), 7921–7925. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf030488y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrero, M., Mendiola, J. A., Cifuentes, A., &amp; Ibáñez, E. (2010). Supercritical fluid extraction: Recent advances and applications. Journal of Chromatography A, 1217(16), 2495–2511. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2009.12.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoe, B. C., Chan, E.‐S., Nagasundara Ramanan, R., &amp; Ooi, C. W. (2020). Recent development and challenges in extraction of phytonutrients from palm oil. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 19(6), 4031–4061. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12648</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Q., Xu, J., Chen, S., &amp; Yang, F. (2004). Antioxidant activity of extracts of black sesame seed (Sesamum indicum L.) by supercritical carbon dioxide extraction. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 52(4), 943–947.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Z., Shi, X., &amp; Jiang, W. (2012). Theoretical models for supercritical fluid extraction. Journal of Chromatography A, 1250, 2–26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2012.04.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Z., Ye, C., Li, L., Zhang, X., &amp; Qiu, T. (2016). Measurement and correlation of the mass transfer coefficient for a liquid‐liquid system with high density difference. Brazilian Journal of Chemical Engineering, 33, 897–906. https://doi.org/10.1590/0104‐6632.20160334s20150488</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilieva, P., Kilzer, A., &amp; Weidner, E. (2016). Measurement of solubility, viscosity, density and interfacial tension of the systems tristearin and CO2 and rapeseed oil and CO2. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 117, 40–49. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2016.07.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isah, A. G. (2015). Production of cooking oil from corn germ using supercritical CO2 as solvent [M. Phill]. University of Birmingham. https://etheses.bham.ac.uk/id/eprint/6411/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivanovic, J., Ristic, M., &amp; Skala, D. (2011). Supercritical CO2 extraction of Helichrysum italicum: Influence of CO2 density and moisture content of plant material. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 57(2), 129–136. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2011.02.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafarian Asl, P., &amp; Niazmand, R. (2020). Modelling and simulation of supercritical CO2 extraction of bioactive compounds from vegetable oil waste. Food and Bioproducts Processing, 122, 311–321. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbp.2020.05.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joana Gil‐Chávez, G., Villa, J. A., Fernando Ayala‐Zavala, J., Basilio Heredia, J., Sepulveda, D., Yahia, E. M., &amp; González‐Aguilar, G. A. (2013). Technologies for extraction and production of bioactive compounds to be used as nutraceuticals and food ingredients: An overview. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 12(1), 5–23. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jokić, S., Nagy, B., Zeković, Z., Vidović, S., Bilić, M., Velić, D., &amp; Simándi, B. (2012). Effects of supercritical CO2 extraction parameters on soybean oil yield. Food and Bioproducts Processing, 90(4), 693–699. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbp.2012.03.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kashulines, P., Rizvil, S. S. H., Harriott, P., &amp; Zollweg, J. A. (1991). Viscosities of fatty acids and methylated fatty acids saturated with supercritical carbon dioxide. Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society, 68(12), 912–921. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02657535</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kauffman, J. F. (2001). Quadrupolar solvent effects on solvation and reactivity of solutes dissolved in supercritical CO2. The Journal of Physical Chemistry A, 105(14), 3433–3442. https://doi.org/10.1021/jp004359l</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kayathi, A., Chakrabarti, P. P., Bonfim‐Rocha, L., Cardozo‐Filho, L., &amp; Jegatheesan, V. (2020). Selective extraction of polar lipids of mango kernel using supercritical carbon dioxide (SC–CO2) extraction: Process optimization of extract yield/phosphorous content and economic evaluation. Chemosphere, 260, 127639. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127639</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kellens, M., Gibon, V., Hendrix, M., &amp; De Greyt, W. (2007). Palm oil fractionation. European Journal of Lipid Science and Technology, 109(4), 336–349. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejlt.200600309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khaw, K.‐Y., Parat, M.‐O., Shaw, P. N., &amp; Falconer, J. R. (2017). Solvent supercritical fluid technologies to extract bioactive compounds from natural sources: A review. Molecules, 22(7), 1186. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules22071186</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, W.‐J., Kim, J.‐D., Kim, J., Oh, S.‐G., &amp; Lee, Y.‐W. (2008). Selective caffeine removal from green tea using supercritical carbon dioxide extraction. Journal of Food Engineering, 89(3), 303–309. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2008.05.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King, A. D., Jr., &amp; Coan, C. R. (1971). Solubility of water in compressed carbon dioxide, nitrous oxide, and ethane. Evidence for hydration of carbon dioxide and nitrous oxide in the gas phase. Journal of the American Chemical Society, 93(8), 1857–1862. https://doi.org/10.1021/ja00737a004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kostrzewa, D., Dobrzyńska‐Inger, A., &amp; Reszczyński, R. (2021). Pilot scale supercritical CO2 extraction of carotenoids from sweet paprika (Capsicum annuum L.): Influence of particle size and moisture content of plant material. LWT, 136, 110345. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.110345</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehotay, S. J. (1997). Supercritical fluid extraction of pesticides in foods. Journal of Chromatography A, 785(1), 289–312. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0021‐9673(97)00461‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Fan, Y., Li, J., Tang, L., Hu, J., &amp; Deng, Z. (2013). Evaluating and predicting the oxidative stability of vegetable oils with different fatty acid compositions. Journal of Food Science, 78(4), H633–H641. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.12089</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau, H. L. N., Choo, Y. M., Ma, A. N., &amp; Chuah, C. H. (2008). Selective extraction of palm carotene and vitamin E from fresh palm‐pressed mesocarp fiber (Elaeis guineensis) using supercritical CO2. Journal of Food Engineering, 84(2), 289–296. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2007.05.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim, J. R., Chua, L. S., &amp; Mustaffa, A. A. (2022). Ionic liquids as green solvent and their applications in bioactive compounds extraction from plants. Process Biochemistry, 122, 292–306. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procbio.2022.10.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lippi, G., Targher, G., &amp; Franchini, M. (2010). Vaccination, squalene and anti‐squalene antibodies: Facts or fiction? European Journal of Internal Medicine, 21(2), 70–73. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejim.2009.12.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López, M., Arce, L., Garrido, J., Rı́os, A., &amp; Valcárcel, M. (2004). Selective extraction of astaxanthin from crustaceans by use of supercritical carbon dioxide. Talanta, 64(3), 726–731. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2004.03.048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machmudah, S., Kitada, K., Sasaki, M., Goto, M., Munemasa, J., &amp; Yamagata, M. (2011). Simultaneous extraction and separation process for coffee beans with supercritical CO2 and water. Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research, 50(4), 2227–2235. https://doi.org/10.1021/ie101252w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machmudah, S., Kondo, M., Sasaki, M., Goto, M., Munemasa, J., &amp; Yamagata, M. (2008). Pressure effect in supercritical CO2 extraction of plant seeds. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 44(3), 301–307. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2007.09.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machmudah, S., Martin, A., Sasaki, M., &amp; Goto, M. (2012). Mathematical modeling for simultaneous extraction and fractionation process of coffee beans with supercritical CO2 and water. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 66, 111–119. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2011.11.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maciassanchez, M., Mantell, C., Rodriguez, M., Martinezdelaossa, E., Lubian, L., &amp; Montero, O. (2009). Comparison of supercritical fluid and ultrasound‐assisted extraction of carotenoids and chlorophyll a from Dunaliella salina. Talanta, 77(3), 948–952. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2008.07.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maheshwari, P., Ooi, E. T., &amp; Nikolov, Z. L. (1995). Off‐flavor removal from soy‐protein isolate by using liquid and supercritical carbon dioxide. Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society, 72(10), 1107–1115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markom, M., Singh, H., &amp; Hasan, M. (2001). Supercritical CO2 fractionation of crude palm oil. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 20(1), 45–53. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0896‐8446(00)00104‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matricardi, M., Hesketh, R., &amp; Farrell, S. (2001). Effect of operating conditions on static/dynamic extraction of peanut oil using supercritical carbon dioxide. Analytix_Ltd.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzocchi, A., De Cosmi, V., Risé, P., Milani, G. P., Turolo, S., Syrén, M.‐L., Sala, A., &amp; Agostoni, C. (2021). Bioactive compounds in edible oils and their role in oxidative stress and inflammation. Frontiers in Physiology, 12, 659551. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2021.659551</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melgosa, R., Sanz, M. T., &amp; Beltrán, S. (2021). Supercritical CO2 processing of omega‐3 polyunsaturated fatty acids—Towards a biorefinery for fish waste valorization. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 169, 105121. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2020.105121</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mezzomo, N., Mileo, B. R., Friedrich, M. T., Martínez, J., &amp; Ferreira, S. R. S. (2010). Supercritical fluid extraction of peach (Prunus persica) almond oil: Process yield and extract composition. Bioresource Technology, 101(14), 5622–5632. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2010.02.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mhemdi, H., Rodier, E., Kechaou, N., &amp; Fages, J. (2011). A supercritical tuneable process for the selective extraction of fats and essential oil from coriander seeds. Journal of Food Engineering, 105(4), 609–616. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2011.03.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montanari, L., King, J. W., List, G. R., &amp; Rennick, K. A. (1996). Selective extraction of phospholipid mixtures by supercritical carbon dioxide and cosolvents. Journal of Food Science, 61(6), 1230–1234. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2621.1996.tb10967.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mouahid, A., Crampon, C., Toudji, S.‐A. A., &amp; Badens, E. (2016). Effects of high water content and drying pre‐treatment on supercritical CO2 extraction from Dunaliella salina microalgae: Experiments and modelling. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 116, 271–280. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2016.06.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwaurah, P. W., Kumar, S., Kumar, N., Attkan, A. K., Panghal, A., Singh, V. K., &amp; Garg, M. K. (2020). Novel oil extraction technologies: Process conditions, quality parameters, and optimization. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 19(1), 3–20. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12507</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagy, B., &amp; Simándi, B. (2008). Effects of particle size distribution, moisture content, and initial oil content on the supercritical fluid extraction of paprika. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 46(3), 293–298. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2008.04.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naziri, E., Glisic, S. B., Mantzouridou, F. T., Tsimidou, M. Z., Nedovic, V., &amp; Bugarski, B. (2016). Advantages of supercritical fluid extraction for recovery of squalene from wine lees. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 107, 560–565. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2015.07.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norhidayah, S., Baharin, B. S., Hamed, M., &amp; Zaidul, I. S. M. (2012). Squalene recovery from palm fatty acid distillate using supercritical fluid extraction. International Food Research Journal, 19(4), 1661–1667.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyam, K. L., Tan, C. P., Lai, O. M., Long, K., &amp; Che Man, Y. B. (2009). Physicochemical properties and bioactive compounds of selected seed oils. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 42(8), 1396–1403. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2009.03.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development (OECD). (1995). Test no.107: Partition coefficient (n‐octanol/water): Shake flask method. Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development. https://www.oecd‐ilibrary.org/environment/test‐no‐107‐partition‐coefficient‐n‐octanol‐water‐shake‐flask‐method_9789264069626‐en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development (OECD). (2022). Test No.117: Partition coefficient (n‐octanol/water), HPLC method. Organisation for Economic Co‐operation and Development. https://www.oecd‐ilibrary.org/environment/test‐no‐117‐partition‐coefficient‐n‐octanol‐water‐hplc‐method_9789264069824‐en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Othman, N., Chong, G. H., Azman, E. M., &amp; Suleiman, N. (2022). Effect of process variables in supercritical carbon dioxide extraction of tocotrienols from hydrolysed palm fatty acid distillate (PFAD). Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 46, e16533. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.16533</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özkal, S. G., &amp; Yener, M. E. (2016). Supercritical carbon dioxide extraction of flaxseed oil: Effect of extraction parameters and mass transfer modeling. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 112, 76–80. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2016.02.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papamichail, I., Louli, V., &amp; Magoulas, K. (2000). Supercritical fluid extraction of celery seed oil. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 18(3), 213–226. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0896‐8446(00)00066‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira, C. G., &amp; Meireles, M. A. A. (2010). Supercritical fluid extraction of bioactive compounds: Fundamentals, applications and economic perspectives. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 3(3), 340–372. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐009‐0263‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perrut, M. (2000). Supercritical fluid applications: Industrial developments and economic issues. Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research, 39(12), 4531–4535. https://doi.org/10.1021/ie000211c</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poletto, M., &amp; Reverchon, E. (1996). Comparison of models for supercritical fluid extraction of seed and essential oils in relation to the mass‐transfer rate. Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research, 35(10), 3680–3686. https://doi.org/10.1021/ie9600093</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pourmortazavi, S. M., &amp; Hajimirsadeghi, S. S. (2007). Supercritical fluid extraction in plant essential and volatile oil analysis. Journal of Chromatography A, 1163(1–2), 2–24. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chroma.2007.06.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pourmortazavi, S. M., Saghafi, Z., Ehsani, A., &amp; Yousefi, M. (2018). Application of supercritical fluids in cholesterol extraction from foodstuffs: A review. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 55(8), 2813–2823. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐018‐3205‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raveendran, P., Ikushima, Y., &amp; Wallen, S. L. (2005). Polar attributes of supercritical carbon dioxide. Accounts of Chemical Research, 38(6), 478–485. https://doi.org/10.1021/ar040082m</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raveendran, P., &amp; Wallen, S. L. (2003). Exploring CO2‐philicity: Effects of stepwise fluorination. The Journal of Physical Chemistry B, 107(6), 1473–1477. https://doi.org/10.1021/jp027026s</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raynie, D. (2023). Practical understanding of partition coefficients. LCGC North America, 111, 95–98. https://doi.org/10.56530/lcgc.na.tc2970o5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rebolleda, S., Rubio, N., Beltrán, S., Sanz, M. T., &amp; González‐Sanjosé, M. L. (2012). Supercritical fluid extraction of corn germ oil: Study of the influence of process parameters on the extraction yield and oil quality. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 72, 270–277. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2012.10.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riha, V., &amp; Brunner, G. (2000). Separation of fish oil ethyl esters with supercritical carbon dioxide. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 17(1), 55–64. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0896‐8446(99)00038‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roh, H.‐S., Park, J.‐Y., Park, S.‐Y., &amp; Chun, B.‐S. (2006). Isolation of off‐flavors and odors from tuna fish oil using supercritical carbon dioxide. Biotechnology and Bioprocess Engineering, 11, 496–502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roselló‐Soto, E., Barba, F. J., Lorenzo, J. M., Dominguez, R., Pateiro, M., Mañes, J., &amp; Moltó, J. C. (2019). Evaluating the impact of supercritical‐CO2 pressure on the recovery and quality of oil from “Horchata” by‐products: Fatty acid profile, α‐tocopherol, phenolic compounds, and lipid oxidation parameters. Food Research International, 120, 888–894. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2018.11.054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross, C. F., &amp; Smith, D. M. (2006). Use of volatiles as indicators of lipid oxidation in muscle foods. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 5(1), 18–25. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1541‐4337.2006.tb00077.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy, B. C., Goto, M., &amp; Hirose, T. (1996). Extraction of ginger oil with supercritical carbon dioxide: Experiments and modeling. Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research, 35(2), 607–612. https://doi.org/10.1021/ie950357p</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubio‐Rodríguez, N., de Diego, S. M., Beltrán, S., Jaime, I., Sanz, M. T., &amp; Rovira, J. (2012). Supercritical fluid extraction of fish oil from fish by‐products: A comparison with other extraction methods. Journal of Food Engineering, 109(2), 238–248. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2011.10.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rincón, J., Martínez, F., Rodríguez, L., &amp; Ancillo, V. (2011). Recovery of triglycerides from used frying oil by extraction with liquid and supercritical ethane. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 56(1), 72–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahena, F., Zaidul, I. S. M., Jinap, S., Karim, A. A., Abbas, K. A., Norulaini, N. A. N., &amp; Omar, A. K. M. (2009). Application of supercritical CO2 in lipid extraction—A review. Journal of Food Engineering, 95(2), 240–253. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2009.06.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahena, F., Zaidul, I. S. M., Jinap, S., Saari, N., Jahurul, H. A., Abbas, K. A., &amp; Norulaini, N. A. (2009). PUFAs in fish: Extraction, fractionation, importance in health. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 8(2), 59–74. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1541‐4337.2009.00069.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salgin, S., &amp; Salgın, U. (2006). Supercritical fluid extraction of walnut kernel oil. European Journal of Lipid Science and Technology, 108, 577–582. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejlt.200600046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salgın, U. (2007). Extraction of jojoba seed oil using supercritical CO2+ethanol mixture in green and high‐tech separation process. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 39(3), 330–337. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2006.03.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salgın, U., Döker, O., &amp; Çalımlı, A. (2006). Extraction of sunflower oil with supercritical CO2: Experiments and modeling. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 38(3), 326–331. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2005.11.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Şanal, İ. S., Güvenç, A., Salgın, U., Mehmetoğlu, Ü., &amp; Çalımlı, A. (2004). Recycling of apricot pomace by supercritical CO2 extraction. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 32(1), 221–230. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2004.02.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez‐Camargo, A. P., Martinez‐Correa, H. A., Paviani, L. C., &amp; Cabral, F. A. (2011). Supercritical CO2 extraction of lipids and astaxanthin from Brazilian redspotted shrimp waste (Farfantepenaeus paulensis). The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 56(2), 164–173. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2010.12.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez‐González, L., Vargas, M., González‐Martínez, C., Chiralt, A., &amp; Cháfer, M. (2011). Use of essential oils in bioactive edible coatings: A review. Food Engineering Reviews, 3(1), 1–16. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12393‐010‐9031‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santana, Á. L., &amp; Meireles, M. A. A. (2023). Extraction of essential oils with supercritical fluid. In Essential oils (pp. 671–684). John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119829614.ch30</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sapkale, G. N., Patil, S. M., Surwase, U. S., &amp; Bhatbhage, P. K. (2010). Supercritical fluid extraction ‐ A Review. International Journal of Chemical Sciences, 8 (2), 729‐743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savoire, R., Subra‐Paternault, P., Bardeau, T., Morvan, E., Grélard, A., &amp; Cansell, M. (2020). Selective extraction of phospholipids from food by‐products by supercritical carbon dioxide and ethanol and formulating ability of extracts. Separation and Purification Technology, 238, 116394. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seppur.2019.116394</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schönsee, C. D., &amp; Bucheli, T. D. (2020). Experimental determination of octanol–water partition coefficients of selected natural toxins. Journal of Chemical &amp; Engineering Data, 65(4), 1946–1953. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jced.9b01129</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott, S. E., Rozin, P., &amp; Small, D. A. (2020). Consumers prefer “natural” more for preventatives than for curatives. Journal of Consumer Research, 47(3), 454–471. https://doi.org/10.1093/jcr/ucaa034</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Setianto, W., Atmaji, P., &amp; Anggoro, D. (2013). Palm kernel oil solubity examination and its modeling in extraction process using supercritical carbon dioxide. Reaktor, 14(3), 242–246., https://doi.org/10.14710/reaktor.14.3.242‐246</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahidi, F., &amp; Zhong, Y. (2010). Lipid oxidation and improving the oxidative stability. Chemical Society Reviews, 39(11), 4067–4079. https://doi.org/10.1039/B922183M</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, Z., Palmer, M. V., Ting, S. S. T., &amp; Fairclough, R. J. (1996). Pilot scale extraction of rice bran oil with dense carbon dioxide. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 44(10), 3033–3039. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf950761z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, Z., Palmer, M. V., Ting, S. S. T., &amp; Fairclough, R. J. (1997). Pilot scale extraction and fractionation of rice bran oil using supercritical carbon dioxide. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 45(12), 4540–4544. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf970292w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shinde, S. S., Sarkate, A. P., Nirmal, N. P., &amp; Sakhale, B. K. (2023). Bioactivity, medicinal applications, and chemical compositions of essential oils: Detailed perspectives. In S. Pati, T. Sarkar, &amp; D. Lahiri (Eds.), Recent frontiers of phytochemicals (pp. 353–367). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐443‐19143‐5.00010‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith, J., &amp; Hong‐Shum, L. (2011). Food additives data book. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soh, S. H., Agarwal, S., Jain, A., Lee, L. Y., Chin, S. K., &amp; Jayaraman, S. (2019). Mathematical modeling of mass transfer in supercritical fluid extraction of patchouli oil. Engineering Reports, 1(4), e12051. https://doi.org/10.1002/eng2.12051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soh, S. H., Jain, A., Lee, L. Y., Chin, S. K., Yin, C.‐Y., &amp; Jayaraman, S. (2021). Techno‐economic and profitability analysis of extraction of patchouli oil using supercritical carbon dioxide. Journal of Cleaner Production, 297, 126661. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.126661</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris, J. Solvent fractionation. https://lipidlibrary.aocs.org/edible‐oil‐processing/solvent‐fractionation</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sundram, K., Sambanthamurthi, R., &amp; Tan, Y.‐A. (2003). Palm fruit chemistry and nutrition. Asia Pacific Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 12(3), 355‐62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Separeco. (2023). Supercritical fluid fractionation (SFF). Separeco. https://separeco.com/co2‐extraction‐physics/supercritical‐fluid‐fractionation/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamkutė, L., Pukalskas, A., Syrpas, M., Urbonavičienė, D., Viškelis, P., &amp; Venskutonis, P. R. (2020). Fractionation of cranberry pomace lipids by supercritical carbon dioxide extraction and on‐line separation of extracts at low temperatures. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 163, 104884. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2020.104884</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temelli, F. (1992). Extraction of triglycerides and phospholipids from canola with supercritical carbon dioxide and ethanol. Journal of Food Science, 57(2), 440–443. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2621.1992.tb05512.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tietel, Z., Hammann, S., Meckelmann, S. W., Ziv, C., Pauling, J. K., Wölk, M., Würf, V., Alves, E., Neves, B., &amp; Domingues, M. R. (2023). An overview of food lipids toward food lipidomics. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 22(6), 4302–4354. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.13225</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timms, R. E. (2005). Fractional crystallisation—The fat modification process for the 21st century. European Journal of Lipid Science and Technology, 107(1), 48–57. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejlt.200401075</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tonthubthimthong, P., Chuaprasert, S., Douglas, P., &amp; Luewisutthichat, W. (2001). Supercritical CO2 extraction of nimbin from neem seeds—An experimental study. Journal of Food Engineering, 47(4), 289–293. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0260‐8774(00)00131‐X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Top, A. G. M., &amp; Rahman, H. A. (2000). Squalene in oils and fats. Palm Oil Developments, 32, 36–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres‐Valenzuela, L. S., Ballesteros‐Gómez, A., &amp; Rubio, S. (2020). Green solvents for the extraction of high added‐value compounds from agri‐food waste. Food Engineering Reviews, 12(1), 83–100. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12393‐019‐09206‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDR FoodLab. (2024). TOTOX value and its relationship with food oil rancidity. CDR FoodLab. https://www.cdrfoodlab.com/cdrfoodlab/learn‐more/totox‐value‐food‐oil‐rancidity</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turek, C., &amp; Stintzing, F. C. (2013). Stability of essential oils: A review: Stability of essential oils. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 12(1), 40–53. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Türkmenoğlu, A., &amp; Özmen, D. (2023). Deterpenation techniques of citrus essential oils and the role of oxyterpenes in food industry. Flavour and Fragrance Journal, 38(6), 407–415. https://doi.org/10.1002/ffj.3758</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulrich, N., Goss, K.‐U., &amp; Ebert, A. (2021). Exploring the octanol–water partition coefficient dataset using deep learning techniques and data augmentation. Communications Chemistry, 4(1), 90. https://doi.org/10.1038/s42004‐021‐00528‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uwineza, P. A., &amp; Waśkiewicz, A. (2020). Recent Advances in Supercritical Fluid Extraction of Natural Bioactive Compounds from Natural Plant Materials. Molecules, 25(17), 3847. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules25173847</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varona, S., Martin, A., Cocero, M. J., &amp; Gamse, T. (2008). Supercritical carbon dioxide fractionation of Lavandin essential oil: Experiments and modeling. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 45(2), 181–188. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2007.07.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieira de Melo, S. A. B., Costa, G. M. N., Viana, A. C. C., &amp; Pessoa, F. L. P. (2009). Solid pure component property effects on modeling upper crossover pressure for supercritical fluid process synthesis: A case study for the separation of Annatto pigments using SC‐CO2. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 49(1), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2008.12.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., Wang, X., Wang, P., Xiao, Y., &amp; Liu, Q. (2016). Optimization of supercritical carbon dioxide extraction, physicochemical and cytotoxicity properties of Gynostemma pentaphyllum seed oil: A potential source of conjugated linolenic acids. Separation and Purification Technology, 159, 147–156. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seppur.2016.01.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yener, M. E., Kashulines, P., Rizvi, S. S. H., &amp; Harriott, P. (1998). Viscosity measurement and modeling of lipid‐supercritical carbon dioxide mixtures. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 11(3), 151–162. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0896‐8446(97)00036‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousefi, M., Rahimi‐Nasrabadi, M., Pourmortazavi, S. M., Wysokowski, M., Jesionowski, T., Ehrlich, H., &amp; Mirsadeghi, S. (2019). Supercritical fluid extraction of essential oils. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 118, 182–193. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2019.05.038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaaboul, F., &amp; Liu, Y. (2022). Vitamin E in foodstuff: Nutritional, analytical, and food technology aspects. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 21(2), 964–998. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12924</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaidul, I. S. M., Nik Norulaini, N. A., Mohd Omar, A. K., &amp; Smith, R. L. (2007). Supercritical carbon dioxide (SC‐CO2) extraction of palm kernel oil from palm kernel. Journal of Food Engineering, 79(3), 1007–1014. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2006.03.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeković, Z., Filip, S., Vidović, S., Jokić, S., &amp; Svilović, S. (2014). Mathematical modeling of Ocimum basilicum L. supercritical CO2 extraction. Chemical Engineering &amp; Technology, 37(12), 2123–2128. https://doi.org/10.1002/ceat.201400322</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zougagh, M., Valcárcel, M., &amp; Rı́os, A. (2004). Supercritical fluid extraction: A critical review of its analytical usefulness. TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 23(5), 399–405. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0165‐9936(04)00524‐2</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>