<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39286041</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2590-1575</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food chemistry: X</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem X</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Innovative strategies for protein content determination in dried laver (<i>Porphyra</i> spp.): Evaluation of preprocessing methods and machine learning algorithms through short-wave infrared imaging.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>101763</StartPage><MedlinePgn>101763</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">101763</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.fochx.2024.101763</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In this study, we explored the application of Short-Wave Infrared (SWIR) hyperspectral imaging combined with Competitive Adaptive Reweighted Sampling (CARS) and advanced regression models for the non-destructive assessment of protein content in dried laver. Utilizing a spectral range of 900-1700 nm, we aimed to refine the quality control process by selecting informative wavelengths through CARS and applying various preprocessing techniques (standard normal variate [SNV], Savitzky-Golay filtering [SG], Orthogonal Signal Correction [OSC], and StandardScaler [SS]) to enhance the model's accuracy. The SNV-OSC-StandardScaler- Support vector regression (SVR) model trained on CARS-selected wavelengths significantly outperformed the other configurations, achieving a prediction determination coefficient (Rp<sup>2</sup>) of 0.9673, root mean square error of prediction of 0.4043, and residual predictive deviation of 5.533. These results highlight SWIR hyperspectral imaging's potential as a rapid and precise tool for assessing dried laver quality, aiding food industry quality control and dried laver market growth.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Eunghee</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smart food manufacturing project group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Jong-Jin</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food safety and distribution research group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Gyuseok</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smart food manufacturing project group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cho</LastName><ForeName>Jeong-Seok</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smart food manufacturing project group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food safety and distribution research group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Seul-Ki</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smart food manufacturing project group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yun</LastName><ForeName>Dae-Yong</ForeName><Initials>DY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food safety and distribution research group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Kee-Jai</ForeName><Initials>KJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smart food manufacturing project group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food safety and distribution research group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lim</LastName><ForeName>Jeong-Ho</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smart food manufacturing project group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food safety and distribution research group, Korea Food Research Institute, Wanju-gun 55365, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem X</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101751436</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2590-1575</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dried laver</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Machine learning model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Preprocessing method</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Protein content prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Short-wave infrared imaging</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing financial interests or personal relationships that may have influenced the work reported in this study.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39286041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11403402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fochx.2024.101763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2590-1575(24)00651-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aheto J.H., Huang X., Tian X., Lv R., Dai C., Bonah E., Chang X. Evaluation of lipid oxidation and volatile compounds of traditional dry-cured pork belly: The hyperspectral imaging and multi-gas-sensory approaches. Journal of Food Process Engineering. 2020;43(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amirvaresi A., Nikounezhad N., Amirahmadi M., Daraei B., Parastar H. Comparison of near-infrared (NIR) and mid-infrared (MIR) spectroscopy based on chemometrics for saffron authentication and adulteration detection. Food Chemistry. 2021;344</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33229154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bermolen P., Rossi D. Support vector regression for link load prediction. Computer Networks. 2009;53(2):191–201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng J.-H., Sun D.-W. Partial least squares regression (PLSR) applied to NIR and HSI spectral data modeling to predict chemical properties of fish muscle. Food Engineering Reviews. 2017;9:36–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai Q., Sun D.W., Cheng J.H., Pu H., Zeng X.A., Xiong Z. Recent advances in de-noising methods and their applications in hyperspectral image processing for the food industry. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety. 2014;13(6):1207–1218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elmasry G., Kamruzzaman M., Sun D.-W., Allen P. Principles and applications of hyperspectral imaging in quality evaluation of agro-food products: A review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition. 2012;52(11):999–1023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22823348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatemi A., Singh V., Kamruzzaman M. Identification of informative spectral ranges for predicting major chemical constituents in corn using NIR spectroscopy. Food Chemistry. 2022;383</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35182865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Figueroa V., Farfán M., Aguilera J. Seaweeds as novel foods and source of culinary flavors. Food Reviews International. 2023;39(1):1–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Poza S., Cotas J., Morais T., Pacheco D., Pereira L., Marques J.C., Gonçalves A.M. Sustainable global resources of seaweeds volume 2: Food, pharmaceutical and health applications. Springer; 2022. Global trade of seaweed foods; pp. 325–337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golden C.E., Rothrock M.J., Jr., Mishra A. Comparison between random forest and gradient boosting machine methods for predicting Listeria spp. prevalence in the environment of pastured poultry farms. Food Research International. 2019;122:47–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31229101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golovynskyi S., Golovynska I., Roganova O., Golovynskyi A., Qu J., Ohulchanskyy T.Y. Hyperspectral imaging of lipids in biological tissues using near-infrared and shortwave infrared transmission mode: A pilot study. Journal of Biophotonics. 2023;16(7)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37021842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He H.-J., Wang Y., Zhang M., Wang Y., Ou X., Guo J. Rapid determination of reducing sugar content in sweet potatoes using NIR spectra. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis. 2022;111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong G.-T., Lee C., Cha E., Moon S., Cha Y.-J., Yu D. Determination of optimum processing condition of high protein laver Chip using air-frying and reaction flavor technologies. Foods. 2023;12(24):4450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10742992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38137254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin X., Wang L., Zheng W., Zhang X., Liu L., Li S.…Xuan J. Predicting the nutrition deficiency of fresh pear leaves with a miniature near-infrared spectrometer in the laboratory. Measurement. 2022;188</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang Z., Zhao Y., Chen L., Guo Y., Mu Q., Wang S. Advances in machine learning and hyperspectral imaging in the food supply chain. Food Engineering Reviews. 2022;14(4):596–616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kästner F., Sut-Lohmann M., Ramezany S., Raab T., Feilhauer H., Chabrillat S. Estimating heavy metal concentrations in Technosols with reflectance spectroscopy. Geoderma. 2022;406</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loggenberg K., Strever A., Greyling B., Poona N. Modelling water stress in a shiraz vineyard using hyperspectral imaging and machine learning. Remote Sensing. 2018;10(2):202. doi: 10.3390/rs10020202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/rs10020202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manthou E., Karnavas A., Fengou L.-C., Bakali A., Lianou A., Tsakanikas P., Nychas G.-J.E. Spectroscopy and imaging technologies coupled with machine learning for the assessment of the microbiological spoilage associated to ready-to-eat leafy vegetables. International Journal of Food Microbiology. 2022;361</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34743052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marques de Brito B., Campos V.d.M., Neves F.J., Ramos L.R., Tomita L.Y. Vitamin B12 sources in non-animal foods: A systematic review. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition. 2023;63(26):7853–7867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35343314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meiyan S., Jinyu Z., Xiaohong Y., Xiaohe G., Baoguo L., Yuntao M. A spectral decomposition method for estimating the leaf nitrogen status of maize by UAV-based hyperspectral imaging. Computers and Electronics in Agriculture. 2023;212</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra G., Panda B.K., Ramirez W.A., Jung H., Singh C.B., Lee S.-H., Lee I. Application of SWIR hyperspectral imaging coupled with chemometrics for rapid and non-destructive prediction of Aflatoxin B1 in single kernel almonds. Lwt. 2022;155</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Msuya F.E., Bolton J., Pascal F., Narrain K., Nyonje B., Cottier-Cook E.J. Seaweed farming in Africa: Current status and future potential. Journal of Applied Phycology. 2022;34(2):985–1005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murai U., Yamagishi K., Kishida R., Iso H. Impact of seaweed intake on health. European Journal of Clinical Nutrition. 2021;75(6):877–889.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32908248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagy M.M., Wang S., Farag M.A. Quality analysis and authentication of nutraceuticals using near IR (NIR) spectroscopy: A comprehensive review of novel trends and applications. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology. 2022;123:290–309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niemi C., Mortensen A.M., Rautenberger R., Matsson S., Gorzsas A., Gentili F.G. Rapid and accurate determination of protein content in North Atlantic seaweed by NIR and FTIR spectroscopies. Food Chemistry. 2023;404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36279781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özdoğan G., Lin X., Sun D.-W. Rapid and noninvasive sensory analyses of food products by hyperspectral imaging: Recent application developments. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology. 2021;111:151–165.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozturk S., Bowler A., Rady A., Watson N.J. Near-infrared spectroscopy and machine learning for classification of food powders during a continuous process. Journal of Food Engineering. 2023;341</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raja R., Hemaiswarya S., Sridhar S., Alagarsamy A., Ganesan V., Elumalai S., Carvalho I.S. Evaluation of proximate composition, antioxidant properties, and phylogenetic analysis of two edible seaweeds. Smart Science. 2020;8(3):95–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribeiro M.N., Carvalho I.A., Fonseca G.A., Lago R.C., Rocha L.C., Ferreira D.D.…Pinheiro A.C. Quality control of fresh strawberries by a random forest model. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture. 2021;101(11):4514–4522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33448405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Pulido F.J., Hernández-Hierro J.M., Nogales-Bueno J., Gordillo B., González-Miret M.L., Heredia F.J. A novel method for evaluating flavanols in grape seeds by near infrared hyperspectral imaging. Talanta. 2014;122:145–150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24720976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shafagh-Kolvanagh J., Dehghanian H., Mohammadi-Nassab A.D., Moghaddam M., Raei Y., Salmasi S.Z.…Gholizadeh-Khajeh B. Machine learning-assisted analysis for agronomic dataset of 49 Balangu (Lallemantia iberica L.) ecotypes from different regions of Iran. Scientific Reports. 2022;12(1):19237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9649721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36357455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Souza Zangirolami M., Moreira T.F.M., Leimann F.V., Valderrama P., Março P.H. Texture profile and short-NIR spectral vibrations relationship evaluated through Comdim: The case study for animal and vegetable proteins. Food Control. 2023;143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian H., Wu D., Chen B., Yuan H., Yu H., Lou X., Chen C. Rapid identification and quantification of vegetable oil adulteration in raw milk using a flash gas chromatography electronic nose combined with machine learning. Food Control. 2023;150</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wada K., Tsuji M., Nakamura K., Oba S., Nishizawa S., Yamamoto K.…Nagata C. Effect of dietary nori (dried laver) on blood pressure in young Japanese children: An intervention study. Journal of Epidemiology. 2021;31(1):37–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7738648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32201400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yong W.T.L., Thien V.Y., Rupert R., Rodrigues K.F. Seaweed: A potential climate change solution. Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews. 2022;159</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J., Guo Z., Ren Z., Wang S., Yin X., Zhang D.…Ma C. A non-destructive determination of protein content in potato flour noodles using near-infrared hyperspectral imaging technology. Infrared Physics &amp; Technology. 2023;130</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z., Lai Z., Xu Y., Shao L., Wu J., Xie G.-S. Discriminative elastic-net regularized linear regression. IEEE Transactions on Image Processing. 2017;26(3):1466–1481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28092552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu M., Long Y., Chen Y., Huang Y., Tang L., Gan B.…Xie J. Fast determination of lipid and protein content in green coffee beans from different origins using NIR spectroscopy and chemometrics. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis. 2021;102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou H., Hastie T. Regularization and variable selection via the elastic net. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series B: Statistical Methodology. 2005;67(2):301–320.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>