<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39288718</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-3171</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Poultry science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Poult Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Molecular characteristic, evolution, and pathogenicity analysis of avian infectious bronchitis virus isolates associated with QX type in China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>104256</StartPage><MedlinePgn>104256</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">104256</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.psj.2024.104256</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0032-5791(24)00835-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) is one of the major avian pathogens plaguing the global poultry industry. Although vaccination is the primary preventive measure for IBV infection, the emergence of virus variants with mutations and recombination has resulted in IBV circulating globally, presenting a challenge for IB control. Here, we isolated 3 IBV strains (CZ200515, CZ210840, and CZ211063) from suspected sick chickens vaccinated with IBV live attenuated vaccines (H120, 4/91, or QXL87). Phylogenetic analysis of the S1 gene sequence of the spike (S) revealed that the 3 isolates belonged to the QX-type (GI-19 lineage). Whole genome sequencing and recombination analysis indicated that CZ200515 and CZ210840 contained genetic material from 4/91 and Scyz3 (QX-type), possibly due to recombination between the circulating strain and the 4/91 vaccine strain, while no evidence of recombination was found in CZ211063. Pathogenicity analysis in 1-day-old specific pathogen-free (SPF) chickens demonstrated that all 3 isolates caused severe tissue damage and varying degrees of mortality. Virus cross-neutralization assay revealed decreased antigen relatedness between the isolates and the QX-type vaccine strain (QXL87). Amino acid sequence homology analysis of S1 revealed 5%-6.5% variances between the isolates and QXL87. Analysis of the S1 subunit structure revealed that mutations of amino acid residues in the hypervariable region (HVR) and the neutralizing epitope region resulted in antigenic variation in isolates by changing the antigen conformation. Our data indicate antigenicity variances between QX isolates and QXL87 vaccine strains, potentially resulting in immune evasion occurrences. Overall, these results offer crucial insights into the epidemiology and pathogenicity of QX-type IBV, facilitating improved selection and formulation of vaccines for disease management.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Yuanlu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Yiran</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Haowei</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qiao</LastName><ForeName>Bingchen</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meng</LastName><ForeName>Qi</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dai</LastName><ForeName>Zijian</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Na</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Lingcai</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meng</LastName><ForeName>Xianchen</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lihua Nanjing Industrial Research Institute Co. Ltd. Nanjing, 213168, China; Key Laboratory of Jiangsu Preventive Veterinary Medicine, Key Laboratory for Avian Preventive Medicine, Ministry of Education, College of Veterinary Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, Jiangsu, 225009 China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Haitao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lihua Nanjing Industrial Research Institute Co. Ltd. Nanjing, 213168, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xia</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Prevention and Control of Herbivorous Animal Diseases of the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs &amp; Xinjiang Animal Disease Research Key Laboratory, Xinjiang Academy of Animal Sciences Institute of Veterinary Medicine, 830000, China. Electronic address: 1065291747@qq.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ping</LastName><ForeName>Jihui</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, Engineering Laboratory of Animal Immunity of Jiangsu Province, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, 210095, China. Electronic address: jihui.ping@njau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Poult Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0401150</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0032-5791</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infectious bronchitis virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antigenic variation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">genome recombination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neutralizing epitope</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenicity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>DISCLOSURES The authors declare no financial or commercial conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39288718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11421327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2024.104256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0032-5791(24)00835-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Andoh K., Ashikaga K., Suenaga K., Endo S., Yamazaki K. Identification of novel linear epitopes located in the infectious bronchitis virus spike S2 region. Avian Dis. 2018;62:210–217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29944406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boursnell M.E., Brown T.D., Foulds I.J., Green P.F., Tomley F.M., Binns M.M. Completion of the sequence of the genome of the coronavirus avian infectious bronchitis virus. J. Gen. Virol. 1987;68:57–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3027249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callison S.A., Hilt D.A., Boynton T.O., Sample B.F., Robison R., Swayne D.E., Jackwood M.W. Development and evaluation of a real-time Taqman RT-PCR assay for the detection of infectious bronchitis virus from infected chickens. J. Virol. Methods. 2006;138:60–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16934878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh D. Corona viruses in poultry and other birds. Avian Pathol. 2005;34:439–448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16537157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh D. Coronavirus avian infectious bronchitis virus. Vet. Res. 2007;38:281–297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17296157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh D., Davis P.J., Cook J.K., Li D., Kant A., Koch G. Location of the amino acid differences in the S1 spike glycoprotein subunit of closely related serotypes of infectious bronchitis virus. Avian Pathol. 1992;21:33–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18670913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen N., Li S., Zhou R., Zhu M., He S., Ye M., Huang Y., Li S., Zhu C., Xia P., Zhu J. Two novel porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV) recombinants from a natural recombinant and distinct subtypes of PEDV variants. Virus Res. 2017;242:90–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28947336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y., Jiang L., Zhao W., Liu L., Zhao Y., Shao Y., Li H., Han Z., Liu S. Identification and molecular characterization of a novel serotype infectious bronchitis virus (GI-28) in China. Vet. Microbiol. 2017;198:108–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7117283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28062000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H., Shi W., Feng S., Yuan L., Jin M., Liang S., Wang X., Si H., Li G., Ou C. A novel highly virulent nephropathogenic QX-like infectious bronchitis virus originating from recombination of GI-13 and GI-19 genotype strains in China. Poult. Sci. 2024;103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11223121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38865766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook J.K., Orbell S.J., Woods M.A., Huggins M.B. Breadth of protection of the respiratory tract provided by different live-attenuated infectious bronchitis vaccines against challenge with infectious bronchitis viruses of heterologous serotypes. Avian Pathol. 1999;28:477–485.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26911602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook J.K., Jackwood M., Jones R.C. The long view: 40 years of infectious bronchitis research. Avian Pathol. 2012;41:239–250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22702451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Wit J.J., Cazaban C., Dijkman R., Ramon G., Gardin Y. Detection of different genotypes of infectious bronchitis virus and of infectious bursal disease virus in European broilers during an epidemiological study in 2013 and the consequences for the diagnostic approach. Avian Pathol. 2018;47:140–151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28972403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eldemery F., Joiner K.S., Toro H., van Santen V.L. Protection against infectious bronchitis virus by spike ectodomain subunit vaccine. Vaccine. 2017;35:5864–5871.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7111290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28899630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eldemery F., Li Y., Yu Q., van Santen V.L., Toro H. Infectious bronchitis virus S2 of 4/91 expressed from recombinant virus does not protect against ark-type challenge. Avian Dis. 2017;61:397–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28957002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng K.Y., Chen T., Zhang X., Shao G.M., Cao Y., Chen D.K., Lin W.C., Chen F., Xie Q.M. Molecular characteristic and pathogenicity analysis of a virulent recombinant avain infectious bronchitis virus isolated in China. Poult. Sci. 2018;97:3519–3531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7107092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29917155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong H., Ni R., Qiu R., Wang F., Yan W., Wang K., Li H., Fu X., Chen L., Lei C., Wang H.N., Yang X. Evaluation of a novel recombinant strain of infectious bronchitis virus emerged from three attenuated live vaccine strains. Microb. Pathog. 2022;164</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35122972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gravendyck M., Tritt S., Spenkoch-Piper H., Kaleta E.F. Antigenic diversity of psittacine herpesviruses: Cluster analysis of antigenic differences obtained from cross-neutralization tests. Avian Pathol. 1996;25:345–357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18645862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gribble J., Stevens L.J., Agostini M.L., Anderson-Daniels J., Chappell J.D., Lu X., Pruijssers A.J., Routh A.L., Denison M.R. The coronavirus proofreading exoribonuclease mediates extensive viral recombination. PLoS Pathog. 2021;17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7846108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33465137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y., Bai X., Liu Z., Liang B., Zheng Y., Dankar S., Ping J. Exploring the alternative virulence determinants PB2 S155N and PA S49Y/D347G that promote mammalian adaptation of the H9N2 avian influenza virus in mice. Vet. Res. 2023;54:97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10588254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37858267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall T., Biosciences I., Carlsbad C. BioEdit: an important software for molecular biology. Gerf. Bull. Biosci. 2011;2:60–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He W.T., Ji X., He W., Dellicour S., Wang S., Li G., Zhang L., Gilbert M., Zhu H., Xing G., Veit M., Huang Z., Han G.Z., Huang Y., Suchard M.A., Baele G., Lemey P., Su S. Genomic epidemiology, evolution, and transmission dynamics of porcine delta corona virus. Mol. Biol. Evol. 2020;37:2641–2654.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7454817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32407507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmes E.C., Worobey M., Rambaut A. Phylogenetic evidence for recombination in dengue virus. Mol. Biol. Evol. 1999;16:405–409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10331266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou Y., Zhang L., Ren M., Han Z., Sun J., Zhao Y., Liu S. A highly pathogenic GI-19 lineage infectious bronchitis virus originated from multiple recombination events with broad tissue tropism. Virus Res. 2020;285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7198173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32380209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang M., Zou C., Liu Y., Han Z., Xue C., Cao Y. A novel low virulent respiratory infectious bronchitis virus originating from the recombination of QX, TW and 4/91 genotype strains in China. Vet. Microbiol. 2020;242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7111478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32122588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang L., Zhao W., Han Z., Chen Y., Zhao Y., Sun J., Li H., Shao Y., Liu L., Liu S. Genome characterization, antigenicity and pathogenicity of a novel infectious bronchitis virus type isolated from south China. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2017;54:437–446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7106192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28800976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang L., Han Z., Chen Y., Zhao W., Sun J., Zhao Y., Liu S. Characterization of the complete genome, antigenicity, pathogenicity, tissue tropism, and shedding of a recombinant avian infectious bronchitis virus with a ck/CH/LJL/140901-like backbone and an S2 fragment from a 4/91-like virus. Virus Res. 2018;244:99–109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29141204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan B. Vaccination against infectious bronchitis virus: A continuous challenge. Vet. Microbiol. 2017;206:137–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28081857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanh N.P., Tan S.W., Yeap S.K., Lee H.J., Choi K.S., Hair-Bejo M., Bich T.N., Omar A.R. Comparative pathogenicity of Malaysian QX-like and variant infectious bronchitis virus strains in chickens at different age of exposure to the viruses. J. Comp. Pathol. 2018;161:43–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30173857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kolb A.W., Lewin A.C., Moeller Trane R., McLellan G.J., Brandt C.R. Phylogenetic and recombination analysis of the herpesvirus genus varicellovirus. BMC Genomics. 2017;18:887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5697016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29157201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee H.C., Jeong S., Cho A.Y., Kim K.J., Kim J.Y., Park D.H., Kim H.J., Kwon J.H., Song C.S. Genomic Analysis of avian infectious bronchitis viruses recently isolated in South Korea reveals multiple introductions of GI-19 lineage (QX Genotype) Viruses. 2021;13:1045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8228071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34072981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Legnardi M., Franzo G., Koutoulis K.C., Wiśniewski M., Catelli E., Tucciarone C.M., Cecchinato M. Vaccine or field strains: The jigsaw pattern of infectious bronchitis virus molecular epidemiology in Poland. Poult. Sci. 2019;98:6388–6392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6870560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31399745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S., Fan S., Li N., Shen Y., Xiang X., Chen W., Xia J., Han X., Cui M., Huang Y. The N1038S substitution and (1153)EQTRPKKSV(1162) deletion of the S2 subunit of QX-Type avian infectious bronchitis virus can synergistically enhance viral proliferation. Front. Microbiol. 2022;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9006875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35432239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S., Zhang X., Wang Y., Li C., Han Z., Shao Y., Li H., Kong X. Molecular characterization and pathogenicity of infectious bronchitis coronaviruses: complicated evolution and epidemiology in China caused by cocirculation of multiple types of infectious bronchitis coronaviruses. Intervirology. 2009;52:223–234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19590226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H.X., Wang C.C., He Y., Wei X.F., Cheng J.Z., Yang W.W., Shi K.C., Si H.B. Assessing a respiratory toxic infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) strain: isolation, identification, pathogenicity, and immunological failure insights. Microbiol. Spectr. 2024;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11302067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38904372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu P., Yue C., Meng B., Xiao T., Yang S., Liu S., Jian F., Zhu Q., Yu Y., Ren Y., Wang P., Li Y., Wang J., Mao X., Shao F., Wang Y., Gupta R.K., Cao Y., Wang X. Spike N354 glycosylation augments SARS-CoV-2 fitness for human adaptation through structural plasticity. Natl. Sci. Rev. 2024;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11282955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39071099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma T., Xu L., Ren M., Shen J., Han Z., Sun J., Zhao Y., Liu S. Novel genotype of infectious bronchitis virus isolated in China. Vet. Microbiol. 2019;230:178–186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7117389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30827386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin D.P., Murrell B., Golden M., Khoosal A., Muhire B. RDP4: Detection and analysis of recombination patterns in virus genomes. Virus Evol. 2015;1:vev003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5014473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27774277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendoza-González L., Marandino A., Panzera Y., Tomás G., Williman J., Techera C., Gayosso-Vázquez A., Ramírez-Andoney V., Alonso-Morales R., Realpe-Quintero M., Pérez R. Research note: High genetic diversity of infectious bronchitis virus from Mexico. Poult. Sci. 2022;101</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9449659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36041394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng X., Zhang J., Wan Z., Li T., Xie Q., Qin A., Shao H., Zhang H., Ye J. Molecular epidemiology of infectious bronchitis virus in eastern and southern China during 2021-2023. Poult. Sci. 2024;103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11254719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38909507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu X., Liu M., Yang S., Xu J., Hou Y.J., Liu D., Tang Q., Zhu H., Wang Q. A recombination-resistant genome for live attenuated and stable PEDV vaccines by engineering the transcriptional regulatory sequences. J. Virol. 2023;97</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10734454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37971221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parsons L.M., Bouwman K.M., Azurmendi H., de Vries R.P., Cipollo J.F., Verheije M.H. Glycosylation of the viral attachment protein of avian coronavirus is essential for host cell and receptor binding. J. Biol. Chem. 2019;294:7797–7809.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6514631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30902814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed L.J., Muench H. A simple method of estimating fifty per cent endpoints12. Am. J. Epidemiol. 1938;27:493–497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabir J.S., Lam T.T., Ahmed M.M., Li L., Shen Y., Abo-Aba S.E., Qureshi M.I., Abu-Zeid M., Zhang Y., Khiyami M.A., Alharbi N.S., Hajrah N.H., Sabir M.J., Mutwakil M.H., Kabli S.A., Alsulaimany F.A., Obaid A.Y., Zhou B., Smith D.K., Holmes E.C., Zhu H., Guan Y. Co-circulation of three camel coronavirus species and recombination of MERS-CoVs in Saudi Arabia. Science. 2016;351:81–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26678874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanger F., Nicklen S., Coulson A.R. DNA sequencing with chain-terminating inhibitors. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 1977;74:5463–5467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC431765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">271968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schalk A.F., Hawn M.C. An apparently new respiratory disease of baby chicks. J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc. 1931;78:413–422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shan D., Fang S., Han Z., Ai H., Zhao W., Chen Y., Jiang L., Liu S. Effects of hypervariable regions in spike protein on pathogenicity, tropism, and serotypes of infectious bronchitis virus. Virus Res. 2018;250:104–113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29684409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shang J., Zheng Y., Yang Y., Liu C., Geng Q.B., Luo C.M., Zhang W., Li F. Cryo-EM structure of infectious bronchitis coronavirus spike protein reveals structural and functional evolution of coronavirus spike proteins. PLoS Pathog. 2018;14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5933801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29684066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sjaak de Wit J.J., Cook J.K., van der Heijden H.M. Infectious bronchitis virus variants: A review of the history, current situation and control measures. Avian Pathol. 2011;40:223–235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7154306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21711181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terregino C., Toffan A., Beato M.S., De Nardi R., Vascellari M., Meini A., Ortali G., Mancin M., Capua I. Pathogenicity of a QX strain of infectious bronchitis virus in specific pathogen free and commercial broiler chickens, and evaluation of protection induced by a vaccination programme based on the Ma5 and 4/91 serotypes. Avian Pathol. 2008;37:487–493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18798022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thor S.W., Hilt D.A., Kissinger J.C., Paterson A.H., Jackwood M.W. Recombination in avian gamma-coronavirus infectious bronchitis virus. Viruses. 2011;3:1777–1799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3187689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21994806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trang N.T., Dien T.C., Tam N.T., Cuong P.M., Duyet L.V., Thuong N.T.H., Trang V.D., Thach P.N., van Doorn H.R., Kesteman T., Grp O.C.-R. Detection of co-infection and recombination cases with Omicron and local Delta variants of SARS-CoV-2 in Vietnam. Sci. Rep. 2024;14:14225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11190198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38902306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valastro V., Holmes E.C., Britton P., Fusaro A., Jackwood M.W., Cattoli G., Monne I. S1 gene-based phylogeny of infectious bronchitis virus: An attempt to harmonize virus classification. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2016;39:349–364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26883378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C., Hou B. A pathogenic and recombinant infectious bronchitis virus variant (CK/CH/GX/202109) with multiorgan tropism. Vet. Res. 2023;54:54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10318653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37400928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M.M., Bo Z.Y., Zhang C.C., Guo M.J., Wu Y.T., Zhang X.R. Deciphering the genetic variation: A comparative analysis of parental and attenuated strains of the QXL87 vaccine for infectious bronchitis. Animals-Basel. 2024;14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11200882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38929403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Worobey M., Holmes E.C. Evolutionary aspects of recombination in RNA viruses. J. Gen. Virol. 1999;80:2535–2543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10573145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L., Han Z., Jiang L., Sun J., Zhao Y., Liu S. Genetic diversity of avian infectious bronchitis virus in China in recent years. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2018;66:82–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7185438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30244092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L., Ren M., Sheng J., Ma T., Han Z., Zhao Y., Sun J., Liu S. Genetic and biological characteristics of four novel recombinant avian infectious bronchitis viruses isolated in China. Virus Res. 2019;263:87–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7185608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30641197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan S., Liu X., Zhao J., Xu G., Zhao Y., Zhang G. Analysis of antigenicity and pathogenicity reveals major differences among QX-like infectious bronchitis viruses and other serotypes. Vet. Microbiol. 2017;203:167–173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7117262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28619139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y., Wang D., Bai Y., Huang W., Gao S., Wu X., Wang Y., Ren J., He J., Jin L., Hu M., Wang Z., Wang Z., Ma H., Li J., Liang L. Genetic and pathogenic characterization of new infectious bronchitis virus strains in the GVI-1 and GI-19 lineages isolated in central. China. J. Integr. Agric. 2024;23:2407–2420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>You R., Liu K., Huang M., Tang L., Zhang X., Huang Y., Zhao J., Zhao Y., Ye L., Zhang G. Identification and comparison of the sialic acid-binding domain characteristics of avian coronavirus infectious bronchitis virus spike protein. J. Virol. 2023;97</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10231253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37097156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yount B., Roberts R.S., Lindesmith L., Baric R.S. Rewiring the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) transcription circuit: Engineering a recombination-resistant genome. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 2006;103:12546–12551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1531645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16891412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zúñiga S., Cruz J.L., Sola I., Mateos-Gómez P.A., Palacio L., Enjuanes L. Coronavirus nucleocapsid protein facilitates template switching and is required for efficient transcription. J. Virol. 2010;84:2169–2175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2812394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19955314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao W., Gao M., Xu Q., Xu Y., Zhao Y., Chen Y., Zhang T., Wang Q., Han Z., Li H., Chen L., Liang S., Shao Y., Liu S. Origin and evolution of LX4 genotype infectious bronchitis coronavirus in China. Vet. Microbiol. 2017;198:9–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7117135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28062013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou N., Xia J., Wang F., Duan Z., Miao D., Yan Q., Cao S., Wen X., Liu P., Huang Y. Two novel neutralizing antigenic epitopes of the s1 subunit protein of a QX-like avian infectious bronchitis virus strain Sczy3 as revealed using a phage display peptide library. Vet. Immunol. Immunopathol. 2015;168:49–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26315775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>