<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39280981</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0107-055X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>2024</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Feb</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nordic journal of botany</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nord J Bot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle><i>Dianthus sylvestris</i> subsp. <i>sylvestris</i> as a promising candidate for phytostabilization of copper-contaminated post-mining sites in Alpine ecosystems.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e04199</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/njb.04199</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The lack of remediation of inactive mine sites is a serious global concern, as they pose risks to the environment, human health, and safety. The potential of <i>Dianthus sylvestris</i> subsp. <i>sylvestris</i> to remediate post-mining sites contaminated with copper (Cu) at high altitudes, which is a challenging task for most management strategies, was explored in this study. More than 1300 mg Cu kg<sup>-1</sup> in shoots were found in plants collected at the Monte Avanza legacy mine site (Alps). However, it is unclear whether this is due to hyperaccumulation or foliar contamination. To address this gap, field samples were washed with two different protocols, and a controlled Cu-tolerance test was conducted. While very high Cu concentrations, exceeding the Cu hyperaccumulation threshold of 300 mg kg<sup>-1</sup>, were found in samples washed with water, results for the plants cleaned with a more rigorous approach with EDTA suggested Cu exclusion strategy. Under controlled conditions, the plant showed Cu hypertolerance but did not hyperaccumulate Cu. Thus <i>D. sylvestris</i> presents a Cu exclusion strategy rather than hyperaccumulation potential, making it a suitable candidate for Cu phytostabilization at high altitude legacy mine sites. The study emphasizes the need for experiments under controlled conditions when assessing the phytoremediation potential.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pošćić</LastName><ForeName>Filip</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6642-1532</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Science, The University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ginaldi</LastName><ForeName>Fabrizio</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agriculture, Food, Environment and Animal Sciences, University of Udine, Udine, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferfuia</LastName><ForeName>Claudio</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agriculture, Food, Environment and Animal Sciences, University of Udine, Udine, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pasković</LastName><ForeName>Igor</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Agriculture and Tourism Poreč, K. Huguesa, Poreč, Croatia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Babst-Kostecka</LastName><ForeName>Alicja</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Science, The University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>Dryad</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>10.5061/dryad.cz8w9gj8b</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P42 ES004940</GrantID><Acronym>ES</Acronym><Agency>NIEHS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Denmark</Country><MedlineTA>Nord J Bot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9886922</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0107-055X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">exclusion strategy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">foliar contamination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metallophyte</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phytoremediation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39280981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1971537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11392045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/njb.04199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">e04199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ali H, Khan E and Sajad MA 2013. Phytoremediation of heavy metals – concepts and applications. – Chemosphere 91: 869–881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23466085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker AJM 1981. Accumulators and excluders – strategies in the response of plants to heavy metals. – J. Plant Nutr 3: 643–654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker AJM, McGrath SP, Reeves RD and Smith JAC 2000. Metal hyperaccumulator plants: a review of the ecology and physiology of a biological resource for phytoremediation of metal-polluted soils. – In: Terry N and Bañuelos G (eds), Phytoremediation of contaminated soil and water. Lewis Publishers, pp. 85–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banásová V, Ďurišová E, Nadubinská M, Gurinová E and Čiamporová M 2012. Natural vegetation, metal accumulation and tolerance in plants growing on heavy metal rich soils. – In: Kothe E, Varma A (eds), Bio-geo interactions in metal-contaminated soils. Soil biology, vol. 31. Springer, pp. 233–250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brullo S, Brullo C, Colombo P, Galdo GGD, Ilardi V and Perrone R 2015. Dianthus borbonicus (Caryophyllaceae), a new species from Sicily. – Phytotaxa; 233: 49–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaney RL, Reeves RD, Baklanov IA, Centofanti T, Broad-hurst CL, Baker AJM, van der Ent A and Roseberg RJ 2014. Phytoremediation and phytomining: using plants to remediate contaminated or mineralized environments. – In: Rajakaruna N, Boyd RS and Harris TB (eds), Plant ecology and evolution in harsh environments. Nova Science Publishers, pp. 365–391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dondi M, Palenzona A and Puggioli G 1995. La miniera di Monte Avanza, Forni Avoltri (UD) (In Italian) [The Monte Avanza mine, Forni Avoltri (UD)]. – Riv. Mineral. Ital 2/95: 125–136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ernst, W. H. O. 1974. Schwermetallvegetation der Erde. – Fischer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fassou G, Korotkova N, Nersesyan A, Koch MA, Dimopoulos P and Borsch T 2022. Taxonomy of Dianthus (Caryophyllaceae) – overall phylogenetic relationships and assessment of species diversity based on a first comprehensive checklist of the genus. – PhytoKeys 196: 91–214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9849041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36762028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faucon M-P, Shutcha MN and Meerts P 2007. Revisiting copper and cobalt concentrations in supposed hyperaccumulators from SC Africa: influence of washing and metal concentrations in soil. – Plant Soil 301: 29–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feruglio G 1966. Il giacimento cuprifero del Monte Avanza in Carnia (In Italian) [The copper deposit of Monte Avanza in Carnia]. – Atti I Simposio sui giacimenti minerari delle Alpi; Trento, Italy, vol. 1. pp. 97–118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frangipani E 2004. La mineralizzazione del Monte Avanza (In Italian with abstract in English) [The Mount Avanza mineralisations]. – Studi Trent. Sci. Natl. Acta Geol 81: 47–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghaderian SM and Ghotbi Ravandi AA 2012. Accumulation of copper and other heavy metals by plants growing on Sarcheshmeh copper mining area, Iran. – J. Geochem. Explor 123: 25–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO International Organization for Standardization. 1994. Soil quality: determination of the specific electrical conductivity. ISO. 11265. – Int. Org. for Standardization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO International Organization for Standardization. 1995. Soil quality: determination of organic and total carbon after dry combustion (elementary analysis). ISO. 10694. – Int. Org. for Standardization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO International Organization for Standardization. 2000. Soil quality: determination of particle size distribution in mineral soil material – method by sieving and sedimentation. ISO. 11277. – Int. Org. for Standardization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunst L and Samuels L 2009. Plant cuticles shine: advances in wax biosynthesis and export. – Curr. Opin. Plant Biol 12: 721–727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19864175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam EJ, Cánovas M, Gálvez ME, Montofré ÍL, Keith BF and Faz Á 2017. Evaluation of the phytoremediation potential of native plants growing on a copper mine tailing in northern Chile. – J. Geochem. Explor 182: 210–217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam EJ, Gálvez ME, Cánovas M, Montofré ÍL and Keith BF 2018. Assessment of the adaptive capacity of plant species in copper mine tailings in arid and semiarid environments. – J. Soil Sediment 18: 2203–2216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambers H, Chapin FS and Pons TL 1998. Plant physiological ecology. – Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin C 2007. Flora e vegetazione metallifera del sito minerario del Monte Avanza (Alpi. Carniche) (In Italian) [Flora and metalliferous vegetation of the Monte Avanza mining site (Carnic Alps)]. – MS thesis, Univ. of Udine.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattiello A, Novello N, Cornu JY, Babst-Kostecka A and Pošćić F 2023. Copper accumulation in five weed species commonly found in the understory vegetation of Mediterranean vineyards. – Environ. Pollut 329: 121675.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10204647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37085100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumann D, zur Nieden UZ, Schwieger W, Leopold I and Lichtenberger O 1997. Heavy metal tolerance of Minuartia verna. – J. Plant Physiol 151: 101–108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Normes Françaises et Européennes. 1988. Soils quality. Determination of pH-value in H2O. Electrometric method. – NF X31–103. – Normes Françaises et Européennes.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novello N, Ferfuia C, Pasković I, Fabris A, Baldini M, Schat H and Pošćić F 2020. Independent variation in copper tolerance and copper accumulation among crop species and varieties. – Plant Physiol. Biochem 156: 538–551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33059265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oorts K 2013. Copper. – In: Alloway B (ed.), Heavy metals in soils. Trace metals and metalloids in soils and their bioavailability. Environmental pollution, vol. 22. Springer, pp. 367–394.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pošćić F, Fellet G, Vischi M, Casolo V, Schat H and Marchiol L 2015. Variation in heavy metal accumulation and genetic diversity at a regional scale among metallicolous and non-metallicolous populations of the facultative metallophyte Biscutella laevigata subsp. laevigata. – Int. J. Phytoremediat 17: 464–475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25495937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pošćić F, Ginaldi F, Ferfuia C, Pasković I and Babst-Kostecka A 2023. Data from: Dianthus sylvestris subsp. sylvestris as a promising candidate for phytostabilization of copper-contaminated post-mining sites in Alpine ecosystems. – Dryad Digital Repository, 10.5061/dryad.cz8w9gj8b.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5061/dryad.cz8w9gj8b</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11392045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39280981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Punz W and Mucina L 1997. Vegetation on anthropogenic metalliferous soils in the Eastern Alps. – Folia Geobot. Phytotax 32: 283–295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reeves RD and Baker AJM 2000. Metal accumulating plants.– In: Raskin I and Ensley BD (eds), Phytoremediation of toxic metals: using plants to clean up the environment. John Wiley and Sons Inc., pp. 193–229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schat H and Ten Bookum WMT 1992. Genetic control of copper tolerance in Silene vulgaris. – Heredity 68: 219–229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sokal RR and Rohlf FJ 2012. Biometry. The principles and practice of statistics in biological research, 4th edn. – W.H. Freeman and Company.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song J, Zhao FJ, Luo YM, McGrath SP and Zhang H 2004. Copper uptake by Elsholtzia splendens and Silene vulgaris and assessment of copper phytoavailability in contaminated soils. – Environ. Pollut 128: 307–315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14720473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terlević A, Bogdanović S, Frajman B and Rešetnik I 2022. Genome size variation in Dianthus sylvestris Wulfen sensu lato (Caryophyllaceae). – Plants (Basel) 11: 1481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9183063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35684254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA United States Environmental Protection Agency. 1995a. EPA method 3051: microwave assisted acid digestion of sediments, sludges, soils, and oils. In: Test methods for evaluating solid waste, 3rd edn. – USEPA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA United States Environmental Protection Agency. 1995b. EPA method 3052: microwave assisted acid digestion of siliceous and organically based matrices. In: Test methods for evaluating solid waste, 3rd edn. – USEPA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Ent A, Baker AJM, Reeves RD, Pollard AJ and Schat H 2013. Hyperaccumulators of metal and metalloid trace elements: facts and fiction. – Plant Soil 362: 319–334.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Ent A, Malaisse F, Erskine PD, Mesjasz-Przybyłowicz J, Przybyłowicz WJ, Barnabas AD, Sośnicka M and Harris HH 2019. Abnormal concentrations of Cu–Co in Haumaniastrum katangense, Haumaniastrum robertii and Aeolanthus biformifolius: contamination or hyperaccumulation? – Metallomics 11: 586–596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30664146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venturini C 2006. Evoluzione geologica delle Alpi Carniche (In Italian) [Geological evolution of the Carnic Alps]. – Pubblicazione no. 48. Museo Friulano di Storia Naturale.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venturini C 2009. Metamorfiti erciniche del Monte Avanza (In Italian) [Metamorphosized rocks by Variscan orogeny at Monte Avanza]. In: Cucchi F, Finocchiaro F and Muscio G (eds), Geositi del Friuli Venezia Giulia. Regione autonoma Friuli Venezia Giulia. – Arti Grafiche Friulane/Imoco Spa, pp. 30–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woch MW, Kapusta P and Stefanowicz AM 2016. Variation in dry grassland communities along a heavy metals gradient.– Ecotoxicology 25: 80–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4722054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26493699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeats TH and Rose JK 2013. The formation and function of plant cuticles. – Plant Physiol 163: 5–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3762664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23893170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon J, Cao X, Zhou Q and Ma LQ 2006. Accumulation of Pb, Cu, and Zn in native plants growing on a contaminated Florida site. – Sci. Total Environ 368: 456–464.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16600337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zucchini R 1998. Miniere e mineralizzazioni nella provincia di Udine – Aspetti storici e mineralogici (In Italian) [Mines and mineralization in the province of Udine – Historical and mineralogical aspects]. – Museo Friulano di Storia Naturale.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>